<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Martin Conway that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline the measures being planned to address the shortage of chefs in the hospitality industry.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jennifer Murnane O&rsquo;Connor of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline the time remaining in the examinership for the Sammon Group and Carillion; the amount paid to the Sammon Group from Carillion on each school project, specifically Tyndall College, Carlow, and up to what date were they paid.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to consider including physiotherapists on the list of referrers for X-rays.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to confirm when he intends to announce the funding for group sewerage schemes, and if he will confirm when the Milltown sewerage scheme, County Monaghan can expect confirmation of funding.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the provision of a 20-room unit for cystic fibrosis patients, which was included in the programme for Government.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to outline when the members of the Garda who have retired from the Mayfield area in Cork city will be replaced.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform to outline how Boyle, County Roscommon, can benefit under Project Ireland 2040, the Government&rsquo;s national development plan.</blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators that are suitable for discussion, I have selected the matters raised by Senators Conway, Murnane O&rsquo;Connor, Byrne, and Gallagher and they will be taken now.  I regret I had to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Colm Burke on the ground that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  I also regret I had to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Feighan on the ground that it is a repeat of the statements on Project Ireland 2040 held in the Seanad yesterday and on 7 March 2018.  Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in may give notice on another day of the matter that he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#A00300">Commencement Matter</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#A00400">Skills Shortages</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#A00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy John Halligan, to the House.  I have enormous regard for him.  He has a very fundamental understanding of his brief and realises the importance of skills as well as education, and of training and apprenticeships as well as academics.  We have not been good at realising that importance throughout the history of this country, to be quite frank about it.  I have tabled this matter because I am contacted regularly by people in the hospitality industry who express their frustration about trying to get chefs.  Our tourism industry is going exceptionally well.  We have seen enormous growth in recent years.  It provided an essential cushion as we were emerging out of recession, particularly in my area in County Clare.  Young people were able to get jobs in the hospitality, restaurant and tourism industries when they could not get jobs anywhere else because people, thankfully, continued to visit Ireland.  Some 650,000 people visited the Cliffs of Moher, which are 7 miles up the road from where I live, in 2013.  They had 1.5 million visitors in 2017.  I have no doubt that 2018 will see an even greater increase.</p> <p>With that prosperity comes challenges.  Many restaurants, particularly in my area, are finding it enormously difficult to get chefs.  I know of one hotel in my area the owner of which was a chef himself.  That is how he started out his professional life.  He is near enough to retiring but has not retired because he has had to go back in to help out in the kitchen.  That is how bad it is.  Can we bring back the Council for Education, Recruitment and Training, CERT?  CERT was good in its day.  If we cannot, can we introduce something like it?  There are many people who have cooking skills or a flair for baking and who want to become creative.  If they were trained from the ground up through a traditional CERT-type operation, it could help deal with this problem or at least go some way towards doing so.  One restaurateur told me that it is now easier to get a brain surgeon in Ireland than to get a chef.  That is how challenging it is.  Perhaps something could also be done to allow people from abroad to get work permits more easily that they have been able to up to now.  I have no doubt that the Minister of State is fully aware of the challenges from speaking to the people he himself deals with in Waterford and other parts of the south east.  I am sure this issue is not unique to counties Clare, Kerry and Limerick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#A00600"><p>It is a big issue in County Kerry anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#A00700"><p>Absolutely.  As politicians we are presented with problems and our job is to find solutions.  Working together, we have to become a little bit more creative than we have been to deal with this particular problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#A00800"><p>I thank Senator Martin Conway for his very important question and his very kind words.  The hospitality sector is very important to the Irish economy.  It is estimated to be worth approximately &euro;3 billion a year to the Irish economy and to employ approximately 148,000 people.  There are approximately 7,000 establishments in Ireland which serve food and require chefs and cooks.  In 2015, the expert group on future skills needs conducted a study on the future needs of the hospitality sector, including skill needs for chefs and cooks.  Its report, published in 2015, provided a set of recommendations designed to address the needs of the sector right up to 2020.  They included recommendations on boosting skill supply but also on creating sustainable and rewarding career opportunities in the sector in order to reduce the level of staff turnover.  As the Senator will know, there is a big problem with staff turnover in the hospitality industry.  A key recommendation was the establishment of a national oversight and advisory group comprising key hospitality stakeholders, Departments and Government agencies and education and training providers to provide a forum for ongoing collaboration, to support the needs of the sector and to oversee the implementation of the expert group's recommendations.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy John Halligan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2315"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2315&amp;amp;pid=JohnHalligan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That group was established in 2016 and chaired by SOLAS for the first year, and is currently chaired by the Irish Hotels Federation, which I think was a good move.  Senator Conway might know Michael Vaughan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#B00200"><p>I know him well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#B00300"><p>The group identified five priority areas.  Significant progress has been made and a lot more has to be done.  I refer to the promotion of careers in the sector; an audit of hospitality-related courses and facilities in both higher education and further education and training sectors; the development of apprenticeship and traineeship programmes; the launch of a dedicated Skillnets programme for the hospitality industry, which we have done; and making employment connections.</p><p>The group published its first progress report update last year.  This is available on the <i>skillsireland.ie</i>website.  Work is currently under way on the second progress update.  More than 6,000 students are enrolled annually on hospitality-related courses in further and higher education, of which just under 2,500 are on courses to train as chefs and cooks.  We are committed to expanding the number of registrations on apprenticeship and traineeship programmes to 50,000 by 2020.  To date, 11 new apprenticeship programmes have been developed, following the Apprenticeship Council's first call for proposals in 2015, including a new commis chef apprenticeship, led by the Irish Hotels Federation and the Restaurants Association of Ireland working with Kerry ETB.  The programme commenced last year with an initial enrolment of 25.  This year the enrolment has increased to 41.  That is working reasonably successfully but there is a turnover on programmes as people come and go.  It can be difficult.  Work is at an advanced stage on the development of a <i>chef de partie</i>apprenticeship, led by the same organisation.  A number of groups around the country are involved, for example, Crumlin College and colleges in Kerry, Cork, Galway and Cavan, among others.  It is expected that approximately 48 apprentices will enrol on that course.  Work is also under way to develop an apprenticeship for sous chefs which is intended to be rolled out in 2019.</p><p>There are difficulties attached to being a chef.  I refer to working conditions and unsavoury hours and it can be very difficult to get people into the industry.  That is the reason the consortium was put together.  We want to see what we can do to deliver apprenticeships for commis chefs and in related areas.</p><p>There is interest in this area.  For instance, we provided hospitality level 5 and level 6 courses last year and we had more than 100 trainees enrolled in the programmes, which was good.  Would we have liked more?  Yes, we would, but it is not the case that we had not put a call out for those programmes.  A call out goes out every so often and we had 100 trainees.  The generation of interest among secondary school students in careers in the sector is also very important.  The NCCA recently published a draft new specification for junior certificate home economics with a strong emphasis on culinary skills.  There is an effort in all areas of education to deal with the problem of chef recruitment.  In terms of the delivery of the programme we have the involvement of Crumlin College in Dublin, Col&aacute;iste &Iacute;de College of Further Education in Finglas, Kerry ETB, Cork ETB and ETB centres in Galway, Roscommon, Cavan and Monaghan, and Limerick, among other areas.  We are beginning to roll out the programme.</p><p>I would never be untruthful in what I say to the Senator.  I accept that it is difficult to attract people into the industry.  I hope the body that was set up will continue to report back and come up with innovative ideas that might make it easier for people to come into the industry.  There is a definite increase in the take-up of positions as chefs in recent years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#B00400"><p>I acknowledge that those programmes are very important.  I commend the Minister of State on his comprehensive reply.  We will see how we get on.  Other Departments have a role in this area, in particular in the granting of permits for chefs to come from abroad.  That is another avenue that I can explore in the future.  I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1351" speakername="John Halligan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#B00500"><p>If Senator Conway wants to meet me personally I can meet him at any stage or I can arrange a meeting if he wants to meet Michael Vaughan.  The issue is of great interest to me.  Apprenticeships and skills play an important part in the development of the sustainability of the economy and allow us to drive forward in the future.  As the Leas-Chathaoirleach said, the hospitality industry in this country is very important and given that we regularly have tourists coming here we must ensure that all restaurants are at the top of their game in terms of chefs.  Senator Conway is welcome to meet me or anybody from my Department.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.18" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#B00600">Schools Building Contractors</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#B00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, for coming to the House.  I am a bit disappointed that the Minister for Education and Skills is not here but I understand he is busy.  I have a very serious issue to raise this morning which relates to my home town of Carlow.  Two nights ago I met with very concerned subcontractors in Carlow who had worked on the construction of Tyndall College and the college of further education on the outskirts of Carlow town.  Some subcontractors were there also from some of the six other schools that were built by the same group.</p> <p>I remember the day the sod was turned on this multi-million euro investment in the Kilkenny and Carlow Education and Training Board, Carlow campus.  It was a great day for local jobs and the local economy.  This investment promised a much needed new post-primary school for 1,000 students and a new 1,000 place facility for the Carlow Institute of Further Education and Training on the Kilkenny Road, with a shared sports hall and accompanying fitness room at a cost of around &euro;30 million.  They revealed an exciting target date for completion of September 2017, but in May 2018 there is no school and good workers are down in pay and out of a job.  Because Sammon went into examinership the business cannot continue trading and the High Court protection of creditors means debts cannot be enforced before the appointment of an examiner.  The contractors are small businesses, many of whom are family businesses, with entire families depending on their wages.  They cannot absorb the losses.</p> <p>I have previously been in contact with the Minister on the issue but I was not happy with his response to my parliamentary question.  When Carillion collapsed earlier this year the company it hired in Ireland, namely, Sammon, went into examinership and the contractors were not paid.  They deserve good pay for good work.  They worked hard and they should not have lost out.  The Minister for Education and Skills told me that Sammon was paid what was due under its contract.  He also told me that the payment of the subcontractors is a matter for themselves and that he could not intervene.  Why should they be out of pocket for the work that was done in good faith?</p> <p>I wish to ask the Minister questions on behalf of the contractors.  How much time remains in the examinership period for the Sammon Group?  Currently, the process protects Sammon from having to pay what is due to the contractors.  The contractors have also asked me to find out exactly how much has been paid to the Sammon Group by Carillion for each school, and specifically, Tyndall College in Carlow, which is in my area.  Schools all around the country are idle and unfinished.  Parents and students wonder if they will ever see the doors of those fabulous facilities open.  The students, staff, parents and management deserve answers.  They deserve the schools they were promised.</p> <p>What is the status of Tyndall College and the college of further education and training?  I understand a tender went out.  If it is processed will the contractors lose out?  They were promised pay and work and now they have neither.  The contractors are in an awkward position.  They did the work, they got their certification but they did not get paid, yet Revenue seeks to be paid and they have no money to pay it.  Could the Minister intervene?  A special fund should be provided to pay contractors.  I am very annoyed that this situation has been allowed to drag on for months.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2470"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2470&amp;amp;pid=JenniferMurnaneOConnor&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are subcontractors out there who need to pay bills.  They have families, they have mortgages and they have not been paid.  A subcontractor or contractor who has to apply for a C2 certificate has to pay Revenue and cannot tender for other projects without that certificate.  The schools are built on lands owned by the State, which is paid for out of taxpayers' money.  The Minister has a duty to ensure that these subcontractors get paid.  Will the Minister meet with the subcontractors?  When a major contractor does not pay its subcontractors, there should be legislation barring it from tendering for further projects.  I am very disappointed to be standing here while many subcontractors I know - and whose families I know - are not being paid, which is very upsetting for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  Unfortunately, the Minister for Education and Skills is unavailable this morning and he has asked me to respond on his behalf.  I welcome the opportunity to inform the Seanad of the current position regarding the examinership of Sammon and with respect to payments under the schools bundle 5 public private partnership, PPP, contract.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, examinership is a process in Irish law whereby the protection of the court is obtained to assist in the survival of a company.  The Sammon Group petitioned the High Court on 5 April last to enter into examinership.  The application was successful.  The matter came before the High Court again on 16 April last and an examiner was appointed for an initial period of 35 days.  The examiner will next be before the High Court on 8 May when he can request an extension of up to 70 days if he still believes there is a realistic chance that a restructuring of the Sammon Group can occur.  This is the up-to-date position with the examinership as the Department of Education and Skills understands it.</p> <p>The Senator will be aware that the schools bundle 5 PPP project encompasses five school buildings and one further education college across four sites in Bray, Wexford, Kells and Carlow.  The programme will provide for two new education facilities in Carlow: Tyndall College will obtain a 1,000 pupil new post-primary building and Carlow Institute of Further Education will be provided with a new further education college building providing capacity for up to 1,000 students.  The buildings are being provided under a PPP contract between the Department of Education and Skills and the company Inspiredspaces.  Under this contract, Inspiredspaces is responsible for the design, build, finance and maintenance of the buildings in exchange for which it will receive a monthly unitary charge payment from the Department once the buildings are operational.  The National Development Finance Agency, NDFA, which is part of the National Treasury Management Agency, NTMA, led the procurement of the project on behalf of the Department and is monitoring the delivery phase.</p> <p>On the private side of the PPP arrangement, Inspiredspaces had a construction works contract with Carillion Construction Limited.  Sammon Contracting Ireland Limited was, in turn, subcontracted by Carillion Construction Limited to carry out the building work.  Sammon Contracting Ireland Limited then entered into further subcontracts with various contractors and suppliers.  Carillion Construction Limited went into liquidation in January.  As a consequence of this, the construction works contract relating to the PPP project is being retendered.  The tender process in this respect is being undertaken by the Dutch Infrastructure Fund, DIF, on behalf of Inspiredspaces and this is ongoing.  It is important to note that Inspiredspaces is not in liquidation.  DIF is a shareholder in Inspiredspaces and represents it in that context.</p> <p>I will now deal with the specific question in respect of payments to Sammon Contracting Ireland Limited.  Under the PPP structure, responsibility for payments to Sammon Contracting Ireland Limited lay with Carillion Construction Limited.  In its progress report to the NDFA at the end of December 2017, Inspiredspaces provided confirmation from Carillion Construction Limited that Sammon Contracting Ireland Limited had been paid in full in accordance with their subcontract to that point and that there were no issues arising.  The amount due and paid to that point was &euro;85.3 million, out of a total contract sum of &euro;87 million.  As all six buildings are being delivered under one PPP contract, the Department does not have visibility on how much specifically was paid by Carillion Construction Limited to Sammon Contracting Ireland Limited in respect of works at Tyndall College, Carlow.  The Department of Education and Skills will only commence unitary charge payments to Inspiredspaces once the school buildings are operational.  The only payment made to Inspiredspaces to date is &euro;4.4 million, primarily for off-site works that were completed in accordance with the project agreement.</p> <p>Ultimately, the Department of Education and Skills is not party to the construction or other subcontracts relating to the schools bundle 5 PPP project and does not have any authority to intervene in same.  The Department will continue to liaise closely with the NDFA regarding the completion works for the schools bundle 5 PPP project, which is our priority.  In that regard, officials from the Department are keeping management representatives of relevant schools informed of developments.  School principals and chairs of boards of management have also attended a number of meetings with the Department and NDFA officials at which they have been fully briefed on developments.  DIF has targeted, and is working towards, the delivery of all school buildings by the coming school year.</p> <p>I will return to some of the issues the Senator raised after she has spoken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C00300"><p>I will allow a brief supplementary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C00400"><p>Having heard the Minister of State's reply, I am not better off than I was in the aftermath of having a parliamentary question on the matter tabled to the Minister for Education and Skills on my behalf.  It is good to know that the responsibility for payment to Sammon Contracting Ireland Limited lay with Carillion Construction Limited but the subcontractors are seeking a meeting with the NDFA and we will be working on that.  When people have done work and are awaiting payments that will protect their livelihoods and those of their families and that enable them to pay their mortgages but where no one is accountable, it is a very serious matter.  They do the work and obtain their certificates but they do not get paid.  That does not make sense and it does not matter who has to intervene.  There has to be accountability regarding the subcontractors who have done their work and who need their money in order to survive.  Putting the blame on one party or another is not good enough.  The Minister of State mentioned DIF, the NDFA, etc., but what about the students waiting to go into the schools?  I am not happy with the answer and I will not let this go.  I will seek to meet with the Minister again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C00500"><p>There is a legal process involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C00600"><p>I know that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C00700"><p>I understand the Senator's concerns about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C00800"><p>The response suggests that there will be further court cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C00900"><p>I have dealt with issues relating to subcontractors in my own role.  A chain of command needs to be put in place.  In light of the concerns raised by the Senator, however, I will bring this back to the Minister.  He is really sorry that he cannot be here today but I will make sure that a response is given to the Senator in person.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C01000">Health and Social Care Professionals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#C01100"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House to discuss this very important issue.  I have been contacted by the Irish Society of Chartered Physiotherapists, which has concerns regarding the review last year of a statutory instrument that is currently being drawn up and that will include a list of health professionals entitled to refer individuals for X-rays.  The statutory instrument in question is in draft format at present.  Across Europe and the world, physiotherapists have the right to refer people for X-rays and this is in keeping with best international practice.  However, physiotherapists in Ireland are not allowed to do so and they are included on the list to which I refer.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The aim of the physiotherapists is to optimise the accurate diagnosis and clinical interventions they provide to people.  It is in line with advanced physiotherapy practitioners internationally.  The Irish Society of Chartered Physiotherapists, ISCP, was very disappointed that it was not invited to participate in the consultative practice that was held in June 2017.  I understand the society has written to the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, and to the Department and that the Minister referred the matter to Dr. Tony Holohan, the chief medical officer, for examination.  I understand that a meeting is to take place shortly in respect of considering this matter.  At present, people who attend a physiotherapist and who need an X-ray must be sent back to their doctors, who must then refer them for the X-ray.  This is about time and better patient outcomes because the patient is at the centre of this process, after all.  Physiotherapists do not refer people for an X-ray lightly.  It is only if they have a concern and are not quite sure what the injury is.  It quickens up the process as well in terms of the treatment the patient will receive at the other end.  I am interested in hearing the Minister of State's thoughts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Maria Byrne.  I apologise on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Harris, who unfortunately cannot be here.  He has asked me to reply to the Senator on this matter.</p> <p>The matter relates to the transposition of medical provisions for the basic safety standards directive by the Department of Health and whether physiotherapists will be designated as referrers in the transposing regulations.  The basic safety standards directive, for which the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment has overall responsibility, is important European legislation.  It aims to protect the public, patients, workers and others from all forms of ionising radiation.  While ionising radiation has had beneficial applications, as the use of ionising radiation increases so does the potential for health hazards if not properly used or contained.  The directive enhances and strengthens a number of concepts in radiological protection.  The directive stresses the need for a high level of competency and a clear definition of the responsibilities and tasks among all professionals involved in medical exposure.  This is to ensure the adequate protection of patients undergoing medical radiodiagnostic and radiotherapeutic procedures.  In transposing the medical provisions of the directive, the Department of Health sought the advice of the medical exposure radiation unit, MERU, in the HSE and a group it established to inform the transposition process.  The Department conducted a consultation exercise in June 2017 on certain provisions of the directive.  The consultation was posted on the Department's website and notified to likely stakeholders.  The Department also made arrangements to ensure that licenceholders of ionising radiation equipment were notified of the consultation process.  The directive defines referrers and practitioners with certain roles and responsibilities attached to the roles.  The statutory instrument transposing the directive will designate some who may refer from radiological tests and in this regard, it is proposed to designate nurses, doctors, dentists and radiographers as appropriate.</p> <p>The Physiotherapists Registration Board, established under CORU, opened its register in 2016.  The two-year transition period ends in September 2018, when all existing physiotherapists must register, after which time only those registered can practise as a physiotherapist and use the protected title of physiotherapist.  Physiotherapists are not registered as referred in the current regulations, Sl 478 of 2002, and it is not proposed to designate them in the new regulations.  Not all regulated professions will be designated as referrers in the new regulations.  It would not be appropriate to consider this matter in the context of the directive alone.</p> <p>While there are no current plans to extend the scope of practice of physiotherapists, the Minister for Health launched the national strategic framework for health and social care workforce planning in November 2017.  It is intended that the framework will support the recruitment and retention of the right mix of health workers across the health system to meet planned and projected service need.  In that context it is envisaged that in due course, matters relating to health and social care professionals such as physiotherapists, including scope of practice, will be considered through the framework structure currently being established.  The Department of Health is working to finalise the transposition of the medical provisions of the basic safety standards directive in the coming weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  It is disappointing in one way that physiotherapists are currently not included and that there are no plans.  I acknowledge it is up for consideration but they have the support of many organisations such as the triage steering group, the national clinical programme for rheumatology and the national clinical programme for trauma and orthopaedic surgery.  Basically, physiotherapists play a crucial role in people's health and in people coming back to health.  They are fully trained and have their practice and experience behind them.  I hope the Minister of State will be able to bring to the notice of the Minister, Deputy Harris, that he might be in a position to reconsider it in terms of the review and what he is currently examining.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#D00400"><p>I note the Senator's concerns in this regard and what she said about physiotherapists not being included.  I will raise the issue again on the Senator's behalf with the Minister but there will be further consideration in the framework and as stated in the reply, until those structures have been established I cannot give the Senator any further information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#D00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#D00600">Water and Sewerage Schemes Funding</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#D00700"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome to the House this morning.  I thank her for her presence here.</p> <p>I again raise the issue of the funding of Milltown group sewerage scheme.  Those concerned await an announcement from the Department on the amount of funding and a start date.  I have raised this issue here a few times previously with the responsible Minister of State at the time, Deputy English, and then with his replacement in November 2017.  For the information of the Minister of State, Milltown group water scheme is a scheme of approximately 30 septic tanks that lie outside the periphery of Monaghan town.  Unfortunately, septic tanks are causing a pollution and environmental issue and we are all very keen to get the matter addressed.  The scheme did apply for funding and was successful, under the group sewage scheme, that is, the fund that was announced for 2016 to 2018.  The group was one of six successful applicants and it has been waiting since on the go-ahead from the Department regarding the amount of money required.  In order for this project to go ahead it is essential that this group get 90% of the funding.  The Department and the Minister have accepted that and all we are waiting for is the announcement date.  It is important that I pay tribute to and praise the work of the local community of Milltown in pulling all this together and putting in the application.  I praise the hard-working committee, which had a lot of work to do to pull this together and make sure the application went in.  Again I thank Monaghan County Council for its assistance in this regard.  All we are waiting for now is good news from the Minister of State and I hope she will be in a position this morning to give us that.</p> <p>I wish to ask two brief questions.  The multi-annual programme we are discussing this morning was for 2016 to 2018.  That has since expired and I hope the Minister of State has news today as to what are the Government's plans for the next phase in the future.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Unfortunately only six applicants in the country were successful.  That means only two per year were funded, which I am sure the Minister of State will agree is a very disappointing number.  When it is announced this year, I hope that more groups will be eligible to apply because the fund will be much bigger.</p><p>The group schemes and the multi-annual programme need to be looked at.  Considerable responsibility is placed on citizens to put an application together.  For example, they must form a company, which needs directors with all the responsibility that goes with that.  They have to hire an accountant and prepare accounts every year.  They need legal representation.  They need to collect money from the public.  There is considerable work for people who do not necessarily have qualifications in any of those areas, which is unfair.  I believe successful local authorities should be given a fund and they should lead the project, rather than expecting citizens in the local community to do it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#E00200"><p>I thank Senator Gallagher for bringing up this issue, which I understand he has raised previously in this House.  On behalf of the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, I acknowledge his continued interest in the matter.</p> <p>The Multi-annual Rural Water Programme 2016-2018 operated under the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government includes the funding of group sewerage schemes through what is known as measure 4(d).  This is where the clustering of households on individual septic tanks is not a viable option, particularly from an environmental perspective.</p> <p>In December 2015, the Department received sanction from the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform to increase the maximum grant per house from &euro;6,500 to &euro;6,750 to cover a limited number of new demonstration group sewerage schemes, specifically two per year.  In addition, sanction was also given for these new demonstration group sewerage schemes, in exceptional circumstances, to avail of a supplemental grant, subject to the approval of the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, where the project represents the most economically advantageous option.</p> <p>Where a supplemental grant is approved, the overall level of funding from the rural water programme is limited to 90% of the cost per house subject to a minimum household contribution of &euro;2,250 per house.  In January 2016 local authorities were invited to submit bids for consideration by the Department under the new multi-annual programme.  In total, 83 bids were received from 17 local authorities for funding under measure 4(d) of the new programme.</p> <p>A proposed Milltown group sewerage scheme was included by Monaghan County Council in its funding bids under the measure.  The proposed scheme, with a then estimated cost of &euro;280,000, was expected to cover 32 houses and have a unit cost of &euro;8,750 per house.  I understand that Milltown group sewerage scheme proceeded to tender stage in 2016 with an estimated overall cost of &euro;358,000 to cover 30 houses giving a unit cost of &euro;11,933 per house.</p> <p>Under the new multi-annual funding framework for the rural water programme, an expert panel was convened by the Department to examine the 2016 bids from local authorities for projects under a number of the programme&rsquo;s measures, including measure 4(d), and to make recommendations to the Department on funding.  The panel recommended a priority list to the Department under this measure, including the Milltown scheme at priority number five of the six schemes identified.  The recommendations were accepted in full when approving schemes under the new programme in 2016.</p> <p>As only two demonstration group sewerage schemes can be advanced in any given year, funding was not available to Monaghan County Council for the Milltown scheme in 2016 or 2017.  Interim funding allocations under the programme were made to local authorities earlier this year.  While decisions on the 2018 allocations are yet to be made, the Milltown scheme will be included in this year&rsquo;s allocations, which are currently being finalised.  It is expected that this process will be concluded later this month.  Monaghan County Council will be advised on the funding allocation for the Milltown scheme for 2018 at that point.</p> <p>While we are talking about a specific scheme here, it should be noted that the Government is committed to supporting the funding of rural water services.  Under the national development plan, &euro;95 million has been identified for investment in the rural water programme over the period 2018 to 2021.  The annual provision will increase by &euro;5 million from &euro;20 million to &euro;25 million in 2019 and this enhanced level of investment will be maintained up to 2021.  This significant 25% increase in funding for the programme demonstrates the Government&rsquo;s commitment to invest in this valuable and relevant resource.</p> <p>I again thank the Senator for raising the matter again.  I have taken notes.  I acknowledge I did not answer some of his questions and will ask the Minister to come back to him on the two questions he raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her contribution this morning.  If I am reading her correctly, I welcome that Monaghan County Council will be notified by the end of this month as to whether that scheme has the go-ahead.  I welcome that the scheme will be reopened.  I ask that the points I made in my contribution be taken on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#E00400"><p>I have a note.  I do not need to come back in again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#E00500"><p>The Minister of State has made it clear.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.43" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#E00600">Message from Dil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#E00700"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann passed the Criminal Justice (Corruption Offences) Bill 2017 on 2 May 2018, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.45" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.16 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.46" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Childcare Support Bill 2017 &ndash; Committee Stage, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to adjourn no later than 1.45 p.m. if not previously concluded; and No. 2, statements on the CervicalCheck screening programme, to be taken at 1.45 p.m., with the time allocated to all Senators not to exceed six minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#G00300"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that the Minister for Justice and Equality come to the House to explain why the Government has failed to enact the Corporate Manslaughter (No. 2) Bill 2016 as was proposed and debated by us, as was proposed in the previous Seanad and voted down by the previous Fine Gael-Labour Government and is now not the law of the land.  I raised this on Wednesday with regard to the ongoing scandal surrounding cervical cancer checks.  Having watched the proceedings of the Oireachtas Committee on Health yesterday, it was a debacle of mismanagement.  A debacle is one thing but what they have actually done is kill people.  This, unfortunately, is the reality.  Every person before the committee, bar one, was a man.  They were sorry but there will be no consequences for their mismanagement and failure to act.  I again ask why the offence of grossly negligent management causing death is not a law of the land.  Section 3(1) of the Bill states:</p><blockquote>(1) Where an undertaking has been convicted of corporate manslaughter and a high managerial agent of the convicted undertaking&mdash;(a) knew or ought to reasonably have known of a substantial risk of death or serious personal harm,<br /><br />(b) failed to take reasonable efforts to eliminate that risk,<br /><br />(c) that failure fell far below what could reasonably be expected in the circumstances, and<br /><br />(d) that failure contributed to the commission of the corporate offence,that agent shall be guilty of an offence called &quot;grossly negligent management causing death&quot;.</blockquote> <p>If we had managed to pass that legislation, the penalty for that offence would be 12 years in jail.  Never mind the advisers to Government and the people who came in here with the Minister for Justice and Equality at the time and said there was no need for section 3, we will be back here in a year's time and see who was convicted.  Nobody will have been convicted, however, because the Law Reform Commission has said that as a result of the hepatitis C scandal and the fact that nobody was convicted arising from that, there is a gap in our law.  No legislation has been put in place since, and this was confirmed by the Law Reform Commission, that has managed to plug that gap in our law so that those high managerial agents go to jail.</p><p>If the legislation was in place, we would not need any commissions or tribunals because the courts would do the job, find out the facts and convict people.  People would be held accountable.  The best this Government is hoping for is a bit like Siteserv - set up a commission, set up a committee and let it go away but month by month, women will die as a result of gross mismanagement causing death.  Those responsible should be in jail, but unfortunately, while some women will be in their graves, the Government will not enact the Corporate Manslaughter (No. 2) Bill.  If it comes back on Committee Stage, I propose that it be renamed the Corporate Womanslaughter Bill because, unfortunately, the reason for the legislation is the hepatitis C scandal where thousands of women were knowingly infected and women died.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Here we are again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H00200"><p>Is the Senator referring to the Corporate Manslaughter (No. 2) Bill, which is on the Order Paper?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H00300"><p>Correct.  I am asking the Minister for Justice and Equality to come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H00400"><p>It is not the job of the Minister for Justice and Equality to schedule Seanad business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H00500"><p>It is our job.  That is why we have the Order of Business.  I am proposing an amendment to the Order of Business to allow the Minister for Justice and Equality to come in and spare the taxpayer another commission of inquiry and the need to build another shelf to put another report on with more recommendations that people be held to account and sent to jail for killing women.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H00600"><p>I am advised that the Minister cannot come into the Seanad to say why the Seanad has not scheduled the Bill.  We will let the Deputy Leader deal with the Senator's request.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H00700"><p>We propose amending the Order of Business for the Minister to come in and explain the Corporate Manslaughter Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H00800"><p>The Senator cannot propose it in that way.  It is not in the Minister's power to explain to us why the Seanad has not done it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H00900"><p>I will take the Leas-Chathaoirleach's advice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01000"><p>It is up to the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01100"><p>The Minister could explain why the Government has not enacted the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01200"><p>Why does the Senator not do it through Private Members' business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01300"><p>It is because the health committee brought up issues which make the Corporate Manslaughter Bill relevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01400"><p>The Senator will have to frame his amendment differently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01500"><p>I would like to amend the Order of Business to invite the Minister for Justice and Equality to the House to debate cervical screening and the legislation around it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01600"><p>That is scheduled for today.  The Minister for Health is coming in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01700"><p>He is not in charge of this Bill.  Would it help to take the Corporate Manslaughter (No. 2) Bill today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01800"><p>It is not in the power of the Minister for Justice and Equality to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H01900"><p>It is his Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02000"><p>It does not matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02100"><p>We move an amendment that the Bill be taken today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02200"><p>Does Senator Daly want to take his own Bill today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02400"><p>We would have to allow time for Members to table amendments.  There is a two-day deadline for amendments so the Bill cannot be taken today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02500"><p>We can start it today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02600"><p>We cannot take Committee Stage, unfortunately.  Can the Senator take this up with the office of the Cathaoirleach?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02700"><p>No.  I will ask the Minister for Justice and Equality to come into the House to discuss the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02800"><p>It is not the Minister's job.  I will have to rule it out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H02900"><p>Can the Minister for Justice and Equality come into the House to discuss cervical cancer?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03000"><p>That is what the Minister for Health is coming to the House to do today.  The Senator may put down an amendment to ask the Minister for Justice and Equality to come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03100"><p>I am putting down an amendment that the Minister for Justice and Equality come to the House to discuss cervical cancer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03200"><p>It is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03300"><p>No, it is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03400"><p>If it is separate to the Bill, we will take the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03500"><p>The amendment is tabled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03600"><p>Recent history should teach those of us in political life some lessons about taking responsibility for the actions of others.  Ministers have come under pressure in recent times on a number of high-profile cases such as the blood transfusion anti-D cases, which affected 100,000 women.  In 1991 the blood transfusion board was alerted by British hospitals that a batch of anti-D produced in 1977 may have been contaminated.  It would later emerge that the blood donor whose plasma was used to make the anti-D had jaundice and hepatitis but these facts had slipped through a sloppy screening process.  Despite the alert, no alarm was raised and no action was taken to trace the women who had received doses from the batch, which would have ensured screening slip-ups were not repeated.  They were repeated and, in 1982, plasma from another infected donor was used to make anti-D, creating another potentially lethal batch.  Hepatitis C awards so far have amounted to &euro;1 billion, with the last awards being paid in 2016.  To date, 80 women have lost their lives.  We have to ask if the system has learned anything.</p><p>Bridget McCole was aggressively and hostilely treated by this State to the point where she was forced into a settlement on the day before she died, on the basis that if she did not accept it, it would bring her all the way to the Supreme Court.  In respect of the cervical screening failures, in recent days we have learned that senior officials were aware of CervicalCheck concerns but the State put women through an aggressive and hostile litigation process nevertheless.  Would we know anything about the cervical screening issues but for the brave moves of Vicky Phelan, who was prepared to forgo her anonymity to tell us what had happened to her?</p><p>All of these cases make me wonder about governance in the public sector.  They make me wonder about when political responsibility kicks in.  They make me wonder about the most dangerous piece of administrative law ever to have found its way into the public service.  Members may not be aware of the Carltona principles or the ideas expressed in them.  As established by Carltona <i>v</i>. Commissioners of Works in the UK and having found their  way into the Irish public service, the principles make acts of Government Department officials synonymous with the actions of the Minister in charge of the Department.  It means a public servant speaking in an official capacity is speaking the words of the Minister.  This is lethal because I have seen Minister after Minister dragged into the D&aacute;il and forced to resign over decisions taken by administrative people who remain faceless and hide behind the Carltona doctrine.</p><p>I call for a debate on governance in the public sector, which should examine the impact the Carltona principles continue to have on public decision-making and whether they are healthy in a modern State.  In the past few minutes, my colleague has raised the issue of people making decisions but he should not tell me that the Minister for Health is advised and informed of every single decision that is taken in the Department of Health and has to take the hit if something goes wrong.  The same applies to the Department of Justice and any other Department.  It is time we looked at corporate governance in the public sector, in particular how the people who make decisions are responsible for those decisions.  Very often a Minister is not aware of what happened until the action has been started.  What is the Minister do in that case?  Is he or she to come out and say his or her senior officials made a mistake?  We have seen the most aggressive treatment towards the women in this case.  For some particular bloody reason it always seems to be women.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03800"><p>I wonder how quick the action would have been if the same slip-ups had occurred in respect of prostate tests.  I ask for an open and honest debate on governance within the public sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#H03900"><p>I want to raise an issue that springs from a special joint committee meeting we held this morning, involving three committees, the Joint Committee on Health, the Joint Committee on Education and Skills and the Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection.  It was really impressive and I pay tribute to Senator John Dolan, who I believe initiated the meeting to talk about how we deal with disability and transitioning people from education to employment in a unified way, rather than in a siloed way.  I will give a couple of the statistics that came from the meeting.  The first one will really shock us.  We were talking about the good unemployment figures yesterday, and rightly so, but 71% of adults of working age with a disability are out of work.  It is absolutely staggering.  In addition, 26.3% of adults with a disability live in consistent poverty.  The figures are from the Disability Federation of Ireland and are absolutely stark.  They tell us that we have completely failed when it comes to disability and policies of inclusion, and I say this in a non-party political way.</p> <p>Inclusion Ireland makes a point which gets to the heart of the matter.  They ask why we are spending so much money on putting young people with disabilities through an education system which does not see them as adults progressing into further education, training or employment, but as objects of charity to transition into our health and social services systems.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a damning indictment of successive Governments' failure to address the matter and I am calling for a debate on it.  There are people from all parties with important things to say on this, which is clear from the joint committee's meeting earlier.  The idea of using a unified committee system has much merit.  I pay tribute to Senator Dolan on this.</p><p>I am also raising a matter which is more delicate but which I must put it out there.  It relates to the eighth amendment and the campaign for its repeal.  I am fully respectful of people of different opinions.  If their opinion is against repeal of the eighth amendment, we must listen to and respect that.  I ask for respect for people such as myself who support repeal.  Where I struggle is with the people who are hiding on this issue.  As public representatives, all of us have a duty to indicate where we stand.  The Fine Gael organisation in Limerick has gone into hiding on this issue.  It is being openly discussed among the Together for Yes campaign in Limerick.  If one is for or against, that is fine, but this is not a personal matter, it is matter of public health policy.  As public representatives, we all have to say where we stand.  I want to be very direct on this.  I see my colleague, Senator Kieran O'Donnell, in the House.  I ask him, on behalf of the people, particularly the women, of Limerick, to tell us where he stands on this issue.  We will respect what he says but, he should tell us where he stands.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#J00200"><p>I ask the Cathaoirleach for the indulgence of the House for an amendment to the Order of Business to take No. 12 before No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#J00300"><p>I want to speak on two things.  The House will debate the matter of cervical screening later.  Vicky Phelan is a neighbour of mine.  I know her well.  Tony O'Brien, head of the HSE, stated yesterday that what is happening is a personal blow.  For me, a personal blow must come with personal responsibility.  It is extraordinary that someone who heads up an organisation of this size is not taking responsibility in respect of this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#J00400"><p>The Senator should be careful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#J00500"><p>I know.  I am passing a general comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#J00600"><p>There will be a debate later, as the Senator knows.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#J00700"><p>It is akin to the manager of a soccer team whose players do not perform saying that it is a personal blow to him that they did not perform but that he has no responsibility for their performance on the playing field.  This is a scandal of an unimaginable magnitude for the women involved, brave women such as Vicky Phelan.  Earlier, someone wondered whether this matter would be in the public domain if Vicky Phelan had not come forward.  The likelihood is that it would not.  I have not spoken publicly on this but, in life, people come along who make an indelible impression on one at a personal level.  Vicky is one of those people.</p> <p>I welcome the catchment flood risk assessment and management, CFRAM, report which is being launched in Athlone.  I am delighted that the Taoiseach and the Minister of State, Deputy Kevin Boxer Moran, have reaffirmed that &euro;57.4 million will go to Limerick.  That is &euro;56 million for Limerick city and environs, including St. Mary's Park, with which people will be familiar, and areas such as Corbally, Anacotty, Mount Shannon Road, the Mill Road, and other places in the city centre.  There is an additional &euro;720,000 for the village of Castleconnell, which has experienced repeated flooding.  I welcome the funding for the county.  Rathkeel was allocated &euro;300,000 and Athea &euro;380,000.  I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Boxer Moran.  I brought him down to visit on 1 December last and he saw the devastation caused by the flooding at first hand.  I am grateful for this funding of &euro;57.4 million for Limerick city and environs and further funds for the county, including Castleconnell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#J00800"><p>I second Senator Mark Daly's amendment to the Order of Business.  It is crucial that the Minister should come to the House to discuss the relevant matter.</p> <p>I acknowledge the many Lyme disease patients from across Ireland who gathered outside Leinster House with their families and friends to highlight the plight of Irish sufferers of Lyme and tick-borne co-infections.  We should do more to raise awareness of this awful disease.  One of those who gathered outside is a brave woman from Carlow called Nicola Slattery.  She was here with mother, Margaret.  She said that if she could prevent one more person from having to go through the ordeal she had undergone, it would be worth it.  Prevention is about awareness.  There is not enough awareness about this disease, its symptoms and the devastation it brings to sufferers and their families.  The group who met in Dublin joined millions across the world to raise awareness on this debilitating illness.</p> <p>Lyme disease is a bacterial disease transmitted predominantly by means of a bite from an infected tick.  In Ireland, inaccurate testing makes it impossible to know the real number of cases.  Many must travel abroad for diagnosis and treatment.  The HSE recently estimated that there are over 200 cases in Ireland annually but they do not know because Lyme disease tick-borne co-infections can often be misdiagnosed as myalgic encephalomyelitis, ME, chronic fatigue syndrome, multiple sclerosis, MS, lupus, Parkinson's, Alzheimer's, early-onset dementia, depression or arthritis.  Early diagnosis and treatment are vital for cure.  We must all be educated about ticks and the infections, including sepsis, they can pass on.  This week, the HSE issued an advisory on the disease which we would be wise to highlight.  That is why I am raising this matter.  The message we need to communicate is that people must be aware of and should not dismiss any signs of illness, that they should cover up when outdoors, especially near tick bushes, and they should check for insects on clothing or for bites.  If a tick is removed in the first few hours, the risk of infection is very low.  We all need to play our part and raise awareness.  We should encourage better treatment and diagnosis.  Awareness and education must be part of this programme.  It is about the awareness which we do not have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#J00900"><p>I refer to the change in strategy required in respect of employment and unemployment.  Four or five years ago, the unemployment rate was 14.5%.  We are informed that it has fallen to 5.9%.  This creates a totally different challenge for our economy in how we deal with a situation where we are close to full employment.  That is a great credit to everybody but what is the next stage?  The Construction Industry Federation says that 110,000 workers will be needed in the next three years.  How will we build the houses?  We do not have the electricians, plasters or labourers to do the work.  In the past, we depended on people coming here from other countries, but I do not think that will happen now.  We need a very clear, concise, accountable plan in respect of this matter.</p> <p>I am delighted that teachers have been in receipt of improved pay since 1 January last.  As a former teacher - I was a school steward - I am aware that teachers are a key part of the fabric of our country and our communities.  We need to look after our teachers a lot better because they are going into private industry.  My colleague, Senator Craughwell, has often spoken on what is happening to our Air Corps pilots.  It is not an either-or scenario when it comes to the public and private sectors, I believe in the word which should be used is "and".  It is inclusive, it is about connectivity.  We all depend on each other. Salaries will increase significantly, and that is fine, I do not have a problem with it.  However, while it is a bit late now, we need to retrain our workforce so that it is fit for purpose and meets future needs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2482"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2482&amp;amp;pid=PadraigOCeidigh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For example, there are 35,000 primary school teachers and 27,000 secondary school teachers, teaching about 900,000 pupils.  It is really difficult, if not impossible, to get people to go into the teaching profession or to get people in the profession to stay there.  I ask the Deputy Leader to convey this to Government and the relevant Ministers.  The Government needs to produce a new clear strategy to support our future employment needs.</p><p>On the Commencement Matters debate this morning, there was some very good discussion on chefs and our hospitality industry.  This is becoming an epidemic at this stage.  I would appreciate feedback on that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#K00200"><p>As all Senators will know, my home peninsula, Inishowen, was devastated by floods last August.  The village of Burnfoot was particularly devastated.  Journalists from RT&Eacute; and the rest of the national media were based in that village for two days.  They told the story of the families.  In one council estate, Grianan Park, which is a lovely little community, half of the residents were out of their homes.  Raw sewage washed through their homes.  They were heartbroken.  They have been told that they will not be back in their homes this year or for the foreseeable future.</p> <p>Other private homes and businesses were absolutely devastated.  A range of senior Ministers came in and promised them that flood defences would be built.  This was a sore point because, even though it had flooded repeatedly, a cost-benefit analysis ruled out flood defences for the location.  It was assessed to be better and cheaper to let the houses flood than to build flood defences.  It was offensive.</p> <p>Today, eight months later, a major announcement has been made in Ahtlone today and I am shocked that no commitment has been given on Burnfoot. The community in Burnfoot should be getting news today that the village's flood defences are to be built as soon as possible.  We are hearing that further assessments are being done and there could be another announcement in four weeks.</p> <p>The Ministers know who they are because they stood before those families and business owners who were heartbroken, many of whom are still not back in their homes.  They were given promises that this would be sorted out.  The people of Donegal - not just Inishowen - and the north west will not accept those people being abandoned.  We were expecting in the next four weeks flood defences to be confirmed by the Minister of State.  It should have been confirmed today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#K00300"><p>I rise again today to talk about another parliament, the British House of Lords.  The UK Government has suffered its tenth defeat in the House of Lords on Brexit.  This one would give the UK Parliament powers to reject any Brexit deal that includes a hard border in Northern Ireland.  This is hugely significant and at last the politicians in Westminster are seeing the damage that a hard border arising from Brexit could do to the island of Ireland.</p> <p>I thank Lord Patten, the former chairman of the Conservative Party, whose parents actually come from Boyle, County Roscommon, where I live.  He said they were playing with fire and pursuing a policy in Northern Ireland that is "sometimes clueless and sometimes delinquent".  While the issue of the Border and the island of Ireland was not part of the Brexit campaign discussions, effectively the Border will be the Achilles heel to Brexit.  The Border is not just economic; it is a social and psychological issue on the island of Ireland.  I welcome this latest vote in the British House of Lords.  While it is a decision for the UK Government, I hope for all concerned on the two islands that the House of Commons would be able follow what is happening in the House of Lords.  We never thought we would be saying that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#K00400"><p>I second Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's proposal to amend the Order of Business.</p> <p>After the Order of Business yesterday, I introduced a Bill on short-term lettings.  Yesterday evening, I was targeted by an ad for hassle-free hospitality for short-term lets.  When I filled in the form, Airsorted offered &euro;5,250 a month profit on letting a two-bedroom house in the centre of Dublin.  How could ordinary workers have an opportunity to rent premises at &euro;5,250 a month?  Airsorted was also offering hassle-free hosting, cleaning, laundering and providing keys.  The rent for the same unit is &euro;2,000 a month.  Is it any wonder that 3,500 units previously let on a long-term basis by ordinary working people have gone to short-term letting?</p> <p>I hounded the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Coveney, when he was Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, and I continue hound the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy.  Each of them has repeatedly promised legislation, but nothing has happened.  Last year after a circular on planning enforcement for short-term lets was issued, the number of enforcements reduced instead of increasing.  There is a real problem that is not being addressed.</p> <p>I welcome the announcement on the flood-relief work.  I remind the House and the Minister, that more than six years ago I worked alongside Brian Hayes, MEP, who was then Minister of State with responsibility for the OPW, to get a memorandum of understanding with Insurance Ireland, representing the insurance companies, to ensure that when flood protection work was carried out up to a once-in-150-year standard residents in areas covered by that could receive flood insurance.  Every week I get a query about flood insurance despite millions of euro of taxpayers' money having been spent in areas such as Clonmel, Dublin, Limerick and Cork.  The impact is that people in larger family residences cannot sell their homes to young couples because those young couples cannot get a mortgage unless they have flood insurance.  We have been calling for action for six years and nothing has happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#K00500"><p>There is a shortage of dementia beds in County Meath, relating to issues in St. Joseph's public nursing home in Trim.  In 2012 and 2013, HIQA published a report showing that St. Joseph's was not up to HIQA standards.  Senator James Reilly when he was Minister for Health came on board and allocated &euro;1.2 million to St. Joseph's which ended up being a new 50-patient nursing home and passed all the HIQA standards.  In 2014 and 2015, a further &euro;200,000 to &euro;300,000 was invested into St. Joseph's to fix the old roof.  In 2015 and 2016, when planning a new future, a shortage of dementia beds in County Meath was identified and &euro;2.5 million was promised for investment in St. Joseph's.</p> <p>Since then, nothing has happened.  We have very few dementia beds in County Meath.  It is not right that we have a greenfield site state-of-the-art St. Joseph's nursing home that is ready to go.  We badly need this unit in County Meath.  Why is the HSE delaying this project?  The money has been allocated and is in the clouds somewhere.  I want it to come down from the clouds.  We need to invest it in St. Joseph's and get these dementia beds operational.  I would like the Minister to come to the House to explain why the money has not been allocated to County Meath, which really needs these dementia beds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#K00600"><p>Yesterday, we got worrying news from Brussels of a proposed 5% cut in CAP payments.  It forms part of a discussion on the EU budget for 2021 to 2027.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The news of that proposed 5% cut will create fear among small-farm families the length and breadth of the country.  Considering that for many families, the CAP payments make up about 75% of their total income, it is understandable that they would be worried and fearful.  For many small suckler and sheep farmers, the average income is only &euro;13,000 per annum.  It is a very important issue for small-farm families and for rural Ireland.  Rural Ireland depends on the farming community because what the farmer earns, the farmer spends.  I ask that the Leader stresses the importance of the Government and of Commissioner Phil Hogan forcefully rejecting this proposal.  I ask that they use all their clout to ensure this proposal does not go ahead.  Farming families cannot afford this cut; nor can rural Ireland.  I ask the Leader to ensure that the Government does all in its power to prevent this cut from proceeding.</p><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that No. 11 be taken before No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#L00200"><p>I join with other Members of the House in congratulating our two new colleagues, Senators Anthony Lawlor and Ian Marshall.  I wish them well and a long term in the House.</p> <p>I ask the Deputy Leader to secure the attendance of the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection in the House in respect of pensions.  We have all received many letters recently from people working for Irish Life in respect of their Irish Life defined benefit pensions.  This could spread to other companies as well.  The Irish Life scheme meets the funding standard.  There are 1,000 employees in it and the company has &euro;1.3 billion in assets.  As the fund itself has &euro;240 million, it meets all the criteria.  Irish Life is the biggest provider of pensions in the country.  It was bailed out by the State and this is an issue we need to talk about.  I hope the Minister will come to the House to address the whole area of pensions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#L00300"><p>I second Senator Gallagher's proposal to amend the Order of Business in respect of No. 11.</p> <p>I want to touch on something Senator Feighan spoke about this morning.  It was really nice to read the headlines of the national and UK newspapers this morning.  For once, we can be reassured that Ireland has friends in the House of Lords.  That has not just happened but has evolved as a relationship.  I make particular reference to the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, BIPA, of which the Leas-Chathaoirleach and Senators Noone, Feighan and others are members.  It has played a very active part in developing personal relationships.  I have always believed that if one wins people's hearts, one wins their minds.  Breaking bread and sharing hospitality and culture with others makes everyone open to receiving.  Through dialogue and friendship we open doors.  When we open doors, we open hearts and opportunities.  That has been well illustrated.</p> <p>The House of Lords voted yesterday to give MPs a veto on the Irish hard border question.  The peers in the House of Lords have voted to empower their MPs to stop a Brexit deal that might restore a hard border across the island of Ireland.  The Upper House supported an amendment to the EU withdrawal Bill that would bar the introduction of border checks and formation of physical infrastructure without the prior agreement of the Irish Government.  That is very significant.  The House of Lords in Britain is the nearest equivalent to the Upper House here in Ireland.  By building those relationships, we have opened doors.  This deal is not done yet.  There is a lot of water yet to go under the bridge.  I urge my colleagues to continue to build relationships and dialogue, to take up the phone, travel, meet and talk about our genuine concerns for the island of Ireland and, more importantly, for the unity of Europe, the European ideal and the principles that bind Europeans together for the common good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#L00400"><p>I also wish to express my concern at the news emanating from Brussels yesterday that there is a proposed 5% cut to the CAP budget.  We have to redouble our efforts to reverse this proposal.  The Taoiseach has indicated that as a net contributor to the EU budget, he is prepared to allow Ireland to increase its contribution to the CAP and to require other member states to step up to the plate also.  We cannot contemplate this 5% cut.  Payments and supports under the Common Agricultural Policy are the difference between an income and no income for farmers.  It is a very small income at that, with all the costs of running farms, feeding cattle, fertiliser and so on.  The farmers would simply be lost without this payment and we will see people leaving farming if we do not get this right.</p> <p>I welcome the announcement of the national flood management plan today, particularly the long-awaited announcement of a flood relief scheme for Ballina and Westport.  I have intimate knowledge of the devastation that flooding in early 2014 brought to people along the banks of the River Moy in Ballina.  Homes were destroyed, including those of a lot of older people living in Bachelors Walk, Arbuckle Row and Clare Street.  Every time there is heavy rain and a high tide, they are in fear of being flooded again.  I commend Mayo County Council and the fire service.  They are always to the fore with pumps and sandbags, clearing channels and doing their utmost to prevent this.  It has been identified as a significant flood risk area.  We have gone through the processes of the flood report and a proposal for flood walls.  It is very satisfying to hear today that this will proceed to detailed design, planning permission and ultimately construction and, best of all, that it is to be funded under the &euro;1 billion promised for flood defences up to 2027.  That is good news for Ballina.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#L00500"><p>I agree that the Minister needs to come to the House to address the CAP issue.  It is very worrying for farming.  The substantive issue I want to talk about now, however, is the presentation that was made in the audiovisual room earlier this morning.  It was in connection with the drug called valproate and its impact in respect of foetal anticonvulsant syndrome, FACS.  We heard from parents who were advised to take this drug and indeed for whom it was insisted that they take it while they were pregnant.  They now see the impact it has had on their children.  The teratogenic effects of valproate were first reported in the 1980s and have been widely accepted since the mid-1990s.  I am calling for an investigation of the historical impact of valproate.  That has to be done.  No more than what we have been hearing in the past couple of days in respect of cervical screening and the huge cover-up that was done, all the people who were prescribing this drug knew of its effects and kept this from expectant mothers.  Those mothers ended up having children with severe disabilities.  There needs to be a thorough investigation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want the Minister to come to the House to talk about FACS, its implications, the possibility of establishing a redress scheme - as has been done in France - the risk reduction measures that need to be put in place and the overall service needs of these children and their parents.  It is not acceptable that there are 1,300 children on the waiting list at Our Lady's Children's Hospital, Crumlin.  I want a full debate on this matter in the House because it will take much longer to deal with it than the two minutes I have available to me now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M00200"><p>Before calling on the next speaker, I welcome the Waterford active retirement group to the Gallery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M00300"><p>I support the comments of fellow Members expressing concerns about a reduction in CAP payments and support mechanisms for farmers.  It is important that we make very clear that it is not this industry's desire to receive handouts or support payments.  It is a situation at which the industry has arrived through no fault of its own.  The reality is that a drive and ambition to get cheaper and cheaper food has left us in a system where these people are wholly dependent on support mechanisms from Brussels.  That said, we need to be very clear.  We all refer to sustainable agriculture.  What is sustainability?  We are all aware of the three pillars of sustainability: economic, environmental and social.  Very often, the social side of it is the bit that is overlooked because Ireland, both North and South, is completely dependent on the success and vibrancy of its rural economy.  If the rural economy is doing well, the country will do well and that is an important thing to note.  There will be huge concerns if we overlook the importance of the creation of jobs and wealth in rural economies.  If we want to retain jobs and businesses in the rural economy, first and foremost, farming and agriculture must be profitable.  If we are serious about keeping young people on the land and stopping migration to cities and other parts of the world, it is important that we resist any temptation to reduce support mechanisms.  We should remember that this is not about farm support, it is about cheap food support mechanisms.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M00400"><p>I echo the remarks of Senators Feighan and Boyhan regarding yesterday's Brexit amendment vote in the British House of Lords.  It is a strange experience, almost like something from "The Twilight Zone", when one looks to the House of Lords to show a bit of sense in respect of this matter.  I do not say that to be provocative.  I say it as someone who-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M00500"><p>There are some very good people there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M00600"><p>I note that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M00700"><p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach should be there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M00800"><p>We are keeping up the friendships.  We do keep in contact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M00900"><p>One never knows who will finish up there.  Senator Marshall is now a Member of this House, so one never knows.  I note it and despite the bit of craic we have had, it is a very significant amendment and an important process, one that stands in stark contrast to the approach of Theresa May and her Government with their reckless position regarding the progress that has been made in respect of our economy, our political and peace processes and all of the agricultural and social components that have been outlined.</p> <p>There is a blessing in Irish which I am sure many of us have heard - "go maire t&uacute; an c&eacute;ad" - which means may you reach the 100.  Today, that most Irish of institutions - O'Neills - marks its 100th birthday.  It is an institution with which all of us who are participants in or followers of a wide range of sports in Ireland such as GAA, rugby, boxing and many others are familiar.  To me, O'Neills is a real case in point with regard to the potential threat of Brexit to our indigenous businesses.  The O'Neills warehouse straddles the Border up around Strabane.  It employs people from that wider Border region.  It does a fantastic job not just with regard to the quality of product it produces and exports globally but also in providing employment across Ireland.  It is a cause for celebration that it has reached this milestone but in the context of Brexit and what has been already said, we must ensure we do everything we can to make sure O'Neills sees out the next 100 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M01000"><p>I have not had the opportunity to congratulate and welcome our two new Senators.  Senator Lawlor is not here at the moment.  I hope both of them will have a very productive, happy and collegial time here in the Seanad and that they get to work on a lot of the issues.  I was very impressed with Senator Marshall's contribution this morning.  It is great to have them here.</p> <p>Senator Mark Daly spoke about the Corporate Manslaughter (No. 2) Bill 2016.  I hear what he is saying.  The cervical cancer screening issue that is unfolding literally by the hour is disgraceful.  I am astonished that we have to talk about this in the Parliament.  In respect of not just negligence but the willful withholding of information, it is one thing to make a bad decision but to willfully withhold information from women is deplorable.  There are no words.  My heart goes out to the women who have been affected by this and who do not know at this point whether they have been affected.  Every woman in Ireland deals with this issue every so often.  We must have faith in the service.  A really important point needs to be emphasised over and over again.  We need women to continue to have these tests.  We need to restore confidence in the system.  For the most part, it has worked very effectively.  It has been very positive and thorough for any woman I know who has had treatment, such as through a regular smear test and ending up in the colposcopy department.  First and foremost, we need to restore that.</p> <p>On the Senator's amendment to the Order of Business and his request for the Minister for Justice and Equality to come before the House, the Minister is due to go before the Select Committee on Justice and Equality with the Data Protection Bill today.  The select committee's meeting is due to last until midnight.  The Minister has offered to come before the House on Tuesday evening to deal with the issue if that is to the Senator's satisfaction.  That is the earliest point at which the Minister can be here.  There is a wider issue when it comes to political accountability.  The fact that Ministers and Deputies are elected by the people makes them accountable to the people.  By all means, politicians need to be fully accountable but I do not see why the permanent government should not be accountable.  I feel really strongly about that.  Naturally, I would defend the Minister for Health but I thought it was really difficult for him, on a human level, to go into the D&aacute;il with information he was given at very short notice.  How can he have full confidence in the information he has been given when it changes by the hour?  I really think there needs to be accountability in the permanent government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M01100"><p>The same thing happened to the former T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Fitzgerald.  She was given bad information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#M01200"><p>I am not trying to shirk politicians' responsibility to be accountable.  However, let me ask the following question.  How big is the health service?  It is massive.  How can one individual be totally <i>au fait</i>and on top of what is going on in every facet of that service?  It is a physical impossibility so the idea that we cannot rely on managers in that service is beyond the beyond as far as I am concerned.  I hear what the Senator is saying regarding the Corporate Manslaughter (No. 2) Bill 2016.  The Minister for Health has indicated that there will be criminal sanction in the future and that this is his plan in this area for medics or other professionals who withhold this type of information.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We would all be satisfied to hear from the Minister for Justice and Equality about what plans he has for a potential Bill such as the Senator mentioned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N00200"><p>It needs to cover all the public service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N00300"><p>I cannot hear the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N00400"><p>That is what the corporate manslaughter Bill is about, not just the health service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N00500"><p>The Senator can let me know if that is acceptable to him in due course.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell raised a few issues but fundamentally he is seeking a debate on governance in the public sector.  That would be a very useful debate especially in light of recent developments.  He mentioned the mistreatment of women.  I cannot stand here as a woman and say that I do not feel that women have been let down repeatedly by the State.  We are in the middle of a referendum campaign that is, again, about women.  I almost feel that I constantly have to speak about things relating to women that are below the belly button.  It is really too much for the women of Ireland to have to go through this over and over again.  I agree with Senator Craughwell's comments in that regard and I would encourage having a debate on governance in the public sector.</p> <p>Senator Gavan highlighted a positive initiative of the health, education and employment committees this morning on how to deal with disability and getting those who are disabled into work and education.  He also raised the eighth amendment and his comments in that regard are noted.</p> <p>I accept Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's proposed amendment to the Order of Business.  I presume we will deal with that shortly.</p> <p>Senator Kieran O'Donnell referred to Vicky Phelan, who is a neighbour of his and who has done the State an extraordinary and courageous service.  As he said, it is a scandal of unimaginable proportions.  We all owe her a massive debt of gratitude for highlighting the issue.  I hope she receives justice, in more ways than one, over the coming weeks and months.  The Senator also welcomed the CFRAM flooding report, which is positive for his area.</p> <p>Senator Murnane O'Connor raised Lyme disease.  It is a serious disease and awareness is obviously vital.</p> <p>In response to Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh, some years ago when we first spoke about the Action Plan for Jobs I doubt that anybody believed we would reach a point of being close to full employment.  Unemployment is under 6% for the first time in ten years, which is very significant.  Obviously, however, planning is required to get people trained.  I have done some work on the chefs issue and it is a huge issue.  The Senator's point is well made and a debate on that in due course would be a good idea.</p> <p>It so happens that every time I have sat in this chair as Deputy Leader, Senator &Oacute; Lochlainn has raised the flooding issue.  I heard his frustration and I would be hopeful.  However, I cannot comment directly on it because I have not read the report.  It sounds as if the people mentioned by the Senator badly need these flood defences.  I will ask the Minister to communicate with the Senator on what the plan is over the coming weeks.  The Senator is quite right to raise it.  The fact that half of the residents are out of their homes is appalling for them, but I will have to refer back to the Senator on the matter because I do not know the details of what is planned by the Department.</p> <p>I am afraid we will lose Senator Feighan to the House of Lords at some point soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N00600"><p>Lord Feighan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N00700"><p>Lord Roscommon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N00800"><p>No, Lord Boyle.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N00900"><p>Obviously, the vote in the House of Lords is hugely significant.  A hard border is a red line for us in Ireland, North and South.  It is not something we will tolerate.  The fact that the House of Lords had this vote raises the point of the validity and importance of a second chamber.  It has an impact and puts pressure on Theresa May's government and on the House of Commons.  We will have to watch that space for the moment.</p> <p>Senator Humphreys raised short-term lettings, which is a major issue that he raises frequently.  I can convey his points to the Minister with regard to any legislation being considered.  The Senator is tireless on the issue.  He also welcomed the flood relief for his area, which is very significant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N01000"><p>There is also the cost of flood insurance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#N01100"><p>The insurance issue is massive.  It would be good to have a debate on insurance generally in the House, because insurance is not only an issue in that area.  Every time I have taken a taxi recently the drivers have told me they are having problems with motor insurance due to massive increases.  It also affect younger people.  A wider debate on insurance would be a good idea.</p> <p>Senator Butler raised the important issue of dementia beds in his area.  That would be a good item to put forward for a Commencement debate to get a more substantial, direct and specific answer from the Minister.  It is an important issue.</p> <p>Senator Gallagher and others raised the cut in CAP payments.  I cannot say I would be the world's leading expert on CAP payments but it certainly is a massive issue for rural Ireland.  Given the fact that in many cases the payments represent 75% of total income it is a major worry.  Knowing Mr. Phil Hogan, I believe he will do all in his power to ensure it does not happen, but we will just have to hope that any impact that can be made on the issue will happen over the coming weeks.</p> <p>Senator Paddy Burke raised Irish Life and the pensions issue and asked that the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection be invited to the House.  It would be good to have a debate on pensions generally given that we have an ageing population.  I will suggest holding that debate in the coming months.</p> <p>Senator Boyhan raised the vote in the House of Lords and referred to the relationships that are built by different parliamentary friendship groups and the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly.  It is incumbent on all of us, now more than ever, to build relationships with the UK.</p> <p>Senator Mulherin also raised the CAP budget and the national flood management plan.  She welcomed the scheme for Ballina and Westport.</p> <p>In addition to raising the CAP, Senator Conway-Walsh raised the valproate drug which is a hugely negative thing to have happened.  A full debate on that would be a good idea, and I will communicate that to the Leader.  There is always reason for the Minister for Health to come to the House and it could be discussed in the context of a wider debate, but it certainly warrants discussion.  It also could be the subject of a Commencement debate in due course.  I find the Commencement debate offers a very satisfactory opportunity to interact on a specific issue.</p> <p>Senator Marshall also raised the CAP payments.  He had a more unusual take on it in the sense that not many people focus on the fact that the reason for these subsidies is to ensure that everybody can have cheaper and affordable food.  It is not just a requirement or a need to be subsidised.  The sustainability point is very important.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile also raised the vote in the House of Lords.  Obviously, O'Neills is around for a long time but I had not realised it was 100 years.  It highlights how much of an impact Brexit, including the fear of it, is having on companies.  We must do all in our power to support companies such as O'Neills, but we congratulate it today.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That concludes the responses to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O00200"><p>Senator Mark Daly has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That a debate with the Minister for Justice and Equality on corporate responsibility for screening for cervical cancer be taken today."  The Senator has heard the Deputy Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O00300"><p>In light of the reply of the Deputy Leader, I will withdraw the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O00400"><p>The amendment is, by leave, withdrawn.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 12 be taken before No. 1."  The Deputy Leader has indicated she is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>Senator Robbie Gallagher has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 11 be taken today."  The Deputy Leader has indicated she is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.135" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.136" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O00600">Free Education (Prohibition of Fees and Charges) Bill 2018: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O00700"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to prohibit recognised schools, subject to certain exceptions, from charging admission or enrolment fees or from otherwise seeking contributions from parents towards meeting the costs and expenses incurred in providing education at that school; and to provide for connected matters.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O00800"><p>Is there a seconder?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O00900"><p>I second the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.140" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O01100"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O01200"><p>Next Tuesday.  Can I say a few short words on it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O01300"><p>No.  The Senator will have his chance next Tuesday.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.144" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 8 May 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.145" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O01500">First Aid and Mental Health in Schools (Existing Teachers) Bill 2018: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O01600"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to provide for the introduction of a requirement that all existing staff in schools be trained in occupational first aid response and mental health first aid; to require that training in occupational first aid response and mental health first aid forms part of a continuing professional development requirement for school staff; to provide for the approval of first aid response courses and mental health first aid courses; and to provide for related matters.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O01700"><p>Is there a seconder?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O01800"><p>I second the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.149" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O02000"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O02100"><p>Next Tuesday perhaps.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O02200"><p>There is a lot on next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O02300"><p>There always is.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.154" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 8 May 2018.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.155" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.43 p.m. and resumed at 12.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.156" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O02600">Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#O02700"><p>The Joint Committee on Health at its meeting today has completed its consideration of the following order passed by the Seanad on 25 April 2018:</p><blockquote>(i) Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(3)) (Variation of title: Dietician) Regulations 2018, and<br /><br />(ii) Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(3)) (Variation of title: Speech Therapist) Regulations 2018.<br /><br />copies of which have been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 10 April 2018.</blockquote></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.158" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#P00100">Childcare Support Bill 2017: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.159" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#P00300"><p>Amendments Nos. 1 to 3, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.161" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#P00500"><p>I am pleased to have the opportunity to bring the Childcare Support Bill 2017 to Committee Stage.  When I introduced the Bill to the Seanad on Second Stage I was grateful for the strong support I received from all sides of the House and for the constructive engagement from Senators.  In addition to the amendments I am proposing today, I would like to signal in advance that I may propose one final amendment on Report Stage.  This amendment relates to the list of issues specified in section 8 of the Bill.  Section 8 lists the issues which may be included within the contract that childcare providers will be asked to sign should they wish to take part in the affordable childcare scheme.  The potential Report Stage amendment, which I am still examining, reflects my desire to ensure that the Bill is future-proofed and leaves open the possibility of including a sufficient range of potential levers to effectively enhance the quality of childcare provision.</p> <p>Amendments Nos. 1, 2 and 3 are technical drafting amendments.  Under the affordable childcare scheme, personal public service, PPS, numbers will be provided as part of applications for financial support.  PPS numbers are referred to in sections 7 and 9 of the Bill, however section 7 includes a specific reference to the definition of PPS number in the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 while section 9 does not.  The amendment addresses this minor inconsistency to ensure that there is a single clear definition of a PPS number which applies throughout the Bill.</p> <p>Amendment No. 1 inserts a definition into section 1, the section which sets out the interpretation of terms used throughout the Bill.  The definition ties the term "personal public service number" to its use in the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005.  Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 are consequential on amendment No. 1 and delete definitions of "personal public service number" that appear in section 7 of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.163" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.164" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 1, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.165" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 2 to 6, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.166" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.167" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 2:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.168" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.169" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 3:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.170" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.171" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 7, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.172" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 8</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.173" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: &ldquo;That section 8 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#P01700"><p>I wish to note that while I have not tabled any Committee Stage amendments to section 8, I may propose one final amendment to this section on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.175" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.176" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 9</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#P02000"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.178" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 4:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#P02200"><p>Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 clarify which children are taken into account when determining the multiple child deduction that will apply to an applicant's assessable income.  The multiple child deduction is a deduction from income which I intend to provide for families that have more than one child under the age of 15.  It is intended to reflect the cumulative impact of childcare costs on families as it is total childcare costs, the combined costs relating to all their children, which matter to parents when they are making decisions as to whether to participate in the labour market.  More broadly, the deduction is intended to reflect the relationship between a larger family size and economic vulnerability.</p><p>Section 13(5) of the Bill sets out the matters which the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs must take into account when making regulations on the methodology for calculating the level of subsidy under the scheme.  These matters include the number of children in the family.  In other words, this section gives the Minister the power to apply a multiple child deduction to a family's income for the purpose of the scheme's income assessment.  Section 9(3) of the Bill ensures that the scheme administrator is provided with all the necessary information on other children in the family, again in order to allow for the application of this multiple child deduction.</p><p>In providing for the multiple child deduction, it is essential that the Bill is absolutely clear as to which children may count towards it.  The two amendments proposed today are intended to clarify that the relevant children are, first, those children in respect of whom either the applicant or the applicant's partner is a parent or acts in a parental role and, second, are children who reside with the applicant or the applicant's partner.  The first condition, requiring a parental relationship, ensures that the child cannot count towards the multiple child deduction if the child happens to live in the same house as the applicant but the applicant or his or her partner does not care for the child.  In this context it must be remembered that throughout the Bill the term &quot;parent&quot; is defined to include a person acting <i>in loco parentis</i>and includes a guardian.  To be perfectly clear, a child in relation to whom the applicant is a guardian or foster carer can count towards the multiple child deduction.</p><p>The second condition, requiring that the child and applicant or applicant's partner reside together, ensures that a child cannot count towards the multiple child deduction if the applicant is a parent of the child but does not have regular care of the child.  Again, in this context, it should be noted that there is no need to include within the multiple child deduction a child who does not reside with the applicant but for whom an applicant makes maintenance payments.  To remind Senators, maintenance payments made by an applicant are fully deductible in the parents' income assessment as a result of the allowable deductions specified in Schedule 1.</p><p>Amendment No. 4 amends section 9(3) to clarify that information including name, PPS number and date of birth should be provided in the application form only for children in respect of whom the applicant or the applicant's partner is a parent.  Amendment No. 5 amends section 13(5) to clarify that, when making regulations on the multiple child deduction, only children who reside with the applicant or applicant's partner and in relation to whom the applicant or applicant's partner is a parent should be counted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.180" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.181" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 9, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.182" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 10 to 12, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.183" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 13</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.184" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.185" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.186" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 13, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.187" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 14 to 23, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.188" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 24</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#P03200"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 and 7 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.190" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#P03400"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 and 7 are minor technical drafting amendments.  These amendments simply involve punctuation changes to clarify the meaning of section 24.  There is no change in policy and the amendments will have no practical consequence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.192" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.193" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 7:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.194" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.195" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 24, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.196" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 25 to 30, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.197" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedules 1 to 3, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.198" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.199" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.200" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Acting Chairman (Senator Gerard Craughwell)" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#Q00800"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#Q00900"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.202" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Report Stage ordered for Tuesday, 8 May 2018.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.203" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1 p.m. and resumed at 1.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.204" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#U00100">CervicalCheck Screening Programme: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#U00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#U00300"><p>I am very glad to address Seanad &Eacute;ireann this afternoon on this very important issue which has arisen and which I know has caused a great deal of concern, particularly to women, right across the country.  I thank Senators on all sides for providing me with an opportunity to address them today.  I reiterate my gratitude to Vicky Phelan for her courage in bringing this issue to light and acknowledge the important role she has played in highlighting a number of weaknesses in respect of how people have experienced our national cervical screening programme, CervicalCheck.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I wish to provide the Seanad with an update on the actions the Government has taken since the full impact of this issue became apparent.  As Senators know, I took immediate actions, including: sending a serious incident management team into CervicalCheck to get to the bottom of the information that was emerging about the extent of non-disclosure; ordering an immediate change to the process, which was not ensuring that women were automatically informed of reviews of their screens; and announcing that we would have an international review.  The Government has since taken a series of further actions, including the establishment of two clinical reviews by international experts: one in respect of the individual cases of women whose screening results were reviewed and who were not told; and a second to conduct an audit of all previous screening results of every woman diagnosed with cervical cancer in the past ten years.  All of the work under way as a result of these actions will, of course, feed into a wider inquiry on this matter.</p><p>Last evening, I met members of other political parties and groupings in the Oireachtas to discuss the best way forward on the issue.  It was agreed that there is a need for early answers here and, as a result, I am now working on a scoping inquiry which will led by an international expert and which, I hope, could conclude by June.  I consider that to be an important approach to establish some basic facts which can be quickly put in the public domain, while also identifying issues which may merit a full statutory investigation and developing terms of reference for such an investigation.  Let me say clearly that I think we are going to need a commission of investigation with full statutory powers so that people might find out who knew what, where and when and in order that we might learn from this.  What we do not want to do - I am conscious of what Vicky Phelan said we do not want to do - is jump straight into a process that could go on for a period.  What we need to do instead is gather as many facts, data and information as we possibly can through a scoping process, let that process also benefit from the knowledge of the international medical review panel and allow the scoping process talk to women who have been impacted, engage with them and come up with draft terms of reference as well.</p><p>I want to say on the record of this House that it is my clear intention that the process will include engagement with Vicky Phelan and other women who may wish to have an input.  Last night, I also invited party spokespersons to continue to input into the consideration of this matter and I intend to bring a proposal to Government next week.  It is important that the Government moves forward in respect of this matter next week.  We have had a lot of very important discussion this week but now we need an independent expert to get to the bottom of who knew what, when and where, gather the basic facts and look at the terms of reference - and also the process - so that we could perhaps have a modular process to get the answers for women and also the answers that our health service needs.</p><p>For the information of the Seanad, I would like to again go through some of the numbers and facts which have been established.  When the controversy surrounding Ms Phelan's case came to light, the HSE initially advised that between 2008 and early 2018, 1,482 cervical cancer cases were notified to CervicalCheck.  The majority were women who had already been referred for further investigation or treatment by CervicalCheck.  As part of the clinical audit process, these notified cases were re-examined and 277 were flagged for further cytology review.  In 208 of the 277 cases, the cytology review recommendations differed from the original test.  On Friday, 27 April, the HSE established a serious incident management team at my request to go into CervicalCheck and oversee and direct the management of this incident.  The serious incident management team has reported that, as of yesterday, 172 of the 208 women involved have now been informed of the outcome of the audit process and arrangements have been made for them to have appointments with their treating clinicians.  Efforts to reach the remaining 36 women are ongoing and I expect that this work will be largely completed today.  I sincerely regret to say that 17 of the patients involved are deceased and I express my sympathies to their families.  In these cases, contact is being made with the next of kin.  Let me be clear about this: where a woman is deceased the next of kin, the family, has every right to know and be contacted and that will happen.</p><p>Arising from the work of the serious incident management team, it transpired that the number of cases of cervical cancer notified to CervicalCheck does not represent all cases of cervical cancer occurring in Ireland since the establishment of the CervicalCheck programme in September 2008.  That was a most astonishing revelation which was brought to my attention approximately 20 minutes before I was due to address D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and take questions and hear statements for the best part of four hours.  At that late stage, I was landed with the fact by an official that there may be many other cases.  It is the most frightening position to be in, namely, when one hears that what one has been told and what one has truthfully been putting out there now may not be factually correct.  It is not frightening in the sense of looking for sympathy for me but it is frightening knowing that I had a choice to go into D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and tell the truth of what I knew but also that it would add to the uncertainty and concern of women throughout the country.  I find the situation appalling and it is one I want to get to the bottom of, because regardless of whomever is the Minister for Health of the day - across party lines - citizens in this country should expect that the facts that are given to a Minister are the facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#V00200"><p>That they are correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#V00300"><p>The events of that evening were quite appalling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#V00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#V00500"><p>Work has started to ascertain this number now that it transpires that there are cases of cervical cancer known to the national cancer registry that were not known to CervicalCheck.  I have directed that immediate steps be taken so that information from the registry can be provided to the CervicalCheck programme on any additional cases of cervical cancer that occurred during this time.  The screening history of the additional cases will be established, and if any of the women were screened through the CervicalCheck programme, their cases will be reviewed in further detail, with cytology review where necessary.  It is important to say that not all of the cases will have a screening history, so we should be careful in putting numbers out there.  I hear people speaking about definitive numbers.  We need to see how many of the cases had a screening history because not every woman who had cervical cancer may have a screening history.</p> <p>A helpline has been in operation since Friday and appropriate clinical staff will follow up with women on their specific clinical questions.  The helpline has received in excess of 8,000 calls which gives Members an idea of the extent of concern that exists around the country.  I have been advised that waiting times for calls to be answered have reduced significantly following my decision to bring in 40 additional public health staff to deal with the volume of calls being received.  From here on, the serious incident management team and the screening service will give a daily update on progress on all matters directly to the director general, who will provide a daily update to me.  The HSE will also publish a public update each day.  I think that is really important.  A lot of people are worried and I understand why they are worried and why they have been frightened.  We need to show progress each day so that people can see, by means of a published daily update, what is the current position in order that we might try to reassure as many people as possible.</p> <p>There is a new management team in CervicalCheck.  The doctor in charge of the CervicalCheck programme has resigned from her post.  The manager who was in charge of running Cervical Check on a day-to-day basis is no longer in charge.  Mr. Damien McCallion, a national director of the HSE with responsibility for emergency management, is now the official in charge of CervicalCheck, reporting directly to the director general, reporting directly to me.  It is important that we remind everybody of the importance of the screening programme.  I have heard some people say that they do not need reminding.  We need to be very careful at a time like this that while we must get to the bottom of this and establish the answers we approach it in a non-complacent and non-arrogant manner.  We do not take the view that a screening programme could never be better.  There are weaknesses in so many areas, but we need to remember that CervicalCheck has also saved lives, that the rate of cervical cancer in this country has dropped by 7%, on average, each year.  More than 3 million smear tests have been carried out by CervicalCheck.  It is not a diagnostic test.  It is a screening test that indicates the possibility of pre-cancerous or cancerous lesions and thereby identifies women who need to be referred for further investigation or follow-up.</p> <p>Naturally, many women are now concerned about their own health following the publicity surrounding CervicalCheck.  To provide assurance, CervicalCheck will make the necessary arrangements to enable any woman who has had a CervicalCheck smear test, to have a consultation with her GP, in order to help her determine whether she wishes to have a further test without charge.  These arrangements are being confirmed with doctors currently.  I thank the Irish Medical Organisation and the National Association of General Practitioners for their engagement and support in relation to this situation.</p> <p>In addition, I wish to inform the House that in February this year, I approved the introduction of primary HPV screening for cervical smear samples and I can confirm that primary HPV screening will be introduced later this year.  A Health and Information Quality Authority, HIQA, health technology assessment has found that HPV screening would benefit women by making the screening process more clinically effective as well as reducing unnecessary tests for most women.</p> <p>I want to address some of the questions which have arisen with regard to the director general of the HSE and, in particular, news reports in recent days of his role on the board of a US company.  I want to inform the Seanad that I spoke with Mr. O'Brien this morning and he has advised me that he has taken a leave of absence from his non-executive directorship until July at which point I will appoint a new interim director general until the recruitment process is complete.  I recognise that he has resolved to devote the short time he has left to serve as director general in working to deal with the CervicalCheck issue, and I appreciate that he began his HSE career in the screening services and wishes to end it by working to restore confidence in them.  He has an awful lot of work to do in that regard.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Ms Vicky Phelan said very clearly, publicly and in her conversations with me, that she wants to see action taken in order that some good can arise from the most horrific situation that she, her family and other women are facing.  I assured her that this will be the case.  I know that is a desire shared by Senators throughout this House and Deputies in the other House.  It is my intention to take all necessary steps to ensure the integrity of the cervical screening programme, while at the same time ensuring that any lessons we need to learn are extended to all cancer screening programmes.  These programmes are an important component of the progress that we have made over the past ten years in cancer survivorship for our citizens.</p><p>However, we also have to ask ourselves a broader question about the culture of disclosure and candour in our health service.  The fact that we know that healthcare professionals in many institutions around this country had information that pertained to a woman's health record and chose not to share that with her should be a cause of concern for all of us involved in the health service, and for all of us who use and depend on it.  We cannot have a paternalistic culture in the health service.  Regardless of whether it would affect their medical outcomes, which is an issue for somebody more qualified than me, this information belonged to those women.  This information was not shared with those women.  We have to learn from that.  Next week, I will bring to Cabinet a proposal to draft a patient safety Bill, which will deal with mandatory open disclosure for serious reportable incidents.  I will ensure that the definition of serious reportable incidents includes our screening programmes.</p><p>I am fully committed to the further development of our cancer services and to delivering on our new national cancer strategy.  Accepting that nobody has a monopoly of wisdom or ideas, I wish to extend the hand of bipartisanship to all in this House and the other House, to work together in the national interest to get this issue right for the women of this country and for the benefit of all who live here. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#W00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming before the House today.  This is a really serious issue.  Ms Vicky Phelan's case really is a tragedy that could have been avoided.  She is a hero to all Irish women.  She has been an example of what a woman can do.  She was relentless, she was tireless, she was exhausted.  She was a solitary soul fighting against the State.  That is what she was.  The Minister should hang his head in shame that the State and the Department he represents put this woman through legal hell as she went through medical hell.  Fianna F&aacute;il welcomes the recent move to set up an independent investigation into the CervicalCheck scandal.  However, Vicky Phelan was the woman affected by this and she must be part of the terms of reference.  I am glad the Minister mentioned that she will be, and that he has met her.  That is good.</p> <p>The inquiry must be fast and the Minister has indicated that June is his timescale.  I ask him to ensure that he delivers on this.  Such an inquiry must not be used to withhold information from the public.  We need full disclosure from CervicalCheck, the HSE and the Minister.  Following an audit of the 208 cases, the news that more than 17 women have died is truly shocking.  It is beyond belief that today we may still not know the full extent of this.  A serious incident management team is continuing to gather information from about 13 hospitals on the scale of this controversy.  It is unreal.  It is staggering that one woman, her family and her legal team have to go to court to access her own medical truth.  The way that this State continues to treat its women is nothing short of shameful and deplorable.</p> <p>When will someone stand up?  At the first sign of an error or an admittance that something is wrong, the buck is passed.  Why do we leave it up to one brave soul to fight all the battles?  The practice of keeping secrets, whatever the reason - be it fear of litigation or fear of upset - has to stop.  Things are best out in the open.  We can no longer have people hauled through courts just to get what is their own truth, their own information in the first place.  I want the Government, the Department of Health and therefore the Minister to tell us what steps are being taken to hold the HSE accountable.  I acknowledge the Minister has outlined the different steps he is to take, and I welcome this.  However, it is with the Minister that the buck stops at the end of the day.  We cannot allow the HSE to run this Department, and that is what is happening.  The HSE is a law unto itself but the Minister is allowing it.  That cannot happen. </p> <p>Vicky Phelan has recently started on a new drug and is hopeful of being accepted into a US programme offering radical, innovative treatment.  It is disgraceful how this State has let her down, robbed her of her time, her life and peace of mind.  She was made to go through the courts, not knowing what the outcome would be.  The fact that more than three quarters of the 208 women whose cases are being examined by this audit were not told that they had a delayed diagnosis is scandalous.  These women and their families have been failed by the CervicalCheck programme.  All the surviving women must be informed of the situation and given all the supports they need.  There must be full disclosure as to what mistakes were made.  There can never be secrecy again, and I am asking the Minister to ensure that this never happens again.  </p> <p>We also want the Minister to ensure that no other family is forced to go through the courts to find out what errors were made in their care.  We in Fianna F&aacute;il welcome an examination of other national screening programmes, because there are real fears among the population using them.  People are living with the fear of not knowing.  People need to be checked.  If we cannot trust the system and the system is failing then somebody is accountable and that is the Minister.  However, there should not be interference in the work of the inquiry into this CervicalCheck programme, which must be carried out immediately.  I am asking the Minister to make sure that he comes back to us with the answers in June.  </p> <p>There are a lot of questions that the Minister still needs to answer.  Every woman and family in the country has been affected by this.  One can feel people's fear when talking to them.  People are calling my office.  It makes one ashamed.  One wonders how professionals could let this happen.  It is unheard of.  We cannot allow this. </p> <p>Mandatory reporting is needed to achieve this.  Fianna F&aacute;il believes that mandatory disclosure must be provided for under law for all patient care.  We need a system of checks and balances.  When something is flagged, it should never take ten years, a lengthy court case, 17 deaths and a resignation for the truth to be revealed.  Listening to the reports about the court case and reading the information the Minister has put before the House, it is hard to believe that such a serious case was being fought in the High Court by the State, and yet no-one seemed to know.  I believe the Minister was not informed until 16 April.  Someone must be accountable here.  Ms Phelan has been fighting a case for a long time, and yet the Minister says that he did not know until 16 April.  I am not happy with that, and I think something here does not add up.  </p> <p>I am asking the Minister to never allow anything like that to happen to an Irish woman ever again.  We must never put anyone through that.  The cases of the 17 women who have died are absolutely tragic.  I am looking for a full commitment from the Minister that he will hold the HSE accountable.  Deputy Harris is the Minister and he is over the HSE.</p> <p>The issue of Versatis patches arose recently.  The HSE restricted them, even though people are in severe pain.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#W00300"><p>The Senator is running into injury time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#W00400"><p>I have cancer patients fighting for medical cards because they cannot get them.  I hear from people with long-term illnesses.  The HSE needs to have an overhaul.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#W00500"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for coming to the House today, in what has been a hectic week for him, to set out comprehensively in his statement to the House how he has identified the issues and, more importantly, how he proposes to proceed from here.  This is a time for cool heads.  It is a time to stand in solidarity with the people who are suffering, anxious and concerned about their health going forward.  That has to be the key message of our deliberations here today.  Across the Houses and among politicians from all groups, there is a genuine sense of keenness to get on and to set out the stall, because people want to know the facts.  I am particularly encouraged by the Taoiseach's announcement last night that he would seriously look at redress.  A slap on the wrist is no good any more, for anybody.  There must always be redress when people have done wrong.  Ultimately this is about life.  People are fighting for their very survival.  People value their lives.  People want to live and be supported by their loved ones and families, and that is critically important.</p> <p>We all know that the cervical cancer check scandal constitutes a major breach of trust between patients, their doctors and the HSE.  That has been said time and time again.  We have to learn from that and address it.  There are women in the dark today.  What a horrible place to be; in the dark about their health this very day.  There are people and families anxiously waiting to know what the outcome was.  What was the real outcome of a test that they thought was a positive thing to do in pursuit of early intervention against cervical cancer, something that is very important?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I understand that the Minister is angry - the nation is angry - and he made that anger and his frustration clear in the House.  Ultimately, however, we must hold people to account.  I met a woman on Grafton Street yesterday who asked me if politicians are supposed to be at the centre of the universe in the political establishment, what is this monster that is the HSE and who are all these people?  On another occasion, we will have to have a another debate on how we, as the political establishment, have let go of so many powers which have been devolved to the HSE.  Many people are responsible for that.  We would need a lot of time to go through it but it is a timely reminder that we need to look at how we can dismantle this monster that is the HSE.</p><p>We need due process.  People are entitled to that and to set out their stalls in order to explain the rationale, or lack thereof, behind their decisions.  We must give people the space and time to do that.  People have the right to be angry but we must have accountability, responsibility and consequences.  The independent investigation with full powers has to be welcomed but it must have the power to demand documents, direct attendance of witnesses, and to demand and receive sworn evidence in a timely manner.  Everything in this process must be done in a timely manner.</p><p>It is the task of the Government and the Minister to establish all the facts relating to this case, to restore confidence in cancer screening and to ensure controversies such as this never happen again.</p><p>I want to ask the Minister one question.  Why did he give written consent to the director general of the HSE , Tony O'Brien, to take up a lucrative role in a San Diego-based company, Evofem Biosciences, at a time when the executive is in crisis?  The Minister and the Taoiseach continually field crises relating to the HSE.  Hindsight is a great thing but it was a terrible call to give written consent for this man, who we charged to lead this organisation as its director general.  We cannot undo the past, and I am not asking the Minister to do that.  However, I ask that neither he nor any of his successors should give consent for the director general of such an important organisation - whether it is the HSE or whatever its successor might be - to take his eye off the ball.  The director general should do the job that he is paid damn well to do and that he has 100% failed to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#X00200"><p>I join the Minister in paying tribute to Limerick woman Vicky Phelan and her family.  She is very courageous for being prepared to fight for her rights and ensure that this serious matter became public.  The women of Ireland owe her a deep debt of gratitude for exposing this dreadful situation.  My thoughts are with her and her family, as they are with all women affected by this and the families of the 17 women who, unfortunately, have died.</p> <p>I agree that we need to fully investigate and determine exactly what happened, how it happened and where the systems failed.  It is important to establish where failures occurred and if individuals did not accept or carry our their responsibilities.  There can be no excuse for the concealment of facts by those placed in positions of trust.  People are very angry and upset, which is clear from the 8,000 phone calls to the helpline.  It is most important that we learn lessons from this episode, which has seriously damaged the reputation of the screening programme and the health service overall.</p> <p>I fully acknowledge that the Minister responded quickly and positively having become aware of Vicky Phelan's plight and the continuing revelations to the effect that many others have been made aware of mistakes in their diagnoses.  The serious incident management team, which the Minister established so promptly, must be fully resourced and empowered to undertake this investigation and complete it as soon as possible in order to restore confidence in this very valuable service.  Has the Minster been given an indication of the period necessary to undertake this work?  I want his assurance that whatever resources the team requires will be continue to be made available until the work is completed.</p> <p>The proposal to proceed with a scoping inquiry to report within two months is excellent.  Hopefully, that inquiry will answer most of the outstanding questions and point to the way forward.  We need to establish where responsibility lay and, above all, how we can ensure that this programme and all other cancer screening programmes have clear governance procedures, to define the actions to be taken and the persons responsible for their implementation.  There must be no doubt about what actions need to be taken and who must take them at all levels of the programme.  There must be a clear and definitive procedure to ensure that test results are conveyed to patients.</p> <p>Every effort must be made to eliminate error, although I accept that mistakes can happen.  Where a mistake is discovered there can be no delay in putting up the hand and admitting it.  The onus must be placed on the appropriate personnel to ensure that this happens immediately and that the patient is informed without delay.  A person's GP is the ideal individual to do so but that is a matter for the Minister and his officials to decide.  Any delay can make a difference between life and death.</p> <p>I join Vicky Phelan in encouraging women to continue going for cervical smears.  I advise everyone to partake in the other cancer screening programmes such as BreastCheck, colon cancer screening and prostate testing that are available and which have saved lives.  It is true there have been weakness and failures which we need to identify and redress but many lives have been saved.</p> <p>It is essential that we all remember that the patient is at the centre of all healthcare provision.  The rights of the patient must always be respected and protected.  They must be treated with understanding, respect and kindness.  Adverse results must be communicated immediately with compassion and the offer of ongoing support.</p> <p>Quality of care is paramount in any aspect of healthcare.  Using preventative medial care represents best use of financial resources, keeping people out of intensive care facilities.  News that the Government is planning on moving to the more accurate HPV tests for cervical cancer is very welcome, and I welcome the Minister's announcement that it will happen this year.  Perhaps the Minister can give us more detail on this.</p> <p>It should be mandatory for the HSE to give proper weighting to quality of service and other non-financial elements when assessing tenders for outsourced testing.  It is very important that we adopt a more balanced approach to assessing tenders.  It is essential that cervical screening and all other health screening services are built on the principles of trust, transparency and governance.  These are basic requirements which must be met and constantly monitored for the duration of the contract.  I also support an ongoing internal-external quality audit of these contracts to ensure that the accepted terms of engagement are being adhered to.  There can be no room for any slippage from the standards agreed to in the contract.  We must aim to obtain a service which meets international best practice guidelines and standards.  While we must acknowledge the Trojan work done by many healthcare professionals, it is essential that our healthcare systems have proper procedures for reporting abnormal practice behaviours and suspicious poor practice that jeopardises patient safety.  There can be no room for poor practice, carelessness or any form or casual approach to patient safety.  I particularly welcome the Minister's commitment to introduce a patient safety Bill that will provide mandatory disclosure of events such as we are considering today and ensure that patients are made aware of events which have the potential to adversely affect their health.  I hope this legislation can be prioritised and progressed without delay.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House.  I know that many of my colleagues wished to raise the matter and make suggestions.  We all share the same aim, that this will not reoccur.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#X00300"><p>I thank the Minster for coming to the House.  I appreciate that he has had a busy few days.</p> <p>I want to go back to 2008.  As a woman, I cannot understand how the then Minister with responsibility for health, former Deputy Mary Harney, along with the Fianna F&aacute;il members of the Cabinet, made the decision to outsource such an important service to America.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It just does not add up.  Something stinks here.  Something is wrong when there is advice from experts like Dr. David Gibbons and others and when someone like him feels strongly enough to resign over this matter.  There also were the Well Woman clinics and that was on top of statements from politicians like Deputy &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in, Senator Reilly and many others stating this was the wrong thing to do and this is what would happen in ten years' time.  They still went ahead and decided in their wisdom that this was the right thing to do.  It does not add up.  That requires forensic and intensive investigation and I intend to play a part in that.</p><p>Even from a data protection point of view, it does not sit well with me that all these women's details were being held in America.  In terms of making the decision to bring back that service to the country, how would the Minister envisage that happening, how long might it take and what would it cost?  I do not believe we lacked the capacity in this country to do it.  We had gone through a boom in which money was coming out of the ears of those in the golden circles.  How were the facilities here not given proper investment?  I am apologise to Senator Murnane O'Connor but Fianna F&aacute;il's protestations on this hold no credibility for me.  As for the open disclosure book, what concerns me is whether the Minister now thinks it was a mistake for the Government, supported by Fianna F&aacute;il, to put in the amendment for a voluntary rather than mandatory disclosure in the duty of candour Bill that went through the Oireachtas last year.  Was that a mistake?  It is important that we admit the mistakes that were made and face up to them as otherwise, we cannot hope to find solutions to them.</p><p>The current scandal is unfolding day by day and more is learned from the media than is being given to concerned women by the HSE.  I found the health committee yesterday very frustrating. I found some of the language being used by Mr. Tony O'Brien in particular, deeply condescending and insulting to women and to the families of the women who are deceased.  It does not fit.  Yesterday in the D&aacute;il the Taoiseach described this cover-up as a cock-up.  I was also deeply disturbed to hear him use such glib and dismissive language about such a serious issue as life and death.  This morning, Ms Vicky Phelan has called on Mr. Tony O'Brien to resign.  If we say we are listening to her, we need to hear what she is saying.  Accountability cannot exist where responsibility is not accepted by individuals.  The Minister cannot have it both ways either.  Either he has full confidence in Mr. Tony O'Brien or he has to go.  The fact is that Mr. Tony O'Brien has presided over negligence, concealment and misinformation with the most serious consequences for women and their families.  He cannot remain as director general.  That is the very least the women affected and their families need to see.</p><p>The Minister says he wants a full investigation to discover all the facts and to restore confidence in the screening programme but we do not need an inquiry to determine that women with cervical cancer were not given critical information on their healthcare.  We know that at least 17 women went to their graves not knowing.  We still do not know how many more women did not know and we do not know how many more women do not know right now.  I appreciate that the Minister is putting things in place with the GPs.  I was deeply concerned on Monday morning, because I have experience of it myself, that the GPs said they had not been given anything and they did not know what to do or put in place.  I am also concerned - as I was told - that people can go to a consultant and pay &euro;150.  That is all right, as I am in a position to do that but many women are not.  If one's GP does not do smear tests and there are referrals to consultants, will the consultant's fee be paid as well or to where do those women go?</p><p>I have much more I want to say but will the Minister order an audit for BreastCheck and the other medical checks because confidence needs to be restored in all of those services?  I absolutely believe in screening.  Will the Minister confirm to me -  it was very confusing in the committee yesterday - that there was a 30% failure rate on the cervical screening?  Perhaps the Minister could explain that.  Moreover, why can the redress scheme not be set up before an inquiry is concluded?  Are the Minister and his Department involved in the decisions to fight medical negligence cases?  Is an opinion sought from either the Minister or the HSE in that regard?  I have much more to ask.  I appreciate the Minister coming in and I am sure there will be more opportunities for Members to ask questions.  I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#Y00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming in.  It has been the middle of a busy time but the Minister is right to have been busy and it is proper that he is busy.  This is a very serious issue and one in which the Minister has become completely involved in the most proper way.</p> <p>We would not be having this debate today if it was not for the courage of Ms Vicky Phelan.  Many have said that but also I mention her persistence and fearlessness in refusing a gagging order.  I want to remark on her generosity too, given the amount of time she has given to this issue and the public, which is precious time for her.  I thank her for that.  Equally, I repeat what she has said on her plea to women to continue to get their smears.  I cannot say that often enough.  Many issues have been raised here.  The most important issue is that lives are being saved by cervical screening.  We may have issues with the upper echelons of management and we certainly have major issues with a decision not to share information with patients which is what CervicalCheck is supposed to be all about, namely, saving the lives of women.  Moreover, it is working and as the Minister has pointed out, the incidence of cervical cancer has fallen since 2011.  That is to be welcomed.  I also mention the importance of the HPV vaccine-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#Y00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#Y00400"><p>-----and the manner in which it can protect women and girls from this illness, which robs so many families of their loved ones.  I welcome that we will have an immediate Health Information and Quality Authority, HIQA, inquiry, that we are looking at a statutory inquiry and that a redress scheme is to be put in place.</p> <p>There are broader issues that I want to speak to.  I am glad the Minister did mentions GPs.  He talks about the pressure on the call centre but I can assure him the pressure on GP surgeries at the moment is quite intense and I am grateful that we got the letter today from the HSE to bring people up to date and to remind people that if they are worried to come and talk to their doctor.  I emphasise again the most important thing, which is that even if a women has had a clear smear, if she has worrying symptoms she must go and talk to her doctor.  It is not a guarantee that all is well in the presence of other problems.  I want to raise a number of issues with the Minister, the broader issues around this; the State Claims Agency, its approach to legal actions and its decision on when to proceed as opposed to when it should settle.  I know the Minister is not directly involved in those cases but that must be reviewed.  I also mention the Minister's patient safety Bill.  I believe we need an independent patient safety authority that can advocate for patients and which reports directly to the Minister.  It is something in which I strongly believe.  I mean no disrespect to the Department of Health but it has to be seen to be totally independent.  I agree with the Minister's plan to bring in open disclosure.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator James Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2180"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2180&amp;amp;pid=DrJamesReilly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I want to thank another woman today, Ms Aisling O'Regan from Swords, who said that she was very lucky, that the service helped her a lot and that it has helped many women.  She said that if she had not taken that test she would be telling a different story today.  That is really important.  It underscores what Ms Vicky Phelan said, that women should continue to go for their smears.  There will be a new and improved test, and I welcome that, but the current test picks up 70% of cancers.  </p><p>Senator Rose Conway-Walsh commented on the 30% failure rate.  The test is known to be 70% effective, ergo 30% will not be picked up.  That is normal.  Sometimes, when looking back at slides five doctors will say that there is a problem and a cytologist will say there is not.  It is those which fall outside that scenario, where all agree that there is a problem that should have been picked up, which are seriously worrying.  I believe that the Senator's suggestion, that we should have a look-back audit on BreastCheck and other screening tests where positives transpire subsequently so that we can learn from it, is a good one.   We must ensure that we learn from this and that all information is shared with patients. </p><p>I appeal to women not to lose faith in cervical screening.  The Government has committed to getting to the bottom of this so that we can prevent similar appalling situations from happening again.  I look forward to rapid results on the basis of the actions the Minister has taken.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#Z00200"><p>I am sure that the Minister will agree that in the political sphere we operate in it is time to move beyond business as usual when it comes to political barbs, finger pointing and point scoring.  The issue at hand is far too serious.  The Labour Party absolutely stands with the Minister and accepts his bona fides.  In his efforts to deal with this matter his interaction with our party and with other parties has been to his credit.  Nobody could suggest that he does not treat this with the absolutely seriousness it deserves, as he is doing his absolute best to ensure that this does not happen agains.</p> <p>The Labour Party has been quite strong on the need for a commission of investigation, and I believe the Minister has moved his own position towards that.  That is to be welcomed.  We feel strongly that no woman affected by this issue should in any way be liable for any medical costs whatsoever, and that no woman involved in this situation should have to put her hand in her pocket, nor should her family have to put their hands into their pockets.  </p> <p>On the overall structure of the HSE, it was suggested last night in the media that part of the problem with the HSE currently is that, in the effort by the last Government - which I was a part of - to abolish the HSE, the board was dispensed with.  As a result of the board not being in place, one of the obvious corporate governance checks and balances that would be expected in an institution such as the HSE is no longer there.  Subsequently, when the CEO of the HSE is going about his or her daily business, the lack of a board being there as a check and balance in that institution is a glaring omission.  I am asking that the Minister discusses that with us this evening.  When the HSE was established it was said that politics provides  the policy and the HSE deals with the delivery.  In the delivery there must be political accountability.  </p> <p>I would appreciate if the Minister would address those points.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#Z00300"><p>I believe the concerns of the Minister are genuine.  I welcome the interaction he has had with all political parties; he is trying to resolve the issue and put solutions in place.  I have not had an opportunity to see the letter circulated to GPs; it would be helpful if that could be circulated to everyone.</p> <p>We have to discuss good governance.  I do not believe the HSE has good governance.  It has been raised many times in this House in terms of the lack of boards for hospital groups.  This has to serve as a wake-up call and be used to ensure there is good governance right across our systems.  </p> <p>A woman stopped me yesterday on Dawson Street to talk about the State Claims Agency.  She made me aware of other areas the State Claims Agency is working in, and specifically discussed seven individuals.  I am not going to mention them because I have no intention of ambushing the Minister; I will talk to him at a later stage about that issue.  This matter is too important; we should not seek political gain from it but rather take it seriously and work to resolve it.  I am asking the Minister for an audit of the cases the State Claims Agency is currently involved in.  We do not want women such as Vicky Phelan being dragged through courts unnecessarily when a more humane approach is available.  That audit of current cases should be done immediately.  Once that is done I would like to see an audit of previous cases where the State Claims Agency has sought gagging orders on the result of the case.  There may be other cases that we can learn from in which gagging orders were imposed and which have not emerged in the public discourse.  If we are going to fix the problems with the HSE we have to know what all those problems are and how citizens are being dealt with by the State Claims Agency.  I do not believe that anyone here would stand over the horror story I heard yesterday.  If those two pieces of work could be carried out relatively quickly it would be a good service to the citizens of Ireland.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#Z00400"><p>I welcome the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, to the House and commend him on the work he has done.  Vicky Phelan is a neighbour of mine and I know her very well.  She is an incredible woman, and it is true to say that if she had not refused a gagging clause this story would probably never have come out.  I believe the women of Ireland owe her an enormous debt of gratitude.  One meets people in life occasionally that leave an imprint.  For me, Vicky Phelan is one of those people.  She is formidable and warm.  She is unwell, but she has presented herself to the public.  She is compelling viewing because what she is saying is the truth.  I have been involved in many inquiries and would be worried that we might get bogged down in process.  This problem was caused by people not communicating with each other.  The women of Ireland want the truth.  Vicky Phelan is entitled to the truth.  We need to know why this information, which was available, was not communicated to the women of Ireland affected by this disease.  Vicky Phelan would be in a different position today if that was done.  It is disgraceful and shameful.  No matter what way I think about it, all I can see is a young lady, at 43 years of age, being forced to go out onto the public airwaves and fight her case.  What the State Claims Agency did to her is a disgrace in terms of human decency.</p> <p>I heard Mr. Tony O'Brien, the CEO of the HSE, come out and say that this is a personal blow to him.  It pales into insignificance compared to the personal blow dealt to the women affected by this scandal.  He may have suffered a personal blow, but he should take some personal responsibility.  He should look into his heart on this particular issue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kieran O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2207"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2207&amp;amp;pid=KieranODonnell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->He speaks about lack of personal responsibility.  I spoke about it earlier.  A manager of a football team that is not preforming cannot claim not to have personal responsibility.  He needs to do the decent thing.  Vicky Phelan has called for it.  People, who know me, know that I am pretty much down the middle.  I feel very passionately and strongly about this one.  This is one of the greatest scandals in the history of our State.  It affects our mothers, wives and partners, sisters and daughters.</p><p>It is clear that the HSE is not fit for purpose.  Its officials have been appearing before the Committee of Public Accounts for years.  It is unwieldy, too big and not flexible.  It does not meet the requirements for a modern population's health needs.  It needs to be reformed as a matter of urgency.  What form that takes needs to be looked at.  It is not carrying out its job.  This issue happened under the watch of the HSE.  The Minister went into the D&aacute;il having just been handed a piece of paper detailing something of which he was unaware.  While the Minister was in the Chamber the HSE issued a press statement at the same time.  We cannot have that type of behaviour; this is too serious.</p><p>Women have contacted me.  I welcome that the Minister is allowing for the fact that women can go for a smear test.  Women have contacted me with concerns over previous smear tests.  I am meeting members of the medical profession and they are saying, "Was my previous smear test false?"  Does that need to be looked at as part of this review?  I understand that women in that cohort are getting phone calls, going to their GPs and their GPs are unaware of the reason for the phone call.  The GPs need to be included in this measure.</p><p>I salute Vicky Phelan.  The Minister will know of my relationship and contact with her.  What she has done will go down in the history of Ireland as something heroic and for the betterment of women.  Clearly it must have been difficult for her to have come out, but she feels passionately about it.  I wish her well in her treatment.  She is in the process of undergoing new treatment.  I wish her well in that; I want her to get well.</p><p>I return to the key points.  The truth is the key feature here.  I do not want to see politicians fighting over process.  They are not being affected; women such as Vicky Phelan are being affected.  They are entitled to know quickly why this happened and why they were not made aware of it.  We need to make certain about the process.  Women are entitled to smear tests.  Is there a need to look at the results of previous smear tests?  I apologise to Mr. O'Brien, but he needs to look into his heart on this one.  What happened under his watch is of such a monumental nature that it has affected people's lives.  People have died because the results of smear tests were not picked up properly.  This is what it is about.</p><p>I salute Vicky Phelan and wish her well in her current treatment.  She deserves no less.  The women of Ireland owe her an enormous debt of gratitude as we all do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#AA00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House.  I thank him for having the courage to face this issue.  People sometimes accuse me of being nice to Ministers, but it cannot have been easy to go out day after day and take on the responsibility for what has happened.  More importantly, during his speech today he told us of being handed last-minute information minutes before going into the D&aacute;il, which is totally unacceptable.</p><p>This morning I spoke about our propensity to look for the heads of Ministers when things go wrong, which is politicising what is a corporate failure within the public service.  We take out the Minister and we leave the problem behind.  I am delighted that Mr. Tony O'Brien wants to stay until July; I think he should go now.  He should ring the Minister this evening and say he is leaving because he has not done the country a service and we do not want him.  In particular Vicky Phelan does not want him to be here anymore.  He should do us all a favour and go.</p><p>Before talking further about corporate governance, I wish to deal with an issue that has arisen.  Women have rung the helpline 1800-454555 and sought information.  A few women contacted me yesterday on this issue.  One of the questions asked was about the repeat screening.  The women were told that although the Minister had made an announcement, the helpline knew nothing about it.  I ask the Minister to look into that because it is something within his power.</p><p>I return to corporate governance and will talk about certain things from the past.  The anti-D issue affected 100,000 people in the country.  Officials who knew about it kept their mouths shut and allowed the situation to develop.  The country spent &euro;1 billion settling hepatitis C cases and 80 women died after contracting hepatitis C.  Throughout his career a particular Member of the Lower House has taken an unmerciful amount of stick over the Brigid McCole case.  Some official somewhere started that case before it ever came to the attention of a Minister.</p><p>I spoke this morning about the Carltona principles or doctrine, which effectively means that when a departmental official speaks he or she speaks with the Minister's authority, irrespective of whether the Minister knows or not.  This is one of the great things behind which the faceless bureaucrats can hide.  They make a decision and when that decision is made it is the Minister's decision - not theirs - and they will never be called upon to answer for that decision save getting fired quietly with a large pension and out the backdoor.  That is grossly unfair.</p><p>The Minister sits around the Cabinet table; I do not.  I ask him to do two things.  I ask him to bring about a discussion within the political framework on the impact Carltona is having and has had since the 1940s on decision-making in Government and in politics in particular.  Where a senior official takes a decision to commence a particular process, that official should be answerable for it.</p><p>Senator Humphreys spoke about the State Claims Agency.  Has it learned nothing?  It took Mrs. McCole to the point of a Supreme Court threat before settling with her the day before she died.  What sort of people do we have in the State Claims Agency?  Is there not a process that looks at a claim when it is submitted to see if there is a <i>prima facie</i>case to be answered and if there is, move it to a different track?  Why do we become so aggressive to every poor individual bringing a case forward?</p><p>Ms Phelan, who is the centre of attention in the country now, did not want the publicity this has been brought to her house.  She does not need it in her current state of health.  She forewent the chance of getting more money, I am sure, in order to ensure that women in Ireland knew what was happening.</p><p>Journalists and anybody else who claim the Minister for Health can be on top of every single issue and decision every day of the week, are codding themselves.  However, there is one thing he should be told about.  When a case comes up that is likely to finish up in the courts, he should know about it the moment the Department is informed, not a year later, two years later or when some official decides, &quot;Oh my God, I could get my head on the chopping block for this.&quot;<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are officials who knew things and, my God, the Minister had to be told when walking in the door of the D&aacute;il that there was more coming.  There are officials who knew these things.  Political cover is being given to them and it is the Minister's neck on the block.  People are looking for his head and that is not right.  It is right for those who take decisions to be answerable for them.  Like Senator Reilly, I ask for a look back over all the screening which has taken place.  I get screened for cancer myself and I would like to know that the screening that has taken place is reliable.  I do not expect it to be 100% accurate every time.  I expect to be told that there is a certain rate of failure.  That is fine.  I can live with that if people are being honest with me.  I will stand foursquare behind the Minister for as long as I see him doing what he is doing.</p><p>I have one last point to make.  When the Minister brings political groupings together, I ask him to remember that there are a number of Independent Members in the House and that we would also like to know what is going on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#BB00200"><p>Sure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#BB00300"><p>I know the Minister, Deputy Harris, has just left the House but I concur with other speakers on the job of work he is doing.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne.  Of course the people of Ireland expect nothing less than the job of work the Minister is doing.  This is a scandal and it is happening on our watch.  We have a responsibility to ensure that it is dealt with.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell just mentioned the most important fact of all, namely, that all of the facts must be put out there in order to inform those who need to be informed.  People should be informed as a matter of absolute urgency.</p> <p>I know the Minister has updated us in respect of the number of people who have now been informed but we absolutely need the scoping exercise which is going to take place and the commission of investigation to establish the who, where, how, what and so on.  More fundamentally, we need a change of culture not just within the HSE - although there absolutely must be such a change in the HSE - but across the public service.  Something similar to what has happened in the HSE recently happened in the Department of Justice and Equality.  There has to be a sea change in how information is filtered up from various Departments to Government and to the Minister's desk.</p> <p>What has happened here has been appalling.  We are talking about people's health and people not being informed of a particular situation.  It is absolutely appalling and absolutely not acceptable.  We need to put structures in place under which there will be clear communication and under which a Minister will not be handed a briefing document with additional information 20 minutes before going into the D&aacute;il.  We should not be in that situation.  Whoever the Minister of the day is, regardless of his or her party, he or she should not have to be in a situation in which he or she is given this type of information.  It needs to change.</p> <p>How should it change?  It is up to the experts in change management to come in and put the structures in place.  It is fairly clear to me that information has to be channelled up to the Minister in an appropriate way, in good time and in a speedy fashion.  I hope situations like this will not happen again, but other situations clearly will.  There are going to be more court cases.  Of that there is no doubt.  A level of priority has to be given so that, when there is a court case which is settled, the various elements of information surrounding it are properly communicated in order that other people who may be affected are informed.  The whole scenario in which there is no clear information or no information in good time is absolutely appalling.  If we have learned anything from this, I hope we will put proper structures in place to ensure this type of thing does not happen again.  </p> <p>Like other people, I pay special tribute to Vicky Phelan because sometimes courageous people are a catalyst for change.  I truly believe that Vicky Phelan will be a catalyst for change.  The Minister has given an absolute commitment and I know that commitment will be followed up because Vicky Phelan and the other Vicky Phelans who have been affected by this deserve absolutely nothing less.  We all have a role to play in supporting the people who are trying to do the right thing.  This debate in the Seanad has been useful because we want to assist in articulating a voice for the people who have been affected and we want to ensure that the change does happen because that is what people want.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#BB00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#BB00500"><p>I also welcome the Minister, Deputy Simon Harris, who has had to leave, and the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, to the House to discuss an issue which has involved many women right across the country.  The real concern is that it may involve many more who we do not know of yet.</p> <p>This is a very difficult time for many women and their families.  Many Senators and Deputies have spoken this week of the huge courage and unwavering determination of Vicky Phelan.  I imagine that it is difficult enough for one to deal with a diagnosis of cancer, never mind then finding out that information pertinent to one was withheld and, not alone that, but then having to fight against the State Claims Agency for truth and justice.  The way these women have been treated is absolutely horrific and disgraceful.  We expect better.  We should never have to go through a week such as this in which we have heard of so many cases of women being treated totally disgracefully.</p> <p>I just want to say a few things because we all want to be constructive.  The Minister, Deputy Simon Harris, and the Government, along with Opposition parties and Independent Members, have worked very hard to ensure that solutions are put in place.  It is very important that we establish the facts and I hope the scoping inquiry will lead us to that place.  It is absolutely incredible that facts which were obviously available were not made known to the Minister until minutes before he went into the D&aacute;il.  That is absolutely incredible.  We need to ensure a culture of accountability.  I worked in St. James's Hospital for eight years.  I was accountable for the people whom I assessed, treated and discharged.  Everybody working in the health service needs to be accountable for all of their actions.  We are clearly not seeing this.  We need to make sure that this never happens again.  We have wronged many women.  We need to put it right.  We need to ensure that we never see a situation in which information pertinent to individuals is withheld from them.  </p> <p>I listened to much of the debate at the Joint Committee on Health yesterday.  Since becoming a Senator I have had many concerns about HSE management.  The Minister of State will be aware of this as I have raised it as Commencement matters on several occasions.  HSE management needs to be accountable.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maura Hopkins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2478"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2478&amp;amp;pid=MauraHopkins&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=03"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Until people acting as managers are held to account I do not believe we will see real change, and real change needs to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#CC00200"><p>I apologise for the absence of the Minister, Deputy Harris.  As Members are aware, he has been trying to do a lot of things in recent days and he has asked me to respond to the debate on his behalf.</p> <p>I thank all the Senators who participated in what is probably one of the most important discussions that has happened in a long time in this Chamber and in the D&aacute;il.  As the Minister, Deputy Harris, said today, it is essential that we do not lose focus on the women who are at the  centre of this case.  I add my voice to those who have already paid tribute to Vicky Phelan and the courage she has shown in speaking out about what happened to her and her family.  There are no adequate words to express my outrage, nor undo what has been done.  I sincerely wish Mrs. Phelan well in her continued treatment.</p> <p>As we all know, cervical cancer is a serious issue in Ireland, and we must establish all the facts in this case as quickly as possible, so that women can begin to feel trust and confidence in the cervical screening process again.  The Minister has outlined the steps which the Government will take to ensure that.  The main message I want to convey here this afternoon is that women can and should continue to participate in the CervicalCheck programme.  The international evidence base is clear.  Organised, population-based screening is the most effective way to reduce the incidence of cervical cancer.  We have seen what happened in this country - since 2010 the incidence of cervical cancer has been falling.  Every year in Ireland approximately 270 women are diagnosed with cervical cancer and, sadly, 90 of them die from it.  Cervical cells change slowly and take time to develop into cancer cells, making cervical cancer a preventable disease.  Even with the inherent challenges in screening, having regular smear tests can pick up early cell changes - precancerous growths - and reduce the risk of cervical cancer.  I must emphasise how important it is that women continue to have their smear tests, which can and will continue to save lives.</p> <p>In January of this year I launched the Pearl of Wisdom campaign.  More than 200 women sat in a hall and listened to stories from women who had cancer and women who survived cancer.  In recent days I have been haunted by the faces of many of the people who were there on the day.  I know many of them because they are local women.  I sincerely hope that whatever happens in the coming weeks and months, we can look into people's faces, in particular those of young women, and guarantee them that we will do as much as possible to ensure we never have such an incident happen again in this country.</p> <p>Since the inception of the CervicalCheck programme, more than 1,200 cancers have been detected.  In  addition, 30,000 low grade abnormalities and over 50,000 high grade abnormalities have been diagnosed and treated.  The identification and treatment of such abnormalities prevents them from developing into cervical cancer.  That is incredibly important for all women and also for young women who have yet to begin or complete their families, as treatment for cervical cancer can have a significant impact on fertility.</p> <p>As I have said, the incidence of cervical cancer is failing.  Data published by the national cancer registry shows a significant downward trend in the incidence of invasive cervical cancer between 2010 and 2015, a reduction of approximately 7% annually.  We also know that there has been an increase in the percentage of cancers diagnosed at stage 1, up from 41% between 1994 and 1998, to 47% between 2009 and 2013.  The diagnosis of cancer at the earliest stage possible is an important determinant of survival.  Cancers diagnosed at an earlier stage also result in less invasive treatment and better quality of life post treatment.</p> <p>As Minister of State with responsibility for health promotion, I have responsibility for the implementation of policies under the Healthy Ireland framework.  Cancer prevention sits fully into the Healthy Ireland approach as one of its main goals to protect the public from threats to their health and well-being.  As well as screening for certain cancers, we are taking a population approach to encourage and support people to live healthier lives and to reduce the prevalence of cancer risk factors by making positive changes in terms of diet and physical activity as well as by managing mental well-being.</p> <p>In order to set out our future path towards better health in terms of cancer, last year the National Cancer Strategy 2017-2026 was launched, which will govern the provision of cancer services in Ireland over the next decade.  Cancer prevention is the cornerstone of this cancer strategy as it offers the most cost-effective, long-term approach for cancer control.  The overall vision of the National Cancer Strategy 2017-2026 is to prevent cancer and work to improve the treatment, health and well-being, experiences and outcomes of those living with and beyond cancer.</p> <p>The strategy also has a strong focus on patient involvement.  Patients have direct experience of the health system and this provides them with insight which is not always available to policymakers.  That is an important perspective which has not always been considered in policy decisions and can contribute to the provision of safe, high quality, patient-centred care.  By focusing on what matters to patients we can enhance the quality of the service we provide and the experience of the patient using that service.  As part of the development of the strategy, a cancer patient forum was established.  The cancer patient forum had an extremely valuable impact on the strategy development process and the Minister and all involved acknowledged that its contribution resulted in a better strategy.  In order to build on the work of the cancer patient forum, the Department will shortly establish a cancer patient advisory committee.  Preliminary work has begun on the establishment of the committee and I expect that it will be in place by mid-year.</p> <p>I would like to finish by again offering my most sincere apologies to Vicky Phelan, and to all those women who were not informed of their inclusion in the review process.  I hope that the outcome of the investigation into these issues will provide some clarity for those affected and restore peace of mind for those women using the service.  On a personal level I wish to say that I do not believe it is time for name calling or looking for people's heads.  It is a challenging time in the history of the country.  Women's health must now become a priority.  Never again should women have to wait for three and four years to learn they had a problem with their health.  If we continue to work together, on all sides of the Chamber, and in the D&aacute;il, people will see a real change in the future in women's health.</p> <p>I thank all Senators who contributed, and also the Members of the D&aacute;il who contributed.  It has been a challenging week for us all, especially for the young women in our families.  I have four young daughters and two of them contacted the helpline.  I also have nieces and cousins who have also contacted the helpline.  For that reason I believe that women in every family across the country need assurance and peace of mind about their health.  We are obligated, as women, but also given our privileged position in the D&aacute;il and Seanad, to do our utmost together to bring closure and help to those people who are suffering today because of the mistakes that have been made in recent years.  My sincere apologies to all of them.  I hope to continue to work with the Minister, Deputy Harris, and the rest of the team in the Department of Health to provide some peace to those people who are needlessly suffering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#CC00300"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050300002#CC00400"><p>At 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-03a.239" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 3.10 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 8 May 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>