<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.2" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 12:00:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.4" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.5" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Paul Gavan that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the industrial action taken by the Medical Laboratory Scientists Association. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lisa Chambers on the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the return to full day services at the Sacred Heart Hospital, Castlebar, County Mayo. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Emer Currie on the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State at the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the specified conditions which allow telecommunication mast developments not to be considered exempted developments under planning regulations. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan on the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the current status of draft regulations for planning exemptions on the installation of solar panels on farm buildings and other structures, including timelines for environmental assessments and public consultation. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne on the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the regulation of jet skis. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher on the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on transportation charges for people with disabilities accessing services in community healthcare organisation, CHO, area 1. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne on the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to clarify the legal position under the road traffic legislation regarding insurance in the event of an accident involving a vehicle that is unable to secure a National Car Test, NCT, appointment due to ongoing delays. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators that are suitable for discussion, I have selected those of Senators Gavan, Chambers, Currie and Boyhan and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Kyne on the grounds that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Before we go to our first Commencement matter, I welcome to the Distinguished Visitors Gallery state Senator Ed Reilly, who has served since 2009 in the state Senate in Maryland.  He has described it as a cooling Chamber, like our own Seanad, for legislation coming from their House in Annapolis.  The Senator is most welcome, as is his wife.  We are delighted that they are able to be here and we send our best wishes to everyone in Maryland.  Of the Senator's 16 great-great-grandparents, 12 had Irish heritage, so he certainly goes a long way back.  All politics is local.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.8" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#B00200">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.9" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#B00300">Industrial Disputes</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Justice, Deputy James Browne, back after his address to the United Nations.  He is most welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#B00500"><p>I raise the issue of the strike taking place today by the Medical Laboratory Scientists Association, MLSA.  It is their second week of industrial action.  These workers are essential to the health service.  Unfortunately, last week, as a result of just one day of strike action, 14,000 outpatient appointments were cancelled.  Now these workers have had to embark on a second week of industrial action.</p> <p>To be frank, I am at a complete loss as to how the Government has let this situation arise.  The Minister of State knows full well that this dispute goes back 20 years.  The HSE concedes that the dispute is just and that the expert report of 2001 made it clear there should be pay parity for these workers.  There is a 20% drop-off rate in this area and 20% of positions for these specialist essential workers are unfilled.  They cannot fill the vacancies.</p> <p>A ballot for strike action was carried out last November, with 98% support.  It is unbelievable that, knowing all of this, nothing worthwhile has been done by the Government.  Instead of dealing with this dispute and the real issues involved, that is, justice for pay, career progression and the worrying shortfall in these expert workers because so many of them are leaving the industry or simply will not join it, the Government has done nothing.  The Minister for Health has seen this coming down the tracks for months and instead of doing something about it, we are now into a second week of industrial disputes, with a further three days next week pending.</p> <p>I have met these workers and their representatives and it is very clear that they did not want to go on strike.  They made that absolutely clear to me.  This is the last thing they wanted to do.  They spent two and a half years in fruitless negotiations with this Government.  Unfortunately, it is characteristic of Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael governments that they do not understand industrial relations.  How can it make sense to allow this dispute to continue, rather than resolve it?  Terry Casey, the general secretary of the MLSA said, "Since last week&rsquo;s action neither the HSE nor the Department of Health have come to us with a meaningful proposal, or invitation to talks, that could address the issues involved".<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is an absolutely shocking statement.  The Minister of State can see the chaos that has ensued.  I had a number of calls this morning from people in Limerick asking me why their outpatient appointments have been cancelled.  Let me be clear: they are not criticising the workers on strike - the outpatients get it.  They are criticising the Government for allowing this to happen, for not dealing with the issues, for not listening to the workers and for not having the conversation that, clearly, still has not happened between the Department of Health and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  I want to be very clear about where the blockage is.  The Department of Public Expenditure and Reform is blocking moves to ensure pay parity for these workers.  It is very clear that these disputes will cost us, through the HSE, an absolute fortune.  It makes no financial sense and, in terms of justice for the workers, it makes no sense either.  The Government has been derelict in its duty - those are the only words I can use - in allowing this dispute to drag on for more than 20 years.  The workers have been waiting for pay parity and nothing has happened for them.  There have been two and a half years of completely fruitless talks.  The Minister of State has an opportunity to say something meaningful in his response.  If he does that, the dispute could be called off tomorrow and we could get the workers back to work, which is where they want to be.</p><p>My colleagues were at the picket line in Limerick this morning and they spoke at first hand to the workers there.  They are exasperated with the Government for not listening and not responding.  The Minister of State has an opportunity now to please say something worthwhile and give us a clear indication that meaningful talks that will lead to a resolution of the dispute are available and should happen straight away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#C00200"><p>I acknowledge and pay tribute to the dedication, professionalism, and commitment of all medical scientists throughout the country.  Medical scientists perform a valued and vital role within our health service.  Their drive and determination have been key components in our management of the Covid-19 pandemic.  During the pandemic, they were at the front line of the response providing a crucial role in testing.  This role has not gone unnoticed.</p> <p>The Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, is acutely aware of the ongoing and long-standing claim for pay parity between medical scientists and clinical biochemists.  Health management has been engaging with the Medical Laboratory Scientist Association, MLSA, on these issues at the Workplace Relations Commission, under the terms of the current public service agreement, Building Momentum.  As the MLSA is part of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, it is bound by the terms of the agreement for the remainder of its lifetime.  Building Momentum includes the process of sectoral bargaining to deal with all outstanding claims across the public sector.  The bargaining fund equates to 1% of basic pensionable pay for each bargaining unit set up under the agreement.  Under Building Momentum, sectoral bargaining is the sole mechanism through which the MLSA can advance its claim.  The MLSA requested and was facilitated with its own bargaining unit in the sectoral bargaining process in order to progress its claim for pay parity.  As such, the MLSA has at its disposal a fund equivalent to 1% of basic pay of all medical scientists.</p> <p>While this fund is insufficient to fully resolve its long-standing claims, it can partially resolve the claim and the remainder could be addressed in a future public service agreement, as per the terms of Building Momentum.  As previously stated, the MLSA and health management, in consultation with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, have been engaged in talks in recent months with the aim of finding a way to advance the claim through the sectoral bargaining process.  Several options for moving medical scientists to the biochemist scale, within the fund available, were explored during these talks.  These included options that would partially resolve the claim within this agreement but, to date, none has been accepted.  Any options that were put on the table were taken seriously and respectfully by both sides, and were discussed, costed, and verified by the HSE, the Department of Health and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform in good faith.</p> <p>The Public Service Agreement Group, PSAG, comprising union and Civil Service representatives, with an independent chair, met on 11 May to consider the MLSA's claim and proposed strike action.  It recommended that the matter be immediately referred to the WRC and that industrial peace be maintained in the meantime.  Health management met with the MLSA under the auspices of the WRC on 17 May, but, unfortunately, no resolution was reached.  While the MLSA agreed to engage at the WRC, it did not lift its industrial action, which is a breach of Building Momentum.  The Minister, Deputy Donnelly, is very disappointed that the strike action has proceeded despite it being precluded under the agreement.  The Minister recognises the significant disruption caused by the strike and the impact it is having on the health service.  Health management is committed to continuing engagement with the MLSA, while acknowledging that all parties must adhere to the provisions allowed for under Building Momentum and to resolve any disputes within the framework of the current agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#D00100"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response, although I have to say it is just a standard textbook response which means nothing to the workers involved in this dispute.  It is quite outrageous for the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, to say he is disappointed that the strike action has proceeded.  With all due respect the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, is completely missing the point.  These workers have had 20 years of trying to get pay justice and they have been ignored at every turn.  They were clear last week when they said they did not want to undertake this action and that all they wanted were meaningful negotiations.  I quoted Terry Casey to the Minister of State and he said they have not had any meaningful negotiations and yet we have this statement that the Minister for Health is disappointed.  He is missing the point.  The people of Ireland are disappointed in the Minister for Health and in this Government.  This dispute should never have been let happen.  It was clear and the Government had six months to fix this since the strike ballot, on top of the 20 years governments have already had, and it has come up with nothing.  A creative solution is entirely within the grasp of this Government but it needs the active involvement of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  It is clear from the Minister of State's response that the Minister for Health has failed to get that commitment.  That is why this strike is proceeding.  What hope will the Government offer the people of Ireland next week when it comes to further industrial action?  There is nothing in the speech the Minister of State has given here to offer any hope of a resolution to these workers or to the people desperately waiting for health appointments.  It is not good enough.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#D00200"><p>Again, the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, is disappointed the MLSA has initiated strike action.  Its vital role and presence in clinical settings across the country was suspended last week, causing disruption across the health service.  Its decision to strike was contrary to its commitment under Building Momentum, which states that parties to Building Momentum agree that the industrial peace will be maintained within the lifetime of the agreement.  The Minister has outlined that the Department of Health is bound by the existing pay agreement, Building Momentum, which clearly states that sectoral bargaining is the only mechanism for addressing outstanding claims within the lifetime of the agreement.  I assure the Senator that the health service management, in association with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, remain committed to engaging with the MLSA.  I reiterate how significant its presence is across the health service and the Minister for Health will continue to engage with the MLSA and make every effort to ensure a resolution is found as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.16" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#D00250">Hospital Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#D00400"><p>My Commencement matter is on when the Sacred Heart Hospital in Castlebar will see day services reopen and resume for citizens in County Mayo.  This hospital holds a special place in the hearts of the people of Castlebar and Mayo and has been providing services, including inpatient stay, rehabilitation and day services, for decades in the county town.  Almost all families in Mayo have had cause at some stage or other to use the facilities at this hospital.  In 2019 we were delighted to officially open what was a new facility following &euro;30 million of investment into the hospital.  Day services were closed at the hospital during the pandemic, which was understandable at the time, but we are now post the emergency phase of the pandemic and most services across the country have reopened.  However, we still do not have day services operational in the Sacred Heart Hospital and this beggars belief.  We were told last year that the HSE expected to reopen day services midway through quarter 1 of 2022.  That date has come and gone and we are no closer to the reopening of those services.</p> <p>Why have day services remained closed?  What is the short-term plan to get services reopened?  What is the Minister of State expecting to do for families and elderly persons in the county who badly need these services and who have been left with no alternative, unless they can pay privately, which most people cannot afford to do?  What is the plan to get this service reopened?  Why, when have we built a brand-new facility, are we now being told that the facility cannot accommodate day services because of changes in regulation?  It does not make sense or add up and the people of Castlebar and Mayo are wondering when they will get their day services reopened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#D00500"><p>I thank Senator Chambers for raising the important issue of the Sacred Heart Hospital in Castlebar.  I know she has consistently raised issues around the importance of the hospital in the Chamber, behind the scenes and directly with the Minister.  It is a key priority for the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, and the Government to allow more people to engage in services that allow them to remain independent and live in their homes with dignity and independence for as long as possible.  The HSE has operational responsibility for planning, managing and delivering health and personal social services, including day centres.  These services are fundamental to the health and well-being of our older population.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy James Browne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2443"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2443&amp;amp;pid=JamesBrowne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Just yesterday, my colleague, the Minister of State with responsibility for older people, Deputy Butler, had a high-level meeting with her officials requesting progress on this subject.  Access to the centres can make an important contribution by providing invaluable support, advice and social interaction for older people who may, for any number of reasons, be experiencing isolation and loneliness.  They play a key role in enabling older people to live independently within their own communities.  It remains a priority for the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, to ensure that day centres reopen as quickly and as safely as possible following their necessary closure in 2020 in response to Covid-19.  The process for reopening day centres commenced in 2021, and the HSE continues to actively work on their reopening for older people as a priority, in line with current public health guidance.  The HSE has allocated &euro;6.5 million to community health organisations, CHOs, from within existing resources to facilitate the reopening of day care services for older people.  In addition, &euro;925,000 once-off funding was allocated to the Alzheimer Society of Ireland to assist with the operation of their dementia day-care services.  This funding will support existing services to reopen and, in some, cases expand their services.</p><p>At the end of April, 264 centres for older people had reopened, which represents 80% of centres, and it is planned that a further 14 will reopen this month.  There are two day services operating in Castlebar at present.  Castlebar Social Services day service and the Alzheimer Society of Ireland are continuing to offer a service at home.  However, day services at the Sacred Heart have not reopened.  The HSE has advised the Department that it is making continuous efforts to source alternative accommodation.  The social services space that was considered suitable for day services on the ground floor did not materialise because they rented the space to another day service.  An alternative space located on the upper floor was reviewed by Community Healthcare West, but unfortunately it was deemed unsuitable.  As infection prevention control, IPC, guidelines have now changed, an alternative space on the Sacred Heart Hospital campus is being pursued.  The provision of a day service for the elderly on the Sacred Heart Hospital campus in Castlebar is preferable from an operational, governance and value for money perspective.  The Minister of State, Deputy Butler, has advised me that the HSE is actively pursuing an interim arrangement for the summer and is exploring all options for a permanent space for Sacred Heart Hospital day services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  Some of what he said is very welcome.  It is great that &euro;6.5 million has been allocated to CHOs across the State to get these day services up and running and that &euro;925,000 was provided to the Alzheimer Society of Ireland.  However, it still begs the question as to why a new facility that was opened in 2019 is not being reopened.  We have all of this money being put into getting day centres back up and running - some 80% have reopened and 40 more are due to reopen - so why is the Castlebar facility not reopening?  What is the problem?  It cannot simply just be a case of not being able to find the right building.  There are other locations.  We still cannot get an answer to that question.  How will we have a new facility if it is not fit for purpose to reopen as a day centre?  Nobody can seem to answer that question.</p> <p>I take on board what the Minister of State said about the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, actively exploring interim solutions.  We were told that last year, and it still has not materialised.  I know of one family in particular where it actually accelerated their decision to put their loved one into full-time nursing home care because they could not cope at home.  That was after two long years of the pandemic when there were literally no services for people caring for loved ones with dementia.  What is happening is forcing people into that.  It is a Government priority and a Government policy to facilitate people staying in their own homes for as long as possible because we believe in that option for people, and to provide that dignity for them to stay at home.  This was not an option for the family to which I refer.  The situation is the same for many other families.</p> <p>I am looking for more concrete timelines.  What are the interim arrangements being explored?  When can we expect an update as to what they are, what they will look like and when they will be available?  What is the long-term prospect of reopening day services at the hospital?  Somebody needs to ask the question, and I am asking it here today.  When a new facility was built and reopened, why was it not fit for purpose to provide day services?  It seems as though the ball was dropped when that facility was constructed and that design was done, that it could not cater for updating of guidelines.  Surely, when we opened a facility in 2019, it should have been a long-term facility that can cater for at least the next 50 to 60 years.  That seems to not have happened.  I would appreciate if the Minister of State had any more detail at all about the interim arrangements being explored and when we could see those services back up and running.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#E00300"><p>I thank Senator Chambers again for raising this very important issue regarding the Sacred Heart Hospital in Castlebar.  The Senator has consistently pursued the importance of this facility.</p> <p>On the more specific points, I will certainly raise those with the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, and I will ask her to engage with Senator Chambers on it.  As the Senator rightly pointed out, it is a priority.  It is a policy of this Government to help as many people as possible to stay at home, and to be able to do so with dignity and with the services they need to be able to stay at home.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy James Browne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2443"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2443&amp;amp;pid=JamesBrowne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The HSE has prioritised and will continue to prioritise the reopening of day-care centres for older people.  This focus has been on both directly operated HSE day-care centres and day-care services provided under grant-aid funding by the HSE.</p><p>I reiterate the HSE has assured the Department it is exploring every option for a permanent space for Sacred Heart Hospital day services and the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, has asked her officials to monitor the position over the coming months.  It is hoped interim arrangements will be put in place for the summer.  I will certainly ask her to keep Senator Chambers up to date on all the steps and details relating to the issue.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.23" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#F00200">Telecommunications Infrastructure</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#F00300"><p>This is about telecommunications masks in local communities.  I thank Councillor Ted Leddy, who came across a telecommunications mast that is going up in Castleknock village.  He found it by accident when searching for something else and is now supporting the local community.</p><p>There is major confusion among local communities about telecommunications masts.  I am not absolutely clear on the parameters by which they are considered exempted development.  There is conflicting information in the media when compared with my read of the regulations.  There is confusion because there seems to be absolutely no public consultation even though these masts can be 15 m or 20 m high in prominent community locations.  There is no site notice, advertisement in the newspaper or public submissions process.  Even the local planning authorities do not seem to have a say anymore as An Bord Plean&aacute;la is overturning decisions.  I will summarise some of the information I have and the Minister of State might clarify it for me.</p><p>Under the Planning and Development Act 2000 all development, unless specifically exempted under the Act or associated regulations, requires planning permission.  When I look at the Act under section 4 it lists exempted development but I do not see a reference to telecommunications.  Section 4(2)(a) states, &quot;The Minister may by regulations provide for any class of development to be exempted development ...&quot; and lays out certain conditions.  Is telecommunications infrastructure covered by that?  Under SI 600/2001 - Planning and Development Regulations, 2001, class 31 of Schedule 2 provides that certain classes of development carried out to provide a telecommunications service are subject to exempted development.  Is this the relevant legislation?  If so, I still do not understand what the conditions and size thresholds are.  It refers to overhead equipment and states: &quot;Poles carrying overhead lines shall not exceed 10 metres ...&quot;.  A reply to a parliamentary question put by another Oireachtas Member stated, &quot;The legislative provisions are supplemented by planning guidelines entitled the Telecommunications Antennae and Support Structure Guidelines, which originally issued to planning authorities in 1996&quot;.  It further stated these were updated in 2012 with a circular letter.</p><p>The 1996 guidelines state, &quot;The height of these structures, when the requirements of the backbone network are taken into account, can range from 12m to 60m though most typically they will be between 20m and 40m&quot;.  Also under the guidelines, local authorities are required to have a policy where special conditions would apply or where, &quot;... for various reasons, telecommunications installations would not be favoured ...&quot;.  Such sites might include lands of high amenity value, protected structures or sites beside schools.  However, the 2012 circular states:</p> <blockquote> 	While the policies above are reasonable, there has, however, been a growing trend for the insertion of development plan policies and objectives specifying minimum distances between telecommunications structures from houses and schools, e.g. up to 1km.  Such distance requirements, without allowing for flexibility on a case-by-case basis, can make the identification of a site for new infrastructure very difficult.  Planning authorities should therefore not include such separation distances as they can inadvertently have a major impact on the roll out of a viable and effective telecommunications network. </blockquote> <p>Is it therefore national policy the location of telecommunications masts are to be determined on a case-by-case basis under exempted development such that there is no public consultation for structures that can be up to 60 m high and that even when they are refused that can be overturned by An Bord Plean&aacute;la?  Nobody could reasonably suggest telecommunications infrastructure is not of national and strategic importance but surely there must be some parameters on where it can go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#F00400"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter around the thresholds within which telecommunications masts are not considered exempted development and require public consultation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy James Browne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2443"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2443&amp;amp;pid=JamesBrowne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> On behalf of the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, who sends his apologies for being unable to be here today, I note the current exemptions from planning for telecommunications infrastructure and instances where planning permission is required is as follows.  The Planning and Development Regulations 2001, as amended, provides an exemption from the requirement for planning permission for certain telecommunications infrastructure under class 31 of Part 1 of Schedule 2 to the regulations.  This allows for the deployment of specified telecommunications infrastructure by a statutory undertaker authorised to provide a telecommunications service without having to go through the planning process.</p><p>Where the proposed telecommunications infrastructure is not being installed by a statutory undertaker authorised to do so or where the size of the proposed infrastructure exceeds the limits set out in class 31 of the regulations, such as greater than 12 m in height for a telecommunications pole, full planning permission will be required.</p><p>In this connection, it should be noted that the exemptions from planning do not apply in certain circumstances.  First, if the proposed location for the telecommunications infrastructure is in an area that requires an environmental impact assessment or an appropriate assessment to be undertaken before any works can commence, such as on a European designated site, the exemption under class 31 of the regulations is disapplied under section 4(4) of the Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended, and planning permission for the proposed works must be sought.</p><p>Second, if the proposed location for the telecommunications infrastructure would materially affect the character of a "protected structure", or any element of the structure which contributes to its special architectural, historical, archaeological, artistic, cultural, scientific, social or technical interest, then the planning exemption under class 31 of the regulations is disapplied under section 57(1) of the Act, again with the result that planning permission must be sought before any works can commence.</p><p>Where proposed telecommunications infrastructure does not meet the requirements of the class 31 exemption, or where the exemption is disapplied because of the provisions of the Act, an application for planning permission must, as I have outlined, be made to the relevant planning authority in accordance with section 34 of the Act.  The planning process prescribes a five-week period from the date of application for the making of submissions or observations by any person to the planning authority.</p><p>Following the decision of a planning authority under section 34 of the Act, an applicant for permission and any person who made submissions or observations in writing in terms of the planning application to the planning authority in accordance with the permission regulations, and on payment of the appropriate fee, may, within four weeks of the planning authority decision, appeal the decision to An Bord Plean&aacute;la in accordance with section 37 of the Act.  The appeals process in An Bord Plean&aacute;la includes a four-week period for the making of submissions or observations by any person under section 129 of the Act.  In addition, the board may, in its absolute discretion under section 134 of the Act, hold an oral hearing of an appeal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#G00200"><p>I will have to go through the reply in detail but I can tell the Minister of State that the telecommunications mast in Castleknock is 15 m and there is a mast in Glaslough which is 19 m, and featured in the latest edition of the <i>Sunday Independent.</i>These masts did not go through the planning process but were a section 254 application so the public did not know about them.  The councils have said &quot;No&quot;.  The mast in Castleknock used a section 254 application, which was rejected by the local authority rejected and An Bord Plean&aacute;la overturned that so there is an issue.  The telecommunications mast has been located in Castleknock in a prominent area with one of the highest footfall in the community.  The local Tidy Towns committee has spent the last two years trying to reflect the beauty of this picturesque village, so the notion that a 15 m mast can be erected without public consultation or even an awareness by the public is very worrisome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#G00300"><p>I thank Senator Currie for raising this important matter.  Obviously I cannot speak about a specific case because it would be inappropriate for me to do so.  What I can say is that where any person or body is unsure if planning is required for specific proposed telecommunications infrastructure they may, on payment of the prescribed fee, submit a request in writing to the relevant planning authority seeking a declaration under section 5 of the Act on whether the telecommunications infrastructure is or is not development, or is or is not exempted development within the meaning of the Act.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy James Browne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2443"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2443&amp;amp;pid=JamesBrowne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These provisions and arrangements as outlined in the Act and in supplementary regulations are considered to be reasonable, balanced and proportionate in terms of enabling specified forms of development to proceed without having to undergo the full rigours of the planning system, while simultaneously ensuring that certain development proposals that exceed the exemption thresholds or which may have impacts on the environment or on protected structures are subject to assessment under the planning process and involve public consultation with the right of appeal before any such development proposals are authorised to be progressed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.30" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#H00200">Planning Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#H00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House and agreeing to take this Commencement matter.  The topic concerns solar panels on farm buildings and structures.  I am conscious that the Minister of State is a rural Deputy for Wexford so he will be very familiar with the issues and challenges in respect of solar panels for agriculture.  This is a wonderful time for strawberries in Wexford so I can see the synergies and the potential for solar panels for soft fruit crops, particularly in the sunny south east of Wexford.</p> <p>I am asking that the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage clarify the current status of the draft regulations and the timelines involved.  That is important.  It is an issue we have discussed at great length in the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, of which I am a member.  Deputy Cahill, a member of the Minister of State's party, is the Chairman.  We have discussed it and teased out the issues and challenges.  We have invited different representative groups and stakeholders in this area to make presentations to the committee.  We see major challenges there, but we also see major opportunities.  That is very important.  I am also conscious of the need for strategic environmental assessment.  That is a requirement, not a choice.  In talking about planning law and environmental law, it is critical that we follow the processes.  There is a requirement for a strategic environmental assessment, the publication of the proposals and a public consultation process, which is critical in all this.</p> <p>I would appreciate if the Minister of State could give some type of guidance on where the Government intends to go now, the position with regard to the timelines and the position with the environmental impact assessment and statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#H00400"><p>I thank the Senator for raising the important issue of the current status of the draft regulations and planning exemptions for solar panels on farm buildings and other structures, including timelines.</p> <p>To provide some background on the issue, under the Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended, all development, unless specifically exempted under the Act or associated regulations, requires planning permission.  Various exemptions from the requirement to obtain planning permission are set out in the Act and regulations, and these exemptions are subject to compliance with general restrictions on exemptions set out in the Act and regulations.  Included in the planning exemptions are those applying to the installation of solar infrastructure on a variety of building types, including houses, businesses and industrial and agricultural structures to which specific conditions are attached.</p> <p>The Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, in the context of the climate action plan and in consultation with the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications, has completed a review of the existing solar panel planning exemptions set out in the regulations, with a particular focus on facilitating increased self-generation of electricity and in recognition of the limitations of the current exemptions.</p> <p>Further to this work, substantial changes to the current planning exemption thresholds for solar panels are proposed, as well as the introduction of new classes of solar panel planning exemptions for apartments and educational, community and religious buildings.  Draft regulations have been prepared by the Department which have been screened for appropriate assessment, AA, under the requirements of the habitats directive and strategic environmental assessment, SEA, under the requirements of the SEA directive.  While the need for AA was screened out by the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage's ecological assessment unit in April, it has been determined that a full SEA on the draft proposals, which will include public consultation as part of the process, is required.</p> <p>A four-week statutory consultation with the environmental authorities on the scope of the draft SEA environmental report commenced on 28 April 2022 and will run until 27 May 2022.  Following this consultation process, the draft environmental report will be updated to take account of submissions received from the environmental authorities, and a four-week public consultation on the draft environmental report will subsequently be launched.  This public consultation is expected to commence in the coming weeks.</p> <p>As required under planning legislation, the proposed exempted development regulations must be laid in draft form before the Houses of the Oireachtas and receive a positive resolution from both Houses before they can be made and the SEA process concluded.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy James Browne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2443"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2443&amp;amp;pid=JamesBrowne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Therefore, it is envisaged that the process for finalising the solar panel planning exemptions will be completed in the coming months, following the conclusion of the public consultation process and the finalisation of the strategic environmental assessment report.  The regulations will also be subject to Oireachtas approval.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#J00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  He has given us a bit of clarity, which is great.  I understand that the public consultation is nearly due for completion.  I thank the Minister of State for the confirmation that the regulations will be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas for affirmation.  That will give us an opportunity.  Measures like these usually come in without debate but it is open to us to seek a debate.  I put the House on notice that I will seek some sort of engagement in the House on this matter.  As I said, I believe it is important.  However, it is also important that we follow the environmental report.  I thank the Minister of State for bringing some clarity to this matter today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1618" speakername="James Browne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#J00300"><p>I again thank Senator Boyhan for raising the important issue of the current status of draft regulations on planning exemptions for solar panels on farm buildings and other structures.  The Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, had hoped the new regulations would be in place much sooner but the timeline has been delayed by the necessity to comply with European environmental reporting requirements, particularly those relating to the strategic environmental assessment and habitats directives.  However, as I said, the Department is now in the final stages of the process.  I understand every effort is being made to bring this matter to a conclusion as speedily as possible.  Once again, I thank the Senator for raising this important issue, which remains at the top of the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke's agenda.  The Minister of State looks forward to the imminent introduction of the revised exempted development regulations in the coming months and to the positive impact they will have on the roll-out of renewable solar infrastructure throughout the country, thereby helping to achieve our climate objectives and reduce our dependency on energy derived from fossil fuels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.36" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 12.42 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 1 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 12.42 p.m. and resumed at 1 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.37" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(3)) (Variation of title: Chiropodist) Regulations 2022, referral to committee, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, the Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022 - Committee Stage (Resumed), to be taken at 2.15 p.m. and to adjourn at 4.30 p.m., if not previously concluded; and No. 3, motion regarding arrangements for the address to Seanad &Eacute;ireann by Congressman Richard Neal, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. in accordance with the arrangements set out in the motion agreed by the House on Thursday, 19 May 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#N00400"><p>I agree with the Order of Business as outlined by the Leader.  I want to raise a number of issues, the first of which is the national retrofitting scheme that was announced by the Government last February.  It would be welcome to have an opportunity to have this conversation with the Minister for Environment, Climate and Communications, Deputy Eamon Ryan, and the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, when we get a chance.  As it stands there are only five designated one-stop shops that have made it through the registration process to facilitate the deep retrofit of homes.  Before the new scheme was launched back in February, there were around 20 companies one could go to for that service in the old scheme that was operational last year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lisa Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2449"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2449&amp;amp;pid=LisaChambers&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is my understanding that some of those companies are still in the process of registering with the Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland, SEAI, but it is taking a lot longer than they would have anticipated, and I am sure longer than the public would have anticipated.  On the SEAI website, the one-stop shop grants information section has five companies or operators listed.  At the bottom of that page it states that it is getting a lot of calls and emails, which is understandable, and that people can expect to wait.  It makes it tricky to deliver on the targets we have set if people cannot even access the service.  It would be welcome to get an update on why it is taking so long to re-register companies that were already providing the service and that were very much up to speed on what the new scheme was going to do, and why it is taking so long to get them back up as registered companies to do the one-stop shop service.  I am sure that the five companies listed are finding it difficult to cope with the demand that is there.<br/><br/>I acknowledge and congratulate the author Sally Rooney, who comes from my county of Mayo and who has been named in <i>Time</i>magazine's list of 100 most influential people.  She is a fantastic role model.  We are extremely proud of her in Mayo.  I congratulate her and her family on her fantastic achievements.  As somebody who is really only starting out in her career, I have no doubt she will go on to do even more great things.<br/><br/>I wish to raise the issue, as many colleagues have done over the past months, of the passport service.  It is still experiencing huge delays.  It would appear the adult passport service is no problem.  If one is renewing a passport as an adult, the service is absolutely super.  A person can have his or her passport back in a day or two, which is phenomenal.  However, trying to get a child's passport for the first time is an absolute nightmare.  All of us, as public representatives, are dealing with a huge number of queries and representations on the issue.  Many families have been saving for the past year, have booked the family holiday, and are waiting on their child's passports.  Families cannot go on their holidays and are losing that money.  It is not a luxury to get a passport.  The passport service is not doing people a favour by giving them passports.  As a citizen of this State, a person is entitled to that really important document.  There really is no excuse for it taking three to four months to deliver a child's passport.  Perhaps we could try to encourage the Department of Foreign Affairs and the Passport Office.  Is there a shortfall in staff or resources, or whatever?  We get an increase in demand every year at this time of year because of the summer holidays.  It is anticipated and foreseen.  Let us make plans to increase the support in the Passport Offices to deliver the passports.  This would take that strain off parents and, hopefully, people can get their holidays in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#O00200"><p>I welcome the announcement by An Bord Plean&aacute;la that planning permission has been granted for the Celtic interconnector between Ireland and France.  This is hugely important for energy supply and for the exchange of electricity between Ireland and France.  I hope that one day it will be part of an exporting cable for naturally produced wind energy as well.  In the meantime, we will be takers of electricity from France.  This connectivity to a European Union partner is hugely important for energy security.  I certainly welcome the decision.  We often give out about delays in the planning process but, thankfully, this is something that has now been granted by An Bord Plean&aacute;la.</p> <p>I was at an Irish Farmers' Association, IFA, meeting last night in Corrofin in Galway organised by the Connacht IFA on the concerns around import costs and food security in the coming year.  It was a well-attended event.  The EEC was established to ensure the security of supply of food across the European Union after the ravages of World War II.  It was hugely important.  In some way, perhaps the Union has become a little complacent over the years and thought that this was no longer an issue.  The illegal invasion of Ukraine and the war there has put a different perspective on that, which is worrying.  The message from some of the farmers yesterday was that there was concern now around the supply of food in the Union.  Import costs are a huge concern with regard to fertiliser and meal.  Ukraine is regarded as the breadbasket of Europe and perhaps people were not as aware of its importance until issues arose because of the war and supply constraints.  The farmers are gravely concerned about the cost of fertiliser and the supply of fertiliser into the future.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I welcome all the supports that have been provided by the Government and the Minister and Ministers of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  I look forward to the details of the fodder scheme that is due to be announced.  This could see a payment of up to &euro;1,000 for farmers.  That will mitigate some of the costs and is extremely important.  However, I ask for a debate on agriculture, food supplies and food security in the coming weeks.  We still have a chance to ensure that there will be no fodder shortage next winter or in the early spring, and it is behoves us all to ensure that everything is put in place to ensure that such a shortage does not happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#P00200"><p>I second what Senator Kyne just said.  Every word of that is important, but we also need to broaden this to address the terror many of us feel at what may be facing other parts of the world as well as a result of the threat to the grain supply coming out of Ukraine.  We think of the populations of countries in the Middle East, such as Egypt, south-east Asia and north Africa.  The populations of these countries are going to suffer enormously if the grain harvest from Ukraine cannot be got out of that country.  The world is very big and we, sometimes rightly, feel we are very small.  Listening to the debate about this and news of the proposal from Lithuania that there be some kind of coalition of the willing to get the grain out through the Black Sea past Russian warships, it is terrifying to think that might not be possible.  We are facing into the next six or seven weeks when the grain will be ready.  What is going to happen to it then?  I was listening to former President McAleese on "The Late Late Show"  on one occasion being sharply critical of the Russian ambassador and feeling at the time that approach was perhaps ill-advised.  If there is ever an argument for a small, neutral country raising its voice, even in this dreadful time of hatred and degradation from Russia, surely we should be trying to create some diplomatic space to be a persuader, even in the midst of all this horror and for some recognition the less fortunate and most vulnerable people of the world must not be forced into a situation of hunger and starvation.  I ask for a debate that will take on board fully the importance of the issues Senator Kyne has raised but that will also focus on the people in the other parts of the world who are really going to suffer if a solution is not found.</p> <p>If I may, I would like to use the rest of my time to mention an important name, albeit one perhaps not as well-known to people in Ireland as it should be.  The name is Titus Brandsma.  I was in Whitefriar Street Church on Sunday, as was the Dutch ambassador, for a ceremony to mark the recent canonisation of St. Titus Brandsma, who surely is a hero for our times.  He was a Carmelite friar who resisted Nazi propaganda going into Catholic, and indeed other, media.  He spoke out strongly against the persecution of Jews and the infringement of basic human rights by the Nazi occupiers.  He died in Dachau in 1942 by lethal injection.  He was called "the dangerous little friar" by the Gestapo.  The account of how it arrived at the Carmelite friary at Nijmegen to arrest him is quite harrowing.  The remarkable thing is that the nurse who gave him his lethal injection returned to her faith because she observed that he had compassion for her.  This man had an almost supernatural capacity to not hate his enemies, despite the horrors they were inflicting on him and others.  He spoke out boldly for freedom in the midst of tyranny - freedom of individual conscience, freedom of religion and freedom of the press.  It is appropriate that we honour people like him.  They exist in our world, they come forward from time to time and they witness against the horror and depravity others wreak on our world.  They should be celebrated for their inspiring example even if all of us, or most of us, feel we would never be able to follow that example.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#P00300"><p>I thank the Senator for his contribution and for remembering somebody who showed generosity to everyone, including his enemies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#P00400"><p>The window we have for climate action, especially in the midlands, is very exciting.  It is an opportunity for us to define our identity for decades ahead.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pippa Hackett:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=0000"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=0000&amp;amp;pid=PippaHackett&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is imperative for us in government to bring people along the way as we do this.</p><p>Henry Ford's combustion engine drove the transport revolution in Ireland in the early 20th century.  It led to a move from horses to cars that were available in any colour as long as it was black, and available to people who could afford them.  There was no State aid and no possibility of any money back for use.  It was a revolution that became inevitable very quickly but many people were left behind for decades.  Solar panels, which are also only available in black as far as I am aware, can be installed on a roof in a matter of weeks.  The scheme would be supported by a Government grant and has the potential to reduce one's energy bill through the self-consumption of the energy produced or through payment for the excess energy that is not used.  As inevitable as the motor car was a 100 years ago the economics continue to go only way with renewables.  The choice is how quickly we transition and how democratically.</p><p>In the midlands, we are to be further supported through the EU Just Transition Fund, which will likely open for applications later this year.  My vision is that the fund will be used to help community driven projects to literally take power into their own hands.  Last week, saw an announcement of provisional offers in the renewable energy support scheme, which is the Government's way of supporting grid-scale renewable energy projects through a series of auctions.  A higher level of support is payable to those projects that are 100% community owned.  Calling a solar company about installing panels on a roof is relatively easy to do but the idea of starting a community project may be very daunting.  Thankfully, the work is already under way and people can join in.  For example, in Laois, Offaly and Westmeath there are about 35 sustainable energy communities that have an interest in community-led renewable energy.</p><p>As well as speaking to people in the midlands, in recent months I have travelled from Donegal to south Kerry, to Sligo, Mayo, Galway, Limerick and Clare.  Last week I was closer to home in Kildare as part of biodiversity week.  The common theme everywhere I go is that people understand the need for climate action and they want to do what they can to get involved.  To everyone who wants to play their part in this great transition of our time, I suggest three easy steps to build on one's own personal climate action this week.  The first is to get a quote for a solar panel, the second is to reach out to the nearest sustainable energy community and see how it can benefit you and your environment and the third is to sit down at one's kitchen table and plan.  Many of us do this for our family budget so why not for a carbon budget?</p><p>Speaking for my own constituency in Laois-Offaly, I know this is a once-in-a-lifetime opportunity to redefine the midlands, breathe life into the region through job opportunities and service, and to drive collective ways of working in transport, energy and in the circular economy social enterprises.  Let us lead the way in the midlands and set ourselves the goal of being the best area in western Europe for positive community-based climate action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#Q00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#Q00300"><p>I salute the An L&aacute; Dearg protest that took place in Belfast at the weekend.  Anyone who watched it on television would say that it was spectacular.  There must have been at least 20,000 people there.  Even though my colleague, Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile, is quite a young man, I noticed that most of the people who took part were younger than him.  It was such a vibrant and powerful protest.  Of course, their key ask is absolutely just and it is that we see Acht na Gaeilge made law in the North.  I express my solidarity and support for all of those who took the time to protest last Saturday and wish them continued success in their campaign.</p> <p>The second topic I want to raise concerns what is happening in our hospitals at the minute.  I tabled a Commencement matter on medical laboratory scientists but I wish to put the following on the record again.  I cannot for the life of me understand how this Government has allowed this strike to come about given that it had six months since the strike notice was given last November to sit down and have concrete, meaningful negotiations with these workers.  I am genuinely at a loss as to why that has not happened.  To hear the statement repeated to me this morning by a junior Minister that the Minister for Health is very disappointed misses the point.  We need to see the Minister engage meaningfully.  There is a solution for every industrial dispute but it takes both sides to make that happen.  These people did not want to go on strike and they were very clear about that when I met them, so we need to see action.</p> <p>In a similar vein, I am concerned about University Hospital Limerick.  Again, I wish to express solidarity with the laboratory scientists there, in particular.  As members will know, a task force was established to solve the ongoing crisis in University Hospital Limerick.  That is a good thing and is something we have sought for a long time.  I am, therefore, flabbergasted to report that so far, the task force has met a number of times but has not even asked for a meeting with any of the unions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Given that the staff are keeping that hospital going, it is astounding that it has not even occurred to the task force to reach out to SIPTU and the nurses' unions to ask them what the problems are.  Unfortunately, that is the case at present.  I am very much at a loss in that regard.  As always, I call for a further debate on University Hospital Limerick because of the depth of the crisis there and what is facing us next winter.</p><p>Regarding the comments on passports, again, I am astounded at the statement by the Department of Foreign Affairs that there is no backlog in passports.  It made that statement this morning.  At one point last week, all four Sinn F&eacute;in representatives were on the telephone to the Passport Service.  I am sure it is the same for Fine Gael, Fianna F&aacute;il and Independent Members.  It is astounding to say there is no backlog.</p><p>Finally, I pay tribute to Cathal Coughlan, an amazing singer with Fatima Mansions and Microdisney.  He was a great Irishman and a complete genius who unfortunately died far too young at the age of 61 years at the weekend.  I wish to put that on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#R00200"><p>He will be remembered from town to town.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#R00300"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#R00400"><p>I wish to raise the issue of dereliction in our towns and cities.  A report has just been published by the Oireachtas Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage on the issue of dereliction.  We have worked on this issue for a number of months and have reached a cross-party and broad-based consensus on some of the issues that have to be tackled in order to tackle dereliction.  Unfortunately, some of the indications we see coming from the Department are that there are no low-hanging fruit when it comes to dereliction and that a vacant sites tax will not bring in much money, so it is not worth doing and administering.  That is very worrying.</p> <p>The issue of dereliction is not just about raising money and taxes.  It is to try to bring properties that could be used as housing back into use or if they could be used for something else they could be brought back into use as smaller businesses.  If the owners cannot do that, there should be a tax on them so they will sell them on to somebody else who can afford to do it.  Dereliction is a blight.  It is not just one of the underlying causes of the housing crisis, it is also a blight on our towns and cities and it causes anti-social behaviour according to the broken-window theory.</p> <p>I will outline some of the suggestions on which there is that cross-party, broad-based consensus.  The first is to collect the proper amount of data on what is actually derelict and then categorise that information and break it down.  Some of it may be housing, some might be otherwise.  Some may have issues with probate, but some could potentially be brought back into use.  We should include things such as a vacant homes tax.  For example, if somebody got permission for residential use and it is registered and zoned as residential, a vacant homes tax should apply to it if it is willfully being left vacant.  That applies to, for example, my village of Chapelizod.  Half of it could be brought back into use for housing, but instead, it is lying there derelict.</p> <p>The second one is a zoned land tax.  The vacant sites tax had so many exemptions that it did not work.  However, the zoned land tax that has been passed also has exemptions.  I am afraid that by the time it is implemented, two years hence and at a lesser rate, there will be so many exemptions it will not be worthwhile.  We have to look at streamlining the appeals process around that.</p> <p>Finally, there should be an expansion of the definition of what is derelict.  Often, the legal interpretation that local authorities have of what is derelict is very different from what we or people on the street know and see as being derelict.  Each local authority should have a derelict sites section.  It could emulate the amazing work that the repair and lease scheme has done in places such as Waterford and Louth in terms of tackling dereliction in a city.</p> <p>I ask the Leader for a debate on that.  I believe we are proposing that time be put aside in both Houses to have a debate on the report.  I cannot emphasise enough that a vacant homes tax in Housing for All and in the programme for Government is an essential part of the response because sometimes, people wilfully leave property that could be used for housing vacant.  I can point to a number of places in my constituency where that is the case and local authorities cannot take action on it.  We need to have carrots for people, but we also must introduce the sticks to try to get people to bring good land that is connected to services back into use.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#S00100"><p>If I may, I will dedicate most of my time to the wonderful successes of Lisa O'Rourke and Amy Broadhurst.  Lisa O'Rourke was the winner of the women's world elite boxing championship in Istanbul.  Castlerea, County Roscommon, was alive and kicking at the weekend.  Thousands of people turned out.  Tears of absolute joy were shed for a beautiful young woman who is very involved with her community.  She is a leader in that community and has a quiet manner.  Of course, her sister, Aoife, also has had great success in Europe.  We congratulate them.  If it is in order and if the House agrees, perhaps we could write to Lisa O'Rourke and Amy Broadhurst to congratulate them because this certainly was historic.  It is absolutely fantastic and brilliant.  It was very uplifting not only for Castlerea and County Roscommon, but for all of Ireland.  The celebrations have been absolutely fantastic.</p> <p>I also want to acknowledge the fact that I attended a meeting of farmers in Galway late last night.  They have concerns and issues.  I know the Minister is engaging constantly with Oireachtas Members and farm leaders.  There are many difficulties ahead in light of the Ukrainian war.  While the price of beef is extraordinarily good at the moment, the benefit is being taken away by the costs involved, particularly in respect of silage and fertiliser.  I wanted to acknowledge that and to say that my colleagues and I, as Members of the Oireachtas, are aware of this and are working on it.  I am sure we will have some solutions in the weeks ahead.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#S00200"><p>Last September, I tabled a Commencement matter on the human papillomavirus, HPV, vaccine.  The Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, came in on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, and committed to eliminating the charge for the catch-up vaccination.  I was quite disappointed when this was then referred to the national immunisation advisory committee, NIAC, because what this vaccine has achieved speaks for itself.  I was even more disappointed when it was not included in the women's health strategy published last April.  Having said that, I am an eternal optimist.  I tabled a Commencement matter on this issue last week because six months had elapsed since the last.  Unfortunately, due to other demands on the Cathaoirleach, he was not in a position to accept that matter.  I am thankful that, on Friday evening, it was announced that cost of the HPV vaccine is to be eliminated for everybody under 25, irrespective of when it is taken.  Anybody taking a vaccination as part of a catch-up programme will, therefore, not have to pay the &euro;400 to &euro;600 cost, which is quite punitive, especially if a number of members of a family did not, for whatever reason, take the vaccine when in first year at school.  I hope that we will now see an uptake rate of close to 100% in first year at school and that there will be no need for a catch-up programme but, for the next period of time, there will be need for one.</p> <p>I seek a debate, or even statements, at some stage outlining the detail of the catch-up programme, where it is going to be rolled out, the type of information campaign that will be associated with it and, more broadly, the kind of information campaign there will be in respect of the HPV vaccine for secondary schools next September and onwards.  Information is key.  If the facts are put out there, people will get the vaccination.  The messaging around this and the use of modern technology such as social media and so on is critically important.  I spoke in the media yesterday with Laura Brennan's parents, Larry and Bernie.  They are absolutely delighted that everybody under 25 years of age will now be able to access the HPV vaccination free of charge.  It is a fitting tribute to the phenomenal campaigning work the late Laura Brennan did in the period before she passed from this world.  We can never forget Laura's legacy and what she did for health, and women's health in particular, in this country.  Her legacy will live on but we still have to keep our finger on the pulse to ensure information campaigns are rolled out in association with the catch-up programme and to persuade people in first year at school to take the vaccine.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is critically important because that is how we will honour the legacy of her great work and commitment to Irish society.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#T00200"><p>We learned yesterday about the obscene amount of wealth that has been accumulated by billionaires in this country and around the world since the Covid pandemic began.  According to Oxfam, the wealth of the world's billionaires rose more in the past two years than it had in the previous 23 combined.  In Ireland, billionaires have increased their worth by more than &euro;15 billion since the start of the pandemic.  This highlights very starkly the scourge of social inequality and an economic system that is rigged in favour of those at the very top.  We know that the wealth is created by workers, by those who fail to share in the value that they create.  The Leader should schedule a debate on the Oxfam report and also on whether this country should implement a wealth tax, as has long been called for by those on the left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#T00300"><p>Yesterday, the BBC did the world a service by releasing documents hacked from the Xinjiang police relating to the Uyghur population in that part of China.  There is nowhere for China to hide now on this.  There is no doubt that what we are witnessing in Xinjiang is a genocide.  It is a programme of re-education and the forced separation of families, and all the other awful things that we know are happening.  Given that we know they are happening, we as a Government, a country, and a community, have a responsibility to do something about that.  The very least that we can do is have a debate about it.  We should bring the Minister for Foreign Affairs and other members of the Government in here to ask them what steps Ireland can take to bring to China's attention that we will not accept the carry-on and appalling behaviour of China in relation to the minority population in the Xinjiang Uyghur autonomous region.  It is unacceptable and there is now nowhere for China to hide.  We know it is happening.  There is conclusive proof.  One of the most respected international journalistic organisations, the BBC, has verified this information.  It spent quite a lot of time carefully doing so.  We now know it is happening.  Anybody who had any doubts now knows that it is happening, and that includes the Irish Government.  The time has come for us to say "Stop" to that and to send a very clear message to China that it cannot be allowed to act with impunity in respect of its own citizens in the way it has.  It must end.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#T00400"><p>I wish to raise urban regeneration, in particular in light of the report which was launched this morning by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage.  The report details not less than 39 recommendations to be taken to address dereliction and to champion urban regeneration.  The report, with cross-party support, specifically endorses a number of actions that are captured in Housing for All.  I refer to initiatives such as the lease and repair scheme, the buy and renew scheme and the living city scheme but also the commitment to introduce a vacant property tax.  There is no faster or more sustainable way to increase our housing stock than to reuse existing buildings that are available and lying vacant in many towns and villages.  They are on streets that have public lighting, sewerage and public transportation.  They are close to schools, doctors and shops.  This report presents an opportunity not just to address the dereliction and the vacancy, but it also captures actions that can actively promote living cities, living rural towns and living villages.  I would like if the Leader would schedule time to debate the report.  The House could contribute greatly to the championing of the recommendations in the report and to informing the Government on the broad support that it enjoys.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#U00100"><p>Today marks three months since the start of the war in Ukraine.  I want to first acknowledge the Cathaoirleach for visiting Kyiv last week, along with the Ceann Comhairle, and for showing the solidarity that we as a country should show Ukraine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#U00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#U00300"><p>He met with President Zelenskyy and with the Prime Minister.  There is a worrying trend within the European Union in the conversation of where the war is going in Ukraine by putting pressure on Ukraine to negotiate with Putin.  The Cathaoirleach was there last week.  He knows that Ukraine is winning this war.  Russia is retreating.  Now is not the time to be asking Ukraine to negotiate with an army and country that are losing.  Ukraine will win this war.</p> <p>We have seen even this morning other atrocities in Mariupol, where another mass grave of 200 bodies was found when Ukrainian forces got in there to see these atrocities.  However, Ukraine will win this war if we give it the support it needs, whether that is with weapons or with finances to support it to pay its army, doctors and nurses.  The will and the resilience of those people is phenomenal, and they will win.  It is not the time for us to be saying that they should start talking to Putin. </p> <p>I understand from a European perspective and from an Irish perspective that this war has an effect on our economy, on the cost of living and on prices going up.  However, there is a greater good in giving freedom to people who deserve it and who want to join the European Union.</p> <p>There is another element that we can play in our role as members of the European Union.  A number of neighbouring states of Ukraine, such as Estonia, Lithuania and Latvia, have called what Russia has done as genocide.  However, no western European country has done that yet.  The Cathaoirleach has seen what has happened over there.  What has happened there and what Russia has done is genocide.  Even the conversations that Putin has had can be called genocide.  When one kills mothers and fathers, takes children away into Russia, gives them documentation and passports and tells them they are Russian for the rest of their lives, that is nothing more than genocide.  It is taking away a generation.  The narrative needs to continue, which it has for three months, in support of Ukraine to win this war.  This should not be a time, when they are actually winning to say, "Let us end it".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#U00400"><p>I thank Senators Ahearn and Ward for speaking to what is happening in Ukraine and for their continued work behind the scenes with parliamentarians to make sure that the war is eventually won by the people of Ukraine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#U00500"><p>I spent most of yesterday in the Scottish Parliament as part of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, BIPA.  I was over there for a day or two.  What a wonderful place Edinburgh is and what a wonderful place is their Parliament.  If ever the Cathaoirleach can make it to Scotland and Edinburgh, he should certainly go to the Scottish Parliament.  Its design and everything about the Parliament is amazing.  I would urge everyone to go.  One thing that struck me was the democratisation of the building itself.  The public has free access right through the buildings, the libraries and the reading rooms.  All offices have glazed doors.  The interface with Edinburgh itself is quite an experience.  I recommend everyone to go there.</p> <p>I want to talk today about the focus of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly there, which was to meet with representatives from the Scottish Parliament, as well as representatives from Wales and the UK.  Unfortunately, on this occasion, Northern Ireland was not present because of the current situation there and its representation at the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly.  This was about minority languages and about the islands.  What struck me when talking about it was how much we have in common with the Scottish and Welsh people.  That is something we perhaps did not think enough about in the past.  It is obvious in terms of our relationships with the parliamentarians in Scotland and Wales and also around our engagement of the issue of minority languages and support for them.  The recurring theme that various Ministers spoke about was the issue of how we can protect language in rural communities, such as by favourably disposing towards it in planning and through similar issues. </p> <p>I would like more than anything if we could have a focused debate on the islands of Ireland and the unique challenges that are posed for their culture, identity and language.  Language is so important because it is part of our identity.  We have made great strides regarding the Irish language.  However, this is now being focused on in all of the jurisdictions of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly.  It would also be important that somehow we bring the work of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly into the Chambers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Maybe we could have a report by the members of BIPA, who are Senators, and make time in our schedule to give some account of our work and engagement with the parliaments within the jurisdiction of BIPA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#V00200"><p>I wish to acknowledge the fact that University Hospital Limerick, UHL, and the University of Limerick, UL, are very much involved in clinical trials.  On 19 May, they celebrated Clinical Trials Day.  Clinical trials are so important from a research perspective, especially for very sick children.  I want to acknowledge the work of all involved.  It is really important to say, "Thank you", to the people who are working in this area and to wish them all the best for the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#V00300"><p>I commend the Cathaoirleach on travelling to Ukraine and representing this House.</p> <p>I would like to raise the issue of hormone replacement therapy, HRT.  There has been unprecedented investment in women's health under the current Minister for Health, including the opening of menopause clinics in major urban areas.  There has also been significant public discourse on the menopause, including on "Liveline" and there is now a huge awareness among women of what exactly the menopause entails.  However, with this new information comes massive empowerment and women are now effectively addressing their symptoms head on.  This is leading to severe shortages of HRT products in Ireland and the UK.  Yesterday, the Irish Pharmacy Union, IPU, asked the Minister to amend the rules so that pharmacists can prescribe alternative HRT treatments to address women's menopausal symptoms.  At the moment there is a severe lack of supply of HRT products, in particular, oestregen patches.  The HSE's medicines management programme needs to make it more attractive for pharmaceutical companies to provide HRT to the Irish market.  At the moment, were they to enter the market they would have to sell their products at a 60% loss.  The women of Ireland ultimately need oestrogen but it is not available and they are really worried.  I would like to make sure that this issue is put at the top of the Minister's agenda again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#V00400"><p>Before I call the next speaker, I welcome to the Public Gallery members of Longford Men's Shed and thank them for being here today.  They are accompanied by Deputy Joe Flaherty who will, I am sure, look after them and make sure they see all the Chambers and some of the other rooms that we have available for their enjoyment.  I thank them for coming to Leinster House and to Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  I call Senator Currie.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#V00500"><p>Our guests are very welcome to the Chamber.  It is nice to share it with the public again.</p><p>I want to raise passports and menopause.  The front page of the <i>Irish Independent </i>today tells us that 40% of passport delays are due to errors.  While I accept that there are errors, we must also accept that some delays are not related to errors but are partly due to the enormous volume of passport applications.  A huge amount of work is being done by the Passport Office and the Minister for Foreign Affairs to overcome the delays.  Adult passport renewals are being processed speedily but when it comes to children's first-time or renewals, there can be delays.  What can we do to communicate with people who have holidays booked and who are afraid that they will not get their passports on time?  If people have applied for the wrong passport, whether that be for a renewal instead of a first-time passport or <i>vice versa</i>, is there a way to ensure they do not have to start the process all over again when this is identified?  Sometimes these issues are not being flagged until a passport is about to be issued and then the applicant has to start all over again.  Communication and early detection of issues is key.  People who are living in the North do not have ready access to passport service appointments.  It is &euro;150 for such appointments, which are available in Dublin and Cork.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Emer Currie:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=EmerCurrie&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is nowhere near the North where appointments are available.  I suggest we open a passport office in the north west.</p><p>There was a programme about menopause on RT&Eacute; last night.  If ever there was an example of women being expected to get on with things, it is the menopause.  There is more awareness now but still not enough.  It is a red flag when someone suggests women should not accept the first answer they get and that women must go and seek answers for menopause.  It is about awareness and affordability.  It is also about access to the drugs or hormones that people need.  I am quoting my colleague, Councillor Anna Grainger, when I say there should be a champion in every workplace.  Let this Chamber be a champion for this issue.  I know that Councillor Grainger is such a champion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#W00200"><p>Yesterday, I was invited to attend an Irish Farmers Association, IFA, briefing in Corrofin, County Galway.  It was hosted by Mr. Stephen Canavan, who is the new IFA county chair for Galway.  Now that things are opening up again, we are getting an opportunity to meet people again.  We very much had an opportunity to understand the concerns of farmers at that meeting.  The high costs are hitting home.  Many farmers are not spreading fertiliser, which is causing issues.  Normally farmers spread fertiliser if they are doing a first or second cut but that is not happening because they are not getting fertiliser and are not spreading it.  Some of the reasons come back to what we have heard anecdotally.  Providers, farm suppliers and merchants are not able to provide credit whereas previously, credit would have been made available and farmers would have paid it back when they got their payments in September and October.  That is not happening as often now because costs have risen so high.  The same applies for the farm suppliers themselves.  They are only getting one third of what they would have had for the same cost this time last year.</p> <p>It is having a considerable impact.  Concerns have been raised with me and many of my colleagues who were in attendance at that briefing in Corofin.  We need to ensure that supports are being given to farmers at an early stage.  More than &euro;55 million is coming through for silage measures.  That is a support to ensure there is fodder available in the winter months.  There must also be an onus on how we manage cattle coming into the winter months and follow-on sales of cattle.  It is going to be crucial that we discuss these matters with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, the Minister, Deputy McConalogue, and the Minister of State, Deputy Heydon, and consider how we will ensure immediate supports for farmers in the time ahead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#W00300"><p>Senators Dolan, Murphy and Kyne raised the IFA meeting in Corrofin last night, which outlined the importing costs, the threats to food security, the increase in the cost of fertiliser and the absence of meal.  While Senators have welcomed the supports from the Government, they are looking for a debate on food security and I will organise that in the next week or so.</p> <p>Senator Currie and others talked about passports and highlighted the concerns that were raised in the newspapers this morning.  I can cite my own bizarre experience in that regard.  One of my constituents contacted me on Sunday morning.  Bags were being packed before the family realised the passport of a young adult son in the family was out of date, which caused major panic.  I asked them to make the application online on Sunday and the passport arrived in the post this morning.  When we can get something that right, one would have to reflect on how we still get so many things wrong.  I know the Department is defending the deployment of additional staff of 600 to 900 people, which I welcome.  I have an office in Balbriggan and the passport office is just up the road from me.  I probably spend too much time there, to be honest.  We need to reflect on our communications.  An advertising campaign is required so that we do not have people packing their bags on a Sunday morning and discovering an out-of-date passport.  The communications between the Department and our citizens has to be brought to the attention of the Minister because it is not accurate and it is not working, as reflected in the contributions of the Senators.</p> <p>Senators Currie and Ardagh both talked about the unprecedented demand for hormone replacement therapy.  I believe that is a result of the debate that has happened not only in this Chamber but also on our airwaves in recent years.  That has absolutely made women come forward to say they have an increased awareness and are no longer going to accept being told by doctors or anybody else to just get on with it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is a very welcome change in society but we must be aware that increased awareness was always going to bring about increased demand for the product.  The competitiveness and attractiveness of the Irish market has to be recognised by the Minister and the teams in the medicines agencies.  In a free market, no business will sell its product at a 60% loss compared with other markets.  That is just the reality.  We certainly need to step up to the plate to make sure we make Ireland competitive and attractive for those businesses so we can supply the needs of Irish women.</p><p>Senator Maria Byrne talked about UL, UHL, their progressive attitude towards clinical trials and the success of those trials.  Only the other day, I heard a young lady on the radio who is currently participating in a trial speak about what a positive impact it had on her life, which I had never heard before.  We should probably cite and praise these facilities more for conducting these trials and continue to encourage them.</p><p>Senator Boyhan talked about his trip to the Scottish Parliament with regard to BIPA meetings over the past number of days and has requested a debate on the islands, which I will certainly ask for.  Senator Ahearn spoke about the three-month anniversary of the war in Ukraine and his fears the EU might be putting pressure on the Ukrainians to negotiate as opposed to continuing to support them, which I hope we continue to do.</p><p>Senators Fitzpatrick and Moynihan talked about the report on urban regeneration that has been released and both are looking for a debate on it.  The most obvious thing for all of us, as was cited by the Senators, is to reuse our existing buildings in whatever way, shape or form we can, supported by the Government.  It is certainly the low-hanging fruit and something we should encourage.</p><p>Senator Ward looked for a debate on the genocide happening in China with regard to the Uyghur population.  Yesterday's BBC report made for very stark reading.  I will certainly write to the Minister for Foreign Affairs today and make that a matter for priority.</p><p>Senator Warfield looked for a debate on the Oxfam report on the increased wealth of the billionaires of the world, especially those in Ireland.  I know there are only a few of them but it is hard to see people getting richer when others are struggling so much.  I will certainly arrange that debate as quickly as I can.</p><p>Senator Conway very much welcomed the announcement by the Minister for Health on Friday evening of the catch-up programme for the HPV vaccine.  This very welcome announcement brought to all our social media and news programmes the beautiful face of the late Laura Brennan.  We are all mindful of the significant contribution she has made to women's health in Ireland.  We remember her and praise the legacy she has left behind.</p><p>Senator Murphy not only spoke about the IFA meeting but praised Lisa O'Rourke and Amy Broadhurst.  It must have been a wonderful weekend in Roscommon because it certainly lifted the spirits of most people.  I am reminded of the amount of success Irish female boxers have had in the past year.  It is wonderful to see.  I thank the Senator for bringing that to our attention.</p><p>Senator Moynihan looked for a debate on dereliction in our towns and cities.  The Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Senator Hackett, spoke about her anticipation of, and welcome for, EU just transition funds for climate action in the midlands.</p><p>Senator Gavan spoke about the very successfully attended protest on Saturday, which was good to see.  I will say, tongue-in-cheek, that Prime Minister Boris Johnson will solve this in the next couple of weeks but given we are waiting for the past number of years for it to be solved, I probably do not put much store in that.  I hope there will be success in the negotiations in the coming weeks.  He also spoke about the medical scientists' strike and looked for the Minister for Health to intervene.</p><p>Senator Mullen talked about his support for a debate on food security and also brought to our attention the recent canonisation of Titus Brandsma.  The Senator always brings fascinating information to this Chamber, which is very welcome.  I acknowledge Titus Brandsma stayed in Ireland, with the brothers at Whitefriar Street in Dublin and in Cork, before he left for a tour of America.  He was apparently here to learn how to speak English.  In typical Irish fashion we have to lay claim to every beautiful spirit in the world, but he certainly seemed to be one of them.  I thank the Senator for bringing that to our attention.</p><p>Senator Kyne also looked for a debate on food security but, very importantly, welcomed An Bord Plean&aacute;la's decision to give planning permission for the Celtic interconnector between Ireland and France.  It will certainly improve our energy security but, more important, when our final ambitions are realised for the volume of wind, solar and sea energy we can create in this country, we will be able to sell that energy across the EU, which will be very important.</p><p>Senator Chambers opened our debate by looking for clarification on the national retrofitting scheme.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a wonderful scheme that was announced at the beginning of this year.  It seems to be frustrating insofar as the registration process for all the organisations that had previously supplied the other schemes are finding it frustrating to get on the list.  From our perspective, however, and more importantly, the number of people applying to these one-stop companies and not getting access to the immediate service they expect is causing frustration.<br/><br/>Senator Chambers also congratulated Sally Rooney on her inclusion in <i>Time</i>magazine's 100 most influential people.  We wish her continued success because we are all enjoying the fruits of her talents so far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.74" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.75" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#Y00300">Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(5)) (Variation of title: Chiropodist) Regulations 2022: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#Y00400"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:  	Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(3)) (Variation of title: Chiropodist) Regulations 2022, a copy of which has been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 27th April, 2022, be referred to the Joint Committee on Health, in accordance with Standing Order 71(2)(<i>b</i>), which, not later than 21st June, 2022, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.77" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.78" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 1.56 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 2.15 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 1.56 p.m. and resumed at 2.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.79" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#DD00100">Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022: Committee Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.80" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.81" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Debate resumed on amendment No. 23:</p><p>- (Senator Fintan Warfield)</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#DD00400"><p>We resume the discussion on amendment No. 23.  Amendments Nos. 23 and 24 are physical alternatives.  Amendments Nos. 23, 24, 103, 124 and 125 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  Senator Higgins was in possession.  Does she wish to continue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#DD00500"><p>We had an initial discussion on this in which I highlighted my concerns regarding amendment No. 23.  I said that while I knew there were concerns within the specifics of the proposal put forward by Sinn F&eacute;in colleagues, I explained the understanding and reason people have for not wanting it to be limited, but wanting to name many forms of personal data.  It is from a long record of a minimalist approach to what gets shared, and that is where that very long and comprehensive definition comes in.  I would perhaps urge the Minister, if he is not accepting that amendment, to consider and review the forms of personal information.  It is worth checking that they are, in fact, all covered under other the provisions because I do not believe all of them might be.</p> <p>The other amendments were in respect of the question of the Minister putting in place suitable and specific measures.  At the moment, it is suggested that the Minister may, but there are quite significant powers for processing under the Bill, which I know is necessary for the agency and the Adoption Authority of Ireland, AAI.  Indeed, there are specific clauses in the Bill in terms of curtailment of some of the specific rights under general data protection regulation, GDPR.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It would be appropriate for suitable and specific measures to be set out, as is usually is the case.  As I highlighted, one form of processing is deletion so it is important that the Minister, in empowering the authority and the agency to process data, sets out suitable and specific measures to safeguard the rights of data subjects.  One example of what might go into such measures is a specific provision preventing anything that might constitute excessive redaction, deletion or so forth.  I know that is the Minister's intent but it is important that it be set out in the Bill.</p><p>On amendment No. 125, the Minister has been very clear that it is not his intention that Article 15 rights be constrained by the Bill.  As he has rightly stated, Article 15 does not grant an automatic right to information but a right to request information.  However, as I identified, there are provisions within the Bill that seem a little at odds with that intention.  One I consider important relates to the name of a person who has inquired about someone.  That is the kind of thing a person might make a data subject access request, SAR, about but the Bill explicitly prohibits sharing the name of a person who has made inquiries.  Rather than balancing being done around that request from an individual, the Bill is saying one thing while GDPR rights under Article 15 say a different thing.  This amendment would avoid any lack of clarity by stating that in such a situation a person's right under Article 15 would not be in any way constrained by the provisions in this Bill.  I appreciate that Article 15 is not one of the articles of the GDPR named as being constrained but there are provisions in this Bill that could potentially be at odds with the exercise of Article 15.  That is why it would be appropriate to clarify this, possibly by attaching a simple clause where curtailment has been indicated stating that no other article of GDPR would be constrained by any aspect of this Bill.  We do not want people to have to duke it out between national legislation and European law.  It would be better if that were clarified and the precedence of European law in that case were made clear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#EE00200"><p>We had a lengthy debate on this matter the last day.  I spoke in detail about my concerns regarding amendments Nos. 23 and 24 and the rigidity they would build into the legislation by creating a definition of personal data rather than using one that develops according to the European Convention on Human Rights, ECHR.  I also made known my concerns about amendments Nos. 103, 124 and 125.  I do not have anything else to add.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#EE00300"><p>Is the Minister confident about the conflict I identified previously whereby somebody would have the right to make a data subject access request under Article 15 when seeking information about who may have made inquiries about them?  Is he sure there is no danger of a clash or curtailment in that regard?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#EE00400"><p>I am.  We have been very clear about the GDPR rights that are restricted.  They are set out clearly within the legislation, with the minimal possible restriction that is allowed, and Article 15 is not listed among them so I am confident that the SARs can continue to operate without impingement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FF00100"><p>I apologise if I am delaying matters but we will not have the chance to clarify this in the same way on Report Stage.  If somebody is to make a data subject access request on information and they seek information on who has made inquiries into them during a period of time when they were a child in an institution, is it the case that the provisions of this legislation would not in any way impinge on that person having access to that information so that decision is balanced and made separately?  That is one example but it is an example where the Bill specifically states that the name shall not be shared, whereas under the GDPR people are entitled to seek that information and I am worried that the provisions in the Bill could lead to a blanket interpretation of article 15 of same.  Is the Minister clear that some of these article 15 rights for people to request information about themselves, including information on who has made queries about them when they were children in institutions and the names of such, will be looked at under their article 15 rights and in no way will be referenced or curtailed by the provisions in this Bill?  I see a tension there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FF00200"><p>As the Senator knows, under article 15 the data controller makes an individualised decision.  I cannot speak to individualised decisions but I can speak to the fact that there is no provision within this legislation to place limitation on article 15.  Article 15 is not one of the GDPR articles that is listed as being limited by this Bill.  My understanding is, and it is the intent of the Bill, that article 15 and the processes thereunder, are not limited.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FF00300"><p>We may as well move on to the other sections but it is not really about whether article 15 will be limited.  The question is whether there will be a danger of article 15 being interpreted in relation to this Act, which is slightly different.  There is an article 15 process but you do not want an article 15 process which does not look to each data subject access request but in fact looks to a set of guidance from this legislation.  I addressed this point in that specific section earlier and I will be coming back to that area on Report Stage.  I am extremely concerned by that provision, as I have made clear.  I do not need to put forward all of these amendments but I will probably still look for clarification on article 15.  We carry that debate on to Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.91" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FF00500"><p>I move amendment No. 24:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 12, line 21, to delete &ldquo;Regulation;&rdquo; and substitute the following:  	&ldquo;Regulation. For the avoidance of doubt, personal data as defined under the Regulation includes, in relation to a relevant person under this Act, all records relating to the adoption or informal care arrangement of a relevant person, regardless of whether that data is shared with another person, including but is not limited to:<br /><br />(a) personal data in terms of the relevant person&rsquo;s physical, mental, and physiological identity, including but not limited to: <blockquote> 	(i) the relevant person&rsquo;s place of birth;<br /><br />(ii) details, if applicable, of whether the relevant person was carried to full term, and if not, what precipitated early delivery and at what stage in the pregnancy;<br /><br />(iii) the relevant person&rsquo;s health status at birth;<br /><br />(iv) details regarding the circumstances of the relevant person&rsquo;s birth, e.g. was it a normal birth or if there were complications;<br /><br />(v) the relevant person&rsquo;s birth weight;<br /><br />(vi) the relevant person&rsquo;s physical condition and circumstances during their early months and years;<br /><br />(vii) records concerning the relevant person&rsquo;s early-life care;<br /><br />(viii) records concerning the relevant person&rsquo;s health from birth until the time of placement;<br /><br />(ix) the relevant person&rsquo;s medical records from birth until the time of placement, including x-rays, tests, vaccines;<br /><br />(x) the relevant person&rsquo;s family medical history;<br /><br />(xi) records of any vaccine trials in which the relevant person was a research subject; </blockquote>(b) personal data in terms of the relevant person&rsquo;s genetic identity, including but not limited to: <blockquote> 	(i) the relevant person&rsquo;s name at birth;<br /><br />(ii) the relevant person&rsquo;s birth certificate;<br /><br />(iii) the relevant person&rsquo;s mother&rsquo;s forename and surname, as held in the public Register of Births or equivalent if the relevant person&rsquo;s mother was born outside of Ireland;<br /><br />(iv) the relevant person&rsquo;s father&rsquo;s forename and surname, as held in the public Register of Births or equivalent if the relevant person&rsquo;s father was born outside of Ireland;<br /><br />(v) the relevant person&rsquo;s genetic relatives&rsquo; names, as held in the public Register of Births or equivalent if the relevant person&rsquo;s relative was born outside of Ireland; </blockquote>(c) personal data in terms of the relevant person&rsquo;s economic, cultural and social identity, both before and after their adoption or placement in informal care, relating to their economic, cultural and social identity both around the time of their birth and after their adoption or placement in informal care, and which relate to how the relevant person acquired their adoptive identity, including but<br /><br />not limited to: <blockquote> 	(i) the relevant person&rsquo;s name at birth, as held in the public Register of Births;<br /><br />(ii) the relevant person&rsquo;s date of birth;<br /><br />(iii) the relevant person&rsquo;s place of birth;<br /><br />(iv) the relevant person&rsquo;s mother&rsquo;s forename and surname, as held in the public Register of Births or equivalent if the relevant person&rsquo;s mother was born outside of Ireland;<br /><br />(v) the relevant person&rsquo;s father&rsquo;s forename and surname, as held in the public Register of Births or equivalent if the relevant person&rsquo;s father was born outside of Ireland;<br /><br />(vi) the relevant person&rsquo;s relatives&rsquo; names, as held in the public Register of Births or equivalent if the relevant person&rsquo;s relative was born outside of Ireland;<br /><br />(vii) the relevant person&rsquo;s county/country of origin at the time of their birth;<br /><br />(viii) the occupation of the relevant person&rsquo;s parents and family members at the time of the relevant person&rsquo;s birth;<br /><br />(ix) the relevant person&rsquo;s parents&rsquo; ages at the time of the relevant person&rsquo;s birth;<br /><br />(x) the relevant person&rsquo;s grandparents&rsquo; occupations at the time of the relevant person&rsquo;s birth;<br /><br />(xi) the number of siblings in the immediate family of the relevant person&rsquo;s mother;<br /><br />(xii) the circumstances surrounding the relevant person&rsquo;s adoption or informal care arrangement;<br /><br />(xiii) correspondence about the relevant person, including correspondence associated with the administrative process surrounding the relevant person&rsquo;s adoption or informal care arrangement, and correspondence from the relevant person&rsquo;s mother enquiring about the relevant person;<br /><br />(xiv) the assessment process associated with the relevant person&rsquo;s adoption or informal care arrangement;<br /><br />(xv) the administrative process surrounding the relevant person&rsquo;s adoption or informal placement, including records about the decision-making process around the placement, correspondence with the adoptive parents and others, and how the relevant person acquired their adoptive/new identity;<br /><br />(xvi) the names of the people responsible for the relevant person&rsquo;s care during the relevant person&rsquo;s early weeks, months and years;<br /><br />(xvii) the place at which the relevant person resided and the individual who was in charge of that place;<br /><br />(xviii) where applicable, the date and place of the relevant person&rsquo;s baptism or any other ceremony of a religious or spiritual nature performed in the period in respect of the relevant person;<br /><br />(xix) where applicable, any person, agency or organisation who made arrangements for the relevant person&rsquo;s adoption, whether or not an adoption was effected in respect of the relevant person;<br /><br />(xx) where applicable, the date on which the relevant person was made the subject of a foster care arrangement or placed with prospective adopters;<br /><br />(xxi) information regarding whether the relevant person&rsquo;s mother was resident in any other institution offering social care/support either prior to or subsequent to the adopted person&rsquo;s birth;<br /><br />(xxii) information regarding whether the mother stayed at the institution with the adopted person prior to their placement with the adoptive parents;<br /><br />(xxiii) any anecdotal information regarding the adopted person&rsquo;s stay in the institution;<br /><br />(xxiv) if applicable, whether the relevant person&rsquo;s mother was transferred from the Mother and Baby Home to a Magdalene Laundry or other institution, and if so, details of the circumstances;<br /><br />(xxv) if applicable, whether the relevant person&rsquo;s mother was transferred from a Magdalene Laundry or another institution, to the Mother and Baby Home prior to giving birth and if so, details of the circumstances;<br /><br />(xxvi) whether the relevant person&rsquo;s mother gave informed consent to the adoption;<br /><br />(xxvii) whether the relevant person&rsquo;s mother was made aware of or offered any other choices apart from adoption;<br /><br />(xxviii) whether the relevant person&rsquo;s mother received support after their adoption;<br /><br />(xxix) any letters, cards or other materials placed on the adoption file(s) by the relevant person&rsquo;s mother;<br /><br />(xxx) any letters, cards or other materials placed on the adoption file(s) by the relevant person&rsquo;s father or other relatives;<br /><br />(xxxi) any letters, cards or other materials placed on the adoption file(s) by the relevant person&rsquo;s adoptive parents;&rdquo;. </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.93" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FF00700"><p>I move amendment No. 25:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 13, line 14, after &ldquo;incorrect&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or illegal&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.95/1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FF00750"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 8; Níl, 23.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Alice-Mary Higgins and Fintan Warfield; Níl, Senators Seán Kyne and Lisa Chambers..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.95/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2022-05-24" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FF00750">
            <divisioncount ayes="8" noes="23" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" vote="aye">Alice-Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" vote="aye">Annie Hoey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" vote="aye">Marie Sherlock</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" vote="no">Malcolm Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" vote="no">Miche&aacute;l Carrigy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" vote="no">Pat Casey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" vote="no">Lisa Chambers</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" vote="no">Lorraine Clifford-Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" vote="no">John Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" vote="no">Emer Currie</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" vote="no">Regina Doherty</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" vote="no">Timmy Dooley</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" vote="no">Mary Fitzpatrick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" vote="no">Pippa Hackett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" vote="no">Se&aacute;n Kyne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" vote="no">Eugene Murphy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" vote="no">Mary Seery Kearney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" vote="no">Barry Ward</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.95/3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FF00750"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#KK00100"><p>Amendments Nos. 26 to 28, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#KK00200"><p>I move amendment No. 26:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 14, between lines 9 and 10, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(j) any person or organisation involved in facilitating adoptions, or family separation;&rdquo;.  </blockquote> <p>Amendments Nos. 26 to 28, inclusive, all refer to expanding the definition of &quot;secondary information source&quot;.  Currently, there is a list of various Departments, registered adoption societies and other accredited bodies included and there is provision for the Minister to prescribe separate persons, but I believe there are wider categories that should be considered.</p><p>Amendment No. 26 suggests, &quot;any person or organisation involved in facilitating adoptions, or family separation&quot; should be defined and should be considered as a secondary information source.  The reason it is better to do that in the legislation rather than by prescribing is that it would be potentially over-onerous for the Minister to be expected to prescribe under section 43(2) every time and in every instance of where there are persons who have played a role in facilitating adoptions or family separation.  We know, for example, that there were persons who were not in a formal role with a registered adoption society but who effectively acted as brokers in respect of incorrect or illegal adoptions and, indeed, there were those who facilitated the separation of families.  The fact of those actions should be sufficient to be considered a relevant information source, rather than simply the fact that one has been designated as such.  The actions themselves make the person relevant in terms of the information the person may hold.</p><p>Amendment No. 27 is very important.  Relevant religious orders should be considered as secondary information sources.  At present, it is only registered adoption societies or accredited bodies, but many religious orders played a key role.  It is the case that while one branch of a religious order may have been in a particular role in running an institution, the religious order as a whole may hold very important information including, potentially, financial information that is relevant.  In that context, relevant religious orders or religious orders that have been in any way involved in the processes of adoption, regardless of whether they are registered adoption societies or accredited bodies, should be included.</p><p>Amendment No. 28 is also quite important.  It proposes &quot;relevant psychiatric institutions&quot; to be included in the definition of &quot;secondary information source&quot;.  In some cases, children who ended up in these institutions had mothers who were incarcerated in psychiatric institutions.  We know many cases of this where women, especially those women who may have strongly resisted or fought back against certain processes that were under way in institutions, faced a threat in respect of psychiatric institutions.  It was one of the parts in the very large architecture of control that the State exercised against women.</p><p>One of the worst stories I have heard is of a woman, who is now living in the UK and who came back here and spoke to me about it, discovering that her mother had been attributed as having post-natal depression and had been put into an institution - I think it was Grangegorman - and had stayed there for the rest of her life.  Her daughter was not even aware that her mother was alive but, in fact, that mother had been incarcerated in a psychiatric institution ever since that woman's birth.  The woman had come to talk about the memorials.  It is an example of where we cannot have sections of an architecture of control where the information trail would dry up in terms of secondary information sources.  That is why relevant psychiatric institutions should be identified as relevant secondary information sources for the purposes of the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#LL00100"><p>I cannot accept these amendments, which seek to add to the list of secondary information sources provided for in the legislation, primarily because they do not define what they are intended to cover with the clarity and specificity required in the legislation.</p> <p>I will draw attention to the secondary information sources currently included in the Bill, which are: the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth; the Minister for Education; the Minister for Foreign Affairs; the Minister for Health; the data controller of the access to institutional and related records project, AIRR, archive; the Health Service Executive; a registered adoption society; an accredited body; and a person prescribed under section 43(2).  That last category is incredibly important because, as broad as those initial categories are and while they have been designed to cover those sources we know to hold information at the moment, section 43(2) gives the Minister of the day an additional degree of flexibility and allows him or her to prescribe additional information sources.  As I have said, the list currently included in the published Bill, which I have just cited, was carefully considered following consultation with stakeholders and organisations currently operating in the area of adoption, information release and training.  In progressing this legislation, it has been my goal for it to focus on where we know records are at the moment to ensure access can be provided to those records as quickly as possible.  However, the legislation also provides an avenue to allow access to other sources of information, should any be identified.  </p> <p>In light of that, it is important to also recognise section 46, which is another catch-all provision requiring any person or organisation in possession of a relevant record to safeguard that record and to inform the authority that it holds it.  This allows the record to either be taken over immediately by the authority or for that person to be designated as a secondary information source.  The Bill therefore obliges individuals or bodies holding relevant information to come forward and identify themselves, allowing use to be made of the designation element of section 43(2).</p> <p>With regard to the broad ambit of information, I looked into the issue of the application of the GDPR and freedom of information legislation to psychiatric and other health institutions and these do apply.  A subject access request can be made to a psychiatric institution or an organisation that now holds records, including the HSE.  Where records are held by the HSE, they are also subject to freedom of information requests.  </p> <p>In the context of this legislation, of knowing, as we do, where those key sources of information are, of wanting to provide access to that information now, and of having those catch-all elements, including the obligation on holders of relevant records to identify themselves to the authority, and the ability of a future Minister to designate a body or individual as a secondary information source under section 43(2), I believe that the architecture in place to ensure access is given now to information is sufficient and that we have mechanisms available to us should other sources be revealed in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#LL00200"><p>I appreciate that the Minister has the power to designate but I am concerned that he, or whichever other Minister down the line, may choose not use that power.  There is no guarantee for the Oireachtas or the Seanad that the Minister will, in fact, designate religious orders or psychiatric institutions.  I am concerned that the tone of the Minister's response seems to suggest a kind of prioritisation with regard to the sources we know are relevant and so forth.  There is going to be a large volume to deal with and it may well be the case that there is so much to be engaged with in respect of the secondary information sources named that those other information sources, which are important, fall down the list.  In that context, I am conscious that time is pressing in respect of some or many of these records.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We cannot afford a staggered or tiered approach.  We need to get as much information from as many sources into the public domain as quickly as possible.  In terms of the psychiatric institutions, we know that they were used in that regard.  The wording I have proposed may be too loose.  I accept that the wording of amendment No. 26 is quite wide, but I tried to be quite specific in amendments Nos. 27 and 28.  What guarantee do we have that the Minister will designate religious orders or psychiatric institutions as relevant secondary sources?  Effectively, by putting the word "relevant" in the amendment, I tried to give a discretion to the Minister, but if he believes it needs to be worded differently so that it gives an explicit direction, then the reference could, for example, state that the Minister shall designate religious orders and psychiatric institutions as relevant on an ongoing basis.  He could bring in something like that, because what we need is a guarantee that these parts of the puzzle will not fall out and disappear.  With absolute respect in terms of the obligation to let the authority know it has records, that is a very sweeping provision, but which does not really have consequences.  We are absolutely aware that people - I will not mention any individual religious order - but religious orders specifically have been very careful in the guarding of their information.  In many cases they have been very reluctant to share it.  I do not see a rush for them to transfer any records that they may have without good cause or without being in fact required to do so.  That is why it is important that there would be a reference to them.</p><p>We know, for example, that a significant number of adoptions were not through registered adoption bodies.  The whole concern is that so much of it was done in an informal way and by persons not qualified or properly doing so.  I am worried that there are going to be holes in terms of the secondary information.  We should be using the tools that are in this Bill, which are quite good tools, in terms of clearly requiring secondary information services to engage and making clear what the relationship between the authority and the agency is with those secondary information services.  I believe that religious orders that were involved in adoption, whether as registered bodies or not, formally or informally, legally or illegally, should be considered secondary information sources.  I also believe that psychiatric institutions, insofar as psychiatric institutions engaged with other parts of that architecture, be it mother and baby homes or similar institutions, should be considered as secondary information sources.  For example, it is not everything relating to a psychiatric institution, but it is relevant psychiatric institutions insofar as they hold relevant records.  That is appropriate.  I accept that amendment No. 26 is worded quite broadly.  That was an attempt to capture that informal space, the brokers and those who were not employed by anybody but nonetheless facilitated family separations in local areas around Ireland.  Amendments Nos. 27 and 28 are quite specific.  I would like to know if the Minister intends to designate religious orders and psychiatric institutions as secondary sources of information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MM00200"><p>The impression could be given here that religious orders involved in the provision of adoption are not somehow covered.  It is important to be absolutely clear here.  A registered adoption society and an accredited body are both covered, so any religious institution or organisation that is either an accredited body or a registered adoption society is fully covered by this legislation.  I would hate for the impression to go out, based on the tenor of this debate, that there is some great gap here.  There is no great gap here.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Those religious organisations that were accredited, and those involved in those institutions that were accredited organisations, are covered by this legislation.  That is important.</p><p>In terms of what I, or any other Minister, might do in the future, I can say that if at any point it is shown to me that there is a gap in the coverage of the legislation and that it is denying people access to relevant records, I would be very happy to act and to use the provisions of this legislation to fill that gap.  Where it is clear that there is a gap, I will act to fill it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#NN00200"><p>I made it quite clear that my concern is where it is informal and where people are not registered, etc.  That is the concern about where gaps arise.  It is in relation to those who are not in the space of the registered adoption society or of accredited bodies.  I would put it to the Minister that there is a gap, even in the example of psychiatric institutions that I have given to him.  It is in that context that I suggest, rather than waiting to address such a gap under section 43(2), and rather than putting a burden on those who are seeking relevant information to have to identify what they do not know, it would be better for the Minister to provide for such in the legislation.</p> <p>I am happy to reserve my position in order for it to be clarified whether all religious orders are to be covered under the accredited body provision.  If the Minister has further information on that, I would be happy to wait and to address that on Report Stage.  However, it is my understanding that they would not all be fully covered by that.  It may be the case that the majority is.</p> <p>In the case of the psychiatric institutions, the Minister asked where there are gaps and I am informing him that it is a gap.  In that context, I may reserve my right to come back to amendments Nos. 26 and 27, if the Minister can provide information to clarify how religious orders are covered under section 2(1)(g), "a registered adoption society", and section 2(1)(h), "an accredited body", where they are not covered by section 2(1)(g) and section 2(1)(h) and what aspects of their work are not covered by section 2(1)(g) and section 2(1)(h). </p> <p>In relation to the psychiatric institutions, I will have to press that amendment because I really believe this is a gap.  It was part of a whole architecture of fear and control that women faced in Ireland.  It was not only women who were in these institutions, but also women in other parts of Irish society.  These institutions were one of the ways that it was ensured that choice and options were removed from women.  It was one of the tools in relation to forced adoption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.104" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#NN00600"><p>I move amendment No. 27:</p> <blockquote> 	&ldquo;In page 14, between lines 9 and 10, to insert the following:   	&ldquo;(j) a relevant religious order;&rdquo;.&rdquo;  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.106" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#NN00800"><p>I move amendment No. 28:</p> <blockquote> 	&ldquo;In page 14, between lines 9 and 10, to insert the following:   	&ldquo;(j) relevant psychiatric institutions;&rdquo;.&rdquo;  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.108/1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#NN00850"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 9; Níl, 25.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Alice-Mary Higgins and Annie Hoey; Níl, Senators Seán Kyne and Lisa Chambers..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.108/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2022-05-24" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#NN00850">
            <divisioncount ayes="9" noes="25" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" vote="aye">Frances Black</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" vote="aye">Lynn Boylan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" vote="aye">Alice-Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" vote="aye">Annie Hoey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" vote="aye">Marie Sherlock</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" vote="no">Malcolm Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" vote="no">Miche&aacute;l Carrigy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" vote="no">Lisa Chambers</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" vote="no">Ollie Crowe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" vote="no">John Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" vote="no">Emer Currie</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" vote="no">Regina Doherty</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" vote="no">Aisling Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" vote="no">Timmy Dooley</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" vote="no">Mary Fitzpatrick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" vote="no">Pippa Hackett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" vote="no">Se&aacute;n Kyne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" vote="no">Eugene Murphy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" vote="no">Mary Seery Kearney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" vote="no">Barry Ward</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.108/3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#NN00850"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#QQ00200"><p>I move amendment No. 29:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 14, line 13, after &ldquo;incorrect&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;or illegal&rdquo;. </blockquote> <p>I withdraw the amendment and reserve the right to reintroduce it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.110" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.111" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Section 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.112" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sections 3 and 4 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.113" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>SECTION 5</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#QQ00700"><p>I move amendment No. 30:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 14, line 36, to delete &ldquo;in respect of which&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;regardless of whether&rdquo;. </blockquote> <p>This amendment is around the insertion of additional institutions.  I am slightly widening the provision by replacing &quot;in respect of which&quot; with &quot;regardless of whether&quot; a public body has or had a regulatory or inspection function.  The Minister's powers to add an additional institution should not be constrained by whether a public body had a regulatory or inspection function.  There may be institutions the Minister deems appropriate to add even they did not have that function.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am concerned that there is at present a constraint on the Minister's powers in respect of the addition of institutions.  Our amendment would widen it out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#RR00200"><p>During the discussions on this, including some of the informal consultations my officials and I did, this issue was raised.  At the time, we in the Department said we were confident that all institutions that we know to have been involved in adoptions, touching on the issue of illegal birth registrations, were subject to regulation or inspection by a public body and, as such, would be covered within the existing definitions.  At the time, we asked whether there were specific examples and whether there was X or Y institution that would not fall within this definition and, to my knowledge, no clear example of the existing definition failing to cover an institution involved has been provided.  I am of the view, therefore, that we have a clear definition that covers all bodies involved in this area.  If Senator Higgins has a clear example of something we are missing, I am open to considering it, but I think this is a solid and all-encompassing definition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#RR00300"><p>The concern is that, in the past, if an institution or public body did not adopt or perform a regulatory or inspection function, it could end up slipping out.  I will reserve the right to come back to this on Report Stage.  In general, it would be better to provide in the Bill the widest possible scope rather than relying on persons having to prove the exceptions to the rule because we have had many years of that.  That is why in many of the provisions we are putting forward we are going wide.  Yes, there is the risk of going slightly wider than is necessary, but it is a lesser risk than the risk of going more narrowly than is necessary.  That is why we should err on the side of an encompassing power.  Again, this does not bring in every institution; it just gives the scope to a Minister to provide for institutions to be brought in.  The Minister mentioned people bringing cases to him but, at the moment, under the legislation, if people bring an example to him or a future Minister whereby the institution or public body did not have a regulatory or inspection function, the Minister is not empowered to bring in that institution.  Therefore, if an example emerges, the legislation does not empower the Minister to include it on the list of institutions.  It is to be hoped that that gap will not emerge, but the Bill as drafted constraints the Minister.  Again, in these amendments we are seeking as wide a provision as possible.  If that wider provision were not required by a Minister, that would be fine, but it would be better to make a wide provision.  Again, it is a matter of the maximalist versus the minimalist approach and the culture shift around the whole process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.118" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.119" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Section 5 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.120" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#RR00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 31 to 46, inclusive, 49 to 53, inclusive, and 71 are related.  Amendment No. 32 is a physical alternative to amendment No. 31.  Amendments Nos. 42 to 46, inclusive, are physical alternatives to amendment No. 41.  Amendments Nos. 31 to 46, inclusive, 49 to 53, inclusive, and 71 may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#RR00800"><p>It is not agreed.  Amendments Nos. 33 to 39, inclusive, 43 to 46, inclusive, and 49 to 51, inclusive, are all consequential on and related to amendment No. 69.  I wonder, therefore-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00100"><p>I am working from the information that I get from the Bills Office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00200"><p>We are discussing amendments that are consequential on an amendment that has not been discussed yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00300"><p>That is not the opinion of the Bills Office clearly because it would not suggest that grouping otherwise.  Everyone else is in agreement with the groupings.  We can revisit amendment No. 69 later but are we happy to take the grouping as it is for now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00400"><p>Sure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00500"><p>Okay.  I thank the Senator.  We move to amendment No. 31 in Senator Warfield's name.  He is in a position to discuss his own amendment and also the others in the group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00600"><p>The process does not get any easier, does it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00700"><p>I acknowledge that it is quite a big group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00800"><p>I move amendment No. 31:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 15, between lines 8 and 9, to insert the following:<br /><br />&ldquo;<b>6</b>. An tArd-Chl&aacute;raitheoir shall on an application made by a relevant person, a record of whose birth is kept by An tArd-Chl&aacute;raitheoir and who has reached the age of 16 years, supply to that person on payment of the prescribed fee (if any) such information as is necessary to enable that person to obtain a certified copy of the record of his or her birth.&rdquo;. </blockquote> <p>We propose a new section 6, that would replace sections 6 to 8, inclusive.  The amendments would ensure that when an application is made to the Minister, the Minister would furnish a person with information as necessary to enable that person to obtain a certified copy of the record of his or her birth.</p><p>We are opposing section 7.  It relates to restrictive timeframes.  We believe it is arbitrary and contradictory.  The Bill defines early life and care information as the information gathered from birth up until 18 years but section 2 states that a person's early life and care information only covers the period after the birth until the time that he or she was adopted.  One might say that early life and care information will not be available on files from the time that the child is adopted but we believe this is not the case.  Records were created long after adoption.  The same points would apply to section 8.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#SS00900"><p>The Labour Party's substantive amendment is amendment No. 68 which Senator Higgins mentioned.  That will be dealt with separately.  We tabled amendments Nos. 33 to 40, inclusive, which precede amendment No. 68 which is the substantive amendment.  These deal with the mandatory information session which is the big sticking point for the Labour Party.  We are disappointed that we did not see progress made on this in the D&aacute;il.  My colleague, Deputy Bacik, had a full debate with the Minister on Committee Stage and on the floor of the D&aacute;il.  I want to acknowledge how much progress was made on other issues on Committee Stage and in the D&aacute;il.  We all appreciate the improvements that have been made to the Bill but this is still a difficult area for us and for those seeking information.  It means that access to birth information remains conditional in certain cases on the holding of this information session.</p> <p>The Minister has spoken at the committee and in the D&aacute;il of the need to balance information rights and privacy rights but we feel the retention of the mandatory information session means that privacy rights continue to trump identity rights.  During pre-legislative scrutiny the committee unanimously recommended an alternative to a mandatory information session as a safeguard to ensure the balance of rights would be to send an appropriate statement by registered post.  Amendment No. 68 crafts a mechanism whereby such a statement could be sent by the authority setting out the relevant matters in writing to a person seeking information.  We believe this would be a sufficient safeguard along with other safeguards in the legislation such as the information campaign, the contact preference register and the age limit to ensure that these constitutional rights are balanced.  We think it would be a more practical mechanism because it would ensure that there could be no dispute as to what was said and whether a Zoom call or another type of meeting had in fact taken place.  It would also show trust in the people who were seeking this information that they would receive this statement and that it would be sufficient.</p> <p>We looked at section 17 to see what the Government proposes as a safeguard.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Annie Hoey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AnnieHoey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The information session need not be in one place, but it requires that each participant be able directly or by means of electronic communications technology to speak and to be heard by the other participants.  Section 17(2) sets out the relevant information about which the designated person is to inform the adopted person seeking the information.</p><p>We are not entirely clear why this information could not be simply set out in a written statement and be sent by registered post so that there is proof that it has been received, particularly when section 17(4) requires the designated person, on completion of the information session, to confirm that it has taken place and to provide notification.  As the Government has already proposed a mechanism for a written statement, I do not understand why we do not just bypass the mandatory information session and bypass this condition on access of information as the committee recommended.  We should end this rather paternalistic approach that requires an information session and instead simply send it by registered post.  We do this with summonses and other important legal documents.  I believe there is general cross-party agreement that this would be a far preferable method of informing somebody and it would mean that there would be no condition on access.</p><p>I ask for clarification on a point.  What happens if adopted persons will not take the Zoom call or meet the designated person?  My understanding is that they would not get access to information.  I believe that they would need to go through a request via GDPR.  I ask the Minister to verify that.  If it is the case, it seems extremely onerous that they would need to use separate legislation to access their information.  This is a condition upon access to information which I believe is against the spirit of the Bill.  Otherwise, the provisions of the Bill are very inclusive.  We would like to see a change to the stated patriarchal culture.  We think the required information session is a hangover of that.  Amendment No. 68 is the substantive piece.  There was cross-party agreement on this during the pre-legislative scrutiny and in the D&aacute;il.  We think it is patriarchal and unnecessary.  If it is good enough for court summonses and other legal requirements, I do not understand why this information needs to be by a phone call or in-person as opposed to by registered post.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#TT00200"><p>This grouping contains a few amendments.  I think I support the amendment on age proposed by Senator Warfield.  It relates to other amendments we have discussed to ensure that information can be accessed as early as possible.  Persons who are 16 years of age should be able to have those records.  That could be very important to a person coming up to that age of 18 when people make many choices about their lives.  It also allows them to access that relevant information at a time when they have access to various relevant supports.  I believe it is a constructive amendment.</p><p>Our amendment No. 32 relates to section 6(4) which simply provides that if the body finds no entry on the register of births, it shall in writing inform the applicant of that fact.  Our amendment suggests that that is not good enough as an ending point to state it does not have the birth certificate.  The amendment proposes:</p> <blockquote> 	Where no birth information is available, the Authority shall seize all records relating to the relevant person&rsquo;s adoption and/or illegal [I am open to having that changed to &quot;incorrect or illegal&quot;] birth registration and open an investigation into what transpired.  The relevant person will be kept informed and will be consulted throughout the course of the investigation. </blockquote> <p>We have set out a process there, but I am open to other versions of the process that the Minister might propose.  To simply get a note saying &quot;We do not have a birth certificate for you&quot; is inadequate.  If there is no birth certificate, that is an issue which requires investigation.  We have suggested one version of follow-up action.  I would like the Minister to outline what should happen next if the relevant body does not have the birth certificate.  It is not enough to just be told that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The State has a responsibility to investigate and follow up.</p><p>I will speak now to a number of the other amendments - Senator Hoey has already spoken on them - that are consequential on amendment No. 69.  The latter seeks to reflect the recommendation of the committee and the concerns that many had addressed in the context of the information session, as required.  I acknowledge that there has been some evolution from where matters stood in 2017.  At that point, far worse proposals had been put forward.  However, there is still the issue of this information session, which would only apply to persons who had been subject to adoption, as well as in the context of to persons about whom relevant entries had been made in the contact preference register.  Effectively, this means that these individuals are being treated differently from any other person in the State who is entitled to get his or her birth certificate.  It is their right and they are the same as any other person.  A different obstacle is being put in their way, however.  They are being treated differently.  This is treating differently the people who will seek access to their birth certificates under the Bill.</p><p>The proposals tabled by Deputy Bacik and others in the D&aacute;il were very constructive.  I say this because it moved to a situation whereby people were being the given information as to the purposes for which the information was being given to them.  However, they were not being given an information session.  The information was to be provided to all applicants.  It was simply a case that information was to be delivered.  It was not the case that there was to be a session or even a phone call.  The Minister has stated that this is now to be done via a phone call and that it will not be an in-person session.  However, this feeds into a feeling that many people who have been adopted have had about the perception of them that has been reflected back by the State and its institutions, including Tusla and others, over many years.  This reflection is that they are somehow dangerous, that they are less capable of understanding the normal laws of the land than anybody else and that they need to be treated differently.  It sends that message of that they are to be treated differently.  That is why I thought that there should be simple provision of information.</p><p>Information and tracing are two different concepts.  One person might seek just their birth certificate information.  However, another might have preferences in respect of tracing or contact.  That will involve slightly different information.  Anybody who gets his or her birth certificate will be getting it as information.  It will not be a ticket to contact or to tracing.  That is the norm already under the GDPR.  In that context, I do not see why this additional provision would be needed.  It muddies the waters.  We will come to amendments Nos. 68 and 69, which propose different approaches to how that might be addressed, later.</p><p>A constructive amendment has been tabled by the Labour Party Senators regarding the use of registered post.  We have also tabled amendments to section 17 which would make persons aware of the fact that when they get information for particular purposes - that is, as for a person's information about their identity - it does not automatically mean that this information can be used for other purposes.  That is a general provision which could be applied to anybody.</p><p>Amendments Nos. 33 to 37, inclusive, are related to amendment No. 69.  The latter would remove section 7, which provides for the information session.  Amendments Nos. 33 to 27, inclusive, are consequential because they would remove from the Bill other references to an obligatory information session.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Amendment No. 37 is slightly different.  It is another consequential amendment to amendment No. 69.  It relates to section 8, however, which makes provision for birth certificates to be provided to relevant applicants who are aged between 16 and 18 years old.  It also specifies that access to certain kinds of information, including birth certificates, is conditional on the information attending the mandatory information session.  </p><p>Amendment No. 38 is also consequential to amendment No. 69.  It addresses these provisions in section 8.  Amendment No. 39 is another consequential amendment, which seeks to address the provisions in sections 7 and 8.  These amendments are consequential from the provisions in those sections and from the amendments that we propose to make to those sections.  Amendment No. 40 is similarly a consequential amendment.  </p><p>Amendment No. 42 would replace the word "may" with "shall" in respect of the release of a statement.  This refers to where a relevant body may release a statement to a relevant person that would set out his or her birth information.  I appreciate that the word "shall" is used in relation to records in the previous provision.  I appreciate that and it is good that the word "shall" is used.  However, although the word "shall" is used, the caveat of "to the extent that it is practicable to do so" is attached.  We will come back to that issue when it comes up again.  The word "shall" is used in terms of the release of the records, but the word "may" is used in relation to the release of a statement.  The Minister might clarify why that is.  In general, our preference is for the use of the word "shall" throughout the Bill, wherever that is possible.  </p><p>I apologise that my contribution is long, but this is a large grouping of amendments.  Amendment No. 43 is another consequential amendment to amendment No. 69.  There are numerous references to this "information session" throughout the Bill.  It has been a piece of work to remove it.  We believe that there are multiple better ways of addressing these issues and that there should not be discriminatory treatment of persons who have been adopted when they seek to access their birth certificates.  </p><p>Amendment No. 44 is similarly a consequential amendment.  Amendment No. 45 is a consequential amendment which seeks to amend the current provision around access to birth information.  It also relates to section 9.  Amendment No. 46 is a consequential amendment.  Amendment No. 49 is a consequential amendment and it relates to section 10.  Amendment No. 50 is also a consequential amendment and it also relates to section 10.  Amendment No. 51 is a consequential amendment to amendment No. 69 that also relates to section 10.  </p><p>Amendment No. 53 proposes to insert a new section that would seek to create a mechanism whereby a relevant person could request all of his or her relevant records from a body.  This is one example of what we believe would be a more constructive approach to persons being able to access their information.  It would address an issue that is present in the Bill with how the mechanism for requesting records is set up.  It seems at the moment that a high threshold of specificity and knowledge is required on the part of the applicant when he or she is requesting their records.  In the past, the burden has been placed on individuals to navigate a difficult and sometimes hostile system.  This Bill is meant to be the sea change.  Yet, at the moment, there still is quite an onus put on the person who is seeking the information to know almost exactly what it is he or she is looking for.  It is almost the old thing of, "If you do not know, then I will not tell you".  That should not be the case for persons who are seeking information, if indeed we want to take a maximalist rather than a minimalist approach.</p><p>The Bill as it stands sets out specific categories of information that may be requested.  That is fine when the applicant is familiar with the legislation and when he or she knows what to request.  However, there is the potential that an applicant would not know what to ask for, that he or she might not be subject to legal advice and that he or she may not be experts in legislation.  They could effectively end up not getting access to records that are extremely pertinent to them.  </p><p>Currently, the Bill has a distinct section to deal with applications for birth and early life information.  It has another distinct section on the application for medical records.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Within these sections, it is stipulated that a relevant body may provide information to which the application relates: that is, if people request their medical information, they will be provided only with that, despite the fact that the relevant body may hold additional records and the applicant may not be aware of that.  However, there should be a mechanism whereby applicants can simply request any and all records that a relevant body holds on them, which is again realistic because many applicants will not be familiar with the terminology or definitions of "early life information" versus "care information" and may not know what to ask for.  In that case, there should be a provision whereby persons can just ask for all records available to them without having to specify the categories.  It should be sufficient that applicants can indicate their desire to receive all records held about them, and that request should be granted by the relevant body in the widest interpretation.</p><p>This amendment would insert a new section, which would say a person can apply for any and all records and that a relevant body on an application made should to all the extent that is practicable, provide the relevant person with all relevant records.  Where a relevant body receives an application and does not hold relevant records, it shall inform the person of that fact.  This is a wide provision piece.</p><p>I will come to amendments later whereby if people apply for one strand of information about them, they should be at least informed that there are other strands of information about them, which they can then seek to access as well.  That is another way we try to come at this same problem.  This is the wide, all-encompassing provision and the other is to create arrows that would guide people if they applied under one of the strands, so that they would know there are other strands of information.  What we do not want is that people simply tick the wrong box and do not get the full information.  I know that is not what the Minister would want either.  That was amendment No. 53.</p><p>Amendment No. 71 deals with a caveat in the Bill if section 17 is to be maintained.  We have provisions which remove the information session and replace it with a written communication.  Amendment No. 71 states that if the information session is maintained, relevant persons should be able to elect to receive written correspondence in its place.  Section 17 currently provides that in order to access certain information, an applicant must attend an information session with a designated person.  The provision is hugely problematic.  As we have heard, it makes access to certain information, including birth certificates, conditional.  It is a red-line issue for many of the survivor and stakeholder groups.  The Minister will be aware of that, as it has been debated extensively both in the committee and in the D&aacute;il.  However, if the Minister does not prove amenable to the removal of the information session from the Bill, we believe there should at a minimum be a provision where a person can decline to attend an information session and can instead receive information in the post.  It is slightly different from the registered post, which again is just sent out and somebody receives it.  This would be a situation whereby there is engagement from the relevant persons.  They have shown that they are engaging, and they have said they would prefer to receive the information in this different format.  The very fact of that engagement and request being given a proper weighting, means that there is confidence that people are going to receive the information in a written form because they have requested to receive it in a written form.</p><p>I do not think amendment No. 71 is ideal, but it is a provision which at least does not put persons for whom this is difficult, people who feel very upset about how they have been treated, in a position where they are obliged to attend the information session or not access the information.  There is some way that they can register that they want to receive it another way.  We do not want to have a position where people are refusing to attend an information session on principle and, as a consequence, they would not get access to the information, in particular in terms of the birth certificate, given that it is something every other person in the State can access freely.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I do not think amendment No. 71 is ideal, but it at least provides an option for persons for whom attendance at an information session could potentially prove somewhat traumatising.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#XX00200"><p>I thank Senators for their contributions.  What we are discussing here gets fundamentally to the centre of what this legislation is trying to achieve, which is that for the very first time in Irish history, adopted people, people who were boarded out and people who were subject to an illegal birth registration would have an automatic right to their full birth, early life care, medical information and a birth certificate.  For the first time, that cannot be denied to them.  It will not be redacted and their right to that information will not be undermined in any way.  That is what this legislation is trying to do.</p> <p>In order to do that, this legislation recognises that in the provision of that identity information - the constitutional right to their identity for adopted people - it does in some circumstances involve a restriction on the right of another person, the right of parents who do not wish their identity to be known to the child that they gave up for adoption.  These are two fundamental rights, both springing from Article 40.3.2&deg; of the Constitution, both unenumerated rights - a constitutional right to privacy and a constitutional right to identity information.  For too long, Irish law has prioritised the parent's right to privacy over the adopted person's right to his or her identity.  This legislation seeks to reverse that, to almost entirely change it, and to put the protection of rights on the right to identity.  Everyone in this House and in the other House is agreed that is the approach that should be taken.</p> <p>In Irish law, when the Oireachtas takes a decision to balance constitutionally protected rights, in particular when the Oireachtas takes a decision to elevate one constitutional right over another, to give one constitutional right preference over another, a process must be undertaken in the legislation.  That is what we are doing.  We should be clear about that.  We are prioritising the constitutional right of adopted people to their identity over the constitutional right of some parents to their privacy.  We must understand that for some parents, perhaps a very small number, but that does not matter because even if it is just one, we are dealing with a parent's constitutional rights, that is a traumatic experience as well.</p> <p>In order to do that, our legislation has to demonstrate that we have considered both sets of rights and that we have put a balance or mechanism in place in terms of how that prioritisation of the identity rights over the privacy rights is done.  This is what we are seeking to achieve in this section.  There are different views in terms of what is the best way of balancing the privacy rights and the right to identity in the legislation.  In group 11 we will talk about some of the other options.</p> <p>This speaks to some of the opposition to this section by Sinn F&eacute;in.  Fundamentally, if there is not some element of balancing of the rights in this legislation, it is at high risk of being found to be unconstitutional and, as such, at risk of being struck down and we would be back in the same place again where adopted people have no rights to their information.  This legislation guarantees the full release of information under the processes set out: the full release of unredacted information.  It does so after a balancing process has taken place.  That is why we are speaking of this issue.</p> <p>What has been identified, after detailed analysis, is the idea of an information session or call, where in a very small minority of circumstances, where a parent has proactively sought to register a no-contact preference on the contact preference register, that will be conveyed to the adopted person via a phone call.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Once that telephone call has taken place, the full release of information can take place.  We believe this is the best way to vindicate the constitutional right to privacy of the parent who has sought to protect that right by entering a no-contact preference in the contact preference register.  It is about how to balance that right, but at the same time ensure that every adopted person gets full access to all the information in an unredacted manner.  We can perhaps speak later about the alternative methods others have brought forward on this issue.</p><p>Senator Hoey asked about what happens if an adopted person seeks not to use the provisions of this legislation, including the provision on an information call if a parent has indicated a no-contact preference.  If someone chooses not to use the process of this legislation, he or she still has the option of using general data protection regulation, GDPR, and making a subject access request.  In that situation, the data controller will make a determination on the release of the information.  However, it is important to recall the reason we are bringing forward this legislation is that the answer to somebody using this legislation will always be the full release of all information whereas in a GDPR situation, the data controller must assess the rights of the person making the application and balance those against the rights of other persons.  There could be circumstances in which the data controller prioritises the rights of other persons.  Someone can continue to use the GDPR process, however, and those rights continue to sit alongside this legislation.  We should reflect, of course, that this idea of the information session and information call is a process that was put forward previously by Senator Hoey's party in 2017 in terms of a good way to reach that balancing mechanism.</p><p>In terms of amendment No. 71 from Senator Higgins regarding a mechanism where somebody does not wish to take part in the information call, again, I find what she has put forward problematic in the context of one of the options that is being put forward in group 11, which is this idea that registered post can somehow indicate that the information has been successfully conveyed to the adopted person.  I will speak to my concerns about that as an alternative when we come to discuss group 11, but that protection is not even provided in what the Senator has put forward in amendment No. 71.  That is why I would be concerned about that and about the clarity of the no-contact preference, which is the exercise of the privacy rights being conveyed to the adopted person under the mechanism the Senator has set down in this amendment.</p><p>In terms of some of the other points, a range of issues are set out in this group and some of them are quite different.  In terms of the use of "may" versus "shall" in the statement, which we debated during our previous discussion, again, we believe that the statement will take place in the vast majority of situations.  However, there are situations, and I gave the example before of maybe the provision of a birth certificate or something like that, where one piece of information has been sought where a statement will not be necessary, for instance, where the piece of information being provided is self-explanatory and the statement is not needed.  Again, however, clear guidance will be set out in the guidelines to the effect that where there any degree of explanation is needed, a statement should be provided.</p><p>Senator Boyhan spoke very eloquently last week to the case where a record is not found.  There will be situations where records are not found.  This is important for us in terms of honesty and not wishing to create unreasonable expectations for adopted people of what might be there.  There will be situations where adoption records are not available for the AAI or Tusla to provide.  We have mechanisms in place in terms of tracing and other methods to support people who perhaps have not been provided with a birth certificate, in how they can use the additional processes.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> This idea of the automatic consequence of no birth certificate being found resulting in a seizure and an investigation puts a huge burden on Tusla or the AAI in terms of undertaking this when they may not have the mechanisms to provide any conclusive answers to the adopted person as to why that is the case.  It particularly puts a huge burden on them at a time when they should be undertaking the already very big job of implementing this legislation, providing for what will be the many thousands of people who will seek to use the provisions of this legislation to finally provide them with the information they require.</p><p>Fundamentally, what we are seeking is the full release of all information in every circumstance.  That requires a limitation of the privacy rights of parents.  We agree that this needs to be done and that the fact it has not been done for so long has entirely negated the identity rights of adopted people in this country.  Because of the system in which we work, however, a severe limitation on the privacy rights of somebody must contain a balancing mechanism.  We would argue that the balancing mechanism we are bringing forward has changed throughout this process.  It has moved from an in-person meeting to an information telephone call and from being provided by a social worker to being provided by a relevant person.  It has moved from a point where the language used referred to the adopted person understanding the importance of respecting the privacy rights of the parent to one where it solely states that the adopted person will be informed that the parent has exercised his or her privacy rights.  This is a change.  It has been amended to reflect concerns that have been raised.  Fundamentally, however, if this legislation does not contain a balancing mechanism, we risk the overall goal, which is the full release of unredacted information in every circumstance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#ZZ00200"><p>I thank the Minister.  Before I invite Senators back in, I want to welcome all our guests to the Gallery on behalf of all the Senators, ministerial staff, officials and ushers.  We always like to see people here.  As our guests can gather, we are discussing Committee Stage of the Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022.  I hope they enjoy the rest of their day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#ZZ00300"><p>I accept that matters have moved on with regard to the provisions, but I was here in 2017.  I want to acknowledge former Senator Bacik, who, along with me and a number of others, spent many hours with the then Minister.  We were told at that time that a veto was required by the Constitution.  We were emphatically told that the Constitution interpretation of privacy at that time, which, again, we argued was not even consistent with the right to the private life of a person, was of a desire for the non-sharing of information on the part of a parent.  There was a framing of two rights versus another when, in fact, there was a question of the right of privacy being quite nuanced and the right to private life actually being an across the board consideration on the question of identity.  There was an undervaluing of the provisions in respect of the changes that came about through the insertion of the rights of the child into the Constitution.  There was an undervaluing of the obligations in terms of the GDPR in European law in respect of the seeking of rights.  I appreciate that the Minister set out that the GDPR rights will still be there, but that will be subject to an individualised balancing in each case.</p> <p>I understand that the Minister feels this has moved to where it can.  I urge him to consider that suite of proposals that have been put forward by others, however, including the committee and ourselves, in respect of other ways to address that concern and in particular, to look at the issue of birth certificates.  It is one thing in terms of birth information, but that differential treatment of adopted persons in terms of birth certificates gives rise to a particular concern.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have these concerns.  I say this not to dismiss, but we were told in 2017 that, by looking for any requirement for birth certificates or any non-assumption of veto, we were delaying the benign purposes of the legislation.  At the time, it was woefully inadequate legislation.  As such, I will not apologise for seeking better.  Even at this late stage, we can do better.</p><p>Contact is different than information.  The assumption built into the Bill is that there is a desire for contact on the part of the adopted person, which is why that person needs to be informed that people do not want to hear from him or her.  Instead, general information could be given to all persons and they could be told that, if they were thinking of contacting people, there was a contact preference register or a tracing service.  They could be directed to that separate suite of provisions in this way instead of attaching something on tracing and contact preferences to an information provision.  Those are the two parts.  It would be good to inform persons that there was a contact preference register and that, if they were thinking about trying to make contact, they could check it, but a large number of adopted people just want to get their birth certificates and do not want to contact anyone.  They will not be given that option, though.  It may not be appropriate for the information on contact preferences to be provided at the point where persons are simply accessing their birth certificates.  Instead, such information and balancing might be provided in a relevant way when persons are considering making contact.</p><p>The Minister addressed a number of the other issues that I had highlighted.  Our amendment is wide.  When a relevant record is not found, for example, a birth certificate, we suggest a strong measure, that being a seizure and immediate investigation.  If the Minister does not wish to accept this, I encourage him to table something on Report Stage.  If people are being told that their records no longer exist, there needs to be some provision whereby the State at least recognises a pattern.  For example, if a particular adoption agency or relevant authority is consistently telling people that such records are not available, there needs to be some follow-up as opposed to each individual just getting an email to that effect.  The Minister stated that a large volume of work needed to be done.  My concern is that, in that large volume, evasions and loopholes will be created whereby, if there is a pattern of records not being available in a particular situation, it might not get identified.  We suggested that it would require an investigation in almost every instance.  If the Minister cannot accept that, then he should consider whether there needs to be some other mechanism to flag if there have been multiple instances of persons being told that their records are not available.  What can be put into the system to identify or address a pattern rather than just having a set of many disappointed individuals?</p><p>In his reply, the Minister did not get a chance to address an amendment that was buried in the midst of this grouping.  I am referring to the amendment on &ldquo;all relevant records&rdquo;.  Rather than requesting records and needing to be sure to use the exact title, for example, &ldquo;early life information&rdquo; or &ldquo;medical records&rdquo;, and instead of having to engage in separate application processes, I am requesting that there be a provision whereby persons can just say that they would like &ldquo;all relevant records&rdquo; and they would then be given all of those strands of information.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Perhaps that is already allowed for, but I am concerned that persons might not know what to ask for or they may ask for one set of information and not be aware that it will only be partial.  Will the Minister address this amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#BBB00200"><p>I am seeking clarity.  The Minister stated that we have moved on since 2017 and that there have been conversations.  Was he given an explicit reason for why it cannot be by registered post?  Was that legal advice or was it just the preference?  I am not clear on that.  We initially suggested that it could be done via phone call instead of in person, but our own thoughts on this have evolved.  Is there a specific reason that it cannot be done in this way?  Is it a legal reason or is it just the preference of the Minister and his Department?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#BBB00300"><p>Regarding Senator Higgins&rsquo;s query on the phrase "all relevant records", the manner in which the application form for information will be designed will be clear on the fact that a person seeking information under the legislation may choose certain types of information.  We must recognise that some adopted people may wish to do this.  It will be as clear as a box that reads, "For all records, tick here".  We will make it as easy as possible.  While I understand what Senator Higgins is asking for, her amendment is not necessary.  We want to make this process as simple and clear as possible while also respecting the agency of individuals who may wish to pick and choose types of information.  I suspect, and I am sure the Senator does as well, that the majority will wish to choose all of the information.  That will be as clear as possible on the application form.</p> <p>Regarding section 32, I am not fully clear about what the Senator wishes to achieve in terms of an investigation.  If illegality has taken place, there are mechanisms for that to be investigated by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I am not sure how the Senator&rsquo;s amendment, which would place the obligation for a large-scale investigation on Tusla when the answer could be that, for example, a fire at a particular agency had destroyed the records, would advance the process.  The obligation would be on Tusla, not recalling that Tusla&rsquo;s job in this context is to try to provide information to people where that information exists.</p> <p>On Senator Hoey&rsquo;s question, the idea of using a registered letter approach was specifically canvassed during our engagements with the Office of the Attorney General and advisory counsel.  It was advised that the information phone call was the best way of securing and protecting the privacy rights involved.  A great deal of consideration has gone into this.  I have heard people&rsquo;s concerns, which is why there have been significant changes to the information phone call, but the advice that I have received is that this is what is necessary to achieve the constitutional balance that ensures that this legislation is not deemed unconstitutional, which would undermine all that we are seeking to achieve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#BBB00400"><p>As the Minister requested, I will clarify the position.  Amendment No. 32 relates to a situation where someone makes an application to the register of births but no entry is found.  Where a relevant body has received an application and does not hold the birth certificate, it will inform the applicant of that fact in writing and without delay.  A person being told that there is no record of him or her is significant, and we suggested that this should trigger an investigation in each instance.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I had asked that if the Minister felt it would be onerous to trigger it in every instance, could there at least be some mechanism to deal with a pattern.  He mentioned there may be some reason like a fire or something, but the Bill does not even require the authority to outline a reason for not having a birth certificate.  People are simply told it does not exist.  If there are fires, files lost, swathes of records from a particular institution that never filed them properly or whatever, we want those issues to be addressed rather than it being the luck of the draw as to whether someone gets a birth certificate.</p><p>At the moment section 4 simply provides that persons are just informed that a body does not hold a birth certificate for them.  However, there should be a clear next stage even if it is just information about what they can do next.  In addition, if the State sees a pattern of relevant bodies informing a large number of people that they do not hold birth certificates, that should be identified and investigated in some way.  As we are on Committee Stage, I am open to suggestions and thoughts the Minister might have.  However, he might agree with me that to simply get a letter indicating that there is not a birth certificate should not be the end of that process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.149" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.150" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>SECTION 6</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#CCC00300"><p>I move amendment No. 32:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 15, between lines 35 and 36, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(5) Where no birth information is available, the Authority shall seize all records relating to the relevant person&rsquo;s adoption and/or illegal birth registration and open an investigation into what transpired.  The relevant person will be kept informed and will be consulted throughout the course of the investigation.&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#CCC00400"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#CCC00500"><p>I do not see any alternative as there seems to be no engagement on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.154/1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#CCC00600"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 12; Níl, 25.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Alice-Mary Higgins and Lynn Ruane; Níl, Senators Seán Kyne and Lisa Chambers.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.154/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2022-05-24" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#CCC00600">
            <divisioncount ayes="12" noes="25" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" vote="aye">Lynn Boylan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" vote="aye">Alice-Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" vote="aye">Annie Hoey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" vote="aye">Sharon Keogan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" vote="aye">Rebecca Moynihan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" vote="aye">Marie Sherlock</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" vote="no">Malcolm Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" vote="no">Miche&aacute;l Carrigy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" vote="no">Pat Casey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" vote="no">Shane Cassells</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" vote="no">Lisa Chambers</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" vote="no">Ollie Crowe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" vote="no">Emer Currie</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" vote="no">Regina Doherty</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" vote="no">Aisling Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" vote="no">Timmy Dooley</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" vote="no">Pippa Hackett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" vote="no">Se&aacute;n Kyne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" vote="no">Eugene Murphy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" vote="no">Mary Seery Kearney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" vote="no">Barry Ward</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.154/3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#CCC00600"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.155" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.156" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FFF00200">Teachtaireacht ón Dáil - Message from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#FFF00300"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Sick Leave Bill 2022 on 18 May 2022 to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.158" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 4.35 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 4.45 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 4.35 p.m. and resumed at 4.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.159" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#HHH00100">Address to Seanad Éireann by US Congressman Richard Neal</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#HHH00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an cathaoirleach of the Congressional Friends of Ireland and of the Ways and Means Committee in the US House of Representatives from the great state of Massachusetts via Ballyferriter, Congressman Richard Neal.  I welcome the United States ambassador to Ireland, H.E. Claire Cronin.  I also welcome the congressional delegation, Congressman Kevin Brady from Texas, the co-chair of the Congressional Friends of Ireland, Congressman Mike Kelly from Pennsylvania, Congressman Dan Kildee from Michigan, Congressman David Joyce from Ohio, Congresswoman Mary Gay Scanlon from Pennsylvania, Congressman Vern Buchanan from Florida, Congressman Mike Doyle from Pennsylvania and Congressman Ron Kind from Wisconsin.</p> <p>On this, the 100th anniversary of Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I welcome Congressman Neal, the first ever Member of the United States Congress to address this House in our 100-year history.  In the words of one of our Senators, from that first great Senate, W.B. Yeats, "There are no strangers here, only friends you haven't met yet."  Congressman Neal you are no stranger to Ireland and I know you will leave our shores with many more friends.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The support for Ireland from the United States of America is well known.  The United States was there for Ireland 100 years ago during our struggle for independence.  The only country referred to by name other than Ireland in the 1916 Proclamation is the United States, where it says, "supported by her exiled children in America".  The United States of America was there for Ireland just under a quarter of a century ago during the negotiations leading to the Good Friday Agreement.  The United States is still there for us now as we deal with the challenges of Brexit and the threat it poses to the Good Friday Agreement and the peace process.  Congressman Richie Neal is the embodiment of that support for Ireland in the United States.</p><p>As the United States has been there for Ireland in our hour of need, Ireland was there for America in its hour of need.  George Washington, the leader of the American Revolution, acknowledged that in his Continental Army, over a quarter of his soldiers had Irish heritage.  He said of them, "Ireland, thou friend of my country in my most friendless days."  When America finally prevailed in that most bloody struggle for independence, Lord Mountjoy admitted to the British Parliament that it had lost America through the Irish.  In 2026, on the 250th anniversary of the signing of the American Declaration of Independence of which nine signatories had Irish heritage, we look forward to celebrating with all Americans that document which not only inspired the world but changed the world and is still changing the world.</p><p>Congressman Richie Neal was first elected to the city council in Springfield, Massachusetts, in 1978 and became mayor of Springfield in 1984.  As we all know from the words of another great Irish American politician, all politics is local.  Congressman Neal has the honour of hailing from County Kerry.  Like many in Springfield, his connections are in west Kerry, which his grandmother left to make a new life in America.  Congressman Neal was elected to the House of Representatives in 1989 and I am glad to say that the people of Massachusetts have chosen wisely to keep electing him to Congress.</p><p>Congressman Neal and many others were involved in the search for peace long before the Good Friday Agreement.  He was involved in the search for peace when it was unimaginable.  Congressman Neal's involvement and contribution have not only been extraordinary, they have been vital.  In his position as chair of the Ways and Means Committee, the committee which will decide any future trade agreement between the United States of America and the United Kingdom, Congressman Neal has been consistent in telling the UK Government that there will be no trade agreement between the United States and the UK if anything the British do undermines the Good Friday Agreement or the peace process on this island.</p><p>On a personal level, Congressman Neal and I have worked on a number of projects together, some small and some quite large, including when in 2016, Congressman Neal installed a garden of remembrance in his home city of Springfield.  The garden of remembrance initiative was a concept supported by the all-party consultation group on the decade of commemorations.  Those gardens honour the service and sacrifice of the men and women who fought for the ideals of the 1916 Proclamation.  The garden of remembrance in Springfield was the first installed outside Ireland and is one of 365 gardens installed that year.</p><p>Congressman Neal was also involved in another project to get a replica of the 1916 Proclamation installed inside the Washington Monument.  As an indication of how big an achievement that was, only 16 countries have plaques inside the Washington Monument and the last time permission was given to install a plaque inside the Washington Monument was when Alaska and Hawaii became states in 1959.  All other requests made since have been refused.  Yesterday in the GPO, the Congressman unveiled a plaque, a replica of the one inside the Washington Monument.  Having worked with Congressman Neal and the Congressional Friends of Ireland, I am proud to say that now among the immortal words written in stone in monuments throughout Washington DC are the words, "Irishmen and Irishwomen".</p><p>The project I am most proud of was working with Congressman Neal on the establishment of the American Irish State Legislators Caucus.  In the Congressman's own words, this is an initiative in "building the bench", which is a baseball term, meaning ensuring having more players than will ever be needed.  He and we want to exchange Irish American influence at all levels of government.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Just before St. Patrick's Day last year, Congressman Neal was the guest of honour at the 40th anniversary celebration of the American-Irish Legislators Society of New York, one of four such caucuses throughout the United States at the time.  We worked together on building the American Irish State Legislators Caucus across the United States.  There is now leadership in all 50 states.  The official launch took place last October in the Round Room of the Mansion House, where Irish democracy took its first steps.  On that occasion there were state senate presidents and majority leaders from 27 US states to launch that caucus.  Like the Congressional Friends of Ireland in Washington, the American Irish State Legislators Caucus is a bipartisan organisation, which is open to everybody: those who have Irish heritage and those who are supporters of Ireland.  The American Irish State Legislators Caucus will ensure as legislators go from state legislators to Members of Congress and to members of the Congressional Friends of Ireland, that they are aware of the issues around the peace process, the issues in Ireland, and the issues affecting the Good Friday Agreement.</p><p>Last year we saw the 40th anniversary of the Congressional Friends of Ireland.  I can think of no-one better then Congressman Richie Neal to lead that vital organisation at this moment in history.  Congressman Neal is carrying on a tradition of the work of great Irish Americans who have gone before him; those who founded the Congressional Friends of Ireland.  It is appropriate that we remember them at this time: Senator Edward Kennedy, Governor Hugh Carey, Daniel Patrick Moynihan, and Speaker Tip O'Neill.  I am honoured to ask my good friend, and a great friend of Ireland, Congressman Richie Neal to address Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.163" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richard Neal" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#KKK00200"><p>Let me begin by thanking the Seanad for this generous invitation.  This is the rarest of opportunities that a person from another country might get to enjoy.  I thank the Cathaoirleach, Senator Mark Daly, in particular for, as he described, his work with legislative bodies across the country so that we may well create the next generation of the Friends of Ireland.  We are reminded on this occasion of why the Friends of Ireland was brought about.  We agreed to stop the gun running in America in places like the cities we all come from such as Boston, Springfield, New York, Philadelphia, Chicago and Pittsburgh, and the UK decided to get serious about finding a solution to the North.</p> <p>When on 2 February, 1880, the great Irish nationalist parliamentarian, Charles Stewart Parnell, took to his feet in the United States Capitol to address the joint Houses of Congress, he became one of the first non-American political leaders to be granted this rare honour.  This moment reflected the special ties that bound Ireland and America at a time when the Irish-born population of the United States was at its peak.  In thanking the people of America for their unyielding support for Ireland, Parnell expressed pride in his American heritage, which was acquired through his mother.  I stand here today as chairman of the Ways and Means Committee, imbued with a deep sense of pride in my heritage, brought forward from forbears who crossed the Atlantic to make new lives for themselves on our continent.  Not to mention, incidentally, the first chairman of the Ways and Means Committee was named Fitzsimons and he was an Irish immigrant.  In the decades following Ireland's Great Hunger, millions of Irish immigrants transformed America.  Lifting shovels, bringing down hammers, and building canals, they helped to make America a world power.  In return, Irish immigrants and their descendants helped to take Ireland on its way to independence.</p> <p>Parnell was not the only Irish public figure to make his way to America in the decades prior to the emergence of the Irish Free State, the centenary of which we mark this year with all of you.  Douglas Hyde, who went on to become the first President of Ireland, visited my home place of Springfield where he described one of the Irish-speaking hosts as the finest Irishman he had encountered anywhere.  On the first page of Fintan O'Toole's new book, on page one, he mentions the people of Springfield.  Yesterday, we relived that opportunity on the Blasket Islands.  In my constituency there is one person still living who had lived on the Blaskets.  Our visitors today from the congressional delegation, Representatives Kevin Brady, Ron Kind, Mike Kelly, Mike Doyle, David Joyce, Mary Gay Scanlon, Dan Kildee and Vern Buchanan are only removed by one or two generations from this island.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Congressman Richard Neal:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My colleagues on the congressional delegation and I are delighted to be back in Ireland to reconnect with friends and relatives after a difficult couple of years with the pandemic disrupting all of our lives.  It was a joy to have been with the Taoiseach in Washington, as it was again yesterday, for a meeting that lasted more than an hour to discuss the challenges we now confront again.  It was a bold moment for such a small country to receive an audience on St. Patrick's Day with the President of the United States, Members of the Houses of Congress and to be at the centre of the American stage.</p><p>I am joined this week by these Members of Congress who have a long-standing commitment to deepening the ties between our two countries and protecting the precious peace that our country helped supply the background for 24 years ago.  I know something about that agreement.  I helped to urge Bill Clinton and George Mitchell to take it up and it has been successful beyond anybody's imagination.</p><p>Just as Parnell in 1880 paid tribute to Americans for their support for Ireland, let me acknowledge and pass on congratulations for Ireland's unwavering stance on Ukraine.  Ireland has pushed back hard on Russia's brutal aggression, supported unprecedented stiff sanctions and extensive EU military assistance to Ukraine.  I know Ireland has also given shelter to almost 30,000 Ukrainians who have fled their war-torn homeland.  Russia's war of aggression on Ukraine has served to underline and reinforce the democratic values that unite Americans and Europeans who now stand together in determined opposition to the tyranny unleashed by Putin's Russia.  In Brussels, we heard the same message.  The Europeans intend to stand with America and our allies across the globe to push back on this challenge.</p><p>As we convene here today in this marvellous setting, I recognise that this worrying and uncertain time also occurs in Northern Ireland.  We are here to listen to the views of political leaders in Dublin and tomorrow we move on to Belfast for two very serious days with all the political parties.  We want to meet with people so that we can understand how the fallout from the UK's decision to leave the EU has affected all of them and us.  The message we will bring is firm, clear and unambiguous.  The number one priority for the United States on this island is to ensure that the hard-won peace in Northern Ireland is preserved and reinforced.  It was apparent to us during our visit to Brussels that the EU and Ireland's neighbours in Europe remain equally strong in their commitment to Northern Ireland.  They have time and again demonstrated their support for the Good Friday Agreement, as have all the parties in the Irish Republic, unreservedly.  I am pleased that Ireland continues its engagement.</p><p>While I of course respect the UK's decision to leave the European Union, it has inevitably posed unprecedented challenges for the island of Ireland.  I hope we can all focus on this because I think we are losing institutional memory in the UK.  A grim reminder is that 30 years ago there were 30,000 British soldiers in an area the size of our state of Connecticut.  Anybody who travelled there knew clearly what the watchtowers meant and what the Royal Ulster Constabulary, RUC, meant in that small geographic area.  The longest standing political dispute in the history of the western world was proceeding unabated in the Six Counties of Northern Ireland.</p><p>Through good work and goodwill, we helped to find a path forward.  We have found solutions time and again to short-term disruptions.  Now it is the protocol.  A solution through an extended set of negotiations on Northern Ireland and Ireland can be enhanced.  Any incautious move to undo the protocol, which was agreed to by all sides to address these issues, would put at risk this durable agreement that we helped to create and which now we should all be celebrating.  On the eve of the 25th year of the Good Friday Agreement, everything in our power to protect the unrelenting gains should be acknowledged.  In the context of the moment, the way forward is the same as it has been.  We need courage, dialogue and leadership from all sides to keep Northern Ireland secure and prosperous.  The Good Friday Agreement worked because it had something in it for all sides.  It happened because those involved acted together in good faith and the hardest men and women had to make that agreement.  Everybody gave up something to agree to this place.  The Republic of Ireland relinquished Articles 2 and 3 of its Constitution, which laid claim, at the request of de Valera, to the North.  The UK gave up the Border.  The world was a witness to these proceedings.  Unilateral actions, intransigence and ultimatums are not solutions, nor have they ever been.  America will continue to nudge and nurture this agreement.  After all, the Good Friday Agreement is America's too.</p><p>I have no doubt that my ancestors, who instilled a deep and emotional connection to this country, would be proud of the Ireland we have seen this week.  A strong, prosperous and confident Ireland has firmly found its place on the world stage and used its voice, as always, to stand up for the less fortunate.  While Ireland has been remade in recent decades as an open, tolerant and prosperous country, our immigrant ancestors would be heartened to see that its traditional character and distinctive identity remain intact.  The welcome Ireland has extended to the Ukrainians confirms, through solidarity and compassion, that the people of Ireland have not forgotten our own history.  Leaving one's homeland is a deeply painful experience.  For those who depart the communities that were left behind, Irish America carries the memory of that experience.  However, the past does not define us.  What defines us is how we and so many other immigrant communities have helped to build America and make it the great country it is today.</p><p>Representative democracy does not have to mean uniformity.  From the skyscrapers of Manhattan to the mines of Montana, our nation's infrastructure bears an indelible Irish imprint.  That Irish influence is felt in many parts of American life, including in politics, business, education, media and, of course, law enforcement.  Those are just a few of the areas in which Irish Americans have excelled.  The heritage of this congressional delegation, as I noted earlier, along with that of President Biden, epitomises the Irish contribution to government in America.  They made that journey across the Atlantic.  Families such as the Finnegans, the Blewitts, the Kennedys, the Garveys, the Wards, the Harts and the Neals could scarcely have imagined what an impact their descendants would make in their adopted land.</p><p>In the years leading up to 1922, many of my predecessors in Congress did their utmost to advance the Irish question at the highest levels of the United States Government.  In the century since Ireland's independence, this tradition of Irish-American concern for Ireland has been maintained.  Successive generations of Irish-American political leaders have stood by Ireland in good times and troubled ones.  Irish-Americans were instrumental in encouraging the US involvement in Northern Ireland throughout the 1970s, 1980s and 1990s.  The great man John Hume visited America to say it was worth it.  His visits helped to shape that success story.  It created a very important condition for peace in Northern Ireland: the American dimension.  That push led to the founding of the Friends of Ireland 40 years ago.  The Friends and I have the honour of co-chairing the unique bipartisan support for the Good Friday Agreement that has flowed from it.  Half of our delegation are Republicans and the other half are Democrats.  At a time when it is hard for us to find agreement on a lot of issues, we have found agreement, as always, on Ireland.  We introduced a credible and independent voice that helped to pave the way for the Good Friday Agreement.  I am proud that much of my career in foreign policy has been based upon my interest in this achievement.  One of my first speeches in the House of Representatives, a few years ago, condemned the use of rubber bullets in the North of Ireland.  My own heritage compelled me to do what I could but many of the people I represent in Springfield would tell the same story.  It was that story for all of our Congress Members who were trying to conjure up a path to peace that was bolstered by American communities all over the countries and who kept the fortunes of Ireland close to their hearts and at the top of their minds.</p><p>Our visit here is part of that tradition.  As before, representatives from both sides of the aisle are putting their differences aside to help bridge the gaps between the communities on this island.  We are here to listen, to speak and to bring the message to and from Washington that peace needs undying commitment and dedication to achieving positive outcomes.  We know how important the United States has been in helping the parties in the North carve out a path to a better future for all.  We are committed to staying the course and keeping the North on that path of peace and prosperity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Congressman Richard Neal:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I look forward, in the next two days, to visiting once again the old Border.  I have been involved for so long that I can remember the dark days.  I recall crossing that Border either in 1989 or 1990 with the then Speaker of the House, Tom Foley, from Donegal to Derry.  Our bus was stopped by a British Army patrol and we were obliged to wait in the vehicle while it was subjected to a thorough search by armed soldiers with night vision equipment and heavy armaments.  I have far fonder memories of crossing that Border with Speaker Pelosi in 2019.  When we moved across the Border from Derry to Donegal and back again, to make the moment, our phones pinged.  That tells the story.  The contrast between then and now could not have been starker.</p><p>No one wants to return to a time when a Border control across the island divided its people.  That is why the EU-UK protocol is so important and why its implementation needs to be the subject of a negotiated agreement and not unilateral action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.166" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Senators" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MMM00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.167" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richard Neal" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MMM00300"><p>The principle of consent does not mean veto.</p> <p>I have been excited to learn more this week about the Irish Government's shared island initiative, which we discussed this morning with President Higgins.  It reflects an understanding that all communities and traditions on the island have a chance to work together to build a consensus for a shared future.  That is the way forward.  We cannot allow the fallout from Brexit to divert Ireland from the path of peace and progress ,and we must not allow the clock to be turned back.  The United States will continue to be the reliable friend it always has been to Ireland and to have a strong stake in the rich legacy of the Good Friday Agreement that Ireland, along with the US, helped to secure.  We intend not to let it go awry.  We have work to do in protecting and reinforcing the peace in Northern Ireland that has existed for the last 25 years.  As always, we need to work together - the US, Ireland, Britain, the EU and the people of Northern Ireland and their political representatives - to find a space where the planter and the Gael might live in harmony, where instead of two communities there is one community with two traditions.</p> <p>The legacy issue should not be allowed to get in the way of what families need to know about what really happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.168" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Senators" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MMM00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.169" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richard Neal" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MMM00500"><p>That is a very important consideration.  When they come to Washington, we meet with all of the families regardless of their tradition.  There was enough pain inflicted by one side and the other and those families need closure in their lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.170" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Senators" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MMM00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.171" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richard Neal" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MMM00700"><p>Whether it was the Guildford case or Bloody Sunday - I talked to those families on the day that then British Prime Minister David Cameron apologised on the floor of the House of Commons - or whether it was Birmingham or the Raymond McCord case, campaigners on which have been to my office to ask that America intervene on behalf of his son, we need to know, along with the Finucane family as well.</p> <p>I thank Senator Daly for the invitation he extended but as he lobbies, he always brings these issues up as well.  Let me personally conclude with something I have thought a lot about.  But for the rhythms of history, I might be sitting where Senator Daly is today, representing County Kerry, Ireland.  Knowing all of the Senators here and what happens in America, a lot of them would be sitting in Congress, I know that.  Together, we celebrate an ancient culture whose devotion to learning, always acknowledging that words matter, and with a special regard for the printed and spoken word, helped to lift the aspirations of millions of descendants of this island.  The Gaels might have moved west but they took with them the values and resolve that people like today's Senators taught in earlier generations.  Anniversaries are very important in Irish history, more so as we commemorate the centenary of the Irish Republic.</p> <p>We also applaud a very small country that has given so much to world civilisation.  Any anthology offers competing narratives but through conquest, subjugation, occupation, famine, risings, revolutions and civil war, there was always an unbreakable spirit marked by optimism.  For such a country to have produced James Joyce, on the 100th anniversary of Ulysses, the great writers, the monks who saved the ancient scrolls in the Dark Ages, as well as contributions to art, music, literature, theatre and civilisation is remarkable.  In the diaspora, we never forget the candle in the window of the President's residence that we witnessed again this morning and that always welcomes back the emigrants.  Yeats simply described it as the "indomitable Irishry".  I would remind all, as Yeats did, that "Though the leaves are many, the root is one".  Thank you from the United States of America.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MMM00800"><p>Thank you, Congressman.  I would like to inform the House that that was the longest-standing ovation anyone has received in my time in this House.  Thank you for your thoughtful contribution and your quote from a great Senator who led us 100 years ago, W.B Yeats, as you concluded your remarks.  Each of the group leaders will now make a contribution and then we will have some concluding remarks from Congressman Neal.  I call on the Leader of the House, Senator Doherty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#MMM00900"><p>In the presence of Ambassador Cronin and former Ministers Charlie Flanagan and Noel Dempsey, I would like to wholeheartedly welcome Congressman Neal and all of the distinguished guests that we have here today.  We are really proud to have him as a visitor to our shores but I know it is not the first time; he has been here many times.  Protecting the peace on our island is such an important issue to all of us, not least to Congressman Neal.  We can very easily say that he is a true friend of Ireland and I thank him for his time today.</p> <p>The Friends of Ireland group is particularly special.  It is a bipartisan group, with members from the Democrats and the Republicans.  Its members and their forerunners have really demonstrated their love for Ireland and their commitment to maintaining the peace and prosperity that we have enjoyed on this island and that is really important.  As the Cathaoirleach mentioned earlier, the group was founded by Senator Ted Kennedy, Senator Daniel Moynihan and Speaker Tip O'Neill.  They all famously played their part from Washington in crafting the peace accords that led not only to the Anglo-Irish Agreement but also to the Good Friday Agreement.  I cannot tell Congressman Neal how important it is to hear him say that the Good Friday Agreement belongs to America too and does not just belong to Ireland.  I thank him for that.</p> <p>We all know how important and monumental the Good Friday Agreement is, and was, in ending violence and bringing about lasting peace and ultimately in providing hope to our younger generations that the society they would grow up in and raise their families would be much better than heretofore.  We are all very familiar with Ms Lisa McGee's enormously successful "Derry Girls", which, I believe, has made its way across the pond, which is great.  The final episode aired last week and it focused on the referendum and the Good Friday Agreement.  The peace now enjoyed in Northern Ireland was hard fought and was not easily won.  Remarkably, through this television series, new generations, including my own children, as well as people in Great Britain, the United States and across the world, are learning just how valuable the peace process was and continues to be.  That is why we must ensure it is protected.  The importance of defending that peace, as well as the institutions in Northern Ireland can never be overstated.  We must all ensure that neither it nor the protocol which preserves its progress are undermined or discarded.  In the spirit of those who came before us, people like the late John Hume, David Trimble, President Clinton and George Mitchell, we are really hopeful that progress can be made through dialogue and negotiation.</p> <p>As we welcome Congressman Neal and his delegation here today, we cannot forget that the Northern Ireland Troubles (Legacy and Reconciliation) Bill is going through its second reading in Westminster.  That legislation serves absolutely nobody.  It is a Bill which refers to reconciliation but it leaves its victims out in the cold.  That is a real pity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Neither Congressman Neal nor his colleagues are strangers to these sentiments.  He knows what is at stake and knows from his experience what must be done.  That is why he is here, as a well and true friend of Ireland.  Once again, on behalf of this House and all my colleagues, I thank him for a lifetime of commitment to his former home.  He will always be welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#NNN00200"><p>Congressman Neal is most welcome to the Seanad.  On behalf of Fianna F&aacute;il, I extend a c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte to him on the momentous occasion of his significant address to the House at a time when we need his support.</p> <p>As Congressman Neal will be aware, his address will have been watched and viewed by many, not just on this island but further afield.  In 2016, when the Brexit referendum took place, and we all assumed it would go a different way, I am sure we recall how we felt when the result of that vote finally came through.  We knew the change would be seismic and significant, and that we had a long road ahead of us as a country.  At that time, the US rowed in behind Ireland, as did other EU member states.  Make no bones about it, that left the UK under no illusion as to what that meant for us.  The US ensured that we, as a small country, would not be bullied and left behind in what was going to be a significant change for us.</p> <p>We have been through a lot in this process.  It has been six years.  During that time, we found ourselves with a negotiated agreement and an international treaty that was signed up to by the United Kingdom.  Part of that included the Northern Ireland protocol.  It is worth remembering that was the result of years of detailed and extensive negotiations by those on all sides in a process which, as I have stated previously, everybody went into with eyes wide open.  They knew exactly what was being agreed and, because of that, I take great offence and absolutely reject the suggestion by the United Kingdom that it signed up to what was agreed under duress.  That is simply not the fact, not the truth and it is not correct.</p> <p>Congressman Neal gave us the great honour and privilege of addressing the Seanad Brexit committee in December 2020.  He was one of that committee's first witnesses.  His comments were significant and made a major difference to the negotiations that were well under way at that point and that remain ongoing.  During that address, he stated: "a trade agreement without the support of the Chairman of the US Congressional Committee on Ways and Means [Congressman Neal] and the Speaker of the House [Nancy Pelosi] is just not something that can happen."  He could not have been clearer and that was a very strong statement to make at that time.  He went on to say that "a bilateral trade relationship with the United States and the UK is desirable - it would be good for both sides - but not at the expense of jeopardising the Good Friday Agreement."  Again, he could not have been clearer.  That was a significant statement.</p> <p>Congressman Neal also said that he often heard people refer to there being two communities, but that he always pointed out there is one community and two traditions.  He always trod very carefully.  I am always struck by his passion for Northern Ireland and for Ireland, and by his depth of knowledge of the issues facing this island.  He said we must "lead by the power of our example, not the example of our power".  He was quoting former President Bill Clinton when he made those comments.  That is a very strong message to send out to those who are at the negotiating table today.  There is a major responsibility on his shoulders to ensure that we do not jeopardise the Good Friday Agreement and that we maintain good relations - North-South, east-west and between the UK, Ireland and the European Union.</p> <p>I will also quote former Taoiseach Bertie Ahern when he recounted his experiences negotiating the Good Friday Agreement.  He said we also needed a new ethos, "an ethos of tolerance, reconciliation, equality and mutual respect - to underpin the agreement".  Those words ring true again today.  We need those same things to underpin this new agreement between the UK and the European Union.  Congressman Neal alluded to this in stating that concluding the Good Friday Agreement involved difficult choices for the negotiators in having to accept unpalatable elements of the agreement in recognition of their importance to others.  The point he made about all sides giving up something significant to get that agreement showed the power of politics and the power of compromise.  There is nothing to be ashamed about in compromising, reaching agreement and in everybody giving a little.</p> <p>If I could give one message to Congressman Neal while he is in the Chamber, it is to keep doing what he is doing in continuing to support Ireland's cause in the Brexit negotiation.  I have a message for those who are at that negotiating table today: we want an agreement, we want compromise and we want flexibility.  I say that not just to those parties in Northern Ireland and the UK, but to the EU as well.  It is important that those on all sides are flexible and are ready and willing to compromise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#NNN00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte is fiche roimh Richard Neal.  Is &oacute;c&aacute;id iontach &eacute; i gc&oacute;na&iacute; nuair a thagann teachta&iacute; &oacute; na St&aacute;it Aontaithe chuig an t&iacute;r seo.  T&aacute; &aacute;thas orm go bhfuil siad anseo inniu agus cuirim f&aacute;ilte rompu uilig.  Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leo as an m&eacute;id at&aacute; &aacute; dh&eacute;anamh acu ar son na t&iacute;re seo.  I am very happy to welcome Congressman Neal.  It is always a special occasion when we welcome American politicians to this country.  We are so grateful for all that America is and all it continues to do, in particular to advance and continue the important work of the peace process.  Others have spoken about the important issues facing us at present and I echo everything they have said.  I will take this opportunity on behalf of the Seanad Independent Group to thank him and the other members of the Congressional Friends of Ireland present today and at home for all they are doing and to wish them continued success in their efforts on our behalf.</p><p>It is perhaps a measure of American's greatness, and the importance of the familial ties between our countries, that we in Ireland feel we have a stake in America and feel ready to criticise it at times as well as to praise it.  There are those who criticise America very unreasonably and seem to forget what the world would be like without it.  There is then the criticism that comes from friends because it is a measure of true friendship that one can be constructive in one's criticism at times.  I think of that wonderful song &quot;America the Beautiful&quot; by Katherine Lee Bates:</p> <blockquote> 	America!  America!<br /><br />God mend thine every flaw,<br /><br />Confirm thy soul in self-control,<br /><br />Thy liberty in law! </blockquote> <p>I think about that in these days because we need a strong America in the world, an America that is a shining city on the hill, and a beacon for democracy, human rights, the rule of law, and civility in political debate.  All these things are highly important, especially now at a time when we see where the other superpowers in the world are going.  We all need to hope that America finds its balance so it can give the leadership in the world we need at this time.</p><p>I have to tell Congressman Neal that many people here, and I am sure many in his country, are distressed by the disunity we sometimes see there now, such as the coarseness that has entered US politics in recent years, the violent protests of 6 January and the 476 riots that took place in the context of the Black Lives Matter protests and, indeed, the recent protests at the homes of justices of the US Supreme Court.  We need a strong America.  We need an America giving leadership in the world where this does not happen because others will point to America's flaws and use that to justify their far greater depredations on humanity.  We encourage Congressman Neal as he gives leadership.  We can also say many of us respect the diversity in US debate.  There is sometimes a groupthink in this country and in Europe.  There is a balance to be struck between groupthink, on the one hand, and excessive discord, on the other, we might say.</p><p>I will conclude by asking Congressman Neal to take one thing home with him.  He will have heard it from others.  It is not to do with Northern Ireland.  As we think about the conflict in Ukraine, we are facing into a frightening situation if the grain Ukraine is producing that is so vital for the poorest and the poorer countries in the world does not get out of that country in the coming weeks.  I do not know how that is to be solved, but I pray that America can use its position of great power to try to help find a solution so we are not facing appalling hunger and starvation in the Middle East and in places such as Egypt, north Africa and south-east Asia.  We ask Congressman Neal and his colleagues not just to take our Irish agenda, which they are all serving so nobly and well, but to remember that situation as well.  I know I say that on behalf of their people as much as our own.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#OOO00100"><p>The Irish Republic is proudly an independent sovereign state, having won its freedom after centuries of struggle and at great cost.  We are also, however, proudly European, dating back not just to our accession to what is now known as the EU.  For over 1,500 years Ireland has contributed enormously to the security and culture of western civilisation.  The long title of a book by Thomas Cahill sums it up very well: <i>How the Irish Saved Civilization: The Untold Story of Ireland's Heroic Role from the Fall of Rome to the Rise of Medieval Europe</i>.</p><p>It has been well documented that the majority of people in Northern Ireland are against Brexit.  They do not want to ditch the protocol.  It is worrying to recall what I hope is an extreme example of the British Government's attitude to Ireland.  Some time ago a current member of the British Government was reported to have said that if Ireland did not do what the British wanted, Britain would cut off food supplies to Ireland.  That caused grave offence.  During the Great Famine our then so-called masters totally mishandled and mismanaged an unspeakable tragedy.  British unilateral and mismanaged action cannot and must not be allowed to collapse the peace process.</p><p>While France, Spain and others have come to Ireland's aid over the centuries, our special, unique relationship with America is, with respect, on a different level.  The contribution of America to creating the Good Friday peace agreement was pivotal.  It has saved countless lives, and for that we are forever grateful.  American politicians such as the Clintons, the Kennedys, Mitchell, President Biden, Kerry, Morrison, Moynihan, Foley, Pelosi, Boyle, Peter King and Tip O'Neill, to name but a few, are legends, forever etched in the minds of our gratitude.  I am not forgetting the contribution of a young congressman from Massachusetts, elected a decade before the historic Good Friday Agreement, one Richard E. Neal.  President Lincoln said that, in the end, it is not the years in your life that count but the life in your years.  Congressman Neal's life makes us in Ireland proud of his honest stewardship and unwavering courage.</p><p>Some of my ancestors, like so many millions, took refuge in the wonderful United States of America.  Many of them took up sport, including boxing.  My grand-uncle, Vincent &quot;Pepper&quot; Martin, in one of the bouts he won was floored in an early round.  I am glad to report that the following day, in the New York papers, the caption under the photo that had him on the floor stated that he was down but that it was far from a knockout.  We in Ireland are politically down but far from a knockout.  The baton of American peace guarantors has been passed on to the next generation, including Congressman Neal's dedicated delegation, which includes the surnames Doyle, Brady, Buchanan, Kelly, Scanlon, Neal, Kind, Kildee and Joyce.  No, they are not togging out for an all-Ireland final.  They have a different challenge on a different level.  They have a gigantic challenge.  We wish them well with the greatest hope, respect and gratitude.</p><p>Irish America, we need your help again.  Thank you for your continued efforts to rescue, to save and to protect the precious peace.  Please continue to stand shoulder to shoulder with us, north and south, east and west, all denominations and none.  Please help us to do our utmost to ensure that the current scarce commodities of common sense, fairness and respect for the rule of law can be found and nurtured in order to help navigate our people through this most difficult time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#OOO00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte is fiche roimh an Comhalta N&eacute;ill agus an toscaireacht at&aacute; linn &oacute; na St&aacute;it Aontaithe.  T&aacute; c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte rompu go l&eacute;ir.  Congressman Neal and his delegation and our other distinguished guests are all very welcome.  The great strength of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is that they will not have to wait until tomorrow to hear a Belfast or Six Counties voice and perspective on the latest events.  It is for that reason that I hope Congressman Neal and the Chair will forgive me if I go just a little over time.</p> <p>For the past 177 years there has been a special relationship between the people of Ireland and the people of the US, especially the Irish diaspora.  That special relationship, person to person, family to family, county to county, was forged in the cauldron of an Gorta M&oacute;r, the Great Hunger, in the 1840s, a deliberate and cataclysmic consequence of British Government colonial policy.  The Famine caused the deaths of 1 million people and the forced exile of another 2 million people.  The effect of that was a defining moment in the development of Ireland.  It spurred on a century-long population decline, devastated the Irish language and changed the country's demographic, political and cultural landscape.  On the banks of the River Liffey, not far from here, there is a raw and emotional depiction of a destitute, starving family on its way to board a coffin ship in search of a new and prosperous life overseas.  Denied such a life here, those who left never forgot the land of their birth.</p> <p>While the image of that family on the banks of the Liffey is one of destitution, there is another story attached to that family.  It is a heroic story, emblematic of Ireland's long struggle for nationhood, because those who survived the coffin ships and disembarked in the US became a bedrock on which generations of republicans and nationalists organised at home and in the USA for Ireland's freedom.  Without that bedrock of support, the Land League would not have succeeded, the 1916 Rising and the Tan War would not have occurred, this State would not have been established and the republican resistance in the North would not have been sustained.  The IRA ceasefire, the loyalist ceasefires, the peace process and the Good Friday Agreement, in part, all owe their existence and durability to the direct involvement of the Irish diaspora and successive US presidents and administrations.  None of the above would have been achieved without the bipartisan policy of successive administrations, and we thank them all for that support.</p> <p>Much of the Irish diaspora supported Bill Clinton's election campaign and, in return, he took an active interest in Ireland.  Following his election, President Clinton ensured that Gerry Adams and other leading republicans were welcomed into the US.  Out of that, an IRA ceasefire took place.  There would not have been a peace process without President Bill Clinton's personal involvement and, indeed, that of Congressman Neal.  President Clinton appointed Senator George Mitchell to chair the peace talks that successfully led to the Good Friday Agreement.  The involvement and presence of US presidents and politicians in the politics of the peace process has been invaluable.  It has been a positive counterweight to the oft-times reckless behaviour of the British Government and unionist parties, not least Boris Johnson and the divisive Brexit policy.  We have seen the beneficial effects of the bipartisan approach in upholding and defending the Good Friday Agreement.  Over the course of Congressman Neal's visit, we have once again heard clearly that there must be no physical border in Ireland and no unilateral action on the part of the British Government in respect of the protocol and that any attempt to undermine the Good Friday Agreement would result in the US Congress not supporting a bilateral free trade agreement with the UK.</p> <p>The recent elections in the North saw the vast majority of people demanding the re-establishment of the Assembly and the Executive.  It also saw the historic election of my colleague, Michelle O'Neill, as the North's First Minister designate and Sinn F&eacute;in emerge as the largest party.  The amount available to the Executive to spend immediately to support workers and families as the cost-of-living crisis rises has increased to &pound;420 million.  People are struggling to put food on the table and to pay their bills.  We need urgent action now.  Sinn F&eacute;in is ready to form an executive right away.  The blocking by others needs to stop.</p> <p>In recent times US representatives have had to remind the British Government to honour its commitments in respect of legacy, truth and justice for the relatives of those killed in the conflict and that amnesties in any form have no place in the peace process.  Today, in Belfast, before travelling to the Seanad, I joined families and survivors in protesting the British Government's cruel and unjust legacy Bill, proposals which this Seanad unanimously rejected in a recent vote.</p> <p>Similar calls have been made with respect to the long-delayed Acht na Gaeilge, an Irish language Act.  We saw last Saturday thousands of people, mostly young people, on the streets of Belfast demanding respect for the Irish language in the most colourful, vibrant, inclusive, determined and confident way.  Beidh Acht na Gaeilge ann.  T&aacute; m&eacute; muin&iacute;neach faoi sin.</p> <p>The peace process has helped open up Irish society to other rights-based issues such as the right of Irish citizens living in the US and elsewhere to vote in Irish presidential elections.  As a result of the impact of Brexit and the refusal of the British Government and unionist parties to respect the vote of the people of the North who voted to remain in the EU, of whom I was one, there is now a growing debate on and demand for constitutional change leading to a new and united Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Ireland has been transformed from the days when real people shuffled their broken and starved bodies along the banks of the Liffey to board ships for North America.  Today's Ireland has a large US footprint where thousands of people are employed in US-owned companies and where peace and hope for the future now reign.  This transformation is part of Ireland's new, and yet-to-be written story; one which the US underwrites but one that we will write here in Ireland for the benefit of all of us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#PPP00200"><p>We welcome our distinguished guests and friends from the United States, in  particular the ambassador, H.E. Ms Cronin, and Congressman Neal's words of solidarity.  In 1998 when the Good Friday Agreement was signed everybody knew it was not an end game. What it did was provide a framework for a bigger job of a peace process.  It may have been Sunningdale for slow learners, in the immortal words of S&eacute;amus Mallon, but unlike 1973 when the trust between the two Governments was low, the trust had been built over the course of the previous decade and the peace process.  That trust had space to grow because they had allies in the US to act as honest brokers when issues or conflicts arose.  The Good Friday Agreement was based on the assumption that Ireland and the UK would both be members of a wider European Union.  It did not anticipate Brexit but, more importantly, it did not anticipate a sovereign Government acting in bad faith.  That is what we have now.  It is heartening at such a delicate phase of the peace process, post-election and protocol negotiations, that we continue to have friends in the EU and in the US who are clear in their assertions that no government can act unilaterally on an issue which has the potential to undermine much fought-for and actively protected peace.</p> <p>The issue is not the protocol; the issue is a Brexit which was built on a bed of lies and which was enthusiastically supported by those who have now zoned in on the protocol to deflect from the consequences of their own actions and stances.  As a result of their intransigence, they are threatening the future of a generation.  We now have Brexit and we are going to deal with it but we will not deal with it at the expense of protecting the integrity of the Single Market or protecting human rights, which the EU guarantee, and at the expense of the protection of peace.</p> <p>"Derry Girls" finished last week with the hope that the Good Friday Agreement represented.  There is a generation of people on this island who do not remember the days of bombs and guns.  There is a generation born since then who have families and jobs and who contribute as members of society but who, in another twist of history, might have had a very different life.  They have that because of the Good Friday Agreement.  This needs to be protected.</p> <p>The arc of history is not guaranteed to be a straight line of progress.  As events in Ukraine show, we must be vigilant in defence of democracy.  To do that, we need to have friends, honest brokers and allies.  We thank Congressman Neal for being that friend to us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#PPP00300"><p>I am honoured to speak today on behalf of my colleagues, Senators Higgins, Ruane and Flynn of the Civil Engagement Group.  I warmly welcome Congressman Neal here today along with the congressional delegation and the ambassador.  His dedication and his commitment are deeply appreciated by the people of Ireland.  The deep ties between our countries are well known and enduring.  Human connections of family and friendship bind us forever together.  We never take their support for granted and they will always be welcome here.</p> <p>The Good Friday Agreement and peace process are lasting legacies of that co-operation and partnership.  America's care, attention and vigilance continues to make a huge difference but let us be clear: the agreement is at risk because of Brexit.  Boris Johnson's hard Brexit has placed enormous strain on our peace agreement.  We must remember the people of the north of Ireland rejected Brexit.  The region was removed from the EU against its will.  The Border on this island is now an external border of the EU.  The protocol negotiated and agreed between the EU and the UK protects the agreement, underpins continuing North-South co-operation and ensures there is no return to a hard Border.  Unfortunately, the Tory Government in Westminster is threatening to unilaterally derogate from the protocol, acting to pacify the most intransigent radical Brexiteers, disregarding the preferences of the majority of the Northern Irish people.</p> <p>A way forward within and under the framework of the protocol must be found.  That is the collective priority now in the best interests of all the people of Northern Ireland.  The UK Government must re-engaged with the EU in the common effort of finding ways forward within the framework of the protocol.</p> <p>Derogation from the Northern Ireland protocol is not the only example of disastrous unilateral action mooted by the British Government.  The British Government's Northern Ireland Troubles (Legacy and Reconciliation) Bill, which it is attempting to rush through Parliament this week, is a blatant and ugly attempt to deny victims of the Troubles justice and to suppress details of the British state's culpability in acts of violence and terrorism.  The chief commissioner of Northern Ireland's Human Rights Commission, Ms Alyson Kilpatrick, said the Bill violates article 2 of the European Convention on Human Rights and Britain's Human Rights Act 1998.  I know that we can count on our American friends to stand with us as we oppose this perverse Bill which degrades the dignity and memory of the people lost to violence during the conflict in the North of Ireland.</p> <p>In the wake of Brexit, increasingly chaotic British governance and perpetual dysfunction in Stormont, calls for constitutional change in the North of Ireland have become impossible to ignore.  I am chair of Ireland's Future, a civil society organisation working towards responsible preparation for constitutional change.  We have held public meetings across the island of Ireland, in the US and recently at Westminster.  We produce substantial evidence-based contributions to the public debate.  We want to create a dialogue based on reasoned and respectful debate, not fear-mongering and divisive rhetoric.  The scale of ongoing work is remarkable and the constitutional conversation is advancing.  We believe now is the right time to plan properly to give the people of this shared island a choice about their preferred constitutional future.  It is a choice they are likely to exercise in the decade ahead and we must be ready.</p> <p>The Good Friday Agreement offers Northern Ireland a way back to the EU.  It provides a path towards the end of the separation and division of this island.  We have a chance to make the dream of a new and united Ireland a reality.  We believe that US support for this project of constitutional change in Ireland is vital.  We hope that you will be there with us to embark on that new journey.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#PPP00400"><p>Congressman Neal has received great words of praise, all of which are his due.  I ask him to respond to Members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.183" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Richard Neal" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#PPP00500"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach, Senator Mark Daly.  I recognise the ambassador, H.E. Ms Cronin. She has been a terrific friend to Ireland and to me and to she represents America so well.</p> <p>I thought it was remarkable, as I listened to the Senators courteous replies, that we are all still rowing the boat in the same direction.  One of the hardest things in politics, as we all know, is to tell our most ardent friends and supporters that they are not going to get what they want right now.  That is how the Good Friday Agreement was born.  The hardest thing is to walk into a room and say, &ldquo;Stay with us and we will get to where we want to be, even if the moment doesn't dictate how we will get there&rdquo;.  All sides did that to get to the Good Friday Agreement.  As I travel to Belfast tomorrow, my mind will be on somebody else - Mary Ward, another grandmother who left Banbridge.  What is unique about that life is that two left and four stayed.  I will meet some of those relatives again tomorrow.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Mr. Richard Neal:</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The significance of her journey is this: she never returned home.  When she said goodbye that day to her mother and father, whose graves I visited, that was the end of it.  At the post office in Dublin, which was the busiest in the world, again because of the Irish people's regard for the printed word, her lesson was this: she could never return home for a wedding, a funeral, a first communion or a confirmation.  It was writing that kept the memory alive.  When I go up there tomorrow - and I remember what it was like to try to move through Newry to the North - she is going to be on my mind as well.  Looking at the people from the Blasket Islands, the Dingle Peninsula, Banbridge, Roscommon and in between, the fact that all of you agree now on these issues makes our job so much easier as we speak with one voice.  For what Mark and all you in the Seanad have done for me on this occasion, thank you from the United States of America.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052400002#QQQ00200"><p>Last night, I presented Mr. Neal with an Irish flag that had been flown from the same building that Thomas Francis Meagher flew a tricolour from for the first time back in 1848.  When he was asked of its meaning, Meagher said: "The white in the centre signifies a lasting truce between orange and green and I trust that beneath its folds the hands of Irish Protestants and Irish Catholics may be clasped in generous and heroic brotherhood."  I could not imagine that when he said those words nearly 175 years ago, he would imagine that in this Seanad there would be a man who is giving life to those words.  I thank Congressman Neal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-24a.186" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ag 5.52 p.m. go dt&iacute; 10.30 a.m., D&eacute; C&eacute;adaoin, an 25 Bealtaine 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 5.52 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 25 May 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>