<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Rose Conway-Walsh that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State at the Department of Health with special responsibility for disability issues to examine the issue of medical certificates and mobilisation grants to enable people with disabilities and mobility problems to access transport, in particular, the need to examine the requirement for disability to affect the lower limbs in order to be entitled to a medical certificate.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to introduce an independent appeals process under the fair deal scheme to allow a right to appeal for nursing home providers who are unhappy with the fee proposed by the National Treatment Purchase Fund.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the development of, and staffing provision for, a palliative care centre planned by Mayo Roscommon Hospice Foundation at Roscommon University Hospital.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Leas-Chathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>In light of the ever-increasing waiting list for part-time and distance education courses at Ballyhaise Agricultural College, County Cavan, the need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to sanction the necessary temporary education staff so that these courses can proceed without delay.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to comment on reports that munitions being used by Saudi Arabia for indiscriminate bombing of civilians in Yemen may have been transported by US military aircraft through Shannon Airport and that US military midair refuelling planes that passed through Shannon Airport in June, 2016, may have been used to refuel the Saudi Arabian aircraft involved.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Ivana Bacik of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality, in light of recent media reports that an act of female genital mutilation, FGM, has been reported to the HSE and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, to state how many cases of FGM have been reported to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na since the implementation of the Criminal Justice (Female Genital Mutilation) Act 2012; what supports are provided to agencies such as AkiDwA which are working to prevent the incidence of FGM in the community; and if the Government will sign up to the second national action plan on FGM.</blockquote><p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Rose Conway-Walsh, Colm Burke, Frank Feighan and Robbie Gallagher and they will be taken now.  Senators Paul Gavan and Ivana Bacik may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#B00125">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#B00150">Nursing Homes Support Scheme Appeals</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#B00175"><p>As Senator Rose Conway-Walsh is not in the House, we will begin with Senator Colm Burke.  I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Finian McGrath to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#B00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for dealing with this Commencement matter, which relates to the private nursing home sector.  At present, there are over 23,500 people in private nursing home beds under the fair deal scheme.  An issue has been raised with me by representatives of a number of private nursing homes regarding the fact that when the price is fixed - and it is fixed at different levels in different areas - there is no right of appeal for them.  There is no process by which they can have the price that is fixed reviewed.  They have concerns about this because private nursing homes would all have similar costs, including wages, insurance, heating and food but there is a variation in different parts of the country in the price that is set by the NTPF.  The nursing homes do not have any mechanism available to them to have the price reviewed.  It is in that context that I raise this matter and ask that an appeals process be put in place.  I am not saying that everyone would be entitled to appeal but where there are reasonable grounds for an appeal, namely, that the price set does not take into account all of the issues faced by the nursing home on a day-to-day basis, an appeal should be possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#B00300"><p>At the outset, I thank Senator Colm Burke for raising this very important matter.</p> <p>The legislation underpinning the nursing home support scheme requires each private nursing home negotiate and agree a price for long-term residential care services with the National Treatment Purchase Fund, NTPF, should it wish to be an approved nursing home for the purposes of this particular scheme.  The NTPF has statutory independence in the performance of its functions and negotiates with each nursing home on an individual basis.  The Department of Health has no role in such individual negotiations.  The NTPF examines the records and accounts of nursing homes as part of the process with the objective of setting a fair price which delivers value for money to the individual and the State.  In negotiation with the nursing homes, the NTPF has regard to cost reasonably and prudently incurred by the nursing home and evidence of value for money.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The NTPF also has regard to price, prices or prices previously charged, local market price, budgetary constraints and the obligation of the State to use available resources in the most beneficial effective and efficient manner to improve, promote and protect the health and welfare of the public.<br/><br/>When the nursing homes support scheme commenced in 2009, a commitment was made that it would be reviewed after three years.  In advance of the review, which was the subject of an extensive and structured public consultation process, submissions were sought from groups or bodies wishing to make a contribution.  Nursing Homes Ireland made a submission in this regard and sought an appeals system for nursing home providers.<br/><br/>The report of the review was published in July 2015.  A number of issues were identified for more detailed consideration, first, a review of the pricing mechanism of the National Treatment Purchase Fund with a view to ensuring value for money and economy, the lowest possible administrative costs for clients and a minimal administrative burden for providers; second, the need to increase the transparency of the pricing mechanism in order that existing or potential investors can make informed decisions to the greatest extent possible; and, third, to ensure adequate residential capacity for those residents with more complex needs.<br/><br/>Deloitte and Prospectus have been engaged by the National Treatment Purchase Fund to assist in carrying out the review.  They have engaged in extensive stakeholder consultation and this includes Nursing Homes Ireland.  The pricing review will include consideration of the appeals mechanism.  It is not deemed feasible to effectively address this issue in isolation and it must be considered as part of the totality of the pricing system review, which will be completed as soon as possible.  In this context, we need to be careful about placing too much reliance on an appeals system.  There is little point in establishing an appeals system which quickly becomes the default option for almost all of the operators and, therefore, effectively displaces the main price-setting mechanism.  It is more important to develop a robust system that everyone understands and that delivers fair outcomes consistently.  If we can achieve this, an appeals system <i>per se</i>will become far less important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply.  I agree fully with the Minister of State in respect of his last point.  Such an outcome is the last thing we need.  It reminds me of every District Court case that is sent to the Circuit Court, and that is not what I want.  It may be that only one price agreement in every 1,000 is fixed but some mechanism is needed.  The Minister of State referred to arranging this.  Do we have a timescale for when the changes under discussion will be put in place?  Will some mechanism be in place to deal with concerns or cases where someone believes that not all issues have been dealt with in coming to a conclusion about a price fixed for a nursing home bed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#C00300"><p>I thank Senator Colin Burke for raising this important issue.  Since we have over 23,000 people in nursing homes in the State, we have to be vigilant and ensure they have the proper services and prices.</p> <p>Senator Burke raised the issue of no right of appeal.  I will bring his concerns back to the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris.  Of course I take his point about reasonable grounds for an appeal.  That is important.  I also think we should not necessarily blow the idea of a mechanism out of the water.</p> <p>The final issue raised by Senator Burke was on the timescale.  I cannot answer the question directly today, but I will bring it back to the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, and ask him for an update.  I will respond to Senator Burke in the coming days.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.16" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#C00350">Palliative Care Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#C00500"><p>The palliative care centre is one of three major capital projects being developed at Roscommon County Hospital.  I am pleased to report that the &euro;6 million endoscopy project was officially opened recently by the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris.  I am also pleased to report that the Minister, Deputy Harris, has given the green light to an &euro;8 million medical rehabilitation unit at the hospital.  It will serve as a satellite centre from the west of Ireland to D&uacute;n Laoghaire.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frank Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->An eight-bed palliative care unit is the third major capital development being planned on the grounds of Roscommon hospital, bringing the investment to over &euro;20 million.  It is very clear that the demand for palliative care services has never been greater.  It is predicted that the proportion of older people in Ireland will increase by up to 30% over the next decade.  Within the former western health board region, Mayo and Roscommon are predicted to experience the largest increases which consequently will have implications for palliative care services in the region, specifically the number and volume of services required.  The report of the national advisory committee on palliative care in 2001 recommended that there should be up to ten specialists inpatient beds for every 100,000 of population with at least one inpatient unit in each of the former ten health board areas.</p><p>Unfortunately, no such facility exists in Roscommon and this often leads to crisis admissions to acute hospitals, waits and long travel to hospice or hospital facilities in Galway and Dublin away from family and friends.  People who are very ill, and their families, should not have to go through this.  It is unacceptable.</p><p>The good news is the proposed building of an eight-bed palliative care unit on the grounds of Roscommon hospital.  This is very welcome and timely.  This has been going on for the past three or four years.  The unit will provide inpatient day care and community palliative care services to patients with advanced life-limiting illnesses in County Roscommon.  The key to the success of this project is the recruitment of appropriate staff with the necessary skills to deliver quality palliative care and through its great work, the Mayo Roscommon Hospice will fully fund the building costs of the Roscommon project.  The last Minister for Health was very committed to funding staff costs.  This is one of three projects and it has been working very closely with the endoscopy unit, which is already built and with the rehabilitation unit for which the funding has been allocated to get the go-ahead.  I believe the Mayo Roscommon Hospice will provide funding of &euro;5 million but the main issue is the need for the HSE to fund the staffing.  Where exactly is this agreement? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Feighan for raising this very important issue.  I know he is a passionate supporter of, and campaigner for, palliative care centres, particularly in the Mayo-Roscommon area.  It is one of the great success stories of our age that so many more people are living for so much longer.  While many older people enjoy good health for most of their lives, there will also inevitably be increased numbers of people living in the community with chronic diseases and life-limiting illnesses.  As a society, we need to plan now to meet the needs of these people and palliative care is one of the components that we must think about and prepare for, hence I support Senator Feighan's proposal today.  It is the intention of the Government that people will be provided with the type of palliative care services they need, regardless of what diagnosis they have, how old they are or whether they die in a hospice, an acute hospital, a nursing home or at home.  Significant progress has been made in recent years in improving access to specialist palliative care services.  We now have 202 specialist inpatient palliative care beds in ten locations across the country.  That total will rise to 217 once the 15 beds planned for Kerry Hospice are open.  The HSE is also working closely with local hospice groups in several locations to ensure equity of access to specialist palliative care across the country.  All HSE areas have community specialist palliative home care teams.  There are 38 acute hospital specialist palliative care teams across the country and over 170 palliative care support beds in around 80 locations around the country.  At present 92% of people receive specialist palliative care services in the community within seven days of referral while 97% have access to a specialist bed within seven days.  That is a figure we should all be proud of.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> There are, of course, issues that remain to be tackled.  Senator Feighan asked about the palliative care centre at Roscommon University Hospital.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, recently met with the representatives of the Mayo Roscommon Hospice Foundation to discuss the development of the new unit.  The hospice group is working closely with the local Health Service Executive community health organisation and the Saolta hospital group to progress the development of the proposed eight-bed unit, which will be built on the grounds of Roscommon University Hospital.</p><p>With regard to the allocation of Exchequer funding, the HSE's first priority in the region is the opening of the 14-bed special palliative care inpatient hospice in Mayo.  That unit is due to open in 2018.  The HSE will continue to work closely with the Mayo Roscommon Hospice Foundation to agree the financial and staffing requirements for the new unit.  The required funding will be included by the HSE in its annual Estimates request as soon as is feasible.  The successful development of palliative care services in Ireland has been based on a long-standing tradition of positive engagement between the voluntary, statutory and private sectors.  Organisations such as Mayo Roscommon Hospice Foundation have a vital role to play in this work, both by initiating programmes and by collaborating with the HSE in a positive way on a range of fronts to strengthen the provision of palliative care.  The Minister looks forward to continuing to work on this collaborative basis in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#E00200"><p>I am delighted to be the politician who set up the meeting between the Minister and the Mayo Roscommon Hospice Foundation.  Unfortunately, I could not attend as I was getting an ECG in hospital and did not realise how long it would take.  I went in at 3 p.m. and left at 9 p.m.  I pay tribute to the competency of the staff and surgeons at the Mater Hospital.  I saw at first hand the difficult work they do.</p> <p>I welcome the significant developments at Roscommon University Hospital, which serve as a strong reminder that the hospital is very much open for business.  In fact, it has never been busier, which the critics did not envisage five years ago.  Roscommon is a shining example to all small hospitals around the country.  I take this opportunity to commend the air ambulance service, which saves dozens of lives in towns and villages throughout Roscommon and the wider region.  I look forward to the continued development of the palliative care unit in order finally to address the critical lack of inpatient hospice facilities in County Roscommon.</p> <p>I pay tribute to Ms Cynthia Clampett, Mr. John Murphy and everyone involved in the Mayo Roscommon Hospice Foundation for their hard work and commitment to improving palliative care services and enhancing the quality of life of people in both counties.  I look forward to the Minister making an announcement in the coming weeks that the staffing for this vital facility will be progressed.  I thank the Minister of State for all the work he is doing in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#E00300"><p>I take the Senator's points about the long waiting and travel times for people with serious illnesses.  It is an issue that requires our focus.  However, the main message I will take back to the Minister is the need to progress the staffing issue.  I am pleased to hear the Senator received great care in the Mater Hospital and am glad to see him well.  I strongly agree with his comments on the magnificent work done by the staff at Roscommon hospital and the brave and caring work of the hospice movement in Roscommon and throughout the country.  Hospice staff provide a great service and have an excellent relationship with the voluntary and public sectors.  There is a warmth and energy there which one does not always see in other services.  It is something of which we can all be proud.  I assure the Senator that I will bring the message regarding the staffing requirement directly to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#E00400"><p>Unfortunately, there has been a breakdown in communication with Senator Conway-Walsh.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Leas-Chathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->She has withdrawn her matter which we will take on Thursday.  I thank the Minister of State and call Senator Robbie Gallagher.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.25" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#F00150">Agricultural Colleges Courses</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#F00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it go dt&iacute; an Teach seo inniu fosta.  There are already 460 students completing part-time and distance education programmes in Ballyhaise Agricultural College, County Cavan, and there is a commitment that an additional 105 students will start those programmes before the end of 2016.  There are 605 students on a waiting list in Ballyhaise Agricultural College to complete these courses.  To commence additional new courses, Teagasc would require sanction for temporary education staff on a two year contract basis as the contracts for some of the existing temporary staff are due to expire by the end of 2016.  Currently, Teagasc has no commitment from the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine on education staff for 2017 and, as such, it is unable to plan any further courses at this time until this staffing situation is resolved.</p> <p>The green certificate qualifies a person as a trained farmer, and that could be in horticulture, agriculture, forestry or equine studies.  It is, first and foremost, about education.  Having a green certificate is one of the conditions of stamp duty exemption and a transfer of land to a son or a daughter.  It also meets the criteria for schemes or grants that may be available from time to time.  In other words, it is about incentivising education.  It has been hugely successful in educating young farmers in proven farm practices, and in incentivising the succession of farms.</p> <p>As the Minister of State is aware, the contribution by the agricultural community to the economy of this country is immense.  Thousands of jobs depend on it.  At the very foundation of its success are the primary producers, the farmers, working the land, milking the cows and growing the crops.  We can all see how agriculture has developed and changed over the decades.  Our farmers and our agribusiness compete on global markets.  Each generation of farmers brings new methods and better ways of doing things.  Education and the green cert is central to all of that.  I ask the Minister to sanction the funding necessary for the colleges to put the required staff in place to ensure that these very worthwhile courses can commence and be completed without delay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#F00300"><p>I thank Senator Gallagher for raising this matter.  On my own behalf and on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Creed, I wish to thank Teagasc education staff for their hard work and dedication in managing the unprecedented demand for the adult green certificate programme, which is delivered on a part-time and distance education basis at Teagasc agricultural colleges and at its local and regional education centres.</p> <p>While I am not in a position to comment on the staffing issues that pertain in particular locations as that is an internal operational matter for Teagasc and not the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, I understand that Teagasc target available teaching resources where demand for training courses is greatest.  The Department has worked closely with Teagasc to address staffing issues with regard to the delivery of the adult green certificate programme.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Andrew Doyle:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2170"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2170&amp;amp;pid=AndrewDoyle&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The current exceptional demand reflects renewed interest and opportunities in agriculture but is also directly linked to the educational requirements of the young farmers scheme and the national reserve, which require applicants to have a prescribed level 6 agriculture qualification - a green certificate or an equivalent in order to qualify for payment.  This was to ensure that payments were targeted at trained young farmers with a genuine interest in farming as a career.  Approximately, 2,000 young farmers require places on the adult green cert arising from the education requirements of the young farmers scheme and the national reserve.  The Department was concerned that if the additional green certificate places were not made available, young farmers who would otherwise qualify for EU-funded payments would be refused payment or would fail to qualify for full payment.</p><p>In order to address this situation, it was agreed that the additional temporary resources would be provided to Teagasc to enable it to rapidly expand the number of green certificate places and clear the backlog of applications in the shortest possible timeframe.  In conjunction with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, Teagasc was approved to appoint 20 new temporary education officers in 2014 and again in mid-2015 on two-year employment contracts.  It enabled Teagasc to dramatically increase enrolments from a typical year of 500 to over 1,500.  As Teagasc continued to experience strong demand for the adult green certificate over and above the pre-existing high levels of demand, it was allocated 30 temporary posts in November 2015 bringing the overall number of teaching posts sanctioned to 70.  In addition, the Department also approved seven temporary administrative staff for a two-year period to address the huge volume of course administration that arose from the unprecedented demand.</p><p>I understand, that while a small number of temporary teachers have still to be recruited by Teagasc, most have been hired and are now working on the green cert programme helping to deliver record numbers of enrolments, which are forecasted to top 4,500 for the period 2014 to 2016.  It is our expectation that the 70 additional posts will substantially clear the backlog of applications for the adult green certificate ensuring that those young farmers who formally applied for a place can be accommodated.  The question of renewing some of these posts for a further two-year period was raised with my Department recently.  However, it is important to note that the conditions attached by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform stipulate that all temporary contracts - 77 in total - must be phased out as their expiration dates arise.  In addition, under the delegated sanction framework governing staff numbers in Teagasc, there is a prohibition on the establishment of contracts of indefinite duration for temporary staff, which would arise in this instance if the 77 temporary contracts approved to date were renewed for a further two-year period.</p><p>More generally, the agreed delegated sanction arrangements for Teagasc provide it with greater flexibility over permanent staff appointments in research, advisory and education.  The arrangements enable Teagasc to replace staff when they retire and to make 75 new permanent appointments, subject to compliance with multi-annual pay ceilings.  While Teagasc must remain within its overall pay budget, the flexibility provided by the new arrangements will allow it to fill critical vacancies and to react faster when such vacancies arise in the future.  I understand some appointments have been made in the education area to meet the current demand for places.  Within the parameters of that overarching policy, the question of allocating additional resources to particular locations remains an operational matter for Teagasc.  The arrangements implemented to date have greatly assisted Teagasc in meeting the current exceptional demand for the adult green certificate.  Of course, the training of so many young farmers since 2014, which is 4,500 to date, is a very positive development for the agrifood sector both in terms of supporting structural adjustment and encouraging young educated farmers to remain in and enter farming.  In prioritising supports for trained young farmers under the young farmers scheme and the national reserve, the Minister believes we can look forward to an increasing number of young farmers playing a central role in the future development of the agricultural sector in the years ahead.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Andrew Doyle:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2170"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2170&amp;amp;pid=AndrewDoyle&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister, Deputy Creed, and I commend the Teagasc education staff on its proactive approach to enrolling such exceptional volumes in a very short time.  We know that Teagasc teachers give substantial time and commitment over and above their everyday responsibilities in training the next generation of farmers and encouraging the adoption of new technology and practices on Irish farms.  The Department was pleased to secure approval for 77 temporary posts to enable Teagasc to provide almost 3,000 extra green certificate places that would otherwise not have been made available.  The allocation of 75 new permanent posts will also greatly assist Teagasc in delivering services to the farming sector, including education and training.</p><p>As can be expected, the young farmers scheme and national reserve has stimulated added interest in the adult green certificate among other farmers who have registered an interest with Teagasc in completing the course.  It is not apparent, at this stage, how many of those expressions of interest will convert into formal applications.  Historically, leakage between expressions of interest and formal applications is approximately 50%, however current demand may be stronger.  My Department has asked Teagasc to explore other staffing measures beyond temporary recruitment to ensure any residual demand for the green certificate can be accommodated within a realistic timeframe.  The Department will continue to monitor the green certificate situation in Teagasc closely.  Sorry, I have to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#H00200"><p>The D&aacute;il bell is ringing.  We had better excuse the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#H00300"><p>I have to go, but I am a graduate of the farm apprentice scheme.  I did my first year exams in Ballyhaise.  I appreciate the value of it and I will be there launching a timber harvesting simulator course.  I understand the need to get as many people in as quickly as possible.  I am sorry I have to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#H00400"><p>We understand.  Is that all right, Senator?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#H00500"><p>I understand.  Perhaps the Minister might have a look at the specific case and the fact that some education providers' contracts are expiring at the end of the year and people cannot complete the courses they commenced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#H00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.35" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3 .05 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.36" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#N00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on agricultural product prices and the decision by the United Kingdom to leave the European Union, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to conclude not later than 6.30 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be called upon to reply not later than 6.25 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#N00300"><p>Today I would like to raise an issue that I have raised three times previously concerning staffing levels at the Assumption girls national school in Walkinstown.  I wish to propose an amendment to the Order of Business to invite the Minister for Education and Skills to address the House on this matter, as this is my third time raising it but nothing has been done.</p> <p>The aforementioned school applied for developing school status earlier this year and was granted two extra classes.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Ultimately, due to the housing and homelessness crisis, it caused many families in the area to move outside of the catchment area, leaving the school short of seven pupils immediately before the return of the school term.</p><p>It is understood today that the Department of Education and Skills sent a letter to the school refusing the appeal, ultimately ensuring that a teacher will have to be let go this Friday.  The school is in the very heart of Dublin 12, where we have considerable anti-social behaviour - much of the gangland crime we describe stems from this area.  All of this means that children in this area will lose a teacher.  It means that the classes of 90 pupils in the school will have to merge and there will be a merged fifth and sixth class.  Ultimately, this means there will be three larger classes with pupil-teacher ratios of 30:1, well above the EU and Irish averages.  This is in a school in the heart of one of the most disadvantaged parts of Dublin city.  It would not happen in more affluent parts of Dublin city or in any other part of the country.  </p><p>On this basis I am asking for the Minister for Education and Skills to address the House today, explain why the matter has not been addressed properly and to give the House some answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O00200"><p>The House will be aware that the Seanad Bill has now passed Second Stage and is awaiting debate on Committee Stage.  Obviously, it is a matter for the groups to determine when Committee Stage hearings should commence.</p> <p>It occurs to me that perhaps we need a little more clarification from the Government, in particular, before we embark on that process.  I am addressing my point to the Leader, as the spokesman of the Government in the House.  As I understand it, a programme for Government was agreed which stipulated, among other things, that the report of the Manning committee would be implemented.  The Taoiseach has come to the House and spoken about his commitment to this project.  The Members of the other House are under the impression, as I understand it, that the Government is committed to this enterprise.  Presumably, the parties that support the Government, including the Independent Alliance, Fine Gael and the other Independent Members, are committed to the forwarding of this proposal.</p> <p>It seems to me, therefore, that there should be no doubt about the intentions of the Government in respect of this Bill.  I was a little disturbed when I discovered recently that a Member had described this Bill as a Bill of Senators Michael McDowell, Gerard Craughwell, Victor Boyhan, Frances Black and John Dolan.  That is because the Bill is supported by many other Members and it carried their signature.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O00300"><p>Who was it?  Name and shame the Member.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O00400"><p>Can the Chair clarify the matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O00500"><p>I am duty bound to remain silent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O00600"><p>The interesting point is that, with the exception of myself, all the people mentioned as being proposers of this Bill were elected to the House by county councillors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O00700"><p>They were all nominated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O00800"><p>The letter in which they were so categorised and loaded into the same group as myself was addressed to every county councillor in the country, as far as I can see.  This raises the question of why it would be that anyone would so misrepresent the proposals of the Bill in such a way as to somehow excite opposition against them among their electorate.  That raises a further question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O00900"><p>One should not presume anything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O01000"><p>God, Senator McDowell is raising a lot of questions today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O01100"><p>Which Member would be so inexperienced as to make a mistake of that kind?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O01200"><p>A schoolboy error.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#O01300"><p>Why would a Member forget that many other Members have proposed this Bill?  It comes down to this point.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Is the Government committed to what is in the programme for Government, the implementation of the Manning report on the reform of this House?  Is the Leader having difficulty persuading some of his colleagues that they should support the Government on this issue-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P00200"><p>They do not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P00300"><p>Do we need to bring the Taoiseach in here again so that they can hear it from his own lips that he supports this Bill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P00400"><p>Not before Christmas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P00600"><p>I will not embarrass the individual who wrote this letter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P00700"><p>Do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P00800"><p>I would never do such a thing but should this House not at this point seek clarity from the Government as to where its commitment lies?</p> <p>I look forward to Committee Stage of this Bill being brought forward early.  The Leader should take this opportunity on the Order of Business to make it clear that the Government stands behind the programme for Government, that the Fine Gael Party is united in support of the Taoiseach on this measure and that letters of this kind really are not very helpful to the process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.59" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P01000"><p>He deserves it.  Order in the House.  I call Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P01100"><p>I am glad that cleared that up.</p> <p>I refer to the report on media ownership in Ireland that my Sinn F&eacute;in colleague, Lynn Boylan, MEP, launched yesterday.  The report, which examines the effect the concentration of media ownership has on the democratic process, was compiled by Caoilfhionn Gallagher and Jonathan Price of Doughty Street Chambers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P01200"><p>The Senator must not name people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P01300"><p>-----and Gavin Booth - I think the authors of this report should be commended &ndash; and Darragh Mackin of KRW Law.  I acknowledge Lynn&rsquo;s initiative and steadfastness in confronting the elephant in the room of Irish politics and media.</p> <p>The report states: &ldquo;we consider there to be a perfect storm which poses grave risks to freedom of expression and media pluralism in the Irish market&rdquo;.  There you have it.  The control of Irish media, combined with the sustained and regular threats of legal action by one well-known billionaire to media organisations and journalists who are engaged in news gathering or reporting his activities, is a threat to Irish democracy.  I, like the authors of this report, believe that imperative and urgent action needs to be taken.</p> <p>I urge the Government to carry out the recommendations of the authors immediately to establish a cross-disciplinary commission of inquiry to examine the issues and make concrete recommendations within a tight timeframe.  There is a fear that because the legislation as laid out is not retrospective, it has merely cemented the position of the aforementioned individual and means that no one can now come near him in terms of market control.  It is my understanding that there is no legal or constitutional bar to the retrospective application of the Competition and Consumer Protection Act 2014.  This is important as it negates any claim by the Government to be powerless to act due to private property concerns.  The Seanad would be an ideal forum in which to scrutinise this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P01400"><p>As there is no one here from the Civil Engagement group, I will exercise some discretion and call on the father of the House, Senator Norris.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P01500"><p>Uncharacteristically, I have nothing to say.  I find myself listening in admiration to my colleagues.  I very much appreciate the Leas-Chathaoirleach&rsquo;s kind sentiments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P01600"><p>I interpreted the Senator&rsquo;s earlier interjection as meaning that he had something to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#P01700"><p>It is clear to everyone that the Government has no industrial relations strategy whatsoever.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Four weeks ago today, this House approved a Labour Party motion proposing to establish an employer-labour conference to address some of the massive and unprecedented industrial relations issues facing the country.  Since the passage of that motion, we have had rank and file members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and members of the Association of Garda Sergeants and Inspectors voting to withdraw their labour.  In addition, members of the Association of Secondary Teachers in Ireland, ASTI, have decided to take strike action.  The Government is drowning under a tsunami of industrial relations problems and does not have a clue how to go about resolving them.  Our motion was designed to assist the Government in digging itself out of a hole.  What has the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation done to progress the motion we passed?  Is the Government essentially ignoring the democratic decision of this House?  We offered advice on a plate to the Government as to how it could be assisted in resolving some of the major industrial relations issues confronting the country.  If this is new politics, I would like to see the old politics back, and quickly.</p><p>The Government is tone deaf on industrial relations and has no idea how to resolve the problems piling up on Ministers' desks.  When Members advise the Government as to how it might proceed, by introducing a mechanism such as an employer-labour conference, they are apparently given the two-fingered salute.  In the meantime, the problems mount up day in and day out as large numbers of public servants prepare this week to withdraw their labour.  Members expect the Leader to vindicate the rights of this House and ensure the motions that come from it go through the correct process and are implemented by Government.  We have yet to see any sign of that in this case.  What has happened to the motion passed just four weeks ago in this Chamber?  If the answer is that it cannot be implemented, what then is the point of Members passing motions, only for them to be given the two fingers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Q00200"><p>The only silver lining surrounding the dark cloud that is Brexit is the prospect that we might attract additional inward international investment into this country.  IDA Ireland acted very swiftly in sending out 1,400 invitations to companies internationally asking them to consider Ireland as a location in the context of the UK's departure from the European Union.  That was a welcome initiative.  I was pleased, too, to read in the newspapers at the weekend that the Taoiseach is apparently engaged in negotiations with several banks in Britain on their possible relocation here.  All of that is encouraging.  Will the Leader arrange a debate with the relevant Minister or Ministers to discuss how far the IDA Ireland initiative is going, the reaction it is getting, how likely we are to attract new banking and financial services operations here and, critically, whether we will be able to attract new inward investment to the Border region, which is the area most affected by Brexit?  I would like to see counties like Cavan and Monaghan, which already are disadvantaged by virtue of their location on the Border, receiving preferential treatment and the support systems necessary to attract industry.  I seek a debate on how we can go about grasping the only straw of hope in the Brexit scenario.  We need to know what is being done to attract industry, what the response has been to efforts in that regard, how optimistic are the relevant agencies, what we can do to assist and what is the position in regard to financial services and banking.  There is no more relevant or urgent debate we could have and I hope the Leader will arrange it as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Q00300"><p>Will the Leader consider scheduling sittings of the House next week given that we are back only four weeks?  A newspaper in his native Cork pointed out yesterday that in the first three weeks we were back, we had 33 hours and 30 minutes of statements.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Much of that was on Brexit, which is being dealt with by a number of committees and in the D&aacute;il, but we have only spent eight hours and 15 minutes in total debating legislation.  The Labour Party, the Civil Engagement group and other groups have Bills on the Order Paper that could be moved next week.  In light of the fact that work on so much legislation needs to be done and that very little has been done because so much time was taken up at the start of the year with the formation of Government and we are only now in a position to do legislative work, which is what this House and the other House are designed to do, we should consider getting some legislation moving through the Houses to ensure we do our job here.  On average, only 50 Bills are passed by the D&aacute;il and the Seanad in a calendar year.  By the time we get to the end of this year we will have done perhaps one third or one quarter of what should normally be done by the Houses of the Oireachtas.  Much was made about the issue of scrutiny of EU legislation and directives.  Under Standing Orders, there is a requirement to set up a committee on EU legislation.  I ask the Leader when that committee will be established, the way it will be structured and, importantly for the Members, how it will be resourced to ensure that legislation is not simply rammed through the House.  EU directives account for 90% of the laws that come into effect in this country, many of which are needed but some of which may have a detrimental effect here.  They are not getting the scrutiny they should get and that is required under Standing Orders.  I ask the Leader to consider the sitting of the House next week in light of the fact that since the summer, and as of this week, we are only back four weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R00200"><p>I want to raise an issue I am extremely passionate about.  I encourage the Members present to engage with the facts in the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill, Committee Stage of which will be taken in this House tomorrow.  My entry point to this issue is the impact of alcohol-related harm, which I witness every day through my work with the RISE Foundation.  I really believe that, as a nation, we are in denial.  Our relationship with alcohol is so twisted in our culture and psyche, it is often difficult to untangle it and see clearly.  I appreciate that Members are being inundated with representations from small shopkeepers.  My parents were small shopkeepers, and I understand the problems small shopkeepers have to deal with on a daily basis and the pressures they face.  As I have been receiving the e-mails I have been thinking of my parents and small shopkeepers, but the reality is that the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill is about saving lives in the very communities in which those shops are located, such as the small rural areas we are hearing from.</p> <p>I am not anti-business.  I believe the proposals in the Bill are workable but, sadly, the drinks industry is twisting the reality.  Why do we allow the drinks industry to dictate public policy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R00300"><p>I am sorry, Senator, but that matter is on the agenda and it will be debated on Committee Stage tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R00400"><p>I want to make it clear that I am looking forward to the debate tomorrow.  I hope to have time to debate each amendment, and I ask the Leader to encourage fellow Senators to stand together and support the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R00500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R00600"><p>-----but I want to make an important point about the drinks industry.  The lobbying that has been going on, which needs to be raised here today, has been over the top.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R00700"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R00800"><p>I have seen it myself, and it is not right.  I am a new Member of the Seanad and I cannot believe the power it has.  I needed to make that point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R00900"><p>I think all sides have been busy lobbying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#R01000"><p>I raise the matter of the relocation of the Seanad again, given the concerns expressed yesterday in the national media by academics about the planned use of the National Museum of Ireland and the associated costs.  We must ask the question again.  Why can we not look to the regions for an alternative site or at least explore that option?  This move will continue to be highlighted in the national media.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frank Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I probably do it myself in some ways.  If we cannot find accommodation in the city of Dublin, perhaps it is time to move around the country.  I remember how, in 2000, the Fianna F&aacute;il-Progressive Democrats Cabinet met at the regional assembly in Ballaghadereen.  The regional assembly is still there and would be very happy to ask the Seanad to relocate to its location.  If we are talking about bringing politics to the people, perhaps this is an opportunity.  I know the secretariat is working extremely hard but there are turf wars here and it is bringing the reputation of the Seanad into disrepute.  As Senators, we do not mind where we sit but we want to get this sorted sooner rather than later.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S00200"><p>That matter has been dealt with so we should not be discussing it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S00300"><p>It will be dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S00400"><p>It has been dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S00500"><p>I read this in the national newspapers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S00600"><p>The Senator cannot believe everything he reads.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S00700"><p>That is good.  It is nice to see that it has been dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S00800"><p>The Senator should read the "Indo".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S00900"><p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh should write that on his letters as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S01000"><p>There is a difference between correspondence and the media.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S01100"><p>I understand that I have the floor.  I compliment the Ulster GAA county board - and everyone else involved - on the work relating to the Casement Park project in west Belfast.  This is very good news.  Having such a wonderful venue will undoubtedly be a huge boost to Ulster GAA and GAA followers.  I wish Ulster GAA the very best and look forward to the stadium being completed by 2019.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S01200"><p>The Leader knows that I previously raised the issue of the huge gap in infrastructure linking Dublin with Derry, Donegal, Tyrone, namely, the north-west of our island and the 500,000 people who live there.  I asked the Leader to request that the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to come to the Chamber to debate the issues involved.  I will outline them again.  They include: to the failure of the Government to invest even one cent in the City of Derry Airport in recent years even though it is used by 150,000 people from Donegal - 40% of the total number of passengers who pass through the facility - each year/ and the failure to give real commitments with regard to funding the A5, which is a vital dual carriageway linking the north west to Dublin.  Added to that are the issues raised in this Chamber, namely, the Cork-Limerick road, the gridlock on the M50 and the threat of the loss of Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann routes.  These are all really serious issues of concern relating to transport.  I have raised issues relating to the north west but I am conscious other colleagues have raised issues of concern as well.  I ask the Leader to ask the Minister, who is a former Senator, to come to the House to debate these matters with us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#S01300"><p>I apologise for having indicated previously that I did not have something to say.  I do have something to say and it relates to a matter I take very seriously indeed, namely, the coverage by the media of the proceedings of this House.  A week or so ago, we had a very important debate about CETA on a motion sponsored by Senator Higgins.  This led to a defeat for the Government on a very significant matter that is now being debated widely in Europe.  It appears as if this agreement is in great difficulty for certain reasons, some of which were highlighted in this House.  There was not a single whisper about the matter but when a Member of the Lower House referred to it in passing on the Order of Business, it was the subject of a half-page report in the newspapers.  Last week, the Recognition of Irish Sign Language for the Deaf Community Bill 2016, sponsored by Senator Mark Daly, was debated in the Seanad.  This is a very important matter - one of fundamental human rights.  It relates to just 5,000 people and 35,000 of their family members and friends but it is a very significant matter.  This Bill was passed by the House.  There was not a single word about it.  I ask the Leader to contact the broadcasting unit and find out what political intelligence is brought to bear on selecting topics to be broadcast.  We are sometimes dismissed as a talking shop.  Of course, we are.  That is what the word "parliament" means - "parlement" or" talking".  It is very important because we talk on behalf of the citizens of Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We help to bring issues that are otherwise concealed before the public imagination.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00200"><p>No doubt, the Senator may also write.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00300"><p>I will leave the writing to you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00400"><p><i>Touch&eacute;</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00450"><p>Enough of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00500"><p>It is very important that we are not frustrated in this by a lazy or temperamental intelligence guiding what is broadcast.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00600"><p>Would the Leader invite the Minister here to discuss water and sewage?  We will not say "Irish Water", given that it seems to be gone into the history books.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00700"><p>We will say "Irish sewage".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00800"><p>In my local town, Trim, planning permission has been given for 365 new houses, which is very welcome.  However, last year &euro;1.3 million was allocated for the sewerage plant in Trim.  The plant is 35 years old and is creaking.  Raw sewage is leaking out of it.  The water quality is not great.  This &euro;1.3 million has disappeared since Irish Water went off the playing pitch.  As we move on and the economy improves, new developments and houses will be planned, and we need proper infrastructure.  In my area we have the likes of Ballivor, where a hose pipe is bringing water from the reservoir to the houses.  In Kildalkey and Longwood there is no water pressure whatsoever.  We are in the suburbs of Dublin and this is the start of the building, which is welcome, but we need infrastructure.  We are not getting forward planning.  It is backwards we are going.  I would like the Minister to come here and tell us the plan for water and sewerage schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#T00900"><p>I ask the Leader to call in the Minister for Health.  I read in this morning's edition of the <i>Irish Examiner</i>that four new maternity hospitals are needed across the country.  Nearly on a monthly basis I have raised the shame that although we have agreement to build a new national maternity hospital at St. Vincent's University Hospital, Elm Park, we have been waiting ten months for planning permission to be lodged.  What we got is an internal turf war.  It is no longer good enough to hear mediation is happening.  We need action.  The health of women and children seems to be always pushed to the bottom of the queue.  If people want to have a war over who is going to control the budget or who will be members of the board, let them have it.  But let us build a new national maternity hospital.  The funding is agreed.  There is &euro;150 million waiting to be called down.  It is frustrating to hear, over and over again, that there is no agreement.</p><p>I have raised this on the Commencement debate and on the Order of Business, and it has been highlighted by a national newspaper, the <i>Irish Examiner</i>.  Maternity hospitals across the country are in crisis.  We need four new maternity hospitals properly staffed and resourced.  Although we have agreement to build one, because of a turf war we cannot even apply for planning permission.  It is unacceptable and the House should not find it acceptable.  We need the Minister to come here and answer questions about why it has been delayed and why 10,000 children who are born in the National Maternity Hospital every year, and 8,000 women, will be put at risk.  In the other House, we are arguing about repealing the eighth amendment to the Constitution, and it is important.  However, this issue is being overlooked.  We need the Minister to come here and answer very clear questions on why the new national maternity hospital has not gone to planning permission and why we do not have a proper maternity service for the women and children of the country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is unacceptable that a turf war should delay this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U00200"><p>Before continuing, I welcome Dr. Ashwani Kumar, the former Minister of Law and Justice in India, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U00300"><p>I join in the Leas-Chathaoirleach's welcome.  Interestingly, a subject of debate today is that of letters being sent to councillors.  I understand that the Leas-Chathaoirleach is the subject of the former Minister, Senator McDowell's comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U00400"><p>Please, one should not presume anything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.108" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U00600"><p>One should assume nothing.  I accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U00700"><p>The Senator should not make-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U00800"><p>Senator Leyden should not make statements like that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.112" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01000"><p>I second Senator Ardagh's amendment to the Order of Business.  Will the Leader arrange for Second Stage of my Registration of Wills Bill 2016, which is No. 9 on the Order Paper, to be taken next week?  It would be appropriate, as the best will in the world week has just concluded.  It entailed solicitors making wills for approximately &euro;50 each.  My Bill would be an opportunity to highlight this issue.  It was debated by three Seanaid and was passed by two.  It was on Second Stage in the previous Seanad.  I pay tribute to the late Brian Lenihan for his support and assistance in that regard.  If we are sitting next week, I ask that my Bill be debated.</p> <p>Senator Black mentioned the intoxicating liquor Bill.  The Sunday newspapers, all large stores, for example, Dunnes Stores, Tesco, SuperValu, Mace, Londis, Musgrave, and RGDATA support-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01100"><p>Committee Stage will be taken tomorrow.  I have already ruled on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01200"><p>Yes, but I just want to make a point.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach probably likes a small glass of brandy sometimes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01300"><p>Not necessarily, but anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01400"><p>One can buy a bottle of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01500"><p>That is very unparliamentary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.119" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01700"><p>Senator Leyden should withdraw that comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01800"><p>Order, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U01900"><p>If the Leas-Chathaoirleach does not drink brandy, I will withdraw the comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02000"><p>I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02100"><p>I regret that.  I think that a glass of wine is more his tipple.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02200"><p>It-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.126" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02400"><p>A bottle of brandy advertised last Sunday in the newspapers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02500"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02600"><p>-----cost &euro;32.  Today, the wholesale price for that bottle at a cash-and-carry is &euro;35.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02700"><p>Who was the Minister who changed that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02800"><p>It is drawing people in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U02900"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03000"><p>Close the D&aacute;il bar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03100"><p>A bottle of gin was &euro;20, but costs &euro;22.50-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03200"><p>Who was the Minister who changed the groceries order?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03300"><p>The Senators will have to carry this on outside the House.  Senator Leyden's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03400"><p>I am sorry, but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03500"><p>The Senator's time on the Order of Business is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03600"><p>This is a forerunner to the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03700"><p>Make your point quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03800"><p>The Sunday newspapers carried six pages of advertising.  All of the media is involved in the issue of below-cost selling-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U03900"><p>There is a conflict of interest here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04000"><p>Senator Leyden can elaborate on that further tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04100"><p>-----because it pays the wages of journalists and the newspapers' owners.  This is a serious issue.  Coming up to Christmas, customers will be drawn in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04200"><p>The Senator can make his points tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04300"><p>-----through below-cost selling.  Housewives will be brought in and encouraged to take a bottle of brandy, gin or vodka.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04400"><p>The Senator is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04500"><p>It is a serious issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04600"><p>Please, resume your seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04700"><p>I will be in order tomorrow when the Bill is being debated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04800"><p>Yes.  Resume your seat now, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U04900"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.  He was in order when he sent out the letter to councillors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U05000"><p>I support Senator Black's comments on the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill.  We cannot continue to ignore the fact that we have a major cultural problem.  I am sceptical as to the results that we will achieve through these small measures because a more fundamental shift needs to occur in terms of alcohol.  I look forward to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U05100"><p>There will be more than three hours of debate tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U05200"><p>I am finished.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U05300"><p>I have ruled on the issue.  This is the third time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#U05400"><p>Tackling obesity is a matter that I have raised numerous times.  Recently, I researched a UK study that revealed that, when weight loss management programmes were recommended by general practitioners, GPs, to patients, 40% of those patients lost an average of 2.3 kg, which is a significant amount of weight.  Possibly as a result of our culture, GPs often struggle to raise the issue of obesity with their patients out of fear of causing offence or that a consultation will take too much time.  However, they would not ignore a melanoma or tumour on a patient's face.  We should not skirt around the issue of obesity.</p> <p>The study showed positive results overall.  Of those offered a weight management programme, 77% accepted and 40% of those lost significant amounts of weight.  Such a measure is available in Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I think we should be introducing this sort of format for patients - our citizens - and their GPs.  If we were to invest in tackling this at an early stage, it would reduce the vast amount of money being spent in our health services on obesity-related illnesses.  I have already called for a debate in this House on obesity, particularly childhood obesity.  I hope it will take place soon.  I look forward to exploring this issue further then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#V00200"><p>I had a lovely long weekend in Ballykissane, County Kerry, with neighbours and friends from my own parish of St. Matthew's in Ballymacarrett.  We were there to remember a fellow man from our parish, Charles Monahan, who tragically lost his life on Good Friday 1916 as he went to meet Roger Casement, who was coming in on the <i>Aud</i>.  I am sorry I did not see the Leas-Chathaoirleach when I was in County Kerry.</p><p>I met members of the Northern Ireland Youth Forum this morning to discuss a number of cross-Border issues.  They are eager to engage with the youth forum here in the South.  We might be able to facilitate that kind of engagement.  As the Leader can imagine, Brexit was one of the main issues in our discussion.  The Northern Ireland Youth Forum has written to the Taoiseach to seek to be included in the national dialogue, or to have advocates for or representatives of the youth sector involved in that process.  Numerous sectors and walks of life are represented at the youth forum.  I ask the Leader to convey to the Government the message that a broad range of young people are very keen to engage with the national dialogue on this issue.  I think we should do everything we can to assist them and bolster their opportunities to get involved.</p><p>As we know, the implications of and fallout from Brexit will be most acutely felt by young people in the first instance.  As they grow and develop into the uncertainty and the unknown dynamics of a post-Brexit scenario, they will be affected as workers and students.  Brexit will have an impact on their rights as citizens, their ability to travel and their capacity to avail of all the legislation we have been lucky to avail of up to now.</p><p>One of the young people I met this morning made a point that really struck a note with me.  Senator Feighan mentioned the development of Casement Park by the Ulster council of the GAA.  I know that like me, he will be eager to buy tickets to attend some matches there.  A young person asked me this morning what will happen to rugby.  He said he plays for and supports Ulster, but not all of Ulster is in Northern Ireland.  He asked whether there will be an impact on somebody coming from Monaghan to play at Ravenhill and <i>vice versa</i>.  I do not make that point facetiously, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#V00300"><p>I know.  The Senator is well into injury time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#V00400"><p>I mention it as an example of the impact this is having on every fabric and aspect of people's lives and concerns, from the big economic and agricultural issues to sport, community life and business life.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#V00500"><p>I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#V00600"><p>Perhaps the Leader will raise this matter with the Taoiseach.  The Northern Ireland Youth Forum is anxious to engage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#V00700"><p>I call Senator Colm Burke.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#V00800"><p>Go raibh maith agat, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.  I was so nice to you at the start of my contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#V00900"><p>I join Senator Humphreys in raising the extremely important issue of maternity hospitals.  I fully agree that a ten-month delay in the lodging of a planning application is unreasonable.  It is about time those involved resolved their differences and got on with it.</p> <p>I remind the House that a 2003 report on our maternity services suggested that there should be approximately 180 consultants in this area within six or seven years, but we have between 130 and 135 at present.  We have made very little progress even though the annual number of deliveries has increased from 50,000 some years ago to approximately 65,000 at present, having been over 75,000 at one stage in the interim.</p> <p>People on the front-line, including nurses, doctors and administrators, are facing major challenges every day because of the significant lack of staff in the maternity area.  We have not done enough.  We do not have the facilities.  We have to wait for an unreasonable period of time when we want to build the facilities.</p> <p>The development of a new children's hospital has already dragged on for almost 25 years.  We should not allow the same thing to happen in the case of the maternity hospital.  I agree with my colleague that the Minister should come in here to explain what the Department intends to do and when it is going to do it.  When is it going to set a deadline for this matter to progress?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need answers and we should not have wait until this time next year to get them.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00200"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for welcoming to the House Dr. Ashwani Kumar, a former Minister for justice from India and a member of the Indian Parliament who is here as my guest along with Professor Jane Ohlmeyer of Trinity College.  It is an honour to have both of them here, particularly at a time when Trinity is welcoming many students from India and other countries worldwide.</p> <p>In that context, I ask the Leader for a debate on Ireland expressing a welcome to a particular group we are currently seeing in the news, that is, the group of unaccompanied minors who are languishing in the detention centre in Calais, which today is being dismantled by the French authorities.  Several hundred young people who are unaccompanied minors are being kept on-site in Calais in order to be processed, many of them to go to the UK.  It would be a good sign and an important gesture of goodwill if the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality and the Government were to express a welcome and to offer a hand of friendship to a small number, to several hundred young, unaccompanied and vulnerable asylum seekers who are currently in a legal limbo and who are not been transported elsewhere in France but who are awaiting processing in Calais.  We should be offering a refuge to them in Ireland.</p> <p>At a time when there is talk of the Seanad being consigned to the museum, it is unfortunate that we would hear such dated and archaic language in this House as that of "housewives" uttered by Senator Leyden earlier.  It is not a comment that has any time or place in modern Irish society.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00300"><p>I ask the Leader to arrange for the Minster for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, to come to the House to discuss his brief in general. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00350"><p>I am sure the Leader will be able to arrange that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00375"><p>I will start off with some fairly good news, and I am sure the Leas-Chathaoirleach was as pleased as I was to learn this morning that the Lonely Planet has selected the Skellig Ring as one of the top must-see regions to visit in the world in 2017.  The Skellig Ring is a small offshoot of the Ring of Kerry, which gives access to Sceilig Mhich&iacute;l, Valentia Island and so on.</p> <p>I was pleased to be at the launch of the Kerry county tourism strategy in Listowel last Friday where, under the aegis of the county council, the blueprint for the future development of the county was outlined.  The launch was packed and those attending were all the service providers, the hoteliers, the restaurateurs and the transport providers.  Why is Kerry successful in tourism?  First, it is because God gave us things that he did not give everybody.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00400"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00425"><p>Being a Kerry man is an awesome responsibility.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00450"><p>That is false modesty.  The Senator has the complete support of the Leas-Chathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00500"><p>Order, please.  Senator O'Sullivan has the floor and he is speaking on a very important topic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#W00600"><p>Second, we are lucky to have a corps of business people who are prepared to roll up their sleeves and work.  Certainly they look for supports, to which they are entitled, but they do not have the deontas mentality.  They work for themselves, to keep their staff employed and to keep their hotels open.  I congratulate them.  The Minister might be asked to come to the House to see if that approach could be adopted nationwide because God knows we need it.</p> <p>On a less happy note, I heard the chairman of the Road Safety Authority speak in a radio interview as I was travelling to Dublin about the unfortunate increase in road fatalities.  Last year was a great year in that there were a small number of deaths.  However, every death is lamentable and avoidable.  The chairman of the authority outlined a number of reasons for the increase in road fatalities, including additional commuting, people who live outside cities have to commute to work, students who cannot access accommodation close to their college campus have to travel to college, as well as increased economic activity.  These are all the parameters, but the real reason for the increase in road fatalities, and this has been the reason for years, is speed.  We are totally obsessed with the idea of drink in this country.  There all the problems associated with it, and God knows I know about them, and drink driving is a scourge.  There has been too much focus on one aspect and if I was asked, I would say the major cause of deaths on our roads is driving at speed.  As I travel to and from this House on the N7 twice a week, on not one of the trips I have made have I not encountered examples of excessive speed, dangerous speed and reckless speed.  That is only one person's anecdotal experience on a weekly basis.  The Minister might be asked to come to the House to discuss these matters.  I also support what An Seanad&oacute;ir Mac Lochlainn said about Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann's infrastructure, which is another aspect of the Minister's brief.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ned O'Sullivan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2233"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2233&amp;amp;pid=NedOSullivan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In fact, the Minister is a little tardy.  He has been in office for some time and we are still waiting for the Department to examine this.  He is behind his colleagues in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#X00200"><p>Tr&eacute;asla&iacute;m le Nick Henderson at&aacute; ceaptha mar phr&iacute;omhfheidhmeannach ar Chomhairle D&iacute;deanaithe na h&Eacute;ireann.  I congratulate Nick Henderson who has been appointed the new chief executive officer of the Irish Refugee Council.  He was in the House earlier with his colleague, Maria Hennessy, to give us a briefing on the major issues surrounding the refugee crisis across the globe and the Irish response to it.  The scenario they outlined shows that we are quite slow in our response.  We must do a great deal more due to the scale of the crisis, so I would welcome a debate on those issues if possible.</p> <p>Senator Humphreys mentioned a turf war.  We are in for another turf war in Connemara if matters do not improve.  There was an understanding regarding turf cutting and management plans being put in place for the blanket bogs.  I understand there was a debate in the D&aacute;il on the raised bogs issue and that there is a deal regarding 43 bogs which shall remain unnamed.  For some strange reason we are not being told the names of the bogs on which a deal is being made.  However, letters have been sent to turf cutters on blanket bogs in the Connemara area, who number hundreds of people, with regard to special protection areas.  The turf cutters must have environmental impact statements undertaken on their bogs and make an appeal to have their lands and bogs de-designated.  The issue is that the letters were sent last week and the deadline for confirming whether the turf cutters will appeal is next Friday.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to intervene with the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, on this matter to see if an extension to the deadline can be given so people can fully assess what is being asked of them, who will pay for the environmental impact statements and why the situation has changed, given that they had an understanding that domestic turf cutters would not be affected by the changes being introduced.  It is past time that the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, came to the House to discuss issues relating to conservation and so forth.  There was a meeting of the Joint Committee on Arts, Heritage, Regional, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs this morning but the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, and the Minister of State, Deputy Kyne, failed to turn up, which was very disconcerting for the members of the committee.  The Minister should be invited to the House to discuss some of these important issues.  They affect Kerry as well, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#X00300"><p>To follow what Senator Colm Burke and other colleagues said regarding maternity services and what direction we are taking with them, I am deeply concerned by what I read in the <i>Irish Examiner</i>today.  The direction we are taking with these services is a real concern for the population.  The work rate of the people involved is fantastic.  My wife and I had the privilege of using the service in the last few months and I compliment them on what they have achieved.  Cork had the battle six or seven years ago of putting three maternity hospitals together.  That was done.  We put up a beautiful building and it is a beautiful service.  It has worked out very well for the Cork region.  I believe we must plan ahead for the generation that will require the service.  If four hospitals are required and must be provided, we must put the infrastructure in place now.  That infrastructure has two elements, the physical structure and the midwives and consultants.  The lack of midwives is an issue and it is one I hear voiced daily.  It is one of the key issues the Minister must come to the Chamber to discuss.  We must plan a generational service for the future so we can provide what is required in a very important service for the women of this State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#X00400"><p>Like other speakers, I am very disheartened.  Every week, I and other Senators invite Ministers to the House.  The Minister arrives and reads from a script.  We are given a sheet of paper which states that they will revert to Senators with further information.  This is unacceptable.  I will mention four cases I have raised in the past six months but have received no answer.  I will insist that we establish a new system in the House because what is happening is unfair.  I raised the respite issue.  The respite service in Carlow closed a year ago and I was told by the Minister that there was a place and I would be informed.  It is now almost a year since then and I have followed it up repeatedly, but have received no answer.  I raised the Holy Angels Day Care Centre with the Minister.  It was given a small bit of funding because it is in prefabs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2470"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2470&amp;amp;pid=JenniferMurnaneOConnor&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Children have been in prefabs for ten years awaiting a new school.  They were guaranteed a new school last year but now the Minister has said he will get back to me on that.  </p><p>I am really annoyed about the ambulance service.  The Minister of State at the Department of Health was in the House last week to respond to a commencement matter on the ambulance service in Carlow.  There was an audit done on the ambulance base prefab and it was found to be unfit for purpose.  The ambulance drivers have no hot water and there is a massive sewage problem.  I was told in the reply that the Department was looking into this but I got no timescale as to when the necessary work will be done.  I have phoned both the HSE and the Department of Health.  I am going back to people in the constituency and telling them that while I am raising these matters with Ministers, I am not getting any answers.  I am delighted that Ministers and Ministers of State are coming into the House but they must give us answers.  No answers are forthcoming.  I raised the issue of local authority funding for County Carlow months ago but I am still waiting for an answer.  I am ringing the Department time and time again and that is unacceptable.  </p><p>I am now asking whether the entire system should be changed.  How many times have Senators asked that Ministers would come to this House?   </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00200"><p>The Senator should put down a motion of no confidence in the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00300"><p>We need to get answers.  I am very disheartened.  As a first-time Senator, I can approach a Minister and outline the issues in my area that require attention or funding.  I have been a councillor for 20 years and I understand that one must wait, that there are protocols in place and everything cannot be done overnight but there has been no respite service for children in Carlow for more than a year since the closure of T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g, which is totally unacceptable.</p> <p>I am very unhappy and will take this further.  I will seek an overhaul of the entire process because it is unacceptable.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00400"><p>A number of months ago I raised the matter of Our Lady's Hospital, Cashel, on which &euro;12.5 million was spent in a Commencement debate.  Following the improvement works, rooms and beds at the hospital were lying vacant.  I commend the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, on visiting the hospital in Cashel yesterday, as well as the hospital in Clonmel.  The Minister saw for himself the problems on the ground.  I also commend him on his comments on local radio this morning when he said he will make the decisions on how the services will be used.  It is quite obvious that the vacant beds in Cashel need to be used for step-down purposes and the Minister has indicated this will be the case.  Consequently, unlike the last speaker who was very frustrated - as am I on certain issues - I am pleased to say that on this issue, the Minister has closed the circle.  He has visited Tipperary and has given a commitment.  He also gave a commitment with regard to the capital budget for 2017.  I have now said all of the nice things I am going to say today.</p><p>The second issue I want to raise relates to Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann, which yesterday leaked a report on the railway lines across the country.  On the front of <i>The Irish Times</i>yesterday, my home town of Carrick-on-Suir was billed as the town that used rail services the least.  The report did not dig down deep enough to tell the people who read the newspaper, many of whom contacted me yesterday, that if one goes to the railway station in Carrick-on-Suir, it is quite possible the train one is waiting for will not turn up.  It is also quite possible that if one is on a train that should stop at Carrick-on-Suir, it will not do so.  Furthermore, it is quite possible that if one goes to Waterford to get the train to Carrick-on-Suir, one will be told one must get a bus and that there is no train running.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00500"><p>That is a very suitable item for a Commencement debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00600"><p>It is quite obvious that Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann is trying to close the railway line between Waterford and Limerick Junction by stealth.  I am calling for a debate with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, on this issue.</p> <p>Finally, I am sure the Leas-Chathaoirleach will join me -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00700"><p>Senators are normally only allowed to raise one item.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00800"><p>This is a very serious matter.  I would like to pay my respects to the family of former Senator Noel Coonan on the death of his wife, Pauline, a former councillor, who passed away after a long illness.  I am sure the House will join me in offering sincere condolences to the Coonan family.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00850"><p>Thank you, indeed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Y00900"><p>I wish to raise the issue of the withdrawal of Association of Secondary Teachers in Ireland, ASTI, members from supervision and substitution duties.  Effectively, what this means is that the vast majority of voluntary secondary schools in the country will not be able to continue to operate after the mid-term break, which ends on 7 November.  The vast majority of the voluntary secondary schools will not re-open after the mid-term break, meaning there are only two days of scheduled teaching left.  The impasse regarding supervision and substitution has not been dealt with by the Minister for Education and Skills.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to the House to discuss this.  We know that the strike issue is currently being dealt with.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerry Horkan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2476"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2476&amp;amp;pid=GerryHorkan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It needs to be dealt with urgently.  Although the Association of Secondary Teachers in Ireland will not be on strike for many days after the seven scheduled days, it will be effectively closing schools or forcing boards of management to make the decision to close schools, because there will be insufficient staff available to cover the supervision required before school, during break times, after school, in schoolyards and so on.</p><p>The vast majority of principals and deputy principals in voluntary secondary schools are members of the union.  There is no derogation for those principals and deputy principals to administer the scheme or for any replacement people to do so either.  Those involved have not been told to co-operate with other people.  Even if others were brought in, they would need Garda vetting.  That Garda vetting takes several weeks.  Even if we could find such people and bring them in, they would need to familiarise themselves with the school.  If that is not possible - and it is not - then no board of management will be in a position to open a school because does not have the required level of supervision and substitution.  I know this because I am chairman of the board of management of a school.</p><p>More than half of the secondary schools in the country will not reopen after the mid-term break unless the issue of supervision and substitution is addressed.</p><p>This is urgent.  It is putting extraordinary pressure on pupils in these schools.  They are not going to get the education they thought they were going to get.  They are now in competition with people who are in non-ASTI schools or schools which are able to stay open - principally, the education and training board schools.  In other words, different pupils are getting different levels of education but all are doing the same examination.  It is a serious issue that needs to be dealt with urgently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Z00200"><p>I hope the Leader will be able to clarify the position on grants for sporting organisations and National Lottery funded grants to sporting organisations.  I note that before the last general election a grant of &euro;50,000 was promised for the development of Cusack Park and Westmeath GAA.  However, since the fall of the last Government and the subsequent formation of the current Government, that promise seems to have dried up.</p><p>As Members are aware, the sports capital grant had ceased.  Following the budget we have heard from the Minister of State with responsibility for sports that the scheme will be opened again and that there will be more money for sport grants.  I am seeking clarification on some of the other project that had been promised but then put on the long finger.  Will they be looked at again?  If the Leader has some information on that matter, I would appreciate it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Z00300"><p>I want to raise two issues.  Senator O'Sullivan spoke about Kerry.  If we could get the Wild Atlantic Way extended to Limerick, I have no doubt we would be on a level playing field with Kerry.</p><p>The issue I want to raise relates to Irish Rail.  As a frequent user of Irish Rail I welcome the fact that there will be a public consultation on the service.  I have raised this issue before.  If we want to encourage the public to use public transport, in particular, rail transport, then we must have two things.  In the modern world, we must have proper mobile coverage and proper broadband coverage.  Irish Rail provides neither.  We want to encourage business people to use what is an excellent service.  The service includes online facilities and the trains are frequent and on time.  However, we live in the modern world.  If people are on trains and their mobile calls drop every few yards or their broadband coverage is such that they lose something, then they will become reluctant to travel by Irish Rail.  Two infrastructural questions need to be examined.  Why is mobile coverage so poor throughout the Irish Rail service?  Why is broadband coverage so poor?  If remedies to these problems were put in place, we could encourage more people to use the rail service and we might not continue to have these discussions.</p><p>I have no wish for any deterioration.  We lost much of our rail network perhaps 50 years ago.  I believe the service has to be developed in a way that encourages people to use it.  These are two key issues.  I will keep hammering on about them.  The issues are broadband coverage and mobile coverage.  They are atrocious in the Irish Rail service at the amount.  In the modern world, these services need to be corrected and dealt with immediately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#Z00400"><p>I am seeing clarification on the repeal of the eighth amendment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paddy Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1866"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1866&amp;amp;pid=PaddyBurke&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Government said today that the Citizens' Assembly will report to an Oireachtas committee and that the Oireachtas committee will be set up by the Business Committee of the D&aacute;il.  Is there any representation from the Seanad on the Business Committee or do we have any say in that?  Does it mean that the Business Committee sets the whole agenda for both Houses?  Where do we stand in respect of the Business Committee?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA00200"><p>The Business Committee does not set the business in the D&aacute;il either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA00300"><p>The Leader will respond in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA00400"><p>I extend the sympathies of the House to the former Senator and Deputy, Noel Coonan, on the very sad death of his wife, Pauline.  Those of us who had the privilege of meeting Pauline recognised her as a very warm, loving, caring, strong and powerful woman.  We send our deepest sympathies to Noel and the family.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.</p> <p>Now for a happier announcement, I welcome Senator Ardagh back to the House and congratulate her and her husband, Darragh, on their nuptials.  I was hoping the honeymoon feeling would still be here today but the Senator is back to work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA00500"><p>Normal service has resumed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA00600"><p>I wish her and Darragh every success and many years of happiness together.  The Minister for Education and Skills is happy to meet with her at 5.30 p.m. rather than coming into the House if that is acceptable to her.  He is deeply conscious of the issue she has raised.  I have raised the matter with the Department on her behalf.  I know that a letter was sent to the school sometime in October.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA00700"><p>May I address that matter for two seconds when the Leader is finished?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA00800"><p>If that is in order with the Leas-Chathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA00900"><p>If the Minister is dealing with the matter-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA01000"><p>I would rather not divide the House because to be fair to the Senator there are means of having the Minister come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA01100"><p>The Leader can inform the House at that stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA01200"><p>I understand the importance of the issue the Senator raised and I have been endeavouring to bring the Minister in to talk to the Senator and he is willing to meet her and talk to her about the matter.  Rather than bring him into the House I hope that the Senator would accept the bona fides of the Minister this afternoon.  It is a very important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA01300"><p>That is fine when the Leader is finished.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA01400"><p>Senator McDowell raised the issue of Seanad reform.  Not being party to the correspondence he refers to I am in a vacuum.  If he would be happy to share with me the piece of correspondence I would be happy to peruse it and give him a more detailed response.</p> <p>As far as I know the Government position on the Manning report has not changed since the Taoiseach was last here.  Whatever some Members of the House might think, write or say, as the Senator knows, all politics is local and in the event that in the next Seanad election the Manning report has not been implemented and there is no change, I am sure the particular Senator is keeping those who voted for him very happy.  I am presuming it is a "he".  I might be wrong on that. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA01500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#AA01600"><p>Senator Conway-Walsh raised the issue of media ownership.  We are lucky to have very independent media.  I would be happy to have a discussion in due course regarding media ownership and so on.</p> <p>Senator Nash raised the issue of the industrial relations strategy.  While it is important to acknowledge that there is a very strong mechanism in the State to deal with industrial relations, as the Senator, a former Minister of State, knows, I do not accept his narrative that this Government has no interest, relationship or strength in respect of industrial relations.  In fact the opposite is the case.</p> <p>It is important that the discussions taking place now between the Association of Secondary Teachers of Ireland, ASTI, and the Department of Education and Skills and with the Association of Garda Sergeants and Inspectors, AGSI, and the Garda Representative Association, GRA, continue and that they end in a resolution that is not just favourable but can be worked upon in the future.</p> <p>Everything the Government is doing concerns equality.  As a former Minister of State, the Senator knows quite well that the Government he was part of made decisions that would never have been made in any normal situation.  Now that the Government and the country are beginning to turn the economy around towards the future, new pay entrants will receive better pay.  There is a commitment to pay restoration.  It is important that we honour the Lansdowne Road agreement and give the new public service pay commission time to be established but equally that there is dialogue and ongoing discussion of the matters at hand.  I will not continue a dialogue in this Chamber today which is best conducted by those in discussions at the moment.  It behoves everybody to become involved, to speak and to reach a resolution of the matter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Senator O'Reilly referred to Brexit, about which we have had an ongoing series of debates in the House.  It is important that we seek to benefit from the departure of the UK from the Union.</p><p>Senator Mark Daly referred to the sitting times of the House.  In the coming weeks, a number of Bills will come before us for consideration.  I made the point last week that new politics, whatever the particular arrangements might be, has involved a focus on pre-legislative scrutiny.  Senators who were Ministers and Chairmen of committees in the previous D&aacute;il know the system has changed.  Legislation is slowing down in its formulation and in coming before both Houses of the Oireachtas.  As I said, however, a series of legislative items are due to come before us in the coming weeks.  As Leader of the House, the decision I make as to whether we should sit next week will not be based on populism, unlike the actions of those Members of the D&aacute;il today who undermined the Business Committee which they were party to setting up.  As Senator Norris rightly said, we are the people's House and it is proper that we have debates and statements.  Parliament, as the Senator observed, is about discussion and debate.  I appeal to all Members not to undermine this House or give the media further notice to write whatever they want.  Senator Norris noted that they will pick and choose what they want to report, as is their prerogative.  If we have legislation to debate or statements to discuss, we will be here to do it.  The legislative programme is not blank and it behoves us all to ensure we see legislation enacted and issues debated.  I have asked the Government Chief Whip to initiate legislation in the Seanad.  In the weeks ahead we will see a series of Seanad Bills coming to the House.</p><p>Senator Black referred to the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill 2015, Committee Stage of which will be taken tomorrow.  One of the positive initiatives taken by the previous Government was the establishment of a register of lobbying which requires lobbyists to record who they have met and spoken to.</p><p>Senator Feighan raised the issue of the relocation of the Seanad.  We discussed that last week and I do not propose to go into it again.  There is a process under way, as the Senator knows.  It is important to put the matter in context.  It is not just about the 60 Members of the House but also the Seanad staff, the staff who record and transmit proceedings and other staff of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  It is not a question of 60 people decanting to Letterkenny, Roscommon, Cork or anywhere else.  It is a much wider issue than that.</p><p>Senator Norris spoke about media reporting of the proceedings of the House.  Following a contribution by the Senator on the Order of Business some weeks ago, I raised the matter with the relevant person in RTE.  It is up to us to give the copy to RTE, in the case of "Oireachtas Report", and to the print media.</p><p>Regarding the issue raised by Senator Butler, I will be happy to ask the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Coveney, to come to the House to discuss it.</p><p>Senators Humphreys, Colm Burke and Lombard raised the important issue of the redevelopment of the National Maternity Hospital.  It is illogical that we do not have a decision lodged in that regard through the planning process.  The Government is committed to the relocation of the hospital.  The national maternity strategy drawn up by the previous Government was the first such strategy published.  It is vital that we have a coherent strategy around the relocation.  The time for talking is over and it is time now for action.  As Senator Burke noted, the birth rate is rising and there are deficits in terms of the number of consultants in the maternity service.  The national maternity strategy must be implemented and, more urgently, a construction date must be set and commenced for the National Maternity Hospital.  I will be happy to ask the Minister for Health to come to the House to discuss that.  This is about the lives of women and newborn babies, including those infants who require urgent care.</p><p>Senator Leyden raised issues relating to the sale of alcohol, which we will discuss tomorrow.  I remind the Senator that it was the leader of his party who, as Minister, introduced the groceries order and thereby changed the way in which alcohol could be priced and sold in supermarkets.</p><p>Senator Noone spoke about alcohol and obesity.  I will be happy to bring the Minister for Health to the House to discuss that issue.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile referred to the Northern Ireland Youth Forum.  If he gives me the details, I will bring them to the attention of the Department of the Taoiseach.  It is important that we hear all perspectives around Brexit, particularly the North-South aspect.  Young people have a role to play in that regard.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Senator also raised the issue of the new stadium in Casement Park, as did Senator Feighan.  I wish the Ulster council well in that regard.<br/><br/>In response to Senator Bacik, and I should have welcomed Dr. Kumar, the Minister for Justice and Equality is willing to come to the House to discuss the issue of unaccompanied minors.<br/><br/>Senator Ned O'Sullivan raised a number of important issues, the first being road safety and the number of fatalities.  The Senator is right.  One death is lamentable.  I join him in requesting the Minister to come to the House.<br/><br/>Senator Mac Lochlainn raised the issue of transport.  The Senator will be glad to hear that the Minister, Deputy Ross, will come to the House on 16 November for a debate on transport.  However, it is important that all Members of this House would play their part, with the Garda and the Road Safety Authority, in trying to reduce the number of fatalities as a result of car crashes on our motorways and roads.  As we approach the bank holiday weekend, I appeal, as Leader of the House, to all those who will be driving over the weekend not to engage in drink driving because, as we saw this week, it is tragic when we see the way an accident can result in young people in particular losing their lives.  It is important that we highlight that matter.<br/><br/>I commend Senator Ned O'Sullivan and the people of Kerry.  Kerry is called beauty's home for a reason.  It is a beautiful county.  The Senator may have false modesty around it but Kerry has a brilliant tourism product, as we have in west Cork, to sell to the people.  I commend the Senator on the <i>Lonely Planet</i>guide introduction.  Kerry is following Cork city in being included in the <i>Lonely Planet</i>guide.  The most important point he made about tourism is that there is a group of people in Kerry who are dedicated to working hard, promoting the county and creating jobs.  They are to be commended on that.  Other counties could learn from them in that regard.<br/><br/>I join Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh in congratulating Mr. Nick Henderson on being appointed to the Irish Refugee Council.  The Minister is committed to coming to the House to discuss the particular matter he raised about refugees.  We cannot but be moved by the images on our television to do with the camp in Calais and other parts of the world, in particular Aleppo in Syria.  I commend our Navy again which this week saved the lives of many people in the Mediterranean.<br/><br/>Senator Murnane-O'Connor raised the issue of Ministers coming to the House.  I fully concur with the Senator.  As a Member of the House she deserves to be given answers.  She should have been here when her party was in government because it was a lot different from what it is now, but she is right.  As a Member of the House she should get a progress report on what is happening in respect of the issues she raises.  If the Senator wishes to liaise with me later, I would be happy to take up those issues.  I cannot answer for the Ministers, but as a public representative, it is frustrating that Ministers do not reply.  That has been going on since the State was founded but the point the Senator makes is a valid one.<br/><br/>Senator Landy raised the issue of Our Lady's Hospital in Cashel.  I join the Senator in congratulating the Minister, Deputy Harris, who visited the hospital yesterday.<br/><br/>Senator Landy and Senator O'Donnell raised the issue of Irish Rail.  The Minister, Deputy Ross, will be in the House on 16 November to discuss that issue.<br/><br/>Senator Horkan raised an issue regarding education.  The Senator is right.  There are two parts to this issue, and as a former teacher I believe it is one that must be resolved.  The ASTI members will benefit from being involved in the Lansdowne Road agreement.  I appeal to the members of the ASTI to consider the benefits of voting for the Lansdowne Road agreement from which they will see pay restoration, but it is a contentious issue and I hope it will be resolved.<br/><br/>Senator Davitt raised the issue of the sports capital programme.  As far as I know, under the previous round, and there were three in the previous Government's term of office, sports capital programme commitments are to be honoured.  If the Senator has an issue regarding Cusack Park in Westmeath, I would be happy to have that matter resolved for him, but as far as I am aware, once the organisation meets the criteria and the money is allocated, it can draw down the funding on a tiered basis.<br/><br/>Senator O'Donnell made a point about Wi-Fi and mobile telephone coverage.  Many Senators have raised the issue of mobile telephone coverage, not just on trains but in general.  It is an issue to which we should return.<br/><br/>Senator Paddy Burke raised the issue of the Citizens' Assembly.  My understanding is that the Citizens' Assembly will report back to the Houses of the Oireachtas which will then go before a committee of the Houses of the Oireachtas.  I take the Senator's point that there is no Member of this House sitting on the Business Committee but my office is represented on the legislative committee which discusses legislation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important that Members of both Houses are on the committee dealing with the report of the Citizens' Assembly and that it is reported back here.</p><p>Likewise, I hope that Fianna F&aacute;il and Sinn F&eacute;in could provide an update to the Whips about whether they are opposing membership of the Committee on the Future of Healthcare by Members of this House.  I certainly hope they have spoken about this issue to their respective party leaderships and that Members of this House will be on that committee because there are people from both parties, this side of the House and the Labour Party, as well as Independents, who have a huge amount of expertise in the area of health.  That the leaders of Fianna F&aacute;il or Sinn F&eacute;in would prevent Members of this House from being on that committee would send the wrong signal.  It would be a regressive move.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.214" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#DD00300"><p>The information provided to the D&aacute;il last week was that this was the case.  I am only giving Members what I have been told.  There was to be a vote in the House last week and the vote was pulled on the basis that it would not be carried.  I hope that Members would reflect upon that.</p> <p>In respect of Senator Ardagh's amendment to the Order of Business, I do not want to divide the House.  The Minister is willing to meet Senator Ardagh.  I understand the importance of the issue she raised but I hope she will not divide the House.  The Minister will meet her.  There are other means of bringing the Minister in and I would be happy to talk to Senator Ardagh about that afterwards if that is okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#DD00400"><p>I am obliged to the Leader for conveying that message to the Minister who has agreed to meet me today.  I will formally withdraw the proposal to amend the Order of Business today.  However, this is not just a local issue.  It is a national issue.  Dublin 12 and its hinterland is a part of Dublin that is seriously disadvantaged and that is used very often as a dumping ground, not only for education but for housing.  We have seen modular housing in this area where residents do not want it.  I would like to note that you cannot use Dublin 12 as a dumping ground.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#DD00500"><p>I cannot allow Senator Ardagh to discuss it further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.218" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.219" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.220" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#DD00800">Agricultural Prices and Decision by UK to Leave EU: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#DD00900"><p>I am very happy to have the opportunity to speak to the House today about the implications of Brexit for our agrifood and fisheries sectors.  In my opening comments, I would like to provide Members with an outline of the areas that are most likely to be affected by the UK leaving the EU and to give an overview of the preparatory work carried out by my Department to date.  I will also explain how we are feeding into the overall Government response to Brexit.  I look forward to hearing Members' contributions and engaging with them on this very important topic.</p> <p>The UK's decision to leave the EU raises enormous challenges for the Irish agrifood sector.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Michael Creed:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=259"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=259&amp;amp;pid=MichaelCreed&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The UK is by far our largest trading partner.  Last year, we exported almost &euro;5.1 billion worth of agricultural products.  Ireland is also the UK's largest destination for its food exports, worth &euro;3.8 billion in 2015.  My Department, with its agencies and stakeholders, has been carefully considering the potential impacts of a UK exit, examining the areas in which the greatest risks may arise and on which we will need to focus when negotiations begin.  The main areas in which impacts are foreseen are in respect of currency fluctuations, tariffs and trade, the EU budget, regulations and standards, and customs controls and certification.  The UK exit vote also raises complex issues for the fisheries sector.  However, it is important to remember that our trading relationship with the UK is not altered in any way until the negotiations that will dictate the terms and conditions of the UK&rsquo;s departure are completed.</p><p>The Department of the Taoiseach is co-ordinating the overall Government response to Brexit.  It has established a contingency framework which sets out the key issues that will be most important to Ireland and has published a summary of the key actions that will be taken to address them.  It has also established an interdepartmental group to follow up in practical terms on the outcome and implications of the referendum vote and support the work of the new Cabinet committee on Brexit.  This interdepartmental group will be supported by six sectoral work groups which will provide key sectoral and thematic advice to the Cabinet, committee and Government.  My Department will participate in the work groups dealing with the implications for the economy and trade, the EU budget and customs and excise.  It will also chair a subgroup examining the implications for the agrifood sector, which met for the first time last week.  We are also continuing to deepen our analysis of the likely impacts and feed these in to the central contingency framework being co-ordinated by the Department of the Taoiseach.  However, much of the work will depend on the UK's Article 50 notification and its likely asks regarding its future trading relationship with the UK.</p><p>A dedicated Brexit unit has been established in my Department and a consultative committee of stakeholders has been convened in order to ensure a full exchange of information, as negotiations proceed.  The consultative committee held its first meeting in July and its second last week.  The Food Wise 2025 high-level implementation committee has tabled a standing item on Brexit on its agenda.  It has also agreed the establishment of a contact group with representatives from my Department and the various agencies in order to ensure a coherent response to any issues arising.  This contact group will be absorbed into the central agrifood subgroup to which I referred earlier.</p><p>The most immediate impact for agrifood exporters arises from changes to the euro-sterling exchange rate.  While this was not unexpected in light of the uncertainty caused by the referendum result, a sustained period of currency volatility would be of major concern.  The Central Bank of Ireland has pre-established contingency plans to deal with market volatility.  The Central Bank will continue to engage with the Department of Finance and individual financial institutions on the risks involved.  Actions by the European Central Bank, ECB, and other global actors will continue to be monitored closely.</p><p>Bord Bia and Enterprise Ireland are also providing practical guidance to SMEs.  Recently, Bord Bia announced a number of measures - covering areas such as managing volatility impacts, providing consumer and market insight, deepening customer engagement and extending market reach - with the aim of helping companies to maintain their competitiveness.  Similar support is also being provided by Enterprise Ireland.  In the context of budget 2017, I announced a number of measures that will financially underpin the Department's Brexit mitigation efforts through strategic investment in key areas of the Department, its agencies and the agrifood sector.  This includes access to an innovative, low-interest agri-cashflow fund of &euro;150 million, agri-taxation measures designed to address income fluctuations, increased funding of Bord Bia and Bord Iascaigh Mhara, investment in research and development and innovation and increased expenditure on the rural development programme and the seafood development programme.</p><p>It is also important that we renew our focus on the need to reduce our dependence on the UK market.  The development of new markets and the exploitation of opportunities in emerging markets is a key component of the Food Wise 2025 strategy.  I have been following it up in a very real and practical way through my participation in trade missions.  Following a very successful visit to South-East Asia in early September, I plan to undertake further trade missions to north Africa and the Gulf region in the coming weeks.  These activities will continue into the future, given that they play a key part in our efforts to provide as many markets as possible for Irish agrifood exports.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Michael Creed:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=259"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=259&amp;amp;pid=MichaelCreed&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Beyond the immediate currency difficulties, there are potentially very negative impacts arising from possible differences in tariffs, a movement by the UK away from the common regulations and standards of the Single Market, the reconstitution of border controls and the reintroduction of veterinary certification.  These will inevitably add to the costs of Irish producers and processors, affect their competitiveness and disrupt trade.</p><p>We also face significant difficulties on the fisheries side, where the most complex issues are those related to the possibility of restricted access to fishing grounds and resources.  We face a very uncertain situation regarding the management and sharing of a large number of different fish stocks that we currently share with the UK and other member states under the Common Fisheries Policy framework.  This could lead to restricted access to traditional fisheries grounds and resources.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#FF00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  At the outset I would like to express my disappointment, with all due respect to the Minister, at the fact that the Minister's appearance here today coincides with a meeting of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, which discommodes all of us, as spokespeople for our respective parties.  None of us has the power of bi-location and the unfortunate clash is disappointing.</p><p>That said, I welcome the Minister to the House and note his statement on Brexit.  Two very strong themes in his statement are the need for preparatory work and the likely outcomes of Brexit, if and when the British trigger Article 50 of the Lisbon treaty and what may happen two years after that.  However, there are a number of issues that are not about preparation but about immediate action.  The most pressing issue at the moment is the situation in the mushroom industry.  As we are all aware, almost 90% of mushroom product is exported to the UK and the current currency fluctuations mean that the industry is haemorrhaging large sums of money on a daily basis.  Many mushroom producers are on fixed contracts which are up for renewal between January and March 2017 but many will not survive until then.  Producers in the sector are very confident that if and when they sit down to negotiate new contracts they will have a very strong mushroom industry into the future, due to the fact that their main competition was from eastern European suppliers who may not tender for those contracts because they too are struggling.</p><p>Planning is not a solution to this problem.  We need immediate action.  I know that there will be no support coming from the European Union as this is an Irish problem.  While I welcome the Minister's visits abroad and his Department's sourcing of new markets, there is no new market possible for the Irish mushroom industry, due mainly to the short shelf life of the product.  The British market, irrespective of the outcome of Brexit, is and will be the only real, viable market.  The bottom line, however, is that the industry is not going to survive.  I ask the Minister to comment on this because there is a need for immediate action and support.  We have already lost more than 130 jobs in the industry.  We have also lost a supply contract worth &euro;7 million and that is just the tip of the iceberg.  I ask the Minister, in his response, to tell us if there are any plans in this regard.  While the mushroom industry is under the umbrella of horticulture within the Department, it is an enterprise and jobs are at stake.  There may well be a need for input from other Departments.  Has the Minister had any discussions with the Departments of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation and Social Protection, or any other relevant Department, on what life support could be made available to the industry to allow it to survive until the contract renewal dates?  If something is not put in place, the industry will not survive. </p><p>Other sufferers as a result of the difficulties in the mushroom industry are the cereal farmers who supply mushroom producers with wheat and straw.  As the Minister is aware, cereal growers have had their own problems this year from a climatic perspective, especially along the west coast.  I would like to hear the Minister's comments in this regard.  There was a crisis in the industry from a price perspective at the start of the year, even if it had turned out to be a good year.  Almost 2,000 hectares of grain along the west coast is now unsalvageable.  This sector also needs immediate support.  I do not know if something could be forthcoming under <i>de minimis </i>aid rules whereby the Government could help them out on a one-off basis, rather than applying to the EU.  This is badly needed.  It is not just a question of me standing up here and beating a drum.  The problems are obvious and I know the Minister is aware of them.  </p><p>The major long-term issue with Brexit, if and when it is triggered and implemented, will be how we will stand with regard to the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP.  The Germans have already said that if money is not forthcoming from Britain, the CAP budget will be cut.  I would like to hear the Minister's thoughts on that issue.  What can we do in the negotiations to ensure that our CAP allocation remains as is?  Farmers tell us that CAP payments need to improve in order for them to survive.  If, because of Brexit, we are looking at a situation where there will be major alterations to the CAP, then the entire industry will have a major problem.</p><p>Last week, we met EU Commissioner Phil Hogan in this House and raised the areas of natural constraint, ANC, scheme review.  The Commissioner's response was that no submission had been received from the Irish Government on that review.  Why is that the case?  Is that submission being prepared and when will it be submitted?  The ANC payment is vitally important.  It is targeted at disadvantaged areas, those which are the hardest to farm and the people in those areas are most dependent on payments.  I was taken aback to hear that Ireland has not made a submission yet.  </p><p>I ask the Minister to throw some light on the question of when the TAMS II tillage measure will be opened.  This question has been asked on numerous occasions and the answers given have been very open, as in, &quot;in the harvest&quot;, &quot;at the back end&quot;, &quot;shortly&quot; and &quot;soon&quot;.  I ask the Minister to give a specific date for the opening of the TAMS II tillage measures.  </p><p>On the beef sector and pricing, farmers are being offered, on average, &euro;3.75 to &euro;3.80 per kilogram at the moment but Teagasc tells us that the minimum price to break even is &euro;4.  We have a serious problem with pricing.  What actions can the Minister respectfully take to try to regulate prices?  Farmers are price takers but at the end of the day, the buck stops with the Minister.  What can or will the Minister do to try to improve the situation?  Farmers will survive but they would not be looking for money through various agricultural schemes if they were getting a decent margin on their products.  We need to step in and ensure that they do get such a margin.  There are a number of non-money-related actions the Minister could take, which I will now run them by him and I ask for his response.  The 30 month age restriction in the factories is imposing major extra costs, particularly on the suckler industry, which are avoidable.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2464"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2464&amp;amp;pid=PaulDaly&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Calves born at the back end of the year or early in the year hit 30 months in May, June and July, when grass is at a premium.  Since the farmers have no wish to keep them and be penalised over the 30 months, they feed the livestock grain unnecessarily to have them finished within 30 months.  However, if the period were 36 months, the farmers could leave them on the grass until August, September or October without having the extra cost of the grain.  They are being penalised in the factory.</p><p>The 30 month restriction was brought in at the time of the BSE crisis, but that crisis has long since gone.  Factories and processors are hammering the farmer on an antiquated law.  Will the Minister interject to try to have the 30 month restriction changed?  It would yield a considerable saving if they did not have to force-feed the cattle and have them sold before grass reaches a premium.</p><p>The Minister commented on the marine and fisheries as well.  He said there will be major problems.  What solutions or actions have been taken to try to overcome some of these problems?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#GG00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I note that he is proudly wearing an orange and green badge on his lapel.  I noticed it as I stepped into the Chamber and I commented on it to him.  That gives me an opening to say that the Bord Bia strategy for 2016 to 2018 is making a world of difference.  It is an important document.  It is referenced in the programme for Government, and that is to be welcomed.  Clearly, the strategy is going to have some setbacks.  All of this needs to be looked at in the context of the horticultural sector.  Mushroom and cut flower production are among a range of horticultural activities in the food and ornamental sectors that need to be examined.  I think it would be helpful to take some time out at some point to look at the strategy document in conjunction with Bord Bia to see how we can progress as much of the strategy as possible.  I believe it is a good and concise strategy and I salute Bord Bia.  The organisation is an altogether focused one that does a very good job.  That much needs to be acknowledged.</p> <p>We know that the European Union is the UK's largest trading partner, accounting for 62% of UK food and drink exports and 70% of UK imports.  Therefore, it is not surprising that the exit vote has led to significant market volatility and uncertainty.  The UK agricultural industry currently relies heavily on EU subsidies.  A study undertaken by the UK Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs showed that more than 30% of British farms could be in negative income without the Common Agricultural Policy.  There may also be a possibility of a reduced CAP overall without the contribution from the British.  This will have an impact on Irish and EU farms.  It is critical to consider how the changes in CAP will affect farmers in Ireland.  I am keen to hear what the Minister has to say on that point.</p> <p>The UK is Ireland's largest market for food and drink, accounting for 41% of Irish food and drink exports.  The value was &euro;4.4 billion in 2015.  Strong growth in exports to non-EU markets has been evident in recent years.  However, the UK remains the core market for Irish food and drink exports.  Between 2010 and 2015, Irish exports to the UK increased by &euro;1 billion.  This was largely driven by an increase in meat exports.  Meat exports make the highest proportion of Irish food and drink exports to the UK, followed by prepared foods and dairy.  The UK accounts for 54% of total Irish meat and livestock exports, reflecting the fact that this is the highest priced beef market in the world.</p> <p>Exports to the UK represent 30% of dairy, 70% of prepared foods and 30% of beverage exports.  In the edible horticultural and cereals sectors, the UK accounts for 90% of Irish exports.  In the dairy sector, over 65% of our cheddar cheese is exported to the UK while large shipments of butter and infant formula, etc. are exported there too.</p> <p>As my colleague noted earlier, mushroom exports account for the vast majority of the edible horticulture sector category and are, therefore, almost totally dependent on the UK market.  We know about shelf life and so forth.  Will the Minister outline the Government policy or strategy or the nature of supports in place in respect of hedging strategies for currency fluctuations?  The Minister will beware of the major stake the people have in Allied Irish Banks.  How is the Minister or the Government interacting with that bank or any other financial institution in respect of currency fluctuations and hedging?  Clearly, many of these problems are related to the fluctuation in sterling.  What is the role of Enterprise Ireland?  Will the Minister share with us precisely what measures Enterprise Ireland is undertaking in respect of these matters?</p> <p>Liquidity and cashflow are critical.  To be fair, there has been an increase in lending to the agricultural sector, specifically in the past year.  That is to be welcomed.  Clearly, this is a major issue as well.</p> <p>The issue of border controls is relevant.  The withdrawal of the UK from the EU would effectively mean that Ireland's Border with Northern Ireland would be, by definition, an external EU border.  This will lead to increased regulatory requirements and costs as well as a physical border between both parts of the island of Ireland.  This is relevant for the food and drink sectors because it will mean &euro;525 million of fresh food and drinks will be exported.</p> <p>There are serious difficulties in this area.  In this crisis there are major challenges for the island of Ireland.  We have heard the remarks of Nicola Sturgeon in respect of Scotland.  There is a real possibility of another referendum there, and I can understand why.  There may be political implications for Northern Ireland.  A northern Unionist said to me recently that while they may be loyal to the British Crown, they are perhaps more loyal to the half-crown.  That says something.  It is about money, the economy and sustaining the family and the farm as well as farm and producer incomes.</p> <p>There are major challenges for North-South cross-Border co-operation in this regard and I am keen to hear more from the Minister.  Will he tell us more about his plans to foster co-operation?  I welcome in particular the fact that Nicola Sturgeon will come here from Scotland to share some of the same concerns.  Within all of this there are possible opportunities that we should not overlook as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#GG00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I imagine we are going to have many more conversations about this particular issue as Brexit unfolds and as the implications become more apparent.  It is fair to say that we have journeyed a long way since 1 January 1973 when we joined Europe.  Most of our external trade was bilateral trade with the UK.  We diversified into so many areas.  To this day, agriculture and the agrifood sectors still account for a vast amount of exports to the UK.  Of our exports, 43% or &euro;5.1 billion in 2015 went to the UK.  Conversely, we imported 47% of total agri-sector imports from the UK, comprising &euro;3.8 billion.  This figure compares with 14% of exports in other sectors.  Therefore, our agriculture and agrifood sectors are unique and in a more precarious situation, one might argue, because of our dependence on that market.</p> <p>We already know that many analyses have been undertaken.  In November 2015 the ESRI estimated that we could see as much as a 20% drop in trade flow between the two countries.  Without a doubt, that would pose great difficulties for us.</p> <p>The mushroom industry has been mentioned.  Given the nature of the industry it is a good case study.  Immediately we are seeing the impact of the drop in sterling and currency fluctuation.  We can learn a good deal from what is happening to the mushroom farmers and we can be decisive about what interventions work.  We know that 70,000 tonnes of mushrooms are produced in this country with 60,000 tonnes going to the UK.  There is extraordinary dependence on that market.  Already, a number of smaller operations have closed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is testament to those who are there and have captured the market in the UK, competing with UK producers and producers from eastern Europe who are also dealing with the challenge posed by Brexit and the currency fluctuation.  What specific interventions will the Minister make because farming is the backbone of our economy and everyone in the sector has been dealing with international market volatility?  The mushroom industry is particularly affected by Brexit.  Many of the Minister's interventions in respect of beef and dairy products have been to try to find new markets.  While mushrooms and other vegetables are perishable there are new ways to transport them and with assistance perhaps new markets can be explored.  The people in the mushroom industry who appeared before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine are innovative and do a fine job against the odds of exporting into England.  Working with the industry can lead to results and help them get through the difficult time.  What in particular is being done for the mushroom industry? </p><p>We made statements on the budget and I welcome the suite of measures, investments and programmes in the Minister&rsquo;s Department, in particular the provision for low-cost access to credit.  Farmers are paid intermittently by cheque, whether for cattle or produce or through payments from the Department but in the meantime what do they live on?  It is important to protect farmers from the banks which do not treat any sector fairly, whether business or home owners because they do not pass on the benefits of the low-cost credit they get from Europe.  This intervention is very apt and welcome.</p><p>Fishermen may be restricted from going where they can fish and we do not know how the UK will proceed in this respect.  Do we have preliminary feedback on this or on stock management for shared fisheries?  Many of the codes or negotiated management agreements with other countries have a tendency to break down.  This is fishermen&rsquo;s livelihood.  Will the Minister address some of the concerns of the fishing industry?</p><p>On a related matter that affects the bigger picture, farmers and farm organisations are concerned about the demand to reduce our carbon emissions and how that affects farming.  The United Nations ambassador for climate justice, the former president Mary Robinson, suggested recently that people should move towards vegetarianism and veganism to halt climate change.  Any such statements should be grounded in reality and if we want to bring people with us, we have to meet them where they are.  I commend her on taking on this job, climate change affects everybody and she has brilliant stature and experience working on other issues around the world but I do not subscribe to this proposition.  It conflicts with Food Wise 2025.  What is the Minister doing to allay people&rsquo;s fears because meat and dairy products are part of a balanced diet for people in this country?  The only other source is high-protein food crops, which are developed in the tropics, in the southern hemisphere and that would involve taking food from people who are already hard pressed to feed themselves.</p><p>There is also a great deal of food waste because of the way supermarkets grade food, for example, if a tomato or mushroom is ugly it is discarded even though it has the same nutritional quality as one that is not.  United Nations statistics show that 1.3 billion tonnes of food are lost or wasted every year around the world, which is equivalent to the number of people malnourished or hungry.  In Europe we waste enough food to feed 870 million people.  We should begin to study food waste here and the energy required to produce and transport food.  This would be a more realistic step to reduce our carbon footprint and address some of the problems facing the world.  Ms Robinson&rsquo;s proposal is out of touch with the reality of how we need to live and the farmers who produce food.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#HH00200"><p>I remind speakers that the business now is statements on agricultural product prices and the decision by the United Kingdom to leave the European Union and they should try to keep their comments to that topic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#HH00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House to hear the observations and concerns we have about the agriculture and fisheries sectors across the island as a result of the Brexit vote.  This is the third such statement I have made on the subject in this Chamber.  I am more than happy to highlight the issues facing the agriculture and fisheries sectors that I hear from farmers and fishermen who have appeared before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  This highlights the crazy situation that the Tory government has led its citizens and the rest of Europe into.  It is clear that not the Tory government, the European authorities or our Government, of which the Minister is part, knows where we are going on this issue.  What has come out of the visits by the Minister&rsquo;s colleagues to this House when I and other Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; made similar statements?  Rather than Ministers with various other responsibilities coming in here to listen to similar statements every month or so we need a dedicated minister for Brexit who will run the committee on Brexit in tandem with his or her office that will have real teeth to deal with this issue.  This arrangement could invite stakeholders from every Department and examine the daily fallout, which is only going to get worse.  I would like the Minister to take the suggestion back to the Taoiseach and consider it wisely.  We have statements in this House and the D&aacute;il practically every week yet no one has full responsibility.  We are drifting into an abyss.  The hard rhetoric of the British Prime Minister and other British Ministers is particularly worrying.  It seems to be becoming entrenched and can only mean one thing for this island, which would be an unmitigated disaster for all of us, a hard Border.</p> <p>I spoke about the practicalities of day-to-day life in the Border counties in my previous statements and the direct impact on people&rsquo;s lives.  Together with other political, business, farming, tourism and community representatives, I recently attended a protest at the Border at Bridgend between Donegal and Derry.  There were considerable tailbacks at a Border checkpoint set up to demonstrate the impact this would have.  What will happen when this becomes a reality, with tailbacks, document checking in different jurisdictions in respect of agriculture for slaughtering and processing but even worse, tariffs and taxes?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2321"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2321&amp;amp;pid=PadraigMacLochlainn&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Product prices and price volatility in agriculture were already in upheaval even before the impact of Brexit.  This was due to trade restrictions with Russia, possible trade deals with the US and Canada, problems with the payment of schemes, the merger of major processing companies here in the form of the ABP-Slaney deal and the poor weather conditions.  Brexit has compounded them.  With Brexit we have currency volatility, regulation and origin issues, bureaucracy and security issues, potential recession and decreasing purchasing power.  </p><p>For the ordinary farmer and farming lobby groups following these proceedings, I suggest a number of supports from the EU and Ireland, which would work towards reducing price volatility and stabilising prices.  From an EU point of view, these supports should include a commitment to provide direct market intervention for beef if prices collapse in response to a UK-Mercosur deal, the introduction of temporary export refunds to help develop non-EU markets for Irish exports, flexibility on future CAP payments to allow member states to link payments back to supporting active food producers and security around future budgets.  Interventions the Government could carry out include aggressively pursuing markets, particularly the Chinese market for Irish beef, continuing to develop relations with the UK market and strengthening the Irish food brand in the UK in particular.  We need to remember and be conscious that the people who are most exposed to Brexit are British farmers.  Therefore, we should be lobbying them to prevent their Government from allowing their market to be flooded with cheap goods from other markets and should convince them of the importance of sourcing products from their neighbours.  We should also streamline taxation rules on supply of goods and services North and South.  Those are some ideas we would put to the Minister.</p><p>On the issue of fisheries, as a Donegal man I am aware from talking to the members of coastal communities that many of them have been impacted by Brexit.  They have raised the obvious issues of currency volatility, the decrease in profits as a result of that and the issue of territorial waters and how that will play out, particularly as one crosses from Donegal into the waters across from us.  There are serious issues for the fisheries community that need to be understood.  </p><p>To lessen the volatility brought about by the changes in the rate of sterling, we should utilise flexibility to provide direct financial supports to farmers under EU state aid rules in the form of short-term cashflow financing, provide an increase in funding for farms schemes and increase competition in the banking sector, thereby providing additional sources of finance to decrease borrowing costs.  The Irish Government must ensure early agreement and certainty on EU and CAP budgets up to 2020.  We need firm action.  I have outlined our proposals as to how we do that and I stand over them.  We need an accountable, dedicated minister for Brexit.  We need a direct committee and we need to put in place supports such as the ones I put forward.</p><p>I would also like to raise the issue of the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement, CETA, deal.  It seems the regional Belgian authorities, thankfully, have scuppered this agreement and Irish farmers will be happy.  The Minister is fully aware that this House passed a motion rejecting CETA.  Why was this democratic decision not respected?  Senior Ministers were still out lauding and promoting the passing of this deal against the wishes of the Seanad.  It seems ironic that the Minister is in here listening to a debate about price volatility in agriculture when the Government was going to sign up to a deal that was going to flood our market with lower quality produce.  Irish farmers need to be aware of who were the chief proposers of this deal.  In the past the Minister's colleagues in government were calling for a green jersey to be worn in another period of economic uncertainty.  I argue that in this Brexit period it is as important to don that same green jersey.  The consequences of not playing our part and of not putting on that green jersey and playing as part of a team are devastating.  This is too important a period to be going off in tangents.  Let us do this collectively.  Let us do it for the farmers.  Let us do it for the fishermen.  Let us do for the communities.  Let us do it for the businesses and, most importantly, let us do it for our country. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#JJ00200"><p>I would like to voice my concerns over the jobs in the agrifood sector in particular.  Like many of my colleagues, I will focus on the mushroom industry, which seems to be most impacted on at this stage.  The Irish mushroom industry is the fifth largest in the EU.  Irish mushroom growers rely on the UK for 80% of exports, representing &euro;120 million in farm-gate income, twice the value of Irish potato exports.  The industry employs approximately 3,500 people, mostly in rural areas.  Five of Ireland's 60 mushroom farms have been already driven out of business by a 19% drop in the value of sterling relative to the euro in the past few months since the UK voted to leave the EU.  That is &euro;7 million in exports and 130 jobs already gone.  However, mushroom exports are only a small part of the bigger picture of &euro;1.2 billion in bilateral trade that takes place every week between the UK and Ireland across various agri-industries that employ 400,000 people on both of the Irish Sea.  Almost half of our beef exports and 60% of our cheese products are sold to the UK.  Therefore, this situation is critical.</p> <p>The areas threatened with job losses are precisely those that can afford them least.  Unemployment in rural Ireland is still over 10% despite its fall below 8% at national level.  The Government will need to consider greater emergency financial supports beyond those promised in this year's Finance Bill and even an appeal to the European Commission for short-term supports, through CAP, to allow Irish mushroom growers, in particular, to weather this storm without having to move their operations to the UK.  The Government needs to monitor and gather data on the effects of Brexit on Irish industry and agriculture so as to co-ordinate the adaption to the rapidly evolving situation.  The Irish Government needs to work to ensure stability by engaging bilaterally with the UK Government to ensure stability of the Border and to reduce uncertainty.  The fluctuations in the pound are partially caused by the uncertainty regarding UK access to the Single Market and other aspects of the final Brexit deal with the EU.</p> <p>Seeking a quick resolution to the nature of the deal between the EU and UK will go some way to decreasing this.  If Theresa May's Government is, as it seems at this stage, determined to go for a hard Brexit without regard to the consequences, Ireland will have to reconsider its current strategy of trying to be the UK's best friend in negotiations.  Our future lies with the European Union ultimately and while all effort is made to maintain friendly and constructive relationships with our nearest neighbour, especially when it comes to the future of the Border with Northern Ireland, we cannot pursue it at the cost of our position as a full and active member of the EU.  As regrettable as it is, the British people have made their decision to leave the EU and over time we must rebalance our trade focus to a broader European market and possibly away from the UK, which has chosen separation over unity at this stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#JJ00300"><p>Like the Acting Chairman, Senator Horkan, I come from south County Dublin and I got a slight smirking remark from the Whip when I asked for speaking time for this debate this evening.  While, like the Acting Chairman, I spent my entire time in the council representing the 63 farmers in the Glencullen-Sandyford ward to the best of my ability, I appreciate that I do not come from a typical rural background with a typical interest in the agricultural sector.  I welcome the Minister to the House and I thank him for his comments.  Even though my late father lived and worked in Dublin, it was for an agrifood company.  I spent far too many days as a youngster at the National Ploughing Championships and shows all around Ireland handing out brochures and various other knick knacks, not to mention time spent on the beef and dairy farms of both my grandfathers.</p> <p>I want to speak on the post-Brexit situation and how that fateful decision taken by the people of UK will impact on the Irish economy in its entirety.  We appreciate that so much economic activity in this country relies on, is tied to and is dependent on the agricultural sector.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Neale Richmond:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2472"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2472&amp;amp;pid=NealeRichmond&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->One does not need to be from a family farm in rural Ireland to appreciate that and know the importance.  It is in that context that I want to pick up where Senator Mac Lochlainn left off in stressing the importance of new and ever freer and deeper trade deals to allow Ireland to navigate the choppy waters we face into, given the fateful decision by the British people to leave the EU.  The statistic is that 50% of our beef is exported to the UK, which is great.  We can offset that and enter into new EU trade deals with China and the US that would see Irish beef as well as Irish lamb enter those markets.  I welcome the decision announced by the Minister in the past few days that Irish lamb would be allowed into the Iranian market.  What are the other opportunities?  What other trade deals are on the table?  How have the decisions taken by the people of the UK, this Chamber but, more importantly, the parliament of Wallonia last week jeopardised the CETA agreement?</p><p>I stated on the record a few weeks ago that I believe CETA is a good deal that protects the interests of farmers in Ireland and across the EU bearing in mind that 95% of farms in the EU are family farms.  While I appreciate that there is far more commercial farming in Canada, there were necessary provisions in the deal to protect this area.  What will be the impact going forward?  I know the South Korean trade deal has proven to be wholly beneficial both to the Europeans and the South Koreans, particularly Ireland, but is the fateful decision of a region in Belgium with a population of less than three million jeopardising talks with the Australians, as I read in reports on debates in Canberra overnight?  What about possible EU deals that are starting to be negotiated with New Zealand, other Asian countries, Latin America, the Caribbean, China, Russia, Turkey, Africa and, of course, the US in the fateful TTIP agreement?  I have done some work on this agreement through the Committee of the Regions.  I have taken time out to look at the negotiating documents in Dublin and Brussels.  I think it is a good deal.  However, while there may be commercial merit in negotiating trade deals in secret behind closed doors, it jeopardises their well-being and has played a large part in the resistance to CETA, particularly among the labour movement in continental Europe and various sectors here, including food producers and providers.  It is vital for the Government to take cognisance of this issue and for it to be brought back to the European Council.  </p><p>We need free trade.  We need more, better and freer trade but in order to grasp that, take advantage of it and offset some of the obvious negativity that will come post-Brexit decisions, we need to see our leaders at Government and European Council level taking the initiative to make sure these deals are negotiated.  Language from Senator Mac Lochlainn and others that we will flood the European market with low-quality produce harks back to the protectionist ideals and scare mongering we saw in early 1970s Ireland and the UK from certain agricultural producers, manufacturers and elements in the labour movement.  These scare tactics were proven to be untrue.  Anyone in this Chamber can accept that membership of the EC, which became the EU, has been wholly positive, particularly for the Irish agricultural sector, and that we have benefited greatly from the Common Agricultural Policy.  Could the Minister address what possibilities there are in the future in respect of trade, what can be done about it and what changes can be made to negotiating tactics?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#KK00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I am always intrigued by the credentials of other Senators.  I commend Senator Richmond on putting his credentials on the record.  Some people might ask about my credentials in agriculture so I will put them on the record.  I have licences to breed pigs and rear poultry and I previously showed and trained ponies so I think my credentials are pretty okay for a Labour Party guy in Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</p><p>I commend the Minister and Government on the work that has been done to date.  Unlike a previous speaker, I believe that much work is actually being done.  We are in an area of unknowns but I take great solace from a recent round of discussions that I had in my capacity as chairman of the economic committee of the British&ndash;Irish Inter-Parliamentary Body, which is holding an inquiry into the effects of Brexit on the agrifood sector both North and South.  We attended Stormont on 13 October where we consulted with, among other groups, the Ulster Farmers Union, the Northern Ireland Meat Exporters Association and many environmental groups.  On 14 October, we consulted here in Leinster House with the IFA, the Irish Creamery Milk Suppliers Association, the Irish Cattle &amp;amp; Sheep Farmers Association, Enterprise Ireland, IDA Ireland, Teagasc, the Irish Exporters Association and the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  I intentionally left the Department until last.  I want to put on the record my gratitude to a departmental staff member, Paul Savage, for the effort he put in that day in bringing us up to speed on all that is ongoing in this country in respect of the outcome of Brexit.  On the other hand, I must also record my condemnation of the lack of appearance from the Northern Ireland Department of Agriculture, Environment and Rural Affairs.  I have since written to the Minister for Agriculture, Environment and Rural Affairs, Michelle McIlveen, stating the economic committee's disappointment at the response we received, which was that the Department of Agriculture, Environment and Rural Affairs had nothing to say on the matter.  I will leave it at that.  Our disapproval has been registered and has gone by post.</p><p>It is true to say that nobody knows the outcome and that the uncertainty is the biggest problem in respect of this issue.  A voice is badly needed in respect of the issue of currency fluctuations for the main players in the agri sector.  Most people do not understand the term &quot;hedging&quot;.  I am talking about SMEs.  I will not go into individual commentary because it was of a private nature but one of the speakers at an inquiry meeting in Dublin could not express the importance he placed on a forum that would provide information to mainstream farming and the agri sector in respect of currency fluctuations and their implications post-Brexit.  In his speech, the Minister said that Enterprise Ireland is doing some work in this area.  He mentioned some other group as well.  I would like to know exactly what they are doing.  I have taken soundings in my constituency from people I know in the farming industry and none of them has heard anything from anybody on this.  As the Minister knows, sterling has dropped 40% in the past year.  It has already been said so I will not go into it but Senator Paul Daly spent a lot of time talking about the mushroom industry and I completely support him.  One of the businesses that was lost was in Tipperary and it is all because Irish exporters of produce must take produce off the shelves in the UK because while the market is there, they are losing money by leaving it on the shelves.  This is an area in which they need to be educated.  </p><p>Loss of market has already been outlined.  It is a loss of market both ways.  A total of 50% of Northern Ireland beef and milk comes to the South while about 45% of pigs go North so we are not just talking about the &euro;7 billion worth of exports that go to the UK.  We are talking about North-South trade.  I am very concerned about the mixed political messages.  One of the main political parties in Northern Ireland, the DUP, voted in favour of Brexit while others voted against.  They are now telling us that they are totally engaged with the British Prime Minister, Theresa May, who was supposedly a &quot;Remain&quot; supporter but who certainly did not break any sweat in respect of it.  Mixed messages are coming to the market and there are mixed messages internationally.  That also feeds into the difficulty we face because we are going to be minus a market worth &euro;64 million.  The Northern Ireland farmers' associations are concerned.  They provide a quality product that meets all of the requirements of EU standardisation, as we do, but the UK mainstream is already looking to bring in produce from South America that does not meet any standards we meet.  It is not directly our area but this problem will impact on us and the Minister should address it.  </p><p>I know Senator Paul Daly has a particular interest in the horse racing industry in this country.  If one reads this week's <i>The Irish Field</i>, one will see where markers are falling because of sterling.  One will also see that trainers are falling.  One example is given in a two-page article of 26 horses in training.  The net profit for the trainer per month is &euro;847.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Denis Landy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2349"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2349&amp;amp;pid=DenisLandy&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is unsustainable.  I request that the Minister attend the House at another time for a debate on the horse racing industry in view of the fact that Brexit has implications for it.</p><p>The disadvantaged areas scheme has been mentioned.  However, I wish to ask that the Minister consider another matter.  There are flood plains across the country.  Last week, a group from the Blackwater Valley in counties Waterford and Cork visited Leinster House.  The group's problem is not with the disadvantaged areas scheme, but with flooding.  There is annual flooding.  In the mid 1990s when the late Noel Davern was Minister of State with responsibility for agriculture, I, as a councillor, proposed to him that we provide a set-aside scheme for farms that were flooded annually.  When making our submission to Europe, there is an opportunity to seize on this idea.  I am prepared to give the Minister information on this and to discuss it with him.</p><p>What practical steps are being taken in the context of the &euro;150 million fund the Minister has commendably included in the budget?  How will North-South trade pan out?  Many of the companies that trade in the North, particularly in beef, also trade in the South.  Will jobs move south as a result of Brexit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#LL00200"><p>My colleague has already addressed some of the concerns relating to the mushroom industry and rural employment.  It is an issue that I am aware of, having worked with young unemployed people in rural areas and seen the importance of such industries there.  The mushroom industry is one in which standards have been strengthened, particularly in terms of workers' rights.  It is important that we acknowledge, encourage and support this.</p> <p>I will address the question of trade, which the Minister and Senator Richmond discussed.  It is important that we set the record straight.  There has been a suggestion across much of the media that Wallonia is the only area in Europe that has opposed the provisional application of the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement, CETA, but it is actually the case that Belgium and this House are the only places where there has been parliamentary debate on the issue.  We are not talking about Wallonia disagreeing with the consensus across Europe, we are talking about a situation in which only the Seanad, which voted to express sensible and reasonable concerns regarding the provisional application of CETA, and Belgium have held parliamentary debates on CETA.  If we are passionate about being European, as I am, we must point out that we are members of the EU and it behoves us to be able to challenge for and look to better and more appropriate trade deals.  In that respect, Ireland needs to be able to look for better trade in this and future trade missions and agreements.  I encourage the Minister to do this.</p> <p>In Wallonia, it was mainly small farmers who campaigned and agitated regarding the real obstacle, namely, investor courts.  The impasse is not a matter of whether one country or district will sign, rather, it is whether we are willing to acknowledge that the investor court system, which no one will defend and which is unnecessary for dealing with, for example, countries such as Canada that have well-established legal systems, as we do, is an unnecessary obstacle to an effective trade ratification process across Europe.  Senator Richmond referred to family farms.  However, it is not them, mushroom producers in Ireland or small producers that will take cases to the investor courts.  Rather, the major agribusiness companies will be able to take advantage of and be advantaged by the investor court system.</p> <p>We need trade agreements that are workable for farmers, other citizens and the environment, can be passed, deliver sustainable jobs and do not place blank-cheque pressure on future Governments and public policy.  For example, it would be difficult under an investor court system if we wanted to use public policy to intervene and support our local mushroom industry.  I encourage the Minister to reconsider this matter.  It is important that, when the UK makes a trade agreement with Europe, we will have moved past the current unworkable model of trade deals and towards something that is workable for everyone.</p> <p>I echo my colleague's concerns and call on the Government to find appropriate ways to intervene and support those specific food and agricultural product industries that are struggling to make this transition.  I urge the Government to link with groups such as the Vincentian Partnership for Social Justice, which has examined a shopping basket of goods.  We need a goods-by-goods approach to this matter and we must look to each sector - section by section - in order to address this.  We could also link with major supermarket purchasers and apply pressure in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#LL00300"><p>Next is Senator Lombard, who is sharing time with Senator Kieran O'Donnell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#LL00400"><p>I welcome the Minister and compliment him on the impact he has had on agriculture in only a short time.  He provided a safe pair of hands when such was needed.  It is great that we have him with us today.</p><p>In many ways, Brexit is the greatest challenge facing our food and drinks industry.  The coming months and years will say much about how our industry develops.  There have been major changes in recent decades in the form, for example, of quotas and mechanisation, but how we will deal with our largest market being placed in long-term jeopardy will be a significant test.  How the Minister deals with these issues will be his legacy.  I have faith that he will deal with them appropriately.</p><p>Unfortunately, there is a considerable amount of upset about how we handle the issues of sterling and our dairy industry.  Approximately 60% of our cheese goes to the UK.  We are building a magnificent empire in our dairy industry but tariffs could be placed on it.  What of pork products from the North coming to the South and <i>vice versa</i>?  What of labelling issues, for example, Ireland as the place of origin, and the sustainability that we have given our products so that we can sell them on international markets?  Our real brand is our good name.  As such, a cross-Border organisation needs to be established in order to ensure that the good name that we have built continues.  These will be major challenges for us in the period ahead.</p><p>After a number of years, the dairy industry is moving forward again.  However, Brexit has created doubt with regard to its pricing structures.  The Minister has introduced working capital, which has been acknowledged as a forward-thinking move, but the real question for us is how we will deal with the market next door.</p><p>Other industries have been mentioned but what of our dairy industry's stock being sold abroad?  Sterling is having a major impact on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#LL00500"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and commend him on his work to date.  He will undoubtedly leave a legacy, but we will not give him a legacy just yet.</p> <p>I represent Limerick and Clare farmers.  The greatest issue is that of sterling.  Senator Lombard touched on the expansion in quotas and so forth.  Now on top of this is uncertainty over sterling.  The euro could shortly have parity with sterling.  It is more of a probability than a possibility.  One could say that it is even more of a certainty than a probability.  We must determine ways to counteract it.</p> <p>I welcome the low-interest rate agri loan, but when does the Minister expect it to be put in place?  It has been sent to the Commission but farmers are already asking when it will come into play and how it will work practically.  I assume that they will go to their local banks.  What is the appraisal process?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kieran O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2207"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2207&amp;amp;pid=KieranODonnell&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Is it done through the bank?  Will an independent body oversee the loans?  What will be the mechanism?  I very much welcome the measure.</p><p>I welcome also the engagement the Minister has had with his counterparts in the North both at departmental and ministerial level.  In terms of Brexit, an all-Ireland focus is extremely important.</p><p>I refer to an issue that is slightly outside this area but one in which I have a personal interest, and it applies regardless of Brexit.  Farmers have studied in great depth the breakdown of farm prices from the farm gate to retailers, taking into account the producers, wholesaler-retailers and end-customers, because it is impacting on them directly.  The issue arises with the multiples.  In many cases the price they can pay back to the farmer is determined by the price they are getting from the co-operatives.  Will the Minister consider doing empirical work, both at national and European level, to come up with a mechanism to ensure the farmer gets a fair price because in the rural villages I represent in east Limerick, farming is vital?  It continues to grow and prosper to keep businesses open and to keep people living in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#MM00200"><p>If we had finished at 6.25 p.m. the Minister would have had only five minutes but he now has until 6.30 p.m. if he wishes to use the time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#MM00300"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman.  I thank my colleagues in the Seanad for their contributions, observations and suggestions.  This is an unprecedented period in terms of the economic challenges the country faces.  There has probably been nothing equivalent to it since the foundation of the State.  It is that significant.  I am on record as having said there is no upside for Ireland Inc.  There may be localised victories but, overall, it is a real question of damage limitation.  That is an extremely uncomfortable reality and for an industry like the agrifood sector, which has its tentacles spread into every corner of rural Ireland, where in many areas there are not real alternative forms of employment available, it is a challenge to protect the industry in that context.  Our position is best served by remaining within the European Union and in remaining within the European Union we have pooled our sovereignty in respect of negotiations on trade agreements.  I want to take up the point raised by Senators Mac Lochlainn, Higgins and Richmond on that area.</p> <p>In terms of the commentary on trade in these Houses, there have always been naysayers in respect of trade deals we have concluded.  However, with the benefit of hindsight we have seen that, on balance, the trade deals have been beneficial for Ireland Inc., Irish industry and, in particular, Irish agriculture.  We need to bear in mind that we are an island nation of 4.5 million people with a capacity to feed multiples of that number, an ambition which translated in economic terms in 2015 to values of &euro;10.8 billion in exports.  An ambition in Food Wise 2025 is to reach almost &euro;20 billion by 2020.  If we do not trade, that industry dies, and it is not a question of trade under any circumstances.  We need to remain vigilant on the detail and in the context of, say, the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, one of the things we have sought at Agriculture and Fisheries Council level is to ascertain the cumulative impact, particularly in the area of beef exports or imports into the European Union, as the case may be, of multiple trade deals.</p> <p>The fundamental principle is that we need to trade.  We need to get 90% of what we produce off the island.  In principle, therefore, our starting position must be pro-trade, in favour of the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement, CETA, pro-TTIP and in favour of any other trade deal that, on balance, reflects our best interests.  I believe that, on balance, CETA reflects our best interests, and I say that with all due respect to the vote in this House.  I am surprised that some people who voted against that trade deal would now purport to articulate the interests of the Irish agriculture sector.  It is an extraordinary contraposition to take because, on balance, anybody who has looked at this from the perspective of Irish agriculture would undoubtedly conclude that the interests of Irish agriculture are best served by CETA.  The Senators should not take my word for that.  They should ask the people in the broader agriculture-agrifood industry what they think about it.</p> <p>We do not serve ourselves well in terms of all the public commentary on trade and the level of secrecy, which Senator Richmond referred to, is counterproductive and fuels a conspiracy theory that this is big business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#MM00400"><p>I have to correct the Minister on the phrase "conspiracy theory".  We need to be very careful in the language we use.  I hope the Minister is not suggesting that is anything to do with the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#MM00500"><p>I am not talking about any particular person.  If the cap fits, wear it, but the point is true.  There are conspiracy theorists out there who believe that every step taken by the State is somehow a betrayal of the interests of its citizens.  When we look at the history of trade deals, that does not stand up to scrutiny.  In that context, we at least deserve the benefit of the doubt in terms of the trade deals we have negotiated but we also need to look at it objectively.  For example, the study done independently for the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation by Copenhagen Economics identified in clear areas, for example on TTIP, the challenges and the potential downsides but the on-balance assessment was that trade within certain parameters is beneficial for us.  As an agrifood exporting nation, we need to be very aware of that.  Secrecy in respect of our partners in those negotiations brings the system into disrepute and in that sense I have stated publicly that the United States approach to those trade agreements is unfortunate.  The European Union's position has been available online.</p> <p>The issue of access to the courts is very interesting because in the context of Brexit, we are facing very serious challenges to the terms and conditions under which we will access space on the supermarket shelves in the United Kingdom, and we would like to believe that whether it is an artisan food producer or a global Irish agrifood industry, they would have access to an appropriate judicial process to protect their interests.  It is not that there is a process for adjudication on these matters, it is that in the context of Brexit, we may wish to have access to an appropriate structure.  There is an inclination to jump on an anti-trade bandwagon and I do not believe that, on balance, that serves us well.</p> <p>I refer to the North-South dimension to this issue, which was dealt with by a number of contributors.  Tomorrow, for the fourth time since my appointment, I will meet Michelle McIlveen, the DUP Minister for Agriculture, Environment and Rural Affairs in Northern Ireland and officials at a bilateral meeting in Armagh.  The Minister of State, Deputy Ring, also will attend.  This is an area of the most extraordinary complexity, which I will outline in some detail.  On the dairy side, straddling the Border, we have LacPatrick, Lakeland Dairies and Strathroy Dairy Limited in Northern Ireland, processing a milk pool that is broadly collected from both sides of the Border.  The question that arises is that if milk coming South from Northern Ireland for processing in LacPatrick or Lakeland Dairies is to be subject to a tariff post-Brexit, how profitable will that be?  What is the product that is manufactured in terms of food labelling?  Is it Irish?  Is it British?  Is it a hybrid?  Where does that fit into the labelling regulations about which consumers are entitled to know?  That is a glaring example of the complexities we need to work through.  I have made the point previously to Minister McIlveen, that the historical aspect in terms of the Border and the Troubles is entirely a separate debate and anything that raises that issue in the context of Brexit is an unnecessary distraction.  We need to focus on the practicalities.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Michael Creed:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=259"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=259&amp;amp;pid=MichaelCreed&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am interested in protecting the best interests of Irish agriculture, its export opportunities, primary producers and the co-operatives involved in processing.  We need to work through the detail of it, and everything else can be parked for another day.  This is not the time to mix issues that, while they may be significant, are not compatible with the debate.</p><p>Senator Denis Landy referred to the equine industry.  While we are global leaders in the equine industry, the greatest traffic in equine exports is between Ireland and the UK.  This is one of the industries that is incredibly mobile.  If we put serious impediments in its place after Brexit, the industry could up and leave overnight.  The Senator knows this better than anybody, given that he comes from Tipperary, where the industry has a presence.  We need to work through all the detail necessary to facilitate the ease of movement that has facilitated the industry to grow and prosper and provide 14,000 jobs.  The industry is worth more than &euro;1 billion and there is an ambition in Food Wise 2025 to grow the sector to more than &euro;2 billion.  This is challenged by Brexit.</p><p>Approximately 350,000 sheep come to the South from Northern Ireland for processing every year.  Somebody referred to pigs going North of the Border for slaughter, and it is a daily occurrence.  Some 55,000 cattle went North of the Border in 2015 for breeding or slaughter.  It is an extraordinarily complex area.  We need to work through, with our counterparts in Northern Ireland, arrangements around these issues and identify the best solutions to protect our respective interests.  They are not very different interests, although they are different jurisdictions.  We have had the benefit of an all-island approach on animal health.  What will happen if the UK leaves the EU and begins to unpick veterinary certification standards?  It would be an additional cost to business that we could do without.  This bears up my assertion that there is no upside whatsoever.  This is a case of managing a very challenging and difficult situation which will bring the level of ambition in Food Wise 2025 under scrutiny.</p><p>The critical question is whether, given that the value of our exports to the UK is &euro;5.1 billion, we are excessively dependent on our nearest market.  I accept Senator Boyhan's point that it is the most valuable market for us to be in.  The obvious solution is to search for new market opportunities.  They are identified in Food Wise 2025, which mentions emerging opportunities in south-east Asia.  This is why I was recently on a trade mission to China, Singapore, Vietnam and South Korea, along with the Minister of State, Deputy Andrew Doyle.  This area is identified given that is has an emerging middle class with greater purchasing power.  In a very short space of time, while the UK is our premier market for dairy exports, our second biggest market for dairy exports is China, in particular due to the market foothold we have gained in infant formula.  While the UK is our biggest export market for pork, our second biggest market is China.  If we could clear the remaining hurdles on getting beef into China, in a short space of time it would become a very significant market.  Senator Paul Daly and others raised the issue of the beef industry.  It is an extremely challenging area.</p><p>As with all of the debate on Brexit, there is no silver bullet.  There is no one issue.  With apologies to Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn, there is a simplicity about the suggestion that a single Brexit Minister, which Fianna F&aacute;il also raised, would solve all the issues.  It is so enormously complex across all Departments that it oversimplifies the issue.  The issue requires a whole of Government approach and not just saying it is the responsibility of Deputy Michael Creed, Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor or whoever.  The issue has an impact in practically every Department.  One would struggle to find a Department that will not be impacted by Brexit.  Even in the UK, there are three wise men.  David Davis, Boris Johnson and Liam Fox are leading their charge.  Let us see how they progress it.</p><p>We are fortunate that we did a lot of pre-planning, as did many other reputable bodies, institutes and individuals.  When, on 6 May, I was appointed Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, the Secretary General gave me a substantial file and the two biggest parts of it were the climate change agenda and Brexit.  Although we had hoped that by 24 June it would be in the shredder, it has moved to centre stage and informs every single thing we are doing.  We have a dedicated Brexit unit in the Department.  I take the point about my Department colleague, Mr. Paul Savage, who does tremendous work in the area and is involved in the dedicated Brexit unit, as are many others.  It is a very hard-working unit and is scoping out all these issues.  After my first meeting with the Northern Ireland Minister for Agriculture, Environment and Rural Affairs, Michelle McIlveen, MLA, we decided senior officials, North and South, should begin the detailed parsing and analysing of the issues and it has been ongoing since summer.</p><p>We established a stakeholders forum, given that we are not all-knowing.  It is important that my Department and officials, and the agencies that operate under my Department, hear at first hand what the issues are.  The immediate manifestation has been sterling fluctuations.  I cannot fix the market or control currency fluctuations.  Neither can I determine the price of beef or milk, and anyone who says he or she can do so is being deliberately misleading.  What we can do is ensure we are as well informed as we can be as we attempt to navigate a route to bring the industry through this extraordinary challenge in the best shape possible.  Some of the response is finding new markets.  Some of it is encouraging our agrifood sector to move up the value chain and insulate itself against the worst excesses of the market in order that it is moving in an area where prices are premium for the product we are producing.  Fortunately, we have this collaboration between the State agencies, research and development, and the big food companies.  While we were travelling this road before the Brexit decision, it is important we accelerate it.</p><p>One of the things I asked the agencies under my Department, including Bord Iascaigh Mhara, Enterprise Ireland and Bord Bia, to do very early on was to make direct contact with their individual client companies and tailor-make specific interventions that would assist them to come through.  They have been engaged in workshops on currency fluctuation management, hedging options, strengthening engagement and deepening their understanding of the UK markets they are working in.  Last week, I was in the UK meeting the CEO of one of the major multiples and saying that while we are in a difficult space, we are not surrendering the hard-won yards the Irish agrifood sector has made over several decades in terms of supermarket shelf space.  We can and will rise to the challenge.  We are working through it.</p><p>One of the initiatives that will help the industry come through is access to affordable finance.  We had this initiative in the budget and Senator Kieran O'Donnell raised the question of how it will work.  It has been leveraged by &euro;11 million we got in the July compensation package.  There was a &euro;350 million package.  Our share of it nationally was &euro;11 million.  We put &euro;14 million with it and leveraged &euro;150 million.  We used the &euro;25 million we put into it to subsidise the interest rate and put in a guarantee against first losses on the loan.  It is a loan fund of a maximum &euro;150 million at an interest rate of 2.95% and a six year term.  The Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland, SBCI, which is administering the fund, will soon make a call for partners to deliver the loan at a local level.  I have spoken to the CEOs of the pillar banks, AIB and Bank of Ireland, and Ulster Bank.  They are all enthusiastic about participating in delivering the fund at that interest rate to their clients.  It is not an encouragement to farmers to borrow their way out of the difficulties but to say that if farmers have credit at a more expensive rate, particularly merchant credit or overdrafts at a high interest rate, this is an opportunity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Michael Creed:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=259"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=259&amp;amp;pid=MichaelCreed&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is working capital and has minimum red tape around it.  It is a groundbreaking financial product.  In many respects, and Senators have raised this issue regarding the agrifood industry generally, there is now a template for how to access low cost finance for other sectors.  The agrifood industry will need that.  A Central Bank report in April 2016 provided a league table which showed, unfortunately, that we are at the wrong end of the table in terms of interest rates paid relative to those paid by our eurozone counterparts.  My recollection is that Austria had the lowest rates and we were at the wrong end at an average of 5.7%.  Senators will appreciate that with a rate of 2.95% this is a significant product we can use.<br/><br/>There were many references to the mushroom sector.  This sector has been in the firing line.  My colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Andrew Doyle, has met with representatives of the horticulture industry and some of the major players in that industry.  It is a very difficult environment.  Under the low interest loan fund, and under <i>de minimis</i>rules which is a way of overcoming the state aid regulation, we are making some of that access to funding at low interest rates available to the mushroom industry.  In addition, in the budget we increased the capital grant scheme for the horticulture sector to &euro;5 million.  Recently, we paid in excess of &euro;1 million - I do not recall the exact figure but it is probably approximately &euro;1.5 million - to one of the major producer organisations for the mushroom sector.  It is a transnational producer organisation.<br/><br/>The point was made that this is not an sector where alternative markets are an option because of the short shelf life.  It is the most convenient market for us.  It is the closest one and the cheapest to access.  However, one of our main challengers for market shelf space are the Poles.  They have many advantages, including that their minimum wage rates and ours are significantly different, but if they can bring their product that distance to the market it suggests that we should possibly explore alternative markets as well.  Obviously, markets in the eurozone would bring advantages.  We cannot afford to say &quot;No&quot; to any area.  The UK is undoubtedly the market with which we are most comfortable and it has served the industry and its expansion well.  This is one of the areas most exposed to the challenges and through a series of initiatives, such as the low interest loans, capital grant scheme and support of the producer organisations, we are trying to work with the organisations to see what we can do.  We remain open to further dialogue and suggestions regarding an area that is particularly difficult and exposed, given that it is a high volume and very low margin industry.  The movement of sterling versus the euro, year on year from September to September, is over 20%.  That tells its own tale in respect of a low margin business.<br/><br/>With regard to fisheries, the Common Fisheries Policy is an extraordinarily complicated tapestry that has been woven over several years of December Council negotiations.  When one unpicks one strand of that, which is the UK when it decides to leave, the tapestry begins to unravel.  This will be an enormous challenge.  We are a shareholder in over 30 of the 40 species of fish for which the UK holds a quota.  Imagine it simply in geographical terms.  Consider the UK and its coastal waters and if, for example, one of the terms of its Brexit negotiations, and this is a big &quot;if&quot;, is that the UK takes access to those territorial waters exclusively.  That means all of the fishing endeavour that takes place across the European Union, where there are shared rights to fish, will spill into a smaller space because the UK will control exclusive access to its area.<br/><br/>In terms of a finite resource of fish stocks, that will bring enormous challenges for the industry.  The annual total allowable catch, or quota, is based on science and the fishing effort is retrofitted into the science.  That is an uncomfortable exercise every year for the industry.  Unfortunately, fish do not recognise any borders drawn on maps and obviously individual states, particularly if they are outside the European Union, will have an entitlement to regulate their own coastal waters, so fishing efforts will be restricted to those who fly the UK flag.  Interestingly, however, much of the UK fishing effort has been privatised and now flies foreign flags.  One of the hallmarks of the industry in this country is that we have retained quotas in public ownership and they are allocated to the industry almost on a monthly basis, by agreement and in consultation with the industry, after the October or December Council as they may apply to the species of fish.  Brexit is going to be extraordinarily complicated because the UK will then move into an area in which we will still negotiate with the UK but where it will have exclusive access to its own waters.  That is a challenge.<br/><br/>I hope I have dealt with most of the issues.  Senator Mulherin raised the issue of climate change, which is relevant in the context of the greater food industry, and mentioned comments by the former Irish President, Mary Robinson, on veganism and vegetarianism.  The ambition we have for the agrifood industry in very much grounded in sustainability, but it is sustainable intensification of our agriculture.  We have a very good story to tell in terms of our sustainability credentials.  We are, bar none, the most carbon efficient producer of milk on the planet.  In the European Union, we are the fifth most carbon efficient producer of beef and, by virtue of incentives such as the green low-carbon agri-environment scheme, GLAS, and the beef data and genomics programme, we are driving down our carbon footprint each year.  Those incentives are informed by meeting the challenges of climate change.  The investment we make each year in the forestry sector is very significant, with over &euro;3 billion spent by the State on forestry between 1990 and 2015.  We will continue that in the budget this year, which provides over &euro;110 million for the forestry sector.  That is reducing our carbon footprint.<br/><br/>Yes, we have more to do and the sector will not shy away from that.  However, it is subject to some unfair criticism from commentators because it contributes a high proportion of the State's greenhouse gas emissions.  That happens because, as a nation, we never had the historical legacy of heavy industry.  Although the sector is a significant contributor to domestic carbon emissions, it is nonetheless a very carbon efficient producer of food.  It would be at least ironic and ultimately counterproductive to dismantle a food producing sector that is carbon efficient, while stating that we have obligations to produce food to feed a growing world population, and consequently import food at the cost of very substantial air miles or nautical miles.  For example, ships steaming with beef from South America would have a far higher carbon footprint.  There must be joined-up thinking.  We believe that sustainable intensification which is geared towards meeting a global demand for food is the way to proceed.  Certainly, my Department is up for the challenge of meeting the twin objectives of reducing our carbon footprint and increasing our food output.<br/><br/>I believe I have dealt with most of the matters raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#OO00200"><p>The Minister has timed it perfectly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#OO00300"><p>I thank the Members for their contributions and suggestions.  I certainly will reflect on them because this is something that will continue to evolve.  It is an enormous challenge that requires our collective endeavours to ensure we achieve the best results for Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#OO00400"><p>I thank the Minister for his opening statement and comprehensive response to the Members.  I also thank the Members for their participation in the debate.  When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016102500002#OO00500"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-10-25a.252" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.30 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 26 October 2016.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>