<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#A00100">Teachtaireacht ón Dáil - Message from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#A00200"><p>I have received the following message from D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Finance (Covid-19 and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2022 on 4 May 2022, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#A00300">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#A00400"><p>I have received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on increased investment in train services between Dublin and Cork. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on plans for the future operation and development of Shannon Heritage sites. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Seery Kearney of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to provide an update on the construction defects working group. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform to restore fee rates paid under the criminal legal aid scheme. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on funding streams available to local authorities for the provision of public facilities at public amenities. </blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Sharon Keogan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the introduction in July of free travel on public transport for child leap card holders. </blockquote><p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected those of Senators Buttimer, Conway, Seery Kearney and Ward and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matters raised by Senators Tim Lombard and Sharon Keogan on the grounds that the relevant Ministers have no responsibility in those matters.<br/><br/>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  Before we take the first Commencement matter from Senator Buttimer, I would like to take the opportunity to welcome to the Distinguished Visitors Gallery Councillor Conor Casey from Montpelier in Vermont.  He is most welcome.  I thank him for being here today and for being part of the leadership of our American-Irish community over there.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.10" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#B00200">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.11" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#B00300">Rail Network</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#B00400"><p>In the Visitors Gallery are fifth year students from Nenagh.  I welcome them to Leinster House today and hope they find their visit to the Houses of the Oireachtas beneficial.</p> <p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise the issue of the Dublin-Cork rail service.  The Minister of State, Deputy Troy, is very welcome.  As he will know, the all-Ireland rail review is currently being undertaken by the Department.  The electrification of the rail line, provision of a new fleet and the need to meet our climate change targets are all important.</p> <p>As we take a modal shift away from the car to public transport, it is opportune that the Cork commuter rail network is being progressed and advanced.  That is why I welcome today what I hope will be a decision by Government to allow for the drawing down of &euro;74 million of the EU Recovery and Resilience Facility to take place.  The electrification and upgrading of the Cork-Dublin rail line is important.  If we look at the national development plan, NDP, the strategic importance of Cork as a counterbalance to Dublin and Belfast has never been more critical.</p> <p>That is why I am asking for the Government, as part of the all-Ireland rail review, to advance the frequency of the Dublin-Cork rail service in the context of the electrification of the tracks, to replace existing stock and to invest to improve the rail line to ensure greater frequency, especially at peak times.  It is critical that we have a movement from an hourly to half-hourly service.  As I said, the electrification of the line will reduce the journey time and increase the offerings for the travelling public.  Linked to that is the need for an early morning train to Cork from Dublin.  In 2022, I think we will all agree that a 9.30 a.m., 9.35 a.m. or 9.40 a.m. arrival time in Cork is not acceptable.  The optimal time we should have the first train into Kent Station is well before 9 o'clock at 8.30 a.m. or 8.45 a.m.  I ask that this be progressed as a matter of urgency.  Mar fhocal scoir, I am asking for frequency at peak times to be increased, the plan for electrification to be expedited and the journey time be reduced to one hour and 30 minutes from its present time.  I call on Government, in particular the Minister, Deputy Ryan, to look at electrification.</p> <p>I appreciate the issue of fares is controlled by the National Transport Authority, NTA.  The NTA must work with Government, the travelling public and the commuter to ensure a fare that is economical, encouraging and attracts people to travel by train.</p> <p>These are exciting times for Cork with the commuter train network being advanced.  I welcome the appointment of A.J. Cronin as the delivery manager for that.  I look forward to the Minister of State's reply to what is a very important matter, not just for Cork but for the southern region.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#C00100"><p>I thank Senator Buttimer for raising this question and giving me the opportunity to discuss this topic with Members of the House on behalf of the Minister for Transport, who sends his regrets.</p> <p>I have been advised that Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann&rsquo;s operational fleet is currently fully deployed on scheduled services, in line with prevailing passenger demand.  The current capacity on the rail network is primarily based on demand levels pre Covid, when rapid growth in demand resulted in the utilisation of 100% of Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann&rsquo;s operational fleet at peak times.  As it stands, I am given to understand that there are 14 services from Dublin to Cork each day on weekdays, with the first service departing at 7 a.m., and a further ten services from Dublin to Cork on weekend days.</p> <p>The Cork route, as is common with those to other provincial cities, has a dominant demand for travel to Dublin in the morning peak, and from Dublin in the evening peak.  Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann&rsquo;s timetable is designed to service this demand as far as is practical.  However, it is acknowledged that there are alternative travel demands to this established pattern, such as earlier departure times to Dublin, as referenced by the Senator.  Fleet and driver resources would be required to provide additional services and it is something that could be considered in the medium term if demand was established and when new rolling stock expands Irish Rail&rsquo;s operational fleet over the coming years.</p> <p>Post Covid, passenger demand is suppressed in the short term, albeit showing gradual signs of improvement as we exit the Covid-19 pandemic.  Significantly altered travel patterns are emerging and Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann intends to undertake an analysis of post-Covid travel trends across the network in late 2022, including the Dublin to Cork line, in order to review its service offering and adapt its timetable to meet customer demands.  It is expected that this assessment, being undertaken in conjunction with the National Transport Authority, will take a number of months to finalise as new travel patterns become more established with a phased return to the workplace.  This process will also take into account the delivery of 41 intercity railcar carriages, commencing from mid-2022.  Once this analysis process has been completed, a timetable and capacity proposal will be prepared and issued for public consultation on Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann&rsquo;s website. </p> <p>Further, the national development plan that was launched by the Government in October 2021 will result in the introduction of additional public transport infrastructure which will help to relieve congestion on the network while also providing new rolling stock to provide greater capacity for Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann&rsquo;s increasing passenger numbers into the future.  An initial order of 95 electric and battery-electric carriages for the DART+ fleet was placed in December 2021.  It is expected that the first 95 carriages will arrive from mid-2024, entering service on the rail network from 2025 and potentially freeing up existing commuter and intercity rolling stock for use on other routes across the rail network.</p> <p>The strategic rail review, which the Senator referenced, is being undertaken in co-operation with the Department for Infrastructure in Northern Ireland.  This will inform the development of interurban and interregional rail on the island of Ireland over the coming decades.  This will be one of the most significant reviews of the rail network on the island in many years, providing a framework to develop an improved rail network for our future.  The review will consider the potential scope for improved rail services along various existing and potential future corridors of the network, including Cork to Dublin.  The report is due to be finalised in the fourth quarter of this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply and acknowledge the positivity in it.  It is imperative that Irish Rail delivers on an early morning train service from Dublin to Cork.  A 7 a.m. departure time from Dublin is no longer acceptable or tenable.  Notwithstanding the 14 daily services from Dublin to Cork, it is important we have delivery of that early morning train.  The national development plan places Cork at its heart.  Central to that is investment in an alternative to the car, which is public transport.  If we are to complete that modal shift we need that early morning train from Dublin to Cork, which will serve Cork and its hinterlands.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This would be economically positive for the region.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I look forward to the all-Ireland review and to working with the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, and the Minister of State, Deputy Naughton, on delivering this early morning train service from Dublin to Cork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#D00200"><p>The Senator is right to say that the Government recognises the importance of getting more people onto public transport.  It is important for improving their quality of life and for the country meeting its obligation to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by 51% by 2030.  We have committed to making the largest ever investment in public transport as part of the national development plan, which was launched in October 2021.</p><p>I will report the Senator's points to the Minister.  If we are serious about getting people to use public transport, we must ensure that we put services on at times that passengers need them for work and so on, not just at times that it suits to run them.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.17" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#D00300">Heritage Centres</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#D00400"><p>As always, the Minister of State is welcome.</p><p>This issue has been ongoing since the Shannon Airport Authority decided that it no longer had a strategic interest in Shannon Heritage.  The questions then were what would happen to Shannon Heritage's facilities and under whose auspices would they be.  King John's Castle has been transferred to Limerick City and County Council, which is a good fit.</p><p>In Clare, Shannon Heritage essentially comprises the Bunratty, Craggaunowen and Knappogue facilities, which have been visited by millions upon millions of tourists down the years.  Sadly, Shannon Group's capital investment in the castles and various facilities that form part of Shannon Heritage's offering in County Clare has been practically non-existent over the past decade, if not longer.  The facilities have depreciated, not just in monetary value, but in their value as tourism offerings.  This is a great pity because we all remember visiting Bunratty Castle and Folk Park when we were children.  Many also remember visiting Knappogue and Craggaunowen.  These facilities should never have been allowed to deteriorate to their current level.</p><p>Clare County Council has stepped up to the plate and stated that it is interested in taking over and running the facilities in the same professional manner that it runs other facilities, for example, the Vandeleur walled garden in Kilrush and the Cliffs of Moher Experience in north Clare, but why should ratepayers and Clare County Council have to suffer financial loss for doing the right thing?  It is accepted by all parties that the council is the right body to take over and develop these facilities.  Ideally, the Office of Public Works, OPW, should be doing this.  Given the council's tourism experience, though, this is a good fit and will complement the other attractions that the council is running successfully.</p><p>Some &euro;15 million over three years is required, but that will only be the start of it.  I understand that due diligence is still under way.  This investment is necessary so that ratepayers and the council do not take a financial hit.  We cannot compromise critical services that the local authority provides, for example, housing.  If the council is expected to take over the facilities &ndash; it is happy to do so &ndash; then the Government needs to step up to the plate and provide the necessary financial resources to make this happen, allow it to be successful in the short term and make it sustainable into the future.</p><p>Some 150 people are working in the facilities.  They deserve clarity, and only the Government can provide that clarity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Government will be required to write the cheque to make it viable in the short term and sustainable into the future.  I await the response of the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for his comprehensive introduction to the topic, which I am taking on behalf of the Minister for Transport.  As advised by the Minister in February, the Government recognises that Shannon Heritage and its heritage sites are of significant importance not just to the mid-west region but also to Ireland's tourism offering and our historic, built heritage.  Since the previous update, King John's Castle successfully transferred to Limerick City and County Council on 4 April 2022.  I would like to acknowledge the extensive effort and preparation that Shannon Group and the council engaged in to bring this about.</p> <p>I am also happy to provide a further update to the House today on the transfer of the Clare heritage site to which the Senator referred.  Shannon Group continues to engage with Clare County Council regarding the transfer of the Shannon Heritage business and key sites.  Department of Transport officials also met with Clare County Council officials last week and were provided with an update on the due diligence process under way in the council and the work that remains to be done.  Shannon Group considers that the transfer of Shannon Heritage business and the Clare sites is the best way to secure the longer-term viability of the business and the interests of Shannon Heritage employees.  It will also maintain the intrinsic heritage value of the sites in the mid-west for current and future generations.  The transfer also fits in well with the County Clare Tourism Strategy 2030 and the considerable experience that Clare County Council has in operating its existing visitor attractions.  Once the necessary due diligence work is complete for the sites, and final business transfer agreements signed, Shannon Group will seek the formal consent of the Minister for Transport and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform to execute the transfer of the business and the relevant heritage sites.  This will also be done with the agreement of the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage.</p> <p>The Department of Transport has been engaging bilaterally with other Departments on the matter of the transfer.  The Department recently established an interdepartmental working group, which I believe is the most appropriate way to now progress the matter effectively, consider the funding requirements and bring this matter to a successful conclusion.  Representatives from the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Public Expenditure and Reform and Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sports and Media, and the OPW have been invited to participate in this group.  The OPW has agreed to re-engage on its maintenance responsibilities in the conservation and maintenance role of Bunratty Castle and King John&rsquo;s Castle.  In preparation for undertaking this role, the OPW has been carrying out necessary assessments of both buildings to inform the programme of works needed and the associated costs.  The Department of Transport is continuing to engage with the OPW in this regard.  Before any transfer is executed, it remains the responsibility of Shannon Group to operate and manage the Shannon Heritage business in line with its commercial mandate and fiduciary best practice and with awareness of the group&rsquo;s accountability for the proper management of the company.  While Shannon Group was due to close Bunratty Castle and King John&rsquo;s Castle in September 2021 for the winter season, the continuation of Government supports meant that the sites could remain open, although with reduced opening hours.  I understand that the castles are fully reopened for the summer season, which is welcome.</p> <p>Despite the ongoing impact of Covid-19, I am happy to inform the Senator that there were some positive developments last year.  Almost 500,000 people visited the Shannon Heritage sites in 2021 representing a 64.2% increase on the 2020 visitor numbers.  The recent resumption of transatlantic flights at Shannon Airport also presents an opportunity to welcome back international tourists to the sites over the coming months, which is most welcome.  I am confident that this represents a turning point, and that we will see a further increase in international visitors this year, which will be welcomed as a positive development, no doubt by the Senator as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking the time to take this matter on behalf of the Minister for Transport.  I accept people's bona fides in this.  I accept the fact that there is an interdepartmental working group, which is absolutely the correct way to go about this, but there is a bottom line, which is that the taking over of the Shannon Heritage sites in County Clare cannot result in a negative financial impact on Clare County Council.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The council executive will not tolerate it and, certainly, the members of Clare County Council will not tolerate it.  I can absolutely guarantee that the ratepayers of Clare will not tolerate it.  That is the bottom line.  Beyond that, engagement will have to happen in terms of a significant capital investment in the future, which will include significant borrowing because of the audiovisual and all that is on offer in other facilities.  We need to ensure that there is capital investment to protect the buildings in the first instance, but then improve the offering that is available to tourists.  Tourists now are much more discerning and absolutely will be much more demanding in the visitor experience they would want.   I welcome the Minister of State&rsquo;s reply.  I know it is ongoing, but for the sake of everybody, particularly the staff who are working, clarity is needed.  Perhaps in the Minister of State's supplementary reply he might be able to tell me if there is a timeframe and time limit set for this working group to come back with its recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#F00200"><p>To reiterate, there is a commitment at Government level to protect the future of the Shannon Heritage sites.  That is why there has been the establishment of the interdepartmental working group that can work through the issues that the Senator has so articulately raised.  Unfortunately, I do not have a timeframe because it is not my area of responsibility.  However, I will give the Senator a commitment that I will bring back the points that he has raised on the floor of the Seanad to the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, and ensure that he is aware of those valid points.  I will ask the Minister to reply to the Senator directly in terms of the timeframe.  I can understand that this time of uncertainty creates anxiousness and concerns in the community.  We need to bring that uncertainty to a conclusion very quickly.  I will look for the completion date to reported back to the Senator as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#F00300"><p>We are now waiting for the arrival of the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke.  I propose that we suspend proceedings until the conclusion of the division in the D&aacute;il.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.25" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 2.58 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 3.06 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 2.58 p.m. and resumed at 3.06 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.26" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#H00100">Legal Services Regulation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#H00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth, my colleague, neighbour and friend from D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council, who is here to deal with this matter.  I am grateful to him for coming in because this is an important issue, namely the unwinding of cuts to criminal legal aid fees.  It is not a secret that I am a criminal barrister and I still work in that sphere and receive criminal legal aid payments but I am not issuing this request out of self-interest.  There is a sustained campaign by criminal barristers to deal with this issue because it is a serious issue for those practising criminal law.</p> <p>There is a misconception out there that barristers all do very well and that they are all wealthy.  It is a popular thing to say and certain media outlets love to refer to the Four Goldmines but that does not apply to criminal barristers.  Crime does not pay in that sphere and we do not work in the Four Goldmines; we work in the Criminal Courts of Justice on Parkgate St., and in district and circuit courts throughout Ireland.  This affects every county and community because the reality is that the amounts available to be paid under the criminal legal aid scheme were slashed at the time of the financial crisis in this country by between 30% and 50%, depending on the nature of the payment.  It was a significant reduction in the pay available to people practising in the area of crime.  We should bear in mind that they were already the worst-paid lawyers in the system, including solicitors, and then their pay was cut by that amount.  Everybody took that pain at the time that it was necessary during the financial crisis and they dealt with it.  Civil servants, healthcare workers and people providing professional services also took that cut; it was across the board.  Yet here we are ten, 11 and 12 years later and the only people for whom pay has not been reinstated is those practising in criminal law, including solicitors and barristers.  Their fees remain at the level they were cut to after the financial emergency.</p> <p>It does not make sense because the State gets incredibly good value from the practitioners in this area.  They are all self-employed and none of them works for the State.  The State, therefore, does not have to pay them sick leave, maternity benefit, pension rights, PRSI and all the other benefits that come with having employees.  The State does not have to pay that; they pay it themselves and they pay for their offices.  When we are compared with other jurisdictions around the world, we are incredibly good value for the taxpayer.  A number of reports have compared us with other common law jurisdictions in Europe and the most recent one in 2018 shows that the cost of legal aid per head of population was &euro;18.40.  Each person in Ireland contributed &euro;18.40 to the cost of having a legal aid system that provides for those who cannot provide for themselves in legal defence.  When compared with the figures in England and Wales, for example, our neighbouring jurisdiction, it is &euro;38.14, more than double what it is in this jurisdiction, while in Northern Ireland, it is &euro;73.50.  The State gets excellent value and yet it has turned its back on those defending people within our criminal justice system and it refuses, inexplicably, to reinstate that fee.</p> <p>There is a consequence coming down the road, and people are abandoning criminal law.  Although it may not be the case yet that there are no lawyers to do the work of criminal defence, that will happen.  It happened to a great extent in the 1980s and it will happen again if the State does not recognise that the only fair thing to do is not to give a big payment out to these people but to reinstate the rates of pay available to them for work in the criminal courts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#J00100"><p>I thank Senator Ward for raising this matter.</p> <p>I will provide some background on this issue.  The Criminal Justice (Legal Aid) Act 1962 gives expression to the constitutional right that free legal aid must be granted, in certain circumstances, for the defence of persons of insufficient means in criminal proceedings.  The Judiciary is responsible for the granting of legal aid.  Legal services under the criminal legal aid scheme are provided by private solicitors and barristers who have notified their availability to undertake legal aid work.  Thus, they are not public servants but private contractors and are remunerated accordingly.  The Department of Justice is responsible for the payment of fees and expenses to these legal practitioners.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, counsel fees under the criminal legal aid scheme were subject to two 8% reductions, which were imposed in March 2009 and April 2010, respectively.  These reductions formed part of a broader Government agenda to reduce escalating legal costs and were underpinned by Government decisions.  A further reduction was imposed in 2011 primarily to control spending under the criminal legal aid scheme and formed part of a broader Government need to reduce costs across the public service.  This was also underpinned by a Government decision.</p> <p>The Government fully acknowledges and appreciates the very important work undertaken by barristers who prosecute criminal work on behalf of the State.  My Department has engaged constructively with key stakeholders, including the Bar Council of Ireland, the Office of the Director of Public Prosecutions and the Department of Justice on this matter.  In particular, my Department has sought evidence to support any claims that the reductions imposed are linked to significant recruitment and retention issues thereby potentially adversely affecting the administration of justice.</p> <p>Based on data put forward by the Bar Council of Ireland to date, there does not appear to be any compelling evidence that the reduction in fees since 2009 has led to significant recruitment or retention issues or to a shortage of counsel prepared to do criminal work to the extent that the operation of the criminal justice system is significantly hampered.  My Department of course remains available to review any further information that may be provided.  Furthermore, my Department has requested the advice of the Office of the Attorney General seeking clarification as to whether Government has a statutory liability to restore these professional fees.  Those advices are awaited.</p> <p>My Department will continue to keep the matter of these professional fees under review, pending the legal advice that has been sought from the Office of the Attorney General and will continue to engage with key stakeholders, as appropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#J00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I do not deny that the fees were cut at a time when there was a need to make cuts.  It is not the case that criminal and legal aid fees were responsible for escalating legal costs, given that they are controlled by the Government so that is an aspect that is not relevant.  Even if it were the case that the Government cannot identify a looming crisis, that is not a good enough reason not to restore these fees.  All of the fees paid to professionals whether an architect, psychologist or whatever have been restored but for some reason, the Government refuses to restore the fees paid to criminal legal aid practitioners.</p> <p>To put this matter in context, if a barrister appears in a District Court for a case then he or she is paid a rate of &euro;25.20 for the privilege plus VAT for however long he or she works that day.  It is also a reality that he or she will also have to wait for the solicitor to receive his or her payment before the split fee is passed to the barrister.  There is a thing that the Government can do without increasing fees at all and that is to provide a direct payment for barristers out of the District Court, for example, in the same way that they get in the Circuit Court, the Central Criminal Court and other courts.  That could be done to ease the burden, particularly on junior barristers.  Just because we have not yet seen this crisis coming does not mean that it will not come.  It would be a grave mistake for the Government to wait until practitioners have deserted criminal law in their droves to decide to fix the problem.  As we know that the crisis is coming, I implore the Government to fix it now please. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#J00300"><p>There have been negotiations with other professions where fees have been adjusted but that has involved changes to the contract and productivity improvements, which involved long negotiations with the representative bodies.  My Department is available for continuing discussions with the Bar Council of Ireland, if that does go ahead.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I take the Senator's point about his worry there would be a reduction in the quality of service, the numbers available or the ability to recruit or retain people.  My Department so far does not have evidence to support that but is open to receiving same, should it be produced.  I agree it is something that must be watched carefully.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#K00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, to the House.  He is always worth waiting for.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.33" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#K00300">Fire Safety</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#K00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this matter today.  On 26 April, apartment owners in a particular complex in Dublin South-Central were informed by the management company that they were each going to be levied with a fee of &euro;32,000 for construction defects in the complex to cover the work needed to bring it up to the correct fire safety standards.  Of that sum, &euro;7,000 must be paid by the first week of June.  Regardless of their circumstances, they have been levied with this amount.  The cause of this deficit is being borne by the apartment owners.  It is a result of the self-regulation system that was at the core of construction in the Celtic tiger years.  Homeowners are not to blame yet they are the ones being obliged to find these eye-watering sums to rectify something that was most certainly was not of their doing.  I received several emails from residents of this particular complex.  I will read an extract from one of them in which the writer states:</p> <blockquote> 	I am a single, working mother, paying a mortgage and trying to keep my head above water as the cost of living soars.  All my life I have tried to do the right thing, I work fulltime &hellip; and have never before looked to my  politicians for help.  To be landed with a bill of 32,000Euro , which I consider a life -altering amount, is quite simply beyond my capabilities and I am so distraught and stressed over it that I really don't know what to do or who to turn to.  How is any normal person supposed to face this? </blockquote> <p>Institutional landlords and private landlords get to write this cost off against tax and yet normal owner-occupiers have to pony up such huge amounts without any support, as yet.  However, it is unconscionable and an issue that must be addressed urgently.  These homeowners need a resolution.  I appreciate there is a working group and I can almost predict the speech the Minister of State will give in response.  I am conscious the working group is ongoing.  It is due to report by June, one would hope.  Presumably its report will make a redress recommendation that will then go to Cabinet and be hammered out in the budget negotiations.  That is all of our hope in this situation.  However, it is too long for the homeowners I have mentioned.  If a redress scheme is envisaged, then why can we not look at an interim one?  We all agree some sort of scheme is going to happen here.  In light of mica and pyrite there is going to have to be an apartment owners redress scheme.  If we know that, why can we not establish some sort of State loan or give letters of comfort, on the back of which those homeowners can be guaranteed to go to credit unions?  Why can we not set up some sort of system like that, such that loans will be repaid out of tax allowances or some other way for the homeowners to be reimbursed?</p><p>I wish this complex was the only one in Dublin South-Central but unfortunately it is not.  Pretty much every email I get in asks me not to mention the name because they are now terrified their properties cannot be sold.  They are in a dire situation.  I appreciate also that next week, the Minister is going to bring a memo to Cabinet on the defective blocks redress scheme.  In light of that we know that where homeowners have been caught out through what was a deficit in construction oversight, the State is going to put in redress.  On the back of that, I ask that we put in some sort of a system that supports these homeowners in that interim period.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#L00100"><p>I apologise for being delayed.  We were voting in the D&aacute;il.  I thank the Senator.  This is a very important issue.  It is a very distressing position for those she represents to be in, as she has quite rightly articulated.  I have met a number of homeowners in my own constituency who are unfortunately faced with similar problems because of defects in properties delivered to them, defects that were no fault of their own.  It is very frustrating.  There are a number of such cases right around the country.</p> <p>In recognition of the difficulties faced by residents who are encountering defects in housing, the programme for Government sets out a number of commitments in respect of the important policy area of addressing building defects.  Housing for All, the Government's national plan on housing to 2030, reiterates this commitment.  In this context, my colleague, the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, established a working group to examine defects in housing under the chairmanship of Mr. Seamus Neely, the former chief executive of Donegal County Council.  The plenary working group has been meeting monthly since March 2021, with the exception of August.  In addition, regular sub-group meetings have been taking place to advance elements of the work.  The group's terms of reference are focused on purpose-built apartment buildings, including duplexes, constructed in Ireland between 1991 and 2013.</p> <p>In summary, the terms of reference are: to examine defects in housing having regard to the recommendations under heading 4, "Addressing the legacy of bad building and poor regulation", in chapter 4 of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government's report entitled "Safe as Houses? A Report on Building Standards, Building Controls and Consumer Protection"; to establish the nature of significant and widespread fire safety, structural safety and water ingress defects in purpose-built apartment buildings, including duplexes, constructed between 1991 and 2013; to establish the scale of the issue, including work to estimate the number of dwellings affected by the defects identified, including those already remediated; to consider a methodology for the categorisation of defects and the prioritisation of remedial action; to suggest mechanisms for resolving defects; to evaluate the potential cost of technical remediation options; and to pursue options on possible financial solutions to effect a resolution in line with the programme for Government commitment to identify options for those impacted by defects to access low-cost, long-term finance.  That last point was one of the key components of the argument the Senator put forward for her area.</p> <p>As part of its deliberations, the working group has consulted with a wide range of relevant stakeholders.  The insights gained through engagement with stakeholders, as well as the outcome of an online consultation undertaken earlier this year, will inform the ongoing deliberations of the working group and support the group in delivering on its extensive terms of reference and finalising its report to the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien.  I have sought an update from the Minister, who has said that he is satisfied that the group is working effectively and efficiently on this very complex matter.  He awaits the group's report, to be delivered later this year when it has concluded its deliberations.  I wish assure the Senator that work is ongoing in that regard.</p> <p>I understand the pressures these people are facing.  The same pressures are present in my own constituency.  Solutions are needed quite quickly because of the great liability being placed on ordinary families through no fault of their own.  I will raise the issue with the Minister again.  If the Senator would like to detail the specific issue in her area, I can raise that with him as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#L00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  This is an issue in everybody's constituency.  The worrying aspect is not just that homeowners are barred from the possibility of sale or the costs involved, but also that there are insurance issues.  These homeowners cannot get insurance on their properties.</p> <p>The management companies of some of these complexes are now insolvent because they have spent their sinking funds.  Some homeowners are withholding funds from these management companies.  They are not paying because they are not going to get services and are nervous about their own financial well-being.  As a consequence, common areas are not being refurbished and lighting is not being maintained.</p> <p>All of the things that flow from this issue are really urgent.  Using words like "later this year" in respect of the timeline makes me very anxious and suggests there is not the level of urgency that is needed in this regard.  Unfortunately, these homeowners are not as vocal as the mica and pyrite people.  They are not outside at the gates because they are terrified and broke.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The fact they do not mobilise should not take from anything.  We must insist they are at the top of the political agenda, that they are being heard and their issue is being addressed urgently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#M00200"><p>I take the Senator's point very seriously.  In the first instance, we must capture exactly the extent of this issue right across the country and also in terms of the budget that will underpin what will be a significant remediation scheme.  I would point to the many legacy issues with which we are still grappling post the previous decade and more, including that we are trying to establish the professional register for building contractors, which will assure people into the future of a standard of quality assurance in the work they contract builders to do.  Much of that good work is ongoing.  It will improve matters.</p> <p>I appreciate the point the Senator has made.  I have met a delegation from my constituency on many occasions who have sought to further advance this issue which, in their position, relates to fire safety, which is also a very serious matter.  People potentially could be at risk from the outbreak of a fire.  I will do my best to pressure the Department as much as I can in this regard.  I understand it is a genuine issue.  It is a major debt to force upon ordinary constituents which can be very difficult to discharge.  As a State, we need to step up to wrongdoing which is not due to any fault of the apartment owners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#M00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State and the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.40" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 3.26 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 3.30 p.m.  

Sitting suspended at 3.26 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.41" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. <i>a</i>1, report of the Committee of Selection, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business without debate; No. 1, Finance (Covid-19 and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2022 - Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to conclude at 6.15 p.m., with the opening contributions of the Minister not to exceed eight minutes, all Senators not to exceed six minutes and the Minister to be given not less than seven minutes to reply to the debate; No. 2, Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022 - Second Stage, to be taken at 6.30 p.m., and to conclude at 9 p.m., with the opening contribution of the Minister not to exceed 15 minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given not less than ten minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#N00300"><p>I agree with the Order of Business.  The first issue I wish to raise, and which I have raised previously, is the ongoing cost of childcare, the difficulty in accessing places and reliable childcare services.  I request that at the earliest opportunity the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman, come before the House to engage with Senators on the matter.  Everyone is aware that new core funding has been announced.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lisa Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2449"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2449&amp;amp;pid=LisaChambers&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is initially to stabilise the sector and ensure we pay people properly and that early years educators get a fair and reasonable wage for the very high level of qualifications and skills they have.  We also want to ensure we can reduce costs for parents, and in order to do both we must invest significantly in childcare in this country.  We must get away from the culture we have had for many years that this is just about minding children; it is not.  It is about providing education in those formative years, between birth and five years, before the children go to primary school.  It is really important we invest in our children so we can offset the damaging effects that can be seen in early years and prevent problems down the line.  In the end this will save the country so much more.</p><p>There are challenges with the core funding scheme as announced but they can be worked through.  The feedback I have received to date has been quite positive in that providers are really happy to see there is a commitment to core funding.  It requires tweaking, however, and I would appreciate a chance to discuss it with the Minister.  In particular, we are going to try to use the core funding as a mechanism through which we will curtail increases in costs of fees for parents.  I am interested in hearing how that will work in practice, with the State trying to control the private sector, and how the Minister believes that will work in the long term.  It is important to get this right.  The kind of childcare provision I see as being the gold standard in the country would be a public system provided by the State.  It would probably take a decade to deliver that but if we do not start now we will never deliver it.</p><p>A second issue I raise is the funding of large marine projects across our coastal areas.  It is easy enough to secure funding, for example, for a feasibility study for a marina project but it is almost impossible to get the millions of euro required to put those projects in place.  Very often it falls back on the local authority because there is no core funding stream within the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine to fund bigger projects.  It is a deficit in the Department.  In the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, for example, there is core funding for urban regeneration for large-scale projects in towns across the country.  Something similar is required in the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine to fund large marine projects.  We have a policy now in the country of trying to invest and grow our marine sector but we have not backed that up with funding to action the policy.  We could do with a debate on marine projects with the Minister with responsibility for the marine.</p><p>I am almost out of time but we must have a discussion in the Chamber on the review that has been announced by Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, of all road projects planned for the next number of years in light of inflation, particularly the increased cost of building materials and labour.  I understand TII is reviewing projects to see what it can deliver within its budget.  That is a cause for concern for the entire country and we would like to hear what projects might be dropped from the list because of rising costs.  I would welcome a debate with the appropriate Minister on that particular review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#O00200"><p>Before calling the next speaker I welcome to the Chamber Councillor Tony Fitzgerald, who served as the Lord Mayor of Cork for a number of years.  He is welcome to Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#O00300"><p>The schools building programme in this country has been very successful over the past number of years but many more schools are needed.  I have a concern that I know is shared with colleagues, which is that come 4 p.m., many of our fantastic school buildings cease being in use.  The Department of Education really must formulate a strategy to use these well-funded and beautiful public buildings for social, community, cultural, arts and music events and so on after hours, along with adult education.  Some schools do this all the time and some do it very successfully but some literally close their doors at 4 p.m. and that is it.  They are shut over the evenings and the weekend.</p> <p>We need a national strategy to use the space that is available in schools after school hours and at weekends to benefit the community and youth groups and the citizens of this country.  We should bear in mind that hundreds of millions of euro are spent every year building beautiful school buildings and it is a shame to see them closed and not used for months in the year from 4 p.m. onwards.</p> <p>I commend and congratulate school management and principals who let their schools be used after hours.  For those who do not, there is a duty, in my view, to change that approach.  I call on those boards of management to do this on a voluntary basis but, really and truly, we need a strategy on this at a departmental level.  Perhaps the Minister could make a statement in that regard at some stage because it is a shame to see those facilities going to waste in the evenings and at weekends.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have been calling for the 9% VAT rate for a long time.  It should be permanent.  The hospitality industry has been through a bruising three years and that is continuing with the war in Europe and the difficulties in finding staff.  I welcome that it has been extended to the end of 2022.  It will provide relief to the many thousands of people who are running small hospitality businesses throughout the country.  These people want to look to the future with more certainty.  We need a discussion now on applying the 9% VAT rate permanently for our hospitality, leisure and tourism industries.</p><p>The biggest problem that tourism and hospitality industry has is with shortage of staff.  We need an urgent debate in the House on expediting work permits, which take too long.  The Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment should come to the House to discuss how we can take a common-sense logical approach to speeding up the granting of work permits.  Many restaurants and hotels are on their knees because they cannot get staff.  I hope the Leader will be able to facilitate a debate on that as a matter of urgency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#P00200"><p>It has been widely reported that the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, Deputy O'Gorman, will come to the House at 6.30 p.m. and that prior to his discussion of the Birth Information and Tracing Bill, he will apologise on behalf of the Government to those affected by illegal birth registrations.  While I welcome this apology and what I am about to say is not a criticism of the Minister, I have some concerns about the timing and nature of the apology.</p> <p>To put it in its context, the special rapporteur on child protection, Professor Conor O'Mahony, has stated that up to 20,000 Irish children may have been affected in this way and that the Government knew about it, collaborated with it through various Departments and officials, and effectively allowed the transport of thousands of Irish children out of the State.  It was a shameful episode in Irish history.</p> <p>I am minded of this because in recent days, I have been writing about the situation in Ukraine, particularly the war in Donbas.  One of the concerns raised by the international humanitarian agencies is the movement of Ukrainian children out of Donbas to Russian territory and then being stripped of their documents and further dispersed through the Russian Federation.  That is exactly what I am talking about in respect of those affected by illegal birth registrations in this country.</p> <p>Throughout Europe, there has been a history of transporting children very often for ideological reasons during the Second World War, during the 1950s and during the period of the Soviet Union.  What is particularly shameful and pernicious about Ireland is that much of the motivation for the transport of these children was monetary gain on the part of the State and those religious orders that were relied upon to provide services that the State was either unwilling or unable to provide in their absence.</p> <p>For fear that this apology might be misinterpreted, for fear that its timing and context does not add insult to injury, however unintended, I call on the Taoiseach to apologise in the D&aacute;il on behalf of all the Irish people for the egregious harm visited upon all these Irish citizens, many of whom are elderly people trying to reconstruct their identities while experiencing ill health.  It is the very least we owe them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Q00100"><p>As a representative from the midlands, it has been a very busy few weeks in my office.  Many people have been in touch to say they must burn turf to warm their homes.  People with turbary rights have been in touch concerned that they were at risk of criminalisation.  This narrative fuelled by some who should know better.  My office has replied to the majority, outlining my position, and where possible, we have been able to alleviate concerns.</p><p>A few weeks ago I stood in this Chamber and I committed to advocating for a balanced approach on the draft clean air strategy.  I did this knowing that turf burning pollutes the air we breathe, causing ill health and death.  I did it also with a clear awareness of the drastic environmental cost of each passing turf harvest.  However, I did it because I felt that, on balance, it was a socially just thing to do and I will continue to advocate for additional supports as homes transition away from a reliance on turf.  I was, therefore,  quite taken aback to read an article last week in <i>The Guardian</i>in which the journalist Rory Carroll reported that for some who knowingly extract turf from bogs in special areas of conservation, it is not about the cost of alternatives to turf but he wrote that for some it was about identity and, to paraphrase him, &ldquo;showing the wildlife crowd that flexing their muscles won't have any impact here&rdquo;.</p><p>I stand proudly with the wildlife crowd and I am asking them today to keep flexing those muscles and fighting for the preservation of nature and to keep calling out unacceptable behaviour where people are proudly destroying habitats.  I also plead with those who think calling for improvements in air quality or habitat preservation is some form of an attack on them to think deeply about alternatives and to think about the damage that is being done.  We are depleting one of our largest carbon stores and the habitats of some of Ireland's most important species.  These bogs have taken thousands of years to form yet just 1% of Ireland's active raised bogs now remain after years of land reclamation and peat harvesting.It is not true to say that because you love the bog, you are doing no harm.  Peat is a fossil fuel and a precious natural resource.  Yes, turf burning will continue for many people but it is reducing every year as more people move with the times and find alternative ways to heat their homes.  However, a person's identity should never be so entangled with a tradition that they can justify harming our landscape in the name of that tradition.</p><p>Our days on the bog are numbered.  I think everyone accepts that because we will look back with mixed views; some of us with reminiscence, some with resentment and some with relief.  However, what the debate must focus on is clean air and the health of people in the midlands.  I will continue to fight for that.  I hope that when future generations visit bogs of the midlands like Clara and Abbeyleix, they will be thankful for the preservation of these wonderful natural resources that many of us stood up to protect when we had the chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Q00200"><p>Ar dt&uacute;s b&aacute;ire, ba mhaith liom labhairt faoin toghch&aacute;n &oacute; Thuaidh.  I am sure the Leader will agree that the people of the North have spoken at the election last week to the Assembly, and they have spoken clearly.  They have, in the first instance, elected a majority of MLAs who support the protocol and want to see it embedded, resolved and continuing to work for everyone.  They also elected a majority of MLAs and parties who want to get back to work and who want to see the institutions, or the Good Friday Agreement in the form of the Assembly and the Executive, back around the table and delivering for people.  We are all very conscious of the difficulties facing people across Ireland not least with the cost-of-living crisis.</p> <p>In my own capacity, I want to congratulate Michelle O&rsquo;Neill, my party colleague and our First Minister elect in the North.  Her election represents a very important historic, symbolic and seismic change in the politics of the North.  When someone like Michelle, a very proud Irish republican and nationalist can take that position in a system and a state that was designed to ensure that such a thing would never happen, the historic significance and the political significance of that is not lost on me or on many people in the North and beyond.</p> <p>I want to take the opportunity today to call on the DUP to stop holding people to ransom and stop punishing the public by not returning to the Executive.  More than &pound;300 million is waiting and ready to go to be directed into the pockets of workers and families.  We can invest more than &pound;1 billion in the health service over the next three years and we can continue the work of building 100,000 social and affordable homes over the next 15 years.  Those are the issues that people want to see addressed.  I know the Leader will agree with me on that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Those are the issues that fall within the remit of the Assembly and the Executive.  The protocol is an issue.  There is no doubt there are issues that need to be and can be worked out, but they will not be worked out in the Assembly or the Executive.  It is an issue for the British Government and the EU institutions.  In the meantime, I encourage colleagues from every party to recommit to the institutions, get back into them and get to work.  In congratulating Michelle O'Neill - I know the Leader would not expect me to be partisan - I also congratulate all those who put their names forward, which we know is not easy, and were returned and commiserate with those who did not make it across the line on this occasion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#R00200"><p>I have a couple of issues I am going to try to fly through.  First, I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Health to appear before the Seanad to discuss workforce planning within the health service.  I know it sounds a little bit niche but I believe it is an issue that goes to the heart of many of the issues facing healthcare staff, most especially nurses.</p> <p>As the Leader may have seen, the Irish Nurses and Midwives Organisation, INMO, at its recent conference launched a report on the experience of physical assaults against nurses in Irish hospitals.  The statistics are really shocking.  On average, seven nurses and midwives are assaulted in work every single day in Ireland.  How we plan for future staffing levels in the HSE is essential to staff well-being in those settings.  As a member of the Joint Committee on Health and the Labour Party's health spokesperson in the Seanad, I think it would be valuable to have a dedicated discussion in the Chamber with the Minister on this issue.</p> <p>Second, if the Leader feels it is appropriate, I ask that she write on behalf of the Seanad to the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence and ask that time be given over at committee to discussing how Ireland could provide true and meaningful international solidarity to women around the world in the face of gender-based discrimination.  I am thinking particularly of the women in Afghanistan, who have suffered terribly under the Taliban regime which has most recently directed that all women must now wear a full burka when outdoors, regardless of their personal wishes.  I know the Seanad has long been a place where matters of international affairs have been given priority.  I believe it was a group of Senators led by Senator Norris who set up the first foreign affairs committees.  I feel, therefore, it would be appropriate for such a request to come from this House.</p> <p>Finally, on a more positive note, I want to take a moment to commend the work of the international Dublin Gay Theatre Festival.  Following a really considerable cut in its funding this year, there was a fear that the festival would not go ahead after 19 years in existence.  Thanks to the hard work of the committee, however, the show did indeed go on with many plays happening all this week and last week.  I have been to many already myself and there are plenty left in the days ahead.  I really encourage any Members of the House who may find themselves floating around Dublin over the next few days to head along.  I have programmes available in my office if anyone needs them.  I want to take a moment to congratulate the committee, actors, writers, producers, set builders, the venue and volunteers for running an incredible festival despite all the hiccups over the past two years and the shortage of funding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#R00300"><p>Under the programme for Government, the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage established a working group to examine defects in housing.  I want to concentrate today particularly on apartment stock and multi-unit development stock.  It is important that this working group does not pit homeowners against each other.  There should be no discrimination between owners of homes and owners of apartments.  We know many apartments in Dublin city and Cork city are affected by fire safety defects and other structural defects.  Many of them are going to be landed with huge lump sums in their management fees to remedy these defects.  Because regulation at the time was so low, it is important that the Government steps in to ensure they get a fair chance and that they have some sort of consistency and reliability in terms of the redress scheme.  It is important that schemes such as the pyrite and mica schemes are not differentiated from schemes that will affect apartment owners.  It is important that they get 100% redress.</p> <p>We also need to look at the retrospective aspect of these schemes.  As we know, apartment owners and multi-unit developments are run by management companies, which have an onus to take out insurance each year.  If steps are not taken to remedy fire safety defects, they will not be covered.  There is a sort of differentiation between homeowners and apartment blocks.</p> <p>I want to make sure this is a priority for this Government.  I ask through the Leader when the Minister expects to publish the final report.  Will there be estimates included in next year's budget?  It is important that homeowners get 100% redress.  Many owner-occupiers cannot get any tax deductions if they have to put up lump sums for remedial repairs whereas a landlord can set this off against his or her tax.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to look at the way the scheme works, not only for homeowners who have an income but also for the many apartment owners who do not and who will not have the means to remortgage in order to pay these huge lump sums.  A fair scheme must be put in place for apartment owners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S00200"><p>I welcome the decision of the Minister for Finance and the Government to extend the 9% VAT rate to February 2023.  This is a very important decision that is designed to support the sector most hit by Covid-19 in order that it can continue to operate in the shoulder season.</p> <p>Senator Conway asked for a debate with the Minister for Education and for a review of the use of schools and related buildings outside of school times.  I join with him in that request.  Considerable Exchequer funding is spent, has been spent and will be spent on school buildings to create school communities.  They do not operate in a silo; they are immersed in communities.  I commend Deputy David Stanton on his work seeking the use of school buildings outside school time, in order that they can be availed of for community use by sporting, cultural and other organisations.  It makes sense.  The Minister for Education has established a review group to look at how we can use school buildings.  I am asking her and the Government to expedite and fast-track this review so that in the future, and, hopefully, in the autumn, school buildings, grounds and facilities, which are funded in the main by the taxpayer, can be used by myriad groups, organisations and people around the country.</p> <p>I will conclude by again referring to the good news of the 9% VAT rate extension.  It will be pivotal to the tourism and hospitality sector in places like Cork, Kerry and other locations outside Dublin.  However, I would ask those in the hospitality sector not to engage in rip-off Ireland tactics with the prices for hotel rooms in the summer season.  It is incumbent on them to work with the Government to make sure hotel rooms are affordable and accessible to all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S00300"><p>I am calling for a debate on the content of the interim report from the UK Government on the Cass review and the implications it has for Irish children being sent to UK-based clinics.  The Cass review is the UK's independent review of the gender identity services for children and young people that have been offered there since 2011.  The HSE has sent 234 Irish children to the UK for treatment for gender dysphoria in response to the recent unexplained exponential rise in young people experiencing severe gender distress.  The clinic in question, run by the Tavistock and Portman NHS Foundation Trust, has been the subject of numerous serious allegations regarding the quality of care being given to the children and young adults in its care.  The interim Cass report details that the standards of clinical care, assessment and treatment there do not match those enjoyed by children accessing other health services elsewhere, and that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S00400"><p>We are all about open debate here but the Senator must be careful of the Standing Orders relating to the Kerins case that we have adopted in the context of naming people who are not in the Chamber to defend themselves.  I would just make that point.  The Senator is aware of the Standing Order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S00500"><p>Have I mentioned somebody who is not here?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S00600"><p>No.  If the Senator is making allegations, however, she has to be very careful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S00700"><p>I have not made any allegations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S00800"><p>The Senator is saying this clinic been subject to numerous reports about its level of care and that therefore-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S00900"><p>This is documented.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S01000"><p>I am just saying-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S01100"><p>I understand the Cathaoirleach's concern.  I would not be coming in here to voice any untruths that have not been stated in a report elsewhere.  I assure him of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S01200"><p>I am just urging caution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#S01300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p> <p>Second, there has not been routine or consistent data collection, which has made it impossible to accurately track the outcomes of clinical intervention in solving gender dysphoria.  Third, due to the explosion in demand, the clinic has not been subjected to best practice quality controls, which are usually required before a new treatment is approved.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> This interim report has prompted a call for an urgent inquiry into the service from the British Secretary of State for Health and Social Care, Mr. Sajid Javid, amid fears that the system is failing children and that vulnerable children are wrongly being given gender hormone treatment.  Mr. Javid was particularly alarmed by the pressures on staff to adopt an unquestioning affirmative approach to physically transitioning children over any form of psychological care or assistance.  A concern among UK clinicians is that this recourse to the clinical approach is becoming a form of gay conversion therapy as a result of frequent cases of people who started identifying as trans after months of experiencing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#T00200"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#T00300"><p>Do I not get extra time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#T00400"><p>I gave the Senator extra time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#T00500"><p>May I finish briefly?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#T00600"><p>Please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#T00700"><p>I was made aware of an incident in this country a few weeks ago where a teenage boy came out as gay in confidence to a group of his female friends.  They responded by saying that, if he liked boys, he must be a girl and, therefore, must be transgender.  He rejected this, saying that he had never felt like a female and that he was simply attracted to men.  As a result of his not accepting his friends foisting a gender identity on him, his female friends in whom he had confided broke contact and refused to speak to him.  This scenario was never envisaged by those who fought for equality - a gay man being pressured to change his gender in order to have his sexual orientation become straight.  A debate is in order so that we can find out the Minister's view on the Cass review and discuss the level of care that we in this Chamber want Irish children to receive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#T00800"><p>I agree with Senator Buttimer and others who have welcomed the extension of the 9% VAT rate, for which we have all been lobbying.  It is important for businesses that there be such incentives to help them recover from the pandemic.  The recovery is still ongoing, and if our tourism season takes off in the way we believe it will, the extension will help the sector to recover.  I wish to acknowledge the wonderful support given by the Government to the sector.  It is acknowledged widely throughout the sector.</p> <p>I commend the management and staff of Roscommon University Hospital who, in a recent patient survey, got the thumbs up for the way they run the hospital, its cleanliness and their friendliness.  We are always quick to talk about the negatives in the health sector, but we should also talk about the positives.  This is a positive story.  I went through the battles when we lost our emergency department in 2011.  It was a battle lasting a number of years, but that is the way these things go.  It is still a matter of contention for people, but the management, staff and services available at Roscommon University Hospital are exceptional.  I visited it with the Minister for Health prior to Christmas.  He was impressed with the layout.  Speaking as someone whose family member has used it, it is wonderful to see the patients and public saying that what is being done there is good and that most people have a positive experience there.</p> <p>If possible, I would like a debate on the roll-out of Local Link rural transport.  In those parts of the country that do not have public bus or train services, Local Link is the answer, but there are many shortcomings.  We need to debate this matter because, while Local Link is doing a good job in parts of our regions, many people who want to go to day centres, villages and towns are being left behind.  They are being told that they cannot be collected because they are too far away.  The purpose of Local Link is to accommodate all of these people.  Perhaps the Leader will consider arranging a debate with the relevant Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#T00900"><p>Senator Ward and I had the harrowing but insightful experience of visiting Kyiv in Ukraine for two days at the invitation of the Chairman of its parliament.  We were the first two parliamentarians to visit that parliament, and it has asked that people keep visiting because doing so shows the EU's support for Ukraine and opposes Russia's propaganda.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Garret Ahearn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=GarretAhearn&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We visited Bucha where 117 people from ten years of age upwards were murdered simply because they were Ukrainian citizens.  We visited Borodianka which was the first town that was essentially decimated by missile strikes.  The Russians chose buildings they knew would crumble and collapse quickly on top of people who were hiding.  People from the age of four were found crushed.  It was an awful experience.</p><p>We are part of a group of parliamentarians from across the world, which is called United for Ukraine.  The sole mission of the group is to try to get the Ukrainian Government&rsquo;s message across to as many governments around the world as quickly as possible.  Part of that is in terms of more weapons because the type of war has changed.  The Russian forces have retreated so the types of weapons Ukrainians need are different.  They need more sanctions against countries that are in some way facilitating Russia; they need sanctions against Russian television which is spreading propaganda by the people who support this war; and crucially, they need support for EU candidate status for Ukraine in June, a role in which Ireland can play a part.</p><p>As Members know President Zelenskyy and most MPs are in Ukraine all the time and have not fled.  Many of the citizens, in particular women and children, have fled.  A number of Ukrainians have travelled to countries around Europe and to Washington to continue delivering the message President Zelenskyy wants to get across, which is unity within Europe towards Ukraine and to fight and defeat Russia.</p><p>While I was there, I invited those MPs from the Ukrainian Parliament to visit Ireland to deliver that message.  I have written to the Cathaoirleach and the Leader to request them to open up the Seanad for those MPs when they come here.  They have accepted my invitation and they will be here in a number of weeks.  It would be a great opportunity for the Seanad to give them a platform to deliver that message in regard to more weapons, more sanctions, EU status and funding to pay for essential services they are going to have challenges with over the coming months.</p><p>There is a real opportunity for them to make their statements on the floor of this House.  We have done this with MEPs over the past number of months and that has been really successful.  In their roles as Cathaoirleach and as Leader, it would be a wonderful opportunity for them.  I do not think anyone in this House would disagree with having three or four MPs from Ukraine speak on behalf of their president and to show the unity for which they are so grateful.  At every meeting we had, whether it was with the vice prime minister, the chairman of the House, the minister for defence or the minister for internal affairs, all they kept saying to us was that Ireland had been supporting them from the very start and they asked if we could convince other European countries to step up as well because there is a narrative that they have, but they have not fully.  We can play a role to make sure that happens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#U00200"><p>I thank Senator Ahearn for his letter.  I think it is a proposal that we would support.  It would be unusual but we are living in unusual times.  I think it would be appropriate that if MPs are travelling from the Ukraine that they would engage with the Seanad and Senators to discuss the issues in person.  I thank the Senator for his visit to the Ukraine.  It is important that people visit Ukraine and Kyiv, see for themselves what is happening on the ground, and bring back the message as the Senator has done.  The opportunity for further engagement with Members of Parliament is important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#U00300"><p>I wish to raise a number of concerns regarding the Stardust inquest.  Tomorrow there is a preliminary hearing into the inquest.  It is being held at Store Street coroner's court.  The families have been invited to attend.  However, Store Street is the venue where the original inquest was held.  It holds many bad memories for the families.  The backyard of the court is where their loved ones' bodies were examined.  The coroner's court was where the families sat through the original inquest which Professor Phil Scraton referred to as an abject failure.  The concern of the families is that they are not going to be able to attend this preliminary hearing because it brings back so many hurtful memories of their last experience in that courthouse.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are asking why, when the Government has taken out a lease on the Pillar Room of the Rotunda, that is not the venue even for the preliminary hearings.  Even if that venue is being used for other inquests, they should obviously be given priority because the lease is specifically for the Stardust inquest.  Could we write to the Minister to express our concern on this?  It seems to be deeply insensitive of the Coroner&rsquo;s Court to pick this location without considering that this would be very hurtful for the families in attending it.  </p><p>The other issue around the Stardust is the Bill I tabled in February about the selection of the jury for the formal inquest that would have it done in the same manner as juries are selected for criminal proceedings.  The Minister, Deputy McEntee, gave assurances to the families that while my Bill might not do the job, she would bring forward her own proposals.  I am concerned that we have very few sitting days left before the summer break to get legislation through both Houses and to have it in place when the inquest starts.  We are not back here until the autumn and the lease on the Pillar Room runs out in February 2023.  We are running out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#V00200"><p>My issue is trite in light of the previous two contributions.  However, I want to raise an issue and ask for the support of both the Leader and the Cathaoirleach in the matter.  Heritage and Tidy Towns groups go to enormous effort to ensure the upkeep, care and love for their communities.  They are to be lauded.  I have a group in the Dublin South-Central constituency that works extraordinarily hard.  They have applied to Dublin City Council to build a commemorative garden, which was at the great suggestion of the Cathaoirleach.  They have made representations to Dublin City Council which has agreed to the replica of the 1916 Proclamation and the seven trees that represent the seven signatories.  However, it will not agree to the third element, which is the flagpole, on the basis of flagpole protocol.  I already got the assistance of the Cathaoirleach of the Seanad, who wrote an excellent protocol surrounding everything to do with flags, which is great for the Taoiseach&rsquo;s office.  He very kindly shared that with me.  I empowered the group with that and along with it wrote a letter to the council myself.  I still have not received anything back.</p> <p>Apart from standing on its own merits, these commemorative gardens are also a feature for Tidy Towns groups.  There are huge community and heritage efforts and a whole community mobilised and incentivised to act, and now Dublin City Council is saying that the protocol for flags cannot be adhered to.  However, it is well established by our own learned Cathaoirleach that street lighting is sufficient to ensure that the flag is illuminated 24 hours of the day.  That is being sufficiently done.</p> <p>I am asking for the Leader and Cathaoirleach to support me in writing to Dublin City Council in support of this group.  I would be obliged if they did that.  I can send them on the details.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#V00300"><p>I thank the Senator for her work in this regard.  She is correct.  I was working with the Taoiseach&rsquo;s Department in the lead-up to 2016 commemorations.  One of the issues that kept coming up was the issue of the flag flying overnight.  Protocol comes from precedent, as we know.  The precedent in relation to the flying of the national flag comes from Thomas Francis Meagher flying it for the first time on 7 March 1848, where it flew continuously, day and night.  We know this from the records of Dublin Castle.  It was flown continuously until it was removed by the authorities.</p> <p>The second recording of it flying was in 1916, and the Senator can imagine that it was not taken down each night during the 1916 Rising because going onto the roof of the GPO would have been a life-shortening exercise.  Again, that was one of the precedents that helped create a new protocol which, as the Senator outlined, has been adopted by the Taoiseach&rsquo;s Department regarding flying the national flag by day and by night, following the precedent that was set by Thomas Francis Meagher, but also the during the 1916 Rising, where it can be flown at night where it is illuminated, preferably by spotlight, but not necessarily so.  Street lighting will do.  I hope Dublin City Council will respond favourably.  I will engage with it on the Senator&rsquo;s behalf on that matter.  </p> <p>The Senator said it is a small issue, but the national flag is flown every morning on the lawn of Leinster House, along with the Ukrainian flag.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are parts of Ukraine that can no longer fly their own flag, as Senator Ahearn and others know.  Flying our national flag should be something we never take for granted.  I call on Senator Carrigy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#W00200"><p>Following on from the earlier contribution by Senator Pippa Hackett,  I do not accept the comments made by her that turf burning days are numbered.  Coming from a county where more than 20% of households use turf as fuel to keep people warm, and particularly people of the older generation, I do not believe it is acceptable to make a comment like that.  As a county, the same as other midland counties, we bought into a just transition up to 2027.  Unfortunately, objections from green-supporting organisations led to the closure of the Lough Ree and Shannonbridge power stations and the boglands in the midlands.  I am not going to accept comments like that.  Until people's homes are insulated to a standard where they do not need solid fuel, and particularly homes in rural areas, then we should be allowed to keep our houses and homes warm.</p> <p>I compliment the Minister for Finance, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, on the VAT rate.  I am a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Sport and Media.  We have been pushing for the extension of the VAT rate, following discussions with the Irish Hotels Federation and the Restaurants Association of Ireland.  I thank the Minister for putting this forward to the Cabinet today and for supporting the industry.  People have mentioned Cork and Kerry, and I too look forward to the summer when people are organising their breaks.  We in Ireland's Hidden Heartlands are an unhidden gem.  I would recommend people pay visit during the summer months in particular.</p> <p>I want to touch base with regard to RT&Eacute; and the fact we have no midlands correspondent for the midland's region since Ciar&aacute;n Mullooly retired a number of months back.  I wish Mr. Mullooly well in his new role in the Roscommon Partnership.  I met with Mr. Mullooly recently at the Irish Rural Link national conference.  He is doing an excellent job.  It is important that all regions in the country are covered by RT&Eacute;.  Perhaps the Leader will write to RT&Eacute; and ask for an update as to the date by which we will have our correspondent put in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#W00300"><p>I support Senator Murphy's call for a debate on rural transport.  I raised this previously in the House.  We have had the very welcome reductions yesterday of 20% and 50% for youth travel cards but, unfortunately, many of the people I represent and live beside will not see the benefit of that because they are on commercial operators, which are still not included under the scheme.  Last night I was contacted by a number of people who are still bypassing their local train station to drive to Sallins to benefit from the local short hop zones there.  Public transport, particularly for those in the commuter counties, as well as rural transport, is still very costly.  We need to address it.  I support Senator Murphy's call for a debate on that.</p> <p>I also wish to raise an issue on which I have been working with a local councillor, Angela Feeney.  The Kildare Down's syndrome group is a wonderful organisation supporting 235 families across Kildare and west Wicklow.  In December 2021 the group received notice from the Kildare Education and Training Board, ETB, that for health and safety reasons, it must remove itself from the prefabs where it is located in Naas by October 2022.  We can just imagine how the parents and the students felt when they received this news.  The group is a magnificent one.  Among the many services it carries out are: early development for infants, toddlers, and preschoolers; adult education classes; literacy; work skills; horticulture; social and political courses; and social activities from primary age activities to teen youth groups.  It does wonderful work for so many families in the Kildare and west Wicklow area.</p> <p>The group is seeking a new premises.  I have written to the chief executive of the Kildare and Wicklow ETB, Dr. Deirdre Keyes.  I am also putting out a call today to anyone who may have a suitable premises in the Naas or Sallins area, where the group is based and centrally located.  This group cannot be allowed to lose its premises.  It needs to encourage and develop the children and young adults it works with on a daily basis.  If anyone in that area has a premises, it would be most welcome.  I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#W00400"><p>I join with my colleague, Senator Ahearn, in calling for an invitation to be extended to our Ukrainian parliamentary colleagues.  We saw terrible things there and the terrible devastation being wreaked by the Russian forces.  The takeaway message for me, however, was the resilience of the Ukrainian people and the Ukrainian politicians.  Their extraordinary determination to overcome this is actually very encouraging.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We should be doing whatever we can to support them.  The four messages that Senator Ahearn mentioned were repeated to us at meeting after meeting and I am pleased to say that Ireland has responded on most of those issues.  The military issue remains a difficulty for us but in the other areas we have been supportive.</p><p>I would like to raise another international issue, namely, the installation of John Lee as the new Chief Executive of Hong Kong.  He is the former Secretary for Security of Hong Kong and was sanctioned by the United States in 2020, primarily because of his involvement in enforcing the appalling national security law that exists in Hong Kong, which essentially removes the right of anybody to get involved in political opposition or protest.  Under the then Chief Executive, Carrie Lam, he was foremost in enforcing that law and in cracking down on any vocalisation of opposition to the Hong Kong Government.  We should consider sanctioning him in Ireland too.  He was not elected but installed by a tiny committee that is controlled by Beijing.  The extraordinary thing is that so many Irish people have lived in, worked in or are connected to Hong Kong.  It is a place where we have many connections and we are watching it slip away as any kind of a normal society.  I do not understand why the Chinese are doing it because they are killing the goose that laid the golden egg in terms of the capital that is flowing out of Hong Kong and I know about the difficulties ordinary people have there.  Ireland should also be taking a stand and acknowledging the fact that John Lee's appointment or installation as Chief Executive is not valid, democratic or wanted because of his track record.</p><p>If the Leader is writing letters about correspondents, D&uacute;n Laoghaire does not have an RT&Eacute; correspondent either.  We are an important region and I do not seek to disagree with Senator Carrigy in any way.  I would love to see an RT&Eacute; correspondent in D&uacute;n Laoghaire as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#X00200"><p>I ask Senators to be cautious in their comments on appointments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#X00300"><p>I want to pay tribute to our Seanad colleagues, Senators Ahearn and Ward, and the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney.  It was a difficult experience to travel to Ukraine and to bring back the real experiences there and tell us what it is like on the ground.  That helps our resolve and helps us to show how important peace will be.  I know that on Sunday, Ukrainian President Zelenskyy put out a video that was so strong.  It was in black and white and he spoke with such heart.  He spoke about the walls of buildings coming down, saying that these walls held photos and that on those photos were people who had fought in the Second World War.  Those walls are crumbling and falling apart.  It was powerful and it shows how important that type of leadership and that soul he has given to Ukraine is.  There is such pride in him as a leader.  It is important for Ireland as an observer with the United Nations to play our role as well.</p> <p>I would like to acknowledge that we had the Fine Gael agriculture and rural development conference in Tullamore last weekend.  It was fantastic because I had an opportunity to meet the principal of Mountbellew Agricultural College, Dr. Edna Curley, who spoke about how getting training in farming these days is like passport to the future for farming.  In other words, training in agriculture is the passport to developing a future but it is important that we see alternative forms of income in agriculture.  It is true that what we saw over that day was how important it is that we, as a group, develop our policies in Fine Gael to fight for farmers across the country, be they dry stock or suckler farmers.  That is particularly true in how we are looking at supports coming in to aid those farmers who will potentially face fodder shortages later this year, especially with the rising costs of fertiliser.  The silage measures that have been brought in, to the tune of over &euro;55 million, will be crucial to offer support to farmers of up to &euro;1,000.  It will be so needed when times are tough, especially when we know that farmers potentially will not be making a second cut.  Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas; I thank our colleagues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#X00400"><p>I agree with Senator Dolan about the conference.  We all know that from a party perspective it is nice to get together with friends from around the country because we only get to see them every couple of years and it is a lovely event.  For me, the vibrancy, engagement, grit and determination that can only be got in rural Ireland were evident in the room on Saturday and it was lovely to see that our rural cousins are in fighting form and are not taking some of the issues we talk about in here week in, week out lying down.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will first reply to Senator Garret Ahearn, and to Senators Ward and Dolan who touched on the issue.  The video that President Zelenskyy did on Sunday really shows how important leadership is, and particularly at times of crisis.  For a gentleman who has not been a political leader for very long he has some metal and support in Ukraine.  I say that because, as Senator Ahearn has spoken about, we can all see the crumbling buildings and talk about the history, and events, that have led to such a situation.  What certainly is not crumbling is the spirit, determination and resilience of the Ukrainian people.  Anything that we can do in Europe, America and anywhere else in the world to keep that spirit alive and provide support is definitely what we should do.  I refer to sanctions and military weapons from other countries, which do not have the position that we do.  An absolute sheer determination from a political perspective that supports them is definitely something we can do.  I will liaise with the officials to see how best we can facilitate them within the next couple of weeks.  I will liaise with the Senator's office to make sure, if it is not within the three days, that we accommodate them for maybe some of the time that we are not sitting but it is really important that we do this.<br/><br/>Regarding Senator Ward, I sometimes think that I have a magic wand but I definitely do not have a wand that extends to RT&Eacute; correspondents for D&uacute;n Laoghaire.  I will convey his concerns about the appointment of John Lee to the attention of the Minister for Foreign Affairs and ask if it is appropriate for us to respond or at least have a debate on same in this House.  I will get back to the Senator on that.<br/><br/>Senator Carrigy, earlier I found myself considering whether I would respond to some of the comments that were made because it might be better to adopt an approach of the less said the easier mended.  I will tell him what really is important.  When we have difficult transitions to go through, and this is one of them, we must not poke people in the eye.  Communications are absolutely crucial.  A just transition, and the funding that is needed to make that transition easier, is crucial.  No amount of bandying back that one is green and someone else is blue is ever going to fix that.  What we need is  proper communication and to respectfully show that people's lives and identities are equally important.  However, the money to make transition easier is the most paramount thing that will resolve this issue.  Finally, the Senator also welcomed the 9% VAT rate as did other colleagues, which is a very welcome move by the Cabinet this morning.<br/><br/>Senator Seery Kearney asked for us to write to Dublin City Council on the protocol that governs flag flying for her heritage groups.  I will liaise with her office and we will help that situation as much as we can.<br/><br/>I assure Senator Boylan that I will write to the Minister and contact her office today.  It seems a logical thing for us to not cause distress where unwarranted and to move to the Pillar Room for which we already pay.  More importantly, I will ask what the status of the legislation is that is required for jury selection and get back to the Senator.<font color="#FFFFFF">End of Take</font><br/><br/>Senators Wall and Murphy sought a debate on rural transport.  Given that it is an advantage, which  we have seen in Dublin this week, and I refer to the reduction in fare prices and the introduction of the 90-minute ticket, and as previously done in some of the cities around this country, it is pity that the fare reduction does not extend to operators in the rest of the country.  We should push for an extension of the scheme and I will organise a debate as quickly as I can.<br/><br/>Senator Murphy recommended the 9% VAT rate.  He also paid tribute to the people who run his local hospital, which has gone through a difficult and painful transition.  It is nice to see the hospital staff and management be rewarded for the excellent services that they provide.<br/><br/>Senator Keogan asked for a report on the interim Cass report and I will try to arrange it.  What might be beneficial first is to write to the clinical lead of the HSE to find out his opinion of the report and then we can frame a debate around the report.  I make that suggestion because I fear that if I sought a report now that I would be told that it is an English report and that the Department does not have anybody to meet and discuss it with us here.  Let us find out how the clinical lead views the interim report, find out whether it will change the practices in terms of clinical referrals done by the HSE, and then I will get back to the Senator to arrange a specific debate that is tailored to her needs.<br/><br/>Senator Buttimer talked about the 9% VAT rate.  Like Senator Conway, he supported the call made by Deputy Stanton this week to open the educational buildings that are in every single town, village and city.  The real concern, and I suppose this has been highlighted because of the conversation on the national maternity hospital, is that when patron bodies own the buildings then they are the people to whom we must beg to use those buildings.  Right now, the vast majority of the patron bodies in the educational system are not the State.  They are either the Catholic Church, the Protestant Church, the Educate Together sector or Gaelscoileanna.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We do not have any uniformity in the provision of services either before schools open or after they close and definitely not at the weekends.  For the hundreds of millions, if not billions, of euro we spent on the construction of those buildings it is an absolute crying shame our sports clubs, community facilities, creches and after-school clubs do not have access to the buildings the State helps supply the funding for.  It is beyond time we had some sort of a protocol and direction from the Government.  I will ask for that debate as quickly as I can.</p><p>Senator Ardagh spoke about the working group on housing defects, looked for the publication of the final report and a debate to accompany that.  I will ask the Minister for that.</p><p>Senator Hoey spoke about workforce planning within the health service and looked for a debate on that, which I will arrange.  She also talked about the international Dublin Gay Theatre Festival and the success of it this week and last, despite public funding being pulled.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile spoke about the elections in Northern Ireland last week.  I suppose Members are all political animals so like me they were glued to the television watching the returns in the different constituencies.  What really is incredible is both Michelle O'Neill and Naomi Long proved to everybody this weekend there is no glass ceiling in women in politics either in Ireland or elsewhere.  I congratulate both of them on their wins.  As Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile said, we hope minds will be focused and everybody will now sit around the table and provide an Assembly and an Executive, get back to work and spend the &pound;300 million he mentioned, which would be lovely to see.</p><p>I am not really sure how to diplomatically answer Senator Clonan's question because I fear I probably agree with everything he said.  Every other apology, heartfelt, has come from the Taoiseach and it probably would be appropriate but the Minister, to be fair to him, has taken real initiative in trying to resolve this issue in the last two years, as a new Minister with genuinely heartfelt concern to try to resolve this issue.  Today was the first opportunity he saw to do so sooner rather than later.  While I hear what the Senator is saying, the Minister probably is the most appropriate person because he is the reason we are where we are today.  I am aware not everybody is happy but he has made some serious inroads into trying to resolve this situation that has gone on for far too long.  I will pass back the Senator's concerns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z00200"><p>I absolutely respect his utmost good faith-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z00300"><p>I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z00400"><p>-----but I think it would be great for the country if the Taoiseach would do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z00500"><p>I absolutely hear the Senator on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z00600"><p>I am sure Miche&aacute;l Martin would have no problem with that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z00700"><p>I will pass it on but he will be here at 6.30 p.m. but we will pass on the Senator's concerns before that anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z00800"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z00900"><p>Not at all.  Senator Conway talked about the school building project and looking for a debate on it.  The 9% VAT rate and staff shortage within the hospitality industry were also raised.  The industry tells us often about the latter issue but I am not sure work permits for people from outside the EU are consistently the answer when we have 150,000 people on the live register.  We need to think outside the box sometimes.</p> <p>Senator Chambers opened today requesting a debate on childcare.  I am in the lovely position of being able to say it will be happening next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z01000"><p>Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agat.  I join the Leader and colleagues on the elections in Northern Ireland.  I congratulate all those who were elected and commend all who put their names forward for election.  It is never an easy thing.  We wish all the best in the future to those who had seats and lost them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.101" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.102" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z01200">Report of Committee of Selection: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#Z01300"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	&quot;That the 12th report of the Committee of Selection be laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann&quot;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.104" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.105" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#CC00100">Finance (Covid-19 and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2022: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.106" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#CC00350"><p>I take this opportunity to welcome one of the Seanad's esteemed alumni, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Paschal Donohoe.  It is good to have him in the House.  I had the pleasure of serving a term with him here in the past.  I invite him to address the House for eight minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1558" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#CC00400"><p>What the Bill before the House does is provide a legislative basis for a number of changes to the main Covid supports that were announced by the Government since the end of last year and that are currently being implemented by the Revenue Commissioners on an administrative basis.  Members will recall that the additional public health restrictions in place at the end of last year necessitated additional supports for those businesses most impacted.  We are dealing with some other matters in the Bill, such as the tax treatment of payments for decommissioning of fishing vessels and a provision to ensure that the pandemic special recognition payment is made tax-free.  We are also going to deal with a number of taxation measures in respect of the cost of living: the excise reduction for petrol and diesel, changes that have been made to marked gas oil and also measures that have been made to deal with, for example, the announcement that the Government made today regarding the 9% VAT rate.</p> <p>Section 1 deals with the normal definitions that are included in legislation of this kind.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Paschal Donohoe:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2244"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2244&amp;amp;pid=PaschalDonohoe&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Section 2 of the Bill deals with a number of different changes in the employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS.  This section provides for further enhancements to the scheme in response to public health situations that developed last December and in the early part of the year.  The scheme was reopened for certain businesses that would otherwise not have been eligible, as announced on 21 December.  Enhanced support was provided to businesses directly affected by the public health regulations introduced in late December 2021, with a delay in the step-down arrangements to such firms that would continue to receive support until the end of May.</p><p>As Senators are aware, the temporary wage subsidy scheme, TWSS, and the employment wage subsidy scheme have played a central role in supporting businesses, encouraging employment and helping maintain the link between employers and employees.  Over &euro;10 billion was paid under both schemes, with 67,000 employers availing of the TWSS and, to date, just under 52,000 employers availing of EWSS with respect to 739,500 employees.  It is an extraordinary number when we consider how many people are at work in our country.  Overall, this process has played a vital role in protecting and preserving our economy when it was under such direct challenge due to the economic consequences of Covid-19.</p><p>Section 3 of the Bill makes clear that the pandemic recognition payment of &euro;1,000 to eligible front-line health and ambulance workers will be tax-free.  This recognises the extraordinary efforts of those front-line workers in supporting our lives and health at a time of such difficulty.</p><p>This leads me to the Covid restrictions support scheme, CRSS, which was introduced in the Finance Act 2020, with &euro;727 million paid under the scheme to businesses affected by public health restrictions.  Section 4 gives a legislative basis for the final changes announced in response to the public health restrictions of last December.  It provides for an increase in the turnover reduction criteria of no more than 25% of 2019 turnover to now no more than 40%.  This was made available to newer businesses that commenced trading in the period between 13 October 2020 and 26 July 2021.  In addition, certain charities and sporting bodies that carry on similar trading activities to businesses became eligible to apply for CRSS in the most recent period of restrictions.</p><p>Tax debt warehousing was introduced in 2020 by the Financial Provisions (Covid-19) (No. 2) Act 2020.  At the end of March, more than 90,000 individual businesses were availing of debt warehousing, with &euro;2.9 billion of liabilities warehoused.  To put this in context, the total debt eligible is &euro;30.9 billion; 90% of that debt has been paid and the amount warehoused represents approximately 10% of the total tax debt eligible for the scheme.  As announced last January, the Government has agreed that the period when tax liabilities arising can be warehoused will be extended to 30 April 2022 for all businesses eligible for Covid-19 support schemes.  This will allow businesses that have been most affected additional time to recover before their tax liabilities must be paid.  Their period of zero interest will therefore commence from 1 May 2022 and last until 30 April 2023, with interest at the reduced rate of 3% payable thereafter until the debt is paid down.  This extension is provided for in sections 5 and 6 and 8 to 11, inclusive.</p><p>Section 12 deals with the changes to mineral oil tax to which I referred earlier.  Section 13 deals with special exemption orders.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Paschal Donohoe:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2244"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2244&amp;amp;pid=PaschalDonohoe&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> In terms of the Government's response to the bulk purchasing of residential properties, section 14 makes an amendment to address a particular issue relating to social and affordable housing in the context of the 10% stamp duty measure.  It is proposed to make provision for a partial repayment scheme for properties designated as cost-rental dwellings by the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage under Part 3 of the Affordable Housing Act 2021.  In practical terms, qualifying taxpayers will get a refund of the difference between the 10% rate and the normal stamp duty rate, which in most instances will be 1%.  The beneficiaries of this amendment will be those involved in the delivery of cost-rental homes at scale, including approved housing bodies such as the Land Development Agency and local authorities.</p><p>The fishing fleet decommissioning scheme is dealt with in section 15.</p><p>Section 16 makes provision for the funding of the Central Bank's central mechanism for information on safe-deposit boxes and bank and payment accounts and in respect of the operation of the register of the beneficial ownership of central financial vehicles, which are required as part of the transposition of EU anti-money laundering directives.</p><p>The Bill provides a legislative basis for changes to various support schemes for businesses that were announced in December and January, as well as a number of additional matters I have outlined.  It underlines the responsiveness of the Government to the needs of businesses for supports while also remaining conscious of the need to carefully manage and restore our public finances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#EE00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I am speaking on behalf of my colleague, Senator Maria Byrne.  I acknowledge the range of supports the Government has provided since the outset of the Covid pandemic.  I thought we were coming to the end of Covid, but, for obvious reasons, it is still in the Title of the Bill.  Hopefully, it will be the last time that it will be.  That is a recognition of not only the amount of money that has been spent but also the impact that Covid has had on our society.  I was a member of Cabinet during that caretaker period and I know that and the Government responded quickly to provide very real supports for businesses, employees and society.  That has been proven by how the economy has rebounded, the number of businesses that have survived because of the supports provided and the number of people who are back in employment.  It is important to acknowledge that we are back to pre-Covid levels of employment.</p> <p>I welcome today's Cabinet decision on the 9% VAT rate for the tourism sector.  I know these things are difficult.  We need to get back to the point where supports are no longer required.  There is a particular issue with the 9% VAT rate.  We have seen the inflationary pressures on our economy in recent months, and the Government has responded to them.  To have prices and VAT increasing in the autumn and winter period would have added to those pressures which have come upon us.  Obviously, the impact is especially acute in the hospitality sector.  We recognise the reach that the hospitality sector has across the entire country but, in particular, in certain areas of the, including Kerry, where my colleague, Deputy Griffin, has been very strong on this issue.  I acknowledge this morning's decision to extend the 9% VAT rate for a further six months.</p> <p>We are still getting queries as to whether certain categories of employee are eligible for the pandemic special recognition payment of &euro;1,000.  The information provided by the HSE indicates that the list is not exhaustive.  Is there a central point from which we can get absolute clarity on whether somebody involved in catering, for example, who may or may not have been under the employment of the HSE, perhaps for a section 38 entity, is eligible?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Is there a direct point of call to which we can go?  Presumably, some of these &euro;1,000 payments have been paid.  It was paid in a case in Beaumont according to the information I have.  Presumably, all of these will be backdated.  If they have been paid, the fact that they are exempt from tax will be retrospective, if you like.  I presume that is the case.  We received a comment today by email from somebody querying when the Act will be enacted and whether the law will be backdated to cover payments already made, which I assume is the absolute case.</p><p>I refer to some of the other issues and the supports that have been put in place.  Obviously this about ensuring the special arrangements are compliant by the end of the tax year.  That is all very welcome.  I suppose it is tidying up what we know to be the case and what was announced previously rather than any new initiatives to ensure the waivers and other issues have been tidied up.  That is important.</p><p>I also welcome the changes made regarding the duties on fuels.  Again, there were, of course, inflationary pressures based on the fact that we are price takers in relation to oil and hence petrol and diesel.  This has been exacerbated, of course, by the situation with the illegal war in Ukraine.  Obviously, these things must be continuously monitored.</p><p>I know the Minister will be starting preparations for the next budget, which will be different from this time last year.  I will not say we were at the height of Covid-19 but we were certainly still very much impacted by it this time last year.  Obviously, we did not have the situation we have at the moment in Ukraine.  Inflationary pressures and cost-of-living issues are real.  Government has acted and provided those supports but it is something I know the Minister will be keeping under constant review with regard to what is allowable under the financial situation we are in and what is possible under the EU laws as well.</p><p>There is uncertainty with regard to the supplies of gas, for example, although not so much here, because we do not get it from Russia.  The knock-on impacts of any supply changes that take place over the course of the year, however, could have impacts on the wholesale price of gas next autumn.  I have heard projections.  These issues are still very real.</p><p>I know the Minister is up to speed and keeping an eye on matters in his role in the Eurogroup as well.  The Government has done much to support businesses and job creation and retention and has provided a range of supports in respect of the cost of living.  As I said, this must be constantly kept under review.  It is a real dilemma, which I know the Minister understands, and a real issue in households up and down the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#FF00200"><p>The Minister is very welcome to the House.  I welcome this Bill.  It is prudent that we examine our financial status in the wake of Covid-19 and seek to "put the debt ratio on a downward path", as the Minister told the D&aacute;il last week.  The Bill comprises a number of assorted financial measures and tweaks.  A miscellaneous Bill always affords a useful opportunity to deal with multiple issues at once.  I would like to discuss a few of those with the Minister.</p> <p>As president of the Eurogroup, can the Minister update us on what progress has been made in this country in preparation for the minting of the digital euro?  I understand the European Central Bank, ECB, is actively investigating the prospect having published a report on payment preferences in March as part of the current phase.  The Central Bank of Ireland has done some looking into central bank digital currencies, which would enable its users to have access to widely accepted, safe and trusted means of payment for the digital age.  Recent global events have given rise to concern over State control of private finances, however.  The extra judicial freezing of assets and transactions by the Canadian Government of individuals deemed associated with anti-Government protests provide a chilling case study in the abuse of centralised power.  In the Minister's opinion, what protections in this area would be necessary to ensure the continued financial autonomy and privacy of Irish citizens?</p> <p>Section 12 of the Bill allows for a refund on the increased level of stamp duty levied on bulk purchase housing, regardless of whether that housing is subsequently used as cost-rental housing.  I share the opinion of many that last year's increase in stamp duty was not sufficient in dissuading real estate investment trusts, REIT, from bulk purchasing residential properties.  I sincerely hope this clause will not undo even that small measure.  I understand this is only in relation to cost rental as per the Affordable Housing Act 2021, but we are all aware of the unintended consequences of legislation, particularly in all areas as complex as housing.  This comes at the same time as the announcement of the new &euro;500 million fund aimed at granting developers up to &euro;120,000 per apartment in order to unblock stalled developments and make the building of apartments financially viable for developers.  It is moves like this that make people think the housing market is being propped up and that we are in for a nasty shock at some point in the future.</p> <p>Across the pond in the US, the biggest financial firms are beginning to use the word "recession" in light of the continued inflation trends.  The country's GDP shrank for the first time since the start of the pandemic.  Another quarter of downward trends will meet the technical definition of a recession.</p> <p>Last week, Deutsche Bank became the first major bank to call an impending recession in America.  History shows that any sort of a collapse in a key player like the United States has its impact felt the world over.  The question then is: what are we going to do to prepare?  What is the Minister's outlook on the global financial near future in terms of inflation and recession?  What steps are being taken on foot of it?  Maybe these issues are beyond the scope of this Bill or perhaps some provisions are simply more miscellaneous than others.  I would be most grateful if the Minister could address them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#FF00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House to discuss the Finance (Covid-19 and Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2022.  As  Senator Kyne said, let us hope that the term "Covid-19" is in our rear-view mirror and is not to return again.  As the Senator said also, when we look back, we will see what the Government did with the significant supports it gave businesses to survive during the last two years was, in fact, incredible, which most in the business community will acknowledge.  While we did not get everything right, we got the majority of things right.  The pandemic unemployment payment, PUP, was able to sustain people.  Much credit must be given to the Government in respect of how it reacted over the last two years.</p> <p>I will mention several of the schemes available to help businesses survive.  The employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS, was one of the main ones.  We started with the temporary wage subsidy scheme, TWSS, which I believe was availed of by 67,000 businesses and 690,000 employees.  When the EWSS came in, a smaller number of employers but a larger number of employees availed of it.  It is important to point out how important it was in keeping employees in work and in supporting businesses.  We then had the Covid restrictions support scheme, CRSS, which allowed businesses to offset some of the additional costs they were incurring over the period.</p> <p>The tax warehousing was a huge benefit to some.  As the Minister said, it was only 10% of the total taxes businesses applied for.  I think 90,000 individual companies applied for it and &euro;2.9 billion has been put into warehousing.  The challenge for businesses now is that they must pay that off.  That is an added burden on some of the businesses.  None of us anticipated during Covid-19 that when we came out of it, we would end up with a cost-of-living crisis, and on top of the cost-of-living crisis, we would have a war in Europe that would add significantly to the cost of doing business.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pat Casey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2431"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2431&amp;amp;pid=PatCasey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Government has reacted as best it can.  There is no point in standing here and saying it can offset every cost.  No Government can offset every cost.  The Government has taken a very good approach.  Initially, it targeted supports to the most vulnerable in society to help them through the cost-of-living crisis and then it had targeted measures through the excise duty and the VAT on fuel and gas.  Those measures must be welcomed also.  Overall, I very much welcome this Bill, which went from a Covid Bill to a cost-of-living Bill to a war in Europe Bill.  It gave the Minister the vehicle to allow him to bring in certain measures that will help offset costs in the future.</p><p>I will conclude on a positive note.  A number of colleagues mentioned the Minister's announcement today on VAT in the hospitality sector.  As he is aware, I am directly involved in hospitality.  The measure was greatly welcomed by everybody within our sector.  It is very important that we maintain the 9% VAT rate, especially when we add in the cost of living, because it is all about our margins, which were tight, and they got tighter with the cost-of-living increases.  It is important that we have the security of retaining the 9% rate for at least another six months and then we might even discuss extending it a bit longer.  When we look at the VAT rate on hospitality, we seem to be spending more time at 9% than we do at 13.5%.  I wonder if the true rate for the hospitality sector is at the lower one rather than the 13.5% rate.  Overall, the Government can take credit for how it has handled the previous two years and the current cost-of-living crisis.  We support the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#GG00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  We are always asking for more, but I do want to give credit where it is due.  I do not envy the Minister his role as Minister for Finance in the past couple of years.  First, I thank him for sticking with it and doing as much as he could within the remit and the budget we have.</p><p>I wish to highlight a few points relating to the Bill.  It is important to say that the unemployment rate is very low currently, at 4.8%, despite war, Covid and inflation.  That is something we as a Government, and the Minister for Finance, must take credit for.  We have delivered the right level of supports for businesses which suffered throughout the pandemic and are now emerging from it.  The Minister outlined that &euro;16.5 billion was made available to support businesses, employees and those who were left unemployed by the pandemic.  Nearly every day, a small business owner has asked me to thank the Government because measures such as the EWSS were a lifeline.  There is always more, and people are always giving out, but it is good to stop and take stock and appreciate the fact that there is a lot of gratitude out there for the Minister and the work he has done.</p><p>The pandemic special recognition payment should also be acknowledged.  Front-line health workers, workers in nursing homes, hospices, hospital cleaners and porters, as well as Defence Forces personnel involved in testing and vaccination centres, were all eligible for the payment.  This will also be provided to student nurses on a <i>pro rata</i>basis.  I thank the Government for not applying tax to the payment, as it would have meant the payment was reduced by about half.  That was a good move as well.</p><p>I also want to highlight the cost-rental scheme.  This is something the Green Party, of which I am a member, has been bringing forward for a long time.  The Bill provides for a partial repayment of stamp duty, charged at the higher 10% rate for residential dwellings designed as cost-rental dwellings.  Unfortunately, everybody feels under pressure in this country to own their home.  That is mainly because, unlike most of mainland Europe, there is very little fixity of tenure and rents are very high.  The cost-rental model the Government has initiated is going to be a game changer because friends of mine, who live all over Europe, do not feel the same pressure to own a home because they have fixed tenure and their rent is based on the cost of the build, as opposed to market value.  That is something very important which we have brought to the Government.</p><p>It is a positive move to reduce stamp duty.  A temporary reduction in the rate of VAT on gas and electricity from 13.5% to 9% was a major win as well, because while we cannot control the cost of fossil fuels, that is a measure we can introduce and it is good that we did it.</p><p>A Bill is waiting on the desk of the Minister's colleague, Deputy Peter Burke, which is part of the cost-of-living crisis.  We need to take it seriously and bring it in before the summer recess.  I am afraid that we will not get it through on time.  It will put money in the pockets of farmers, schools and community groups.  I refer to the photovoltaic solar Bill my colleagues and I in the Green Party have brought to the Seanad.  It will reduce the cost for farmers.  We cannot help farmers in every way because their costs have become so astronomical, between nitrates and diesel, but this is one way we can put money back in their pockets and reduce their bills.  It is very important.  I know from this Bill that this consideration is also important to the Minister, so I ask him to raise the issue with his party colleague.  As someone who lives in north Clare, where most of our jobs are in hospitality and tourism, the VAT rate of 9% is crucial.  I thank the Minister for his work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#GG00300"><p>The Minister is very welcome.  I welcome the opportunity to speak on this legislation, which I hope deals with the last item of Covid legislation we will need as we emerge from the pandemic.  It is important that we remain on our guard in respect of this, because we know the virus is still in our community and we cannot accurately predict the mutation of the virus in the time ahead, but we can hope that the worst of it is over.</p> <p>The Bill mainly provides for the Covid-19 financial measures that were put in place following the outbreak of the Omicron variant.  It will give legislative effect to the changes to certain Covid support schemes announced by the Government in December 2021 and January 2022.  Sinn F&eacute;in supported those measures at the time, and we continue to support them.</p> <p>The Bill provides for the reopening of the employment wage subsidy scheme for businesses which would otherwise not have had access to the scheme at that time, as they would not have been eligible, and that such businesses can continue to be supported until the scheme expires.  The legislation also provides certain businesses which are no longer eligible to re-apply from 1 January from this year, a measure we proposed and supported.</p> <p>The Bill also provides for businesses that were directly impacted by public health measures, introduced in December in response to the variant, such as the 8 p.m. closing time and the 50% capacity restriction to be able to avail of enhanced rates for the month of February with a more gradual and tapered step-down out of the scheme.  Again, this is a measure we welcome.</p> <p>The tax debt warehousing scheme has been crucial to support the liquidity of businesses.  I welcome the extension of both the repayment dates and the interest-free period.</p> <p>Another measure relating to the pandemic is the bonus payment to health workers, which is also included in the Bill.  It is quite unbelievable that the Government would announce a bonus and five or six months later not one health worker has yet received the payment.</p> <p>I would also like to mention family carers.  It is terribly sad that family carers who went through such isolation, as services and respite were cancelled, who worked tirelessly night and day looking after and protecting their vulnerable patients, have got little or no recognition from the Government at all.  We all know the work and services they provide.  In their own way, they were front-line workers.  For the life of me, I cannot understand the Government's unfair treatment of family carers.</p> <p>As I indicated, Sinn F&eacute;in continues to support this legislation but we will put forward amendments on the next Stage, because my colleague, our finance spokesperson, Deputy Pearse Doherty, proposed amendments in the D&aacute;il that I do not believe got enough consideration.  It was a missed opportunity.  I hope the Minister will reconsider them in the light of the ongoing cost-of-living crisis, especially with regard to the rising cost of fuel.</p> <p>Right down the west coast, 66% of people, or two out of three households, depend on home heating oil as their primary source of heating.  Recently, home heating oil has reached astronomical prices.  It cost &euro;1,700 in March to fill a tank with oil.  The price has more than doubled in the space of a year and many households cannot bear this cost.  With Deputy Doherty's amendment, we propose to reduce the cost of filling a tank by &euro;118.  Many households simply cannot bear these price increases.  Not only do households feel they have been forgotten by the Government, they feel they have been punished by it when the increase in carbon tax was allowed to go ahead.  We also introduced proposals to reduce the cost of petrol and diesel.</p> <p>The measures and legislation we have seen during the past year and addressed in this Bill show that there can be flexibility and, where there is a willingness, there is a way to meet the needs of society.  Sinn F&eacute;in recognises that the Government cannot shield everyone from every price increase; however, we are fully aware that the Government can and should do more to support low- and middle-income households which, without support, cannot withstand these price increases without significant hardship.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#GG00400"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  We too very much welcome and support the Bill.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As stated by Senator Casey, this is, hopefully, the final piece of Covid legislation to come before us, but it reflects what can be done when there is political will to save jobs and keep businesses afloat.  While there were some difficulties in the early days in terms of Government not supporting non-rated businesses, that was resolved last year through later iterations of the CRSS payment. </p><p>I welcome the revisions in the Bill.  I am conscious that thus far there has been a significant amount of debate around some of the detail in it.  There are two issues I would like to touch on, the first of which relates to the Covid recognition payment.  We are very supportive of this important payment and we welcome that workers will get the full net benefit of the payment because of the tax measures provided for under this Bill.  However, it is important to reiterate the message conveyed by Senator Kyne that there is confusion and concern about the limited nature of the payment and to whom it will be made.  A very narrow view has been taken by Government as to who should be entitled to it.  We learned in April that those working in acute hospitals, vaccination and testing centres and section 38 organisations will get it, but there has been no update with regard to staff of section 39 organisations, those working in long-term residential home care services or voluntary and private nursing homes.  While private nursing homes should, perhaps, look to themselves to better pay their workers, there is a real issue within section 39 organisations who are reliant on the State for their resources.  The Government needs to step up to the mark and ensure that the Covid recognition payment is provided to those workers as well.  Ultimately, many of those workers put their lives and the health and lives of their families on the line so that they could support the most vulnerable in society.  The message today to the Minister, as a senior Minister in the Government, is that the Government needs to make an announcement, sooner rather than later, on the comprehensive list of workers eligible for this payment and it needs to be generous in spirit in ensuring the net is cast as widely as possible.</p><p>I will move on to the second issue.  The extension and changes to the EWSS are welcome, but my colleague, Deputy Nash, and I retain a very deep concern about the failure by Government to effectively clawback EWSS payments that were not necessary.  We know from replies to parliamentary questions from Deputy Nash that &euro;267.8 million was given to firms to support wages and that some of those firms then went on to file dividend withholding tax returns.  While we know a small number of those firms have made repayments and that a large number of them had made partial repayments, there remains a large number of firms that have pocketed the supports provided by the State to keep their businesses afloat yet at the same time they were able to pay dividends.  That sends out an exceptionally poor message around the use of public resources to keep businesses afloat.  I recall that last year the Revenue Commissioners approached a number of families who had childminders as employees.  Those families did the right thing by those in their employment and put them on the EWSS, but months later they were told the employees did not qualify and they would have to repay that money to the Revenue Commissioners.  Many of those families have limited resources so having to repay that money was an enormous challenge.  </p><p>I have not had an opportunity to express my condolences to the Minister on the passing of his mother.  By all accounts, she was a fantastic constituency canvasser in her time and, obviously, very proud of all of the Minister's achievements.  I express my sympathies to the Minister and to all of his family.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#HH00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and I thank him for his stewardship of the Department of Finance.  I congratulate him on listening to the views of many and on his own vision in terms of the extension of the 9% VAT rate in the hospitality sector.  Retention of that rate is important in terms of jobs and people.  If the Minister were to listen to the dystopian view of the world from Senator Gavan one would imagine the Government we are part of and support has done nothing to help anybody, to assist, to promote or ensure that the infrastructure of the State was wrapped around employers, employees, workers and their families.  At a time when people needed the State, Government acted responsibly and with a vision.  Throughout the world, that was acknowledged.</p> <p>The vast infrastructure was necessary because at the heart of what we are as an economy and as a people is jobs and investment in our cities and towns in rural and urban Ireland.  As a world and as a country, we need to reflect on where we have come from since the pandemic began.  Senator Casey spoke about this being the final Covid-19-related Bill.  The pandemic has changed the world view and our view of work, the workforce, the workplace, what it means to be an employer and what it means to be a worker.  We talk about the future of Europe.  The future of work in our country and in the world is an issue on which we need to have a real and serious conversation whatever our ideologies.  The world of work has changed and the workplace has changed.  We can cast our minds back to the simplicity of the commute into Dublin from Cork to attend at the Oireachtas, at a time when traffic was at a trickle.  Today, it is back to pre-pandemic levels despite the Government having invested in public infrastructure to bring about a modal shift from the car to public transport.  </p> <p>We never thought phrases such as "working from home" or "remote working" would become part of our lexicon and part of the daily lives of so many people.  For many, the work-life balance has improved.  Virtual meetings, flexibility and so on have all become part of the nature of work and of jobs.  That is important.  Equally important are the figures articulated by the CSO, which show an unemployment rate of 4.8% this April compared to 7.5% last year.  This means we have an economy that is growing, notwithstanding the cost of inflation, the cost of doing business,the cost of living increases, the gargantuan war in the Ukraine and the troubles associated with that and the changing world.  The growing employment figures present a stark question to us in regard to particular sections of our economy.  We need to have a real conversation about that.  There is a real need for those of us on the Labour Panel in the Seanad to have that debate.  There are many vacant posts in the hospitality sector.  People will not take up jobs in the sector even though the rate of pay is above the minimum wage.  We can have a debate on the living wage and the minimum wage as part of that conversation, but we need to know what that is the case.  People in the industry say the lack of attractiveness in terms of not being able to spend more time at home and the requirement to work unsociable hours are part of the draw away from the sector.  </p> <p>I acknowledge the work of the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Humphreys, in regard to jobs week, under which 40 different events will be held around the country.  It is an important piece of work in terms of her brief as Minister for Social Protection.  The Minister, Deputy Donohoe, along with the former Minister, Deputy Bruton, and their associated Departments remodelled the world of work.  The T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Varadkar, is continuing that work now in terms of the local enterprise offices and so on.  </p> <p>The CSO figures show that 84% of businesses survived Covid-19, 10% remain at risk and 6% have closed.  The Convention on the Constitution - Citizens' Assembly is discussing a myriad of important issues.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I contend that we need to have a national conversation, in a constitutional convention or citizens' assembly and in tandem with the Houses of the Oireachtas and the Labour Panel of the Seanad, on the future of work.  There is a real need for it.  The Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science is challenging all of us regarding both the role played by apprenticeships and making them more accessible.  I wish I had more time.  I received a very interesting email from a friend of mine who is a builder about trying to get tradespeople and others into the building industry and construction sector and how he thinks the Government can help.  This is important legislation.</p><p>I commend the Minister on his stewardship and his proactivity.  We should not just look at Covid-19 through the rear-view mirror and learn nothing about the world of work.  We need to embrace what has happened, remembering that we need the employer and the employee.  We cannot have one without the other.  I thank the Minister for being here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1558" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#JJ00200"><p>I will reply to the points made by different Senators.  Senator Kyne inquired about the taxation of the pandemic recognition payment and whether tax can be alleviated on payments that were made in the past.  The pandemic recognition payment should not have had taxed paid on it.  When the Government made the announcement on it, we implemented it on an administrative basis through the Revenue Commissioners.  This legislation gives legal effect to that.  Anyone who has contacted the Senator about that &euro;1,000 payment should not have paid tax on it.</p> <p>The Senator also spoke about the extension of the 9% VAT rate, which was referred to by a number of other Senators as well.  The rationale for the extension we have made today is that we recognise we are already in a position of rising prices and to increase VAT on top of that later in the year could be a step too far for many businesses, particularly when we are in the final stage of the employment wage subsidy scheme.  There are many businesses that were receiving between &euro;200 and &euro;350 in respect of each employee on 1 December.  By 1 June, it will be zero.  While that is an appropriate and much-needed exit from this scheme, we also recognise that for many employers it is a very significant economic effect.  I hope that the extension of the VAT rate gives a bit more certainty to businesses, and hospitality businesses in particular, at a time when they are exiting from a significant scheme that kept them going when we asked them to close.</p> <p>Senator Keogan referred to the digital euro and asked about the risk of recession.  It is worth acknowledging that, from a European point of view, even in the most severe economic scenarios published by the ECB, the economy of the euro area, that is, all those countries that share the euro, will still grow by above 2% this year and next year.  The European Commission will be revising its forecasts regarding growth for this year and next year in a few weeks.  Even with the significant changes happening in monetary policy at the moment, we will still be in a situation where the Irish and European economies are growing.  They will just be growing at a very different pace to what we thought possible before this awful war in Ukraine added to the inflationary and supply chain pressures that we were already under.</p> <p>On the digital euro, we are in the very early days of that project.  Privacy has been recognised as a key concern by the ECB.  In the public survey it conducted regarding the future of a digital euro, privacy was the number one issue participants raised.  That is well understood by the ECB as it looks to the future of that project.  An area on which the Senator and I would probably differ is that I believe we must be clear, as we develop a digital euro, that it is not about trying to liberate currencies from the State.  That is certainly not what I would view it as being about.  I am very sceptical about some of the wilder claims that have been made about the future of crypto and digital assets.  The ability of central banks and governments to be the sole issuers of currency is something we must protect and is an essential part of the stability economies need in order to grow.</p> <p>Senator Casey also touched on the 9% VAT rate and made a point about the cost-of-living pressure that many businesses and households are facing at the moment.  As he said, the Government has done much already to try to help those who are coping with these new pressures.  Everybody will always want us to do more but it is clear from the era of Covid that if we had done all we were being asked to do at that point, we would not be in the position we are now in, where the national finances are allowing us to do the additional things we are doing with the cost of living.  We have to try to get the balance right between the demands we are facing today and the need for our public finances to be safe tomorrow.  Every measure taken is criticised by some for not being enough and by others for being too much.  You have to try to get the balance right and that is what we are here to do.</p> <p>Senator Gavan reiterated some of the criticisms of these measures that have been articulated by his party in the D&aacute;il.  He referred to some of the things we are doing as punishing families.  Far from it.  We are trying to help families and businesses at a time when they are facing new pressures in the aftermath of a pandemic.  There is a general understanding that the Government can help and is trying to help but the only money the Government has is the money we collect in taxes or money we borrow.  There is no pot of money that I am not using because I am not compassionate enough to help people at a time of need.  The money we have is either money we must repay or money we collect in taxes.  We are doing as much as we believe is affordable to help those who are feeling the effect of the rise in the price of energy.</p> <p>Senator Sherlock referred to the Covid recognition payment.  I understand the Department of Health will be issuing a guideline and a circular regarding who will and will not receive the payment.  This is imminent and will happen very soon.  The majority of people who can receive the payment have already received it.  We take a different view on the ability of companies to pay dividends while also being on the EWSS.  When I implemented this scheme, the sole criteria was turnover and whether a company was tax-compliant.  My view was that if we brought in an additional measure regarding the level of profit companies could or could not make, it would have undermined the ability of this scheme to protect employment and undermined the ability of employers to be viable as they exit from the pandemic.  It is the case, as the Senator said, that some companies were profitable during the pandemic, but those profits would have been at far lower levels than in pre-Covid times.  Surely profitability on the part of employers is a sign that they can be viable in the future, can retain the people they have in employment at the moment and will even be able to hire and employ more people in the time ahead.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Paschal Donohoe:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2244"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2244&amp;amp;pid=PaschalDonohoe&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The number of companies which were profitable, let alone able to pay a dividend, is a small number relative to the total number of employers the employment wage subsidy scheme helped and protected.</p><p>Senator Garvey made the point about the pandemic recognition payment.  I have acknowledged that and have tried to deal with some issues about it.</p><p>The rate of 4.7% is an extraordinary level of unemployment given all that our economy has gone through.  I remember being in this House at times when we were making changes to the employment wage subsidy scheme with 600,000 people on the EWSS and hundreds of thousands of people on the pandemic unemployment payment.  We have really come some way.  However, as always, we need to look to the future and see how we can do better and guide our economy and our society to a better place.</p><p>Part of that will be the point that Senator Buttimer touched upon regarding the future of work.  He already touched on the enormous change under way regarding work and workplaces in our economy.  There are tremendous opportunities for the Irish economy overall, particularly for the distribution of employment.  I am really encouraged when I meet colleagues who represent constituencies containing a significant share of towns.  They point to the growth in confidence and the increase in employment happening there as we see some work that was happening, for example, in Dublin where we already had very high economic growth and very high employment growth, now being allocated throughout our country.  That is an enormously positive development for our country overall.  With the national broadband plan and the work that the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, is doing, we need to continue to support that trend which is full of opportunities.</p><p>We also need to be conscious of how we can have younger people who are enjoying employment for the first time participate in the environment and learn the skills that are at the heart of an economy which we want to be productive.  As the Senator said, we are not just a people economy but also a skills economy.  We rely on workplaces to provide the learning and development that is needed to allow those skills to continue to develop in the future.</p><p>A number of Senators said they hope this is the last Bill we ever need to debate that contains the word "Covid".  Nobody hopes that more fervently than I do given the amount of emergency Covid legislation we had to introduce.  Above all, it is not about weary legislators dealing with numerous pieces of legislation related to Covid, instead it is about the hope that people are never again forced to shut their businesses and make people unemployed due to this pandemic and that from a health point of view, we can put the darkest days of this pandemic behind us.  It may not have gone away, as a number of Senators have said, but I think we can have confidence about our ability to treat this as a serious and highly infectious disease as opposed to pandemic that closed down our country for so long.</p><p>I again thank the Senators for the points they have made.  I look forward to being back here next week to deal with Committee and Report Stages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#KK00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his comprehensive and individualised response, which is much appreciated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.125" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#KK00450"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#KK00525"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#KK00562"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.129" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 17 May 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.130" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 5.44 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 6.37 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 5.44 p.m. and resumed at 6.37 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.131" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#PP00100">Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.132" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#PP00300"><p>I welcome our guests in the Gallery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#PP00400"><p>I am pleased to present to the House the Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022.  The Bill will mark a major change to the law in Ireland.  It will provide, for the first time, a clear pathway for access to identity records for adopted people and others.  The Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022 was published in January and in April the Bill completed its passage through D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  I look forward to working with Senators to discuss the Bill further over the coming weeks and I extend my thanks to those Senators who sit on the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth and contributed to the pre-legislative scrutiny report.</p> <p>This landmark legislation will provide a full and clear right of access to birth certificates, and birth and early life information for all persons who were adopted, boarded out, the subject of an illegal birth registration or who otherwise have questions about their origins.  The Bill also makes provision for a robust statutory tracing service, a contact preference register and the safeguarding of records.  In addition, it contains a range of important, bespoke new measures to address issues arising for people affected by illegal birth registration.</p> <p>Before I go into discussion of the key sections of this Bill, I want to speak to the issue of illegal birth registrations.  Today, as the Birth Information and Tracing Bill proceeds to the next stage of the legislative process, I believe that it is timely to acknowledge the anguish experienced by those who have been affected by illegal birth registration.</p> <p>In 2018, Tusla discovered documentary evidence of specific cases of illegal birth registration in St. Patrick's Guild, confirming practices that had been long suspected previously.  Indeed, Tusla had identified individual cases of illegal birth registration in the past.  Since then, a series of related reports have been published, including the final report of the Commission of Investigation into Mother and Baby Homes and certain related matters, the independent review report into incorrect birth registrations and most recently, the independent report by the special rapporteur on child protection on proposals for a State response to illegal birth registrations in Ireland.  Collectively, these reports lay bare aspects of our nation's past which were shrouded in shame and secrecy.</p> <p>As has been said previously on the floor of these Houses, the stigma experienced by unmarried mothers and their children was fundamentally wrong.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The shame was not theirs.  It was ours, and it remains our shame.</p><p>In the case of children affected by illegal birth registration, what happened was an historic wrong, with deep and enduring impacts.  Those who were knowingly involved in the illegal registration of births committed a grave offence that robbed children of their identities and their right to accurate birth registrations.  I can only imagine the deep hurt and anguish that people must have experienced on learning of their illegal birth registrations - on learning that the foundations on which their entire identities were built were false.  For this, I am truly sorry and I apologise on behalf of the Government.  I deeply regret the anguish experienced by those who have been affected by illegal birth registration.</p><p>It is well recognised that apologies carry little weight unless backed by practical responses to remedy the rights violation in question.  As such, I assure those affected that the State is actively implementing measures aimed at addressing their situation in a comprehensive manner.  Specifically, the Birth Information and Tracing Bill addresses the situation of people subject to illegal birth registrations by providing clear and guaranteed access to identity information as well as full information on the circumstances of their illegal birth registrations.  It provides a lawful basis for the sharing of information to enable the correction of the birth register, thereby vindicating a person's entitlement to an accurate birth registration.  It provides for the identity by which an affected person has lived to be legally recognised by means of a new register, where that is his or her wish.  Similarly, it provides an assurance to affected persons that acts undertaken and contracts entered into in good faith will not be undermined because a person was the subject of an illegal birth registration.  Importantly, it amends the Succession Act to address inheritance issues arising for affected persons.</p><p>In addition, this Bill provides a statutory basis for the counselling supports that are already made available to persons affected by illegal birth registration.  It provides for a statutory tracing service through which genealogical expertise will be made available to assist individuals and communication and contact will be facilitated between family members and people affected by illegal birth registrations.  Looking to the future, the legislation will provide a mechanism for adoption and other relevant records to be safeguarded and transferred to the Adoption Authority of Ireland, AAI.</p><p>During its passage through D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, I tabled amendments to the legislation to provide for a specialised tracing service.  This specialist service will undertake a review and a full trace of files flagged by Tusla during the independent review as suspicious, and will provide expedited reviews for persons who hold reasonable suspicions that they may have been the subjects of illegal birth registrations.</p><p>Since becoming Minister, I have engaged extensively with people whose births were illegally registered.  These measures, while overdue, will make significant progress towards addressing the practical challenges and difficulties arising for affected individuals.  However, nothing in these measures can undo the past and fully right the wrongs that these people have experienced.  I deeply regret the pain and distress that this has caused and, again, I offer my sincere apology as a Minister of the Government, and on behalf of Government, for this.</p><p>The Bill presented before the House today has undergone extensive changes.  Building on the pre-legislative scrutiny process and D&aacute;il debates, a number of amendments were made to the published text of the Bill.  Many of these arose from concerns raised by stakeholders.  Their inclusion was welcomed by Deputies and they have undoubtedly strengthened the Bill.  Recognising concerns around the terminology of "incorrect birth registration", we tabled an amendment to the Bill to include the words "false and misleading" to recognise the false and fundamentally wrong nature of what happened when people had their births illegally registered.</p><p>Senators will likely be aware of the balancing mechanism &ndash; the section 17 information session &ndash; in the Bill.  I have clarified previously in debates that this is essential to achieving a necessary balancing of EU and constitutional rights.  Having listened to views at pre-legislative scrutiny stage, this information session has been modified.  It can now be held through a phone call and will no longer be provided by a social worker.  Where a parent has registered that he or she does not wish to be contacted, the adopted person will receive a phone call where the privacy wishes of the parent will be relayed to him or her.  I listened to concerns that the original text of section 17 was problematic and I improved the language so that a person would simply be told that his or her parent had lodged a no contact preference, which would represent an exercise of the parent's privacy rights.  Following this phone call, the full and complete set of records will be given to the adopted person in each and every case.  Nothing will be redacted.  Nothing will be held back.</p><p>As the House will be aware, this Bill and the changes it will bring about have been long awaited.  While the Oireachtas has attempted and failed several times to legislate in this area, it is the people affected by this proposed legislation who have been left frustrated, upset and justifiably angry.  Through this opening statement, I aim to outline the key parts of the Bill, as passed by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, and highlight the key amendments that have been made since the Bill was published in January.</p><p>Part 1 contains the standard Short Title, commencement and interpretation provisions.  Section 2 provides definitions of key terms used in the Bill.  A central term is "relevant person", which comprises: an adopted person; a person who is, or reasonably suspects that he or she is, the subject of an illegal birth registration; or a person who has been, or reasonably suspects that he or she has been, the subject of a nursed out arrangement or a boarded out arrangement or resident as a child in an institution specified in the Schedule.  Section 5 provides that the Minister may, by order, add to the list of institutions set out in the Schedule.  This ensures that anyone who was resident in an institution established or operated for the purpose of providing care to children and who is not already captured by one of the categories within the comprehensive definition of "relevant person" can be included within that definition and thereby avail of the provisions of this Bill.</p><p>Another central term is a "relevant body".  This is a body to whom an application for records may be made.  The Bill currently lists the Adoption Authority of Ireland and Tusla as relevant bodies.  The Minister can designate by regulation other persons or organisations as relevant bodies to whom an application for information may be made.</p><p>I appreciate the importance of terminology and, in response to stakeholders' submissions during the pre-legislative process, the term "mother" is now used throughout the Bill to signify the person who gave birth.</p><p>Some of the definitions in this Part were amended on foot of Deputies' contributions on Committee Stage.  For instance, the definition of an adopted person has been amended to ensure absolute clarity that any child born in Ireland and adopted abroad is included in this legislation.  While this was always the intention, I understand that, in some cases, private arrangements were made without the involvement of an accredited body or the Adoption Authority of Ireland.  The definition now ensures that, in all cases, a child born in Ireland who was sent for adoption abroad is included in the application of this legislation.</p><p>Part 2 provides for the release of information, records and provided items to relevant persons on application.  A relevant person who has attained the age of 16 years can apply to the General Register Office or a relevant body for his or her birth certificate and it will be provided to him or her.  A relevant person aged 18 years and over can apply to a relevant body for his or her birth, early life, care, incorrect birth registration and medical information, as well as any provided item, and it will be provided to him or her.  A person's medical records &ndash; as held on adoption &ndash; and institutional files will be released to him or her without restriction.  A relevant person aged 16 or 17 years can apply to the Adoption Authority for his or her birth information, early life, care and medical information held by the authority or the agency and this will be provided to him or her by means of a supportive meeting.  This meeting can be conducted by phone or face to face and the young person can be accompanied by a person of his or her choosing, if the young person so wishes.</p><p>Section 17 provides for an information session to be held between the relevant person and a designated person where there is an application for a birth certificate or birth information and a parent named within the birth information has recorded a preference for no contact.  The information session can be held by means of a short, sensitive phone call or in person, depending on the preference of the applicant.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That conversation will be about the entitlement of the relevant person to his or her birth certificate or birth information and the fact that the parent has registered a preference for no contact and that this constitutes an exercise by the parent of his or her right to privacy.  As mentioned earlier, this information session plays an essential role in adequately balancing constitutional and EU rights so as to guarantee the full release of information to the applicant in all cases.  Again, nothing will be redacted or held back.</p><p>Part 3 of the Bill provides for an application by a person for his or her deceased parent's information and records where that parent was a relevant person.  Such persons can apply for their parent's birth certificate, birth information, care information, early life information and incorrect birth registration information and that will be released to them in cases where the parent, who is the relevant person, and grandparents are deceased.  They can also apply for their parent's and other genetic relatives' medical information and that will be released to them where it is of substantial benefit to the maintenance or management of the person's health.  The development and inclusion of this Part is in response to my consultations with those affected by these issues and also issues raised through the pre-legislative scrutiny process.</p><p>Part 4 creates a legislative basis for the provision of birth, early life, care, incorrect birth registration and medical information to the next of kin of a relevant person who died as a child in an institution.  This next of kin is defined, in order of hierarchy, as a mother or father, brother or sister, uncle or aunt, nephew or niece.  This Part is also a major new addition and I hope that it supports those with questions in relation to a relative who passed away in a mother and baby home or a county home.</p><p>Part 5 provides for a tracing service to be delivered by Tusla and the Adoption Authority.  Traces will be carried out for the purposes of contact or sharing of information.  The tracing service is available to persons aged 18 and over.  An application for a tracing service can be made by a relevant person and certain relatives.  An adoptive parent of an adopted child can also seek a trace where the adoptive parent is seeking further information in relation to the person.  Section 34(6) lists bodies from whom Tusla and the Adoption Authority can request information in order to trace a person and who must provide the requested information.  This list includes Departments and religious organisations.  These statutory provisions will enable Tusla and the Adoption Authority to deliver an effective and efficient tracing service for persons seeking family information or family contact.</p><p>This Part also contains important new provisions for a specialist tracing service for persons whose birth was illegally registered.  These respond to the recommendations of the Special Rapporteur on Child Protection in his recent report on this matter.  The new provisions provide a statutory basis for the review of files.  They also empower a person to request that Tusla or the authority use their tracing powers to ascertain whether the person's birth was illegally registered or not.  This will mean that a thorough review and inquiry can happen for those people who have reason to believe that their birth was illegally registered and I hope this will finally provide insight and answers to people.</p><p>Part 6 provides for a statutory register called the contact preference register.  This register, which is to be established and maintained by the Adoption Authority, allows persons to register their contact and information sharing preferences.  Relevant persons and their relatives can also use the register to lodge information and provided items that they wish to be shared with a specified individual.  This Part also provides for the full transfer of all information and preferences from the existing non-statutory register established by the authority in 2005 to the new register to be established under this Part.</p><p>Part 7 provides that prescribed bodies, termed "information sources", must safeguard any relevant records they hold.  An information source other than Tusla can be asked by the Adoption Authority to furnish a statement to the authority which will state the nature, current location and condition of the relevant records held.  They can also be required to transfer these records to the Adoption Authority.</p><p>Part 8 amends the Succession Act 1965 and expands that law so that persons whose birth is illegally registered will have the same rights of inheritance from the family they grew up in as they have from their birth family.  This is required because in the case of an illegal birth registration no adoption order was made and, therefore, the persons always retained their inheritance rights from their birth family.  This Part is urgently required to provide certainty to persons impacted, ensuring that they can inherit from their social parents and not be disadvantaged by virtue of their birth being illegally registered.</p><p>Part 9 also contains new, specific measures to address issues related to illegal birth registration.  It amends the Civil Registration Act 2004 to provide for the General Registrar to receive or request certain information concerning people with an illegal birth registration, to correct an affected person's birth registration and to create a separate registration in a new register that reflects the affected person's social identity.  By social identity, I mean the name of the relevant individuals and their social parents as recorded on their incorrect birth registration.</p><p>Part 10 deals with other matters, including: the requirement that the Adoption Authority shall undertake a public information campaign; offences for the concealment or destruction of records; provisions clearly setting out any GDPR rights affected; and the provisions on counselling for all relevant persons and parents.</p><p>Section 59 in Part 10 also contains another important provision for persons affected by illegal birth registration which I brought as an amendment on Committee Stage.  It provides assurances that contracts, legal documents and any acts undertaken in good faith prior to the passing of the legislation and-or before the affected persons discovered that they were incorrectly registered will not be invalidated or that the persons affected will not experience any adverse consequences simply because they were subject of an incorrect birth registration.</p><p>I look forward to hearing the views of Members of the Seanad and working with them to bring forward the best possible legislation so that those who need it can access effective information and tracing services.  As I have outlined, the Bill addresses many of the issues impacting directly on the lives of people affected by illegal birth registrations, people to whom I have made an apology on behalf of the Government today.  This legislation is designed, and has been amended, to specifically include issues raised by the Special Rapporteur on Child Protection, Professor Conor O'Mahony, in terms of addressing the needs of those who know they were the subject of an illegal birth registration but also the many people who suspect that they were the subject of an illegal birth registration.  I ask Senators to support the passage of this Bill and I commend it to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#RRR00200"><p>I thank the Minister.  As a member of a party in government and as the leader of the Green Party in the Seanad, it is appropriate for me to join the Minister in apologising.  I would also like to hear apologies from the other parties in government, which I am sure they will join with me in making.  </p> <p>Fundamentally, what lies behind this is a denial of rights that has been going on for decades.  The campaign has also been going on for decades and while this is an historic day, it does not change much of the hurt that this illegality has caused.  It is not just the hurt of not knowing where one has come from but also the generational impact on all of those who come after a person who is impacted by illegal birth registration.  All of the healthcare that people have received over generations has been impacted but now, finally, there will be a vindication of their rights and that is very welcome.</p> <p>It is important to put on the record my thanks to those who have campaigned for decades to get to this point.  I also express my thanks to all of the members of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth, who have done extensive pre-legislative scrutiny of this Bill.  An unprecedented amount of work has gone into this Bill, both by committee members and by stakeholders including the Clann Project and the Adoption Rights Alliance, who appeared before the committee.  The fact that 1,200 amendments were submitted on Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il speaks volumes.  We will go through our own Committee Stage in the Seanad but given that the average number of amendments submitted per year is 4,500, the figure of 1,200 is significant and shows how much all of us want to get this right.  There were 83 recommendations from the Oireachtas committee.  The Minister engaged with the committee extensively and in order to avoid any delays, a mere month after the pre-legislative scrutiny concluded, he brought this legislation to the D&aacute;il.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pauline O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=PaulineOreilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I think that it is important to show how urgent this legislation is but in the past there have been delays.  A couple of Ministers had attempted to do something similar, and it is fair to say that was the subject of some of the recommendations made by the committee.  One of the recommendations concerned a veto, which was quite a significant issue for those who are adopted, that allows, as had been possibly suggested, for parents to have a veto.  I think that this matter has been addressed.  We must strike a balance between the right to identity and privacy, which is what the information session is there to do,  but there have been many changes by the Minister as he took on board the views of the members of the committee, and the hundreds of the people with whom the Minister has engaged who are impacted by this legislation, in order to arrive at an information session that is appropriate in the circumstances.  I will discuss further on Committee Stage.</p><p>It has been shown that the legalistic language, which is used in legislation, is quite inappropriate for the legacy issues that we face in this country.  It has been shown that it distances people from legislation that has a major impact on their lives.  The term "birth mother" was used in the original legislation.  There was strong opposition to the term and the Minister responded to this matter.  I do not like using the phrase "to commend the Minister" because on a matter like this, it is an absolute duty for the Minister, which I think he recognises.</p><p>I will not speak for much longer because it is important that we discuss issues in detail on Committee Stage.  I have outlined the most essential issues that have been discussed, having looked through the debates.  We will discuss many other smaller pieces, which the Minister has taken on board as he has tabled amendments and engaged on Report Stage.</p><p>Finally, I say to everyone who is listening to this debate that there is nothing that I can say that will right the wrongs that have been done but I hope that people feel that we have made progress.  It is not the end of the line but this legislation will enable people to access records that they never could access before.  Gaining access was an unequivocal underlying fundamental job for this legislation and that has been done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#SS00200"><p>I warmly welcome the people seated in both of the Galleries of this House because this legislation is about them, their families, their past, their lives and their circumstances.  We all need and require our identity and it is very important to each one of us.</p> <p>As I have told this House before, I am one of seven children and I originally come from the lovely Grangecon, County Wicklow and the borders of Athy, County Kildare.  Through no circumstance of either of my parents my siblings and I were all brought up in care.  I did not know until I was five or seven years of age that I had brothers and sisters.  With the will of my parents, who sought to bring their children up as they thought best, they resisted any stress and pressure to allow us to be adopted.  Indeed, my name was Kenneth Boyhan but as there was another boy in care called Kenneth I was called Victor.  I am glad of that because I feel that I have stepped into the word, "Victor", and I would not want anybody to take it away from me now.  I use that example to explain how strange it can be about one's sense of identity.  When I became a Senator and applied for a diplomatic passport, an embassy official contacted me to say that was not the name they had.  That simple example shows how important our identity is to us.</p> <p>I cannot say that I had a sad or bad life.  I can say that through efforts, not by social services nor the State but by others, my siblings and I maintained contact.  Not a week went by that I did not speak to all of my siblings.  So history, origin, heritage and identity are really important to people but it takes strong parents or guardians to fight sometimes to retain contact with their children.  The lesson to be learned from all that is that it actually works.</p> <p>To those who are here today and to all of the other people who are listening in here, I am not going to respond to the apology because it is not my place or experience and, therefore, it would not be right for me to respond in any way other than to thank the Minister for making an apology in the House.  The apology will take time.  The people who heard it today will have heard it for the first time.  Indeed, I assure the people outside of this House that I, and I do not think any other Member of this House, were aware of the content of the apology until the Minister put it on the record here today although we were aware that it would happen today.  Language and timing is so important when one talks about ourselves.  I thank the people who went on this journey with us over the years.  The people who shared their experiences with us had to put into the public domain things they did not really want people to hear and had to tell people about their circumstances.  Many of us blend into our community.  When you think about it, people do not really know that much about any of us but somehow, all of this has been painful.</p> <p>I wish to state to the Minister that identity is important and the legality of the actions of others is important too.  To suggest that the St. Patrick's Guild was the only institution involved in the illegal registration of births would be foolish and wrong.  There were many adoptive arrangements within families, as well as inter-family arrangements.  There were many different traditions in this country and different religious organisations were involved.  Indeed, I grew up with many people who were adopted and still do not know anything about their past.  They cannot get anything about their papers or anything.  Consequently, it would be foolish to single out one institution in this State and suggest that it was solely, and wholly, the only institution that did this and there are issues in that regard.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for engaging with Oireachtas Members and thank the committee for all of the work it did on this legislation.  Access to a range of information is critically important to us, and it is important to have this feature in the Bill.</p> <p>Early life information is an issue that the Minister touched on here today.  It has been broadly defined in this Bill as being the place where the person resided and the dates of that residency; where applicable, information relating to his or her baptism or any other ceremony of a religious or spiritual nature; information on medical treatments, procedures or vaccinations administered; information on whether a person, being a parent or other genetic relative of him or her, visited or inquired in relation to him or her.  That is quite profound because I know of many instances where birth parents went to institutions, which were run, managed and overseen by this State, yet were denied access to their children.  They were told that their children had been adopted and not to stand in the way of a better life and better opportunities for their children.  Those parents walked away thinking that that was going to happen.  There are a lot of issues related to these matters but it is important that we move forward.</p> <p>The Bill states that the relevant bodies, including the Adoption Authority of Ireland and Tusla "shall, to the extent that it is practicable to do so", provide early life information to relevant persons of age 18 and over.  I have something of an issue with that qualification and may table an amendment.  The tracing service is important.  I believe that the Minister has been honourable in his dealings here.  He has been fiercely committed and a wonderful advocate.  However, he has had to learn himself.  He has gone on this journey over the last two years and come a long way.  I do not doubt his commitment to get this legislation right.</p> <p>On the face of things, and subject to a few possible amendments, I support this Bill because I believe that it is the right thing to do.  This week, I will be 61 years of age.  As I came in here today I thought about how I never thought that I would be somewhere like here talking about tracing and legislation.  I support this Bill because it is the right thing to do.  We owe this legislation to people but the process will be difficult and there will be many bridges to cross.  There will be many people hurt and disappointed.  In some cases they will not be surprised because much of this has been wrapped in denial, but it is a real journey.  This is really important legislation in terms of identity.</p> <p>In conclusion, I thank the people who shared their personal stories and the hundreds of people who have participated on &ldquo;Prime Time&rdquo;.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I recognised one lady, from her television appearance more than anything else, and said hello to her.  They were brave, courageous people.  They had to tell their partners.  Sometimes people were married for years and they never talked about their secrets, as they called them.  I support the Bill.  It is the right thing to do.  I acknowledge the importance of the Minister's apology but it is not for any of us to accept that apology.  It is for the individuals, and that is going to take time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#TT00200"><p>I thank Senator Boyhan for his contribution.  Coming from where he has come and given what he said of his journey, how he never imagined he would be in here when he was in one of the mother and baby homes and how he has ultimately ended up in Seanad &Eacute;ireann speaking on legislation that affects so many people, I think it fitting and appropriate he take the Chair for the remainder of the session.  I call on him to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#TT00300"><p>I thank colleagues and thank the Cathaoirleach for his words there.  I call on Senator McGreehan to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#TT00400"><p>Go raibh maith agat a Chathaoirligh Gn&iacute;omhaigh.  The Minister is very welcome to the House.  It is a really important day.  We all know this Bill is long overdue.  I am nervous about this contribution because it is so important.  We have really important people with us today and I acknowledge their presence.  We do not have enough of them, to be honest.  I am distracted by the Minister's apology.  I am also distracted by the fact there are very few people in our Visitors Gallery today when it should be overflowing with people who have been affected by illegal birth registrations.  They do not want to be here.  They have continuously worked hard to try to find resolutions to the situation.  While the Minister's apology is offered in such good faith and is genuine, today is not an appropriate day for it.  I am sorry to be that dissenting voice but today is about a Bill.  It is the Second Stage of a really historic Bill.  It is about information and tracing and getting the Bill through this House.  I genuinely feel the apology should have been made by itself, to acknowledge the severity and the trauma those illegal birth registrations have caused those people in the Visitors Gallery today.  For what it is worth, I am sorry there was not more work done before this apology.  I was disappointed there was only 24 hours' notice given.  There are many people from all over the country and abroad who were not able to make it here.  I will leave it at that because I want to acknowledge the importance of the apology but also the upset and the fact the State is not ready for that apology just yet.</p> <p>Returning to the legislation, which is all we should be speaking about today, it is landmark and a game-changer for people's identity.  It fundamentally addresses the needs of adopted people and people who have questions about their origin of birth.  It will achieve this through the guaranteed provision of full and unredacted birth certificates, birth and early care information, the statutory tracing service, the contact preference register and the safeguarding of all the adoption-related records.  All this is so good.  We have done really well.  I commend my fellow Senator, Senator Seery Kearney, who worked tirelessly on this Bill, and all members of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth.  Blood, sweat and an awful lot of tears went into this Bill in working with all stakeholders, listening to the heartache and the trauma and people's lived experience of their lives being turned upside down and inside out and having to deliver their most intimate details to us, in public and in private.  As such, today is a really important day for this Bill.  I am very proud to have played a little part as a cog in bringing change for so many people.</p> <p>I am not going to speak about the detail of the Bill because we are going to go through it in fine detail on Committee Stage.  There is an awful lot of discussion to be had on that Stage.  Today I am emotional and I am also distracted by that apology.  We should not be distracted by an apology.  We should be concentrating on this Bill to apologise for the desperate wrongs that were done.  The State knew about them from the 1950s and had evidence of them from the early 1990s but failed to act.  I am sorry for that but it is not for me to be sorry.  I again acknowledge the faces I have met from the In It Together and Who Am I? groups that are not here today.  I hope they are watching because I know the Minister is genuine in his apology, but it was misplaced today.</p> <p>Again, I really commend this Bill to the House.  It is a game-changer for people who have been abused and mistreated for generations and decades.  The Bill will, I hope, create the framework that will allow people start to trust in our institutions again.  The Minister well knows the stories of trauma from people who have had to engage with the Adoption Authority of Ireland and with Tusla.  They felt they were asking for a kidney and not just information.  They felt like they owed Tusla something to get their information and they begged for that information.  Today is the start of that framework.  I hope the framework builds that trust so we can stand tall in our systems and show people their legacy and their trauma mean something and that change will come because of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#TT00500"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House.  We stand in a quite magnificent room that carries with it a whole heap of history and magnificence.  Am I proud and do I think it appropriate our Government would issue an apology in the surroundings of the Seanad, given the honour this noble House has?  I so.  Do I agree with it?  I do not.</p> <p>The Minister has done an extraordinary amount.  He is no small cog.  He has been a big cog and that is possibly the only thing I disagree with.  From his coming into office, the Minister has driven forward on the mother and baby homes, the Birth Information and Tracing Bill and the institutional burials.  I have worked very closely with him.  He is a very fine Minister and deserves to issue the apology.  However, the people in the Gallery and the people who could not be here because of the short notice deserved that the apology come from the Taoiseach on behalf of the State and be delivered on the floor of the D&aacute;il.  In that respect, I disagree with it.  I find it very hard to say those words to the Minister because I am conscious of how hard he works and how committed and passionate he is about inclusion.  Nevertheless, I disagree with it being done in this House and know of the hurt it has caused.  It behoves us to ensure the needs are absolutely met and in that regard, I wish it was the Taoiseach who did so on the floor of the D&aacute;il.  That said, this is a forum whereby we can depart from the usual formalities.  It is a forum that has hosted many unusual debates and we are surrounded by colleagues who have also shared their personal experience.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I cannot imagine what it must feel like to experience the pain of the consequence of a deliberate illegal act, orchestrated and facilitated by an institution in which people were born, to deny them their identity, nor what it must feel like to hear that information as a grown adult.  At times, that information was imparted to people in the most inappropriate of surroundings and in the most inappropriate way.  I have heard Mr. Bernard Gloster address that on behalf of Tusla, but mistakes were made along the way that should also be included in an apology for the additional pain and hurt caused to people.</p><p>The State has known for certain since 2018 that, at the very least, 151 people had their births illegally registered.  The independent reviewer's report, taking just a small sample, leads to believe that the figure is in excess of 20,000.  The report in question is that compiled by Professor Conor O'Mahony.  Those who have been identified are only the tip of the iceberg of what is yet to come.  The Minister quoted Professor O'Mahony's report.  In the context of recommending that an apology be given to victims of illegal birth registration, Professor O'Mahony stated that apologies will carry little weight unless they are "backed up by practical measures to remedy the rights violation in question."  I agree with the Minister that there are many measures within the Bill, and within the amendments he brought forward in the D&aacute;il, that go further than we had originally imagined.  They certainly meet many of the recommendations in the pre-legislative scrutiny report of the children's committee.</p><p>Nevertheless, we need to go further.  I recognise in the Minister's response to the recommendations scope for further consideration by the Government and I ask that we consider that.  Professor O'Mahony's recommendations are very realistic in that we should build on the work of the independent reviewer and follow up on the files marked as suspicious in the course of that review.  I acknowledge the Minister will install a specialist tracing team, which very much mirrors the recommendations in the report.  Even so, it appears that tracing team, although I am open to correction, will act in response to an individual rather than proactively address what the UN rights bodies have repeatedly recommended, namely, a full investigation into illegal adoptions in Ireland.  This concerns not only the people in the Public Gallery and their very identity but also their families, children and descendants and the stories of all their lives, although they are not just stories.  They are lived experiences that demand a response and we need to go further.  I appreciate the logic of getting the Bill passed and working hard to ensure we get the mechanisms up and running - I completely agree with the Minister in that regard, but we also need scope such that there can be more and there will be more because there is a shamefulness that needs to be exposed, addressed and dealt with comprehensively.  The Minister used the word "illegality".  Illegality is distinguished from unlawfulness.  The latter is a civil act, whereas illegality is equated with criminality, and there have to be appropriate responses.</p><p>This brings me to a place of worrying about the statute of limitations and other such matters.  Who will we prosecute and how will we prove collusion?  Were innocent people unknowingly led along because they believed the religious orders and institutions could not possibly do something so appalling?  In that context, I am in favour of the establishment, with some modification, of a truth commission, a proposition put forward by Professor O'Mahony, in order that we will get out the truth without having to worry about the statute of limitations.  We need to gather all the existing records of which we are not in control as a State because, fundamentally, I do not trust them being in the hands of anyone other than the State, although I appreciate that Tusla has been in an awkward position over recent years.  Since the GDPR was introduced, there should have been a comprehensive response, although I have heard the Minister say that on a number of occasions, which I welcome.</p><p>I will fully support the Bill.  I am disappointed, and I believe we are storing up trouble for ourselves in this regard, about the recommendation regarding registered letters.  If the  Minister were to roll his eyes at that, I would empathise with him, but I am disappointed that the information requirement, the balance of constitutional rights and the State vindicating the right to privacy will not be dealt with by a registered letter.  The provision for a phone call is problematic.  What will happen if people do not accept the call?  Will they get a phone call when they are on their own?  How will we ensure they have support?  At least if it is a large package arriving, which the person will have been expecting and which will come as registered post, that can be opened with the support of someone else.  If it will stand for evidence in the High Court, I do not see why it could not have worked.  Nevertheless, I understand the Minister is working within the advice of the Attorney General.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#UU00200"><p>I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#UU00300"><p>We will deal with many other issues on Committee Stage.  For today, I join with the apology, as my party&rsquo;s spokesperson on children and as a Government colleague, and I apologise for the grave hurt these people have been caused, which can never be undone and in respect of which they can never be fully consoled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#UU00400"><p>I welcome both the Minister and our guests in the Public Gallery.  These are their Houses and they are very welcome here.  I welcome also those who are watching the debate from elsewhere.</p> <p>The apology the Minister made on behalf of the State is welcome.  I have no doubt it will have been a difficult moment for many people.  It has come on the same day we have learned that no agreement has been reached with the religious orders in regard to contributing towards redress for survivors of mother and baby homes.  As my party colleague, Deputy Funchion, pointed out, it is deeply worrying that we cannot compel in law religious orders that so willingly took public funds to run these horrendous institutions to contribute towards redress.  Having welcomed our guests to the Public Gallery, I commend those who have shared their stories.  I also commend my colleague, Senator Boyhan, on his work in this area and on placing his personal experience into the public domain.  Many of those who have shared their stories publicly will have watched the D&aacute;il debates and the committee proceedings as Members and colleagues worked through the legislation.  The significance of the matter is not lost on any of us in the Houses and we will continue to work to ensure victims and survivors are heard.  As the Minister and Senator Seery Kearney noted, it is well recognised that apologies will carry little weight unless they are backed up by practical responses to remedy the rights violation in question.  We have to ensure State apologies are backed up by action.</p> <p>Despite several attempts to address the issue through legislation, we continue to operate a closed and secretive structure when adopted people seek to access their birth and early life information.  Currently, all adoptive files are held at various locations, most notably within Tusla, which is extremely problematic for some survivors.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some are held by the adoption authority, county councils, religious orders, hospitals and various adoption agencies.  There is no statutory right for adopted persons to access birth records, adoption files or any records relating to them.</p><p>It is important to remember that the right to information and the prospect of a relationship with natural family members are two separate matters.  There is no evidence that natural mothers sought privacy from their children.  In reality, the opposite is true.  However, this myth has permeated adoption services, including State, church and private adoption agencies, with devastating consequences.  It is clear there is an urgent need to legislate for the provision of information and tracing in two key areas.  All adopted people should have full and unfettered access to their adoption and care arrangement records and any other relevant information.  Provision must also be given to the establishment of an independent and central archive or agency to facilitate the efficient and judicious sharing of information.  The State has consistently failed adopted people in this country and although the recent mother and baby homes report has brought the matter into sharp focus again, we must remain cognisant that this is a matter affecting all people who have been adopted in this country and any legislation must reflect that.</p><p>I commend the members of the children's committee who are here.  I served on the committee for four years from 2016.  The committee published a comprehensive report in December 2021 in which it made 83 key recommendations on matters such as language and terminology, the mandatory information session and the express need to provide unrestricted access to information and resources, including the creation of a new agency.</p><p>Sinn F&eacute;in understands that balancing the identity rights of applicants and the privacy rights of birth and natural parents is difficult.  I know this topic has generated the most lengthy discussions in the D&aacute;il and in committee.  Sinn F&eacute;in has pushed the position that despite the legislation making more advances than has been previously attempted - I commend the Minister on that - more must be done to ensure unfettered access of applicants to birth records, adoption files or any records relating to them.</p><p>Mandatory information sessions remain in all but name, but the removal of any requirement for an information session is paramount.  The Minister has argued that this element must be included to balance the rights of birth and natural mothers' privacy if a no-contact preference has been recorded.  I note that the Oireachtas joint committee in its deliberations proposed an alternative in that a registered letter could be sent to applicants outlining their obligations in the case of a preference for no contact to respect the birth or natural mother's expressed wishes.  Sinn F&eacute;in still holds the view that this should be the position.  We are cognisant that changes have been made by the Minister and the Government has made some key concessions with this legislation.  However, this extremely contentious mandatory information session remains.</p><p>We are pleased the Minister has amended the question around medical information and the Bill now allows family medical information to be released to adopted people and a person's family without the intervention of a GP.  We acknowledge these advances but we cannot support the legislation in its current form.  Any alternative proposals to legislate in this area must not leave one adopted person behind.  This is a human rights matter.  Ireland has been in breach of adopted persons' human rights dating right back to the foundation of the State.  The Minister indicated in his closing remarks that he looks forward to working with Senators in bringing forward the best possible legislation.  We will do that with him in good faith.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#VV00200"><p>I thank the Acting Chairperson for sharing his own experience and stories so eloquently.  I also thank the Minister for coming to the House to discuss the Bill with us.  I pay tribute to him, and I know it is not something he hears often coming from Opposition politicians, even in the friendlier of the two Houses, namely, the Seanad.  It bears saying that the Minister has done important and difficult work in this area and nobody could question his intention around it.  It is beyond time to see this matter being progressed.</p> <p>There is no doubt that the Minister's apology on behalf of the Government is welcome, but we have had apologies before in the D&aacute;il from Governments of the recent past but those apologies should be the beginning and not the end of the work that must be done to compensate for the mistakes made and damage wrought on people's lives.  This is not to take away from the Minister's words but it is incumbent on the Taoiseach to offer a full apology and give the opportunity to those directly affected to be in attendance when that happens.</p> <p>It is only appropriate and right that we would take a moment to thank the people who should never have had to fight as hard and as long as they have, namely, the survivors of the mother and baby homes.  I know some of them are here tonight, and I thank them.  We stand with them and we will work really hard with the Minister to try to ensure we get this right.  I also take a moment to acknowledge and recognise the experience of a former Labour leader and T&aacute;naiste, former Deputy Joan Burton, and her own adoption experience and journey.  It took over three decades for Joan to find out her information.  She was in her 50s at the time, had graduated, married, given birth and served as a Deputy and Minister before she found the information she sought.  She has spoken openly and eloquently many times about her experience, which I recognise today as well.</p> <p>So much pain and cruelty was visited upon these women, their children and their families, and it was all State-sanctioned.  As somebody who was not even born when most of these places were in operation, I feel a deep sadness and, to be very honest, an enormous amount of shame when I stand in a room speaking on this matter.  I am aware the decisions made, perhaps in this room or the Lower House, political and governmental decisions, led us to this.  It is beholden on all of us as legislators as we go about our work today to consider every decision we make not only within the context of our personal or political beliefs but what our decisions, taken in these rooms, might mean for the lives of every one of our fellow citizens.  I doubt many of the Deputies, Senators or decision makers at that time thought that future generations of lawmakers would be here so many decades later unpicking the work they did and trying to provide redress for the pain arising from their role.  This Bill is an important reminder that although we cannot future-proof every decision, we must strive to ensure that, in the present, everything we do is grounded in the needs of people, care and compassion for people.  Our work must be done in congruence with people's wishes.</p> <p>I have a couple of questions and observations, although I do not know if the Minister will have the opportunity to respond.  Many of us in the Labour Party have spoken with survivors in mother and baby homes and people placed for adoption.  A wide spectrum of people have been affected by this.  Something that arose was a sense of confusion and sometimes hurt and bewilderment about some of the language used in this Bill.  Some people have expressed those feelings about use of terms such as "social parents" and maybe the use of the term "adoptive parent".  That is for some people; it is not for everyone.  I can only reflect the experience of the people we have spoken with.</p> <p>There are many questions about the resources that will be given to rolling out the provisions in the Bill, where they will come from and what will be used.  The Minister repeatedly referred to the &euro;800 million scheme, but people really want to conceptualise or understand what this will mean for each person.  That might be an impossible question to answer but people want to know what it means on an individual basis.  The &euro;800 million is a figure and it does not relate to people's lives and experiences.  I appreciate the Minister may not be able to give an answer but it is something we must think about.  What does this mean and how will this affect people individually?  We must highlight that there is a group of older people who have never been able to access any information on their birth.</p> <p>Following the publication of this Bill, Deputy Bacik, on behalf of the Labour Party, expressed her concerns about some aspects of the legislation.  The Minister and the Deputy went through these concerns in the Lower House.  Survivors of mother and baby county homes and all adopted persons have been waiting decades for recognition of the right to information on their identity.  Campaigners have been crying out for legislation to provide them with access to birth certificates and information about their adoption and origins.  This is something many of us in the Labour Party have worked hard to achieve.  In early 2021, we published legislation to facilitate information and tracing for adopted persons and challenged the Government to make good on the commitment to make good on the commitment to do the same.  I recognise that the Minister has responded positively to those calls.</p> <p>Deputy Bacik, on behalf of the Labour Party and in conjunction with other Members of the Houses and witnesses, participated extensively in pre-legislative scrutiny of the legislation before us.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Annie Hoey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AnnieHoey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Labour Party will be submitting amendments to this legislation.  I look forward to engaging with the Minister in good faith on those.  When the Bill was going through the other House there were concerns about retention of the controversial information session for those seeking information about their origins.  The joint committee had recommended the deletion of any requirement for a meeting or information session so it is disappointing to see that some form of information provision session has been retained in the revised Bill.  I echo Senator Warfield's call that full unfettered information be made available and that there be a central archive.  I still have not fully got my head around the idea that there are bits and pieces of information still scattered around the place for something so serious that effects so many lives.  It is not good enough that this information is still in so many depositories.  A central archive would be crucial.<br/><br/>It is vital to listen to those who will be most directly affected by this legislation and the wishes of survivors and adopted persons must be heard.  We have an awful lot left to do and unfortunately, in this area, time is not necessarily on our side.I will conclude with the words of my Labour Party colleague, Joan Burton who said:</p><blockquote>	I will welcome the public apologies and justifiable redress schemes.  I will welcome even more the essential law reforms that must come as the true memorial to Ireland&rsquo;s banished babies. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#WW00200"><p>Others have spoken of how some feel the apology was too soon as it came without sufficient notice.  There is also a strong case that it has also come very late from the State.  I do not think that this will be the only apology.  We are in a period when there cannot only be indications from the Government, the State and its institutions of a message of apology and regret but also a determination to act and change and that it will act both forwards and backwards in the delivery of justice.  An apology is not the same thing as accountability and accountability is still badly needed in this area.  It could be the truth commission recommended by Mr. John O'Mahony or the investigation of systemic practices that could be illegal or practices that were criminal, and known to be criminal, at the time.</p> <p>I say the apology is a little late because it is regrettable that it has been such a battle at every single stage to get every small improvement.  I glanced back today at an old headline in a newspaper.  It was 2017 or 2018 when myself and Senator Ruane, who was a member of the joint committee on children, were accused of terribly delaying something badly needed because we raised the idea of the veto and the idea of an automatic assumed opt-out on contact.  It was an assumption of non-contact, not even a veto, that was stated before.  We were told that we were questioning the Attorney General's advice at the time and it was wrong.  It was post-GDPR and it was wrong.  That is why it is difficult for us.  We have been speaking about GDPR and the Minister has probably grappled with it more than most by now.  It has been painful to have to push it again and again on each piece and to say "No"; people have rights.  Those rights are there in European law.  Yes, the State needs to vindicate, support and deliver those rights but it must also ensure that in no way does it ever attempt to dilute, supplant, corral or limit them.  The Minister will be aware that there is still considerable concern about those areas.  The fact that only certain bodies are being named as having to give subject access requests and are information sources means we must ask where it leaves all the other bodies which have information that individuals may wish to seek an access request and to which they are entitled to access under the GDPR Act under subject access requests.  There has to be absolute clarity in the Bill as it leaves this House that there is no question but that this is a cul-de-sacing of people's rights to information into limited areas.</p> <p>There is some regret around the Minister's power to designate new relevant bodies under the Act.  We know there are a lot of very relevant bodies but at the moment there is a very limited list of relevant bodies and in terms of primary and secondary sources.  It is quite a narrow list and there are obvious omissions and entities that clearly should be there.  The Minister will understand that while we may have faith in him that he intends to designate all the relevant bodies, as legislators and people who have been waiting a long time, we want to see as much of that as possible in the legislation at the outset, while making it clear that the list is not exclusive or closed.</p> <p>Others have noted that it is good that it has moved from the very closed system and the assumption of non-contact and the kind of stigma that was in the rationale as was evident even from the officials who spoke on it at the time.  It is good that we have progressed beyond that but equally it is still the case that persons who are adopted face a different obstacles to getting their birth certificate than any other person in the State.  That remains a concern.  The registered letter was put forward but the Bill should really say that everyone should get information.  If you are getting a birth certificate, that is a person's information.  In a way, it is not related to contact.  There is a question about general public information.  If a person is seeking contact, there is a register where they can inquire as to whether a relative has requested non-contact but that is a discussion that is relative to the point about contact.  There is still an argument as to whether it is relevant at all to someone's personal information.  </p> <p>There are still some gaps and concerns around relevant records definitions that the Minister will be aware of.  Take care information, which is very blunt.  It is just what the arrangements were.  It does not have that texture about what was the care.  Were there reports?  Were you one of the children who, say, inspectors identified?  Were you treated well or badly?  Is there a record of concern about your care?  It relates to all the texture of that care information.  Then there is early life information.  I have raised a point with the Minister and I am disappointed to see that it is still in the Bill.  I know there is information about medical treatment and so on but I find it extraordinarily cruel that in the "early life information" that the section includes "information on whether any person, being a parent or other genetic relative of him or her, visited or inquired in relation to him or her, which information includes the degree of relationship of the other person to him or her, but does not include the name of the other person".  To learn that someone inquired about you at this point and to not know who that person was seems cruel.  There is not even the proviso that the person might have put themselves on a register of not wanting contact.  That element is unacceptable and goes back to the drip-feeding of tiny clues about people's lives that they have had to struggle with as they get these little scraps of information to try to put together a picture of their early lives and maybe the lives of their parents.</p> <p>I am concerned about the definitions of qualifying relatives and genetic relatives.  There is a definition of genetic relatives in the Bill.  However, where a relative wants to access information, they are limited in many cases to accessing information in relation to a relevant person who is deceased.  There is a qualification that they be the next of kin.  It seems that under the Bill a sibling would not be able to seek information if there was a parent still alive who was not seeking such information.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These are the nuances that matter hugely.  It is fundamental that we do not place people into a labyrinth and that we recognise that error.  The immunity points are very important.  I know that it is immunity going forward, but it must be made very clear that there is no immunity retrospectively.  However, I am concerned that relevant bodies which may omit information can claim not to have acted in bad faith, because we know that some of these bodies have systematically hidden and blocked information in the past.  I would not want anything to allow them to have a potential immunity in the future if they continue to block access to important information.  We must ensure there is no defence for those actions going forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#XX00200"><p>I also acknowledge how you spoke, Acting Chair, about your own experience.  Hopefully, that will mean an awful lot to people listening today as well.</p> <p>This is an historic day.  The Birth Information and Tracing Bill means that all adopted children can now access records.  As the Minister clearly states, in all cases, any child that was born in Ireland that was sent abroad is included under the legislation.  That is crucial.  The law that we make today is having such an impact on so many people's lives.  I acknowledge the people who are with us today in the Visitors Gallery, and in the Houses of the Oireachtas, but also everyone who is watching the proceedings as well.</p> <p>We are looking at how we can offer justice for the abuse, stigma and shame that has led to the illegal birth registrations.  It begins with an apology from the State.  However, we need practical help and support and that is what this Bill begins to do, to provide access.  This impact is on women and children mainly.  It was women, back in the 1940s and 1950s, who had to endure incredible ignominy and shame that led to them living their lives in shame in society, families and in institutions.  Following the Minister's apology, we must stand up now and shine a light.  That is what has been done.  It has been a very difficult process.</p> <p>The Minister has visited the mother and baby home in Tuam.  He has given time to people.  It has been an extremely harrowing process for the people and families involved.  So many people have come forward and engaged with the process, but my thoughts are with people who have not yet spoken - older men and women that have never spoken about this.  I am very conscious that anyone who is listening would be aware that there are supports provided by the HSE and Connect counselling.  Counselling is nearly always the first step to how we engage with the issue and this Bill speaks about counselling.</p> <p>The purpose of the Bill is to correct the birth register and to have an accurate record, so that there is a tracing service delivered by the State and that genealogical expertise will be available.  I very much acknowledge the pre-legislative scrutiny by colleagues in the Seanad and in the D&aacute;il as well.  The Minister has taken that into account in the amendments he has introduced in terms of the balance that must be struck with the preference of parents.  What is crucial about this Bill in a very practical way is the access to medical information for people who have never had that access.</p> <p>The Minister refers to next of kin in the Bill, many of whom may be deceased at this stage.  Brothers, sisters, cousins, nephews and nieces are also mentioned.  The Bill ensures that Tusla and the Adoption Authority can request information.  I note that the Minister underlined the fact that Departments and religious organisations must share information with them.  He also mentioned the Succession Act, to balance inheritance rights between the birth family and the adoptive family.</p> <p>The O'Mahony report referred to a number of illegal birth registrations, which Tusla flagged as suspicious.  I presume a specialised team is probably looking at those files, but could the Minister provide any further comment on the issue?  It is the case that so many people are old or have passed away.  How are we going to guarantee access to the information?  Given the acceleration by the Department, the officials and the teams in their engagement and public consultations that have been happening in recent years, I do not underestimate what has been achieved, but we must ensure that we have something available as quickly as possible for people who need the support right now.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for his apology.  Having read the report, the points that stuck with me were the shockingly high rate of infant mortality in the 1940s and 1950s and the fact that no comfort was given in some of these homes.  The Minister's role in representing the Government and all of us as public representatives is to give that comfort to families now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#XX00300"><p>The Minister is welcome to the House.  Thank you, Acting Chair, for always being willing to share your story.  A high-profile person such as Senator Boyhan sharing his story does so much for those who have no voice.  I wish to recognise that today.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for making an apology on behalf of the Government.  I await an apology on behalf of the State.  I do not believe the State has made an apology.  That needs to come from the Head of the Government, the Taoiseach himself.</p> <p>I agree very much with what has been said by my colleague Senators this evening.  I came here to speak against this Bill.  I toyed with the issue all last night.  Since I became a Senator in 2014, I have been confronted with legislation that I never wanted to be a part of and yet finished up supporting.  I supported the gender recognition Bill.  I supported the marriage Bill and referendum.  For an auld fella like me, who comes from a conservative background, it takes quite a lot to move there.  What has moved me this evening to now wanting to support the Minister is the word "illegal".  I grew up in an Ireland that is so different to the Ireland we have today.  A girl getting pregnant in my home town disappeared and she returned no longer pregnant, or she never returned.  Those who did have children, even though they may have given the child up for adoption, which in most cases they were forced to do, when they came back their reputations were destroyed and not only their reputation, it extended to their family in some cases.</p> <p>As I think about that this evening, I think about the lies that have been told to those who were adopted, to friends and relations, in order to cover the fact that an illegal registration of birth had taken place, the professional people involved - people that we looked up to.  In my young days, people like doctors, priests, nuns and teachers had a position in society which was above the rest of us, and we looked up to them, yet here we had this criminal behaviour going on in institutions around this country.</p> <p>This Bill is vitally important, but I do have great sympathy for the mothers that are about to be exposed, because a lot of them were children themselves when they were pregnant.  Many of them were the direct result of rape or incest and it was all buried under the carpet.  In my home town, a few priests were used and when a girl was pregnant, irrespective of how she became pregnant, she was moved on.  In the society we live in, even today, girls are expected to be the ones that will say "No, stop, I do not want to do this.  I do not want to get pregnant."  Where are the fathers in this Bill?  Where are the men who brought about or participated in bringing about the pregnancy?  We will never know them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some of them hold responsible positions in society today and they are delighted that their little misdemeanour, as they would have thought of it, was moved on.  Whether we like it or not, institutions in this country sold babies and that is the truth of it.  I want to know how we will recover that.  How will we make these institutions repatriate to the State the moneys they took for selling citizens of this State?  They sold them to America and all over the world and it is disgraceful.</p><p>They say in the medical profession, "First, do no harm".  My advice to the Minister is not to do any more harm; we need a balance of harms.  I was thinking last night of an 82 year-old woman sitting in her sitting room with her husband and children with this dark secret sitting in the background that may be 65 years old, waiting for the knock or the registered letter and waiting for her past to come back and abuse her for a second time.  I am not so sure that every mother was happy about the adoptions they were forced into and I am not so sure that those girls have ever forgotten the hurt that was done to them.  I lived in those years and I saw what went on.  I commend the Minister on bringing this forward and I will work with those who want to bring amendments forward.  I will support the Minister and I complement him on what he has done.  I hope he does not take any personal insult from me requesting the State to make a proper apology.  The Minister has done a great job in bringing this Bill forward and I know how committed he is to this.  I complement the Minister on his work but I want the State to step forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#YY00200"><p>That last contribution was quite a remarkable one and I relate to it on so many levels because of my age and because I grew up in a similar society to Senator Craughwell.  I relate to the things he said.  It was a remarkable and profound contribution and I commend it for its considerable reflection on a number of fronts.  Having said that, I thank the Minister for this work and I thank the members of the committee who are here.  The Minister's apology is appropriate on a number of levels.  It is appropriate coming from a man of such patent sincerity and commitment to dealing with this.  It is appropriate that it is taking place in the Seanad, which has, to mention recent phraseology, always been the place for minority voices and major change.  It is not an inappropriate setting.  It is a fulsome and good apology and it is appropriate coming from the Minister.  If other apologies follow then well and good but it stands alone and I would say to the people in the Visitors Gallery and to their friends outside that they should value and accept this apology as wholesome, thorough and full.</p> <p>I want to allude to one aspect of Senator Craughwell's contribution, which I was impressed with, because I grew up in that same world and it is hard for a lot of those here to relate to that, which is understandable and thank God they do not relate to it.  The Senator has a point that there will be mothers for whom this will be traumatic.  There are people who have lived with a dark secret for years, which they have held from their new children from their new relationships and from their grandchildren.  As Senator Craughwell said, this can explode on them now.  I know there is a clause on this and I have heard the Minister say that their wish for privacy will be relayed to the victim, which is fair enough.  The Minister might return to that fundamental point in his response and it might merit considerable thought on support or counselling and on how we deal with the mothers.  That is a relevant point and I do not mind dwelling on it a little.  Senator Craughwell brought an interesting dimension to the debate, which is not to in any way detract from all the other things that are correct.  It was a horror that people's identities were kept from them, that there were illegal adoptions, that new and false identities were created for people and that they could not access the truth.  That was wrong.  It is important that full information would be made available now and that there will be a pathway to that information.  It is also important that there will be tracing and genealogical services and that there will be counselling and full disclosure.  That is all well-spoken of and documented, which is good.  The Minister summed it up in a nutshell when he said: "The shame was not theirs.  It was ours, and it remains our shame."</p> <p>It is also so important that children abroad are included and one would not need a degree in science to understand that the medical records are important.  Neither would one need a degree in science to understand that the early life care dimension is important.  I relate to that as a teacher and a parent and it is important that they would be made aware of that.  I commend the Acting Chairman in the way Senator Craughwell did as he displays great courage in the way he speaks to this House.  He is giving extraordinary leadership, courage, support and hope to others in that regard.  All of those supports are necessary, including early life care, but I want to make the point that the holistic care, as identified by Senator Craughwell, must be understood.  While some people might, understandably, be a little impatient for more change, for people like Senator Craughwell and I and for our generation, this is a monumental and momentous evening.  This is transformational, progressive, major and wonderful movement.  We celebrate, laud and commend it and we are proud to be part of it.  People used to say they would love to live to see a united Ireland; well I would say that I am delighted that I lived to see this and that I am part of it.</p> <p>We all owe an apology to the people in the Visitors Gallery.  Whether it was in the attitude of the men, whether it was in the attitude of society or whether it was the fact that we pushed away responsibility, we all owe them an apology on so many fronts.  Those of us who lived through that time particularly owe them an apology and those who did not owe them an apology for not getting on to this quicker.  They are in our hearts and thoughts and we treasure and respect them but we all owe them that apology.  I will leave it at that.  It is an important evening and one I probably thought I would never live to see but it is wonderful to see it.  It is just as important to see this as it is to see a united Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#YY00300"><p>I want to thank all Members of the House for the considered contributions they have made in the context of this legislation and in relation to the apology that has been delivered to those who were the subject of illegal birth registrations.  I want to thank the Acting Chairman for his insightful contributions, as ever.  He focused his contribution on the importance of identity and that is fundamentally what the issues we are seeking to address in this legislation are about.  It is the fundamental issue that those who were subject to illegal birth registrations were denied their identities.  The depth of the denial of that identity for those subject to illegal birth registrations is particularly acute in light of the way that so many of them found out about their identities.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Not only did they not know their identity, they were led to believe a completely different identity. </p><p>I hear and acknowledge what has been said by Senators McGreehan, Seery Kearney, Craughwell and those to whom I have spoken before tonight's meeting, who are in the Public Gallery, in terms of whether this was the best place to make the apology on behalf of the Government.  In making the apology here and in doing it this evening, in particular in linking it with Second Stage of the Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022, I wanted to demonstrate that this apology was being followed by meaningful action.  I have always believed that this Bill is a meaningful response to those who have been subject to illegal birth registration.  When I met a number of those present on a web meeting last year, I made the commitment that the delays that people had faced in terms of a resolution to the identity issues, but also those very real and practical legal concerns, would come through this legislation.  That is why I have linked the apology today with this Bill.  I hear what they and Senators have said.  As I said, I will engage further with the Taoiseach in terms of ensuring there is full parity of esteem between the group who were subject to illegal birth registration and others who have received a State apology, in particular those who were in Magdalen institutions and those who were in mother and baby institutions.</p><p>A range of very important issues have been raised across the House.  We will have the opportunity on Committee Stage to address these in more detail, but I would like to take this opportunity to discuss some of the issues at this point.  The Acting Chairperson, Senator Boyhan, listed the key types of information to which this legislation will provide access.  It is important to remember the breadth of what we are trying to achieve.  The Bill provides for access to the birth certificate, the document that for so long has been denied to so many people; and access to birth information, which is information that could be on a birth certificate but on many birth certificates is not present.  In that situation, it is usually the name of the father that is not present.  That information may be elsewhere in a file of the individual but is not on the birth certificate.  That is why we are including birth information as well.  The Bill also provides for care information, which is information about the period during which an individual was in care.  In response to Senator Higgins, where there is any file that discusses any element of the treatment of the person, that information will be available under care information.  The Bill also discusses early life information as another source.  Some of these areas cross over.  It is a Venn diagram in terms of covering of information.  We have put these successive definitions into the Bill to provide the broadest level possible of information.  The Bill also provides for medical information, which is absolutely essential.  This is an issue of the most urgent concern to many people, particularly people with a hereditary condition.  It is important they can get any medical information about themselves.  Importantly, this legislation also gives them a legal right to medical information about somebody else.  That is something none of us have.  We talk about knowing if one's mother had a hereditary condition.  I know that information because my mother tells me it, not because I have a legal right to it.  It does not happen but were any of our mothers or fathers to decide not to tell us about a medical condition, that would be their legal right.  This Bill, for the first time, gives an adopted person a legal right to the medical information of a parent in order that he or she can know if a parent had a hereditary condition.  </p><p>Incorrect birth registration information is a new category we entered by way of amendment in the D&aacute;il, recognising that there may be information on the file that can tell us about how the incorrect or illegal birth registration came about, if there is any detail about who did it.  That is a new category that we brought in which, again, is particularly important in terms of the accountability that a number of Senators talked about.  The Bill makes provision for provided items.  If a photograph or letter has been left on a file, that information is available as well.  We specifically, again by way of amendment, we have set out that the term "provided items" includes photographs.  </p><p>Senator McGreehan made a really important point about trust in institutions and how trust has broken down.  Having spoken to many adopted people, but particularly in the context of those who were subject to illegal birth registrations, that the manner in which that information was conveyed to them was hugely inappropriate in many circumstances and has further eroded trust.  We have to try to rebuild that trust as part of this legislation, but the work we are doing goes beyond this legislation.  We are working with the agencies involved, namely, Tusla and the Adoption Authority of Ireland.  A departmental implementation group works with these agencies in terms of ensuring that the culture in these institutions is a culture of giving rather than of withholding information.  The default should not be to not give information; it should be to provide information.  We are doing that through an implementation group.  My Department, Tusla and the Adoption Authority of Ireland work together on how this legislation will work.</p><p>The legislation gives the Minister the power to draft guidelines in regard to how this legislation should be interpreted.  There is also the matter of resourcing, which was raised by Senator Hoey.  We need to resource these agencies better in order that they can undertake the very significant work that this legislation gives to them.  In this year's budget, for example, we have given a significant &euro;4 million additional allocation to Tusla, specifically to resource the Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022 and an additional &euro;1 million allocation to the Adoption Authority of Ireland specifically to resource the Birth Information and Tracing Bill 2022.  Those two bodies have been hiring relevant staff with that range of competencies and they have been updating their knowledge base to be able to resource and implement this legislation.</p><p>Senator Seery Kearney raised the important point with regard to people with suspicions of illegal birth registration.  As stated earlier by the Senator, what happened in the St. Patrick's Guild is just the tip of the iceberg.  I agree.  We made additional changes in this area during Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il.  We are resourcing a specialist tracing service.  It can work in two ways.  First, if an individual comes forward with a strong belief or a piece of information that suggests that he or she was the subject of illegal birth registration, he or she can engage with that specialist tracing team.  It has the mission and the legal basis to inquire because other agencies or bodies now have the obligation to work with such a trace.  While the GDPR has done many good things, it has been, whether correctly or not -  I am sure Senator Higgins would have strong views in that regard - used as a reason for one agency not to share information with another in terms of tracing.  This legislation gives that legislative basis.  It also gives a legislative basis to Tusla.  Where it sees markers or suspicions on a file, Tusla itself can proactively undertake a trace.  That is important.  It is a new power, one that does not exist at the moment.  It is a significant power in terms of recognising that there is a wider body of illegal birth registrations out there and a process to try to reveal that information and give people a right to their identity.</p><p>Senator Warfield stated that there is no right to access files in Irish law.  That is fundamentally what we are about here, namely, the right to access one's information as an adopted person or someone subject to an illegal birth registration, which does not exist.  That is what we are seeking to do.  It is important to say that this legislation does not supplant GDPR, which brings me to some of the points made by Senator Higgins.  This legislation sits alongside GDPR.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=10"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->People retain their existing rights to put in subject access requests.  This legislation conclusively determines that at the end of a process, everyone will get full access to all of their information.  That is not guaranteed under GDPR because there is that balancing mechanism in GDPR where the data controller must make a call each time.  There is no call in this.  People are entitled to their birth information, their early life information, and all of those categories.  They are entitled to them fully and unredacted.  That is why we did not just rely on GDPR.  We never wanted a situation where someone would be refused their right to this vital information.</p><p>I want to talk about the issue of balancing of rights, which has been a key theme in a number of the contributions, and the approach that this legislation takes to the issue of balancing of rights.  I agree with Senator Craughwell's point.  There is a group, how many we do not know but I believe it is a small number and the size does not matter.  This is a group of parents, probably all mothers, who have never discussed with their families what happened to them because of the secrecy and the stigma that Irish society placed on women and girls who got pregnant outside of marriage.  Their right to privacy and to keep that secret, and the right of an adopted person - who is their child - to know their identity, are two fundamental rights.  Up to this point, Ireland has always prioritised the right of privacy over the right of identity.  That changes with this legislation.  It entirely flips and we give precedence to the right of identity.</p><p>I do not need to tell Senators that any time one balances two sets of constitutional rights and gives precedence to one over the other, the legislation that does this must explain the process and must show to the courts that both sets of rights were considered.  This is why we must have a balancing mechanism.  I believe there is general agreement that there has to be a balancing mechanism, and the question then becomes what that balancing mechanism will be.  We believe in the idea of an information session.  I must be clear that such an information session would not happen in every circumstance.  It would happen in a small minority of circumstances where a parent has clearly registered a no-contact preference, and this can happen from now on, once this legislation is passed on.  This preference will indicate a clear affirmative act demonstrating that they have a concern about their privacy.  They cannot keep their identity secret any longer under this legislation but they have the right to register this no-contact preference.  The question then becomes how to convey that to their child.  The process of an information session was originally to be a physical meeting, under the original draft, but we have changed this to a phone call.  Originally, we were going to have a social worker involved.  We were coming from a mindset of the adopted person maybe needing support, but we must also recognise that this is the conveying of a piece of information.  Many adopted people do not want such support and they do not want to be treated as though they are something delicate.  They want to be given the information.  This is why we moved away from the idea that the information session would be provided by a social worker.  It is the conveyance of two pieces of information, namely, that the birth parent has asked that there would be a no-contact preference, and a recognition that this is an exercise of their privacy rights.  Once that phone call has been made, the full suite of information, unredacted, is released.  We believe this is the most constitutionally compatible way of balancing those two sets of rights.</p><p>We did examine the issue of the registered letter.  This was examined but the advice we received was that the information session is the best way.  This approach has been proposed in the past, as Members may be aware, with regard to the information session.  I have heard the concerns raised by some adopted people about that information session.  If it was something easy to change, then I would do that.  We are, however, fundamentally balancing two sets of constitutional rights here.  We are in a space where we know that issues have previously gone to the courts on the release of adoption information.  The I. O'T case, which is the case that has caused so many of the difficulties we are experiencing, was someone objecting to the release of their name and adoption information to the child they gave up for adoption.</p><p>In my introduction I did not speak at length on, but I am very conscious of, how many efforts there have been to pass legislation providing for information for adopted people, and how all of those efforts have failed.  Senator Higgins referred to what was said to Senator Ruane at a previous point.  I will not get into that space but I am very conscious that we need to get this done.  Having listened to the advice of the Office of the Attorney General on the terms of the balancing mechanism, I believe we have a balancing mechanism that gets us through constitutional balancing and delivers full access to all information, unredacted, with no more vetoes and no more are being held back, with everyone getting access to their full set of information.</p><p>I will make two further brief points on some of the wider issues.  Senator Dolan spoke of the mothers who may be afraid.  Under this legislation, counselling is provided for everyone who wishes to receive counselling.  The person seeking information or the person who has lodged a no-contact preference will be provided with counselling as some element of the supports to them.</p><p>On the wider issue of the retention of information and where the information is, this has come up and it was discussed in the D&aacute;il.  Senator Warfield has also spoken on this.  I was always very clear.  Previous legislation had tried to bring everything together.  It was to bring everything together and then allow for access to information.  We must recognise, however, that this would take a number of years to do.  It could be done, and this Bill allows for it to be done, but we want to be able to give people access to information as soon as possible.  This is why we put an obligation on Tusla, the Adoption Authority of Ireland, and the various bodies, to provide information under this legislation.  We also recognise the need for, and in the response to the commission of investigation we clearly set out the objectives for, a records and memorial centre.  The Government recently announced steps it is taking to create a site where people can learn about and understand the tragedy of institutional abuse in Ireland in the 20th century, and be able to access appropriate records.  There will be a physical building but we also know this must be available in a wider setting for those people living abroad.  This is particularly important.  That plan is being advanced.  This legislation provides for the protection of all existing records and allows the Adoption Authority of Ireland to request and instruct bodies to provide their records to it as part of the work of collating information.  This legislation does advance the achievement of that goal.</p><p>I thank Senators for their time today.  I thank them for their engagement on this legislation.  I look forward to continuing to engage with Senators as the Bill moves through the House.  In particular, I thank those who are with us today in the Gallery.  I hope the apology I have delivered on behalf on the Government has meaning to you.  The Senators are right that this is your apology.  How you understand it is not something that I or anybody else can seek to dictate.  I hope that in discussing the Bill today, you see the efforts that are being made by the Government to provide you, and others in the same situation as yourselves, with a route to the access to your identity, while at the same time addressing those very real concerns that the fact of your illegal birth registration has created in your lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#BBB00050"><p>I thank the Minister for his comprehensive response to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.162" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#BBB00200"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#BBB00300"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#BBB00400"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.166" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 17 May 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#BBB00600"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022051000002#BBB00700"><p>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-10a.169" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ar 8.31 p.m. go dt&iacute; 10.30 a.m., D&eacute; C&eacute;adaoin, an 11 Bealtaine 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 8.31 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 11 May 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>