<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment to outline the measures being taken to ensure the viability of the post office network in the future.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to outline his plans for the establishment of a regulator for the approved housing body sector.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the recommendations made by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation in its report entitled, The Situation of Non-EEA Crew in the Irish Fishing Fleet under the Atypical Worker Permission Scheme.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to consider the provision of a public swimming pool in north Fingal.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to extend the Copyright and Related Rights Act 2000 to the legal deposit of digital publications.</blockquote><p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised Senators M&aacute;ire Devine, Victor Boyhan, Paul Gavan and Lorraine Clifford-Lee and they will be taken now.  Senator Fintan Warfield may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#B00200">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#B00300">Post Office Network</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne, to the Chamber and ask Senator M&aacute;ire Devine to outline her case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#B00500"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  I raise the issue of the future of the national network of post offices, the standing of which has been wobbly in the past decade or so.  Many post offices have shut their doors and the future remains uncertain for those which continue to operate.  Postmasters and postmistresses have provided a great community service and a warm space for communities to gather.  This service is obviously under serious threat.  Will the Minister of State outline the future of post offices and set out what the policy will be?  How does the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment envisage the network improving and expanding in order that post offices will become vibrant spaces within all of our communities?  What is the position on the long-term commitment to provide social welfare payments which represent 40% to 50% of the business transacted in post offices?  The purchase of ancillary services over the counter alongside the social welfare payments contract brings the figure to 60%.  Will the Minister of State publicly provide a detailed plan and timeline for the roll-out of the promised Government and financial services in post offices?</p> <p>Looking at the issue in an international context, I cannot help but think of the idea of a people's bank.  In this country we have been subjected to immense suffering and a lost generation have emigrated because of the dismal performance of the banks, which are interested only in maximising profits and accounting to shareholders.  Their sole focus is on commercial banking, not the public interest which is served in other ways in different countries.  I note the position in North Dakota and Germany where there are public banking systems in place which have had great success.  Notwithstanding the fact that it has a population of only 750,000, $1 billion has been returned to the state in North Dakota.  That money is given back to its citizens.  We must not be disenfranchised, therefore, in being kept from ownership of public banking.  Does the Minister have a policy on post offices in the context of mortgage lending, foreign exchange, motor vehicle registration, driver licensing, identification verification cards, foreign exchange cards, bill pay services, parcel lockers and so on?</p> <p>I want to introduce a local dimension.  Rialto post office in Dublin South-Central shut its doors for various reasons but public demand ensured it was reopened.  It is now thriving.  I grew up on St. James's Street where a post office has been in place since 1890.  It is adjacent to the Guinness brewery and the largest health infrastructure project in the history of the State, namely, the national children's hospital.  There is student accommodation available there and the street is on the country's primary tourist trail which leads along the same road from Trinity College Dublin to Kilmainham Gaol.  Many foreign workers are employed in the area in which many foreign students, nurses and doctors live, including within the accommodation on the St. James's Hospital campus.  The post office has been given notice, albeit we have managed to have the date extended to 18 July.  I plead with the Minister of State to intervene to find suitable alternative premises for it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Given the evident demand and the historic importance of this post office in that area which has served Guinness workers throughout their lifetime, old age pensioners, the young and now an influx of people from abroad who will need those services, I would like a response on this.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.13" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#C00200">Visit of European Committee of the Regions</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#C00300"><p>Before I call on the Minister of State, I am sure that Members of the House will wish to join with me in welcoming a delegation from the European Committee of the Regions led by the President of the Committee, Mr. Karl-Heinz Lambertz.</p> <p>On my own behalf and on behalf of my colleagues in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I wish to extend a warm welcome to you and good wishes for a successful visit to Ireland.  T&aacute; f&aacute;ilte romhaibh.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#C00400">Commencement Matters (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1314" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#C00500"><p>I thank Senator Devine for raising this important issue which I, as Minister of State in the Department, am taking on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Naughten.</p> <p>As Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten, has responsibility for the postal sector, including the governance of An Post.  The Minister is acutely conscious of the value placed by communities in both rural and urban areas on services provided by post offices and is concerned to ensure the needs of those communities continue to be met.</p> <p>Reflecting its commitment to sustaining a nationwide post office network and daily mails service, the Government has made &euro;30 million available in State funding to An Post, &euro;15 million of which will be used to support the renewal of the post office network and &euro;15 million of which will be used for the continued fulfilment of a five day per week mails delivery service.  This, in turn, will secure the future of mail and post office services for local communities throughout the country in both urban and rural areas.  In addition, the company proposes to invest &euro;50 million in growing and modernising the network over the next few years.</p> <p>As part of its strategy for modernising the post office network, An Post has established a dedicated business unit within An Post called An Post Retail.  An Post recently announced its plans for a modernised post office network.  The vision centres around the availability of new services in a modernised, revitalised network.  Such services will include a better range of Government services, financial services and e-commerce services for shoppers and small businesses.  The announcement by An Post is supported by an agreement reached with the Irish Postmasters' Union, IPU, executive following three months of intensive negotiations, which has subsequently been endorsed by 80% of IPU members.</p> <p>The announcement represents a positive first step in reinvigorating our national post office network and making it a viable service that meets the needs of communities across the country, particularly in rural areas.</p> <p>Given the challenges it is facing, the company will have to pursue an ambitious agenda across its various business areas and there is likely to be significant change and new business models implemented in the coming years.  This should be viewed positively as it will result in a solid, sustainable business future.  Enhanced banking services are becoming available through the post office network with the smart bank account.  It is expected that further such opportunities will be available across the network, especially as high-speed broadband becomes widely available through the roll-out of the national broadband plan.</p> <p>As part of its consideration of the financial position of An Post, Government agreed that further opportunities for Government business through the post office network, particularly the payment of motor tax, should be explored.  While Government policy is to offer Government services online, there is always likely to be a segment of the population that is not comfortable or proficient accessing online tools or services.  The post office network is the obvious choice as the "offline gateway" for citizens with its nationwide network and existing strong relationship with offline citizens.</p> <p>Department officials have engaged with An Post and other relevant stakeholders,  such as the Office of Government Procurement, the Office of the Government Chief Information Officer and other Departments to assess how additional Government business might be channelled through the post office network.  Discussions have been positive in this regard.  The Minister, Deputy Naughten, along with the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Ring, the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, and myself, are actively engaged in this to ascertain how we can bring more Government services into the local post office network.  We are determined to ensure that is happening while also remaining cognisant of the need to adhere to public procurement procedures.</p> <p>The first practical step that the Government is taking is the digital assist pilot programme.  Under that programme, post offices will provide access to a wide range of Government services.  Government funding of &euro;80,000 has been secured, through the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Ring, for the roll-out of a pilot digital assist scheme.  Ten post offices will be equipped to help citizens with online Government interactions.  The ten pilot schemes will be located in rural post offices and will be in place later this year.</p> <p>The affiliation with the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection remains a significant feature for the future of the post office network.  In April 2018, the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection renewed her Department's contract with An Post to provide pensions, child benefit and other social welfare payments in cash at post offices.  Last year's contract amounted to &euro;51 million for 33.6 million payments, and the value of the 2018 contract is expected to match that.  This reaffirms Government policy which sees the post office network as a key piece of the country's financial and social infrastructure, particularly in rural areas.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Accordingly, A Programme for a Partnership Government commits to actively encouraging payment at post offices.  All avenues are being explored to ensure that services available to the post office network are enhanced so that we have a strong, customer-focused network.  The contract has been renewed.  It was agreed, along with the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection, in 2013 for an initial two-year period with an option to extend annually up to 2019.  That is welcome news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  There is some &euro;15 million for growing and modernising the network.  Who makes the decisions on the priorities and where this &euro;15 million will be invested?  Does the Minister have any influence over that?  The Minister of State says people are not proficient or comfortable in accessing digital services online at home and he is providing some training within ten pilot post offices in rural areas.  The point also needs to be made that a significant amount of those people who are not comfortable with online tools actually prefer human interaction.  It is an important part of the fabric of communities, building resilient and stronger communities, and battling isolation.  Perhaps the Minister of State cannot give me an answer on my local post office in St. James's Street, Dublin 8.  Will he ask the Minister if he could make inquiries into this?  It is historic.  For that to go would spell the death knell of many more post offices.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1314" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#D00300"><p>I thank Senator Devine.  I will certainly ask the Minister.  I know the commitment reached by the Irish Postmasters' Union, IPU, and approved by 80% of its members, included that An Post will open up to 20 new offices in communities of 500 or more currently without a post office, with a post office for every community of over 500 people within 15 km of 95% of the population, and 3 km in urban areas.  St. James's Street post office may fit into that.  I am not sure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#D00325"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1314" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#D00337"><p>The Senator is shaking her head.  I will ask the Minister to revert about that post office.  I would not have the facts.  It was not brought to my attention.  The digital assist is a positive.  It is a pilot but, subject to it working, I see no reason that would not be extended to many other different areas.  As I said, funding of &euro;80,000 has been provided.  The proposed pilot locations are to be agreed between An Post and the IPU, which is positive.  I will revert on the issue I have raised.</p> <p>I accept the importance of the post office network and that there are people who prefer the social interaction that the post office provides.  I have listened carefully to the Senator's views.  It is Government policy that An Post remains strong and that the network remains strong.  The agreement reached between the IPU and its members would be that there would be no compulsory closures of post offices.  We are committed to a high-quality, nationwide service in both rural and urban areas.  I think all Members would aspire to having maximum coverage of the country, providing an important service for communities across the country.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.22" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#D00350">Approved Housing Bodies</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#D00400"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I had the benefit of meeting with him in the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government, though I tabled this matter before that.  In essence, I am asking about the need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to confirm his plans to establish a regulator for the approved housing bodies sector, to oversee the effective governance and financial management of the voluntary and co-operative housing sector and to safeguard the public and private investment in the sector.</p> <p>I have received a number of comments relating to this sector over the last few years and am conscious that the Government is on to something here.  It is part of pillar 2 of Rebuilding Ireland.  Action 2.15 is for the Government to, "establish a Regulator for the AHB sector to oversee the effective governance and financial management of voluntary and co-operative housing bodies".<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The deadline was quarter 1 of 2017 and, therefore, the Minister is running a little late.  There are suggestions that there is a need for legislation and regulation to give effect to this commitment and it would be important to introduce legislation to ensure good governance in the AHB and voluntary housing sector.  I acknowledge the importance of the sector as part of a suite of opportunities and possibilities to deliver much-needed housing for rent and purchase.  The sector has made a good contribution and it is willing to continue to shoulder some of the responsibility and make a positive input to providing much-needed affordable homes for the public.  I am interested in the Minister's reply regarding the appointment of a regulator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  I am aware from his membership of the Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government that he has a keen interest in the matter.  We often battle politely in that forum and I very much appreciate his engagement, expertise and interest in this area.</p> <p>Rebuilding Ireland - Action Plan for Housing and Homelessness recognises the key contribution that approved housing bodies, AHBs, make to the delivery of social housing.  AHBs are expected to contribute approximately one third of the 50,000 new social housing units that are to be provided over the period of the plan.  The capacity of AHBs to deliver on the targets set out in the plan will require them to expand greatly and to seek significantly increased levels of external investment in the sector.  AHBs that have statutorily regulated standards of governance and management capacity will be better able to access loan finance, which will greatly assist them to develop and expand in line with the objectives set out in the Rebuilding Ireland plan.</p> <p>Under existing legislation, housing bodies are granted approved status by the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government under section 6 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 1992 for the purpose of receiving funding from local authorities to provide social housing.  This arrangement has been in place since 1992 and the Government acknowledges that a more modern regulatory system needs to be put in place to oversee a sector which has developed significantly since then.</p> <p>My Department is working with the Attorney General's office in drafting the housing (regulation of registered housing providers) Bill which will provide statutory regulation for the AHB sector.  It is intended to establish a regulator to oversee the effective governance, financial management and performance of voluntary and co-operative housing bodies in providing housing in accordance with the Housing Acts.  The Bill aims to introduce stronger safeguards for public and private investment in the social housing provision sector, to establish a framework that will enable the voluntary and co-operative housing sector to contribute more effectively to the provision of social housing, and to ensure the assets built through investments in the sector are managed sustainably.  The statutory regulatory framework will provide further assurances to tenants, the Government and investors and to the sector itself that social housing providers operate in a well-regulated and stable environment.</p> <p>The regulator will be responsible for approving and registering housing bodies and the setting of regulatory standards.  The Bill will provide extensive powers for the regulator in respect of the undertaking of inquiries, investigations and assessments.  The regulator will also have enforcement and other powers.  My Department is working with the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel to finalise the text of the Bill for publication as soon as possible.  I had hoped that the Bill would be published before now, but the complex nature of some issues related to transitioning from voluntary to statutory regulation has required additional time.  Notwithstanding this, I hope to publish the Bill before the end of the current D&aacute;il term.</p> <p>The Government is acutely aware of the importance of this sector and, in advance of establishing the statutory regulatory framework, put in place measures to prepare the sector for the new regulatory regime.  In 2014, an interim regulation committee for the AHB sector was established under the auspices of the Housing Agency, which, supported by a regulation office based within the agency, oversees implementation of a voluntary regulation code, VRC, for AHBs.</p> <p>A number of recent developments, including the decision by EUROSTAT and the CSO to reclassify AHBs as being part of the general government balance and the Central Bank's amending regulations to facilitate credit unions to provide funding to AHBs under certain conditions, are feeding into our considerations on the legislation and will ensure that the regulatory framework reflects the current and forward-looking policy context for the approved housing body sector.  My Department is working intently on finalising the legislative proposals for submission to Government.  In the meantime, I am confident that the interim arrangements for regulating the sector will ensure that it continues to operate to a high standard and enable it to fulfil its role under the Rebuilding Ireland action plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister for his comprehensive response.  There is provision to initiate legislation in the House, and given we have little work to do and we are constantly told there are so few Bills on the way, will the Minister consider initiating this legislation here?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is priority legislation.  There is nothing to stop this legislation being initiated in the Seanad.  Will the Minister give the matter some consideration and talk to his colleagues about it?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#F00200"><p>There is a provision for the Senator to introduce his own Bill, or his group's Bill, in Private Members' time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#F00300"><p>I am happy to support the Government's Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#F00400"><p>I thank the Senator.  I will consider the proposal he has made about where we initiate the legislation.  The Senator is aware of the importance of the AHB sector to our delivery stream.  When we talk about the State building social housing and local authorities building social housing, we include what the AHBs are doing because they are one of the new delivery streams that were not there in the past.  They are building fantastic homes, some of which provide for the quite niche requirements of some of our population who have different and special needs.  They make a very important contribution to increasing the overall stock of social housing that we have at the moment.  We are almost there in terms of the legislation.  It is priority legislation for me.  I want to have it published before the end of the D&aacute;il term.  If we can do it by initiating it in the Seanad I will certainly consider it.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.31" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#F00500">Fishing Industry</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#F00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  The Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation produced a report last December on the situation of non-EEA crew in the Irish fishing fleet under the atypical working scheme.  It is important to note the report had the unanimous support of all committee members.  We were all very concerned by incidents of abuse of workers in this sector.  This abuse involved breaches of the National Minimum Wage Act, the Organisation of Working Time Act, the Terms of Employment (Information) Act and the Payment of Wages Act.  The issues highlighted included: withholding of pay; arbitrary cuts to rates of pay; forced unpaid labour on repairs at port; rates of pay below the legal minimum; restrictions on movement because of one's status as an undocumented worker; inability to avail of public healthcare services because of one's status as an undocumented worker; sleep deprivation; verbal and physical abuse; dangerous working practices; working without mandatory Irish safety training certificates; workers left hungry; cramped living conditions; and poor sanitary arrangements.</p> <p>Since the report was published things have gotten significantly worse.  Last Thursday, the International Transport Workers' Federation confirmed that 12 possible cases of human trafficking have been identified in the industry.  The Government is now facing legal proceedings unless it pauses the atypical working scheme.  Seven of the 12 cases have been positively identified as suspected victims of trafficking in human beings, with five referrals still under investigation by the Garda National Protective Services Bureau.</p> <p>The number of potential victims identified equates to one in ten of the permits issued over the past 18 months.  The Department of Justice and Equality, in its statement, plays pass the parcel on this issue citing the Workplace Relations Commission and the marine survey office as the relevant authorities.  It is worth repeating that.  When faced with the most serious potential charges of human trafficking, the Department of Justice and Equality has said it has nothing to do with it and has passed the buck to the Minister of State's Department.</p> <p>Will the Minister of State tell us what he intends to do regarding the recommendations in this report?  The Department has had six months to consider the report and is now aware of the most serious charges of human trafficking in the industry.  The Minister of State will know that the figure quoted by our Naval Service clearly shows there is a problem in the sector.  There were 109 workers found working illegally on 86 boats.  The key recommendation from our report is that one Government Department takes overall responsibility for the sector.  We also call for a moratorium on the issuing of new permits until such time as all non-EEA nationals are regularised.  We recommended a reconstituted task force be set up, including the International Transport Workers' Federation, in order to deal with the myriad problems in the scheme.  We recommended a review of the marine survey office and a simplified and transparent permit process.  Will the Minister of State tell me what he has done in the six months since receiving this report?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#F00700"><p>I thank Senator Gavan for raising the issue.  As the Senator is aware, the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation published its report on the situation of non-EEA crew in the Irish fishing fleet under the atypical worker permission scheme last December.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Andrew Doyle:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2170"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2170&amp;amp;pid=AndrewDoyle&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As outlined in the report, the matters that arose regarding the non-EEA workers in the fishing industry in late 2015 required a cross-departmental and cross-agency response and the Government quickly set up an interdepartmental task force to examine the issues involved.  The main recommendation of that task force was the establishment of a sector-specific atypical worker permission scheme, which is an extension of the existing atypical worker permission scheme administered by the Department of Justice and Equality.</p><p>The scheme was established and is operated through the co-operative efforts of the Department of Justice and Equality, the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation, the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection and the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  As a number of Departments are involved in the scheme it is monitored by an oversight committee with members from relevant Departments and State agencies.  The Department of Justice and Equality retains responsibility for immigration matters under the scheme while the memorandum of understanding put in place, which is led by the Department of Business, Enterprise and Innovation with relevant State enforcement bodies, provides for a rigorous and effective inspection system.  This system provides, for the first time, a structured and transparent framework for the employment of non-EEA workers within defined segments of the Irish fishing fleet.  The scheme sets down minimum terms and conditions of employment applicable to these workers, which are in line with the general statutory terms and conditions applicable to workers more generally in the State.  Any abuses or otherwise of the specified employment conditions of a non-EEA national in the Irish fishing industry are a matter for the relevant enforcement agencies - the Workplace Relations Commission, the marine survey office of the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport and other appropriate authorities of the State.  Inspectors of the Workplace Relations Commission, based on newly acquired powers, have been trained and equipped with support from a number of agencies to board vessels and carry out their own inspections.  This has already happened.</p><p>The role of my Department in the scheme is solely in respect of maintaining the central depository of contracts and supporting documentation submitted under the scheme, in order to monitor to ensure that the cap of 500 is not exceeded in any 12 month period.  To date, 262 contracts have been lodged with the central depository.  The Irish Naturalisation and Immigration Service has granted atypical worker permissions to 229 applicants under the scheme since its commencement in February 2016.  The atypical worker permission scheme for non-EEA crew is still a relatively young scheme and further time is needed to allow the scheme to become established and to deliver on its objectives.  There are undoubtedly enforcement challenges under the scheme.  These challenges fall to be addressed by the appropriate enforcement agencies, and there is ongoing work in this area.  Finally, cases of human trafficking are outside the scope of the scheme and must be dealt with firmly under the human trafficking legislation in order to eliminate such behaviour and to ensure that non-EEA workers in the fishing industry are only engaged in full compliance with the terms of the scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#G00200"><p>Will all due respect, the Minister of State has not answered my key question.  When is he going to implement the recommendations of the Oireachtas committee's report?  He has not addressed any of the recommendations.  It is deeply disappointing.  He commented at the end that human trafficking issues had to be dealt with under human trafficking legislation.  That is true, but the problem is that the Department of Justice and Equality said last week that it had nothing to do with that Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#G00300"><p>It is a Garda matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#G00400"><p>It is pass the parcel, in effect.  No Department is willing to take responsibility for the disgraceful abuses taking place in the fishing sector.  That was the main recommendation of our report but the Minister of State did not address the question I asked.  I can confirm on the record here that all 12 recommendations have been ignored.  In time to come there will be a tribunal of inquiry on what is happening in this sector and the one thing the Minister will not be able to say is that he did not know.  He knows, and he has done nothing about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#G00500"><p>I reject that.  This is a new scheme that was started following the work of the previous Government.  Four Departments were required to implement it.  There is cross-departmental co-operation on it and there is a memorandum of understanding.  The Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine's role is to hold the numbers in the depository and to deal with matters relating to the fishing sector.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Andrew Doyle:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2170"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2170&amp;amp;pid=AndrewDoyle&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have comments on five of the key recommendations.  One recommendation is that a single Government Department takes responsibility for the fishing industry.  I do not think that is possible.  Another is that vessels under 15 m should be included in the scheme.  The reason they were not included in the first place is that vessels under 15 m tend to be smaller and generally provide local employment.  It was not intended that this scheme be open to all fishing boats around the country.  It was felt that some should be reserved for local employment.  As someone who chaired a committee in the last Oireachtas which considered the role of coastal and island communities in the small fishing sector, the whole idea was that we would provide local employment for local people.  The reconstituted task force should be considered but I am not sure that it should run in the way the Senator envisages.  The report recommends that permissions be linked to the employee and not the specific vessel or owner.  In that case the contract would be gone and it would be a wholly different scheme.  It would not be the scheme that is in place.</p><p>Finally, it is recommended that applications should be made directly to a central registry that is open to the public.  This scheme as designed is based on a contract between an individual who is a non-EEA citizen and an owner.  That contract has to be signed by a solicitor, witnessed and given legal status before it can go to the Department of Justice and Equality and before that permission can be issued.  The Senator is talking about designing a completely new scheme.  He wants to do this before the current scheme is fine-tuned and made work.  On eliminating trafficking, I have no doubt that the trafficking dealt with in recent media coverage relates to people who are not part of this scheme.  That is part of the problem.  They came in a different way.  They were not participants in the scheme in the first place and they should be dealt with by the law.  The Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is the appropriate authority to deal with that particular scenario.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.40" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#H00150">Swimming Pool Programme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#H00200"><p>As the Minister probably knows, Fingal is the fastest growing county in Ireland and north Fingal is the fastest growing area within it.  North Fingal includes Balbriggan, Balrothery, Skerries, Naul, Rush, Lusk, Garristown, Oldtown, Donabate and Portrane.  The area has a rapidly expanding population and substantial future growth is planned.  To give an idea of the size of the towns involved, Balbriggan has a population of approximately 26,000 and Rush currently has a population of approximately 10,000.  As I have said, there are also future plans for the area and, as I have also outlined, the demographic is young.</p> <p>There is no swimming pool in the north Fingal area.  The children of north Fingal cannot readily avail of swimming lessons, which are now seen as almost a standard part of the school curriculum.  They cannot avail of something as basic as swimming lessons without having to travel long distances and incur the additional costs of that travel.  Children with autism and ADHD particularly benefit from water-based therapies but unfortunately the distances such children would have to travel from north Fingal in order to avail of such therapies in a swimming pool would negate any benefit they might derive from them.  Older people can also derive great health and social benefits from access to a swimming pool within their community.</p> <p>Plans for a swimming pool for north Fingal stretch back to the year 2000 when a swimming pool for Skerries was planned through Fingal County Council, which applied for the local authority swimming pool programme administered through the Minister's Department.  When these plans fell through Fingal County Council put forward a plan for construction of a swimming pool in conjunction with Balbriggan Rugby Football Club in Balrothery.  These plans ultimately fell through and in January 2016 Fingal County Council voluntarily withdrew from the local authority swimming pool programme.  I raised the need for a swimming pool in the area by way of Commencement matter on 9 May 2017.  I was told by the Minister of State, Deputy Helen McEntee, who attended the Chamber on that date that it was now open to Fingal County Council to apply for a sports grant which is capped at &euro;500,000 due to its withdrawal from the local authority swimming pool programme.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2461"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2461&amp;amp;pid=LorraineCliffordLee&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is significantly less than the &euro;3.8 million per project which was available under the previous local authority swimming pool programme.  I was told on that occasion that the future funding of swimming pools was being examined by the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport as part of a review of national sports policy which was to have a particular focus on how sporting facilities are to be funded into the future.  I was advised that the Department was in the process of making a submission under the mid-term capital review to seek additional funding for large-scale sports infrastructure like swimming pools.  I was told that if this funding was received, it would allow the Department to give further consideration to new projects like swimming pools, thereby allowing county councils to submit plans for such projects.</p><p>I would like to know what the outcome of the review of national sports policy was, particularly insofar as it related to the construction of swimming pools.  I would like to know whether the Department has received additional funding under the mid-term capital review plan.  If so, has a new programme been established?  I emphasise the urgent need for a swimming pool in the northern part of Fingal, especially in light of the demographics of the area and the lack of facilities to match the housing that has been built in the area in recent years and the housing that is planned for the future.  We should not pile houses into an area without providing adequate facilities for the community.  The people of Balbriggan recently came together to form a committee to press for the development of a swimming pool.  This is an expression of the level of public support and demand for a swimming pool in north Fingal.  I would appreciate it if the Minister could address the specific points I have raised with regard to this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#J00200"><p>I thank Senator Clifford-Lee for raising this topic, with which I have a great deal of sympathy.  Swimming pools are an essential part of a child's education and upbringing.  It would be every Minister's ambition to have a swimming pool in every populated area.  That is not quite possible, but we are doing our very best to achieve it.</p> <p>The local authority swimming pool programme, which is administered by my Department, provides grant aid towards the capital costs of new public swimming pools or the refurbishment of existing pools.  The programme provides for maximum grant aid of &euro;3.8 million per project.  The four principal stages which must be undertaken by a local authority in developing a swimming pool project are: preliminary report stage, including feasibility study; contract document stage; tender stage; and construction stage.</p> <p>Regarding the provision of a swimming pool in north Fingal, a proposal for a new pool in Skerries, County Dublin, was originally included in the 2000 round of the local authority swimming pool programme.  The Department approved the preliminary report in January 2001.  As no contract documents or tender reports were ever received for Skerries, no grant was approved for that project.  The Skerries project was planned as a public private partnership.  In March 2009, the Department received a letter from Fingal County Council stating that this proposal was terminated due to difficulties with the residential element of the proposed scheme and that the new priority for Fingal County Council was to locate a pool in Balbriggan.  In April 2009, Fingal County Council forwarded a preliminary report for the proposed Balbriggan pool.  As the Senator has outlined, the proposal was for Balbriggan Rugby Football Club, in conjunction with a private operator, to build a swimming pool on the club's grounds at Balrothery.  It was proposed that the pool would be managed by the swimming pool operator, which would put finance in place for the development.</p> <p>The OPW approved the preliminary report for the Balbriggan proposal in May 2009, subject to a minor modification and subject to the council and the Department being satisfied that the tender process would be transparent and fair.  The council was asked to consider issues of procurement and state aid to a private operator and to ensure all relevant EU directives would be adhered to.  I understand that due to difficulties in adhering to these requirements, no further progress was made with the project at the Balbriggan site.</p> <p>Accordingly, my Department wrote to Fingal County Council in January 2016 to raise concerns about the delay and to ask the council to consider withdrawing this project from the local authority swimming pool programme.  The letter stated that if Fingal County Council agreed to the withdrawal of Balbriggan swimming pool from the local authority swimming pool programme, it may be possible for Fingal County Council and Balbriggan Rugby Football Club to receive a sports capital programme allocation instead.  Fingal County Council agreed to the voluntary withdrawal of the Balbriggan project from the local authority swimming pool programme and the Department formally notified the council of its removal in April 2016.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Shane Ross:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1974"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1974&amp;amp;pid=ShaneRoss&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Fingal County Council subsequently applied for a special sports capital programme allocation for Balbriggan RFC.  The application must meet all of the usual terms and conditions of the programme and funding is capped at &euro;500,000.  I understand the application is under ongoing consideration in my Department, with Balbriggan RFC recently having received approval to go to tender.</p><p>With regard to swimming pools, the projects remaining in the current local authority swimming pool programme are those in Castlebar, Buncrana, Edenderry and Lucan, all of which are at various stages.  The priority in 2018 is to progress these projects.</p><p>With regard to the future funding of swimming pools, the issue the Senator raises, the national development plan contains a commitment to establish a new "Large Scale Sport Infrastructure Fund", with at least &euro;100 million available in the coming years.  My officials are in the process of drafting the terms and conditions of the new fund and engaging with relevant stakeholders in that regard.  An announcement on when applications will be accepted will be made once the terms and conditions have been finalised.  It will be open to all local authorities, including Fingal County Council, to submit an application for any suitable project under the terms that will apply.  In addition, the upcoming national sports policy which I expect to be considered by the Government in the coming weeks, with a view to its publication shortly thereafter, will include a specific focus on how the Government should fund sports facilities, including swimming pools, in the years ahead.  </p><p>I hope this clarifies the current position.  I thank the Senator for raising the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#K00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his response which is practically identical to the one I received on the same issue this time last year.  The only difference is that whereas the Minister indicated that the priority in 2018 would be to progress the projects mentioned, I was informed last year that the priority in 2017 was to progress them.  It appears that the project has not advanced in the meantime.</p> <p>The Minister referred to the commitment to establish a large-scale sports infrastructure fund and stated &euro;100 million would be available in the coming years.  Is this a reference to the additional funding which he last year indicated would be allocated to his Department in the mid-term capital review?  If so, has this funding been received or does the Minister hope to receive it in the future?</p> <p>The Minister stated the terms and conditions for the fund were being finalised.  Will they be finalised by the end of this month or perhaps by the end of the year?  I would appreciate it if the Minister provided a timeframe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#K00300"><p>I thought I had answered the Senator's question.  It is somewhat unfair to state the fund has not progressed.  It has because we have the results of the mid-term capital review which we did not have this time last year.  In addition, as part of the Department's submission in the mid-term review of the capital plan, additional funding of &euro;100 million has been allocated for a large-scale sports infrastructure fund.  This will allow consideration to be given to new swimming pool projects.  It will be open to all local authorities, including Fingal County Council, to submit an application under the terms that will apply.  The relevant division of the Department is in the process of drafting the terms and conditions for the new large-scale sports infrastructure fund and engaging with the relevant stakeholders in that regard.  I expect applications to be ready in the coming months and allocations to be made as soon as possible thereafter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#K00400"><p>Has the Department received an allocation of &euro;100 million for the fund?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#K00500"><p>The Senator may not make a further contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#K00600"><p>In that case, I will assume that the allocation has been received.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#K00700"><p>I am not sure what the Senator can or cannot assume.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.51" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.52" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#N00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Data Protection Bill 2018 [<i>Seanad Bill amended by the D&aacute;il</i>] &ndash; Report and Final Stages, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business, and No. 2, motion for earlier signature of the Data Protection Bill 2018, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#N00300"><p>I am alarmed and saddened today to learn of the rise in suicide rates among young women living in Dublin South-Central.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We learned that there were 37 deaths by suicide in Dublin South-Central in 2017, 50% of whom were women.  The numbers are equal, but this is a very new departure.  Unfortunately, young men are more likely to take their lives by suicide.  There has been a rise in the number of women doing so.  These women have been described by HSE psychiatrists from Dublin South-Central as a new profile of women and it was stated that the statistics are unique to the area. </p><p>They include mothers with young children, women who were early school leavers, women who are homeless, women with adverse childhood experiences and women with drug and substance abuse histories.  These figures are very worrying and shocking and cannot continue.  They demonstrate the importance of women's mental health.  These women clearly did not have the right supports and are not being given any supports from the State.  I hope the figures do not become the norm into the future.  It is very worrying that the figures are so unique to one of the poorest parts of our country.  We need to take heed of them and do something about the issue.  It is outrageous that it has been described by psychiatrists working for the HSE as a unique situation to the particular area.  I would like the Minister to come to the House to discuss this matter.</p><p>The second issue I would like to raise is the former Harold's Cross stadium site which has been earmarked for use as a school.  I have been contacted by groups of parents from primary schools in Dublin 8 and 12 who have raised concerns about their exclusion from the process by which the Minister is awarding patronage to the intended school for the site.  I would like to ask the Minister for Education and Skills to reconsider disallowing groups in Dublin 8 and 12 from participating in the process for applying for patronage of the school at the site.  I cannot understand why they would be disallowed from applying for patronage as the school is in close proximity to residents of Dublin 8 and 12.  There is a lack of multidenominational, non-fee paying schools in Dublin 8 and 12 and given their proximity to the site it is outrageous that parents have been excluded from the process.  Would it be possible for the Minister to come to the House to explain how the catchment area for the new school was decided and why Dublin 8 and 12 were excluded?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#O00200"><p>I refer to small and medium enterprises, SMEs, an area on which I will focus.  They are the backbone of our economy.  Some 97% of all businesses in Ireland are small or medium sized and employ a significant number of people.  The EU Commission recently published a report which stated that small and medium sized businesses in Ireland contribute &euro;55.5 billion to the Irish economy.  I want us to focus on this issue and support SMEs in any reasonable way we can in terms of their growth, development and sustaining them in future.</p> <p>I will focus on two areas today.  One is the skills gap.  A significant skills gap is appearing in Ireland, in particular in respect of SMEs.  Larger companies, many of which are multinational, are attracting many prospective employees, but SMEs do not have the resources to compete with them in incentivising people to work for them.  This is particularly true in rural, rather than urban, areas of Ireland.  I have the details of the report here.  It found a 39% skills gap in marketing, 35% in sales and 33% in production.  It is a significant in issue in the technology industry in Ireland.  Most of the technology industry comprises small and medium sized companies.  Some are based in third level institutions.</p> <p>Apprenticeships and qualified people staying in particular businesses are also issues.  Senator Craughwell spoke about pilots from the Air Corps on a number of occasions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2482"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2482&amp;amp;pid=PadraigOCeidigh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They are leaving in droves and we have to do something about it, from a State perspective and from an SME perspective.  Staff retention and acquiring staff are huge issues and I will come back with suggested solutions to these.  This Friday, 25 May, the general data protection regulation, GDPR, comes into effect but the majority of small and medium-sized businesses know next to nothing about it or about how it affects them, which will be in a huge way.  There are consequences, unintended when the legislation was passed, for small and medium-sized businesses with significant fines in what is significant legislation.  There is a significant disconnect between the State and SMEs on what it is about, how the legislation can be put into practice and its cost, which is very significant.  There should be workshops and some space should be afforded to SMEs to allow them to get up to speed with the legislation.</p><p>I have a couple of solutions.  We should have an effective employee share option programme, and I welcome the statement made yesterday by the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport at a round-table conference I attended regarding employees potentially having some form of a shareholding in State bodies.  A programme is available for SMEs called the SAYE programme, a Revenue-approved save-as-you-earn scheme.  It is a fraction of what is available in the UK and SME employers and employees are not taking it up.  It has to be a lot more user-friendly to be beneficial to both employers and employees.  By having such a scheme, employers and employees will stick together more and employees will not jump ship to larger employers as often as they do at the moment.  We now have a different problem from the one we had three years ago when there was unemployment of 14.5%.  It is now down to just over 5.5% so we need a very different strategy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#P00200"><p>I extend my sympathy and that of the Sinn F&eacute;in team to the families of Ana Kriegel and Jastine Valdez who lost their lives over the past week.  They are tragic and shocking situations and they should refocus us on the work we need to do to keep everyone, but particularly women, safe in Ireland.  Everybody is horrified at what happened in recent days.</p> <p>I also want to talk about agriculture and farming and about vulture funds.  Some 2,500 or even 3,000 farmers may be in danger of losing their lands to vulture funds.  This amounts to at least 150,000 acres under threat.  Vulture funds specialise in forcing though quick-fire sales when an alternative is available, and I have spoken to many farm families on this matter who tell me that vulture funds are refusing to engage.  The banks say the protection afforded to the loans they sold off to vulture funds continues after the sale but that is not the case.  The funds are refusing to restructure loans, meaning farmers are forced down the legal route when they do not have the money for the huge legal expenses which are involved in that.  The vulture funds have the money, however, because they are hugely wealthy companies in the first place but also because they get away without paying any tax.  The farming community do not get away without paying tax.  The smallest of farm incomes are taxed and farmers have to submit their returns every year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is a real contrast between how vulture funds and farm families are treated.  Recent comments were made in committees and by commentators that farmers are not engaging on non-performing loans.  It has been said again that non-performing loans have to be dealt with but that is not correct because in many cases the level of defaulter arrears is quite small.  Our experience is that farm loans are very attractive to vulture funds as their level of security is very strong.  The cynicism shown by the companies will have a devastating effect on families that have worked the land for generations and make a hugely positive contribution to their communities.  Does the Government have any plans to ensure the agricultural sector is not hit hardest and that forced sales to make a quick buck are not allowed to threaten the social fabric of rural Ireland.  One must ask who will end up owning those farms at the end of the day.  Farms are located in the middle of communities.  In some cases relatives often own parcels of adjoining land and the question is who will end up owning it.  That has significant consequences for us in the short, medium and long terms, and it needs to be stopped.  Legislation must be put in place to control vulture funds and how they are treating farm families at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#Q00200"><p>First, I join with Senator Conway-Walsh in expressing my horror at the brutal murder of two beautiful, young, intelligent women in this country.  We recently passed the Domestic Violence Bill but that is obviously not enough when young women can be just randomly assaulted and killed in the suburbs.</p><p>The second matter to which I wish to refer is child abuse within the Roman Catholic Church worldwide.  I note the fact that the Archbishop of Adelaide has been convicted of covering up child abuse.  He is the highest ranking member of the church to be so convicted.  The entire hierarchy of Chile has offered the Pope its resignation on this matter.  This is a good Pope.  He is a Christ-like man.  I think he is absolutely wonderful.  That is why I initiated the invitation to him from this House.  He learns on the hoof.  He first of all dismissed these accusations but when he went to Chile he learned about them and he has since apologised.  He invited three of the abuse victims to meet him in Rome.  That is a wonderful thing.  One of the victims, Juan Carlos Cruz, told the Spanish newspaper <i>El Pais</i>that the Pope told him during a meeting in the Vatican that the fact that he is gay does not matter.  Mr. Cruz said Pope Francis had also told him that God made him this way and loves him this way and it does not matter to him.  He said the Pope loves him this way and that he must be happy the way he is.  How wonderful.  What a magical transformation from the vicious, condemnation we got under the papacy of Pope Francis's two predecessors.  I welcome this very much, in particular since last week when I stood in the Phoenix Park at the papal cross holding a message asking the Pope to moderate the language of the catechism on this issue.  He certainly seems to me to have gone a considerable way and I welcome that fact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#Q00300"><p>I also add my sympathies to the families of Jastine Valdez and Ana Kriegel.  It is very sad to see a young girl going about her everyday business and to end up dying in such a brutal way.</p> <p>I wish to speak today about vacant properties in town centres in rural areas.  I would like to see tax reliefs such as we had during the Celtic tiger in order that people can do up their premises within a period of 12 months.  Councils should be given new powers in order that developers who bought premises in disrepair would be made to fix them up within a certain timeframe or councils could serve compulsory purchase orders.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ray Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2303"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2303&amp;amp;pid=RayButler&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In my constituency of Meath West, there are buildings in Athboy, Kells, Navan and Trim which have been left in a terrible state with no regard to health and safety.  Roofs are ready to fall in and slates are being blown off on windy days.  Walls are ready to collapse on pedestrians.  Tidy Towns groups try to clean up and do their best for competitions, but these premises are left to go to rack and ruin.  The local authority has erected barriers around some of these premises which means people cannot use the footpaths.  In Athboy, there is a bus stop right beside one of these premises and people have some job to board their buses.  Pedestrians have to step out onto the road to pass these premises.</p><p>We need legislation to address this problem.  I call for the Minister to come to the House to discuss that legislation.  I am not on a witch hunt here and I do not seek to belittle any owner of any premises, but it is unfair to others in the community when someone leaves premises in a terrible state.  I would like to see action taken and certain premises in rural Ireland tidied up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#R00200"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il also pays tribute to those who have died.  What happened to those young ladies was horrific and our sympathy is extended to their families.</p> <p>On education and the priority we place on it, I want to discuss investment in education before the next budget is decided.  I agree with Senator Ardagh that we need to have the Minister for Education and Skills attend the House in the next few days.  We have long prided ourselves on our terrific education system.  That is great.  There are great schools, principals, teachers and students.  We are placing huge pressure on parents, however, to keep the lights on in some schools.  It is just not good enough when they are paying tax to provide these utilities.</p> <p>I have been in contact with the Catholic Primary Schools Management Association and individual primary school principals following the slashing of &euro;100 million in capitation grants from education budgets over a number of years.  Capitation grants are paid to voluntary primary and secondary schools based on the number of recognised pupils enrolled.  While the grant is supposed to cover the overall cost of running schools, it fails to meet these.  Although it costs as much to run a large primary school as to run a secondary school, the rate of pay for the latter is almost three times the rate for the former.  Primary schools are losing out.  Unless parents reach deep into their pockets, some schools will be at a disadvantage.  While some schools are lucky to have amazing fundraising committees, the parents at others are under severe stress because they cannot pay their voluntary contribution.  They simply cannot afford it.  While we spin the idea of free education, any parent will say that it is far from free.</p> <p>I join principals in calling for the restoration of the grant to the pre-cut level of &euro;200 per annum per child.  We must invest more in the schools we have now.  We must complete the school building projects we have started and fulfil the promises we have made before announcing new schools and, as usual, blaming the guys from before.  Our children deserve our full commitment to giving them all the best chance, not just those with wealthy parents or machine-like fundraising committees.  Grants for primary schools can certainly be increased if we see them as a necessity.  We all look at them that way, or at least those of us who have put our children through the Irish school system.  If the grants were restored, we could then contribute for nice things instead of paying for heat, light and paper as is happening now.</p> <p>I call on the Minister to come to the House to address this very serious issue.  Children are returning to school in September and their parents are panicking about what they can pay.  They just do not have the money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#R00300"><p>I join Members in offering sympathy to the family of Ms Jastine Valdez.  It is a beautiful part of the country and it is hard to imagine that a young lady walking along and minding her own business could be grabbed and murdered.  I also offer my sympathy to the family of Mark Hennessy whose wife and two children will be left trying to explain matters to themselves if it is proved that he killed this girl.  I cannot begin to imagine what those children will grow up thinking of their father.  While it is easy to show sympathy for the person who was murdered, we must also have some respect for the family of the murderer.</p> <p>I note also that there has been a rush to judge the actions of the garda who fired the shots.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->None of us can make any judgment on that case.  None of us was there.  None of us knew what was going on.  I commend the garda for doing what he thought was right at the time.  Time will tell whether the decision he took, obviously, a split-second decision, was the right one.</p><p>Yesterday, in Galway, the Minister for Finance delivered a speech on insurance and the insurance industry and it was most impressive.  The work that is being done on insurance, particularly for young drivers, is quite impressive.  I understand there has been as much as a 20% drop in premiums in some cases.  That is good work.  However, the Minister told the assembly in Galway yesterday that there is urgent legislation needed and he is ready to move on some immediately.  He stated there were four pieces of legislation.  While there is a need from time to time to have statements in this House on various issues, can we shorten the statements and find time to start introducing the Minister's legislation?  It is important that we get that legislation before the House.  I would ask the Leader to consider that and let us know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#S00200"><p>I presume the issue the Senator raised about that incident on Sunday where the man was shot is a matter on which GSOC will decide and it is not a matter for the Leader or the Government, although I understand the Senator's reasons for raising it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#S00300"><p>I draw the attention of the House to the fact that today is the 20th anniversary of the signing of the Good Friday Agreement which brought power-sharing to the Northern Ireland Assembly.  It brought cross-Border institutions and the principle of consent, and recognised the legitimacy of the people of Ireland to aspire to a united Ireland while recognising the current wish of the majority to remain in the UK.  Over the weekend we saw a poll which effectively looked at a Border poll.  It is quite interesting that should Northern Ireland remain in the customs union and the Single Market, the results would not be hugely in favour of a united Ireland but should a hard Brexit happen, we would be in a very different space.  We should have a debate in this House regarding this poll and its significance.</p> <p>We had the royal wedding last Saturday.  I did not watch it, but I visited pubs and I visited my mother in the nursing home.  Nobody talks about Fine Gael, Fianna F&aacute;il or Sinn F&eacute;in Ard-Fheiseanna that are broadcast live but everybody seemed to be talking about the royal wedding.  It was a little crass of politicians to state is was a waste for RT&Eacute; to spend funding on the royal wedding because there is a significant amount of people on the island of Ireland who want to watch this.  Some 20% of the people in this country aspire to watching royal events.  If we really are reaching out and talking about uniting the people of our country, remarks such as this are crass.  Everyone knows who I am talking about.  These are one-off remarks and they do not represent the thinking of a certain party.  For anybody talking about a waste of money in RT&Eacute;, if we want to unite the people of Ireland it will cost our country an awful lot more.  I have no problem in putting my hand in my pocket but it is a two-way street.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#S00400"><p>I add my voice on the matter of the brutal and tragic killing or murder of a young child and a young woman over the past few days.  I am not sure about others, but I and the women of Ireland feel a deep injury at the killing off of the voices of this girl and this woman who would change our nation.  My sympathies and heartfelt condolences go to the families.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->According to recent research by the <i>Irish Journal of Psychological Medicine</i>, the rates of psychosis and mental illness among inmates in prisons is much higher than for the rest of the population, yet we have the lowest <i>per capita</i>secure psychiatric bed availability.  The prevalence of mental and psychological illnesses is at 8% in prisons.  Alcohol and substance misuse disorders are at 51% and the homelessness rate of prisoners on committal is at 18%.  They are all significantly higher than the general population and all are both a cause and consequence of imprisonment.  We have the opening in 2020 of the new forensic unit in Portrane which will accommodate some of the extensive waiting lists.<br/><br/>There are people in approved centres and in prisons.  The majority in prisons are very unwell and awaiting transfer to this high security unit, the Central Mental Hospital in Dundrum.  Some wait for 15 years and some are released because they have served their sentence with no treatment whatsoever and then come back into the prisons because of reoffending due to mental instability.  We know that it increases demand, that there is a staff shortage and that retention and recruitment is difficult.  It is endemic throughout health services.<br/><br/>Tomorrow, at the Joint Committee on Future of Mental Health Care, we will discuss this and plans for the future.  I hope that the Minister will at some stage come and inform the rest of the Members of this House of policy and plans to realise A Vision for Change, although it is well past its sell-by date, and to give the healthcare needed by patients in the prison system which criminalises them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#T00200"><p>Senators might notice that some of us are wearing our green ribbons in the Chamber today.  I know Senator Devine works very hard on the areas of mental health, as does Senator Ray Burke.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#T00300"><p>It is Colm Burke.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#T00400"><p>The green ribbon signifies our opposition to the stigmatisation of mental health here in Ireland and acts as a reminder of the damage that such stigmas have done to those suffering from mental health issues in the past and in the present.  One would think at this stage that this would be clear and would not be a controversial issue.  During the current debate on the referendum to repeal the eighth amendment, we have seen some serious assaults on the concept of mental health and we have heard words like "vague mental health" and terms that simply contribute to the further stigmatisation of mental health.</p> <p>On "Claire Byrne Live" and "The Week in Politics", it was insinuated by someone that he does not believe that mental health is health.  That was Senator Mullen.  I do not know what utopia he lives in but I live in a world where mental health is a real health issue to which we in this country, as Senator Devine just said, are not giving enough time .  In this debate, the fact that something such as mental health should be lowered by people from this House is unacceptable.  I ask for Senator Mullen to come into the House to explain to us why he said that he does not believe that mental health is health.  I would like him to qualify that statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#T00500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#T00600"><p>I join my colleagues in conveying my sympathies to the families who have suffered a loss over the past week.  It is a difficult time for them and for all of the people directly or indirectly involved in the events of the past seven days.  It is important that we pay tribute to everyone involved in helping, including the Garda, those who volunteered to assist the Garda, and those who gave information about the events at a very early date.  They reacted in a positive and proactive way to assist the Garda.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The remains have been identified and located in both cases but there are many cases of remains not being located with families left without knowing what happened when a loved one went missing.  That is the reason I introduced the Civil Law (Missing Persons) Bill in 2016.  It has passed two Stages in the House.  I have had discussions with officials in the Department of Justice and Equality about it and they intend to table amendments, but I ask the Leader to progress the legislation.  Where a body is not found, a death certificate cannot be issued and that causes problems for families.  Will he ask the Minister for Justice and Equality to take the next Stage of the Bill?  A mechanism like this has been in operation in Scotland for more than 30 years and it is time it was in operation in Ireland as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#U00200"><p>I pass on my condolences to the families of Ana Kriegel and Jastine Valdez.  As a former councillor in D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown, I am familiar with Rathmichael and Cherrywood, as I have driven through them regularly.  These were awful tragedies for both families, particularly the abduction in Enniskerry where someone was walking along a road and had this happen to her.  I extend my sympathies to her family.</p> <p>I wish to raise the planning process.  The Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government is busy on the housing and local government fronts but the planning process is antiquated and is not delivering for those who make planning applications or those who have issues with those who apply.  Recently, other Members have raised the Apple issue in Athenry, County Galway, and how we build critical infrastructure.  We must also accommodate the housing needs of everybody in the State and those who feel under siege in their communities from what is going on.  It is a long-winded, convoluted and expensive process and it is of a different time.</p> <p>I do not blame anybody working in a planning department.  They are doing their best 99.9% of the time, if not all the time, under outdated and inappropriate legislation in many cases.  It would be helpful to invite the Minister or the Minister of State, Deputy English, to the Chamber for a discussion on what changes the Government proposes to the planning process because we need to deliver infrastructure for the benefit of all our citizens.  We also need safeguards to ensure the infrastructure takes account of the current population, pylons, wind farms, high rise buildings and Luas or metro extensions.</p> <p>All these issues take much longer that most of us would like.  In other countries a light rail system is promised one year and, two years later, it is operational.  Here something is promised and 20 years later it is still not operational.  I do not criticise a particular Government but the planning system tends to slow us down and the current Government needs to examine it.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to the House as soon as possible to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#U00300"><p>I welcome the announcement yesterday by the National Youth Council of Ireland, NYCI, that based on preliminary figures, 125,000 young people have been added to the supplementary electoral register ahead of this week's referendum.  This highlights that young people have a deep affinity with the issue of abortion and that they will respond and vote in droves when engaged.  They are major stakeholders in our political system.</p> <p>The marriage equality referendum, the third anniversary of which is today, proved that young people, when engaged, will be at the forefront and cutting edge of change.  I commend the efforts of the NYCI, the Union of Students in Ireland, individual students' unions and youth groups who tirelessly reach out to young people and fill a void on the part of the State and its institutions, which largely shirk their responsibilities when engaging with young people and new voters.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The last data collated on youth turnout was compiled in the 2011 election by the CSO.  In that election 62% of young people aged between 18 and 25 voted and the overall turnout was 69%.  I expect it would have been higher if it were not for emigration in 2011.  When asked by Deputy Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire in July last year whether the Government would consider collating turnout data by age, the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, stated the Government had no immediate plans to do so.  There seems to be no political will to collate such important data.  The Department does not seem to want to place that responsibility on any other public body either.  Without sufficient data on age, a behavioural analysis of youth turnout cannot be carried out.  We also cannot encourage it.  Following the referendum, I will call on the Minister of State with responsibility for electoral reform to the House to discuss options for enhancing youth voting and to ask why such obvious measures have yet to be put in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#V00200"><p>I raise the issue of farm safety.  In 2017, 50 people lost their lives in farm-related accidents.  Farms, by their nature, are generally family enterprises.  They are great places to grow up but unfortunately dangerous places to live in.  The age profile of those killed is also of great concern.  The old and the young are exceptionally vulnerable to death and serious injury on farms.  Animals, machinery and slurry pits are among the greatest dangers posed to adults and children on family farms.  The nature of the accidents on our farms can have long-lasting, heartbreaking and devastating impacts on families.  At this time of year, farmers are exceptionally busy working long hours, often on their own.  In cases such as this, fatigue can creep in.  The Health and Safety Authority, HSA, has now refocused on improving farm safety by way of a television and radio campaign that focuses on all aspects of farm safety.  I too appeal to members of the farming community to be extra careful on their farms.  It is an exceptionally busy time of year for farmers.  School children will be getting their school holidays shortly and will be helping on the farms.  I appeal to all members of the farming community to be extra careful and to be conscious of all the dangers that surround them as they go about their daily tasks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#V00300"><p>I thank the 14 Members of the House who made contributions to the Order of Business.  On behalf of the Government and the House and on my own behalf, I join with Senators Conway-Walsh, Norris, Butler, Murnane O'Connor, Craughwell, Devine, Colm Burke and Horkan in offering our sympathies to the families of Jastine Valdez and Anastasia Kriegel on their very sad deaths.  The brutal and callous killings sent a chill across society.  They were brutal.  We all know there is no place for killing in our society.  We must always respect each other.  Today there are families distraught.  They have lost a loved one, an only daughter.  It is mind-boggling.  Senator Craughwell also mentioned the family of Mr. Hennessy.  We should remember that family as well.  I commend the garda&iacute; for their tremendous work.  I commend all the first responders who helped and those who gave assistance.  We must always work to ensure our society and our streets are safe for all people.  When one sees young women and girls being killed, it prompts the question: why and what more can we do as a society?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I join in the condemnation of the killings and hope we will all stand in support of, and solidarity with, the families at this awful time.</p><p>Senator Ardagh raised the suicide rates in Dublin South-Central.  The increase is a worry.  Senators Devine and Grace O'Sullivan also referred to the issue of mental health.  First, the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Jim Daly, is focused on increasing resources in the mental health area to ensure that we continue to develop mental health services and to improve access to treatment and assessment.  He secured an increase in the budget for 2018 and current funding is &euro;910 million.  As Senator Devine mentioned, there is capital investment in new facilities and new staff.  Mental health is an issue we must continue to prioritise.  I agree with Senator Devine about the people in our prisons.  They are in there for a variety of reasons but if one believes in restorative justice and rehabilitation we must always ensure that our prison system, which has one function we are all aware of, rehabilitates people as well.  I agree with the Senator that people in our prisons who have mental health issues deserve to be looked after and treated.  Equally, I agree with Senator Grace O'Sullivan that mental health is health, pure and simple.  Regardless of what viewpoint one has in the referendum campaign, mental health is about the health and well-being of all citizens.  It is an important issue that must be prioritised.</p><p>In referring to the increase Senator Ardagh also referred to the new profile of women.  It is a worry.  The mental health of women is an important matter and it needs to be addressed in view of the figures she gave us today.  As I said, improvements have been made in a variety of areas but it is distressing to hear Senator Ardagh's remarks.  I do not have that information to hand.  However, we will have a continuing debate on mental health.  She also referred to the former greyhound racing stadium in Harold's Cross in Dublin.  It is a good news story that there will be a new primary and secondary school with 1,000 places.  I believe it is open to all prospective patrons and patron bodies to apply for patronage of a new school under the patronage process.  The Department of Education and Skills is developing a new online patronage scheme.  I am not familiar with the matter Senator Ardagh raised but I will be happy to invite the Minister, Deputy Bruton, to the House again.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh spoke about small and medium enterprises and awareness of GDPR.  The Irish Small and Medium Enterprises Association, ISME, produced a survey which showed that 90% of small and medium enterprises are aware of GDPR but the Senator is correct that we must continue to promulgate awareness of the effect and potential consequences of the new regime that comes into force at the end of the month.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Bruton, and the Minister of State, Deputy Halligan, have been very proactive on the skills gap.  I agree with Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh that small and medium enterprises are the heartbeat of our country.  The Government is committed to developing that sector.  I will be happy to invite the Minister of State, Deputy Halligan, to the House to discuss the points the Senator made in the context of small and medium enterprises.</p><p>Senator Conway-Walsh raised the agriculture sector and the issue of vulture funds with regard to farmers, particularly small farmers.  The Government is acutely aware of this.  I hope the loans can be resolved within the existing bank structure.  The banks and the farmers or landowners have an obligation to engage.  As the Senator knows, when one engages one puts a stop on the clock and an element of fear and uncertainty is taken away.  It is important to recognise that the farming community and small and medium enterprises are at the heart of what we are as a people and nation.  That is the reason there is regulation by the Central Bank to regulate the matter raised by Senator Conway-Walsh.  However, it is important to have engagement and conversation so I will be happy to invite the Minister to the House to discuss the matter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is an issue we recognise as important.</p><p>Senator Norris raised the issue of the court case involving the cover-up of child abuse and the Archbishop of Adelaide.  I am happy to let the courts decide on that matter.  We have a very robust child protection code in our country which needs to be upheld at all times.</p><p>Senator Butler raised the issue of vacant properties.  The Government is aware of the needs in some rural towns.  A variety of schemes have been introduced by Government to try to incentivise people to relocate and open businesses, but there is an obligation and duty on local authorities, Government and the business sector to work together to ensure that we continue to have vibrant rural towns.</p><p>Senator Murnane O'Connor raised the issue of education.  I regret that she is not here.  I was not going to blame Fianna F&aacute;il for cutting funding at the beginning.  I was going to say that the Minister, Deputy Bruton, is committed to increasing the capitation grant in the forthcoming budget.  He was the Minister who secured an extra &euro;1 billion for education in the previous two budgets.  He has strengthened the core of our education system.  The Minister has created more school places, employed additional teachers and taken on more special needs assistants.  This means that the pupil-teacher ratio has been reduced and that our education system has more teachers, more places and more new buildings, which is a pretty good record, to be fair to him.  A sum of &euro;10 billion was allocated for education in the previous budget, and the Minister has also committed to reducing costs for parents with the forthcoming publication of the education (parent and student charter) Bill.  Senator Murnane O'Connor should reflect upon that.</p><p>Senator Craughwell raised the issue of the garda who fired the shots on Saturday night.  The Cathaoirleach rightly said that there is an inquiry by the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission, GSOC.  I will not stray into that area.  The Senator also mentioned the Minister of Finance's speech in Galway.  I am happy to have the Minister come to the House to debate that matter.</p><p>Senator Feighan recognised the importance of the Good Friday Agreement.  Is our country not a better place as a result of the signatures of Ireland, the UK and the parties in the North to the Good Friday Agreement?  It is important that we continue to promote the benefits of the agreement.  In that context it is equally important that we all resolve to have Stormont back in action and a government in the North of our country.  I commend Senator Feighan on  his work not just in the UK and on British-Irish and North-South bases but across the United States where he has been promoting Ireland and good relations.</p><p>I commend Senator Feighan on his words of wisdom on the royal wedding last weekend.  While many people pretended that they did not watch it, the number of people who said to me, when I was out canvassing, that they could not talk because they were watching the royal wedding was extraordinary.  It is good that we can have the conversation here.  It is important that we continue to promote good relations.  We are lucky that Senator Marshall has joined us to show that we can build bridges and have diverse views in the Houses of the Oireachtas.  That is a positive.</p><p>Senator Grace O'Sullivan raised the issue of the green ribbon and mental health.  I have addressed that.  Senator Colm Burke raised the issue of his Civil Law (Missing Persons) Bill 2016.  I assure the House that it is not the Leader stalling the Bill.  I commend the Senator on his work.  He makes the very wise and legitimate point that death certificates cannot be issued and that is a significant issue for many families awaiting news or who, for a variety of reasons, understand that the only outcome is going to be death.  I commend Senator Burke on his work.  We on the Government side will bring that Bill back to the House as soon as possible.  It will not be held up from my end.</p><p>Senator Horkan raised the issues of planning, the planning process and the need to have a debate about planning.  He is right.  The decision by Apple in the context of the planning delay illustrates difficulties we have and which we must overcome.  The Senator is right and Government is looking at the issue of streamlined and fast-tracked planning.  It is important that we look at having a debate on making our planning system more efficient.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While we do not want to go back to the bad old days, it is important, as the Senator rightly said, for the development of key infrastructure to take place in a variety of ways.  I think his point is well made.</p><p>Senator Warfield raised issues relating to the supplementary register, young people and voting.  I think his comments highlight the need to have an electoral commission that can take charge of election issues independent of the Government and of the Oireachtas.  I would be happy to have a debate on this matter when we resume after the referendum.  It is important for us to have an independent electoral commission to deal with the electoral register, encourage people to vote, look at what happens between elections and manage the democratic process.  I would be happy to have a debate on this issue.</p><p>Senator Gallagher spoke about farm safety.  As he will recall, Senator Conway chaired the Seanad Public Consultation Committee when it considered this matter.  The Minister has been to the House to discuss farm safety.  The points made by Senator Gallagher are very relevant as we approach the busy season for the farming community.  The Senator highlighted the potential dangers associated with parts of the farm like the slurry pit, the silage pit and the machinery yard.  It is important to create awareness.  Regardless of the section of the Government that deals with this issue, it is important during the busy farming season for people to be aware of the potential disasters that exist on the farm.  Farm safety is something we must highlight.  I will be happy for the Minister to come back to the House again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.84" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.85" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.25 p.m. and resumed at 4.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.86" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#DD00100">Data Protection Bill 2018: [Seanad Bill amended by the Dil] Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#DD00200"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 148, this Bill is deemed to have passed its First, Second and Third Stages in the Seanad and has been placed on the Order Paper for Report Stage.  On the question, "That the Bill be received for final consideration", the Minister may explain the purpose of the amendments made by the D&aacute;il and this is looked upon as the report of the D&aacute;il amendments to the Seanad.  </p> <p>For the convenience of Senators, I have arranged for the printing and circulation of those amendments.  The Minister will deal separately with the subject matter of each related group of amendments.  I have also circulated a proposed grouping in the House.  A Senator may contribute once on each grouping.  I remind Senators that the only matters that may be discussed are the amendments made by the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.88" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be received for final consideration."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#DD00275"><p>I call on the Minister to deal with the subject matter of the amendments in group 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#DD00300"><p>I want to welcome Senators back to Report Stage, which deals with amendments made to the Bill by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  Before introducing the amendments in group 1, that is, amendments Nos. 1, 9, 11 to 23, inclusive, and 85 to 83, inclusive, I wish to thank Senators for their detailed comments, all of which were helpful to me and the Bill in its latest iteration.  Senators will be aware that the GDPR comes into force on Friday of this week.  I hope we can get through our business as expeditiously as possible.  In this regard, I look forward to a continuation of the constructive approach adopted by the House during the earlier detailed discussions we had on the legislation.  I look forward to the support of the House for the completion of the Bill's passage today.  This will be necessary in order to ensure its entry into force on Friday to coincide with the GDPR.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The entry into force of the GDPR necessitates the amendments to the Acts of the Oireachtas which contain cross-references to the 1988 Act and the 2002 Act, or which may be otherwise affected by the entry into force of the GDPR.  These changes form the subject matter of the largest group of D&aacute;il amendments, namely, amendments Nos. 112 to 121, inclusive, and 123 to 184, inclusive.  Subject to the approval of this House, it is not my intention to deal with the amendments individually but as a group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#EE00200"><p>That is in order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#EE00300"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#EE00400"><p>It is agreed.  We are here to assist the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#EE00500"><p>I should never have given any indication that I intended doing anything without agreement or the prior approval of Senators.  Many of the amendments made by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann arise from proposals and suggestions first made during the early discussions here and most of them go in the direction advocated during those discussions.  I trust, therefore, that they will find ready acceptance here this evening.</p> <p>The first group of amendments is concerned with the membership and operation of the data protection commission, established in Part 2 of the Bill.  The following amendments form part of this group.  Amendment No. 1 adjusts the Long Title to the Bill.  Amendment No. 9 inserts subsections (3) and (4) in section 12 to clarify that the commission is designated for the purposes of Chapter 4, mutual assistance with the Council of Europe's data protection convention - these provisions are currently in section 15 of the 1988 Act.  As regards section 15 on the membership of the commission, amendment No. 11 clarifies that the Public Appointments Service shall recommend a person for appointment as commissioner following an open selection competition held for that purpose, and that it should appoint a selection panel for that purpose, according with the normal Public Appointments Service procedures for selection in respect of such appointments.</p> <p>Amendments Nos. 12 to 14, inclusive, deal with the retirement age of the commissioners.  Amendment No. 15 replaces section 18, regarding the acting commissioner, with a more detailed text which precludes a member of staff acting as a commissioner from exercising certain specified functions more appropriate to the commissioner.  Amendment No. 16 amends section 20 to clarify matters relating to the assignment of staff to the data protection commission.  Amendments Nos. 17 to 23, inclusive, involve technical changes to section 23, which deals with the accounts of the commission.</p> <p>Amendments Nos. 83 and 84 incorporate a reference to the data protection commission into section 92 in order to safeguard investigations and prosecutions taken by the commission under Part 5, an issue which exercised Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile and other Senators.  Amendment No. 85 clarifies that the commission is not a supervisory authority for courts when acting in their judicial capacity under Part 5.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#EE00600"><p>I recognise the strong engagement the Minister had with this House throughout this process and the fact that he has taken on board many proposals in the D&aacute;il on Committee and Report Stages.  I believe there was a change, which was made on Committee Stage but was undone on report Stage, relating to the appointment of data protection commissioners and I wonder if the Minister could clarify.  The idea of having a role for the data protection commissioner on the selection panel in the European Data Protection Supervisor's office was discussed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The data protection commission in Ireland will play a key role on a European level.  Much as the fundamental rights agency has a role in the selection process for the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, it had been envisaged that there would be a potential role for those European authorities in the selection process.  I know that had been discussed and I believed the change had been made on Committee Stage so perhaps the Minister might just explain the rationale for why that change has not been maintained and perhaps give some assurances that we will ensure these are open competitions and that we ensure the very best people that are available on a European level or globally can come and fill the roles.  It has been made clear by the current Data Protection Commissioner that this is a key role for Ireland.  We will effectively be a first line of regulation in many cases, certainly affecting the large tech agencies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF00200"><p>I acknowledge the point raised by Senator Higgins.  It is one that did form part of our discussions here earlier, and one that was the subject matter of discussion in the D&aacute;il.</p> <p>My officials did make direct contact with the office of the European Data Protection Supervisor, EDPS, on the matter of a subsection that may require him to nominate a member of the selection panel.  We received a response and that response merely said that the EDPS had reservations about the idea and did not think it would fit within the system of international co-operation.  We did notify the office but ultimately, the European Data Protection Board advised us of its wish to stay neutral and impartial in all of the issues surrounding appointments and procedures.  It was precisely because of that, that we decided to proceed as we are now doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF00300"><p>I accept-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF00400"><p>I am sorry but I cannot allow Senator Higgins in again.  We are moving on to group 2.  These amendments relate to the appropriate authority and they are the subject matter of amendments Nos. 2 to 4, inclusive, 89 and 96.  Does Senator Higgins wish to speak on this group?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF00500"><p>Is the Minister speaking on them?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF00600"><p>The purpose of the amendments in group 2, which are somewhat technical in nature, is twofold.  The amendments to subsections (1) and (2) of section 3 provide that where an appropriate authority under the Civil Service Regulation Acts designates a civil servant as its controller, any action taken by a data subject to seek compensation and any administrative fine imposed by the data protection commission shall be taken against, or imposed on, the appropriate authority, rather than the designated civil servant.  That is the purpose of amendments Nos. 2, 3, 89 and 96.  These adjustments arise from the Seanad&rsquo;s earlier acceptance of my proposal to permit the imposition of administrative fines, subject to a limit of &euro;1 million, on public authorities and bodies for infringements of the GDPR.</p> <p>Second, the purpose of amendment No. 4 is to insert a new subsection (3) into section 3, the text of which is carried over from section 1(3)(c) of the Data Protection Act 1988.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF00700"><p>I acknowledge the very important step that was taken by the Minister, which he took in the previous debate, to agree to the imposition of administrative fines of up to &euro;1 million on public authorities.  That is appropriate.  I see the concern the Minister is addressing in the amendments.  I accept them and I think they are practicable.  It is still important that there would be a strong level of internal accountability within public authorities but in terms of the imposition of fines it is appropriate that it is the authority rather than the individual who would pay them.</p> <p>It will be an important test for the Government to follow through on the agreement that fines can be imposed.  It is important that we see a seriousness of approach and message to all public authorities in the implementation of the Bill.  I am sure the Minister can assure me of that.</p> <p>Given that I did not have a chance to come back in on the previous group, I wish to add that I accept the Minister's points on the European bodies but could he assure me that it will be a European-wide competition for the data commission?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF00800"><p>Yes, it will be an open competition that will be advertised.  It will be open to anybody who believes he or she has the appropriate level of expertise and will follow the Public Appointments Service practice and procedure.</p> <p>I thank Senator Higgins for the earlier points she made in respect of administrative fines imposed on public bodies.  We had a pretty comprehensive debate on that.  She need be in no doubt as to the will on the part of the Government to ensure that this legislation is working and workable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF00900"><p>Group 3 concerns amendments relating to regulations, which is the subject matter of amendments Nos. 5, 30 to 32, inclusive, 38, 44, 53 and 67.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF01000"><p>Senators will recall that several sections, notably sections 35, 37, 48, 52, 57 and 70, provide for possible future regulations to be made by the Minister for Justice and Equality or another Minister.  The Bill, as initiated, provided for consultation by the relevant Minister with the Minister for Justice and Equality and the data protection commission prior to the making of regulations.  Nonetheless, concerns were expressed in the House that the Bill granted an excessively wide margin of discretion to Ministers and that improved oversight by the Oireachtas would be desirable.  D&aacute;il amendments to the relevant sections have strengthened the role of the data protection commission and oversight by both Houses of the Oireachtas.</p> <p>As regards amendments Nos. 30, 32, 38, 44, 53 and 67, they will mean that where the Minister for Justice and Equality or another Minister consults the data protection commission on proposed regulations, the commission may make observations in writing on any matter that is of significant concern to it regarding the proposals.  If the Minister or relevant Minister proposes to proceed to make the regulations notwithstanding that concern, that Minister must provide a written explanation as to why he or she is proceeding to do so to the justice and equality committee of the Houses or any other relevant or appropriate committee.  That will ensure that any commission concerns that have not been taken on board by the relevant Minister must be brought to the attention of the appropriate Oireachtas committee.</p> <p>In addition, amendment No. 5, which amends section 6, will require that in the case of any regulations to be made under sections 48, 57 and 70, such regulations may be made only if both the D&aacute;il and Seanad have passed resolutions approving the draft regulations.  Amendment No. 31 deletes section 35(7) and its content is transferred to section 48 by means of amendment No. 38.  I am sure Senators will fully agree with the amendments which allow for a greater level of oversight and input by Members of this House and Members of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#FF01100"><p>I very strongly welcome this set of amendments.  One of the concerns that had been identified which was only partially addressed in the Seanad was around the lack of transparency and accountability in the circumstances under which exemptions were made in areas such as public interest.  I strongly commend all those in the D&aacute;il who put forward what I believe are extremely nuanced and constructive proposals that strengthen the Bill and ensure that, specifically in areas where exemption is being made to a data subject&rsquo;s rights or, crucially, where a decision is being made in the public interest, there is accountability and transparency.  It is in the public interest that exemptions in the public interest would be subjected to a proper process such as this.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These amendments will ensure we do not have a situation whereby any exception, or a series of exceptions, becomes the rule, but instead that an exception to the highest level of protection for data subjects always remains just that, an exception, and is subject to scrutiny.  I commend everyone in the D&aacute;il who proposed the amendments, and the Minister for accepting and keeping them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG00200"><p>I have nothing further to add.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG00300"><p>Group 4 comprises amendments relating to repeals and the scope of the Bill.  This is the subject matter of amendments Nos. 6 to 8, inclusive, 10, 65 and 77.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG00400"><p>Group 4 deals with aspects of sections 7, 8 and 14.  Amendments Nos. 6, 7 and 10 make a number of technical adjustments to subsections (3) and (4) of section 7 and to section 14.  Amendments Nos. 8 and 65 concern the scope of section 8.  They clarify that the data protection commission must complete any investigation under section 10 of the 1988 Act that was commenced by the Data Protection Commissioner but not completed before the establishment of the commission.  This matter was raised here during earlier discussions.  They also provide that the processing of personal data under the Criminal Justice (Forensic Evidence and DNA Database System) Act 2014 or the Vehicle Registration Data (Automated Searching and Exchange) Act 2018 shall continue to the extent that the 1988 Act applies to those Acts.  These are the so-called Pr&uuml;m measures, and the European Commission intends to table proposals to bring its data protection standards into line with the law enforcement directive in due course.  The Pr&uuml;m measures, comprising Council Decision 2008/615/JHA and 2008/616/JHA, are concerned with the automated exchange of data between member states in the matter of cross-border crime and terrorism.  The data concerns DNA profiles, fingerprints and vehicle registration data.  The DNA and fingerprint aspects of Pr&uuml;m are provided for in the 2014 Act, while the sharing of vehicle registration data is provided for in the 2018 Act, which was signed into law less than a month ago.</p> <p>Amendment No. 77 deletes section 86, which excluded Forensic Science Ireland from Part 5.</p> <p>I am happy to assure Senators that any investigations commenced by the Data Protection Commissioner but not completed before the establishment of the commission, which was raised by Senator Higgins and &Oacute; Donnghaile, does not require any great discussion, but I am very pleased to clarify the issues as raised by the Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG00500"><p>I welcome the Minister's assurance.  There is, of course, a section 10 investigation under way at present on the way the public services card has been rolled out and the single customer view system.  It is interesting because we are talking about forensics and crime.  It is funny that while we hear the phrases "cybersecurity" and "cyberterrorism" floated around, there have been very serious concerns about the way data has been stored in the single customer view data system.</p> <p>I welcome the Minister's assurance.  It is very important that we do not simply attempt to give legal sanction retrospectively to activities which may have taken place outside proper legal grounds in the period previous.  While the legislative context may change, it is still important to note that data gathered improperly must be dealt with in a way that fully acknowledges this.  This is not to pre-empt, as we do not know what the discussion will be or what the outcome of the Data Protection Commissioner's investigation will be.</p> <p>I welcome this.  I recognise the need for the exchange of forensic information and information relating to vehicle registration, although I would say this is an area we need to monitor very closely and ensure it is in line with all areas of policing.  We must ensure its usage and application does not end up extending inappropriately.  I know that is absolutely not the intention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG00600"><p>I welcome the comments made by Senator Higgins and acknowledge her earlier contributions and her contributions today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG00700"><p>We now move to group 5, amendments relating to the protection of children.  This is the subject matter of amendments Nos. 24 to 28, inclusive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG00800"><p>Group 5 comprises amendment Nos. 24 to 28, inclusive.  These amendments focus on safeguarding children and their data protection rights under the GDPR.  The subject was debated at some length in this House.  When I introduced sections 29 to 31, inclusive, in response to concerns and worries expressed by Senators I also introduced a review mechanism in section 30, which would have required a review of the digital age of consent of 13 years within three years.  I acknowledge the role of Senators in this regard and, in particular, Senator Ruane and others.  Since the Bill passed through the House on 28 March, sections 30 and 31 have been further amended and a new section has been inserted.  Amendment No. 25 has substituted 16 years for 13 years as the digital age of consent.  This means the review will take place within three years of the entry into force of the section, and will now review the suitability of 16 years rather than 13 years.  Amendment No. 26 extends the scope of codes of conduct for the protection of children under section 31.  It means a code may be drawn up to provide necessary safeguards for the processing of the personal data of children for the purposes of direct marketing and creating a personality and user profiles.</p> <p>Amendment No. 24 inserts a new section entitled "Micro-targeting and profiling of children".  During earlier discussions in the House, and during D&aacute;il debates, I had suggested, based on input from the Office of the Attorney General, that such a provision would be likely to infringe the GDPR and expose the State to infringement proceedings, and perhaps even sanctions.  Following acceptance of the amendment by the D&aacute;il, the Department has formally requested legal advice from the Office of the Attorney General and a response is awaited.  In the meantime, it may be necessary to delay or defer commencement of this section of the Bill, and I am happy to keep Senators informed of developments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG00900"><p>I thank the Minister for his engagement, particularly on this section.  I have been completely opposed to raising the age to 16, not only because I feel it inappropriate from a personal standpoint and as a parent and legislator, but also because I chose to listen to experts in the field, such as the CEO of Barnardos, the CEO of Childline and CEO of the Children's Rights Alliance.  Not listening to the people who are there to protect our children and advocate for our children was an odd move on behalf of some of the other political parties.  The amendment which the Minister states might be an issue is an amendment I support.  I understand the Minister's concerns about it, but for me it is a positive amendment.  My only fear is that it is weakened by the age of consent being set at 16.  The reason I believe it is weakened is from the beginning of the debate we heard from people who wanted the age set at 16 because this is about protecting children's data, protecting children online and protecting them from being targeted.  We will only allow children to stay within the loop of not being targeted through amendment No. 24.  Setting the age at 16 means those aged 13 must say they are 16, and by the time they turn 15 their online profile will state they are 18, which will allow them to be targeted before they have reached the age of consent.  While I see amendment No. 24 is very strong, those who campaigned to raise the age to 16 have done a disservice to the function of amendment No. 24 and I want to put this on the record.  I do not know why it was not picked up earlier in the D&aacute;il when Sinn F&eacute;in and Fianna F&aacute;il supported raising the age of consent to 16 that, in fact, amendment No. 24 would have done what we set out to do while also protecting children and allowing them to tell the truth about their age at 13.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#GG01000"><p>I want to add my own words of support for amendment No. 24 and its significance.  It is an important amendment.  This section of the Bill and the matters contained therein have proved contentious and difficult to deal with.  Despite this, there has been a great deal of co-operation and sincerity in terms of trying to come to a legislatively competent conclusion that can, if such a thing is possible, at least go some way in trying to meet the concerns about this and the differing and competing views on it.  I take Senator Ruane's points with deep sincerity because I know how passionate she is about this issue.  There is no doubt there is merit in what she has flagged, and that is the difficulty there has been with this part of the Bill.  Yes, we have had to listen to competing views and competing expertise on this.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have also had to listen to a wide range of parental and family views as well as those of children and young people.  For our part, it has been a difficult, long and drawn-out process internally in the Sinn F&eacute;in group within both Houses of the Oireachtas.  Ultimately, we have decided to err on the side of caution for the digital age of consent by opting for 16 years of age.</p><p>The issue on amendment No. 24 and what it seeks to do was summed up well by Senator Ruane.  We have flagged and talked previously and at length about the dangers concerned with cultivating and harvesting data relating to young people.  I am keen to hear what the Minister has to say on some of the more mechanical points raised about the general data protection regulation.  I believe it would be a pity if, at this stage, we were to unnecessarily replicate a vote in respect of which we might know the outcome.  I do not mean to be presumptuous in that regard.  I simply want to flag that I hope we can get this done in a way that is speedy and compliant for the Minister and his officials.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#HH00200"><p>I wish to acknowledge the Minister's efforts in this area.  I absolutely note the position of Senator Ruane on the digital age of consent.  To be honest, it confuses me a little.  Unlike Senator Ruane, I am not blessed with having children so she is probably far more in tune with them than I am.  Having said that, I have a deep concern for their welfare.</p> <p>Children are particularly ICT-aware now.  In many cases they show their parents how to deal with technology and so forth.  Unfortunately, we are in a world where the question of whether the digital age of consent is 16 or 13 years is probably academic.  This is because even from a younger age, children are able to access the Internet.  What troubles me is that a 13 year old child could put up a compromising picture of himself or herself on the Internet.  If the digital age of consent was 13 years, the parents would not have the authority or right to tell the child to take it down.  The child would have legal control of what goes up from age 13 years.  This is very much an evolving situation.  I imagine we will see this legislation amended many times in future as technology, lifestyle and habits change.</p> <p>It has been a useful debate.  I have listened to the arguments and my views have evolved on the matter.  I have come down very much on the side of leaving the age at 13 years because I believe it is academic and it seems to accord with international best practice.  One message that really needs to go out from both Houses is that, whatever position people take, everyone is in unison in terms of the importance of protecting children from the Internet.  We have a great deal of work to do to ensure that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#HH00300"><p>Others have spoken to the question of the age of consent.  I note that there will be a review of it.  The Minister mentioned that this would be within three years.  Perhaps the Minister can outline in his response what the process is likely to be around that review.  Different ages have been set across different EU states.  I believe we will be in a position to look at best practice and what the consequences may have been, whether direct or inadvertent, of setting the age differently in different EU states.  Perhaps the Minister could indicate the process of that review here and how we plan to draw on the experience elsewhere.</p><p>I want to address one thing that for me is far more significant than the question of the age of consent.  The issue was originally highlighted by myself and Senator Ruane.  It relates to the profiling of children and micro-targeting of children.  I commend those in the D&aacute;il who worked to ensure that amendments were inserted to address this issue.  The phrasing proposed by Deputy Donnchadh &Oacute; Laoghaire is reflected in amendment No. 24 and it is important.  Amendment No. 24 states:</p><blockquote>It shall be an offence under this Act for any company or corporate body to process the personal data of a child as defined by <i>section 29</i>for the purposes of direct marketing, profiling or micro-targeting.  Such an offence shall be punishable by an administrative fine under <i>section 139</i>.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>I note amendment No. 28 is similar and reflects this view as well.</p><p>I was a little concerned when the Minister mentioned that there may be a delay in the commencement of certain provisions in the Act.  I am keen to ensure we do not overly delay the commencement of the important amendments around micro-targeting and profiling of children.  I believe they are positive amendments.  They strengthen the Bill and represent good practice.  They are compatible with the GDPR.</p><p>Article 22 of the GDPR addresses the question of automated decision making, that is, decision making that may be facilitated by profiling and micro-targeting.  Article 6 also has relevance here.  Crucially, the intention of the GDPR is made clear in the recitals.  Recital 71 specifically says that automated decision making, including profiling that has significant effects, should not apply to children.  Recital 38 states:</p><blockquote>Children merit specific protection with regard to their personal data, as they may be less aware of the risks, consequences and safeguards concerned and their rights in relation to the processing of personal data.  Such specific protection should, in particular, apply to the use of personal data of children for the purposes of marketing or creating personality or user profiles and the collection of personal data with regard to children when using services offered directly to a child.</blockquote> <p>The definition of a child in all these provisions is set out in section 29 and applies to a child of 18 years or under.  None of the protections under the GDPR is in any way diluted by the age of consent or by the fact that a child may have given consent with regard to a service or participating online.</p><p>I believe these are excellent amendments.  I believe they are absolutely in tune with the letter and interpretive recitals of the GDPR.  I call on the Minister to assure me that there will be no undue delay in the commencement of these sections.  I heard that and I want the matter clarified because I would be very concerned if that was the case.</p><p>This will make a real difference at a concrete level.  This is the difference between a young person, whether 17 years or 13 years of age, being online and being subject to aggressive marketing.  Examples include lip fillers being sent to 17 year olds or young people having messages targeted at them that may play on the particular vulnerabilities or insecurities of young people.  The same applies to exploitative marketing.  I call on the Minister to outline the plan for commencing the provisions.</p><p>My final point on the section relates to the code of conduct.  I welcome and recognise the importance of the code of conduct that the Minister has indicated will be introduced in respect of the protection of children.  Will the Minister indicate specifically with regard to the question of age verification that arises in these situations, whether for those aged 13 years or those aged 16 years, if there are proper guidelines around the age verification process?  The idea is to avoid a situation whereby national identification papers, data that is effectively or potentially linked to the public service identity set or biometric data are not inappropriately sought, kept or stored by private companies.  I am not asking the Minister to tease out all of this today.  However, he might indicate if he believes that within the code of conduct there will be scope to ensure we have process to ensure we do not have inappropriate leakage of public or State data.  The same applies to data of individuals that is shared with the State.  It should not be overly captured by private company actors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00100"><p>On the final point made by Senator Higgins, if there is leakage it would be inappropriate, and if there is inappropriate leakage there will be sanctions.</p> <p>I shall make some brief comments on the amendments with regard to setting of the digital age of consent.  I acknowledge the will and wish of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann as far as this issue is concerned.  It is not my intention to revisit the debate in its entirety but while acknowledging the majority view of the House I do not agree with it.  It is not my intention to revisit the putting of the amendment in any other form.  I assure Senators that the only issues with which I have a real and serious remaining problem are issues that might have been the subject of amendment in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, and that may have constitutional consequences or may give rise to infringement proceedings on the part of our EU colleagues.  I accept the view of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.</p> <p>Senator Higgins referred to a delay but I assure the House that there will be no undue delay.  I am very supportive of the objective of the new section.  I intend to ensure that we have the appropriate level of advice from the Office of the Attorney General at the earliest opportunity.  I cannot do anything further than that.  The creation of a new offence, under this section, will require an element of advance notice so that individuals - or anybody who may be involved, affected or interested - will know that they are committing an offence that is criminal in nature and hence the issue being discussed today.  I am happy to engage bilaterally, perhaps with Senator Higgins or with the spokespeople, as soon as the advice comes through.  I assure the House of my support for the objective, subject to receiving clearance and no undue delay.   The only reason I ask for forbearance now is to ensure we meet our commitment to the completion of the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00200"><p>That concludes discussion of the group 5 amendments.  I now invite the Minister to discuss the group 6 amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00300"><p>With the consent of the House I will invite my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Pat Breen, who has specific and special responsibility for the area of data protection.  I am due in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and I will leave now, with the greatest respect to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00400"><p>We are sorry to lose the Minister, but we are thankful to have the Minister of State, Deputy Breen, to ably step into the seat the Minister has occupied.  Perhaps he is here to keep an eye on Senator Conway, and maybe <i>vice versa</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00500"><p>In advance of matters being completed this evening I thank Senators for their engagement during the course of this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Breen to the House, and I thank the Minister, Deputy Flanagan.  We will ask the Minister of State, Deputy Breen to speak on the group 6 amendments.  Amendment Nos. 35 to 37, inclusive,  39 to 43, inclusive, 45 to 47, inclusive and 49 to 52, inclusive, giving further effect to GDPR in relation to data processing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00700"><p>This group of amendments deals with GDPR related data processing under Part 3 of the Bill.</p> <p>Amendment No. 36 amends section 41 of the Bill, which reconciles the right to data protection with freedom of information rights.  It broadens the scope of section 41 by incorporating reference to the European Communities (Access to Information on the Environment) Regulations 2007.</p> <p>Amendments Nos. 35 and 37 are drafting amendments to section 38 and 42 respectively.</p> <p>Amendments Nos. 39 to 42, inclusive, are drafting amendments.</p> <p>Amendment No. 43 is an amendment to section 52 and will permit the making of future regulations to authorise, where necessary and proportionate, the processing of conviction data to assess the risk of bribery or corruption or both, or to prevent bribery or corruption or both.</p> <p>Amendment No. 52 is a related amendment and it would permit, should the need arise and if the Houses of the Oireachtas agree, the making of regulations to restrict student access to examinations scripts in order to safeguard the integrity and security of the examination systems.</p> <p>Amendment No. 46 inserts the additional safeguards in section 54, which deals with automated decision making.</p> <p>Section 57 is a further amendment with amendments Nos. 47, and 49 to 51, inclusive.  Amendment No. 47 replaces the text of subsection (2) with simpler wording.  Amendment No. 49 inserts the word "commercial" in subsection (3)a 6.  Amendment No. 50 incorporates reference to the Comptroller and Auditor General in subsection (3)c, alongside the Data Protection Commission and the Information Commissioner.  Amendment No. 51 is a drafting amendment to subsection (7)c.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00800"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  Do Senators have any contributions on matters covered by the group 6 amendments? No.</p> <p>We shall move on to group 7 amendments relating to elected representatives, amendment Nos. 33, 34 and 122.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ00900"><p>This is a very important part of the GDPR for public representatives.  Senator Conway first raised the potential impact of GDPR on the ability of elected representatives to make requests or representations in the House.  Arising from that intervention, the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, announced his intention to introduce new provisions to establish a robust legal basis for the making of representations by Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas and by members of local authorities.  The Minister took the view then, and it remains his view, that assisting constituents by making representations and requests on their behalf are time honoured and valuable aspects of our democratic system of government.</p> <p>Amendment No. 33 introduces a new section that will facilitate specified persons to use personal data in the course of their electoral activities in the State for communicating with their data subjects.  Under subsection (2) such a communication is considered as the preference of a task carried out in the public interest.</p> <p>Amendment No. 34 introduces a new section that will provide a robust legal basis for making representations on behalf of individuals.  Where special categories of personal data are involved, subsection (3) will require that measures to limit access to the data would be taken in order to prevent unauthorised consultation, alteration, disclosures or erasures of the data.</p> <p>Subsection (4) establishes a legal basis for responding to representations and requests received by public authorities and public bodies from elected representatives on behalf of data subjects.</p> <p>Amendment No. 122 amends the Electoral Act 1992 to provide for continued use of the electoral register in connection with the two new sections.</p> <p>The combined effect of the amendments will permit the elected representatives of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, Seanad &Eacute;ireann and local authorities to continue to perform their functions as elected representatives by continuing to communicate and serve their electorate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ01000"><p>Do Senators have any contributions to make on the group 7 amendments?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#JJ01100"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Breen, for his clarification on the amendments.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When the House dealt with Committee and Report Stages, concern was raised by a number of people about their role in engaging with local authorities and their members.  A number of colleagues in the Fine Gael Parliamentary Party raised serious concerns about how this would impact on those people doing their job daily.</p><p>Ireland and Malta are the only two countries in the world with a proportional representation single transferable vote system, PR-STV, on a multi-seat constituency basis which creates a certain dynamic and requirements.  Ireland is probably even more distinct than Malta in that people go to their elected public representatives for citizens' advice and information.  Deputies, Senators and local authority members provide an advocacy role for their constituents with local authorities and various State agencies as well as private financial institutions.  I regret that banks and other private companies are not covered by the Bill.  If we are asked to advocate with a financial institution which is privately owned, I understand we will be subject to the same data protection requirements as anybody else.</p><p>If we are engaging with public organisations, such as SUSI, the fact that public representatives have a mandate means that they have an implied and absolute authority and freedom from any data protection requirements to engage, as do their staff.  Constituency staff in my constituency, that of the Minister of State, Deputy Breen, and anybody else's who have to advocate and engage to try to resolve a difficulty for constituents can do that.  The data protection legislation, which is very important in the advancing ICT world, will not preclude representatives from advocacy.  It would be a great pity if a culture of political representation on behalf of constituents were to be stopped or frustrated in any way as result of important data protection legislation.</p><p>I am glad that Minister, Deputy Flanagan, following the substantial case I made on behalf of Senators and our colleagues in local authorities, has responded positively and has brought in a suite of amendments to ensure that we can continue to do our job and perform our role as we have done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#KK00200"><p>I have very serious concerns about this area.  I raised them when the Bill was passed by the Seanad and they have deepened somewhat.  While I recognise that there are some constructive elements to the amendments which have been made and it is important that people are able to do their representative work as described by Senator Conway, I am concerned that the serious dangers I flagged very clearly during the course of the debate in the Seanad were not addressed at all.  In fact, the danger may have increased.</p> <p>There have been ongoing revelations in recent months around the role of political consultancy and data mining firms such as Cambridge Analytica in election campaigns.  We know there are hundreds, if not thousands, of clones of similar public and political consultancy and data mining firms.  My concern about the previous incarnation of the Bill was that it did not have enough to ensure that the exemptions which were being made in respect of electoral activities by specified persons, such as political parties, Members of the Houses or the European Parliament, candidates for office for election to any House and so forth, would preclude such actors from signing a contract with or hiring the services of a private company such as Cambridge Analytica, or its many imitators, and effectively using the exemption granted in the Bill.  We need to bear in mind that a single candidate could decide to become a candidate simply for this purpose.  I am concerned that we may have given a very wide exemption to such an actor and, through him or her, to private actors or companies which may wish to influence electoral outcomes in our country.</p> <p>I highlighted that Article 9, which deals with what is recognised by the GDPR as a special category of personal information, that is, political opinion, is recognised as a sensitive category of personal information and one which needs particular protection.  I highlighted that I was concerned that what had been brought forward in the Bill had exceeded the generous provision which was made under Article 9(2)(d), that is, the processing of a special category of personal information like political opinion.  It states that it is legitimate to process political opinion when that is carried out in the course of legitimate activities, with appropriate safeguards by a foundation, association or any other not-for-profit body with a political, philosophical, religious or trade union aim.  Crucially, this is on the condition that the processing relates solely to the members or former members of that body or persons who have regular contact with it in connection with those purposes, that is, for example, party members or constituents, and that the personal data are not disclosed outside that body without the consent of the data subject.</p> <p>Under Article 9(2)(d), a person can function as a political party or representative and communicate in respect of the political opinion of constituents or members.  A person cannot, however, share the information of constituents or those in touch with him or her or party members with a private company or another external actor without getting consent.  That might mean a person can work with a focus group, RED C and so on, but if he or she does so, that person needs the consent of data subjects.  I raised the concern that the Bill as posited did not contain the same limits and an attempt has been made to get around that.</p> <p>An amendment invokes the public interest.  Instead of relying on Article 9(2)(d), the part which refers to the question of public interest seems to have been invoked in a very sweeping way.  This is the section to which I will speak longest.  I will be much shorter about other sections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#KK00300"><p>Are we dealing with amendments Nos. 33, 34 and 122?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#KK00400"><p>Yes.  It is framed as section 38 in the Bill.  I am speaking to amendments Nos. 33 and 34.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#KK00500"><p>Okay.  Go ahead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#KK00600"><p>I am referring to sections 38 and 39 of the Bill and amendments Nos. 33 and 34.  There is real concern that a very sweeping interpretation of public interest has been proposed, which effectively states that any electoral activity on the part of any party, candidate or Member of the House is in the public interest and therefore bypasses any need for consent.  There is some clarification in that it is proposed to include the dissemination of information, including information as to a person's activity and policies that might reasonably be of interest to electors.  It does not, however, exclude anything.</p> <p>I am very concerned and I would like a response from the Minister of State on the proposals to ensure that we do not have a situation whereby private companies can build political profiles of individuals in the State and be hired by or exchange that information with individuals who are considered specified persons and then use that as a context to carry out data harvesting or micro-targeting.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Let us be realistic about it.  We know that one company was reported in the newspapers just a few weeks ago as having used the period in advance of the GDPR to build databases and political profiles of Irish citizens.  It has had the aggressive and very expensive promotion of quizzes about one's political views for Irish citizens.  It informs us, on its website, that it has 93,000 political profiles of Irish citizens which are effectively available for purchase and use.  What is in this Bill to stop an actor in Ireland from hiring this company, accessing those 93,000 political profiles and arranging for a barrage of micro-targeted messages using the exemptions granted in this section?  What are the protections relating to such measures?  Where is it said that certain activities are not considered to be electoral activities within the public interest remit?  There is no nuance here.</p><p>I am concerned.  I have flagged these interests.  I was more assured when it left the Seanad because at that point the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, had indicated that he believed that any activities would have to be conducted directly by a member or candidate of a political party.  With this new, wide interpretation, I do not see where the protections are for individuals.  I respect electoral activity and cherish the engagement that we have with our constituencies.  I want us to engage in active, engaged campaigning.  I also realise, however, that we bring in rules and regulations in this area for a reason and that Article 9 recognised political opinion as an area of sensitivity for a reason.  I am worried that we have sought in effect to ensure that political activity evades the protections accorded to the political opinion of individuals.  Will the Minister of State address these concerns?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL00200"><p>As a rural Deputy, I think it is important that a Deputy, Senator or local authority member is able to communicate with constituents.  It is very important.  It is part of the role.  It is also important to point out with regard to the Bill that Oireachtas Members and local authorities have the same obligations as anybody else with regard to the protection of data that they hold.  They are obliged under the Bill to ensure that the information they hold on the constituent or such is secure and safe.  That is very important.</p> <p>The area that Senator Higgins is dealing with, section 38(2), relates to communication.  As she rightly pointed out, communication is very important.  Some Oireachtas Members like to communicate with their constituents.  That is an important part of the job, whether by electronic mail or door-knocking.  There are different means of communication.  The information that people have, particularly relating to communications, is that the data that one has on hold are not for sharing with others.  That is important to point out.  Any information that one has must be in the interests of the electorate, as the Senator has rightly pointed out.  Any communication is for sharing with the electorate only, not with others.  That is in section 38(2).</p> <p>I thank Senator Higgins and I also thank Senator Conway for his comments on the change that the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, brought in.  It is an important change to allow public representatives to be able to communicate and work with their constituents in a responsible way.  When one is elected as an Oireachtas Member or to local government, one has responsibilities in every area to ensure one upholds those responsibilities as a public representative.  Now there is the GDPR coming into place and the Data Protection Bill, and everyone has the same obligations in terms of the protection of data and ensuring that data are stored safely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL00300"><p>I ask the Minister of State to deal with the amendments in group 8.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL00400"><p>Group 8 includes amendments Nos. 48 and 107 to 110, inclusive.  They are court related amendments.  These amendments are concerned with the application of data protection safeguards and rules by courts when acting in their judicial capacity.  Section 155 deals with the processing of personal data, where the controller is a court acting in a judicial capacity.  Amendment No. 107 amends subsection (2) of section 155 while amendment No. 108 converts subsections (3) to (5) of that section into a more detailed, separate, stand-alone section.  Consequently, amendment No. 48 deletes the reference to judicial independence and court proceedings in section 57(3) which is no longer required.</p> <p>Amendment No. 109 inserts a new section into the Bill which provides for the making of court rules by the rules committee for the superior courts, the Circuit Court and the District Court in respect of personal data contained in court records.  Such rules may also provide for the processing of personal data and the disclosure of personal data to facilitate fair and accurate reporting of court proceedings.  Amendment No. 110 replaces section 156, which is an expanded text which incorporates a legal basis for the publication of a list or schedule of court proceedings or hearings in court proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I do not think anybody is indicating to speak on this grouping.  I will move on to group 9 and call the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL00600"><p>Group 9 is quite short.  It includes amendments Nos. 29, 54 to 64, inclusive, 66, 68 to 74, inclusive, 78 to 82, inclusive, 86 to 90, inclusive, 93, 98 to 104, inclusive, 106, 111 and 185.  They are technical and drafting amendments.  It is a large group and it comprises various amendments to the Bill of a technical and drafting nature.  They include corrections to cross references, minor drafting changes etc., and I do not propose to speak on them individually or we will be here until tomorrow morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL00700"><p>I do not have anybody interested in contributing on this section so I ask the Minister of State to speak on the amendments which are the subject of group 10.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL00800"><p>Group 10 is quite short.  It includes amendments Nos. 75 and 76.  They relate to the data protection officer, DPO.  Amendments Nos. 75 and 76 amend section 85 and their purpose is to support and strengthen the independence of DPOs operating under Part 5.  Amendment No. 75 reads:</p><blockquote>(c) ensure that the data protection officer&mdash;(i) reports directly, in relation to his or her functions under subsection (5), to the highest level of management of the controller,<br /><br />(ii) does not receive any instructions regarding the exercise of such functions, and<br /><br />(iii) is involved in an appropriate and timely manner in all matters relating to the protection of personal data.</blockquote> <p>Amendment No. 76 provides that the DPO will act as a contact point for data subjects when seeking to exercise their data protection rights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL00900"><p>They are positive amendments and will strengthen the role of the data protection officer in ensuring that they do not come under undue pressure with regard to the performance of their function.  That is especially important given that we have significant fines which can apply to a public authority.</p> <p>The Minister of State might clarify a point.  If a data protection officer is reporting to the highest level of management and is meeting resistance or is finding concerns unanswered, I expect he or she would be able to reach out directly to the data protection commission or others.  Will the Minister of State clarify that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL01000"><p>I thank Senator Higgins for her support.  The concerns that she raises can be reported to the data protection commission.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL01100"><p>That concludes group 10.  I ask the Minister of State to speak on the amendments in group 11.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#LL01200"><p>Group 11 includes amendments Nos. 91, 92 and 105.  They relate to judicial remedy.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Pat Breen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1766"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1766&amp;amp;pid=PatBreen&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Amendment No. 91 will mean that in cases taken on behalf of data subjects by a not-for-profit body, organisation or association arising from an alleged infringement of the GDPR a court may grant relief by means of an injunction or declaration, or by way of compensation for material or non-material damage suffered by the data subject.</p><p>Amendment No. 92 will provide similar remedies for infringements of Part 5 of the Bill.</p><p>Amendment No. 105 which amends section 148 will mean that the leave of the court will not be required for the purpose of appealing to a higher court on a point of law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM00200"><p>I welcome these amendments which are very important because a lacuna in the original Bill made it very difficult for individuals to seek a redress where the data protection commission may or may not have taken individual complaints on board.  In many cases, those who do wish to raise concerns do so not simply because they seek redress for themselves but because they want to highlight concerns about the system and they want to improve the process for others, which is an act of generosity.  This is an opportunity to pay tribute to those, both in Ireland and in Europe, who have done us some service, people, including Max Schrems, who have taken individual cases, and groups, such as Digital Rights Ireland, which have done important work in strengthening laws here and internationally by highlighting problems and ensuring they are addressed.  This is a constructive amendment which ensures that civil society, which we in the Civil Engagement group endeavour to represent, can play a constructive role in supporting those individuals whose data has been breached.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM00300"><p>I acknowledge Senator Higgins's contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM00400"><p>That concludes group 11.  Will the Minister of State refer to the subject matter of the amendments in group 12 please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM00500"><p>There are three amendments in this group, amendments Nos. 94, 95 and 97, which concern administrative fines.  Amendments Nos. 94 and 95 delete section 131(11) because the provision to which the subsection was connected, that is, section 139(2) is also being deleted.  These provisions, which dealt with the rule that two sanctions may not be imposed for the same offence or infringement, have been deleted on the advice of the Office of the Attorney General.</p> <p>Amendment No. 97 inserts subsections (4), (5) and (6) in section 139.  They outline the procedure to be followed when the data protection commission imposes an administrative fine on a controller or processor.  They also provide that all income from fines received by the commission must "be paid into or disposed of for the benefit of the Exchequer".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM00600"><p>That concludes the matters in group 12.  We move on to speak on the subject matter of group 13, which is the final group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM00700"><p>This group deals with amendments Nos. 112 to 121, inclusive, and Nos. 123 to 184, inclusive.  They are consequential amendments to other Acts.</p> <p>Discontinued application of the Data Protection Act 1988, following the entry into force of GDPR and the legislation, necessitates the amendment of a significant number of Acts of the Oireachtas especially those containing cross-references to the 1988 Act.  These changes are set out in amendments Nos. 112 to 121, inclusive, and amendments Nos. 123 to 184, inclusive.  Except for those that already fall within the responsibility of the Department of Justice and Equality, these have been notified to the Department by the Departments concerned and the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel has drafted them.  In each case the amendments to the Acts concerned are intended to ensure compliance with the GDPR and legislation.  It is not necessary to speak to each of these amendments individually.  They speak for themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM00800"><p>There are 72 of them so I would not recommend that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM00900"><p>It is common sense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM01000"><p>We are on the final amendments and 25 May has been flagged for a long time in respect of the requirement for this new data protection legislation.  There is a motion for early signature.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM01100"><p>We are not there yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM01200"><p>It will be the law on Friday.  Many people who are not computer literate cannot deal with the intricacies, difficulties and challenges of websites.  I would like the Department, through the Data Protection Commissioner, to have a dedicated telephone hotline for a few weeks.  Many people may be non-compliant through no fault of their own because there may be bits of information on websites.  It is very technical, challenging and new.  The Minister of State cannot do this but the officials sitting behind him can.  They have a responsibility, and it is required that they would do this because the last thing we want is a flood of people who find they are not compliant.  That goes against the spirit of what the EU and this legislation are trying to achieve.  The best we can have is a free flow of information and access to information and clarification for businesses, community and voluntary groups which might have a barrage of complaints against them through no fault of their own.  As an example, the Gaelic Athletic Association, GAA, is extremely well versed in its obligations under this legislation but I am sure there are many other community groups that are not as well versed in their obligations.  We need a hotline to ensure that the people who work every week for nothing, doing their best for their communities, do not inadvertently find themselves in breach of data protection legislation.   This is extremely important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM01300"><p>I recognise there is a suite of amendments here and while I do not propose to challenge them I note two strands within them.  The first is insurance and banking legislation and I have some concerns about the Bill in these areas.  We know, for example, that private insurance companies have been implicated in inappropriate data breaches in accessing social protection information and so on.  I do not know that we have adequate safeguards and I hope the Ministers will engage if necessary to create further safeguards for some of the wide exemptions we have granted to banks and insurance companies.</p> <p>Second, I note that the Residential Institutions Redress Act 2002 and the inquiry into child abuse and other important inquiries are rightly given the exemptions they need to ensure that information that is in the public interest in this area is brought forward.  Does the Minister of State feel there is enough future proofing in the Bill for future similar inquiries?  Those under way are properly protected in this suite of amendments but what part of the Bill allows scope for future inquiries to avoid a cumbersome legal process to ensure that appropriate data can be accessed?  The public interest measure is probably the relevant one but can the Minister of State clarify that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#MM01400"><p>I thank all the Members of both Houses for their input into this Bill.  There was a great deal of engagement in both Houses when I took part of the debate for the Minister, Deputy Flanagan.  A lot of work has gone into the Bill to ensure we get the best possible Act.</p> <p>In response to Senator Conway, I have engaged a great deal with the Data Protection Commissioner and her team in many areas, particularly to ensure that not only companies but also organisations, agencies, etc., would be compliant with GDPR on 25 May.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Pat Breen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1766"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1766&amp;amp;pid=PatBreen&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I do not have any issue with many of the big companies out there.  They will be GDPR-compliant because they have data protection officers, etc.  I am always concerned about small and medium-sized enterprises and micro-enterprises.  During the period leading up to 25 May, we have had a number of engagements and meetings around the country.  For example, we have engaged with the GAA, which was mentioned by Senator Conway.  Representatives of all the umbrella bodies for all the sporting organisations were brought into the Department of the Taoiseach for a meeting which was attended by officials from the Office of the Data Protection Commissioner.  When the representatives of the various organisations left the Department after a serious three-hour engagement, they were very happy with the information they had received from the assistant data commissioners.</p><p>Senator Conway also mentioned other sporting organisations.  We are very conscious of their concerns.  We engaged with representatives of many sporting organisations from around the country at a meeting in the Federation of Irish Sport complex in Blanchardstown a few weeks ago.  Most of the organisations - I will not go through them all, but they were all there - were very happy with the information they received from the Office of the Data Protection Commissioner.  That engagement is extremely important.  The Data Protection Commissioner and her team have gone all over the country to speak to organisations.  The idea of a hotline has been proposed by Senator Conway.  I think it is worth considering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN00200"><p>It could be put in place for a short period of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN00300"><p>Additional resources would be needed for a hotline.  The Senator is putting pressure on me to ensure the Data Protection Commissioner gets more resources in this year's budget.  We have increased her resources sixfold in recent years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN00400"><p>It is up to her to find efficiencies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN00500"><p>Although the hotline proposal is worth considering, it should be pointed out that a hotline might not provide an instant answer.  The Office of the Data Protection Commissioner has been inundated with calls in recent months.  It cannot get back to everybody immediately.  It can do so over time.  The provision of a hotline may or may not be the solution, but it is worth considering.  We will bring it to the attention of the Data Protection Commissioner for the Senator.</p> <p>If 500 or 600 people from all over the country try to ring the hotline at the same time, they might not be satisfied with the response they receive from within the resources that are available.  The resources of the Office of the Data Protection Commissioner will be taken up with some of the bigger cases for a number of weeks.  The Data Protection Commissioner has said she will take a very sympathetic approach in the early stages of the new regime.  If people are trying to comply, that will be acknowledged along the way.  That is something to point out as well.  It is important to point out to Senator Higgins that the safeguards she mentioned will be built into the legislation as we go along.</p> <p>I thank those who contributed to the debates on this Bill in both Houses.  It has been a long journey, but it has been well worth it.  Most Members of the Oireachtas who spoke on this legislation can be happy with the input they made.  We look forward to seeing what will happen on 25 May next.  Someone said to me recently that all the work will start on that date.  It is important to thank the officials in the Department of Justice and Equality who spent many hours on this legislation, particularly when drafting Committee Stage amendments.  The long hours they worked meant they had many sleepless nights.  I thank S&eacute;amus Carroll and the team in the Department of Justice and Equality for their efforts.  I hope many Irish companies will be GDPR-compliant by 25 May.  It is important for all companies, including micro-enterprises and small enterprises, to be GDPR-compliant as we move forward because it will mean more business for them.  Ireland needs to lead the way in embracing digital technology because that is the future of work and the way it is going.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN00600"><p>That concludes group 13.  I was in the Chair for much of this debate, particularly in its earlier Stages.  I thank all the Members, the Minister and the Minister of State for their contribution to the debate in the Seanad.  I also thank the officials from the Department of Justice and Equality for their work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.170" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.171" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN00900"><p>I acknowledge the engagement from the Department, particularly from S&eacute;amus Carroll and others who have spent time teasing this out.  I believe we will return to this area.  There is a huge amount of work to be monitored.  Like Senator Conway, I recognise that as people get used to the new regime, there will be a period of time when they struggle to figure out how to comply with it.  While it is important for supports to be provided in such circumstances, it is also important for us to take this matter seriously.  The existence of long processes should not mean that breaches do not have clear consequences down the line.  We must struggle to make sure we get that balance right.</p> <p>As a very passionate European, I think this is one of the most fundamentally important things that the member states of the EU have done together.  The Minister of State, Deputy Breen, will recall that I have been very critical in this House of things like EU trade policy and the Comprehensive Economic and Trade Agreement.  We have had disagreements about things like permanent structured co-operation in the past.  The implementation of the GDPR is a strong signal of what the EU should be, which is a space where we co-operate, protect and engage our citizens.  As legislators, we need to ensure we can create spaces of empowerment of citizens.  We should not simply be subject to the overflow of corporate or market forces.  We need to be able to set down markers regarding what constitutes appropriate use of data and what is acceptable in the spaces we share.  I think this is a really important marker.  I look forward to continuing to engage with everyone in the House on this issue in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01000"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire St&aacute;it.  I echo Senator Higgins's remarks about the significance of this legislation and this issue.  I am sure it will warrant constant attention and review, legislatively and otherwise.  The process of passing this gargantuan legislation - that is not a term I get to use very often in this House - has been complex.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01100"><p>The Senator can use it every day as long as he uses it appropriately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01200"><p>I would never use it inappropriately.  The manner in which both Houses have been able to co-operate on this Bill with mutual understanding and appreciation has been very telling.  It is understandable that there have been some nuanced disagreements, but there has also been an appreciation of the significance and importance of this legislation.</p> <p>It is worth noting the work of the officials and of the Minister and his colleagues.  They have worked co-operatively to get this through.  I hope it does not sound slightly facetious when I say we will see how it goes.  It is incumbent on us to ensure we do all we can to get the word out to people about compliance, the operation of this legislation and how it works for people.  Regardless of where one stands on the more nuanced aspects of this Bill, the constant thread throughout the debate has been the need to ensure the rights of citizens are protected and their security is upheld.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01300"><p>I pay tribute to my constituency colleague, the Minister of State with responsibility for data protection, Deputy Breen.  It is appropriate that a Minister of State is dealing specifically with this new, innovative and demanding area.  I acknowledge the Minister of State's role and the role of the officials.  It is important to acknowledge the role of Parliament as well.  Some aspects of this legislation, such as the debate on the digital age of consent, have been quite controversial.  As I said earlier, I have reviewed the matter and I think the digital age of consent should have been left as it was, but others did not agree with that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01400"><p>We are not reopening the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01500"><p>We were scheduled to sit until 10 o'clock, so I think we are doing quite well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01600"><p>Hear, hear.  Maith th&uacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01700"><p>We are doing pretty well, but if we start reopening the debate-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01800"><p>I have the floor.  I can keep talking for a few hours if the Chair wants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN01900"><p>The Senator knows I am on his side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN02000"><p>I would not do that to the Minister of State and his officials.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN02100"><p>I hope the Senator would not do it to me either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#NN02200"><p>I would not do that to the Chair either.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have never met Ms Helen Dixon, but everyone seems to sing her praises.  Clearly, she is doing a great job.  There has been quite a roadshow.  I am aware of the engagement that took place with the GAA.  I am delighted that there have been similar, successful attempts to engage with other sports organisations.  As time passes, we will probably discover that there is a nucleus of organisations that have been under the radar.  As the Minister of State said - he is right - after Friday the job will intensify significantly.  </p><p>In protecting data in a fast growing world in terms of information technology, communications, the Internet, digital technology and so on, this is a marker for the way things should be done and people's information and details should be protected.  As we move forward, I have no doubt that this legislation will be amended many times.  It is the introduction to a book, a mission statement and a statement of intent on how the country will respect the integrity of data and information.  It respects the uniqueness of our political system.  I am very pleased that our role, as public representatives, is respected and now part of the legislation.  We will be better equipped and protected in doing our job.  </p><p>As the Minister of State said, it has been a good period, with long hours.  I say, "Well done," to everyone involved.  As time passes and the legislation has to be amended, I am sure we will not be found wanting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#OO00200"><p>I thank the Senator.  I am sure if we were to tot the hours spent on the legislation in this and the other Chamber, there is not much legislation that has been deliberated on for as long.  I hope after all of that deliberation and the amendments, it is a good, workable Bill that will deliver what it is supposed to.  I offer my congratulations to all those who pulled it together, including the Minister of State, Deputy Pat Breen; the Minister, Deputy Charles Flanagan, and the Members of both Houses who participated in and had to chair some of the debates.  I will leave myself out.  I am referring to the Cathaoirleach, the Ceann Comhairle and everybody else.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#OO00300"><p>The Acting Chairman will be fine.  He has served his apprenticeship.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#OO00400"><p>I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.190" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.191" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#OO00600">Data Protection Bill 2018: Motion for Earlier Signature</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#OO00700"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That pursuant to subsection 2&deg; of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad &Eacute;ireann concurs with the Government in a request to the President to sign the Data Protection Bill 2018 on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.193" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#OO00900"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018052200002#OO01000"><p>Maidin am&aacute;rach ar 10.30.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-22a.196" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.25 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 23 May 2018.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>