<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700002#A00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700002#A00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Protection of Children's Health from Tobacco Smoke Bill 2012 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken at noon and conclude not later than 1 p.m., and No. 2, statements on an update on the situation in Ukraine, to be taken at 1 p.m. and conclude not later than 2.30 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be called on to reply not later than 2.25 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700002#A00400"><p>There are many songs about water, one of which goes "Water, water, everywhere and not a drop to drink".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700002#A00500"><p>Is the Senator going to sing it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700002#A00600"><p>If I knew all of the words, I would.  There appears to be an ongoing spat between the Government parties on the question of water charges.  The Taoiseach was in the House last evening and we all welcomed his presence in the Chamber.  I commend him for coming.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700002#A01000"><p>Why would he not come?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700002#A01100"><p> I am sure it was appreciated by Members on all sides of the House.  It is right and proper that Taoisigh should visit the House on a regular basis.  The Taoiseach talked about honesty and truth and seeking and telling the truth in the context of the terms of reference for the tribunal.  I commend him for at least providing figures which gave the population some indication of what it might face in terms of water charges from 1 October through to January.  However, questions have arisen and they have been presented by the Labour Party.  In fact, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, is quoted in the newspapers news as saying no deal has been done on water charges.  The figures provided by the Taoiseach appear to be based on the subsidy the Government is allowed to give, coupled with the amount of money that will be generated, but there will still be a shortfall.</p> <p>The question remains, particularly some weeks ahead of the local and European elections, as to what exactly people will be paying come the end of this year.  This really is the nub of the problem because it appears on the face of it as though the figure given out by the Taoiseach may not be the figure with which one eventually will end up.  It might be considerably more, primarily because only 25% of households in the State will be metered and it appears as though the remainder will then be charged not based on the size of the house but using some sort of system that has yet to be devised.  Moreover, it appears as though such a system may result in those in the lower income levels paying as much or perhaps more than those who, as someone observed, live in Sorrento Terrace, Dalkey.  I am sure the Labour Party, among all parties, would not wish to endorse such a policy, and therefore, it is time for the Minister, Deputy Hogan, to come back before the House.  He should clarify, obviously not today but sometime between now and the end of next month, what precisely is going on in respect of water charges.</p><p>While he is in the Chamber, he might also revisit a debate Members had last week.  Although it was held under the terms of a motion pertaining to SI 105, that debate also should have been about SI 9, which the Minister did address.  I appreciate that a communications problem on Fianna F&aacute;il's side - I put up my hands in this regard - meant it did not include the wording &quot;SI 9&quot; in the motion leading to the debate on SI 105.  The Minister answered some but not all of the questions involved and since then, I have received representations from a variety of people, including a representative of the Irish Association of Self Builders.  He stated the association was astonished that the Minister, Deputy Hogan, mentioned that self-builders and that organisation had been kept informed and had participated in the formation of the regulation, when in fact he ha not met the association at all.  That person also wishes to know, as do I, the reason the Minister has given architects, engineers and surveyors a monopoly on certifying and getting money for each new house and house extension of more than 400 sq. ft.  This will add thousands to the cost of a self-build project and while this may not be an issue in urban Ireland, it is an issue in rural Ireland.  It is yet another indication to me of the anti-rural attitude the Government has adopted since it first came to power.  It will now prevent people in rural Ireland from building their own houses because it will add considerably higher costs to those houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700003#B00200"><p>That is not true.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700003#B00300"><p>I reiterate what I said at the time, which is that I support fully the new building regulations.  It is long past time they were introduced and I commend the Minister, Deputy Hogan.  He appears to me to be the nearest thing to a Fianna F&aacute;il Minister when it comes to having the vision thing.  He has the vision thing and I appreciate that because he is someone who-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700003#B00500"><p>He is someone who, when he gets an idea into his head, proceeds with it without fear or favour.  However, in this particular instance, I suggest that the Minister is wrong.  It is time he revisited SI 9 to ensure that those who wish to build their own houses under certified conditions will continue to be allowed to so do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700003#B00600"><p>While Senator Mooney spoke for my good friends opposite in Fianna F&aacute;il, it is no harm to remind Members that Fianna F&aacute;il has a recurring problem in dealing with its amnesia.  I remind Members opposite that Fianna F&aacute;il signed up to a four-year programme in 2010 and agreed with the troika that it would transfer water services to a water utility and that there would be a charge for which the indicative figure at the time was &euro;400.  As I understand it, although nothing has been signed off by the Government in this regard, the indicative figure at present is only approximately &euro;240.  Consequently, I believe Fianna F&aacute;il should revisit what happened.</p><p>Moreover, Members must remind themselves of the cost of providing water through the taps, piping and everything else.  At present, 40% of water produced is leaking into the ground.  Any government must be responsible - the present Administration is extremely responsible - and this problem must be and will be sorted out as part of the overall package.  Equally discussions are continuing on how water service charges will be made affordable.  Circumstances will apply in some instances in which families will not be able to afford it and there will be exemption limits.  As all this is yet to be made available, Members opposite should not panic.  The Government is on course, everything will be agreed and everything will be acceptable.  In addition, Fianna F&aacute;il Members should remember that it signed up to a great deal more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700003#B00700"><p>In the light of the peak of friendship in relations between Ireland and the United Kingdom after the highly successful visit by President Higgins to the United Kingdom last week, I seek a debate on Northern Ireland in which I ask the Acting Leader to invite the T&aacute;naiste to participate.  It is important that this time the momentum of goodwill is not lost.  The relations between our Head of State and Queen Elizabeth, to whom Orangemen and loyalists profess their loyalty, could not possibly be better.  Moreover, the working relationship between the Ceann Comhairle and the Speaker of the Northern Ireland Assembly, Mr. William Hay, working on the North-South Interparliamentary Association, is most cordial.  Indeed, the Donegal parade at Rossknowlagh has been a model for such parades for quite a while.  As we again approach the marching season, Northern Ireland does not need to have its trade and tourism disrupted by it.  Members should seek to bring forward policy initiatives that would take out the tension from the marching season.  This would be a good time to do it.  The T&aacute;naiste should facilitate the House and the Acting Leader should ask him to come in.</p><p>The second matter I wish to mention is the raising by the Minister for Finance of the option of a quick sale of National Asset Management Agency, NAMA, assets.  It is among a number of options, and the quick sale of these assets has many attractive aspects.  Non-performing assets would be transferred to new owners and a fall in asset price could stimulate the economy.  Holding onto assets in the hope that asset prices might pick up at some stage delays the recovery of this economy.  The ghost estates should be sold, for example.  While they may be built in the wrong places, people can trade off longer commuting distances and get a bargain there.  As Senator Quinn and I have observed, upward-only rent reviews also delay the recovery.  It is not desirable to have NAMA hanging around for decades longer than it is needed, as happened with the old Land Commission.  Consequently, the option of asset sales and the fall in asset and property prices should be perceived as a way in which to stimulate the recovery, which already is under way.  While this could be a major boost to it, holding onto assets forever and holding onto NAMA for a long time, as was done with the Land Commission, will delay the recovery of this economy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700003#B00800"><p>First, in response to Senator Mooney, let there be no doubt that the T&aacute;naiste has made the position clear.  The Labour Party is only too well aware of the fact that one quarter of households in Ireland will be metered and it will not be signing up to any water charges system that does not take into account fairness, equity and ability to pay.  This point should be put on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700003#B00900"><p>I am greatly reassured.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700003#B01000"><p>On the issue of Irish families currently living in hotels because they have nowhere else to live as they are homeless, I welcome the announcement by the Leader the day before yesterday that Members would have a discussion with the Minister for Social Protection on 28 May to consider the role of rent supplement in this debacle.  All Members are only too well aware that in the urban areas in particular, one cannot access properties at the rent supplement limit and that rent supplement is a serious factor in homelessness in Ireland today.  However, I note that 2014 marks the tenth anniversary of the introduction of the Residential Tenancies Act, which was the occasion of a sea change in legislation in Ireland to protect tenants and give them security of tenure in the private rented sector.  It has come to my attention, particularly over the past six months, that there has been a significant rise in the number of what I would describe as spurious evictions on the grounds that an owner wanted to sell the property concerned or because the owner's son or daughter wished to live there.  These all are based on the fact that some landlords - not all - are able to get more money out of someone else.  What is happening at present is that people's security of tenure is being undermined severely.  I seek a debate on the issue of regulation and security of tenure in the rented sector today.  It is a serious matter to see people coming home to find their clothes in black sacks outside the door and being evicted for nothing other than economic reasons.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00100"><p>I support what Senator Paschal Mooney said about water charges.  It is critical.  The position in Roscommon is that there is definitely water - water, water, everywhere - but not one drop to drink because the supplies are contaminated with cryptosporidium.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00200"><p>How is the Senator managing in the western D&aacute;il bar?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00300"><p>How are we to charge for water when people cannot drink it?  Meters are being installed in houses in Boyle where people have to boil water and also in Castlerea where the water is unsafe to drink.  An interim plant has been put in place in Roscommon town through the work of local councillors who have been very active on the ground.  They were successful in having the interim plant put in place in the town which has relieved the pressure.  Approximately 19,000 people do not have a supply of drinkable water.  What is going on is a scandal.  I sympathise with Labour Party Senators, although I do not feel all that sorry for them.  When they call to doors, they run away, as from reports I have received I understand they are getting a very bad reception on the doorstep.  The fact that the Government has gerrymandered constituencies such that it will have all of the seats on the eastern coast will ensure it will have some survivors.  Fine Gael councillors are in a very-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00400"><p>Objection.  It is outrageous to suggest any political party has gerrymandered constituency boundaries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00500"><p>The Labour Party has.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00600"><p>That is absolutely outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00700"><p>The Labour Party decided to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00800"><p>I ask the Senator to withdraw his remark.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C00900"><p>No, it is official policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01000"><p>I ask that the remark be withdrawn.  It is outrageous.  An independent electoral commission sets the boundaries.  The Senator's accusation is outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01100"><p>Senator Terry Leyden to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01200"><p>On a point of order, I am not competent to make a factual comment on this case, but I am sure the Senator will remember the very remarkable gerrymandering that was given the name "Tullymander" in memory of the Labour Party Minister who had organised it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01300"><p>That is not a point of order.  Senator Terry Leyden to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01400"><p>I thank Senator David Norris for reminding me of that fact.  I knew Jim Tully well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01500"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01600"><p>Is it a point of order?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01700"><p>Yes, it is.  An independent electoral commission sets the boundaries.  It is outrageous and a slur on the Government parties and this House for the Senator to make those accusations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01800"><p>Will the Senator, please, resume her seat?  Senator Terry Leyden should proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C01900"><p>It is also a slur on the independent electoral commission.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02000"><p>The Tullymander helped to have Fianna F&aacute;il voted in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02100"><p>I knew Jim Tully well; he was a fine man.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02200"><p>That is not relevant to the Order of Business.  Does the Senator have a question for the Leader on the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02300"><p>By the way, if the Government wanted to have an independent commission to draw up constituency boundaries, it would not have the Secretary General of the Department of the Environment, Community and local Government draw up the plans or the technical people-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02400"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader on the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02500"><p>The Minister knew what areas were in and interfered in the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02600"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02700"><p>The point I am making is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02800"><p>The point the Senator is making is irrelevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C02900"><p>There is nothing to fear but fear itself.  Even with all of the gerrymandering they are still going to lose their seats - thanks be to God.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03000"><p>Will the Senator, please, resume his seat?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03100"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03200"><p>I call the Senator on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03300"><p>Senator Terry Leyden is out of order and I am very disappointed with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03400"><p>The truth will prevail.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03500"><p>The Senator should not cast the first stone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03600"><p>The Senator to continue on the Order of Business, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03700"><p>How many of them are true socialists?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03800"><p>I refer to the welcome announcement made this morning by the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, that &euro;15 million would be made available for the school book rental scheme capital fund available to all primary schools.  I have been a strong supporter of cutting school costs for parents.  In my role as a member of the Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection, I have advocated this position at our meetings and also with the Minister.  The &euro;15 million was originally to be allocated to primary schools that did not have in place a book rental scheme, but following lobbying by me, as I had received representations from many schools which had initiated their own book rental schemes, the fund will now be made available to all primary schools, which is something to be welcomed in these economic times.  The roll-out of this allocation will give recognition to the hard work done by schools with book rental schemes.  By aiding the schools with book rental schemes and helping others to create new ones, we will ease the back to school cost burden on many parents and provide much needed assistance for schools through this worthwhile endeavour.  I am delighted that 13 primary schools in my constituency have been allocated a total of almost &euro;300,000 to support the setting up of book rental schemes.  This is another good effort by the Government to reduce the cost of education for parents.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C03900"><p>I agree with Senator Aideen Hayden on security of tenure, which is very important.  I am astonished as, I suppose, an elderly man that once again in this country we are seeing evictions, but it is not just evictions of tenants.  Last Friday, as I was leaving the office, I was contacted by people who were in distress.  They were occupying the premises of an auctioneering company which was selling off, by private treaty, repossessed farms.  I was given information which indicated that criminal damage was being caused to a property by the receiver and his agents and that the Garda had charged another party for allegedly causing criminal damage and assault in the taking of possession of the farm in Tipperary.  I  have photographs of a house on the property which was burned down.  I have photographs of a horse which was brutally killed and had one of its hind legs removed, apparently with some kind of hacksaw.  Angle grinders were used to gain entrance to the property.  I am referring to a widow who lives on her own and such behaviour is not appropriate.  It is a disgrace.  I asked the Garda if I could enter the premises without infringing the law because, as a law-maker, I could not publicly be seen to break the law and it stated it was all right.  I expressed my sympathy to the young man in charge of the office because he was just an employee, but the directors' attitude was not helpful.  They just brushed past and I am told they laughed at the people in distress outside.  I ask for a debate on evictions, in which we could take in the very serious points made by Senator Aideen Hayden, but we need to examine the question of evictions throughout the country because it is appalling that this is happening.<br />As we approach the Easter period, I would like to end with some good news.  The Committee on Procedure and Privileges unanimously supported the suggestion that Pope Francis be invited to come to the House.  Seanad &Eacute;ireann concurred with it unanimously.  I notice a report in the newspapers which states Peter Robinson, First Minister of Northern Ireland,stated: &quot;If a Papal visit takes place it is largely a matter of what basis he is coming on.  If he is coming as head of state then clearly, as with any other head of state, I could meet the Pope.&quot;  That is remarkable.  <b></b>I cannot imagine a previous circumstance in which a member of the DUP indicated publicly that he would be prepared to meet and welcome the Pope.  Although this suggestion may be progressing slowly, the Seanad has initiated it and I hope it will play some role in the process, although we should not exaggerate it.  I understand there is a possibility that the Vatican Embassy will be reopened with a resident ambassador in the comparatively near future.  If that is the case, we will have clear contact between the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade and the Vatican.  Whether one believes, or, like me, is not a member of the Roman Catholic Church, everybody would get a bounce from the presence of this remarkable, spiritual man who has a vision that encompasses not just the interests of his own flock but also the welfare of humanity as a whole.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C04200"><p>The Senator has his own good direction.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700004#C04300"><p>I thank Dr. David Robert Grimes, physicist at Oxford University, for his excellent opinion piece in <i>The Irish Times</i>yesterday.  He notes that UNICEF estimates that immunisation saves 9 million lives a year and has eradicated smallpox and made polio a thing of the past, among other huge advances.  Many here will know survivors of the disease who are living with post-polio syndrome, from a time in Ireland when immunisation was unheard of, yet there are still those who are in denial and refusing to have their children immunised against the most prevalent and dangerous diseases.  Whether through ignorance or genuine fear, they are putting their children and the population as a whole in danger.  Measles is a good case in point.  Without delving into the science in too much detail, to protect infants and others who cannot avail of the vaccine, the general populace must have an immunity level of approximately 94%, but we are nowhere near it.</p> <p>The incidence of measles is on the rise.  Dr. Grimes noted that in 2011 there were 26,000 cases of measles in Europe, resulting in nine deaths and nearly 7,300 hospitalisations.  One outbreak in west County Cork in 2012 infected more than 50 people, with a staggering 88% of those infected never having received a single dose of the vaccine.  Potentially life-saving vaccines are not being administered as they should be, with potentially very serious consequences for the population as a whole.  I ask the Deputy Leader to facilitate a debate on the matter with the Minister for Health.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D00200"><p>I ask the Deputy Leader for a debate on the proposal for free GP care for those aged under six.  Despite everybody's best intentions for reform in the health service, it is worrying that we are going ahead with a political gimmick in making free GP care available for those aged under six.  It is not supported by the GPs and they have not been consulted on it.  They are advising against it for a variety of reasons, yet we still intend to press ahead.  This is happening at a time when we are inundated with distressed elderly people being subjected to reviews of their medical cards and in many instances losing discretionary cards.  This requires very close examination before we press ahead with it.  There have been many GP meetings throughout the country.  Their criticisms represent more than vested interest and we should listen to them.</p><p>I agree with Senator Mooney on the concern nationally about Irish Water.  There is concern about the cost and confusion.  This outfit is now established.  While most people agree with the principle of those who can do so paying something towards their water infrastructure, we have set up this super-quango and in the interim all national capital works have ground to a halt.  For example, there is a scheme in Sligo known as the bundle scheme, where Tubbercurry, Strandhill and Grange are waiting for wastewater treatment facilities.  Everything is ready to go, but because Irish Water is now in control of such schemes, it has come to a complete stop.  The time to secure a single connection for a rural dwelling seems to have gone back by several months.  These are legitimate concerns that need to be addressed.</p><p>As for the accusation that Fianna F&aacute;il signed up to this, that or the other in the past, I was never in government and never signed up to anything.  Even if I did, I listened to the people who indicated by taking 53 seats from the then Government that they did not approve of what it was doing.  It must be stupid in the extreme for a government not to learn from the mistakes of a previous one when the public spoke so clearly against what it was doing.  Just because somebody happened to do something in the past and played for the same team, it does not require me nor any of my colleagues to do anything today.  We cannot play last season's matches again this season.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D00300"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il is good at playing the game though.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D00400"><p>I join Senator Moran in welcoming the funding that has been made available for the schoolbooks scheme in primary schools.  It is a very practical way of supporting parents and children in schools and reducing the cost of schoolbooks and the cost of going to school.  More importantly, it introduces efficiency.  We have long complained about the waste of schoolbooks and the number of schoolbooks that cannot be recycled and so on.  Because both new schools and existing schools will benefit from the money being made available I trust that those schools with an existing scheme will endeavour to assist those schools, if required, in setting up new schemes so that best practice can be followed by those schools.</p><p>I am a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and Marine, which has been discussing this week the problems facing fishermen who specialise in shellfish and who lost pots during the recent storms.  We have been talking to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Marine about improving the compensation scheme that was put in place.  There are various problems with the scheme, not least that the number of pots fishermen are allowed to seek is quite low and the need for receipts, which are very difficult to produce, particularly for pots that have been in their possession for a long time.  Some of these fishermen are struggling after some months.  While the compensation scheme is welcome, it needs some improvement.  Perhaps we could also raise the matter with the Minister in this House because while a small number of fishermen are involved, for them it is their livelihood.  Some of them are unable to go out and fish and because they have no cashflow they are unable to buy any replacement pots.  If they could do that they would get the compensation returned to them, but they have no cash in their pockets to do so.  Thus, the scheme is welcome but it is flawed.  It would be good to have a debate on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D00500"><p>When we consider that this is the 100th anniversary of Cumann na mBan, we can see that equality eludes us still.  This can be compared with the commemoration for the 100th anniversary of the Irish Volunteers in the Garden of Remembrance, broadcast live on television, at which the President spoke and there was a guard of honour.  The commemoration for the 100th anniversary of Cumann na mBan was on a Wednesday.  The President did not speak at the event, nor did any Minister.  The chairman of the Glasnevin Trust was the main speaker.  One would have to say that equality eludes still when last year for the first time in the history of the State a bridge over the River Liffey-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.68" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D00700"><p>Senator Daly without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D00800"><p>Sorry, Paul; I did not hear you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D00900"><p>Through the Chair, Senator Daly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D01000"><p>I was interrupted again, Paul.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D01100"><p>Senator Bacik is the Deputy Leader today.  I ask Senator Daly to speak through the Chair.  Does he have a question for the Deputy Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D01200"><p>For the first time in the history of the State a bridge over the Liffey was named after a woman, a member of Cumann na mBan.  Considering Dublin is quite an old city, that in itself is a disgrace.  I propose an amendment to the Order of Business to include our motion that the Government name previously unnamed roads, buildings and parks after Cumann na mBan and its members.  I ask Members on both sides of the House to consider how many public buildings, parks and roads are named after women.  They would be very hard-pressed to name five.  Equality eludes us still.  Given that the Deputy Leader would support it, perhaps she would press for what has happened in other counties, including in Carrick-on-Suir and Carrick-on-Shannon, where, following motions from this party, it has been proposed that public parks and housing infrastructure be named after Cumann na mBan.  That is happening in Cork and Kerry, where the President's wife will open a park in honour of Cumann na mBan.</p><p>I also call for a debate on emigration and employment.  A report by UCC shows that up to 60% of those who emigrate are leaving employment.  When the Government claims it is creating jobs, the reality is that emigration is creating jobs, because 60% of those leaving are leaving jobs and those jobs are being filled by others.  Thus, it is not a recovery; it is just a recovery by emigration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700005#D01300"><p>I support Senator Norris's request that Pope Francis be invited to Ireland.  He has been a positive influence on the Catholic Church since his election as Pope.  He has been very reforming and it would be positive for us to have him come to the country.</p><p>I also support Senator MacSharry's reasonable request for a debate on the proposed introduction of free GP care for those aged under six, about which there are concerns.  I would go a step further and suggest that we could have a public consultation in this House.  Obviously we would not want to duplicate the work of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Health and Children.  However, I believe it would be useful.  We have seen how this Chamber can be useful in public consultation.  It may be an opportunity at this stage to air concerns that various interests have on the issue.</p><p>I wish to raise an agricultural issue that I would not normally raise, but it is one that has great potential for the economy overall.</p> <p>During the week the Irish Dairy Board reported an 87% increase in pre-tax profits for last year, up &euro;10.6 million to &euro;22.8 million.  The company's turnover was also up 5% in 2013, rising to &euro;2.12 billion.  This is just the beginning because when the milk quotas, which have been in place since 1984, end in April next year it is estimated that there will be a further increase in production of up to 50%.  This will lead to the creation of a potential income of &euro;800 million for daily farmers and a value of &euro;1.3 billion for the agrifood sector.  There is a major opportunity for us to open up previously untouched markets.  Work is being done to increase the market in places such as the Middle East, Asia and west Africa.  The Minister, Deputy Coveney, is a regular visitor to the House, and we could discuss and debate this positive story in the House in the near future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E00200"><p>Although I welcome the fact that the Minister, Deputy Coveney, has commissioned a report on fluoride, I wish he would not waste our money on that report because I am not paying water charges if I am going to be medicated without my permission.  We are all being mass medicated and the Irish citizen has not been educated about this.  From a cost perspective, 1.6 million litres of water per day must be fluoridated, and we all know how much is wasted because we need to improve our water system.  A 2003 report conducted in the last town in Switzerland to fluoridate its water, Basel, found only 0.1% of the water was being drunk by humans, with the rest going into the environment.  Even in small amounts fluoride is very damaging to water systems.</p><p>Coming back to the Minister, Deputy Coveney, and the last speaker, we should think of our agriculture, food business, export success, the end of milk quotas and our grass-fed beef.  Then we should think of 1.6 million litres soaking into our rivers and environment and being sprayed on our plants.  A proper study has never been done on the effect of fluoride on our environment.  It is time to stop this and save the money spent on the expert fluoridation group.  What does the rest of Europe know that the Irish expert group on fluoridation does not know?  This must stop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E00300"><p>I second the amendment to the Order of Business tabled by my colleague Senator Daly.  It would be opportune to commemorate the founding of Cumann na mBan 100 years ago and I regret that the Government has not taken the initiative.  These women dedicated themselves in a selfless way to achieving Irish independence.  There is a great debate on the need for more women to be involved in politics.  Rather than seeking artificial means of achieving that, one way to do it would be to highlight the contribution these women made, which gave not only the women but the men in these Houses the opportunity to take their place in an independent Irish Parliament.  The dismissive, arrogant way the English Government and politicians are treating Scotland indicates what would be happening if we had not achieved our independence 100 years ago and were pursuing it now.  We should value those women and properly commemorate them by ensuring buildings and public roads are there as a permanent reminder of their selfless sacrifice for this country.  I am very happy to support the amendment.</p><p>Could we arrange for the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, or his successor in the event that the Labour Party and the Government ever recover their moral fibre, to come here to discuss the issue of the report by the Competition Authority in 2006 which sought that competition be injected into our predatory legal fees system?  Access to the courts is available only to the very wealthy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E00500"><p>Those who participate in the profession get obscene amounts for very little effort and work.  It is unconscionable that it has not been tackled, given the IMF recommendations, one of which was to ensure competition in our legal profession.  The fact that we still pay people &euro;200,000 to &euro;500,000 per year from public finances when hard-pressed taxpayers and those on social welfare are paying the price shows the lack of political commitment to dealing with these very unfair issues which must be addressed if we are to have a more just society.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E00600"><p>I agree with Senator Mooney's comments on the excellent debate here last night with the Taoiseach on the terms of reference of the commission of investigation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E00700"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E00800"><p>As the Senator said, it was good to see the Taoiseach here and we would like to see him here more often.  He has been here much more often than the previous Taoiseach, Brian Cowen; it is probably a fair comment.  It was an excellent debate and clarified a number of issues about the important commission of investigation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E00900"><p>It is an unfair comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01000"><p>Senator Mooney also raised the issue of water charges.  This morning, the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, made clear on "Morning Ireland" that no decision had been made, nothing had been signed off and Labour Party Ministers in particular felt they had not received enough notice or information to come to a decision on the method of charging.  The figures given are average figures, with an average meter charge of &euro;240.  My colleague Senator Paul Coghlan pointed out that this is less than the average set out by the Fianna F&aacute;il four-year programme in 2010, which proposed an average charge of &euro;400 and stated that it would transfer water services to a water utility.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01100"><p>We wait with great interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01200"><p>As Senator Hayden pointed out, the T&aacute;naiste said the Labour Party would not sign off on any water charge that is not fair and equitable.  In particular, we want to ensure that families on low incomes are not disadvantaged unduly by water charges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01300"><p>It will be a first for the Labour Party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01400"><p>Senator MacSharry acknowledged, and all of us accept, that there is a water conservation issue and that charging for water will have an effect-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01500"><p>There is a water quality issue also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01600"><p>And fluoride.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01700"><p>There are many issues around water and colleagues have raised a number of them.  We will all benefit from moving to a better and more sustainable water infrastructure.  The Government has made figures available that show that the State has been under-investing in water services for years, and we all agree with that.  Senator Leyden mentioned that nationally 18,000 or 19,000 people boil their drinking water every day.  That is unsustainable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01800"><p>That is in Roscommon alone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E01900"><p>I have been given that figure as a national figure.  Dublin is struggling to meet capacity requirements.  We have had water switch-offs in Dublin and many treatment plants are inadequate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02000"><p>We use whiskey to purify our water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02100"><p>I will make no comment on whiskey in the Senator's water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02200"><p>Is it whiskey in the water or water in the whiskey?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02300"><p>The State has been underspending for decades.  It has spent an average of &euro;300 million per year while the true cost of meeting the national requirements for water and wastewater treatment plants and for upgrading infrastructure would be more than &euro;600 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02400"><p>How will the Government deal with the shortfall?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02500"><p>With water charges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02600"><p>Senator Bacik without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02700"><p>Give her a chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02800"><p>Senator Paul Coghlan has pointed out that there is a great deal of wastage and a great deal to be done.  May I speak without interruption?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E02900"><p>Senator Bacik without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E03000"><p>I listened with courtesy, although it was difficult sometimes not to interrupt my colleagues on the other side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E03100"><p>I am just a little excited about it.  I apologise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E03200"><p>I know the Senator is a bit excited with the holidays starting this evening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E03300"><p>Allow the Acting Leader to speak without interruption and reply to all the questions raised on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700006#E03400"><p>Thank you.  We had an extensive debate on the establishment of Irish Water and the concept of a water charge and we have been told the Government will make a decision on that in due course but that there was not enough information available to make that decision at this week's Cabinet meeting.</p> <p>I am happy to seek a debate with the Minister after Easter when the Cabinet decision has been made, but the Leader has pointed out that we have had extensive debates on a measure to which Fianna F&aacute;il signed up when in government.  </p><p>I take issue with Senator Paschal Mooney's rather clich&eacute;d charge that the Government has an anti-rural bias.  Every party in opposition during the years has stated the Government has an anti-rural bias.  There is no truth in it and we should scupper the notion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F00200"><p>The Government parties will not win a seat in Roscommon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F00300"><p>Members should allow the Deputy Leader to reply to questions put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F00400"><p>As someone who grew up in rural Ireland, I reject any notion that the Government is anti-rural Ireland.  It is nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F00500"><p>It has changed since then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F00600"><p>Senator Paschal Mooney magnanimously acknowledged that Fianna F&aacute;il had referred to the incorrect statutory instrument durng Private Members' time.  If he wants to have a debate on the matter, he should put forward the correct statutory instrument next time and, of course, we will have a debate on it.</p><p>Senator Paul Coghlan referred to Fianna F&aacute;il's amnesia about water charges.  There has, as yet, been no sign-off by the Government, as the Minister of State, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, made clear in her interview on &quot;Morning Ireland&quot;.</p><p>Senator Sean D. Barrett called for a debate on Northern Ireland with the T&aacute;naiste.  We will look to arrange such a debate.  It would be good timing to have it in advance of the marching season.  </p><p>The Senator also raised the question of the transfer by NAMA of non-performing assets and referred to the need for NAMA not to hold onto assets forever as this could delay recovery.  This is acknowledged, but there is a difficulty with flooding the market.  NAMA is conscious of the fact that there must be a judicious approach to the disposal of assets.</p><p>Senator Aideen Hayden referred to water charges and called for a debate on security of tenure in the rental sector and the regulation of rental properties.  I am well aware, particularly in Dublin, of the serious implications for many families living in rental accommodation, for which landlords have hiked up the rent without giving much notice and in such a way as to make it unaffordable for families.  This is a serious matter and I am glad that the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, will speak about the rent supplement issue.  We will seek a separate debate with the Minister of State, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, on regulation and security of tenure in the rental sector.</p><p>Senator Terry Leyden referred to water charges, but I will pass over his comments about the local election constituencies.  Suffice it to say, Senators Aideen Hayden and Mary Moran dealt with that issue and it is outrageous to suggest the independent electoral commission was in some way biased in its approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F00700"><p>Who drew up the plans but the Secretary General of the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F00800"><p>That is utterly wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F00900"><p>We cannot have independence if we are relying on civil servants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01000"><p>The Senator has already spoken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01100"><p>I know all about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01200"><p>I did not interrupt the Senator.  When the leader of Fianna F&aacute;il, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, made a comment about this issue after the conference, he was utterly contradicted by the members of the independent electoral commission.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01300"><p>They would say that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01400"><p>The Senator should allow the Deputy Leader to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01500"><p>Senator Mary Moran welcomed the announcement made by the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, of the allocation of &euro;15 million for the school book rental scheme for all primary schools.  I join her in welcoming the measure which is hugely important.  The cost of primary school books is very high and difficult for parents to meet.  People can no longer pass on books because they are in workbook format and can only be used by one child.  That is a real problem with school publishers.<br />Senator David Norris supported Senator Aideen Hayden in seeking a debate on security of tenure.  He also referred to the serious matter of evictions.  If he has information on the serious criminal offences he disclosed to us, it should be reported to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, as I think he has done.  Any information he has available should be handed on.  He also referred to a visit by the Pope and the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  We have already covered that issue at the committee.<br />Senator Hildegarde Naughton thanked Dr. David Robert Grimes for his article in <i>The Irish Times</i>on immunisation and called for a debate with the Minister for Health on the vaccination programme.  I agree with her in her point about the dangers of the non-immunisation of schoolchildren and the increased incidence of measles.  Like her, I was concerned about the outbreak in west Cork in 2012.  Too many parents are relying on the concept of herd immunity and not having their children immunised.  We need a public education campaign to remind them of the huge importance of immunisation.<br />Senator Marc MacSharry called for a debate on free GP care for children under six years.  It is welcome that the Cabinet finaly agreed to it this week.  We will have a debate on the legislation which is due to be brought before the House before the summer, according to the Minister of State, Deputy Alex White, who has invited consultations with GPs, many of whom are objecting in a way that does not recognise the major benefits the scheme will have for parents.  It is also a milestone on the way to providing universal health care for all, to which the Government is committed.  It is an important reform that will move us away from the inequitable two-tier health structure we have inherited.  Colleagues interested in the point should look at the study published in <i>The Irish Times</i>health supplement by Professor Tom O'Dowd of Trinity College Dublin which contradicts some of the claims made by GPs at public meetings.  They suggest they will face an enormous hike in the numbers of visits as a result of the introduction of the free GP scheme.  The study by Professor O'Dowd shows the increase in the numbers of visits will be far lower than what they suggest.  I urge all colleagues to look at the study which was published yesterday.<br />Senator Susan O'Keeffe spoke about the school book scheme and I agree with her.  She also called for a debate with the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine on a compensation scheme for shellfish fishermen who lost pots in the storms.  She referred to some flaws in the scheme.  We can ask the Minister to attend as he is receptive to requests to come to the Chamber.  It may also be appropriate to table the matter for discussion on the Adjournment if it concerns a specific point about flaws in the scheme.<br />Senator Mark Daly proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, although I am not clear to what it relates.  He spoke about a motion on the Order Paper and I am not sure if he is looking to have it debated today.  The motion calls on the Government to name currently unnamed public buildings, roads or parks after Cumann na mBan or a member of it.  I agree with the spirit of the motion and that it would have been nice to see more done to commemorate the 100th anniversary.  I was sorry I was unable to attend, because of business in this House, the event at Glasnevin Cemetery which the President attended.  This is not a matter for the Government but local councils which deal with the naming of public parks and roads.  I commend Dublin City Council for recently passing a motion to name the new bridge after Rosie Hackett.  It is the first bridge in Dublin to be named after a woman, one who was active in the independence movement.  It was an initiative taken by citizens, many of whom were involved in the Labour Party, Labour Women and Labour Youth.  I commend them for taking it.  The motion is problematic because it deals with a matter that is not one for central government to deal with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01600"><p>Can the House ask the Government to call on the local authorities to deal with it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01700"><p>The Senator may wish to reword the motion which may then attract all-party agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01800"><p>Senator Mark Daly is being mischievous, as ever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F01900"><p>He may be a little mischievous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F02000"><p>He is from Kerry, after all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700007#F02100"><p>In the spirit of commemorations, I have asked the Leader to commemorate in June this year the 750th anniversary of the first parliamentary gathering in Ireland, held in Castledermot, County Kildare.  It is referred to on the Oireachtas website and colleagues interested in commemorations may be interested in it.  </p><p>Senator Mark Daly called for a debate on emigration.  The job creation figures which have been referred to in the House many times are positive and contradict the Senator's assertion that the welcome downturn in unemployment is due to emigration.  It is not; there is net job creation.</p><p>Senator Catherine Noone referred to a visit by the Pope and called for a debate on the provision of GP care for those under six years of age.  We will have a debate on the legislation.  Public consultation has been scheduled for Tuesday, 6 May.  Senator Katherine Zappone has communicated with us about that event, on compliance with international human rights instruments, particularly the International Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, and all colleagues are encouraged to attend.  I do not think we will have time before the summer recess to engage in another public consultation exercise which takes time to set up.</p><p>Senator Catherine Noone also mentioned the Irish Dairy Board.  We might invited the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Simon Coveney, to speak about the positive figures from the board and the possibility of finding new markets for our dairy exports.  </p><p>Senator Mary Anne O'Brien referred to fluoridation.  I have dealt with the matter of water charges.  We can ask the Minister to come to the Chamber to discuss the issue.  The Senator welcomed the fact that there was to be a review of fluoridation, an issue on which we had a full debate in response to a motion tabled by Senator David Norris.</p> <p>I hope we will have a full debate on the outcome of the review that has been announced, which again will be in the context of a transformation in the maintenance of our water infrastructure and the provision of water services.</p><p>Senator Walsh also referred to the motion, which I have dealt with.  He called also for the Minister for Justice and Equality to come to the Chamber to discuss legal fees.  The Government has taken action already, as the Senator probably will be aware, by not only introducing the Legal Services Regulation Bill 2011 which is progressing through the Oireachtas but also in requiring a reduction in fees when the State is the client.  I am familiar with criminal legal aid and the fees in that area have been greatly reduced.  Action has been taken already on this issue.</p><p>I wish colleagues a Happy Easter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700008#G00200"><p>On a point of clarification, does Senator Daly wish to move motion No. 44(5)?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700008#G00300"><p>In light of the Acting Leader's suggestions, I will withdraw the motion and have it reworded.  I hope the motion will then get Government approval and the Government will call on local authorities to name buildings after members of Cumann na mBan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.134" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.135" nospeaker="true" time="11:20:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.31 a.m. and resumed at noon.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.136" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700009#H00100">Protection of Children's Health from Tobacco Smoke Bill 2012: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700009#H00200"><p>I welcome the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly.  Before we commence, I remind Senators that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment who may reply to the discussion on the amendment.  Amendment No. 1 is a Government amendment which arises out of committee proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.138" nospeaker="true" time="11:25:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:
In page 3, lines 7 to 12, to delete all words from and including &quot;AMEND&quot; in line 7 down to and including line 12 and substitute the following:
&quot;create an offence of smoking a tobacco product in the presence of a child in a mechanically propelled vehicle; and to provide for related matters.&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700009#H00400"><p>T&aacute; &aacute;thas orm bheith anseo inniu le haghaidh na d&iacute;osp&oacute;ireachta ar an mBille seo.  This amendment sets out the Long Title to the Bill.  The Senators' Bill has been presented as an amendment to the Public Health (Tobacco) Act 2002 and, as the Senators' know, I have been very supportive of this.  The Senators' Bill seeks to amend section 47 of that Act which prohibits the smoking of tobacco products in the workplace.  I propose that the provisions to prohibit smoking in cars with children present should be set out in a stand-alone Bill for a number of reasons.</p><p>The privately-owned car does not represent a workplace and it is not appropriate that it be included in section 47.  The enforcement officers of this provision will be members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and not HSE environmental officers, as currently set out in the Public Health (Tobacco) Acts.  The penalties outlined for the offence in the Senators' Bill are set out as fixed charge notices and are quite distinct from the penalties already set out in the Public Health (Tobacco) Acts.  Bearing these factors in mind, it is more appropriate for the Bill to be presented as stand-alone legislation as its operation does not rely on provisions from existing tobacco legislation and for those reasons, I commend this amendment to the House. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700009#H00500"><p>I thank An tAire and his staff for the effort that has gone into getting these Report Stage amendments which my co-sponsors, Senators van Turnhout and Daly, and I accept.  We wish to see the Bill get through as quickly as possible and we understand the reasons for the fundamental change in the nature of the Bill for clarity's sake.  The reason we did it this way was that we thought, perhaps somewhat naively two years ago, it would have been faster if we did it as a simple amendment to existing legislation.  We will accept the Minister's amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700009#H00600"><p>I would like some clarification.  When we met the officials the other day - I thank them for all the work they have done, in particular Geraldine Luddy and Dilly O'Brien - they clearly said that there was no outstanding issue or impediment to this Bill going to the D&aacute;il.  The Minister's Department has no issue nor does any other Department, so when we accept these amendments, there is no reason the Bill should be in any way slowed down or impeded from going through the D&aacute;il relatively quickly.  We could have it in place by the summer.  I would like to get that reassurance from the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700009#H00700"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for his support for this legislation.  I commend Senators van Turnhout and Crown on pushing this forward.  Following on from what Senator van Turnhout asked, will this Bill get through the D&aacute;il before the summer recess in light of the fact the amendments are agreed to and that no further amendments should be necessary in the D&aacute;il?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="11:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700009#H00800"><p>I echo what my colleagues have said and welcome the Minister.  I was inadvertently working on his behalf as the tobacco lobbyists are about again and were asking for interviews.  However, I will not let the Minister down in the cause.  I just told them to send in whatever papers they have and I would read them.  However, I do not wish to be lobbied by the tobacco industry.  I think we are <i>ad idem</i>on all of that.  As my colleagues have said, I hope the Bill will proceed quickly because the original objective two years ago was to protect children going on holidays in cars and that they would not experience tobacco smoke.<br />As a non-lawyer, I thought we were splitting hairs in substituting the amendments for what was in the Bill but if it all works out well at the end, I will join with my colleagues in welcoming it.  However, I could not see the point in some of the amendments to the original Bill.  <br />We are all at one on this and I will support the Minister in his other moves on plain labelling and restrictions on the sale of tobacco.  I share his goal of a tobacco-free society, and that includes in cars and in cars with children.  There is also a road safety dimension.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for bringing the Bill to the House and wish him every success in his continuing efforts to create a smoke-free society.  He knows more than anyone else the damage smoking does to people's health and the health service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J00200"><p>I remind Members that just as the Seanad's business is ours, the business of the D&aacute;il is a matter for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J00300"><p>Following those very wise words from the Cathaoirleach-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J00400"><p>Is Senator David Norris indicating that he wishes to speak to the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J00500"><p>I just want to make a brief contribution.  I welcome the Minister.  There is very judicious collaboration between Senator John Crown and the Minister in producing the Bill which I very much hope will go through because it is very important because children are so vulnerable.  A motor car is a much more confined environment than even a room or public bar.  I have no doubt that there are children whose health has severely suffered as a result.  The Bill is a very good one and I hope we will have time to deal with the amendments.  For that reason, I will not say anything more than Senator John Crown's initiative and those of my other colleagues, Senators Sean D. Barrett and Feargal Quinn, in producing legislation in very important areas have demonstrated post-referendum the significance and the value to the country of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J00600"><p>I am nearly afraid to stand up in case I have to sit down again.  An bhfuil cead agam seasamh suas anois ar feadh tamaill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J00700"><p>T&aacute; an Ghaeilge go fl&uacute;irseach ag an Aire.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J00800"><p>T&aacute; go leor Gaeilge agam.  T&aacute; seanfhocal ann a deir, "N&iacute; neart go cur le ch&eacute;ile".  T&aacute;imid &aacute; dh&eacute;anamh sin anseo anois.</p><p>There is great strength in working together in the way we have done and I thank everyone involved.  As we know, this is part of a long battle and I acknowledge the latitude demonstrated.  Senator Sean D. Barrett makes a very important point that the tobacco industry will be very active and bring its considerable forces and might to bear on this small island in order to frustrate our attempts to protect children from the harmful effects of tobacco, effects which are not just harmful but also killer effects.  We are all in the one smokeless car together on this one.</p><p>There may be a difficulty in discerning the differences between the amendments, but they are serious.  I refer to a point that has delayed the other legislation in being published, that we have to be ultra careful in everything to do in dealing with tobacco.  The industry has rafts of lawyers poring over everything we do and say, looking to find holes and a rationale for a challenge.  Everything has to be done particularly carefully or there will be an attempt to knock it down in the courts.  The industry has very deep pockets and will do whatever it takes.  We know what it has been like in the past when it has been less than forthcoming with evidence showing that its product is a killer product.  We have had this discussion that it is the only product we know of that, when used as directed by the manufacturer, kills one in two of those who use it regularly.</p><p>I refer to Senator Jillian van Turnhout's request that I give some guarantee.  I cannot give one.  There are 166 reasons in the D&aacute;il there might be an amendment because any one Member of the other House might table an amendment that might make sense and I do not wish to preclude this from happening.  As the Cathaoirleach has pointed out, it would not be appropriate to do so.  I emphasise that I want the Bill to be enacted as quickly as possible.  I want to see children protected in every way possible and as quickly as possible and as such, I will do everything to expedite the Bill.  I thank Senators Jillian van Turnhout, Mark Daly and John Crown for promoting it, sticking with it and co-operating so well with staff in the Department.  Like so many things in life that look simple from the outside, it can become very complicated when so many Departments are involved, which was a concern.  Some of the later amendments might seem to some to be a little lenient, but the Office of the Attorney General was very clear on the issue of proportionality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.152" nospeaker="true" time="11:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.153" nospeaker="true" time="11:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 2:
In page 3, to delete lines 14 and 15 and substitute the following:&ldquo;Definitions
1. In this Act&mdash;
&ldquo;child&rdquo; means a person who has not attained the age of 18 years;
&ldquo;mechanically propelled vehicle&rdquo; has the same meaning as it has in the Road Traffic Act 1961;
&ldquo;Minister&rdquo; means the Minister for Health;
&ldquo;public place&rdquo; has the same meaning as it has in the Road Traffic Act 1961;
&ldquo;tobacco product&rdquo; has the same meaning as it has in the Public Health (Tobacco) Act 2002.&rdquo;.Amendment No. 2 sets out the definitions of &quot;child&quot; and &quot;mechanically propelled vehicle&quot; which were set out in the Senator's Bill.  In addition, I have included the definition of &quot;Minister&quot; to refer to the Minister for Health and the definition of &quot;tobacco product&quot; as having the same meaning as set out in the Public Health (Tobacco) Act 2002.  The inclusion of these definitions is necessary for the Bill's presentation as stand-alone legislation, as opposed to amendments to the Public Health (Tobacco) Act.  The definition of &quot;public place&quot; was deemed necessary following consultation with the Department of Justice and Equality and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to bring the provisions in the Bill into line with other road traffic offences.  I commend the amendment to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J01100"><p>I agree with the amendment which we will accept.  I stress that at a time when the legislative agenda is at an all-time low, the arguments for advancing the Bill in the coming term are overwhelming.  This was one we had hoped would have been protecting children in the summer of 2012.  We urge the Minister to take it on as a personal project and ensure his officials prioritise it.  Let us get one on the score sheet for the good guys in the battle against tobacco.  We can pass the Bill quickly and then proceed to work on the Minister's more definitive Bill on packaging and other regulatory matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J01200"><p>I welcome the Minister's decision to bring the definition of "child" into line with the definition in the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child which covers persons up to 18 years of age.  While I accept the Cathaoirleach's ruling that we cannot order the business of the D&aacute;il, I can ask a question of one of the 166 Members of the other House - the Minister.  His officials told us that there were no outstanding issues or questions being raised by the Department.  I appreciate democracy and that any Member can table an amendment.  However, I ask the Minister to confirm that there are no outstanding issues with regard to the Bill and that he expects it to be given a good passage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J01300"><p>I thank the Senators for their support.  In reply to Senator Jillian van Turnhout, I see no issues with the Bill and no reason it cannot pass through unless someone raises an issue we have not foreseen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.157" nospeaker="true" time="11:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J01450"><p>Amendments Nos. 3 to 5, inclusive, and No. 7 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.159" nospeaker="true" time="11:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 3:
In page 3, to delete lines 16 to 33, to delete page 4, and in page 5, to delete lines 1 to 31 and substitute the following:&ldquo;Prohibition on smoking tobacco product in mechanically propelled vehicle in which child is present
2. (1) The smoking by a person (including a child) of a tobacco product in a mechanically propelled vehicle in a public place and in which a child (or another child if the person smoking is a child) is present is prohibited.
(2) A person who contravenes subsection (1) shall be guilty of an offence.
(3) Where a person who contravenes subsection (1) is not the driver of the mechanically propelled vehicle concerned, the driver shall also be guilty of an offence.
(4) In proceedings for an offence under this section, it shall be presumed, until the contrary is shown, that a person who was present in a mechanically propelled vehicle in which the commission of the alleged offence occurred and who appeared to a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, at that time, to be a child, was, at that time, a child.
(5) In proceedings for an offence under this section, it shall be a defence for a person to show that he or she reasonably believed that any person who was present in the mechanically propelled vehicle in which the commission of the alleged offence occurred had attained the age of 18 years.
(6) Without prejudice to subsection (5), in proceedings for an offence under subsection (3) brought against the driver of the mechanically propelled vehicle concerned, it shall be a defence for that person to show that he or she&mdash;(a) was, by reason of his or her driving of that vehicle, unable to prevent the commission of the alleged offence under subsection (2) by another person in that vehicle, or
(b) made all reasonable efforts to prevent the commission of the alleged offence under subsection (2) by another person in that vehicle.&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700010#J01700"><p>Amendment No. 3 sets out the key prohibition; amendment No. 4 sets out the powers of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na; amendment No. 5 sets out provisions for the fixed charge notice; while amendment No. 7 sets out penalties for the offences included in the Bill.  These amendments provide that if a person, an adult or a child, is smoking in a mechanically propelled vehicle, in the presence of another child, the smoker is guilty of an offence.  This amendment also makes a driver of a mechanically propelled vehicle guilty of an offence, whether the driver or another person is the person smoking in the said vehicle.</p><p>The Senator's Bill contained this principle of the driver's liability.  However, we have included defences in our amendments which are proportionate.  We have allowed one defence for the smoker and two additional defences for the driver if he or she is not the person smoking in the vehicle.  These defences are that the smoker and-or the driver reasonably believed everyone in the car was over 18 years of age; that the driver could not prevent a passenger from smoking without compromising safety; and that the driver made all reasonable efforts to prevent the passenger from smoking.  These defences for the driver are reasonable as the driver's main responsibility is to ensure the safety of his or her passengers in the activity of driving, for example, driving safely and ensuring children in the vehicle are strapped in correctly.</p><p>Amendment No. 4 provides for the powers of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Similar to the Senator's Bill, it gives An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na the power to stop a car and request the name and address of the person committing the offence.  If a person fails to stop, refuses to give information or gives false information, he or she is guilty of an offence.  References to the driver's licence or learner permit have not been included as these are more appropriate in the context of road traffic offences, not this offence which is created from a public health perspective.</p><p>With regard to the fixed charge notice provisions, we agreed with the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport that it would not be appropriate for the Road Traffic Acts to be amended on the basis that the offence of smoking in a car with children present was a public health matter, not a road traffic offence.</p> <p>However, it was agreed that the fixed-charge notice provisions should be similar to those already operated by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na for ease of application.  For this reason the period of days allowed for payment of the fine is 28 days and not 21 days as set out in the Senator's Bill.  In addition this section allows for the increase of the original fine by 50% where that fine is not paid within the 28-day period.  The amendment provides that a prosecution shall not be initiated if the fines are paid within the specified periods.</p><p>Amendment No. 7 contains summary convictions where somebody has committed an offence under the Act.  This includes offences of refusing to stop the car, refusing to give a name or address, and giving false information.  The penalty is in the form of a class D fine, which is not exceeding &euro;1,000.  I commend these amendments to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K00200"><p>I fully agree with the amendments the Minister has set out.  I welcome making the driver responsible even if someone other than the driver is smoking.  In the initial debate I spoke about a driver under the age of 18 who is smoking.  The amendments there are very welcome.  The amendments deal comprehensively with the defence and ensuring that road safety needs to be taken into account in dealing with the issue.  As the amendments deal adequately with the matter, I welcome them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K00300"><p>When the Minister referred to smoking compromising road safety, I would make the case very strongly that it does.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, recently introduced legislation in which he rightly increased the penalties for the use of mobile phones and texting.</p><p>We should consider the transactions involved in smoking: finding the cigarettes; finding the matches; lighting the cigarette; flicking out ash and throwing out butts.  It seems far more disruptive of road safety than the use of a mobile phone.  At the next revision of penalty points we might consider that point.  We drew the attention of the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, to German literature on the road safety dimensions which eventually come back to the Minister for Health given that tens of thousands of people are injured in road accidents and approximately 190 people were killed last year.</p><p>There is also the atmosphere, the smoke and the dizziness caused in cars.  I believe that smoking most certainly compromises road safety and we might look at it the next time around.  This is a dangerous, complicated and polluting transaction that takes place.  It seems more serious for road safety than the use of a mobile phone or texting which has deservedly attracted the ire of the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K00400"><p>I concur with Senator Barrett.  I have been a sometime smoker.  While these are not my words, I defend my right to use them if I felt like it.  A well-known English writer described how she was in London and she was driving.  She dropped her cigarette, as she said herself, on to her fanny and nearly crashed the car.  I had the experience of dropping it on to my fly and one wants to get rid of that pretty quickly.  It certainly interrupts one's driving skill.  So there is undoubtedly a question of safety there.<br />Is the prosecution evidence based?  Senator Barrett referred to throwing the butt out of the window.  Is there a requirement to produce the cigarette or ash, or is it just the word of the police?  Is there any evidential qualification?<br />The Minister proposes to insert: &quot;Where a person who contravenes <i>subsection (1)</i>is not the driver of the mechanically propelled vehicle concerned, the driver shall also be guilty of an offence.&quot;  I was thinking of taxis.  Particularly on weekend nights in metropolitan areas and perhaps in the country, taxi drivers often have very obstreperous and drunken or drugged passengers in the back seat and could be at risk of their lives.  I note that subsection (a) states: &quot;was, by reason of his or her driving of that vehicle, unable to prevent the commission of the alleged offence under <i>subsection (2)</i>by another person in that vehicle&quot;.  So I presume that would cover taxis also.<br />I wonder about the term &quot;reasonably believed&quot;.  Is there a legal definition of &quot;reasonably&quot; - there may well be - or is it left up to the judge, who might be a secret smoker and have sympathy with somebody?<br />Amendment No. 4 states: &quot;A member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na may&quot;.  Since becoming a Member of this House we have had battles between &quot;may&quot; and &quot;shall&quot;.  I am suggesting a kind of Anglican solution - the <i>via media</i>- of &quot;should, where possible&quot;, which would strengthen it.  Perhaps the Minister does not want to take amendments here because he wants to get it through.  However, he might bear it in mind and include it as a Government amendment in the D&aacute;il.  Inserting &quot;shall, where possible&quot; puts an extra onus on the garda to be vigilant.<br />While perhaps I should already know this, what is the fixed charge?  I note it is not quantified, but it may be just a routine charge that is in other Bills.  It is referred to subsequently as a class D fine.  Is it &euro;25, &euro;100 or &euro;500 with an option of a week in jail?  Perhaps the Minister could give us information on that.  What is the fixed charge?  I presume it is the same as a class D fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K00500"><p>I very much welcome the Bill and I congratulate the Senators on introducing it.  In the long term it will be very positive for the country just as the smoking ban was.  When the ban on smoking in pubs and public places was introduced, people actually stopped smoking in houses.  Any smoker who came into my house went outside the door to smoke and I was delighted with that.  I hope the Bill will stop people smoking in cars full stop.</p><p>I have similar concerns to Senator Norris over the phrase, &quot;Where a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has reasonable grounds for believing that a person is committing or has committed an offence&quot;.  Will that really hold up in court?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K00600"><p>Even those in the IRA got locked up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K00700"><p>I know, but we can think of people who did not get locked up and we believe that it was wrong.  However, I am just saying that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K00800"><p>Some of them tell us that they were never members of the IRA.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K00900"><p>Have we gone on to a different topic here?</p><p>If one gets the smell off a car that somebody has been smoking in the car, it could be a passenger or driver, if one has not actually caught them doing it, would it stand up in court?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700011#K01000"><p>I agree with much of what Senator Barrett said about road safety.  A driver could be rummaging around trying to find a cigarette or have the unfortunate experience of Senator Norris and find himself or herself in contortions trying to drive down the road.  However, this could be the passenger who is lighting and smoking the cigarette and therefore have no impact.  One could equally argue that part of the match could fly off and hit the driver in the eye.  This is where we avoid the good being delayed by the perfect.  We should proceed with this as quickly as we can, which is everyone's goal.</p><p>In response to Senator Norris's queries on fines, many of the fines are between &euro;80 and &euro;100 for a first offence.  The Senator also raised the &quot;may&quot; or &quot;shall&quot; argument and he and others spoke about the word &quot;reasonable&quot;.  The term &quot;reasonable&quot; is well known in law and accepted as such.  It is used extensively in the Protection of Life during Pregnancy Act, in terms of &quot;reasonable opinion&quot;, as Senators may recall.  So I believe all these things are covered off.  The &quot;may&quot; or &quot;shall&quot; argument can be for another day.  We can look at it and it can be debated in the D&aacute;il. </p> <p>We would like to see the Bill go through today in order that it can be carried on through D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and become law to ensure children will be protected from the dangers of environmental tobacco smoke.  We have been protecting workers but not children, which seems bizarre.  We are where we are and can now correct the anomaly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.172" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.173" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 4:
In page 5, to delete lines 32 to 43 and substitute the following:
&ldquo;Powers of member of Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na
3. (1) A member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na may, where it appears to him or her that a person in a mechanically propelled vehicle in a public place and in which a child, or a person who appears to be a child, is present, is smoking a tobacco product&mdash;(a) require the driver to stop the vehicle, and
(b) demand of any person in the vehicle whom the member suspects of committing an offence under section 2*, his or her name and address.(2) A person who&mdash;(a) fails to stop a mechanically propelled vehicle in compliance with subsection (1)(a), or
(b) on a demand being made of him or her under subsection (1)(b), fails or refuses to give his or her name and address or gives information which is false or misleading, 
shall be guilty of an offence.&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.174" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.175" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:
In page 6, to delete lines 1 to 6 and substitute the following:&ldquo;Fixed charge notice
4. (1) Where a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has reasonable grounds for believing that a person is committing or has committed an offence under section 2, he or she may serve on a person personally or by post at the address at which the person ordinarily resides or, at the time of the alleged offence, gave to the member or another member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, a notice (&ldquo;fixed charge notice&rdquo;) in the prescribed form stating that&mdash;(a) the person is alleged to have committed the offence,
(b) the person may, during the period of 28 days beginning on the date specified in the notice, make to a person specified in the notice at the address specified in the notice a payment of the prescribed amount accompanied by the notice,
(c) if the person does not make the payment specified in paragraph (b), during the period of 28 days beginning on the expiration of that period, the person may make a payment as specified in the notice of an amount 50 per cent greater than the prescribed amount referred to in paragraph (b),
(d) the person is not obliged to make the payment, and
(e) a prosecution in respect of the alleged offence will not be instituted during the period specified in the notice and, if the payment specified in the notice is made during that period, no prosecution in respect of the alleged offence will be instituted.(2) Where notice is served under subsection (1)&mdash;(a) the person to whom the notice applies may, during the period specified in the notice, make to a person specified in the notice at the address specified in the notice the payment specified in the notice, at the appropriate time so specified in relation to the payment, accompanied by the notice,
(b) the person so specified may receive the payment, issue a receipt for it and retain the money so paid, and any payment so received shall not be recoverable in any circumstances by the person who made it,
(c) a prosecution in respect of the alleged offence shall not be instituted during the period specified in the notice, and if the payment so specified is made during the period, no prosecution in respect of the alleged offence shall be instituted.(3) A prosecution in respect of an offence under *section 2 shall not be instituted unless a fixed charge notice in respect of the alleged offence has been served on the person concerned under this section and the person fails to pay the appropriate amount of the fixed charge in accordance with the notice at the appropriate time specified in the notice in relation to the payment.
(4) In a prosecution for an offence under *section 2, the onus of proving that a payment in accordance with a fixed charge notice has been made lies on the defendant.
(5) Income generated by the payment of amounts pursuant to fixed charge notices under this Act shall be disposed of for the benefit of the Exchequer in such manner determined by the Minister with the agreement of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.176" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L00800"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 and 8 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.178" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:
In page 6, to delete lines 7 and 8 and substitute the following:&ldquo;Regulations
5. (1) The Minister may make regulations prescribing any matter or thing referred to in this Act as prescribed or to be prescribed.
(2) Regulations under this section may contain such incidental, supplementary and consequential provisions as appear to the Minister to be necessary or expedient for the purposes of the regulations.
(3) Every regulation made by the Minister under this Act shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after it is made and, if a resolution annulling the order or regulation is passed by either such House within the next 21 days on which that House sits after the regulation is laid before it, the regulation shall be annulled accordingly, but without prejudice to the validity of anything previously done thereunder.&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L01000"><p>The amendment sets out the powers of the Minister for Health to make regulations.  Senators have given the power to make regulations to the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport in consultation with the Minister for Health.  As this is not a road traffic issue, it is more appropriate that the Minister for Health is granted regulatory powers in this regard.  The Senators' Bill sets out provisions in primary legislation allowing for different fixed charge amounts to be prescribed in regulations depending on, for example, the age of the children and the number of passengers.  The smoking of tobacco in the presence of a child in a mechanically propelled vehicle is as serious and harmful as smoking in the presence of a number of children, regardless of their ages.  With this in mind, the amendments proposed do not include provisions to grade the fixed charges.</p><p>Amendment No. 8 sets out the Short Title and commencement date.  It is proposed that the Title of the legislation be amended to read Protection of Children's Health (Tobacco Smoke in Mechanically Propelled Vehicles) Act 2014.  This Title is proposed to adequately reflect the content and purpose of the Bill.  The provision to allow for commencement orders is required in order to allow the Department of Justice and Equality and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na adequate time to prepare for the introduction of the new legislation.  I commend the amendments to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.180" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.181" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 7:
7. In page 6, to delete lines 9 to 26 and substitute the following:&ldquo;Penalty
6. A person who is guilty of an offence under this Act shall be liable on summary conviction to a class D fine.&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L01300"><p>I was amusing myself by working out how much of the original Bill had been left and thought I would give a brief graphic demonstration of the deletions made.  I would also like to give a graphic demonstration of what is left of the original Bill.  What is left of the Bill is "Be it enacted by the Oireachtas as follows".  In keeping with the spirit and intent of the Bill and the co-operation of the Government, I am pleased that we will support the amendments.  I would like to make one small statement of gratitude.  There are some folk who did a huge job in bringing this initiative to where it is.  It is where it is because it originated with folk in Seanad &Eacute;ireann and their staff.  I thank Senators Mark Daly and Jillian van Turnhout who have been constant supporters of this legislation.  Senator Jillian van Turnhout and her colleagues have done much of the running in making sure the Bill negotiates the parliamentary process.  She is more skilled at that task.  I thank Mr. Shane Conneely who was my adviser throughout the process.  He wrote the original Bill and thought through most of the arguments for the defences that should be included.  I am glad that we have had the refining influence of the Department of Health and the Department of Justice and Equality to ensure it will be easy to enforce, but I would not like Shane's contribution to this effort to go unrecorded, as it was extraordinary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L01400"><p>That is very generous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L01500"><p>Was it the Minister's decision that the Title of the Bill should be changed?  Could we not even have it left intact?  I ask for clarification.  Is it the same Bill or a new one?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L01600"><p>It is the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.186" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.187" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 8:
In page 6, to delete lines 27 to 30 and substitute the following:&ldquo;Short title and commencement
7. (1) This Act may be cited as the Protection of Children&rsquo;s Health (Tobacco Smoke in
Mechanically Propelled Vehicles) Act 2014.
(2) This Act comes into operation on such day or days as the Minister may appoint by order or orders either generally or with reference to any particular purpose or provision and different days may be so appointed for different purposes or different provisions.&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.188" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.189" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.190" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.191" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Question proposed: &quot;That the Bill do now pass.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L02500"><p>The two year gestation period of the Bill corresponds to an elephantine gestation period, if I remember my biology correctly.  The Bill has already achieved my principal aim and that of Senators Mark Daly and Jillian van Turnhout, with Mr. Shane Conneely and other staff, that it provoke debate and have an educational role.  People became aware of the real and proximate risk to the health of children if exposed to smoke tobacco products in the confines of a motor vehicle.  While others have stated this is a further element of the nanny state and Government interference, the truth of the matter is that its principal role is educational.  Children will be aware of it; parents will be aware of it and people will understand this is something they should not do.  I would be very happy if there were no prosecutions under the Bill and if no one smoked in a car with a child present.  That would be the ideal outcome.  I thank the Minister and his officials.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L02600"><p>I thank the Minister and, particularly, Senator John Crown for taking the initiative and asking Senator Mark Daly and me to join him.  I was proud to do so.  I also acknowledge the work done by Mr. Shane Conneely.  I thank the Minister's officials and advisers.  It would be remiss of me not to mention Fionn O'Callaghan, aged nine years, whom Senator John Crown brought to the first briefing on the Bill.  He is a young boy from Wexford who wrote to the Taoiseach to ask him to bring forward this legislation.  I have double pride in view of the fact that we are responding to a young person in Ireland who asked the Taoiseach for this legislation.  It is a good day.  The Bill is educational; it is a public health issue and, first and foremost, a children's rights issue.  Children cannot extract themselves from a car filled with smoke.  They cannot extract themselves from smoke-filled environments.  We need to denormalise smoking as we are putting lives at risk.  It is good and we will do everything we can to support the process in the D&aacute;il.  We will encourage it, as we need to see this Bill in place in the summer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L02700"><p>I thank Senators John Crown, Jillian van Turnhout and Mark Daly for their work on the Bill.  I also thank the Department and the Minister for their work on it.  It is welcome that we are using the process in the House to bring forward new legislation.  Senator John Crown said it had taken two years for his Bill to come through, but in October 2009 the Minister and I published the Medical Practitioners (Amendment) Bill making it compulsory for all medical practitioners to have insurance.  The process has not been completed and I ask the Minister to revisit the issue.  I hope it will be done at some stage during the year.</p><p>Likewise, another Bill I have raised is the Civil Law (Missing Persons) Bill.  If we had a similar accident to the Malaysian aircraft crash, we would rush through emergency legislation to deal with the issue of missing persons.  I ask that the legislation be considered in view of the fact that the Law Reform Commission produced a report on the issue.  The groundwork has been done.  A number of Bills have been published by other Members and they should be given serious consideration in the coming months to ensure they get through during the term of the Government.  I thank those involved in bringing forward this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700012#L02800"><p>I agree with my colleagues that Mr. Shane Conneely deserves great praise for his work on the Bill.  It is not often the recognition deservedly due to officials is acknowledged in the House.  It is fitting and appropriate that we do so.  The Bill shows the strength of independent voices such as those of Senators John Crown and Jillian van Turnhout and those who have a particular skill, whether in dealing with cancer or children's rights.</p> <p>That is the role of the Seanad.  I thank the Minister and his officials.  This is a health issue, but given that this is Easter week it would be appropriate to quote the Bible.  There is a line quoted in the opening credits of the film "Schindler&rsquo;s List": "Whoever saves one life saves the world entire."  The Minister&rsquo;s allowing this Bill come through this House protects children from parents or guardians who would, through pure ignorance, smoke in a car with them.  The most telling statistic we have heard is that if a child is in a car for an hour with a smoker he or she inhales an amount of smoke equivalent to what a firefighter will inhale in eight hours at work.  As Senator Crown said, we do not want prosecutions.  The Bill does not aim to punish people but to educate them and point out the stark reality that by smoking in a car a person subjects a child to enormous health risks, immediately and long into the future.</p><p>This Bill was published on 3 May 2012.  That is a long time ago.  The processes within these Houses have failed the people for a long time.  They failed the people in respect of the cause of the economic crisis, because the way we make legislation and bring about change is far too slow and in some cases it does not happen at all.  Senator Burke pointed out some of the great Bills he and others have introduced which just stop because legislators do not legislate.  The bureaucracy decides what goes forward, and there is too much that needs to be done and too few people at drafting level allowed to do it.  We are not allowed to do it.  The Shane Kenneallys of this world are not allowed to do it either, generally.  This is unique.  It should not be unique.  It should be an everyday occurrence that non-contentious legislation such as this, which everyone agrees is needed, is passed.  It does not happen because legislators are not allowed to push it forward.  It gets jammed in the system.  I told the Taoiseach last night that the fact that only four Bills have been passed in four months is not the revolution in democracy required to ensure this society works better for all its citizens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M00200"><p>The House and Irish society are indebted to the Minister for accepting the Bill and to Senators Crown, Daly and van Turnhout for working on it; to Shane Kenneally, who inspired it; and to Fionn O&rsquo;Callaghan, for bringing the matter directly to the Taoiseach and for coming up here to speak about it.  Is it not a matter for reflection, as Senator Daly said, that this Bill, on which we are all agreed, has taken so long?  Recently a letter went AWOL in the Department of Justice and Equality for 15 days.  We really have to question this.  We were all elected on a reform agenda.  Is the system of governance - the machinery - able to respond, even when we are all agreed?  It needs reform.  The Government might pay attention to that in the remaining two years it has to serve.  We need reform of governance to speed up the process, particularly when we are all agreed.  Parliament needs to assert itself.  It seems to have come about that the permanent government decides the priorities and we are just a nuisance.  That is a negation of everything we will celebrate in the centenary of 1916 and of the earlier Irish parliamentary tradition of Grattan and O&rsquo;Connell, praised by Her Majesty the Queen of England last week.  We have to assert our role in serving the people.  They can give us our walking papers very quickly.  The permanent government has to respond when Parliament requires things to be done, and this most desirable and very attractive measure has taken far too long to get onto the Statute Book.  I hope there will be no further delay.</p><p>The question we must all ask ourselves as Members of this Parliament is what prevents us from carrying out reforms in the whole area of governance across the board, because this country proved to be ungovernable between 2008 and 2010, when it had to be rescued by the IMF.  We have not reformed the permanent government enough.  We are still firefighting in so many fields.  Perhaps the ban on recruitment has meant that there is no new talent in the permanent government coming up with ideas.  The people who were here when the country crashed in 2008 are still in charge.  That is serious.  What has happened in this Bill raises issues about how the permanent government operates.  I appreciate the difficulties Ministers have.  They have explained how hard it is to get legislation through Departments and the parliamentary draftsman.  We have to address this because the pace of reform is not fast enough.  Given the trouble we got into a few years ago, we have to reform the system to ensure that never happens again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M00300"><p>I agree with my colleague regarding government.  The Bills Office would probably confirm what we all know - that there is a kind of constipation throughout the session and at the very end there is an effluxion or diarrhoea of Bills all over the place.  Everyone suffers because of this.  This is a departmental problem, not necessarily just in the Department of Health.  Why is it that here in the Seanad we have statements on this, that and the other when we do not even take the Bills proposed by the Independent Senators?</p><p>I support what was said about Senator Burke&rsquo;s Bill on medical insurance.  I tried to force that because I felt he was coming under a certain amount of pressure from within his own party.  I copied the Bill with three or four words changed and registered it but was told the Government would push it and that I would be impeding the matter.  I urge him to push it.  There was agreement on all sides.  The Government said it agreed with it in principle but it would need some amendment.  I cannot comprehend why the Government did not take that Bill and amend it on Committee and Report Stages.  That should have been done.  Senator Burke did this House a service by introducing that Bill.</p><p>There is a phenomenal lack of courage in political life.  I exempt this Minister.  He is not the most popular Minister.  In this House he is all right, but in public he is everlastingly being battered -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M00400"><p>I will need two Easter eggs after that comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M00500"><p>A predecessor of his described his Department as Angola.  The Minister has courage.  He took on one of the most vicious lobby groups on the planet, the tobacco industry.  He deserves a Victoria Cross for that alone.</p><p>I have tabled a privacy Bill.  The Government has a privacy Bill but is absolutely terrified to move it because of the damage the media can do to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M00600"><p>We are on the tobacco Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M00700"><p>I know, but I am talking about courage and moral courage, which is very important.  The Minister has shown great courage and this is a very serious Bill.</p><p>I am entertained and delighted to see that snuff is not included.  In some of the shops near me they still sell snuff.  It is such an engaging and antique habit-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M00800"><p>Is it too late to propose an amendment to the Bill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M00900"><p>I have concluded from a detailed reading of the Bill that if one&rsquo;s chauffeur has his children in the front seat, provided there is a glass wall, the passenger in the back can smoke a cigar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M01000"><p>The only publican in the House, Senator Leyden, wishes to add his comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M01100"><p>I am not really a publican.  I commend the Minister.  It is not often he gets bouquets from Roscommon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700013#M01200"><p>They do not have many flowers in Roscommon apart from the Senator himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00100"><p>I commend the Minister for having the courage to take on a Private Members' Bill promoted by Senator John Crown, supported by his personal assistant, Mr. Shane Conneely, and Senators van Turnhout and Daly, who is my party colleague.  It is a crowning success for Professor Crown to have introduced this with colleagues, and he has demonstrated that this is something very important.  The Minister may be interested to know that in the Gallery are some girl scouts with their leaders from County Roscommon.  They will be the beneficiaries of today's Bill.  History is being made today as nobody will be able to light a cigarette in a car when youths are present, as the youths become involuntary smokers at that stage.  Such an act will be illegal when this Bill goes through the D&aacute;il, and nobody will be able to impose a smoke-filled environment on young people as a result.  Everybody should take credit for this, as it is a step forward.</p><p>It is ten years since Deputy Martin was courageous enough to introduce the ban on smoking in places of work, and it is now administered practically everywhere.  I returned from Montenegro yesterday and although a similar ban is imposed virtually everywhere there, some people were smoking in public areas in the Parliament.  I was surprised by that.  In all the restaurants and bars, smoking is banned, despite people being very fond of the habit in that country.  Deputy Martin did the State, and the wider world, a great service and is responsible for saving thousands of lives.</p><p>This Bill was brought through the Seanad, and the House has contributed greatly by bringing forward the Bill's concept.  The Minister has made that process easier.  I brought forward a Private Members' Bill dealing with registration of wills, and it is very important, but the Minister's Cabinet colleague, Deputy Burton, was not as courageous as the Minister for Health in allowing it to proceed.  That Bill to register wills was approved by the previous Seanad.  I would like the Minister, Deputy Burton, to adopt the Bill like the Minister for Health has done in this case.  It would show courage and demonstrate that a Minister is prepared to listen to the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00200"><p>The Senator is moving away from the smoking legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00300"><p>The point concerns Private Members' Bills.  The Minister is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00400"><p>He is fuming.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00500"><p>-----big enough to accept this Bill and ensure it can become law.  That is something he can have on his record when he leaves politics in 20 years or whenever his time is up.  He can say that he brought forward this Bill and young children will not be exposed to cigarette smoke in cars.</p><p>It is outrageous to think a child can be strapped into the back of a car with a mother, father or uncle smoking in the same car and exposing the child to second-hand smoke involuntarily at six or nine months old.  It is a health issue but the Minister has run with it.  I suggest he brings it to the D&aacute;il as quickly as possible after the Easter recess so it can be passed by the summer and brought into law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00600"><p>I wish to add my voice in welcoming this Bill.  The children in the Gallery are witnessing history in the making, as this legislation will benefit them and their peers because children will no longer be in cars where people are smoking.  At earlier Stages I mentioned that when my son was about four, my father-in-law was smoking in the car and I did not have the courage to tell him to stop but my son had that courage.  He said "Grandad, stop smoking in the car.  It is horrible and I hate it."  That woke me up because he was right and from then I asked people not to smoke in the car.  Such things come from the mouths of babes.</p><p>It is great to see this become law in Ireland.  As others have stated, I hope the Minister will ensure this gets through the D&aacute;il as quickly as possible in order to be enforced.  I congratulate the Senators who brought it forward and if they did nothing else in this term, they would still have done a great favour to the children of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00700"><p>As the proposer of the Bill has another compliment for the Minister, I will break all the rules by allowing him to contribute again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00800"><p>I thank the Minister as I know he will use his personal influence to ensure the Bill travels expeditiously.  I hope that at some stage before the summer, I will have the opportunity to thank him and the President when he signs the Bill in the presence of Fionn O'Callaghan, who provided much of the inspiration for the Bill, on the evening when the protections it contains are enshrined.  He was correctly acknowledged by Senator van Turnhout.  I must thank another group which was critical to the Bill getting here today, namely, the office of the Leader of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  Senator Maurice Cummins has taken this on board and by specifying timelines for the Bill, he has facilitated its progress through officialdom.  I thank Ms Orla Murray and the others in his office for their great work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N00900"><p>We are all on the same page and I have some comments.  I agree with speakers in that garda&iacute; will have very little to do with this issue, as it will be self-policing.  Anybody who sees an adult smoking in a car with a child will take immediate offence and make it very clear to the individuals concerned that a law is being broken and a child is being harmed.  It is very important that this forms part of an overall approach to a tobacco-free Ireland and we denormalise smoking, as Senator van Turnhout has indicated.  In Fingal smoking is banned where children gather, such as in public parks and playgrounds, etc., and that should be extended.</p><p>I am very concerned about the use of e-cigarettes.  They may have a role in helping people kick the addiction but they certainly have no role as a lifestyle choice and they should not be marketed as such.  We need to remember how many people die every year from smoking - it is 5,200 - and 700,000 Europeans die from smoking every year.  Getting the directive on tobacco through Europe was another big win for Ireland and the people of Europe.  I attended a non-communicable diseases conference in Europe last week which dealt with diabetes and other chronic illnesses and I was told the World Health Organization held a conference the day before at which it was said there was a lack of political leadership with regard to public health.  I would criticise us as politicians in that respect as well, as we find it much easier to open a wing of a hospital or an MRI scanner than to introduce a public health initiative like the one before us.</p><p>Having said this, the comment was qualified by noting the two exceptions of Australia and Ireland.  The picture was used of the Healthy Ireland document, which contains much about measures to combat tobacco and alcohol use, as well as initiatives to control obesity and promote physical activity.  I hope we all agree that across government we must maintain people's health, and it is not just about the Department of Health.  We need the Department of Justice and Equality to make products safe and the Department of Finance to impose tax policies to encourage healthier eating and discourage abuse of alcohol and smoking, for example.  The list goes one, as the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government could help in providing a safe place to exercise, etc.</p><p>Much has been mentioned about the slowness of reform and Bills have been mentioned that are having difficulty.  I agree that we must reform our legislative procedures as it takes too long for a Bill to come through.  Senator Burke mentioned the Bill I introduced when in opposition that would not allow people register for the Irish Medical Council without having medical insurance.  That is yet to come through because of various issues, despite for obvious reasons my being keen to see it enacted.  I thank Senator Burke for taking this on through the Seanad process.</p><p>I am mindful of Senator Norris's humorous analogies, with many bodily functions brought into play.  It was once stated that the Department of Health was akin to Angola but it is my goal - and I would like to think it would be everybody's goal - to turn it into East Anglia.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N01000"><p>Hear, hear.  Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700014#N01100"><p>It should be normal and boringly predictable and safe.  There should not be too much excitement.  I thank everybody for their contributions and I will undertake to expedite this legislation through the D&aacute;il.  I will use all my influence in trying to ensure this happens so we can protect our children in future.  I agree that some history has been made today, as the legislation will be on the Statute Book for many years to come as another one of the public health policies that made a difference.  I look forward to the Seanad's support with regard to standardised packaging of cigarettes.</p> <p>I believe if standardised packaging is introduced it will result in no smoking anymore because young people just will not take it up.  If we can stop our children taking up smoking then it will die out as a habit over the next generation.  I again thank Members and commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.220" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.221" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O00300">An Update on Situation in Ukraine: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O00400"><p>I welcome this opportunity to speak about the crisis in Ukraine.  This is not a recent crisis.  It began last November as hundreds and thousands of peaceful demonstrators took to the streets to protest against the decision of the authorities not to sign the association agreement with the European Union.  I met with many of the demonstrators myself when I visited Ukraine and Kiev for the OSCE ministerial meeting in December 2013.  The development of the crisis since then has been extensively reported and we have all watched with increasing concern as the demonstrations were met with repressive and ultimately lethal force.  Then, following the departure of former President Yanukovich, we witnessed the seizure by Russian forces of a part of Ukrainian territory, the installation of a compliant local regime, the orchestration of an invalid referendum under a heavy military presence and the annexation of Crimea and the city of Sevastopol to the Russian Federation.</p><p>The events in eastern Ukraine in recent days are a matter of grave concern.  The actions of masked and armed individuals seizing buildings in several cities there clearly represent a highly organised and co-ordinated attempt to destabilise the country and to undermine the Government in Kiev in advance of the presidential election scheduled for 25 May.  A constant area of focus by the European Union has been the need for an inclusive, fair and lawful election to take place by the end of May.  The election is clearly of huge importance to the communities in Ukraine and the people of Ukraine who seek orderly, fair and efficient government.  The period in the run-up to the presidential election is of great importance.  What we have seen happen is that the Ukrainian Government and the authorities have demonstrated very great restraint in the face of huge challenges and pressures within the country and in the face of huge provocation from elsewhere.</p><p>In my address to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann on the issue two weeks ago, and following statements on this and other related matters in the Seanad, I set out the reasons such developments should be of concern to Ireland and why we must take a strong view on the issue.  The main reason is because as a small country we depend very heavily on the respect others hold for international law and the ability of international law to create an atmosphere in which all countries - small and big - can protect their interests in a peaceful and lawful manner.  There are clear procedures in place in international law on handling issues such as the location of borders and important questions on how communities and countries should govern themselves.  Due to our own history and the many challenges we have faced in the past and currently, we understand the importance of international law.  We understand the importance of being able to deal with neighbours and other countries in an atmosphere of respect and where law is respected.  What we have seen happen in the developments I have outlined is that the body of international law has been completely flouted by the Russian Federation in the actions it has taken in Crimea and in the pressures and decisions that have been made in Crimea in recent months.</p><p>Throughout every phase in this crisis we have worked closely with our partners in the European Union.  The European Union has been strong, consistent and clear during that period.  The approach has been united in making clear that what happened in Ukraine is completely unacceptable and that it will have consequences for our relations with Russia.  From the outset, the EU has played an active role in trying to facilitate a resolution to the crisis in Ukraine.  In addition to its scheduled meetings, the EU Foreign Affairs Council has met twice and the EU Heads of State and Government have discussed Ukraine in extraordinary session as well as during the regular meetings of the European Council.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O00500"><p>Without wishing to be discourteous or to interrupt the Minister of State&rsquo;s flow, is a copy of the speech available?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O00600"><p>I understood the speech was being circulated.  I apologise if Senator Norris has not received it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O00700"><p>I do not have it but perhaps my colleagues have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O00800"><p>I will ask the ushers to look after the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O00900"><p>I apologise to the Senator for any inconvenience caused.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O01000"><p>Not at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700015#O01100"><p>Senators are as aware as I am that at this time in Europe 100 years ago a regional crisis spilled over into events that had consequences for an entire continent.  Senators are aware of the role of momentum, incident and accident in leading Europe to a point 100 years ago where we faced consequences and events that were absolutely catastrophic and that resulted in the loss of life of so many people.  As part of my work as Minister of State with responsibility for European affairs I recently visited Sarajevo in Bosnia Herzegovina and I saw the bridge at which the event took place that triggered so many events that had such a devastating effect on Europe.  That is why the European Union in its response to date to what has happened has been very careful to put in place a framework of response.  It has had three different stages and the leaders of the European Union at each stage have said what they want to achieve is a peaceful resolution to a very complicated crisis that has now been overlaid with the flouting and breaking of international law.  In response to what has happened we have said that measures will be put in place, and have been put in place, to deal with individuals and if events were to further destabilise the situation other measures would then be considered.  That is why, following the holding of the referendum in Crimea the Foreign Affairs Council on 17 March implemented the second phase of measures involving the imposition of travel restrictions against 21 Russian and Ukrainian officials.  The European Council, later that same week, added a further 12 names to the list.  If events were to destabilise further, other measures would be considered and the European Commission was tasked with developing what those options could be.</p><p>The T&aacute;naiste has strongly condemned the recent developments in eastern Ukraine.</p> <p>On Monday of this week, he participated in the Foreign Affairs Council in Luxembourg, where there was a detailed discussion of the crisis in Ukraine.  Ministers decided to expand the list of those to whom visa bans and asset freezes will apply.  Preparatory work continues on so-called phase 3 measures.  The Council also adopted a decision on macro-financial assistance for Ukraine, which brings the total amount of funding being made available by the EU to &euro;1.6 billion.  The support is part of a broader package over the next two years of &euro;27 billion.</p><p>Ireland and the EU have consistently stressed the importance of maintaining open channels of communication with the Russian Federation.  We welcome, therefore, the quartet talks involving Russia, the US, Ukraine and the EU which are to take place in Geneva today.  The EU will continue its engagement in international facilitation initiatives involving the UN, the OSCE and others.  Ireland is participating fully in these efforts.  We sent an officer to the initial interim OSCE mission and will be sending an officer to join the Polish-led second interim OSCE mission.</p><p>Ireland has made it consistently clear that external pressure on Ukraine is unacceptable.  In March, the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade personally expressed Ireland's condemnation of Russia's actions in Crimea to the Russian ambassador to Ireland and requested him to convey Ireland's deep concern to his Government.  Earlier this month, I moved a cross-party D&aacute;il motion condemning the annexation of Crimea and Sevastopol to the Russian Federation and pledging solidarity with and support for Ukraine.  Also, the Foreign Affairs Council yesterday expressed strong support for the holding of free and fair presidential elections on 25 May.  Ireland is sending a team of observers to Ukraine to help achieve that objective, one which will allow the Ukrainian people to determine their own future and help build trust across the country.  Instability does not respect national frontiers.  It is in the interest of the entire region that a sovereign, prosperous, stable, democratic and inclusive Ukraine emerges from the current crisis.  Ireland, together with its EU partners, will spare no effort in trying to bring this about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700016#P00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for outlining the Government&rsquo;s current position on the Ukraine.  However, the sands are shifting and the crisis continues to escalate.  The recent takeover by pro-Russian separatists of Ukrainian army personnel carriers has escalated the crisis to a new plain.  It seems likely that the forthcoming talks in Geneva will end up as a verbal fight between the Russian foreign Minister, Mr. Sergei Lavrov, and the Ukrainian foreign Minister, Mr. Andrii Deshchytsia.<br />There is an old saying that those who ignore history are condemned to repeat it.  What is going on in the Ukraine and Mr. Putin&rsquo;s sabre-rattling is reminiscent of Hitler and his attitude to the Sudeten Germans in 1938.  The Sudeten German Party, led by Konrad Henlein, received both verbal and financial support from Hitler.  Hitler had constantly talked about putting all Germans into one <i>reich</i>and that no true German would have to live outside of Germany.  How reminiscent is that of the language of the Russian President, Mr. Putin, in recent months?  In 1938, Hitler ordered his generals to start to make plans for the invasion of Czechoslovakia.  He also ordered Henlein and his followers to start to create trouble in the Sudetenland, therefore proving to the outside world that the Czech Government was incapable of maintaining order in its own state.  An exact parallel can be found in the utterances coming from Moscow over the past several weeks since the crisis first escalated.<br />Hitler planned to use this chaos to put his army into the Sudetenland to restore law and order.  Fomenting confusion and anarchy in the eastern part of Ukraine is the secret agenda of the Moscow Government so it can justify marching the Russian army into the region to protect the Russian minority there.  That is why I am heartened by the Minister&rsquo;s points about the common approach taken by the EU.  I understand the significance and implications of sanctions, particularly with the move to phase 3 which will impose severe repercussions for the Russian and western European economies.  What will be the implications of such a move for Ireland?<br />Ireland is sympathetic to the Ukrainian cause.  I am pleased there are representatives of the Ukrainian community in the Visitors Gallery to hear this debate.  I want to reassure them that the Irish people are in solidarity and at one with their cause to ensure their territorial integrity and sovereignty is maintained.  We have a long and dark history of colonialism stretching over centuries.  The Irish people have an empathy with any country such as Ukraine when its sovereignty is threatened with violation and invasion.<br />An interesting aspect of the 1938 Sudetenland crisis that draws a parallel with the present day crisis is that Britain, under Neville Chamberlain, chose to negotiate with Hitler over the Sudeten crisis.  Part of the reason for that was because Britain was incapable militarily of taking on the might of the Third Reich.  France had signed an agreement with Czechoslovakia offering support if the country was attacked.  However, Hitler could all but guarantee that in 1938 the French would do nothing.  The USSR had also given Czechoslovakia a promise of help but the USSR was in internal chaos during this time and unlikely to help Czechoslovakia out.<br />History proves that one has to stand up to bullyboy tactics.  I urge the European Union collectively to stand down the Russian President, Mr. Putin, and his expansionist plans.  Irrespective of what he is saying, I do not believe one word coming from Moscow.  I believe they want to break up the Ukraine and take away its eastern provinces to incorporate them into the Russian Federation.  That is unacceptable.  The Minister of State made it clear that any violation of Ukrainian sovereignty would be met with stiff resistance from the European Union.  As Churchill put it, it is far better to jaw-jaw than war-war.  I hope the continuing negotiations will bear fruit.<br />Ultimately, we in the European Union, and in Ireland as part of it, stand steadfast with the people of the Ukraine and support them in their free and democratic elections in the next month.  One of the key planks of the argument made by pro-Russian forces is that they do not want to deal with what they see as an undemocratic and fascist-led Government in Kiev.  It is unfortunate that in the current interim administration, there are representatives of a party, the ideology of which none of us would share.  It is an unfortunate reality that, following the revolution in Kiev, the compromise arrived at by the various democratic forces has resulted in part of the Government comprising a party that would not be acceptable in any country.  I hope this is a temporary arrangement and the people of the Ukraine will have the opportunity to elect a free and democratic Government.  I am pleased the Minister of State indicated there will be Irish monitors there next month for the presidential election.<br />We on the Fianna F&aacute;il side fully support the Minister of State&rsquo;s and the Government&rsquo;s efforts to ensure the Ukraine, ultimately, will live in peaceful co-existence with its Russian neighbours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700017#Q00100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and thank him for his endeavours in this regard.  I also welcome the debate on this important and serious issue.  The situation in Ukraine poses many issues in the short and long term, on which the Minister touched.  In the aftermath of the internal unrest which occurred following the then government's decision to ally itself with Russia as opposed to the European Union on economic matters, Russia has exerted itself strongly, to say the least.  As Senator Paschal Mooney said, bully tactics were used in the invasion of Crimea, changing the geopolitical map and increasing tensions in the region to a level that had not been seen in many years, which is very frightening.  The situation continues to unfold and last night Ukrainian forces are reported to have killed three pro-Russian militants in the east of the country ahead of international crisis talks in Geneva.  Senator Paschal Mooney is correct that the situation is current, in flux and evolving each hour, and of very serious concern.  Nobody is more aware of this than the Minister.<br />According to today's reports, Ukraine's national guard responded to an attack on its base in the city of Mariupol by approximately 300 people.  Civil unrest is reaching unsustainable levels backed by many local Russian speakers.  As we all know, some of them are demanding a referendum on transferring many powers from Kiev to the regions or even joining Russia.  Ukraine's new pro-West government claims Russian agents are behind unrest that the Kremlin states could spark civil war and rejects demands for federalisation that would give Moscow greater influence in areas where Russian is spoken.  Needless to say, Russia has refuted this, claiming it is an internal protest by Ukrainians who are rebelling against the government.<br />The European Union and the United States have imposed sanctions on Russian political and business figures with ties to the Kremlin and pledge to go further if Russia continues its alleged interference in Ukraine.  The West states some 40,000 of Moscow's troops are massed near Ukraine's eastern border and could invade within hours, if ordered.  This is deeply concerning and adds to the tension.  While this confrontation between Russia and the West over Ukraine imperils the Russian economy which is to the forefront of their minds, the problem runs both ways.  Russia&rsquo;s pre-existing economic malaise also explains why the country is vulnerable to an international crisis.  The Ukrainian crisis has occurred just at the moment when economic growth in Russia has come to depend more heavily than ever on capital-intensive investment, much of which comes from the European Union.<br />As the <i>Financial Times</i>reported this week, Russia&rsquo;s economic problems are structural, even if some cyclical factors such as recession and stagnation in the eurozone &ndash; by far Russia&rsquo;s largest trading partner &ndash; have added to the gloom.  The slowdown of European growth has dealt a much more serious blow to Ukraine&rsquo;s economy than to Russia&rsquo;s and must be reckoned among the underlying causes of the events that have contributed to the crisis.  Political confrontation with the West following the annexation of Crimea has significantly undermined this external investment in Russia, with capital leaking out of Russia as domestic business owners do not see enough investment projects inside it with a sufficiently attractive risk-reward balance.  Although that is how things stood six months ago, the political confrontation with the West following Russia&rsquo;s annexation of Crimea undermines this investment case.  Returns will be impaired by slower growth and western sanctions will create new risks, even assuming that the economic option of forbidding Russian trade and finance is never exercised, and it is unforeseeable that the situation will ever go that far.  However, Russia&rsquo;s dependence on external sources of long-term finance explains why its economy slumped far more after the financial crisis than any other major oil exporter.  This is the position, as it stands, and the threat of military intervention in Ukraine and the intervention in Crimea have undermined Russia&rsquo;s economy.<br />Although the situation in Ukraine is unstable, if agreement is reached in the talks, which it can be, we can continue to work towards restoring stability in Ukraine.  Following this conflict, either the European Union or Russia will need to work with Ukraine to assist its economy in the long term and I am comforted that the Union has taken such a joined-up approach.  Although I thought it would be a major challenge, considering how many member states are involved in the process, I was very pleased to hear that the European Union was having a very positive influence.  This does not take away from the fact that the situation is very serious on a day-to-day basis and evolving.  The Minister is obviously very much in touch with it and I thank him for his work and the update on the Government's position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700017#Q00200"><p>With the permission of the House, I would like to share two minutes of my time with Senator Sean D. Barrett.  </p><p>I welcome the Minister.  I am sorry he was not here a little earlier because, as a former Member of the House who had opposed the retention of the Seanad, I am sure he would have felt the people were right had he seen the Bill, initiated by Senator John Crown, one of our leading cancer specialists, being passed with the co-operation of his colleague, the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly.  The Bill will have a very significant impact on children's health by preventing people from smoking in cars with children.</p><p>I take a slightly dissenting view on this matter because the European Union has not behaved well at all and was extraordinarily cack-handed in its diplomatic approaches to it.  By pushing into an area which was clearly in the Russian sphere of influence without proper discussions and negotiations and without bringing the Russians in, it allowed Russia to pose as being frightened, even if it was not.  With great deference to our friends and guests from Ukraine, the problem is that Ukraine is very mixed.  Even the people who support the European Union told us there were mixed views and divided opinions in Ukraine, including among Russian speakers and Russian nationals.  It was exceptionally stupid of the incoming government after the revolution or coup to ban the Russian language as one of its first acts.  It did not suggest good will.  The appalling right-wing elements in the government are a tragedy.</p><p>I am glad that Senator Paschal Mooney raised the issue of the Sudetenland and that the Minister raised the question of 1914 because there are comparisons but also significant differences.  Had the Prince of Wales been shot in Dublin the British Empire would not have stood silently by.  The Austrians were completely justified in the First World War and we were on the wrong side in terms of the geopolitical elements, although there were also business matters at stake.  Hitler stirred things up in the Sudetenland, but while there is an apparent, superficial parallel, it is not the same.  The very word &quot;Russia&quot; comes from Ukraine, the Russian state and people originate in Ukraine and there is an extraordinary emotional bond.  While I am not saying the pro-western people who are concentrated in the larger western part of Ukraine do not and should not have rights - one hopes the country is sustainable - Crimea was part of Russia and Khrushchev had no right to give it away.  Suppose the people of Hawaii who have been trampled by American colonialism appealed to Russia to take over and protect their rights as Hawaiians, despite the enormous naval installations the Americans have on the islands.  That would be one for the books.</p> <p> With regard to all of this pious stuff, and I know that the Minister of State means it because he is a good person, but it is all bilge basically because there is not a rule of law anywhere in the world.  Just look at the way people's rights have been trampled on all over Africa, inside China and inside the United States.  How can anyone be serious about the rule of law when Obama, whom we all thought would be a breath of fresh air, has authorised ten times the amount of drone strikes in which civilians are killed?  What happened to the rule of law in that instance?  What happened to the right to a trial, the right to be indicted, the right to be arrested, and the right to a fair trial?  That has all gone and is perpetrated by our friends the Americans.  </p><p>What about when we talk about small nations and their right to do this, that and the other?  We had an honourable policy under Frank Aiken with regard to Tibet.  However, every single Government since then has slid away from that.  If we substitute Tibet for Ukraine what does one get?  Not a squeak.  When Dublin City Council tried to give the Dalai Lama the freedom of the city of Dublin its idea was squashed for petty partisan reasons.  I suggested that the Dalai Lama should be invited to the foreign affairs committee but my suggestion was squashed because we are afraid to alienate the Chinese.  That is not a moral position but a financial one.</p><p>I do not believe that sanctions will make a huge difference unless they get to a point where they damage the Irish economy as well.  I agree with colleagues who suggested that we should be given some information about the impact they would have on the Irish economy.  I do not think that it is huge but I know that balance is in our favour with regard to Ukraine.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R00200"><p>The Senator will eat into Senator Barrett's time in 30 seconds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R00300"><p>I was told one minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R00400"><p>No.  The Senator has 30 seconds left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R00500"><p>The Acting Chairman held up one finger.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R00600"><p>It has been brought to the Senator's attention that he has 30 seconds left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R00700"><p>I have said, more or less, what I wanted to say and shall end with the following.  In my opinion it should not be the strategic interests of either Russia or the European Union but that of the ordinary people of Ukraine that should be protected because they will have to pay the price at the end of the day.  It is they who should be protected whether they are Russian speaking, Ukrainian nationalists or whatever.</p><p>I say well done to the Acting Chairman and thank him for using the drums.  I shall obey them and reserve a final comment for the Minister of State.  What if, for example, we could reach a situation in the future where Russia moved to where it naturally should be and became part of the European Union?  I know that is wishful thinking but such a development would be a wonderful solution.  We are moving towards global government and the sooner we move the better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R00800"><p>Senator Barrett is left with one and a quarter minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R00900"><p>Three quarter minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R01000"><p>I am sure the Acting Chairman could give a little latitude because Senators are not queuing up now to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R01100"><p>I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R01200"><p>Go raibh maith agat.  I welcome the Minister of State to the House, as always.  I am trying to recover from the radicalism of Senator Norris's suggestion that Russia should join the European Union.  However, it is great to have men of vision in this House and I commend him on his suggestion.</p><p>In the immediate term, I agree with the Minister of State regarding the elections on 26 May and the fact that we need to ensure, through the Geneva talks and elsewhere, that the elections take place.  It is then that we will find out the answer to Senator Norris's question about how many people in the Ukraine feel more attracted to Russia than to the West.</p><p>The Minister of State has rightly drawn our attention to what happened in 1914 and Senator Mooney drew our attention to what happened in 1939.  We do not want the law of unintended consequences to apply.  Let us remember that in our case one of the consequences of 1914 was that Home Rule legislation was put on hold.  Hence, the completely unintended consequence of anybody in Sarajevo at the time was the partition of Ireland and the falling apart of the two main traditions in this country.  We were on our way to Home Rule because it had been passed by Parliament in the United Kingdom.  Therefore, we know more than most about the unintended consequences of disputes that start in a completely different part of the world. </p><p>The elections are most important and necessitate restraint.  I hope that the Minister and his colleagues will have many advisers accompanying him because we need the Ukrainians to determine their own future.  There seems also to be a need to involve President Putin with the EU at the highest level.  We do need his co-operation and support in this matter so we must not demonise him.  I know that the Minister would not do so but it is important that we do not do it either.  In my remaining quarter of a minute I wish the Minister and his colleagues success in these talks.  We need a peaceful resolution and he has the support of the House in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700018#R01300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  In terms of the history of Crimea-Ukraine, mention has been made of 1914.  However, I would like to mention 1853 when ostensibly the religious rights of citizens in the Holy Land, as it was then known, provoked a war within the Crimea between Russia, Britain and France and the former Ottoman Empire.  Apparently the aim of the war was to prevent Russia from gaining territory at the expense of the Ottoman Empire.  This is not the first time that we have seen a tussle for geo-political domination in the Crimea.<br />I agree, to some extent, with my colleague, Senator Norris but I am a little more critical of the situation.  An interesting article was published in <i>The Sunday Business Post </i>by Dr. Erin Baumann which analysed the motivations, for want of a better word, behind Russian President, Vladimir Putin's, actions regarding the Ukraine.  She outlined an interesting history of Russia's interests and said they were not motivated by a desire to assert Russia's power or establish its position as the centre of the Eurasian sphere of influence, rather to protect itself against what it sees as a loss of critical influence in an important part of the world in terms of its own concerns.  She pointed out, for example, that since 2008 with the establishment of the EU's eastern partnership programme, Russia has been increasingly wary of European influence in its near sphere.  It responded by setting up a customs union between Russia, Belarus and Kazakhstan in 2010.  Effectively, she said that we need to look at what motivated Russia to take action.<br />Dr. Baumann also made the point that the only way to oppose the establishment of Russia's domination in Eurasia was to have a strong and unified European Union.  She pointed out, and I completely agree with her, having lived through what happened in the former Yugoslavia, that the crisis in the Ukraine has demonstrated the limits of the EU's capability to be a strong and unified foreign policy actor because of the different interests of the 28 member states.  She pointed out, as we all know, the dependence of some of our colleagues on Russia's gas and oil.  She also pointed to the Association of European Businesses which promotes the interests of European companies doing business within the Russian Federation, and other parts of that world, as forces that stand in the path of a more cohesive action by the EU member states.  I noticed in a recent report about sanctions that we are awaiting a report from the Commission on the impact of sanctions on EU member states. Therefore, we are quite clearly putting our own interests ahead of the interests of those people we profess to care about who live in the Ukraine.  I found that quite disturbing.  She concluded that the EU can only effectively respond by developing a coherent and unified foreign policy which we clearly do not appear to have.<br />Having said all that I would like, to some extent, to support what Senator Norris said about the internal situation in the Ukraine.  The crisis did not happen yesterday or the day before.  We must remember, aside from our own geopolitical and economic interests, that the Ukraine is facing its greatest internal crisis for over 20 years and since the dissolution of the Soviet Union.  </p> <p>We must also bear in mind that there have been significant ethnic difficulties within Ukraine, which the events of recent months have brought to the surface.  For example, in 2004 there was the so-called Orange Revolution where citizens protested in the aftermath of the presidential elections, which were said to have been corrupt.  Voters were intimidated and there was electoral fraud, there was civil disobedience, strikes and sit-ins, and the Supreme Court was forced to annul the original results and hold a re-election.  In spite of that, there have been numerous political corruption scandals as part of the regular political life in the Ukraine, with all the contenders we hear about every day of the week - Yanukovych, Tymoshenko - all of whom have expressed what would be regarded as questionable attitudes towards democracy.  I thank Steven Balbirnie<b></b>of UCD's <i>University Observer</i>for some of his comments.<br />Successive administrations have defined themselves on whether they were pro-Russian or pro-European.  There has been bad behaviour on both sides.  There has been tit for tat by both government and opposition, with both banning political parties in their local administrative areas which were under their respective control.  This has obviously fanned the flames of the situation in the Ukraine, with outside powers wading in not to help resolve what is effectively a domestic issue but to protect their own geopolitical interests.  In terms of the current situation, Russia has made it clear that it regards Crimea as part of its sovereign territory, regardless of what anybody has to say about it.  The US and the European Union appear weak in terms of their negotiating efforts, and the Government in Kiev is not without its own responsibility for the situation, acting aggressively and making inflammatory remarks while, it would appear, refusing to rein in ulta-nationalist groups that have been going into eastern Ukraine, apparently, in mobs to terrorise Russian locals.  I believe that what we are seeing in eastern parts of the Ukraine, such as Kharkiv and Donetsk, is that locals are trying to separate not due to some plot orchestrated by Moscow but because they do not feel the Government in Kiev is protecting them from ethnic violence.  Whether we believe Russia has desires to annex more of the Ukraine, or simply wants to protect its interests in the Black Sea, or whether this is part of its attempts to protect what it regards as Russian civilians in eastern Ukraine, one way or the other I do not believe the European Union has covered itself in glory in position.<br />Perhaps I can make a controversial statement.  In Ireland, of all the countries in the world, we should be well aware of a situation in which we need to respect different national identities within the same State.  We are not unique.  We see a similar situation within Cyprus.  I think we are being overly simplistic in our statements in regard to the Ukraine.  I am not convinced that the long-term solution to the situation in Ukraine is not to have freely held democratic referendums to decide, once and for all, whether there is a genuine desire to split Ukraine along ethnic lines.  If that is the case I do not think we should ultimately be afraid of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700019#S00200"><p>I  fundamentally disagree with the last point made by Senator Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700019#S00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700019#S00400"><p>The annexation of Crimea by the Russian Federation is an illegitimate act.  Despite the fact that Crimea may have a predominantly ethnic Russian population, it does not provide any justification for it.  If we fail to respect the territorial integrity of nations, ultimately it will lead to chaos and much conflict in various areas around the globe.  My colleague, Senator Paschal Mooney, put it in sharp focus when he raised the analogy of Sudetenland and Nazi Germany.  There is little doubt that the objective of the Russian President, and probably of others within the Russian Administration, is to rebuild and increase its sphere of influence across what was formerly the Soviet bloc.  It has implications not only for Ukraine but other countries as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700019#S00500"><p>Exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700019#S00600"><p>We see today that the conflict in the Ukraine could grow into something far more serious.  Yesterday we saw the special forces of the Ukraine take over Kramatorsk Airport, having to recover it from the separatists.  We saw the Russian separatists commandeering five armoured vehicles and a tank.  All of this, including the fact that people were killed in the conflict yesterday, could lead to a fairly serious conflagration there.  I share some of the reservations of others.  It was a real pity that the agreement of 21 February was not followed through.  It was accepted and then, obviously, rejected.  If that agreement had been implemented it would have allowed a more cohesive and peaceful evolution of the democratic process in Ukraine.  The overthrow of Yanukovych having been agreed raised questions.  Also, I thought the European Union should have passed some condemnatory comments on peaceful protests becoming a form of anarchy when buildings were taken over, occupied and burned.  That type of violence should have no part in peaceful protests.  There is a line beyond which protests can evolve after which they need to be rejected as not being in line with the fundamental freedoms of proper civilian protest.  Unfortunately, that happened in Kiev.</p><p>The West was quick to recognise Kosovo.  I was one of the few voices in the House who felt we should have been far more cautious in that regard.  We have put ourselves in a position in which we have given justification to Putin or anybody else who has this attitude to invade and take over parts of countries or to declare independence of part of countries.  We have created an situation in which it is difficult to be consistent in our arguments.  In fact, I could include Northern Ireland and Gibraltar.  Britain has no legitimacy there.  If we recognise British legitimacy in Northern Ireland, we are saying with regard to Crimea that it is not okay now but in a number of years it will be okay.  The same happened in South Ossetia in Georgia, which was invaded and ceded.  There are a number of areas of conflict.  There is the threat to Moldova.  There are significant Russian populations in the Baltic states.  As this has wider implications, a more nuanced and prudent approach should have been taken. </p><p>In regard to the sanctions that are being imposed, I share some of the reservations that people have mentioned.  I am unsure about how effective they will be.  I see the need for us to do something.  Any consequent decline of the Russian economy will have implications for Putin, and that might in some way encourage dialogue.  It would be a pity if we ended up compromising on some of the actions we can take because of Europe's dependency on, for example, Russian gas.</p><p>There is a need to intensify the negotiations which have started in Geneva with the European Union, the US, Ukraine and Russia to try to find a solution which, hopefully, maintains the territorial integrity of Ukraine.</p> <p>Moreover, it is to be hoped that lessons will have been learned from this and other such episodes in order that in future, a more enlightened approach will be taken from the onset of such issues, rather than trying to retrieve the situation after mistakes have been made on the diplomatic  international scene at an earlier stage that only contributed to exacerbating the situation, rather than to finding solutions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700020#T00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and congratulate him on the great work he is doing in Europe.  In one way, I call to mind that headline in <i>The Skibbereen Eagle</i>of having its eye on the tsar of Russia.  However, as a member of the European Union and being represented by the Minister of State there, Ireland can have a major influence on policy within the European Union towards Ukraine.  After all is said and done, one can talk about Hawaii, Kosovo or wherever one likes but the basic principle is international law and that the integrity and unity of a country must be respected.  People in this State are familiar with what happens historically when the territorial unity and integrity of a country is not respected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700020#T00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700020#T00400"><p>Thankfully however, through negotiation and dialogue, as well as instruments such as the Good Friday and St. Andrews agreements, we are working to resolve peacefully those issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700020#T00500"><p>It remains occupied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700020#T00600"><p>Ireland can bring to bear its own history and its own unique insight to the situation in Ukraine.  What has happened is that international law has been flouted by the Russians and one does not stop the bear by tickling his tummy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700020#T00700"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700020#T00800"><p>Strong action must be taken within the European Union to let the Russians and the world know the ideals and principles of liberal democracy and human rights, as represented in the European Union and throughout the world, must be respected or there will be consequences.  At present, these consequences will take the form of sanctions and such sanctions must be calibrated to the situation.  Moreover, we must be strong in this regard.<br />As for Kosovo, the situation there was slightly different, in that under United Nations Security Council Resolution 1244, Kosovo constituted a case <i>sui generis</i>, which did not call into question the principles of the United Nations Charter and the Helsinki Final Act.  Consequently, there is no legitimacy for what the Russians are doing in Ukraine, regardless of the situation there.  The conclusions on Ukraine approved by the European Council should act as our charter.  The conclusions state the European Union:<blockquote>supports the Ukrainian people and their right to choose their own future.  The European Union stands by the Ukrainian government in its efforts to stabilise Ukraine and undertake reforms.</blockquote>That refers to how there is no point in banning the Russian language, if one takes over as such measures are not helpful.  Consequently, the European Union will assist Ukraine and that is what my message to the Minister of State would be.<br />Furthermore, the conclusions state, &quot;the European Union will pursue further efforts with the international community to assist Ukraine&quot;.  As Members are aware, Russia is seeking to secure its borders and it will not stop.  It will move further and then, having secured its borders and having the greater Europe it seeks - with half being under its hegemony and half within the European Union - it will move on to what it really wants to do, which is to protect its territory east of the Urals from Asia.  That is the policy of Russia and Putin but Members are not interested in that.  They are interested in Ukraine and if Ireland in Europe promotes democracy and human rights in Ukraine, as Senator Noone observed, the European Union must also provide financial support to Ukraine.  Thereafter, we can help to stabilise Ukraine for its own future, be it a unitary state or a federal structure, as that is up to Ukraine.  The Minister of State is doing a good job.  I listened to his statement with interest and ask him to reflect on my modest suggestions to help him in his task.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700020#T00900"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  Following on from what already has been stated about the fluidity of the process, I note that even looking at Twitter now, so much is happening that it is difficult to keep up.  However, the talks in Geneva are a good initiative and I hope they can reduce some of the tensions and begin a process to end this crisis.  While international support for peace and security is needed, ultimately only the Ukrainians themselves can decide their future and they must be allowed to make the decisions free of international pressure.  In a confidence-building measure, the build-up of Russian troops along the border must stop and they should be removed.  Similarly, NATO should cease the escalation and mobilisation of its forces in eastern Europe.  For too long, Ukraine has been used as a geopolitical football by Russia and the European Union to achieve their own strategic aims.  Unfortunately, because of this it has suffered under successive corrupt and ineffective governments for far too long.  The result of this has been a deterioration in socioeconomic conditions and essentially, a bankruptcy of that state.  Some of the recent problems stem from interference by the European Union, the United States and Russia in the power struggle within Ukraine.  Rather than forcing Ukraine to choose between one of two political routes, the European Union and Russia should have been working together to create mutually beneficial and non-exclusive economic, political and social relationships with Ukraine.  This would have been of real, genuine benefit to ordinary Ukrainians.  The interim government in Kiev has little legitimacy in the country and continues to be divided.  Members have heard a lot about this already.</p><p>One can be under no illusion about either Russia's self-interest in this region or its reasons for the recent behaviour but it must be pointed out that the referendum that took place in Crimea obviously is another factor in the escalating crisis.  It was held under the worst possible conditions, there was a sub-standard security situation, a volatile atmosphere, international pressure, the lack of open democratic debate, press restrictions and a lack of dialogue preceding the referendum.  Obviously, Sinn F&eacute;in supports the right to referendums to decide self-determination but they should be in line with good democratic practice.  It is clear there is a great deal of support in Crimea for separating from Ukraine and joining Russia.  However, there first should be dialogue and negotiation within Ukraine, free from the aforementioned outside interference, obviously with a view to finding an overall agreement on the future of Ukraine.  Some Members already have mentioned the perhaps less positive role that has been played by the European Union.  Some people will state the actions of the European Union have been just as disastrous for the Ukrainian people.  The European Union has moved ahead with its association agreement with Ukraine and some would state this is a cause of the escalation in the first place.</p> <p>The European Union should not force through such an important document with an interim government.  It is said the agreement will lock some of the political and economic structures in a straitjacket and suggested one of the first effects will be an increase in domestic gas prices on 1 May.  The European Union and the IMF have been requested to provide financial support for Ukraine.  Before now, domestic gas prices were heavily subsidised by the government, which ensured people did not starve or freeze to death during the winter.  However, that subsidy will be cut under the package.  There have been other threats of spending cuts.  When there is such poverty in the country, threats of such cuts are unpopular throughout Ukraine, especially in its eastern part.  The more Ukraine increases its socioeconomic development, the more autonomy it will have in deciding its own future.  That should be the main focus of the external efforts and in providing support.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House and his contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Paschal Donohoe.  I thank the Leader of the House for allowing time for a discussion of this serious issue.</p><p>I am encouraged by the talks in Geneva today and the press conference given by Vladimir Putin this morning on his intentions or desires in regard to Ukraine.  There is a de-escalation of the situation to some extent because the two countries are in talks.  I listened to the contributions of Senator David Norris and others who discussed the background to the situation and also to the contribution of Senator Jim D'Arcy who is very experienced, as a member of the Council of Europe.  I note that he has learned a good deal from our debates last week in the Assembly in Strasbourg.  </p><p>The action of the European Union was quite provocative.  It was not very well versed in history in seeking to attract Ukraine within western control as opposed to it being linked with Russia.  It was not very observant of Baroness Catherine Ashton, High Representative of the European Union for Foreign Affairs and Security Policy.  She will have left that position at the end of May, about which I am delighted.  I hope the next person who represents the European Union will have vast experience of international affairs and be aware that Ukraine is served by Russia in terms of its energy supplies of oil and gas.  It depends on Russia for its very existence.  Forcing an agreement on it - putting it to it that it was either them or us - was ill-advised, as I said at the meeting of the monetary committee in Strasbourg last week.  Our delegation, led by Deputy Joe O' Reilly, supported the withdrawal of voting rights at the Council of Europe, but we did not support the withdrawal of membership of the Council of Europe  That would be a step too far because it is important to have engagement in dialogue at the Council of Europe, whereas if its credentials were not accepted and withdrawn, it would have been a step too far.</p><p>It was very provocative of Russia to annex Crimea, which was a step too far.  When we were in trouble here in 1970s and there was pressure exerted to force developments, we did not receive that much support throughout the world for our stand.  We should never forget that Ireland is a neutral country.  In the period 1939 to 1945 we did not participate in the so-call Great War.  We stood alone on a neutral basis.  Anything that would endanger our &euro;600 million worth of exports to Russia would be a step too far.  We did not start this conflict and will not finish it.  This is a small country on the edge of Europe and we are taking the right diplomatic approach in condemning the activities of Russia which has not done itself any favour internationally, given that it had built up tremendous respect throughout the world.</p><p>Having been the first Minister from any country to go to the Russian Federation in 1990s and having worked on trade issues and taking account of the efforts made by Aer Rianta in the development of a duty free shop at Moscow airport, our beef exports to Russia and exports generally to it have been hard fought for.  I will totally oppose any ban on Irish exports to Russia in response to its activities in Ukraine.  It is not our fight.  We can do what we like, but we have to bear in mind that nobody is that concerned about Ireland as far as our future prospects are concerned.  Employment in this country would be under serious threat if we were to jeopardise our exports to Russia on the basis of this issue.  I believe the Minister of State and most other European countries would be reluctant to impose an overall trade ban on the Russian Federation.  I certainly would not support such a ban because I believe the activities of the European Union and the United States of the America were highly provocative in this regard.  Senator Jim D'Arcy put it very well when he referred to a sleeping bear.  They caused a reaction which would not have been caused if they had left well enough alone and they would have had good positive relations with Ukraine and Russia.  </p><p>The activities in Geneva this morning and the fact that the two countries are in discussions is very positive and I think there will be a positive outcome.  The activities yesterday in the seizure of tanks were inept as far as the Ukrainian Government is concerned.  It is not a very strong government.  The election on 25 May to elect a President will be very important.  I was not impressed by the previous President who was questionable in terms of her activities and background.  When she appeared in Dublin at a meeting of the European People's Party, EPP, she was given a standing ovation, even though her position was very dubious.  Catherine Ashton should not have embraced her in Kiev or endorsed her as the candidate of the West, seeing her as the shining light of fidelity, honesty and trustworthiness.  She was on trial, although I accept that she should not have been jailed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U00300"><p>The person mentioned is not here to defend herself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U00400"><p>The Acting Chairman was with her at that meeting and clapped her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U00500"><p>Is the Senator sure about that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U00600"><p>No.  The Acting Chairman is certainly a member of the EPP and welcomed her to Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U00700"><p>We could invite her here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U00800"><p>I ask Senator Terry Leyden to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U00900"><p>I will not say anymore about her, as she is not here.</p><p>I will conclude on a positive note.  The Minister of State has heard our differing views.  We express them as Members of the House, not as the views of a particular party.  We all have our individual views in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U01000"><p>The Minister tried to silence them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U01100"><p>Is that right?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U01200"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U01300"><p>I hope the Minister of State has learned a good deal from those who have considerable experience, even more than he has.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700021#U01400"><p>I thank all Senators for their contributions.  I want to make four overall points in response to the issues raised by Senators.  I will then respond  to the comments made by each Senator.  </p><p>The first point I want to make is about the concept Senators used during the debate to the effect that the European Union was in some way forcing Ukraine to sign an association agreement.  I ask them to produce the evidence to back up that claim.  We were dealing with a democratically elected government which was giving all of the signs that it wanted to sign an association agreement with the European Union.  It was on that basis that the European Union proceeded to enter into discussions with it.  The Governments of Georgia and Moldova stated the same thing.  The Governments of Georgia and Moldova signed an agreement, but the Ukrainian Government decided not to do so.  I had the privilege of being part of the team that represented Ireland at the partnership summit that took place Vilnius at which the Ukrainian Government decided not to sign the agreement.  That was its right, just as it was its right to decide to participate in discussions in the run-up to that Council at which it indicated that it was interested in signing.  When people use the word &quot;provocation&quot; or &quot;force&quot; to indicadte that the European Union forced the Ukrainian Government to participate in an association agreement or was provocative in so doing, I ask for evidence to show how the Union forced any country to participate in a discussion and dialogue.</p> <p>In the period leading up to the partnership summit, the truth is the European Union dealt with the then Ukrainian Government who viewed the signing of that agreement positively and for its own reasons then changed its mind.  That is their right.  However, at no point does the EU have the ability not to mention the ambition to force any country to sign an agreement with it.<br />My second point relates to the Members' comments on Russia.  It is very important to be aware of the challenges we all face in many other areas.  Let us consider what is happening in Syria, Iran and the challenges we face on climate change and the many other policy challenges that Europe and the world faces, the reality is that we need to work with Russia to reach a settlement and conclusion on other issues that will have a significant effect on the peace and stability of Europe and the world.  I agree with the decision of the Council of Europe to withdraw Russian voting rights but to keep it within the Council.  In many other areas, there is a clear need to be able to work with and maintain dialogue with the Russian Federation, its Ministers and its leaders.<br />My third point also relates to the comments that Senators have made.  Senator Mooney referred to &quot;the shifting sands of this issue&quot;, a phrase that is very apt in describing how the situation has developed.  Amid all the shifting sands the reality is that the borders of another country were changed without the consent of the government in place, and with the threat of force in the background.  The ballot paper for the referendum in Crimea had options that did not include the maintenance of what was then the status quo<i>.  </i>It is correct that people articulate their perspectives of this very complicated situation, however a core point is that the borders of another country were unilaterally changed.<br />Fourth, what has been crucial in influencing the position the Government has reached and I think many Senators agree with me, is how the decision was reached.  International law, and organisations such as the United Nations and other bodies have processes and procedures in which these matters can be dealt with peacefully through negotiation and agreement.  That did not happen in this instance.  That is the reason the Government has taken its stance.  The Government is very conscious of Irish neutrality and the fact that the bedrock of neutrality is a respect for the rule of international law - a point on which Senator Jim D'Arcy touched.  The capacities and provisions are in place under international law for dealing with the right of people to self-determine how they are governed and where their borders should be, but none of that was used in the decision that was taken in Crimea.  That is the reason that before I address the comments of individual Senators, I want to emphasise the fact that the European Union in the run up to the partnership summit that took place in November, did all of its negotiations on the basis of dealing with the wishes of the Ukrainian Government.  The idea of force or provocation by the European Union in the run up to that period is a view that while others are entitled to articulate it is certainly one that I would strongly reject because I do not believe it is based on the facts of what happened in the run up to that summit.<br />I will now comments on the contributions of individual Senators.  Senator Mooney made the point about the shifting sands of the situation.  He picked up on historical analogies or the lack of analogies, depending on the viewpoint, between where we are now and what happened in Europe in the 1930s and 1940s.  We could spend the entire afternoon debating the consistency of that analogy.  The significant difference between the 1930s and 1940s and where we are now is the degree of economic interdependence that now exists between everybody across the world and within the Continent of Europe and all members of the European Union.  That is best understood by what has happened in terms of energy interdependence.  Some 34% of European energy needs are provided through many of the different countries that we are discussing.  That provides a very clear example of interdependence and that is the reason I believe we have to look at the role of sanctions in that light.  Since these measures were announced we have seen major changes take place in the value of the Russian rouble, the Russian stock market, in the capitalisation of very major Russian companies.  That is an example of how the indirect effects of sanctions and the fear of investors about what could happen in the future has a very major effect not only on the Russian economy but obviously on the economies of countries nearer Russia.  <br />Senator Noone identified one very important and worrying development that has now taken place, which is the mobilisation of the Ukrainian national guard.  In my contribution I made a point of emphasising the restraint that has been shown to date but we have now seen worrying developments take place within Ukraine in response to what they perceive to be happening within their own borders.  Senator Norris referred to the EU being cack-handed in its response.  He made the vital point that it is up to the people of the Ukraine to decide.  That is the basis on which the EU was dealing with Ukraine, that it was dealing with the then Ukrainian Government that wanted to proceed and wanted positive discussions with the European Union.  For reasons of its own, it changed its mind on that, which is its right. <br />Senator Barrett stressed the importance of the elections of 25 May, a point I strongly agree with, not least because they will deal with the concerns that many Senators have articulated on issues such as inclusivity, the security of communities within Ukraine and the different ethic traditions within Ukraine which we have to be cognisant of.  That is the reason these elections are so important and that the period between now and the end of May is so sensitive in terms of what will happen in the Ukraine in the years to come.<br />In respect of some of the points that Senator Hayden made, I touched on the differing view that I have on the role of the European Union up to that point.  While acknowledging clearly that mistakes have been made in reaching this point as well, which I absolutely understand and am aware of, but I still acknowledge that the European Union was dealing with a government at the point in the Ukraine that wanted to change its relationship with the European Union.  <br />The Senator also referred to the role of a common European foreign policy and made a number of observations on it.  We should be aware that foreign policy is very different from trade policy, as Members will know.  In respect of trade policy the people and the government of the European Union decided to make the Commission the lead negotiator in relation to trade policy and gave it a large degree of competence on that.</p> <p>That is why, for example, the lead negotiation on the transatlantic trade and investment partnership with America is Commissioner de Gucht as opposed to the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, or a Minister from any other country.  Ultimately, they have to agree with the trade pact but the Commission has a high degree of competence in relation to it.</p><p>On foreign policy, governments and the people of the European Union have decided - I believe it is the right decision - to retain much of the competence for making foreign policy decisions in their own Ministers.  The Ministers make many decisions on EU foreign policy through the Foreign Affairs Council and with the consent of their governments at home.  Where that leads me is to say that we should not blame the European Union for discharging competences and powers which it does not have in the first place.  Much of the power and role on foreign policy decisions sits with individual foreign Ministers.  It is through agreement and compromise within the Foreign Affairs Council that a general overall approach is reached.</p><p>I wish to pick up on one point made by Senator Walsh on Kosovo.  I have heard the analogy put forward by other contributors to today&rsquo;s debate.  I put it to him that there is a very big difference between Kosovo and where we are now.  The big difference is that in the period leading up to the Kosovan decision they were participating in a realm of international administration under the terms of the UN resolution to which Senator Jim D&rsquo;Arcy referred.  All the decisions that were made in Kosovo happened in accordance with the same international law that was not recognised in Crimea.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W00200"><p>It was unilateral.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W00300"><p>There are significant differences though because, as I said, what happened in Kosovo was in accordance with international law and a UN resolution but that did not happen in the case of Crimea.  I suggest that is the point of difference.</p><p>I agree with the point Senator Jim D&rsquo;Arcy made that the most important principle of all is international law.  I also agree with his point on Kosovo which is similar to the one I just made.  Like him, I believe the European Union will have a big impact on what happens in Ukraine.  He is correct to say that at the moment one of the most important contributions we can make is to try to make Ukraine stable and to ensure that economic support is available to it in what will be a challenging period.</p><p>That leads me to a point made by Senator Reilly, with which I agree, namely, that one of the most important things we can do at the moment is to support Ukraine in its journey to make its own decisions on the future and make sure it has the correct socio-economic circumstances in which to do it.</p><p>Senator Leyden made the point that the European Union is being provocative and forced the situation.  I completely disagree with the point.  I have explained why that is the case.  I agree with the decision that was made in the Council of Europe.  Senator Leyden also referred to exports and the impact on them, including the impact on our stability and the recovery we want to happen and continue in the future.  I am deeply aware of all of the economic considerations involved and other matters that must be taken into account.  As we weigh all of that up, it is vital to take account of the fact that the borders of a country on the continent of Europe were unilaterally changed.  That is a major event that will have significant consequences that will ripple through us all and affect many other decisions that will be made in decades to come.</p><p>I wish to conclude on one point made by Senator Norris on which Senator Barrett picked up, namely, Russia being a member of the European Union at some point in the future.  If Senator Barrett had said in the late 1980s in this House that we would end up in a situation where we would have many of the Baltic states as members of the European Union, a peaceful end to the Cold War and the USSR dissolve in a way that did not trigger war across the entire Continent many would have questioned the likelihood of such a vision.  However, that is what happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W00400"><p>One should remember the role of Mr. Gorbachev.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W00500"><p>Senator Walsh is correct to refer to the role of individual leaders.  In the 1980s we would not have considered it possible that the USSR could have a leader like Mr. Gorbachev who would make the decisions he did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.282" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W00600"><p>He referred to Europe stretching from the Atlantic to the Urals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W00700"><p>Yes, but the point on which I wish to conclude is that we should not rule out possibilities that could occur in the future-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.284" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W00800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W00900"><p>-----regardless of how implausible they are now.  In tandem with the condemnation of what happened in Crimea it is vital that we continue talking to all of the players involved to explore the possibility of bringing the situation to a peaceful end, which we all want to see happen.  While we are cognisant of the deep challenges we face elsewhere in the world, most notably what is happening in Syria and the Middle East - of which I am most aware - we must also be conscious of the significant possibilities that still exist within Europe for prosperity and security that might seem unlikely now but are possible given what has been achieved that seemed most unlikely many years ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W01000"><p>Before I call on the Acting Leader to move the Adjournment I wish everyone a happy Easter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014041700023#W01100"><p>I wish you a happy Easter, Acting Chairman, and I propose the adjournment of the House until Wednesday, 7 May at 1.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-04-17a.288" nospeaker="true" time="13:45:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.20 p.m. until 1.30 p.m. on Wednesday, 7 May 2014.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>