<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the scoliosis treatment waiting lists for children.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Seery Kearney of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for public health, well-being and national drugs strategy to make a statement on the apportionment of funding to drugs and alcohol task forces from the drugs strategy funding announced in budget 2022.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement on the continuing incarceration of Julian Assange. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on plans to ensure water supplies are reliable and safe, particularly in light of issues at the Ballymore Eustace plant.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on the lack of parity between the use of traditional and simplified Chinese characters in leaving certificate Mandarin classes.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Fitzpatrick of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the timeline for the appointment of a design team for the west wing critical care unit of the Rotunda Hospital, Parnell Square. </blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the current Covid-19 vaccine uptake and whether continuing with the requirement to show a digital Covid certificate would assist in encouraging further take up of the vaccine. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator John Cummins of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to broaden the commercial to residential planning exemption to include former pubs. </blockquote><p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and I have selected Senators Boyhan, Seery Kearney, Gavan and O&rsquo;Loughlin and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.  <br/><br/>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Frankie Feighan, for coming to the House.  </p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#B00150">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#B00200">Health Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, and welcome him back to the Seanad.  This issue relates to the Scoliosis Advocacy Network.  I am not sure if the Minister of State has been briefed on this issue, but its representative appeared last week on "Today with Claire Byrne" on RT&Eacute;.  One of the reasons I am following up on this is that the Scoliosis Advocacy Network has been in touch with me, as it has been in touch with many other Members.  The network's concern is what it describes as children languishing on waiting lists to have their medical needs and surgery addressed.</p> <p>On "Today with Claire Byrne", the cofounder of the Scoliosis Advocacy Network, Ms Clare Cahill, said there had been no engagement with the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, despite repeated requests.  That surprised me.  I have a lot of time for the Minister; he is most engaging.  Any time I have had any reason to deal with him on any matter he has been prompt and responsive.  That is on the record and I have checked it again.  This story was covered on RT&Eacute; radio.  I checked again this morning just to be sure.  The network has said it is a concern and I would like some clarification on that assertion.</p> <p>The network has cited the last-minute cancellation of surgery, as well as the experience that some children have had of surgery being cancelled; many of them have had it cancelled three times.  That is clearly unacceptable.  We know that the Ombudsman for Children has highlighted access to scoliosis care for children and has spoken about it as being a fundamental children's right.  I agree with him. </p> <p>The HSE promised it would buy surgeries and provide health services through the private health system, in a similar manner to the National Treatment Purchase Fund, NTPF.  I now understand this is not available for those with very complex needs, and I can understand that.  That is fair and reasonable.</p> <p>Two issues stood out in RT&Eacute;'s coverage of this issue.  The Taoiseach has said that the delays in treatment are not because of the lack of resources, but rather are the result of a systemic failure.  He said he has spoken to the Minister for Health about these matters.  The Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Leo Varadkar, said the Government severely regrets that children and their families are experiencing long waiting times for scoliosis treatment and that he is seriously concerned about it.  I think that is fair comment.</p> <p>I had hoped to ask the Minister for Health about this.  There are now 172 children waiting for scoliosis treatment, many of whom are, as their parents have described, in agony.  They have specific needs and the longer interventions are delayed, the more impact there will be on them.  It is a scandal. Health is an important issue.  It is something that has to be addressed, in particular where children are concerned.</p> <p>I am not sure if the Minister of State is in a position to answer my question, but I intended to ask the Minister for Health to explain why there is such a delay in surgery and what the systemic failure is that the Taoiseach is on the record as saying exists regarding scoliosis treatment.  In a nutshell, I want the Minister of State, if he can, to set out a timeline for how these children will be treated and, more importantly, an absolute commitment that the Minister and Department of Health will engage in a meaningful way with the Scoliosis Advocacy Network.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#B00400"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this very important issue.  On behalf of the Minister, Deputy Donnelly, I welcome the opportunity to address the House.</p> <p>I sincerely regret that children can experience a long waiting time for scoliosis treatment and I remain conscious of the burden this places on them and their families.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frankie Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The priority of the Minister for Health and the Government is to improve waiting times for all patients accessing hospital treatment, and reducing paediatric waiting lists for orthopaedic procedures remains a priority within that.  The Department, the HSE and the National Treatment Purchase Fund, NTPF, are working on a multi-annual waiting list plan to address waiting lists and bring them in line with Sl&aacute;intecare targets over the coming years.  This process will be overseen by a ministerial task force, chaired by the Secretary General of the Department and including representatives from the HSE and the National Treatment Purchase Fund.  It will take the learnings from the achievements of the vaccine task force to inform the plan.</p><p>To support the work of the task force, an additional &euro;250 million is being provided in budget 2022 to improve access to care across the health system.  It is recognised that waiting times for scheduled appointments and procedures have been impacted in the past 19 months as a direct result of the Covid-19 pandemic and, more recently, as a result of the ransomware attack.  The cyberattack in May 2021 in particular caused significant disruption to the orthopaedic service and all services across the Children's Health Ireland, CHI, hospital group.  Without access to a patient's full history and previous diagnostic investigations, it was not considered safe to proceed without all electronic support systems in place.  This impacted patients with complex needs in particular and restricted the patient cohort that could safely proceed without surgery during this time.  Most systems are now back up and running across CHI sites, but backloading of information is ongoing, and this continues to have an impact on waiting lists and the numbers of surgeries completed.</p><p>Despite the impact of the pandemic and the cyberattack, Children's Health Ireland advises that as of the end of September 2021, 266 spinal surgeries had been carried out, which is an increase of 41 compared with the same period last year.  CHI has remained committed to increasing activity levels and examining innovative measures to improve access to all specialties.  For example, additional theatre sessions are being held in Cappagh National Orthopaedic Hospital for non-complex, age-appropriate orthopaedic patients.  CHI also continues to develop the advanced clinical triage model in Citywest.  Active clinical triage is a system which has been adapted for use within the paediatric orthopaedic unit at CHI Crumlin.  Its purpose is to reduce the overall orthopaedic outpatient waiting list, starting with the longest waiting clinically appropriate referrals.</p><p>A new orthopaedic consultant with a specialist interest in neuromuscular conditions started in Temple Street in September, which should also enable the use of additional theatre capacity and support additional capacity as part of the Cappagh kids programme.  Officials in the Department of Health remain in regular contact with CHI regarding scoliosis services, and CHI has advised that all patients with a diagnosis of scoliosis require a preoperative work-up prior to spinal surgery, including multiple diagnostic investigations and a review by a multidisciplinary team.  The plan of care, which is implemented for each patient, is tailored to best meet a patient's clinical requirements.  It is the responsibility of the treating consultant to prioritise patients clinically on the waiting list for surgery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#C00200"><p>I am very disappointed.  I do not know who prepared the Minister of State's response.  This matter was specifically about scoliosis.  This was not about the National Treatment Purchase Fund or waiting lists generally.  This was a very focused Commencement matter about 170 children with scoliosis.  It was as a result of an episode of "Today with Claire Byrne" on RT&Eacute; last week and correspondence that had been sent to the Taoiseach, the T&aacute;naiste, the Minister for Health and the leader of the Labour Party, Deputy Kelly.  There is no comfort in the Minister of State's reply.  What do I say when I pick up the phone in ten minutes' time to speak to the Scoliosis Advocacy Network, whose members asked me to make a case for them here today?</p> <p>The reply does not talk about the systemic failure the Taoiseach spoke about and is on the record as having spoken about.  It does not talk about the severe regrets expressed by the T&aacute;naiste or children's experiences of long waiting lists or the need to remain conscious of the burdens that are placed on the families concerned.  None of that is addressed in the Minister of State's response.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I respect the Minister of State.  He has a task to do and he is delivering the substance of this message on behalf of the Department but I ask him to go back to it and say this is urgent.  It relates specifically to the 172 children who want to know when they are having their treatment.  They do not want to hear, for the fourth time, that their treatment has been deferred.  I thank the Minister of State for giving the Department&rsquo;s response but I respectfully ask him to go back to the Department and say he is not happy with it.  It is not comprehensive and it does not give comfort to the children and families involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#D00200"><p>Again, I thank to Senator for raising this issue.  I am acutely aware of the distress and inconvenience caused to patients and their families when urgent care is delayed.  Improving waiting times for hospital appointments and procedures is a priority.  I will relay the Senator&rsquo;s concerns and annoyance to the Minister and the Department.</p> <p>It is recognised that waiting times for all scheduled appointments and procedures have been impacted in the past 19 months as a direct result of Covid-19.  There have been some positive aspects but the needs of the 172 young children need to be addressed as quickly as possible.  I hope my officials in the Department will work closely with Children&rsquo;s Health Ireland and the wider HSE to try to improve access to this treatment.  </p> <p>The Senator asked for a commitment to a timeline.  I cannot give him one.  However, I thank him for raising this difficult and important issue.  I will relay his views to the Department and try to get him a response as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.16" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#D00300">Departmental Funding</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#D00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State, as always.  I really appreciate his great commitment to us in the Seanad.</p><p>I really welcomed the announcement in the budget of an additional &euro;6 million for the Minister of State&rsquo;s Department.  I have submitted this matter because we really need to understand how much of the funding is being apportioned to the drugs and alcohol tasks forces under the drugs strategy.  The Minister of State is no doubt aware of the views of the chairs of the drugs and alcohol task forces around Dublin.  I am privileged to be the chair of the Dublin 12 drugs and alcohol task force.  For much of my contribution, I will use its words.  The drugs initiative budget was cut every year between 2008 and 2014, resulting in an overall cut of 35% to key services responding to the drug problem on the ground.  There has been little or no attempt to restore the pre-recession budgets and no increase in the allocation between 2014 and 2018.  In 2019, there was an additional &euro;20,000 per drugs task force but half of that was clawed back in 2020.  In 2021, a need for an increase in drugs and alcohol task force budgets was anticipated.  There has been a failure year on year, which is frustrating and demoralising for those working on the ground.  The drugs problem has become more widespread.  It is complex and deep rooted.  Each community has its own problems to deal with and its own needs to be met.  Therefore, communities need discretion to model their actions and respond at local level.</p><p>We have a commitment in the programme for Government.  It states:</p> <blockquote> 	The Drug and Alcohol Task Forces play a key role in implementing this strategy and increasing access at local level to harm reduction initiatives.  We will examine how we can continue to support it in identifying local need in communities, and support targeted initiatives addressing drug and alcohol misuse. </blockquote> <p>To date, there has not been great progress in supporting the increase in the demand for those services, although I acknowledge the Minister of State&rsquo;s absolute commitment and support.  I acknowledge also that he recently met representatives of each of the drugs task forces and set out the six strategic areas on which he is going to work with them.  However, the matter highlighted in the budget submission of the drugs and alcohol task forces is that, although there is inflation, the budget has not matched it.</p><p>There is an increase in demand, the tsunami expected after Covid.  We need an increase.  There is an increase in the number of people with a dual diagnosis to which we need to be able to respond.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is no discretion for design and delivery in the scope of the funding available to services.  We need to build back better.  The pandemic response needs to be phased, targeted and very community focused and community-based because the culture and context is unique to each task force.  I see this even with our task force and the individual areas within Dublin 12.  I would welcome the Minister of State's comments on how much of this budget is being allocated to task forces.  It would be great to see a major amount because it is more than needed, to say the very least.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#E00200"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising this issue.  I welcome the opportunity to update the House on the funding allocated in budget 2022.  I echo her contribution regarding the work the task forces do.  I will put on the record my great admiration and thanks for the great work the volunteers and people in the task forces have done.</p> <p>I am providing &euro;6 million in new funding for new measures to support the implementation of the national drugs strategy.  This funding will strengthen the health-led approach to drugs and alcohol use and will deliver on new strategic priorities for 2021 to 2025 under the national drugs strategy, including commitments in the programme for Government, which the Senator referenced.  I am happy to inform the Seanad that I am providing &euro;500,000 to increase access to, and provision of, community-based drug and alcohol services in budget 2022.  The funding will have a specific focus on services for women, ethnic minorities and LGBTI+.  It will address the barriers women and minority groups can face in accessing drug and alcohol services.  </p> <p>The lived experience of people who use drugs will be central to the design and delivery of the new services.  The new services will be developed in conjunction with the national network of drug and alcohol task forces.  The Department of Health has published a fact sheet on the allocation of the &euro;6 million funding, which is available online and is being circulated to all stakeholders, including drug and alcohol task forces and the community and voluntary sector.</p> <p>The Senator will be interested in the other measures I am supporting in budget 2022.  These include &euro;1.7 million to increase the availability of HSE drug and alcohol services on a nationwide basis for people with alcohol addiction, people under 18, families affected by drugs and rehabilitation and recovery programmes; &euro;700,000 to reduce the impact of parental drug and alcohol use on children and young people in line with the joint HSE-Tusla Hidden Harm strategic statement and practices guide; &euro;300,000 for harm reduction responses to address high-risk drug use, such as crack cocaine and stimulant drugs in local communities and the night-time economy, and to extend the Naloxone demonstration project to prevent drug overdose deaths; and &euro;700,000 to provide health screening and brief intervention for people who use drugs known as SAOR.  This service will be a core component of the health diversion programme for people found in possession of drugs for personal use, so they are treated with compassion and have the opportunity to avoid a criminal conviction.  There will also be &euro;300,000 to expand health supports for people who are homeless and have complex health and addiction needs.  This includes an additional 260 tenancies under Housing First and an enhanced health service for up to 4,000 single homeless people in Dublin. </p> <p>I envisage a key role for community and voluntary organisations, including the network of drug and alcohol task forces, in delivering these new measures I announced in budget 2022.  Additional resources will be directed towards interventions that lead to reductions in problem drug and alcohol use and achieve an improvement in public health outcomes.  Measuring the effectiveness of these additional services will, therefore, be an important objective of public policy.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising the issue of dual diagnosis, which is one that we must work on in all sectors across all Departments.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frankie Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am keen to work with all stakeholders on ensuring that we can tackle it a bit more robustly than has been the case in recent years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#F00200"><p>I acknowledge the Minister of State&rsquo;s personal commitment from the moment he took on this responsibility.  He has shown an extraordinary commitment and openness in the context of listening to the sector.  I welcome the breakdown of the funding allocated.  I will be delighted to share that information with the chairs and co-ordinators of the drug and alcohol task forces when I go back to my office.  The health model is problematic, though, when we are dealing with such a complex basket of needs.  What is required is an interdepartmental and interagency response.  I hope that we will get an opportunity in the context of the strategic review to highlight this aspect with the Minister of State.  We need discretion in this area and the budget provision must have some sort of discretionary element.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#F00300"><p>Following agreement on the strategic priorities for the national drugs strategy for the period 2021-25, I recently met with the drug and alcohol task forces, as the Senator said, to outline the additional funding I am providing to deliver on these strategic priorities.  This includes &euro;1 million in funding for the development of a programme of community-based drug and alcohol services.  The programme will adopt a population-based approach to the provision of drug and alcohol services in line with the Sl&aacute;intecare model.  An allocation of funding will be provided to each community healthcare organisation, and there will be engagement with the drug and alcohol task forces to identify service priorities for their regions.  That development has been welcomed by the task forces.  I will also be announcing shortly a prevention and education programme on alcohol and drugs use among children and young people.  The drug and alcohol task forces will have an opportunity to develop proposals for funding under this programme.  Together with the measures announced in budget 2022, this additional funding will strengthen the health-led approach to drugs and alcohol use and deliver on the strategic priorities for the period 2021 to 2025 under the national drugs strategy, as well as on the commitments in the programme for Government.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.23" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#F00400">Freedom of Speech</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#F00500"><p>It is always good to see the Minister of State.  I thank him for coming into the House.  I raise the issue of the continuing incarceration of Julian Assange and ask for urgent action from the Irish Government on this issue and for it to speak out about it.  Since 9/11 and the subsequent, and misnamed, war on terror, respect for international law by the US, NATO and other allied countries has virtually collapsed.  That has led to the most horrific war crimes and abuses being committed.  Sadly, Ireland is implicated in this situation because of our facilitation of the US military at Shannon Airport.</p><p>Mr. Assange has spent ten years incarcerated, first in the Ecuadorian Embassy in London and then in solitary confinement for the past two years in Belmarsh Prison in the UK.  Although a British court refused to extradite Mr. Assange due to fears that he would not survive the US penal system, that decision is now being challenged by the US Government.  If the appeal succeeds, then Mr. Assange will face a sentence of 175 years in prison.  He will likely spend that time in extreme isolation.  This is clearly a politically motivated case, taken simply because Mr. Assange exposed US military and other war crimes, human rights abuses and corruption in the US-led wars in Afghanistan and Iraq.</p><p>The documents released by WikiLeaks were published widely by mainstream media outlets such as <i>The Guardian</i>, <i>The New York Times</i>, <i>Der Spiegel</i>, <i>Le Monde</i>and many others.  First came revelations of the breaches of international law at Guantanamo Bay and then the collateral murder video, which recorded US pilots in an Apache helicopter gleefully slaughtering 18 innocent Iraqi civilians.  In co-ordination with international media organisations, Mr. Assange followed those revelations with the Afghan war diaries and the Iraq war diaries, which exposed major war crimes committed by US forces and their allies.</p><p>Mr. Assange is, in effect, a political prisoner.  His continued incarceration and threatened extradition to the US, therefore, is not just a threat to him personally but to all journalists, editors and publishers and the cause of investigative journalism, press freedom and freedom of speech generally.  It is ironic that western countries, which claim to be defenders of freedom, are acting in this way.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> In fairness to the Government, in recent times the Minister for Foreign Affairs has been very outspoken on both the failures of international policies and the very clear abuse of power shown by nations, in particular in respect of journalists and political opponents.  Recently the Minister condemned the incarceration of Alexei Navalny in Russia.  He also spoke out about the Ryanair flight that was in effect hijacked over Belarus to detain Roman Protasevich, a journalist who was outspoken against the Belarusian Government.  Even more recently the Minister outlined his views on the catastrophic failures in US foreign policies in Afghanistan.  It was those failures of American policymakers that Julian Assange helped to highlight and let the world know about.  He is an outstanding journalist and a credit to the work he has done.  He should be treated as such and should not be held in captivity any more.  He should be released immediately.  Ireland now has a very strong voice in our position on the UN Security Council.  It is time we used that for the common good and spoke up for Julian Assange.</p><p>Mr. Assange has suffered enough simply because he exposed through his journalism extensive government deceit, corruption, war crimes, state-sponsored killings, extraordinary rendition, military cover-ups of unlawful killings and, ultimately, the true wholesale horror of the disastrous, futile wars led by the US and British Governments.  It is time for us to speak out.  We cannot pick and choose which human rights issues we wish to speak out about.  If we believe in freedom of speech, it must apply to Julian Assange as well as others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#G00200"><p>I thank Senator Gavan for raising this matter, which has been the subject of much media comment in recent years.  My colleague, the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Minister for Defence, Deputy Coveney, has informed me that officials of his Department are following the case of Mr. Julian Assange.  Mr. Assange, an Australian citizen and the public face of the Wikileaks website, was arrested by British police in London in April 2019 after he left the Embassy of the Republic of Ecuador because the asylum that had been granted to him by Ecuador about seven years previously was withdrawn.  He was initially jailed in May 2019 at Belmarsh Prison, London, for a breach of bail conditions.  In September 2019 his remand status was changed from a serving prisoner to a person facing extradition.  Mr. Assange is currently detained in the UK on an extradition request from the United States.  In September 2020 he appeared before the Central Criminal Court of England and Wales for an extradition hearing.  He faced a United States federal grand jury indictment.  According to a US Department of Justice release of 24 June 2020, this indictment included charges of conspiracy to obtain and disclose national defence information, conspiracy to commit computer intrusions, seven counts of obtaining national defence information and nine counts of disclosure of national defence information.</p> <p>On 4 January 2021, at Westminster Magistrates Court, the request of the United States for Mr. Assange's extradition was refused.  The full text of this ruling can be found on the website of the Judiciary of England and Wales.  I understand from press reports that the United States Government lodged an appeal against this ruling on 15 January 2021 and was given more time to submit detailed grounds for its appeal.  Recent media coverage indicates that in August the UK High Court handed down a judgment that will allow the US Government to expand the grounds for this appeal.  According to the press reports, Mr. Assange appeared at the hearing via video link from Belmarsh Prison.</p> <p>The Minister considers this to be a legal matter within the jurisdiction of the United Kingdom that appears to be subject to ongoing legal proceedings.  The question of the next steps for Mr. Assange rests with the UK judicial authorities.  As legal proceedings are under way on this matter in another jurisdiction, the Minister does not intend to comment on this case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#G00300"><p>It is so disappointing.  We have a seat on the UN Security Council yet the Minister of State says the Government will not comment on perhaps the biggest human rights case facing the western world.  What a contrast with the situation in Belarus.  That is a situation involving a legal case.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is a legal matter and the Government has no problem commenting on it.  It has no problem commenting on legal proceedings in Russia but it will not offer a word of condemnation or stand for human rights when it comes to a man who has done more to expose war crimes than any other individual in my lifetime.  The Minister of State is here to say there is nothing to see here and he will not comment.</p><p>Where are the values of this Government?  How can this be acceptable in the face of the horrendous plight of Mr. Julian Assange?  We all know why this is happening.  The US wants to send a message to the world that if anybody tells the world what it does, this is the treatment that will be meted out.  This is the punishment that will be received.  We can see that happening to Julian but the Minister of State is here saying he has no comment.  It is appalling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#H00200"><p>I thank the Senator and have taken note of his remarks on the matter, specifically those on our seat at the United Nations Security Council and what is, effectively, a difference of opinion on matters related to Belarus and Russia.  I will bring them back to the Minister.  This is a legal matter within the jurisdiction of the United Kingdom and it appears to be the subject of ongoing legal proceedings, as I have already explained.  The next steps in what happens to Mr. Assange rest with the UK judicial authorities.  Again, as legal proceedings are under way with this matter in another jurisdiction, it is very difficult for us to comment on it.  I will bring the Senator's views and concerns back to the Minister and I hope we can get a reply from the Department.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.30" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#H00300">Water Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#H00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Malcolm Noonan.  The next matter is from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin and relates to the water supply issues at the Ballymore Eustace plan in the great County Kildare.  She is welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#H00500"><p>It is absolutely the great county of Kildare.  I am glad the Acting Chairman said that.  I welcome the Minister of State, and I hope he will take on board the comments and points I will make.  I certainly welcome any answers he has.</p> <p>"Water is the lifeblood of our bodies, our economy, our nation and our well-being."  That is a quote from Mr. Stephen Johnson, a former head of the American Environmental Protection Agency, and it rings completely true to us.  I know the Minister of State is familiar with Kildare, where Ballymore Eustace has Ireland's largest water treatment plant, serving a population of almost 1 million people.  It is located in County Kildare, although it is looked after by Dublin City Council.  I am raising the really important question of water quality and the management of our water treatment plants.</p> <p>We were all shocked in August to learn of the incidents that occurred at the Ballymore Eustace treatment plant, as well as the Creagh water treatment plant at Gorey.  It is clear the management of these facilities failed miserably.  Essentially, the management had to protect and safeguard the quality of water coming from these facilities but that did not happen.  The failure of the local authorities, including Dublin City Council and Wexford County Council, to report issues with water quality to Irish Water in a timely manner led to an absolutely unacceptable delay in the Environmental Protection Agency and the Health Service Executive being notified, meaning there was no opportunity to issue a boil water notice.  A prompt response could have protected the over 900,000 people dependent on this water supply from being needlessly put at risk.</p> <p>We all accept a boil water notice is a major inconvenience, and I agree that they should be used sparingly and only issued when absolutely necessary.  In these cases, however, a notice would have allowed people to protect themselves while the problems at water treatment plants were resolved.  The failure in communication allowed consumption to continue as normal when it was known there was a problem.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I put it to the Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, that this was simply unacceptable.  I find even more concerning the reports of how the specific issues were dealt with, such as the pump failure in Ballymore Eustace and the power failure at Creagh water treatment plant.  Even under normal circumstances we were failing to protect our water supply.  A safe and secure water supply is the very least that any of us can expect in our country.  A recent audit has found that chlorine levels at the Ballymore Eustace plant were below standard even when the facility was functioning normally.  This means that the water coming out of people's taps was regularly put at risk.  That is absolutely unacceptable.  Unfortunately, these are not isolated incidents.  The entire process of how we supply water in the State needs to be reviewed.  It is clear that enhanced scrutiny and oversight of the entire process is needed.  Indeed, a month ago in this House I spoke about the issue whereby a number of eels were entering the water supply in the Carlow north regional water facility, which supplies water to Castledermot in south Kildare.</p><p>These are just three examples I have given to the Minister of State but I could go on all day recounting stories of issues from across my county and the country.  What plans are in place to ensure a reliable and safe water supply to be provided to Irish citizens?  What mitigation measures were put in place to give the general public confidence in the water coming from their taps?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#J00200"><p>I agree with the contention about the great County Kildare.  I have Kildare blood in me too.  It is a fantastic county.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  It is of deep concern to us all.  The recent issues at both the Ballymore Eustace and Gorey water treatment plants gave rise to genuine concerns regarding operational failures at these plants as identified by the Environmental Protection Agency, EPA.</p> <p>At the outset, I can assure the Senator that at recent meetings with the managing director of Irish Water and the chief executives of Dublin City Council and Wexford County Council, the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, was informed that both treatment plants are stable, operating normally and are producing clean and wholesome water.</p> <p>The Minister requested that Irish Water undertake audits on the largest water treatment plants in the State serving the majority of the population.  These are now complete and refresher training has been provided to the operatives at these plants.  In addition, refresher training is being provided to all local authority management and engineers who are then cascading this training to all operatives and technical staff in all 800-plus water treatment plants nationwide.</p> <p>In the longer term, ensuring security of water supply requires fit-for-purpose working arrangements and appropriate investment.  As to the limitations to the current working arrangements between Irish Water and local authorities, a process is now under way in the Workplace Relations Commission to deliver the transformation of this service so that Irish Water has full control of the water services workforce and is therefore fully responsible and accountable for the delivery of the service.</p> <p>On funding, as part of budget 2022 the Government will be investing more than &euro;1.57 billion to support water services next year.  This includes more than &euro;1.4 billion for domestic water services provision by Irish Water.  This is part of the commitment under the national development plan for &euro;6 billion of capital investment to be undertaken by Irish Water in the period 2021-25.</p> <p>We should note that the recast EU drinking water directive, adopted on 16 December 2020, updates the obligations on member states regarding the provision of water intended for human consumption.  The objective of this directive is to protect human health from the adverse effects of any contamination of water intended for human consumption by ensuring that it is wholesome and clean, and to improve access to water intended for human consumption.  This will be achieved through a number of measures including the introduction of a risk-based approach to water supply that incorporates drinking water safety plans.  A programme of drinking water safety planning is currently under way as part of Irish Water's water services strategic plan.</p> <p>I assure the Senator that we acknowledge there were clear and unacceptable failings here in terms of communication.  People took ill from what happened at these plants.  The Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, acted swiftly with Irish Water, with the local authorities and with local government in general to ensure that incidents of this nature do not happen again</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#K00100"><p>I appreciate that it has been acknowledged that there were clear communication failures in what happened with the Ballymore Eustace and Gorey supplies.  We have to ensure that does not happen again.  I appreciate the plants are now stable and operating normally, are producing clean and wholesome water and the refresher training has been put in place for all staff.  That is very important.</p> <p>The Minister of State has mentioned very significant investment of &euro;1.57 billion next year, which is an incredible amount of money.  If that is what is needed for a safe and secure supply of clean water, then it is money well spent.  It is about the outcomes, however, it is not about the money spent.  We must ensure we do not have these systemic failures again because, as I said at the start, the very least people can expect is access to safe, secure water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#K00200"><p>Again, I want to give that assurance the Senator that certainly the learning experiences from this incident have been taken on board.  The Minister, as I said, has acted swiftly and the Senator is correct in saying the investment of &euro;1.57 billion is needed.  That is sustained investment that is required over a period of time.  The investment of &euro;6 billion over the lifetime of the national development plan, NDP, is required because, as we have heard in this House and in the D&aacute;il, we have had a number of incidents throughout the country where there have been discharges of raw sewage into watercourses.  It is unacceptable from a human health and biodiversity point of view and these have to be addressed.  That is why the Government is deeply committed now to ensuring we have a fit-for-purpose water and wastewater treatment system that is suitable for the needs and growth of the population in years to come.  It is only fit and right we continue to invest, and this Government is committed to record investment in water and wastewater treatment over the next decade.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.37" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.17 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.38" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#N00050">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#N00100"><p>Since we were here last there have been a number of tragedies and sad passings.  M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi and my fellow Kerryman, Brendan Kennelly, are a great loss to the nation and to their families.  Our condolences to all the bereaved.</p> <p>Last Friday, we saw the killing of Sir David Amess.  I know I speak on behalf of all members of Seanad &Eacute;ireann when I express our heartfelt sympathies to his family on their unimaginable loss.  I also extend our sympathies to his parliamentary colleagues in Westminster who have felt his loss keenly on a personal level.  They rightly see this, as we do, as an attack on democracy itself.  All of us in Seanad &Eacute;ireann are all too well aware of the degrading language and intemperate attitudes often used in political discourse in this day and age.  While we all recognise that vigorous debate is part of our democracy, those who refuse to recognise and respect the right of people to hold different views and opinions need to reflect upon the kind of intolerance that sometimes leads to events such as the killing of Sir David.  Sir David was a man of great dignity and principle.  He was a decent man.  He was a good friend of Ireland and he was an associate member of the British-Irish Parliamentary Association.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#N00200"><p>I join the Cathaoirleach in his comments on Sir David Amess.  His death has sent shock waves through politics here and in the UK.  Most worrying was the commentary to the effect that somehow it was justified because of the job he was doing or the party he was a member of.  This is a cause for concern for all of us.  It is something to be vigilant about.  We send our thoughts, prayers and sympathies to his family, friends and colleagues and to the community he served with distinction for so many years.</p> <p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on Sl&aacute;intecare, to be taken at 5 p.m. and to conclude at 6.30 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to opening remarks by the Minister not to exceed ten minutes and the time allocated to all Senators not to exceed five minutes, with the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 84.4, Private Members' business, motion regarding flooding, to be taken at 6.45 p.m., with the time allocated to this debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#N00300"><p>On behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il party, I join the Cathaoirleach in sending sympathies to the family and, indeed, to the Westminster family of Sir David Amess.  He was a very fine and distinguished parliamentarian.</p> <p>I also send condolences to the families of M&aacute;ire Mhac An tSaoi and Brendan Kennelly,  At a time when coarse language is something that is used all too often, we had two wonderful poets who espoused the positive use of language.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are the poorer for their loss but the richer for their having lived.</p><p>I will support the proposed Order of Business.  There are a number of issues I wish to raise.  The first relates to an article I read yesterday that shocked me.  It concerned a man who tried to choke his ex-partner and was jailed for just three months.  His defence maintained that the fact he was "off his face" on cocaine was almost an explanation for the brutal attack he committed.  It is shocking.  His three small children, who were witnesses to the attack, tried to protect their mother and stop the attack using Power Rangers swords.  It was such a vicious attack, in which the mum was left badly bruised and with broken fingers.  That the sentence was only three months long is completely wrong.  We talk about Supporting a Victim's Journey, which is the name of a new plan under the Department of Justice, but this sentence does not send a clear message to perpetrators or would-be perpetrators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#O00200"><p>I remind Senators that in respect of court judgments, sentencing can always be appealed.  We must be mindful when we raise issues relating to courts in the context of the separation of powers between Seanad &Eacute;ireann and the Courts Service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#O00300"><p>I accept that but sentencing should reflect the crime.  We have to take into account the impact on children.</p> <p>I raise also the issue of derelict sites.  I have become aware of a number of derelict sites within my town of Newbridge and around south County Kildare that are owned by investment funds.  They are a blight on the estates on which they are situated.  Dumping is going on and young people are hanging around, yet it is difficult for Kildare County Council, in this instance, to secure the property because of the legal issues.  There needs to be a streamlined system whereby properties can be secured if, after a period, the owners cannot be contacted in order that the sites can be taken by the local authority and turned into accommodation.  We all recognise and acknowledge the need for more houses but something needs to be done in respect of derelict sites.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#O00400"><p>I thank the Deputy Leader for outlining the proposed Order of Business.  On behalf of the Fine Gael group in this House, I join the Cathaoirleach in extending our sympathies to the family of Sir David Amess.  As a new member of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, of which Sir David was also a member, it is a sad day for me.  Many of our colleagues in this House met him and worked with him on British-Irish relations over the years.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam.</p> <p>I join also in the tributes to Brendan Kennelly and M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi.  Brendan Kennelly was a feature of the streets of Dublin city for decades and always gave up his time freely to young people who were interested in literature.  This country has benefited greatly from the wisdom of both Brendan Kennelly and M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi.</p> <p>It is good news that society is reopening, as will happen on Friday.  That must be welcomed but caution has to be exercised.  The issue of personal responsibility is now coming to the fore.  I have no doubt that when the people are asked to show personal responsibility, to be careful, cautious and considerate and to step back when necessary, that will happen.  I wish the businesses that will reopen on Friday, after 19 long months, the very best.  I hope it will go smoothly, carefully and safely.</p> <p>On health issues, the hospitals in Galway and Limerick are very overcrowded.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We also know the flu vaccination season had begun.  While I welcome the Government's announcement that it will extend the remit of those who can receive free flu vaccines, we need to go further.  We have seen the success of the Covid-19 vaccine in this country and we need to see the uptake of the flu vaccine at 90% plus.  I call on the Government to make the flu vaccine free to everybody - it will be a small cost - and to encourage take-up.  At present, it is a case of us being penny wise pound foolish.  If we can get 90% of the population to take the flu vaccine injection, we would reap the rewards with fewer presentations at accident and emergency units throughout the country, and it would be a small cost to bear.  I call on the Leader to contact the Minister to articulate that view and, if necessary, to allow a debate in this House on the flu injection and its free provision.</p><p>There was an incident in my constituency whereby an ambulance had to travel from Galway to Kilkee to attend a road traffic accident.  That is totally unacceptable.  We need a debate in this House on the National Ambulance Service.  There are great women and men, paramedics and drivers, working in the National Ambulance Service but there seems to be a problem with response times and the methods used to co-ordinate it at national level.  We need a debate on the National Ambulance Service in recognition of the great work our paramedics do and to ensure the service is quick and responsive and available when people need it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#P00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising the issue of the paramedics.  I know the case of a family in distress who were told that no ambulance would attend them.  While the ambulance had to travel from Galway to Kilkee in the Senator's example, there was no ambulance available to help this family.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#P00300"><p>That is not acceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#P00400"><p>I concur with the sympathies expressed by the Cathaoirleach to the family of Sir David Amess.</p><p>On Thursday evening, I called to my grandchildren - I know the Leader has young children - and the excitement in my six-year-old granddaughter&rsquo;s eyes when she sat me down to tell me she was going to read me a story and, as she read me the story, the excitement in the four-year-old sat beside her, watching as her sister read, was something to behold.  I missed a lot of that with my own kids, but it was really something else in this case.</p><p>Why I am bringing this up today?  On 19 August, at the United Nations Security Council, Ireland and Mexico urged the Security Council to place the utmost priority on protecting and vindicating the rights of Afghan women and girls in all decisions and actions on Afghanistan&rsquo;s future.  They jointly outlined the actions that the council must take.  They stated:</p> <blockquote> 	1. The Security Council must unite and express clearly its rejection of these assaults on the rights of women and girls.<br /><br />2. The Council must as a matter of urgency call on all parties to respect and facilitate the emergency evacuation and safe and timely departure of Afghans, including human rights defenders, women leaders and those involved in public life, women&rsquo;s rights activists, peacebuilders and journalists, who wish to leave the country.<br /><br />3. The Council must continue to demand full, safe and unimpeded humanitarian access: this must include access for women humanitarians and frontline workers throughout the country to carry out their lifesaving work.<br /><br />4. The Security Council must insist with all Afghan parties that the full, equal and meaningful participation of women in any new government is a non-negotiable condition of international engagement. </blockquote> <p>What does all this mean?  They are all fine words, but no real impact has been made on the care for women and girls as a result of this statement.  Ireland spent millions to win the seat in this talking shop, known as the United Nations Security Council, but the permanent members can literally veto anything they wish to defend their national interests, to uphold something in their foreign policy, or because of some issue of particular importance to their state.  The use of the veto by Russia and China has risen considerably since 2012, with the conflict in Syria accounting for the bulk of these.  Since 2011, Russia has cast 19 vetoes, 14 of which have been on Syria, two on the conflict in Ukraine, and one on Yemen.  Eight of the nine vetoes taken by China during the period have been about Syria and one has been about Venezuela.  The United States has cast three vetoes since 2011, all of them to do with Israel-Palestine issues.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Perhaps someone might tell me what is the purpose of having a seat on the United Nations Security Council.  Why even bother with this bloody talking shop?  I have pages upon pages of vetoes since 1946.  In all, there were 220 vetoes between 1946 and 2004.  From 2004 on they have stepped up the number of vetoes.  Why are we participating in this talking shop?  How has this talking shop helped the women of Afghanistan today who are prevented from what my granddaughter takes for granted?  How do we get women participating in education?  Can you even begin to imagine what it is like for a young girl who had three or four years' schooling not to have it now, or for a young woman who had been in university and maybe had one or two years' university education and suddenly it is gone?  Talk is cheap and at the end of the day I see no practical steps being proposed by Ireland in any way.  Our presidency of the United Nations Security Council is meaningless when you can have anything we say vetoed.  I would love a debate on this in the near future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#Q00200"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that is, that No. 19 be taken before No. 1.  I wish to introduce the Safe Access to Termination of Pregnancy Services Bill 2021.  While Sinn F&eacute;in is proud to be supporting this Bill, all credit for this Bill belongs to Together for Safety, a national campaign group for safe access zones that I have had the privilege to work with for the past number of years.  This is very much a cross-party initiative.  I acknowledge the strong support of the Labour Party, which will be seconding this proposal this morning, and the Civil Engagement Group, which has been consistently to the fore in engaging this issue.  I also acknowledge the support of Senator O'Reilly from the Green Party, Senator McGreehan from Fianna F&aacute;il and the father of the House, Senator David Norris, all of whom have co-signed this Bill.  I also want to acknowledge the contribution of Senators O'Loughlin and Fitzpatrick who joined us behind the Together for Safety banner at lunchtime today.  </p><p>Every week, there are gatherings of anti-choice protestors outside maternity hospitals.  The previous Government promised safe access zone legislation to ensure these protests would not take place outside these hospitals.  There are people monitoring, marching, praying and watching women and pregnant people going in and out of maternity hospitals.  Every day there are protestors outside the maternity hospital in my home city of Limerick.  I hope the Leader will agree with me that people have fundamental rights to privacy and dignity, especially so when they are visiting a hospital.  I ask Members to think about the impact of these protestors on people as they access healthcare throughout the State.  I ask them to listen to just two quotes from people who have encountered these protestors.  I am grateful to my colleagues in Together for Safety for supplying these quotes.  The first quote reads: </p> <blockquote> 	She asked me if I had an appointment across the road.  I presumed she was making small talk as she also had one so I said yes I did.  She told me she and her friends were praying that no babies were murdered in the hospital that day. </blockquote> <p>The second quote reads:</p> <blockquote> 	They were sprinkling holy water and saying prayers outside our hospital setting while there is women having miscarriages, or having stillbirths each week or carrying their babies out in white coffins. </blockquote> <p>These protests, which are happening outside many hospitals throughout the State, are attempting to intimidate and cause upset.  They are invading the privacy and bodily autonomy of women and pregnant people at a profoundly vulnerable and sensitive time.  People should not have to access healthcare like this.  We have been promised legislation for more than three years.  It was supposed to be passed in 2019 by then Minister for Health, Deputy Harris.  It was not.  What was particularly worrying was a reply I received from Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, to the effect that there was no need for such legislation.  I received that reply in May, and a similar reply was given to the <i>Irish Examiner </i>in August.  Thanks to Together for Safety, we have a Bill in the Seanad.  I appeal to Members from all parties to get behind this Bill and ensure a swift passage through this Chamber.  Women and pregnant people have been left waiting for far too long.  My party colleague, Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile, along with the leaders of the Labour Party and the Civil Engagement Group in this House will be writing to the Leader asking for an early cross-party slot for Private Members' time so that we can progress this Bill which is in line with a commitment given in the programme for Government.  I ask all Members on a cross-party basis to support this legislation and get this done.  Women should not have to continue to access healthcare in this fashion.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#R00100"><p>I want to be associated with the vote of sympathy at the start of business today on behalf of the Labour Party.</p><p>I want to raise two issues today.  The first is to seek a further debate on housing.  My colleague, Senator Moynihan, has continued to raise the housing crisis on an almost daily basis.  In asking for a debate I want to reference an interview I heard this morning on my local radio station, KFM, on my way to the House.  Professor Rory Hearne of Maynooth University was interviewed about an article he had written about NAMA the previous day in the <i>Irish Examiner</i>.  He called for an urgent review from a social and economic perspective of what NAMA does and how it contributes to the State from that point of view.  I join him in that call.  Some headlines from what he said refer to the fact that NAMA has &euro;1.2 billion in funding reserves and 577 ha of residential development land.  NAMA is currently selling 400 homes across the country.  Professor Hearne stated NAMA could be directed to provide 4,000 cost rental and 4,000 affordable homes a year.  Given the crisis, I totally agree with him.  We cannot ignore what NAMA is doing and could do.  Too many families in the State are continuing to cry out for housing and are in need of help.</p><p>The second item I want to raise today is rubbish and the continuing problem of illegal dumping in this country.  In March this year, with the support of the House, we passed Second Stage of the Local Government (Use of CCTV in the Prosecution of Offences) Bill.  In his reply to the debate, the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, welcomed the Bill and stated that the Government was working on Ireland's waste action plan for the circular economy, originally published in September 2020, which commits the Government to implementing a range of measures including tackling the problem of illegal dumping.  On the specific advice received from the Data Protection Commissioner regarding the Bill, which I hope the Bill will address, the Minister of State said that was currently under consideration by the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications.  He also stated that, for its part, the Government was in contact with the County and City Management Association, CCMA, on practical issues raised by the Data Protection Commissioner and those which our Bill also raised.</p><p>Unfortunately, as I am sure many Members of the House are aware, illegal dumping is as bad as ever.  My local authority, Kildare County Council, recently ran a one-day amnesty on mattresses and couches.  In one day alone, it collected 75 tonnes of couches and mattresses at an estimated cost of &euro;50,000.  I continue to receive calls on a weekly - sometimes daily - basis about this issue.  There is no doubt that we need solutions and the use of CCTV will help.  We estimated at the time of the debate on the Bill that &euro;90 million is being spent nationally on the clean-up of illegal dumping.  As I said before, we can imagine the number of community projects we could complete with this money.  I want to thank once again all of the Tidy Towns and community groups that do so much to combat this problem.  They are to be congratulated.  I would appreciate if the Leader could organise a debate on the circular economy Bill with the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications so that we can discuss, and finally come up with some solutions to, this massive problem for our State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#R00200"><p>Anyone who has ever had a problem with his or her sight or has had an injury to his or her eyes knows how frightening it can be when one's vision is compromised.  Unfortunately, recent figures from the National Treatment Purchase Fund, NTPF, make for depressing reading.  As of August 2021, 41,200 people were waiting for an outpatient eye care clinic appointment, with approximately 7,800 people waiting on an inpatient eye procedure.  Waiting lists, as we know, were high before Covid.  Unfortunately, Covid, to put it mildly, has not helped matters.  The Association of Optometrists Ireland says it can provide a solution to this problem.  There are 300 optometrists and 700 practitioners located across the country in state-of-the-art premises providing great care on a private basis to many of our citizens.  They are highly trained and have the necessary equipment to be able to address the problem that we currently have.  However, unfortunately in this country we do not seem to engage with such professionals to the same extent as many colleagues across other European countries do, and I believe this is a major mistake on the part of the HSE.  I recently mentioned the Sligo cataract scheme, which was a joint operation between the HSE and optometrists in the area who tackled the long waiting lists for cataracts.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It was a success.  I believe what is being proposed would reduce waiting times and would be a cost-effective service.  It would be very accessible and a better use of equipment and personnel than is currently the case.  Surely it is time we opened our eyes to the benefits of such a scheme.  I ask that the Minister be invited to the House so we can debate the merits of developing such a relationship.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#S00200"><p>I wish to express my grave reservations over our media and their coverage of the current state of Covid-19 in this country.  Ever since the beginning of our vaccination programme, I have been constant in warning against the dangers of dividing society along the lines of vaccination status and opposed any legislation that encouraged it.  Imagine my disappointment then when I tuned into "The Pat Kenny Show" to hear the host demonising 17-year-old children for going to the cinema and referring to them as "vaccinatable", as if a person's worth is based on whether we can jab them and include them as a figure on the vaccine uptake tally.</p> <p>Only a few weeks ago, we were all smugly patting ourselves on the back as articles about our great vaccine uptake flooded in.  The unspoken message was that we were great, selfless and educated, unlike other countries, whose people were acting like savages.  A fat lot of good that has done us as the Taoiseach has confirmed that our restrictions will once again live on past their supposed expiry date, while other countries with much lower vaccination uptakes are now more successful at suppressing the virus.</p> <p>It is clear then that the current tone reflecting the position that the only reason we are having a problem with the virus is due to the individuals choosing not to get vaccinated is not only deeply insulting, discriminatory and harmful, it is also incorrect.  This hunting around for some cohort of ordinary people to blame must stop and the responsibility for that lies with our media figures and outlets.</p> <p>It was not even two weeks ago when we stood in this Chamber and were told that the continuation of Covid certificates past 22 October was unlikely.  At this stage, I cannot even muster any surprise that while the rest of Europe is up and running, the Government maintains its policy of fear and stifling caution, and rushes to move the goalposts once again.  The message after today's announcement is very clear.  People who are not vaccinated can and will be treated like second-class citizens.  They will be dehumanised, labelled and cancelled unless they do what they are told.  "Follow the science" means, "Shut up and do as we say."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#S00300"><p>I will make one response to Senator Keogan.  Large sections of Europe have opened up but anyone who travels anywhere in Europe is required to show a vaccination certificate on entry to bars, restaurants and venues.  I know that from experience.  The Government is, therefore, in line with the rest of Europe in requiring the Covid certificate to be shown and that is the correct approach.</p> <p>I wish to raise two linked events that have happened in recent days.  The first was the rather amusing takedown of Nigel Farage by RT&Eacute;'s Claire Byrne, exposing his lack of knowledge of Irish history.  The fewer platforms that are given to his anti-immigrant, anti-European, populist nonsense, the better.  The second event happened last Friday when, in a much more serious vein, film director David Puttnam, speaking at a lecture in honour of the late Shirley Williams, spoke of the pig ignorance of some British politicians regarding Ireland, and in particular his fear of the way in which Rupert Murdoch has helped to remake Britain in his own malevolent image.  We should have concerns about both of those events.  There is an issue around the level of awareness of Irish history and politics among some in British society.  That sometimes stems from ignorance and is often because education of that history does not exist in Britain.  It is important for us, in our efforts in foreign affairs, to communicate effectively our history and politics.</p> <p>We should not rest on our laurels and simply assume that we do not have populists here.  Unfortunately, we have seen a deterioration in standards among some involved in journalism to the level of the red-top standards we see in the UK.  There is a real responsibility on those of us in politics and journalism to ensure that commentary is informed and, in particular, constructive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#T00100"><p>I want to raise an important matter, namely, the employment wage subsidy and the Rebuilding Ireland home loan.  Last week, in budget 2022, the Government extended the employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS, until 30 April 2022.  This is an extraordinary measure for extraordinary times.  It is further evidence of the Government's support for businesses to help them to get back on their feet as the pandemic recedes.  However, I am facing increasing unwillingness on the part of councils, the Department and the Housing Finance Agency to approve Rebuilding Ireland home loans for applicants in the EWSS.  One such case, with which I am dealing, concerns a hospitality worker who is now working more hours than he ever did.  He has received a promotion and a corresponding increase in wages but is unable to get approval for a Rebuilding Ireland home loan because his company is availing of the EWSS.  Another case of mine involves a childcare worker who is in very similar circumstances.  While I understand that the EWSS is to support businesses, its extension until April 2022 brings more uncertainty for those very people whom we are trying to support as a State, and whom we are trying to support in becoming the owner of their first home.  Therefore, I would appreciate it if the Deputy Leader could arrange a debate on this matter and if we, as a House, wrote to the Department asking it to address this issue as a matter of urgency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#T00200"><p>Even though I do not always agree with Senator Keogan, and did not agree with some of her comments today, I am glad she has recovered and is back in the Chamber.  It is good to see her back in full health again.  I join other Members in extending our sympathies to the family of the Conservative MP Sir David Amess and also to the families of Brendan Kennelly and M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi.</p> <p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that is, that No. 20 be taken before No. 1.  During my term in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, I produced a Bill on flooding along the River Shannon.  I am reintroducing it as the Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill 2021.  The scourge of flooding over many years, particularly along the basin of the River Shannon, has not been properly addressed by politicians in this country.  We all attend the meetings, listen to the complaints, put on the wellies and walk the land that has been destroyed but, in reality, the time has come to truly deal with this issue.  It can be dealt with in an environmentally friendly way, and this could take away a lot of the misery felt by people along the river.  Everybody knows the pattern of rainfall has changed dramatically in recent years.  The amount of rain that fell over two days years ago can now fall in two or three hours.  This, in itself, has brought new and untold problems to many families.  Businesses have been wiped out and farms have been destroyed.  People's mental health has suffered drastically over flooding along the River Shannon.  I hope that when the Bill is introduced, we will have a good debate on it and it will be supported.  It is time that we got the necessary legislation through and dealt with what has been a terrible scourge, affecting mainly people in rural areas.  I acknowledge, however, that flooding can hit many communities in Ireland nowadays.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#T00300"><p>Today I would like to talk about the further digitisation of Irish society.  Particularly in the past year and half, owing to Covid, society has become more cashless than ever before.  For example, I do not even carry a wallet anymore.  I have my ATM on my card.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John McGahon:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=JohnMcGahon&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I rarely carry cash any more and it is the same for many people across the board.  </p><p>When I talk about the digitisation of Irish society it is about how we make it more efficient.  I have not come up with exactly who we have to ask yet and will definitely take advice on that, but there are two ways in which we can make it more efficient.  First of all, when people have ATM cards on their mobile phones they should be able to withdraw money if they need it from an ATM cashpoint using their phones.  They are not able to do that unless they have a hard copy card.  This is something that would aid the digitisation of Irish society more.  The second point relates to IDs and we see it with Covid certificates.  In order to enter any place, whether it is a pub or restaurant, one needs to have a Covid certificate accompanied by ID to prove who one is.  Again, since so few people are carrying wallets any more, very few people keep physical ID on them, unless it is a driver's licence in their car and so on.  </p><p>The point is we should also look at introducing variable IDs on people's mobile phones so they can rock along and will be able to show straight up drivers' licence or passport in a digitised version that is accepted across the board.  To be fair, I would not expect to go somewhere and be allowed to show a photo of my passport or my ID.  We accept IDs in hard copies.  We should now be able to accept them in soft copies.  The Government should be able to introduce something that it has labelled and agreed and can be used right across the mark.  The same thing should be done with ATM cards where physical money can be withdrawn from an ATM bank machine with a mobile phone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#U00200"><p>I am not here to speak on the Order of Business but to second the safety access Bill.  I did not think I was down to speak.  I will happily speak-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#U00300"><p>We always like to hear the Senator's words of wisdom.  She is on the list I have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#U00400"><p>I have not got anything prepared.  I compliment Senator Gavan on his work with Together for Safety in Limerick in bringing in safe access zones legislation.  I will make the point that the women who are being intimidated as they go through maternity services include women who are coming out of the hospital having received terrible news or are going in to access abortion services.  Protests outside hospitals and GP surgeries also create a chill effect on GPs being able to operate their services.  Just 10% of GPs and just over half of maternity units in this country are operating abortion services.</p> <p>We still have a very long way to go in offering safe, legal and local access for women to services.  That is why it is so important this legislation is passed.  There are women now who are, let us say, living in a county like Sligo who have to undertake a 100-mile round trip to access a GP in another county and return after three days.  The repeal review is coming up.  We know that women still have to travel to the UK because their timelines are very short and because there are many grounds that are not covered under the legislation.  I ask and urge Members of the Government side of the House in particular, to advocate within the Government to try to fast track the safe access zone legislation. </p> <p>I saw in last week's budget something about which Senator Chambers has been very passionate and has spoken about a number of times in the House, that is, the funding for free contraception that came out of the committee work on the eighth amendment.  It is very important this legislation is passed because the chill effect on GPs and maternity services means women are not able to access the local services they need.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#U00500"><p>I second Senator Murphy's proposed amendment to the Order of Business.  In doing so, I compliment him on the great work he has put into that issue.  He has come up with a very common-sense approach to what is an ongoing issue.</p> <p>I will raise an issue that both the Leas-Chathaoirleach and the Cathaoirleach will possibly tell me before I am finished is more appropriate to a Commencement matter, but I received a message regarding it last night, we are in recess next week and it is important it is brought to the House.  My lobbying will be strengthened by something from the House.  A member of the Irish diaspora in Canada turned up at the airport to come home, unfortunately, for his father's funeral.  He was fully vaccinated and had his certificate stating same, but he was told Ireland did not recognise mixed vaccinations and he was sent away to get a test.  He had to go home and come back the next day.  He just made the funeral by a matter of hours but could equally have missed it.  </p> <p>This is a vitally important issue.  I will make personal representations to the Minister for Foreign Affairs and the Minister for Health, or whoever is responsible for areas outside the EU where its digital Covid-19 certificate does not apply, particularly for people of Irish origin and Irish citizens.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2464"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2464&amp;amp;pid=PaulDaly&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some of those people got mixed vaccinations, but it is important that we recognise that they are vaccinated.  They have the certification that states they are vaccinated.  The fact that it may have involved the use of two different vaccines may be a bonus, as many people would tell us.  Apparently, however, the man to whom I refer was told that the authorities in Ireland are not recognising mixed vaccinations.  He was sent home to get a test and then barely made it back to his father&rsquo;s funeral by the skin of his teeth.  </p><p>It may well have been more appropriate for me to address the Minister directly about this issue.  As we are in recess next week, I would appreciate if the Leader and the House would strengthen my case with the Minister in this regard by adding their voices in support of the necessity of recognising the vaccination status of Irish and non-Irish residents abroad.  If these people are vaccinated, they are vaccinated, and this issue must be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#V00200"><p>I also extend my condolences to the family of David Amess.  I felt emotional reading all the comments on Twitter.  Even after this man's death, there continued to be negative comments.  It is shocking to see that someone has no peace even in death.  I do not want to turn this into being about us as politicians, but Senator Moynihan spoke about a chill effect in her contribution and this event is having a chilling effect on politics.  One does feel a little exposed standing up to speak about something or, indeed, putting oneself forward to participate in politics.  I hope people feel that there is a sense of solidarity across the Chamber and across the two islands.</p> <p>I commend Senator Gavan for the proposed Bill on safe access zones and Senator Moynihan as well.  Those on the Government side of the House support the Bill as well and it is good to see that we have that cross-party support for an issue of this importance.  Safe access zones should have been a part of the original legislation in 2018, but we are where we are.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, has acted on this issue.  He told me that I could raise the issue and that Government legislation is being drafted.  This is positive news from both sides of the House and I look forward to further debate on the issue.  This year's budget contains much feminist healthcare and that is remarkable compared with previous budgets.  I refer to the provision of free contraception and menopause centres being established across the country.  All I can say is "let us have more of that".  I am delighted that we can progress some of these issues, but safe access zones must now be a priority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#V00300"><p>Everybody from my generation will be familiar with this beautiful poem written by M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi, who sadly passed away at the weekend:</p> <blockquote> 	Le coinnle na n-aingeal t&aacute; an sp&eacute;ir amuigh breactha,<br /><br />T&aacute; fiacail an tseaca sa ghaoith on gcnoc,<br /><br />Adaigh an tine is t&eacute;ir chun an leapan,<br /><br />Lu&iacute;fidh Mac D&eacute; ins an tigh seo anocht. </blockquote> <p>She was one of the outstanding poets writing in Irish and she left a fantastic legacy.  M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi was an extraordinary woman.  The daughter of Se&aacute;n MacEntee, she was educated in the Sorbonne and then became a diplomat.  M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi was the wife of Conor Cruise O'Brien, and what a contrast there must have been there and what great debates they must have had.  </p><p>It is extraordinary that on the same day she died we lost our great Kerry poet and the most beautiful voice of Brendan Kennelly.  I did not know M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi personally, but I am privileged to say that Brendan Kennelly was a great friend of mine.  I knew him from home.  One of the great advantages of becoming a Senator was that I was able to meet him fairly regularly here in my early years in town.  We generally met on Duke Street for a chat.  In later years that was over coffee, where we would be pretending that it was much better for us than whiskey.  He still retained a wonderful charm and facility for the English language.  He was a poet of the people.  He and John B. Keane, my other neighbour, had great roguery in them.</p><p>I will finish with a story.  I do not know which one of them it is about, but the two of them met one time and they were discussing their literary legacies.  One asked the other what he would like to be remembered as.  By the way, they were also nice footballers in their day.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ned O'Sullivan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2233"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2233&amp;amp;pid=NedOSullivan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The other said he would like to be remembered as the man who scored the winning point in the final of the north Kerry championship.  That simplicity and that genius were in both of them.  We have lost two wonderful voices.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a n-anamacha.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#W00200"><p>Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh anam Brendan Kennelly, and thank you, Senator O'Sullivan, for sharing that story.  Being from Kerry, I know the importance of scoring the winning point in the north Kerry championship.  In north Kerry, it is more important than scoring the winning point in an all-Ireland final for Kerry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#W00300"><p>I thank Senator O'Sullivan.  That is a hard one to follow.</p> <p>I wish to raise Circular 0050/2021 on teacher substitution.  We need to take the word of principals on this issue.  There has been a chronic crisis regarding substitute teachers, or a chronic shortage of them, over the past few years, not just as a result of the pandemic.  I have spoken to principals about this, and the panel system is a really good initiative but is effective only for well-flagged and planned absences.  In Dublin West, the substitutes are booked up until January 2022, I am told, and it is impossible to find a substitute teacher at short notice for a day or two.  Most schools I spoke to said their own lists of subs had been exhausted and that the people on them are in longer term contracts with schools to cover absences.  The schools are not getting any response from the text-a-sub service or the national sub service.  The demand for substitution is not diminishing.  To take just one 32-classroom school in my area, last week eight teachers were absent, with no teachers coming from the panel.  The school managed to get three subs and the principal lost a weekend trying to find replacements.  At another school, there were 17 teacher absences.  The school was able to secure two substitutes, neither through the panel.  Another school has needed a sub on 19 occasions.  Schools are pulling subs from everywhere they possibly can, whether through special education teachers, SNAs, early years educators or the principals themselves.  It is not just about the special education teachers; it is about schools just trying to stay open.  That is not sustainable and not good for continuous professional development.</p> <p>I think the teachers are quite upset about this because the Department is aware of the issue and these schools fight for special education day in and day out and for resources for their schools.  They would not do anything to compromise special education.  They are in this position because they have no choice at the moment.  I welcome what has been said about looking at the teacher supply action plan and teacher colleges, but we need a realistic and an empathetic plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#W00400"><p>I support Senator Murphy's comments on the River Shannon, which traverses both our counties.</p> <p>The Residential Tenancies Board, RTB, was established under the Residential Tenancies Act 2004 to act as a service to mediate and provide dispute resolution between landlords and tenants.  The board offers a free mediation service, not only for landlords and tenants but also to third parties directly affected by an issue - for example, an overhanging tree from a neighbour's property affecting one's own.  This could be blocking daylight, shedding leaves, blocking gutters or destroying patios or gardens.  The mediation service for third parties is not known by most homeowners and is poorly promoted through the RTB website.  Homeowners email and contact their local councillors regularly, some even going as far as court in order to deal with issues, not just overhanging trees but, indeed, more extreme problems such as harassment from neighbours.  The latter is something my wife and I suffered.  We had to go to court, where we found that the RTB was not dealing with the issue.  The RTB essentially has no power or does not use it and is considered not an option by many, whether due to lack of funding or lack of resources.  If the RTB were to reform its website to ensure it is clear that these mediation services are being offered, not only to landlords and tenants but also to those who feel their property is being adversely affected by a neighbour, people would have a body they could contact and work with on an issue.  Most people living in semi-detached houses have experienced an issue with a neighbour in their life, whether it be overhanging trees or some more sinister problems.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MichealCarrigy&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There must be an adequate organisation to work with property owners on their behalf to resolve a matter they may have with neighbours.  The RTB is established but it must use its power to support property owners and prevent such matters going to court and costing many homeowners, landlords and renters money they may not have.  The RTB must ensure that its website and mediation services are clear, accessible and understandable for all people.  More funding may be required from the Government to improve these services and act as a support for those homeowners, landlords and renters experiencing issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#X00200"><p>I welcome the announcement by the Taoiseach earlier today on the continued use of digital Covid certificates.  It is something I raised in the Chamber last week.  I did so because I felt there was an opportunity to protect businesses and people.  It is good that the announcement was made today, and it is significant because a number of measures would not have been possible today if we did not continue using digital Covid certificates.  Those measures include unlimited numbers of people being allowed to attend weddings and the reopening of nightclubs.  There will now be talk about Christmas parties for the first time in two years.  That will only be possible because digital Covid certificates will remain in place.</p> <p>Speaking to those in the industry, I know this reassures people who have been concerned about going into environments like pubs and caf&eacute;s.  They will now feel protected.  It is significant that digital Covid certificates have been protected.  The arguments used by people for this being the wrong approach were used a number of months ago, when the certificates were introduced, but the sky has not fallen in.  In fact, people have found them quite easy to use.  I welcome that the process is being continued until the end of the year.</p> <p>On Friday, 22 October, it will be International Stuttering Awareness Day.  In Ireland, we have a stuttering awareness and mental well-being campaign starting today.  Three people - Mr. Michael Ryan in Templemore, Mr. Jamie Gogan and Mr. Michael O'Shea - started that campaign.  They met the Lord Mayor of Dublin this afternoon and will be in Buswell's Hotel tomorrow for a number of hours.  I encourage Senators to meet them.  They will be at the hotel from 10 a.m. until 1 p.m.  They are trying to raise awareness in Ireland about stuttering and stammering.  They want to encourage people to be who they want to be.  It is an opportunity for us to support them.  New US President Joe Biden suffered from a stutter.  There is a real encouragement to build awareness of the matter.  I ask Members if they are available tomorrow between 10 a.m. and 1 p.m. to meet those three guys.  They are very impressive people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#X00300"><p>Codail, a laoich dar thugas gr&aacute;,</p> <blockquote> 	codail go s&aacute;mh i m'bh&aacute;nbhaclainn,<br /><br />tusa mo rogha fear F&aacute;il,<br /><br />thatr r&iacute; na bhFiann is a ch&oacute;ir fairis -<br /><br />Codail, codail, a ch&uacute;l na l&uacute;b,<br /><br />le faobhar na ho&iacute;che, codail, a r&uacute;n. </blockquote> <p>As Senator Ned O'Sullivan said, M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi - and Brendan Kennelly - represented the best of our tradition, writing and communicating as they did in our two main spoken languages.  The only contact I had with M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi was when seeking her permission to use the poem that Senator O'Sullivan recited on a Christmas card I sent from this House a number of years ago.  They really were two very impressive people.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh siad.</p><p>There was a much more untimely, tragic and horrifying death in Britain that we have all recalled.  Sir David Amess had great concern for the unborn, the elderly, those at risk of fuel poverty and the animal kingdom.  He was a model of humanity and consistency in a way that is exemplary for many of his contemporaries.  If he knew our circumstances, he would have reflected on how the legislation proposed by Sinn F&eacute;in and others here today is not necessary.  As the Garda Commissioner, Drew Harris, has stated, we have the laws we need to deal with any breaches of public order if such events were to take place.  We have our constitutional protection of that delicate but important thing that is freedom of expression and the right of people to assemble.  We have the reality that we do not have abortion clinics in Ireland and that abortions take place in relative anonymity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Those who meet to give witness to the dignity of all human life and to the possibility of positive alternatives, we are saying to do this in a way that is very respectful.  We need to be careful about trying to pretend that there is no counter narrative on abortion.  There is and there always will be.  It is important that we hear all voices in society and dialogue with each other respectfully.  I believe this is what Sir David Amess would have believed in.  I know many of his mutual friends, who are understandably heartbroken.  They recall a man who was exemplary in his respect for others and in the way he made his point in politics.  It is something that we all, myself included, should to try to imitate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#Y00200"><p>I want to mention the platform, Speak Out, that was launched this week by the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Harris.  Speak Out is an anonymous online platform that allows students and staff to report incidents of sexual harassment, sexual assault, rape, bullying, cyberbullying and everything in between.  It is to operate across our third level institutions.  It must be a welcome thing.  It is wonderful that there is an anonymous online platform that makes it as easy as possible for people to report these activities so they can be dealt with at whatever level is appropriate.</p> <p>I wonder, in the circumstances, if we should be looking at advancing this tool into secondary schools also.  It is not as if we do not know that this kind of behaviour is happening also at second level.  There is an opportunity for a similar anonymous online platform to be available to secondary school students, teachers in secondary schools, and parents of students in secondary schools.  We know this is happening, and we mention these issues a lot in this House.  They have come to the fore particularly in recent years and such behaviour causes enormous damage to the victims.</p> <p>Sometimes, we expect people to come forward and do what we see many brave victims or survivors of this kind of behaviour do, which is to come forth and stand in the media, sometimes in the spotlight of television cameras, and say what happened to them, but not everybody can do that.  It is actually an exceedingly difficult thing to do.  The idea of an anonymous online platform is welcome because it allows people who perhaps do not have the wherewithal to stand in the glare of a camera, or the media or in the public eye to say these things.  It allows them still to report it and to register what has happened to them, and still to put it into the hands of the officials, and hopefully the mechanism to monitor what is happening and take steps to deal with that.</p> <p>I welcome Speak Out.  It is an excellent initiative and I congratulate the Minister, Deputy Harris, for it.  I hope we could possibly extend it into other areas of education, particularly into second level education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#Y00300"><p>I thank the Senators.  I now invite the Deputy Leader to respond on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#Y00400"><p>I first propose, as suggested by An Cathaoirleach, that we hold one minute of silence in respect for David Amess.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.79" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#Y00500">Minute's Silence for Sir David Amess</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.80" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Members rose.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#Y00700"><p>Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.82" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#Y00800">Order of Business (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#Y00900"><p>Senator Fiona O'Loughlin started the Order of Business today and paid her respects to M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi, Brendan Kennelly and Sir David Amess.  A number of colleagues also paid respects to M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi and Brendan Kennelly.  Senators Mullen and O'Sullivan recited very beautifully some poetry for all of us, which was a pleasure to listen to.  It is not something I would be capable of doing and I am always very impressed when people recite such things.</p> <p>Senator O'Loughlin raised a very important issue around the level of sentencing that is being handed down for certain crimes, and particularly for domestic violence crimes.  I do believe that three months seems extremely lenient, but we cannot really say much more than that without having the full knowledge of all factors.  We do need to send a certain message on sentencing, across the board.</p> <p>The Senator also raised the important issue of derelict sites in Newbridge and the need to bring those back into use.  This would be a huge help in increasing our housing stock.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lisa Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2449"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2449&amp;amp;pid=LisaChambers&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Conway spoke about the reopening of Ireland, which was announced earlier, and the need to proceed with caution.  He wished the businesses that will reopen their doors for the first time in 19 months this Friday well and I concur with those remarks.  </p><p>He also referred to the ambulance service and the unusual circumstance where an ambulance was sent from Galway to service an incident in Kilkee and the requirement to have a debate in this House on the National Ambulance Service, which has also been requested by other Members.  It is something that we will seek to have in the near future.</p><p>Senator Craughwell raised the issue of the UN Security Council and said that words are just words.  I agree with him.  The UN Security Council has the potential to do great good but the veto limits its work, of which there is no doubt.  A good example of where it did fine work was in response to the Ebola crisis when it passed a resolution to bring people together but one does not often find issues that unite everybody.  The Senator eloquently pointed out the deficiencies in that.  It is important that we use our time and our seat on the council to try to effect some good. </p><p>The Senator correctly pointed out the worsening condition for the rights of women and young girls in Afghanistan.  The Taliban, just two days ago, stated that they would permit women to work where they were needed and that it would take time to get women and girls back to school.  I believe we will be waiting a long time and that words are not going to encourage the Taliban to do anything differently this time around.  We certainly need to see action on that issue.</p><p>Senator Gavan proposed an amendment to the Order of Business regarding No. 19, which I will accept.  This is the Safe Access to Termination of Pregnancy Services Bill 2021, which was put together for safety reasons, introduced by the Senator, and seconded by Senator Moynihan.  I agree with the Senators on the need to progress this legislation and I have been told by the Minister, Deputy Donnelly, that his Department is also currently drafting legislation.  We will all agree that it does not matter which Bill does this work as long as it gets done.  Whichever happens more quickly is the best option.  This is a commitment in the programme for Government.  There was an expectation that the Bill would have advanced further when the Minister entered office but he has taken a great deal of advice on board, some of which is to say that it is not needed.  He is clear in his commitment to get the legislation over the line.  That is positive if the endgame is to get this over the line regardless of which way it happens. It is important that there are cross-party initiatives, which show that we have come a long way as a country on this front.</p><p>I take on board the remarks of Senator Mullen that there is a significant and different view out there.  I respect this and we have had many debates, particularly at the Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution on this issue.  There are different views on this but we respect each other&rsquo;s views.  I understand the complexities in balancing free speech and the freedom to demonstrate and protest peacefully.  That is a very delicate balancing act and I agree that we need to be careful on that front.  I have no doubt that the Minister will strike the right balance in that regard.</p><p>Senator Wall sought a housing debate, in particular, on the National Asset Management Agency, NAMA, being potentially a vehicle through which, in his own figures, 4,000 cost rental and 4,000 affordable houses could be provided.  Certainly, if there is any other way of delivering more housing more quickly, we should look at it.  </p><p>He also raised an interesting amnesty that Kildare County Council have put in place to take mattresses and sofas on a given day and on the level of uptake there was on that offer.  The issue of illegal dumping is prevalent and widespread in the country.</p><p>Senator Gallagher raised the issue of the ongoing significant waiting lists for eye procedures, both inpatient and outpatient.  The colossal waiting list for outpatient appointments of more than 41,000 is a scourge on the health system and on those people waiting for those procedures.  I listened to Tony Canavan on the radio this morning where he said that the term &ldquo;elective surgery&rdquo; does not cover what it means to be on a waiting list.  It may be elective but that does not mean that it is not urgent, necessary, or that the person is not living in considerable pain and suffering.  It is important that we get those waiting lists down.  In excess of &euro;200 million was allocated in the budget specifically to deal with reducing those waiting lists across the board.</p><p>Senator Keogan raised the issue of media coverage and vaccines and she may have a slightly different view on vaccines.  We need to encourage as many people as possible to take up the vaccines to try to protect everybody but not everybody will avail of that, as we know from the figures.</p><p>Senator Malcolm Byrne raised an issue and gave two examples.  One was of Claire Byrne and Nigel Farage and the highlighting of the lack of knowledge of Irish history and the importance that it plays in politics to know the history of the country that one is speaking about.  He also referred to David Puttnam who suggested that the knowledge of Irish history and politics among members of parliament in the UK was not as good as it could be.  He suggested that it was something that we should take the initiative on on this side of the water to try to inform people a little better, and that we would all be the better for it, if I can put it that way.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lisa Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2449"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2449&amp;amp;pid=LisaChambers&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Cummins raised a very important issue that I was not aware of.  He mentioned a blockage facing people accessing the Rebuilding Ireland home loan while benefiting from the employment wage subsidy scheme.  I will certainly ask the Minister to take a look at that.  We will be seeking a debate on housing in the future in order to get an update on the progress of the Housing for All plan.  </p><p>Senator Murphy proposed an amendment to the Order of Business relating to No. 20, the flooding Bill, which I will be accepting.  I commend Senator Murphy.  He has been working on this issue for a number of years now.  In the last term, he was a really strong advocate for communities that face flooding every year.  It is very distressing for families to watch their homes flood again and again.  They cannot get insurance and it is really stressful.  If we can bring legislation that would help people before the House, that is exactly what we should be doing.  I look forward to that debate when it comes before the House.</p><p>Senator McGahon raised the issue of the digitisation of Irish society.  He raised two issues he feels need to be addressed but was looking for advice not only from myself, but from the House, as to how best to progress some ideas he has.  One of these ideas was that people should be able to withdraw cash using an ATM card loaded on their phones.  That is a clever suggestion and probably the next step given that we have become so used to using our phones and not carrying a wallet, purse or anything of that nature.  He also spoke about carrying hard copy identification and suggested that there should be a digital way to carry ID.  That is again clever and progressive and something we should be looking at.  It probably depends on the type of ID he is seeking to digitise.  He would need to talk to different Departments but it is certainly a conversation we should be having.  It is logical and it makes sense.</p><p>Senator Moynihan seconded the amendment proposed by Senator Gavan and also spoke about a chilling effect on GPs arising from those protests and demonstrations.  Only 10% of GPs are providing these services and that is a very low figure.  It is something we need to address.  I am very keenly aware of a deficiency in many parts of rural Ireland.  It is something we need to address.  These services must be accessible to people without having to travel great distances.  Otherwise, what is the point?  We need to look at that.  GPs have told us that they are worried about providing the services.  In Roscommon, for example, there is only one GP providing them and she regularly has to pass demonstrations to get into her workplace.  That is really not acceptable but all credit to her for continuing her work regardless of that extra stress.</p><p>Senator Paul Daly raised an issue regarding mixed vaccinations.  I have had some issues helping people to get access.  People who get one dose of vaccine administered in Ireland and another in the UK get their certificate where they receive the second vaccination.  That is also a difficulty.  I hope we will be a bit more open-minded about what we accept.  We have to take care of our own citizens trying to get back into the country.  It was really only by luck that the individual the Senator mentioned made it back for his father's funeral.  It would have been unthinkable if he had not.</p><p>Senator Pauline O'Reilly referenced the issue of safe access zones.  I know the Senator has been a very passionate advocate for this legislation and very supportive of the Together for Safety campaign.  She also referenced the strong commitment to women's health in the budget.  That did not happen by chance.  There was a great push for those changes in the last year, particularly from female Members of the Oireachtas.  Now that we are increasing in number, albeit at a slower pace than we would like, we are finding our collective voice and we are working better together on those acute issues that are specific to women.  She is right; between the roll-out of several menopause clinics across the country, free contraception for young girls and women, increased access to obstetrics and gynaecology and funding for the National Maternity Hospital, in excess of &euro;30 million was allocated to women's health initiatives in this budget alone.  That has never happened before.  Between the advocacy of a number of female parliamentarians in the Oireachtas and the open-door policy of the Minister, who actually understands the need to invest in women's health, we have had a good team advocating for these issues across the board and we are now seeing the fruits of that advocacy, which is great.</p><p>Senator O'Sullivan very beautifully recited one of M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi's lovely poems.  He paid great credit both to her and to Brendan Kennelly.</p><p>Senator Currie referenced the ongoing issue of the lack of substitute teachers for schools across the country.  It is a problem and it is widespread.  We need to find a better way of putting together panels and making sure that schools have access to substitute teachers because the nature of the job is that they are required at the last minute.  Their use is not planned far in advance, or at least not for all absentees.  In my own county of Mayo, I know there is a problem in getting supply teachers.</p><p>Senator Carrigy raised an issue regarding the Residential Tenancies Board, RTB.  We have all dealt with issues, at some stage or another, we thought the RTB would be able to assist with only to find it did not have the powers or scope to do so.  It is important that we help property owners.  Access to the courts is fine but it can be quite an expensive route to take and is not open to everybody because of the cost involved or the fear that one will not be able to afford it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lisa Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2449"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2449&amp;amp;pid=LisaChambers&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=19"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We all should be able to have our rights vindicated and protected and have our property protected, so the need for the RTB to step up in that regard is certainly required.  Perhaps a Commencement matter to the relevant Minister might start the ball rolling on that discussion.</p><p>Senator Ahearn raised the issue of the digital Covid certificate and welcomed that they would be extended into February of next year and possibly beyond that.  It was one thing that, at the outset, we required digital Covid certificates when we had not offered everybody a vaccine and those who had not been offered one were the very ones who were working in hospitality, so you could work in hospitality unvaccinated but you not participate, which I had a difficult with because I thought it was not the right call, whereas now everybody has been offered a vaccine, so if you have not taken one through choice, and not because you cannot, because some people cannot, then there should be no apology made for requesting a vaccine cert to make sure everybody is kept as safe as possible.  It is the right balance to strike in terms of protecting everybody's rights and ensuring businesses can stay open and people can socialise safely.  The Senator rightly pointed out we would not see the numbers lifting for weddings and nightclubs opening if that system was not in place and were it not for the high levels of vaccination we have, thankfully, but we still have a way to go on that.</p><p>Senator Ahearn said 22 October is International Stuttering Awareness Day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB00200"><p>That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB00300"><p>The Senator said that the representatives of the organisation will be in Buswells Hotel tomorrow from 10 a.m. until 1 p.m. for anyone who is available to pop along to show their support.  It is very important for us to support those awareness campaigns.</p> <p>Senator Mullen paid tribute to M&aacute;ire Mhac an tSaoi and Brendan Kennelly.  I also responded to the issues the Senator raised about the Bill proposed by Senator Gavan.</p> <p>Senator Ward finished off the Order of Business by drawing attention to the Speak Out facility that has been launched by the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, which allows for the online, anonymous reporting of sexual assault, harassment and other violence against people in third level institutions.  I will be honest and say that I am not fully up to speed on all of details of how that would work, but it might be welcome to have the Minister in at some stage to talk to us about that, how it would work in terms of anonymous reporting, and the procedures to follow up on that.  It is a welcome step, and anything we can do to make our campuses a safer place for everybody, both men and women, is very welcome.  Certainly, if it works in those settings, there is no reason it could not be extended across the board.  It is a very welcome initiative and I look forward to hearing more about it from the Minister.  That concludes the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB00400"><p>Senator Paul Gavan has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 19 be taken before No. 1."  The Deputy Leader has indicated she is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>Senator Eugene Murphy has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 20 be taken before No. 1."  Senator Paul Daly has seconded the amendment.  The Deputy Leader has indicated she is willing to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.90" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.91" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB00900">Safe Access to Termination of Pregnancy Services Bill 2021: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB01000"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to protect the free and unencumbered access to facilities providing legal termination of pregnancy services; protect individuals providing or facilitating legal termination of pregnancy services from harassment; and to provide for matters connected therewith. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.93" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB01200"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB01300"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB01400"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.97" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 26 October 2021.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.98" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB01500">Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) Bill 2021: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB01600"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to reduce restrictions on the power of the Electricity Supply Board to carry out works concerning the levels on the Shannon Lakes (Lough Derg, Lough Ree and Lough Allen), for this purpose to amend the Electricity (Supply) (Amendment) (No. 2) Act 1934; and to provide for related matters. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.100" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB01800"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB01900"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101900002#BB02000"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.104" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 26 October 2021.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-19a.105" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.43 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>