<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the provision of a primary care centre in Douglas, Cork.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Michelle Mulherin of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on the progress by Mayo County Council in implementing Government schemes to bring vacant homes back into use.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on the powers of An Bord Plean&aacute;la to grant planning permission that may be contrary to city or county development plans.</blockquote><p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Buttimer and Mulherin and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Boyhan on the ground that it requires the Minister to provide an interpretation of the law.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600002#A00350">Primary Care Centres Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600002#A00400"><p>I welcome Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, and thank him for his courtesy in attending the House.  The issue before us is a very important one concerning the provision of a primary care centre in Douglas.  Given the importance we, as a Government, place on primary care in our health policy, I hope the Government will prioritise the location of a primary care centre in Douglas.  There are many suitable locations in this area and the success of other such centres, such as in Carrigaline and in other parts of the city, underscores the importance and need for a primary care centre in Douglas.  We have had a number of briefings with the HSE, which highlighted its role in primary care.  It is an opportune time to deliver a primary care centre in Douglas with, I might add, a daycare centre for the elderly, but that is a different matter.</p>  <p>A national needs assessment was conducted and identified the need for primary care centres in many parts of the city but, in particular, Bishopstown, Togher and Douglas.  I hope that today we will get a clear indication from the HSE and the Government that this matter is a priority and that this will be the beginning of the journey to having a primary care centre located in Douglas.  As the Minister of State, the Cathaoirleach, Members of the House and those watching the proceedings at home know, we are now living in an expanded Cork city council area, and Douglas has become part of Cork city.  This is, therefore, an opportune time to promote the establishment of a primary care centre in Douglas.  Douglas is a centre of population which is crying out for the location of a primary care centre.  Confusion surrounds the plans and proposals for the primary care centre but we now have an opportunity to bring clarity and certainty and to remove the confusion around the primary care centre.</p>  <p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, for being here and I commend him on the work he is doing in his brief.  He is a very progressive and proactive Minister of State.  I hope that today we will see the beginning of a new chapter and a good news story for Douglas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600002#A00500"><p>I thank Senator Buttimer for his kind words.  As the Senator may be aware, the HSE has responsibility for the provision of primary care centres and other primary care facilities.  I am happy to update Senator Buttimer on work being undertaken on the potential provision of a primary care centre in Douglas.</p>  <p>I understand previous efforts by the HSE to secure a primary care centre in the area have proved unsuccessful because of the high cost of suitable sites for developers.  However, I am pleased to be able to advise the Senator that Douglas has been included in a recent advertisement by the HSE seeking expressions of interest from developers for the next tranche of 47 centres to be delivered under the operational lease model.  This advertisement was published on 3 May and interested parties had up to the 31 May to make submissions.  I understand that all bids have now been submitted to HSE estates centrally and that they are currently being compiled.  The bids will issue shortly from estates central office for local assessment by the relevant estates offices in conjunction with local primary care staff.</p>  <p>There are a number of distinct phases to be gone through under the operational lease model before a centre can be delivered.  After the HSE selects the preferred bidder based on submissions received, a letter of intent issues to that bidder who must then satisfy a number of requirements.  Among other things, the bidder must enter into an agreement with GPs to co-locate at the site; provide evidence of ownership or interest in the site; obtain planning permission; and provide evidence that financing for the development is in place.  Once these conditions have been satisfied, the HSE signs an agreement for lease with the relevant developer.  The HSE will lease the accommodation for the facility which is built to the HSE's specification.</p>  <p>In the case of Douglas, subject to bids to an acceptable level being submitted, the HSE will issue a letter of intent and the process I have just outlined will begin.  However, it is important to note that issues can arise during this process, and there is a risk that delivery of a given centre may not be able to proceed for any one of a number of reasons - for example, where planning may be refused or where GPs do not indicate an interest in co-locating.</p> <p> The HSE has informed me that all other options for developing a primary care centre in Douglas have been explored but that, regrettably, nothing suitable has been identified and the recent advertisement for expressions of interest is the best way forward.  I am advised that, with the exception of community nurses and the home support office, there is no accommodation for other community services in Douglas and that clients must travel to Cork city centre or the nearby Blackrock Hall primary care centre.  As a result, the case for developing a centre in Douglas is clear and fully accepted.  It would serve a population of approximately 20,000 people and offer services at a single site.  This means that people would no longer have to travel to different places for different services, which would save considerable time and expense.  Such a centre would undoubtedly enhance and expand capacity in the community sector in Douglas, enabling us to deliver high-quality, integrated care to people in the locality and on the vision for a reformed health service set out under Sl&aacute;intecare, namely, "the right care, in the right place, at the right time".  It is for these reasons that I very much hope that the recent expression of interest for Douglas will generate a positive response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600003#B00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State's comments and the expression of interest.  As he noted, there is now a clear need for a primary centre to be located in Douglas, where there is no accommodation for other community services.  I hope the matter will be progressed today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600003#B00300"><p>As I outlined, a process is under way.  At national level, it is clear that the future direction of primary care services will be guided by Sl&aacute;intecare.  We are moving in the right direction by investing in primary care infrastructure, while the expansion of primary care staffing and services was prioritised in the previous Estimates process and the HSE's national service planning.  Overall funding for primary care was increased by more than &euro;50 million, which will enable a range of measures to be advanced, including recruitment of additional nursing and therapy staff.  I am sure the city and county of Cork will benefit appropriately as these staff are recruited.</p>  <p>Although concerns will always be raised about specific locations, we must not lose sight of the fact that we continue to make good progress in the development and roll-out of primary care centres.  There are now 127 such centres, 18 of which became operational in 2018.  While I appreciate the Senator's interest in Douglas, I am sure he will be happy to hear that 12 of the operational facilities are in County Cork, as are three of the nine centres expected to open this year, at Carrigtwohill, Bantry and Newmarket.  It is also expected that the Beara and Clonakilty centres will become operational in 2020, while a further eight locations are at various stages of planning.</p>  <p>I reiterate that I hope the latest development round will be successful in attracting developer interest to enable Douglas to join the list.  I thank the Senator for putting focus on the matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600003#B00400">Vacant Properties</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600003#B00500"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise this important matter and the Minister for his attendance.  As the Minister will be aware, a considerable number of people throughout County Mayo are seeking suitable housing, both social and private.  From my weekly clinics dealing with people on many housing matters and having had the opportunity to canvass many parts of the county, I know it is an important issue for many people.  Having travelled throughout the county, however, I can safely say there are far too many empty houses in towns, villages and rural areas.  On the main streets and in the older parts of some such towns and villages, there are many empty houses, which, I am sure the Minister will agree, is a depressing sight.  Irrespective of how many social houses are built or how much private house building is encouraged - I welcome the increase in this regard - we cannot ignore empty houses.  Something must be done because they will not go away and we do not want them to fall down.</p>  <p>Many such houses have been empty for years.  Vacancy is not a recent development.  I have observed several examples.  Nothing seems to be happening, which is why I asked the Minister to come before the House.  Many people look around their towns, villages and the rural areas in which they reside and ask why a particular house has been empty for five, ten or 15 years.  It is far too common.  I say this notwithstanding the repair-and-lease scheme, the buy-and-renew scheme and all the other initiatives the Minister and his predecessor have put in place to address the issue.  It is clear that they have not had the impact we would have liked.  In the older parts of a town, there could be a street where one or two elderly people could die and their houses could then be closed up.  Similarly, houses in some estates may be caught up with banks or there may be some other reason they are empty.  Whatever the reason, the matter should be explored further.  Notwithstanding the schemes and the fact that they are advertised by Mayo County Council, there does not seem to be much interest in or take-up of them, which begs the question as to how attractive it is to be a landlord.  From conversations with people, I suggest they do not want the hassle or cost.  It is not as lucrative as populist media might like to indicate.  It is a big responsibility for people who take it seriously and many do not want the hassle.</p>  <p>I acknowledge that Mayo County Council has beefed up its housing section and that despite being busy, it does good work.  It has a vacant homes officer and seems to have all the ingredients to address the issue.  I would like it to be more proactive, however, in order that there can be results on the ground in respect of the eyesore houses that could be used.  They are a valuable resource and using them as part of the liveable housing stock should be a priority.  The council needs to assign a technician to go door to door and establish why a house is empty, who owns it and what can be done to bring it back into use.  There have to be boots on the ground.  Standing back in an office will not sort out the problem.  Will the Minister consider all the issues I have raised?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600003#B00600"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue and giving me an opportunity to set out the extensive range of measures the Government has introduced to allow for the reactivation of long-term vacant residential dwellings into the liveable housing stock.</p><p>An overarching action within Pillar 5 of Rebuilding Ireland is a commitment to develop a national vacant housing reuse strategy, which I published in July 2018.  The strategy strives to provide a targeted, effective and co-ordinated approach to identifying and tackling vacancy throughout Ireland.  My Department and local authorities have been proactive in dealing with vacant properties with all local authorities, having prepared vacant home action plans.  In addition, a number of schemes are available to incentivise reactivating appropriate dwellings into the liveable housing stock.</p><p>We continually examine new ways of reducing the number of vacant residential dwellings.  For example, when the initial national roll-out of the innovative repair-and-lease scheme did not yield the results hoped for, we examined it and made improvements to its terms to make it more desirable to those who wish to bring their vacant property back into use.  Correspondingly, the buy-and-renew scheme also has strong potential to purchase and reuse empty dwellings where properties that are suitable for social housing use are available and, therefore, it is a valuable companion to the repair and leasing scheme.</p><p>Mayo County Council is committed to utilising the aforementioned schemes.  Of the 80 applications made to it in respect of the repair-and-lease scheme, the council is engaging with the owners of 42 properties, while 12 agreements to lease have been signed.  Three homes have been completed under buy-and-renew and the council is assessing a further ten homes.  Similarly, nine homes have been compulsorily purchased by Mayo County Council in 2019 for housing.  Three of these are being considered for progression under the buy-and-renew scheme.  Mayo County Council is one of the local authorities that participated in a pilot field survey on vacancy to assess the level of long-term vacant residential homes.  Having visually inspected some 1,065 properties in their administrative area, some 61 homes were identified as being vacant over the six-month period of the survey.  This equates to a vacancy rate of 5.2%, which is in line with what could be expected to allow churn in a normal housing market.  The council will aim to engage with the owners of the 61 homes with a view to getting them reactivated as part of the housing stock.</p><p>The Council has also developed the website <i>vacanthomes.ie</i>, on behalf of the local government sector, to serve as a central portal for individuals anonymously to log possible vacant homes in order that local authorities can follow up with the registered owners.  The website has proved a useful tool in aiding local authorities identify vacant homes, with the latest statistics indicating that almost 3,000 properties have been registered on <i>vacanthomes.ie</i>to date.  Aside from the reactivation of privately-owned vacant homes, the Department supports the comprehensive maintenance and remediation of local-authority-owned vacant housing stock by way of the voids programme.  Since the outset of the programme in 2014, and in addition to its own resources, Mayo County Council has been provided with funding of &euro;1.456 million to bring some 320 vacant homes back to productive use.  Some 57 homes, or 2.7% of Mayo County Council's housing stock, are vacant, with 13 currently having a tenancy offered and a further eight due to be the subject of offers in the coming weeks.</p> <p>Following a call for proposals for 2019, Mayo County Council submitted 32 properties for inclusion in the voids programme seeking funding of &euro;225,000.  Allocations for the voids programme are due to issue shortly.</p> <p>Both centrally and at local level, we are committed to optimising the existing housing stock and, in that context, we will continue to review all initiatives with a view to offering the best supports to those who wish to bring vacant homes back into use.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600004#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his reply.  I am glad to note there is some activity.  I would be interested in getting more information on the 61 vacant properties the Minister mentioned.  I agree the majority of empty houses are privately owned.  There are not many long-term voids in the council housing stock.  However, I could point to 61 such properties in my town alone, which is only a small part of the county.  I do not know where from where the council got that figure.  Equally, I could point to 61 houses that have been long-term empty.  I am not sure how those figures are being calculated.  There is no substitute for going door to door, as we have the joy of doing during an election campaign.  In that way one could quickly establish there are many empty houses and one could get to the bottom of this.  I do not want to be disrespectful about the information provided but I cannot accept there are only 61 private houses vacant in Mayo.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600004#C00300"><p>I thank the Senator for her follow-up remarks.  I hope the information I provided is useful in terms of actual numbers.  The reason we can provide that is that we have vacant home action plans for, and vacant home officers in, each of the local authorities.  As I said in my initial response, Mayo was involved in this pilot programme.  When we get high level numbers around vacancy - we see reports from the Central Statistics Office, CSO, and from GeoDirectory - and what we have seen when we have gone in to do the work is that the true level of vacancy has been overstated because of what was counted.  In the case of the CSO, it counts summer homes and houses that are for sale or for rent.  These types of homes do not speak to the type of vacancy that we are talking about.</p>  <p>In the six-month period of that survey, there was a series of inspections of each property to make sure they were still vacant in that period.  That was a visual inspection of more than 1,000 properties.  Not every property was inspected.  It would not have included all the homes the Senator might see in her constituency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600004#C00400"><p>So it was a sample.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600004#C00500"><p>Of the 1,000 properties inspected, 61 are what we would consider to be truly vacant homes, which Mayo County Council believes it can bring back into liveable stock.  It will engage and do that now, which is important.  The council has also received 80 prepare and lease applications.  That is another 80 vacant homes it can bring back into use, which is separate from the applications it received under buy and renew.  Of its own vacant social housing stock, 320 vacant homes requiring the investment of serious money, have been brought back into its stock of social housing.  There are now 57 homes vacant under the voids programme in Mayo County Council.  We will work on a plan for an application for funding for 32 of those homes to bring them back into use with that funding this year.  Good progress has been made, although more needs to be done.</p><p>I thank Mayo County Council for setting up the website <i>vacanthomes.ie</i>.  It is doing the heavy lifting for the rest of country in allowing members of the public to identify vacant homes on their roads wherever they are based in the county.  That information is submitted.  People can take a picture of the home on their mobile phone, and it is geo-co-ordinated with the global positioning system, GPS.  People will know where the property is and can visually inspect it.  This applies to each of the local authorities throughout the country, and they can then determine whether it can bring such properties into their programme, be it under the repair and lease, the buy and renew, compulsory purchase order, CPO, or another measure.  Mayo County Council has developed a very helpful tool and I was very happy to see it do that.  Not long after I came into this brief, it stepped forward and it has been leading the way since and I thank it for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.22" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 10.55 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.23" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600005#G00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600005#G00200"><p>I ask the very nice Deputy Leader to outline the business of the day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600005#G00300"><p>I thank the very nice Cathaoirleach.</p>  <p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Criminal Justice (Mutual Recognition of Probation Judgments and Decisions) Bill 2018 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 12.45 p.m.; No. 2, Coroners (Amendment) Bill 2018 - Committee Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1; No. 3, Perjury and Related Offences Bill 2018 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken on conclusion of No. 2 and to adjourn at 3.30 p.m., if not previously concluded; No. 4, Industrial Relations (Amendment) Bill 2018 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 3.30 p.m.; No. 5, Private Members' business, Criminal Justice (Public Order) (Amendment) Bill 2019 - Second Stage, to be taken at 4 p.m. or on conclusion of No. 4, whichever is the later, and to adjourn after two hours, if not previously concluded; and No. 6, statements on the summer economic statement, to be taken at 6 p.m. or on conclusion of No. 5, whichever is the later, with the time allocated to group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600005#G00400"><p>I would like to raise three matters, the first of which is the closure of a homeless hostel.  The Dublin Regional Homeless Executive has informed us of the imminent closure of Br&uacute; Aimsire on Thomas Street, which is run by a charity called DePaul Ireland.  We want to know whether there will be adequate provision of emergency beds.  Where will these people sleep from now on?  The hostel is full most evenings and people are worried because they do not know where they will be accommodated.  I call for a discussion on this in the House because it is quite worrying for people who rely on homeless hostel services in this city.</p>  <p>The second issue relates to a stabbing last night the Liberties.  I raised the issue of knife crime last week.  There has been a serious increase in the incidence of knife crime in this city but nothing is being done about it.  There was a stabbing on O'Connell Street and two stabbings in Cherry Orchard and then this stabbing last night where a young lady in her 30s was stabbed in her home.  This epidemic of knife crime is very concerning but we have done nothing about it.  We need to consider offences in regard to the sale, purchase and possession of knives.  We need to tackle this issue because it is a growing one.  I hope I do not have to raise it again next week.</p>  <p>The third issue I wish to raise is today's strike by 10,000 health support workers.  A further strike is planned for next week.  A pay rise has been agreed and it is incumbent on the Government to stand over what it agreed to as part of the Lansdowne Road agreement.  It is unfair that these workers must go on strike.  Ultimately, it is the patients who are affected by this action.  I call on the Minister for Health to be proactive and engage with SIPTU to ensure the strike planned for next week does not go ahead because patients and this country cannot afford any more industrial action in the health service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600005#G00500"><p>I have spoken many times about the Public Service Pay Commission report on the Defence Forces but I have reached the end of my tether.  The Chief of Staff of the Defence Forces, who has no control over public service pay, but who is doing his best to lead his charge, wrote on 20 June 2019 to his charge, that is, to all members of the Defence Forces.  He said:</p><blockquote>On the 31st of May I informed you that the Public Service Pay Commission report on the Defence Forces would be published in the coming weeks.  It is now most likely that the report will be presented to Cabinet for approval <i>next Tuesday, the 25th of June</i>.  The report will be made available to all members of the DF at the earliest opportunity after that and its contents and recommendations will need to be studied in detail.  It is my intention with the General staff to visit the majority of Barracks and installations after the publication of the report.<br /><br />Appropriate remuneration and conditions of service for all service personnel are fundamental priorities for the General Staff.</blockquote><p>The representative bodies were told they had to meet the Department of Defence to hear the content of the Public Service Pay Commission's report.  Several times over the last month and a half or so, they were told they needed to come in to hear the outcome of the report and yet on each occasion they were told that it would be the following week.  Yesterday, the Taoiseach told the D&aacute;il that it was never the intention to release the Public Service Pay Commission report.  This has gone beyond a joke.  Yesterday, members of the Judiciary received a &euro;12,000 a year pay rise and I do not begrudge them their pay rise.  Our Defence Forces are the most loyal citizens of the State and the only citizens of the State who sign away their right to take industrial action and defend this State and yet we treat them like this.  Every year Ministers and taoisigh laud the founders and defenders of this State such as Padraig Pearse, Thomas McDonagh, etc.  Maybe it is time we recognised those who gave their life in the service of this State.  I intend to read into the record the names of every member of the Defence Forces who has died in overseas service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600005#G00600"><p>The Senator will not have the time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600005#G00700"><p>Senator Craughwell has 15 seconds to do it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00100"><p>Colonel Justin McCarthy; Lieutenant Kevin Gleeson; Sergeant Hugh Gaynor; Corporal Peter Kelly; Corporal Liam Dougan; Private Matthew Farrell; Trooper Thomas Fennell; Trooper Anthony Browne; Private Michael McGuinn; Private Gerard Killeen; Private Patrick Davis; Corporal Liam Kelly; Corporal Luke Kelly-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00200"><p>Senator Craughwell is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00250"><p>I beg the Cathaoirleach's indulgence on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00275"><p>I am not sure that reading the names of these noble gentlemen or ladies into the record will achieve anything or is relevant to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00300"><p>What it achieves, as far as I am concerned, is it brings home the fact that the men and women who serve this country are prepared to give their lives on a daily basis for whatever duty they are assigned.  They never question it.  They cannot march up to the gates tomorrow morning, withdraw their service or turn around and say to the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00400"><p>The Senator can call for a debate on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00500"><p>I am sick of calling for debates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00600"><p>The Senator has used his four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00700"><p>The Cathaoirleach is an extremely generous and decent man.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00800"><p>He should not test my generosity.  I have to rule on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H00900"><p>The Taoiseach made a statement in the D&aacute;il yesterday.  How many times will he push back the report of the Public Service Pay Commission?  How many times will the Government tell these struggling families it will deliver the pay commission's findings next week, the week after or not at all?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01000"><p>With respect, the Senator is almost two minutes over his time.  I am trying to be fair.  I ask him to resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01100"><p>I want the Taoiseach to come to this Chamber and explain what it is about the Defences Forces that makes him unwilling under any circumstances to give them their just rewards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01200"><p>Please resume your seat, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01300"><p>A Chathaoirligh, please do not ask me to resume my seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01400"><p>I rarely rise but I have to be fair, as I believe I am to most people.  The Senator has exceeded his speaking time by more than two minutes.  I ask him to respect due process in the House and resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01500"><p>I have been disciplined all my life.  I have always obeyed the rules but somebody somewhere has to disobey.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01600"><p>Will you resume your seat?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01800"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01850"><p>Senator Craughwell is looking for a headline.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600006#H01900"><p>I cannot tolerate this sort of belligerence.  I will suspend the House for ten minutes to reflect on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.51" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.42 a.m. and resumed at 11.53 a.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00100"><p>To move on, I call Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00200"><p>The Cathaoirleach asked me-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00300"><p>I know Senator Craughwell is looking for a headline.  I gave him five minutes and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00400"><p>The Senator wishes to make a proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00500"><p>We know that the Government has had the report of the Public Service Pay Commission for more than six weeks.  There is no reason for the report not to have been released to the men and women who are depending on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00600"><p>The Senator may call for a debate on the matter, but I cannot prolong the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00700"><p>I am proposing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00800"><p>The Senator should be very brief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J00900"><p>-----that no business take place in the House today until the Taoiseach, who is also the Minister for Defence, comes to the House to explain the delay in publishing the report.  I ask all Members to support the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01000"><p>The Senator will have the option to vote against the acceptance of the Order of Business if he so desires.  That is his prerogative.  However, I cannot allow him to stay on his feet because there are another 11 speakers and the Senator is depriving them of their speaking time.  The Order of Business must finish by 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01100"><p>Is my proposal clear?  It is that no business take place in this House today until the Taoiseach comes to the House to explain the impediment to releasing the Public Service Pay Commission report on Defence Forces pay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01200"><p>Is the Senator proposing an amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01300"><p>The Senator should amend his proposal that the House not take any other business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01400"><p>It is too extreme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01500"><p>If he were to propose that we take statements or have a debate on the issue later today, I would be happy to support it-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01600"><p>Yes, exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01700"><p>-----but we have other important business to deal with today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01800"><p>Senator Craughwell is making two proposals.  One is that the Taoiseach come to the House, which may not be easy to achieve, and the other is that the Minister for Defence come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J01900"><p>I am inclined to agree with Senator Nash.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J02000"><p>I ask the Senator to briefly make his proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J02100"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that the Taoiseach come to the House to explain why the Public Service Pay Commission report has not been released to the Defence Forces.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J02200"><p>That is clear.  I ask the Senator to resume his seat.  I call Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J02300"><p>I wish to support Senator Craughwell's amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J02400"><p>Is the Senator formally seconding it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="11:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600007#J02500"><p>Yes.  I wish to address the issue of carers.  It is time that we cared for the carers.  Some 355,000 people, or one in ten adults, are unpaid carers in Ireland.  Only 81,071, or one in five, of those carers receive carer's allowance.  They save the State the massive sum of &euro;10 billion each year.  The Government spends almost two and a half times more on the nursing home fair deal scheme than it does on carers.  The point I am trying to make is that it is time for us to care for the carers.</p>  <p>I commend Family Carers Ireland on the launch of its pre-budget submission, which contains very simple requests.  The first is to reform the means test for carer's allowance.  It has not been reformed since 2008.  There has been no change in the disregards and the allowable deductions are too limited.  This means that many people do not meet the means test for carer's allowance.</p>  <p>We need to give consideration to the fact that carer's allowance is taxable.  We do not tax vulture funds or multinational companies and banks are getting away without paying tax for 20 years, but we tax carer's allowance.  That must be examined and changed.</p>  <p>Another matter that need to be changed is the restriction of 15 hours a week in respect of carers who work, take up a course in education or engage in voluntary work.  That must be extended to at least 18.5 hours per week.  We must value our carers.</p>  <p>We need to end the postcode lottery in regard to home care and carer supports.  In my county of Mayo, we do not have the home care or carer supports that exist in other areas of the country.</p>  <p>We also need to replace the mobility allowance and motorised transport grant which were withdrawn in 2013.  There is no reason these measures should not be brought back in, particularly for people living in rural areas who must travel long distances to hospital and for medical supports since the centralisation of such supports.  In addition, the GP visit card should be extended to include carers in receipt of a carer's support package.</p> <p>I ask that the Minister be asked to come to the House for a meaningful debate on how we treat our 355,000 unpaid carers in this State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600008#K00200"><p>We should have that debate.  The Labour Party will propose a motion in the D&aacute;il later this evening regarding additional supports for carers.  I hope that the House will unite behind that proposal, which includes many of the propositions outlined in Senator Conway-Walsh's contribution.</p>  <p>The spin that we have seen over the last couple days in particular from Fine Gael on today's hospital workers strike has been remarkable.  There has been a common thread and a common pattern running through the contributions of Fine Gael backbenchers over the last couple of days and a succession of Fine Gael cannon fodder has been marched through the doors of various television and radio studios over the last two or three days, claiming that the strike is SIPTU's fault and that, to use the word referenced by the Minister for Health yesterday, it is "extraordinary" that the dispute has not been referred to the Labour Court and that health workers across the country are having their pay restored.  These kinds of phrases display a remarkable ignorance of what this particular health dispute is about.  Fine Gael is deliberately muddying the waters in this regard.  This is not about pay restoration.  Rather, it is about the implementation of a solemn deal and a job evaluation review process that was carried out in the context of the existing public sector pay agreement and within the architecture of successive public sector pay agreements.  This is essentially about ensuring that our health care assistants, porters, chefs and other critical support staff grades across our hospital service are given just reward for the work they do.  Their roles were independently and objectively assessed by experts in this field.  A deal was done with the Department of Health and the HSE and now the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe, is withholding the moneys that are legitimately owed to those health care staff.  It is pathetic that Fine Gael has chosen to pick a fight with the lowest paid workers in our health service in order to re-establish its damaged reputation in terms of its management of the public finances.  It is telling.  This morning, I spent some time on the picket line at Louth County Hospital in Dundalk and Our Lady of Lourdes Hospital in Drogheda, supporting the stance that low paid health workers have been forced to take in a bid to have their rights vindicated.  This is a classic upstairs-downstairs type scenario.</p>  <p>There is another upstairs-downstairs type scenario of which I was made aware yesterday.  I do not necessarily want to identify the individual, but I know that she is happy for me to do so.  A colleague of mine, a newly elected councillor in Drogheda, Councillor Michelle Hall, who represents the Drogheda rural electorate, works as a special needs assistant in Aston Village Educate Together school in Drogheda.  She has learned through the school, her union and the Department of Education and Skills that unlike teachers she is not entitled to ten unpaid leave days to attend to her public duties.  This is unfair and discriminatory.  Fine Gael believes that only doctors and nurses are important in the context of the health service and it likewise believes that only principals and teachers matter in the context of the education system.  This is unfair and discriminatory and it needs to be corrected.  The Minister needs to respond to this issue immediately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="11:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600008#K00300"><p>I reject what has been said by Senator Nash.  Fine Gael worked very closely with the Labour Party in a very difficult time.  The Labour Party and Fine Gael helped to rescue this country.  Senator Nash's comments are not representative of what I believe.  We will agree to differ.</p>  <p>As Chairman of Committee A of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, I mentioned yesterday that the committee visited various locations in Northern Ireland and the Republic in the context of its study on illicit trade between Ireland and the UK along the Border in the context of Brexit.  There is a particular issue that we need to address, namely, counterfeit goods.  A lot of work was done to develop the marker to eliminate washed diesel used, in the main, by paramilitaries or subversive groups.  While this practice has been dealt with those involved are cunning, professional smugglers and they have now moved into washing powder, alcohol, meat processing and cheap whites, namely, cigarettes.  People who buy these goods need to be mindful of workers' rights, workplace conditions and product origin.  These products, in particular the washing powder and cheap whites, are dangerous and the proceeds finance drug gangs and gun crime.  We need an information campaign.  People who holiday in Spain and so on and purchase counterfeit designer handbags and football jerseys and so on from salespeople along the breach front need to be made aware that they are funding criminal activity.  We need to wake up and recognise that these products are not good value.  Rather, they are bad produce, the proceeds of which is funding criminal gangs.  We need an information campaign or a debate on this very serious issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="11:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600008#K00400"><p>I rise today to raise the issue of electric vehicle charging points, but not the lack of same or the need for more.  I have been contacted by a number of people who  recently invested in electric vehicles in regard to their inability to access charging points, particularly in rural areas and small villages, as non-electric vehicles are being parked or abandoned in front of them.  This is happening in rural areas in particular where there is no paid parking and hence no parking wardens.  There is nobody policing the charging points.  This issue needs to be raised with the relevant Department.  There is need for additional signage at electric vehicle charging points and increased penalties or fines for those who park in front of them.  One can imagine the frustration of an electric vehicle owner who, when the battery is almost dead, arrives at a charging point to find a three litre diesel car parked in front of it, which means he or she cannot access it or continue on his or her journey.  There is nobody policing charging points in small towns in rural areas where there is no paid parking.  I ask the Deputy Leader to raise this issue with the relevant Minister.</p>  <p>If the people who raised this issue with me are speaking to other people about this matter they are probably speaking negatively about electric vehicles, thereby deterring those who might be considering purchasing an electric vehicle from doing so.  As we are all aware, this is the direction in which we have to go.  The charging points are limited enough.  If they are not accessible, this is another black mark against purchasing an electric vehicle.  They need to be policed in the areas I have mentioned, although I admit I do not know how this can be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="11:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600008#K00500"><p>I welcome the report on the future of the beef sector in the context of Food Wise 2025.  The Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine is to be commended on its diligent work and dedication to the production of this report.  However, as detailed and referenced in the report, it is not a silver bullet for the industry.  No one solution exists to protect the fortunes and futures of those involved in this industry.  All involved, including the farming fraternity, the processors, the industry bodies and the Government, have a responsibility and a part to play.  The report makes recommendations with regard to unfair trading practices, market information, exports, pricing, CAP support, added value and research funding, all of which are important and relevant.  There is a special acknowledgement of the significant threat posed by the prospective EU-Mercusor free trade agreement and the unintended consequences and detrimental impact, potentially, it could have of undercutting Irish beef with the importation of cheaper beef into the European market.</p>  <p>The importance of the Irish beef sector cannot and must not be understated for the socioeconomic benefits it presents for rural Ireland.  The importance of retaining people on the land and ensuring that this sector is truly sustainable on economic, environmental and social grounds is paramount, not alone for the rural economy but the entire Irish economy, urban and rural.  My concern is that there is no recognition of costs of production and efficiency.  We must acknowledge that some businesses are not sustainable if beef is at &euro;6 per kilo.  The stark reality is that it will not be that price.  The market is the market.  The Government must ensure mechanisms are in place to establish cost of production modelling and seek to assist farmers in understanding cutting cost production, maximising efficiencies and maximising profits from a technical farming perspective.</p> <p>Let us focus on the things a farming business has control of rather than all of the aspects over which they have no influence.  Vertical integration of a supply chain and the sharing of risk and rewards across the supply chain must be discussed.  The supply chain must become a value chain adding value at every point.</p> <p>Reports and recommendations are one thing but this must be with implementation and delivering impact.  This report is only a starting point to build a sustainable beef industry with support mechanisms, market awareness and sustainability at its core.  The committee, with the Minister, now have responsibility to ensure that targets relating to the food sector are set out in Food Wise 2025 and are delivered as part of a sustainable and profitable industry with farmers and their families central to the conversation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L00200"><p>I compliment the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission for organising the all-Ireland food fair to which we were all invited last week in the Members' Restaurant.  It was a treat for the senses and the food was absolutely fantastic.  I particularly want to single out the Mayo Mountain Blackface Sheep Breeders group who were represented on that occasion by Pat Chambers of Newport and Peter Chambers, who is involved with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  It is a fantastic success story with a lot more potential.  It is a producer group from the west of Ireland with 350 members who sell premium breeding stock and factory lambs.  The group works with the Kildare Chilling Company to supply finished lambs.  This business has grown from processing 2,000 lambs in 2012 to processing 25,000 lambs in 2018.  This means a great and fantastic deal to the local economy.  It encompasses a great geographical spread in Mayo including the Nephin Beg wilderness on the Wild Atlantic Way and from Toormakeady to Bangor Erris.  There is a lot of species-rich grassland there upon which this particular breed of blackface sheep roam.  I believe this to be a unique selling point.  This is the way our primary producers need to go to maximise the value for their product.  I also compliment the South West Mayo Development Company and the rural social scheme there, along with the breeders and the group secretary, Breege Biggins.  It is a real success story that I wanted to highlight.  They have a product they can stand over and they need support in promotion so they can go further afield.  I sincerely hope they get that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L00300"><p>I wish to speak about this morning's strike that was commenced by health service staff and workers, as Senator Nash has already referred to.  We are aware from different strikes in the health services that the spin from the Government and the Department gives a sense that workers and unions just strike for the crack of it and go to the gates and discommode a lot of people, including themselves, their families, patients and those on waiting lists.  This, however, is quite false or as a Trumpian would say it is "fake news".  It is not as simple as just saying that the Workplace Relations Commission is available.  The Department has reneged on an agreement that was made in 2017 for these 10,000 workers for job evaluations and an agreement and a price was put on the cost of that decision.  I was with health service workers at the gates of St. James's Hospital this morning and I give a shout out to Patricia Slattery who organised that strike.  Workers such as this are the engine rooms of hospitals.  The nurses and doctors are seen as the more visible face of hospital staff but these 10,000 health service workers are in the engine rooms providing essential services for our patients.  They are marching but it is not for the good of their own health.  They are looking to strike also over two or three days next week looking only for the implementation of what has already been decided.  As Senator Nash has said, this is not a new pay claim.  It is a claim that has been hanging over health service staff for years.  Government inaction has made it sound as though these workers are greedy and the bogeyguys, but this is not the case.  These workers need what is rightly due to them.  They are workers on modest wages who work in the engine rooms of our hospitals and health services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L00400"><p>There are a lot of Senators indicating so I ask all Members to be cognisant of the fact that we had a delayed Order of Business and that they please stick to the time of two minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L00500"><p>I will respond to some of the issues raised already around the strike.  It is important to outline that pay has been restored to that group earning under &euro;30,000 income-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L00600"><p>This is not about pay restoration-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L00700"><p>With all due respect-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L00800"><p>This is not about pay restoration.  This is the spin we get.  It is not about pay restoration.  It is about independent job evaluation-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L00900"><p>The Senator should show some respect to the Chamber and to the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01000"><p>This is wrong-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01100"><p>-----to the Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01200"><p>This is the truth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01300"><p>The Senator is only delaying-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01400"><p>The Senator should show some respect to the health service workers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01500"><p>The Senator should show some respect to the Chamber and to the Chairman when he is speaking-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01600"><p>I ask Senator Conway to stay out of the argument.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01700"><p>The position I am quite clearly stating is that people earning under &euro;30,000 have had their pay restored and it is now 4% above the 2009 pay level.  That has not occurred in other sectors of the HSE.  This is point No. 1.</p>  <p>My second point is that an additional 13,000 whole-time equivalent, WTE, staff were taken on in the HSE in the last four years in order to assist and make sure we can continue to deliver the same level of care or an increased level of care.  There are now 135,000 people working in the HSE.  There were 103,000 WTE workers and that has now gone up to 116,000 whole-time equivalent staff in four years, which is a huge pay cost of some &euro;600 million per annum of additional cost.  With regard to the situation we are discussing, yes an evaluation was carried out and yes it needs to be implemented, and the Government is quite clearly saying it will start to implement it from November.  There are other issues that need to be resolved and the Government is quite prepared to go back into conciliation on those issues and has made its position quite clear.  Let us not go back to the period between 2000 and 2008 when public sector pay went from &euro;8 billion per annum to &euro;16 billion per annum and then-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01800"><p>Why did the Government agree to a job evaluation process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L01900"><p>If Senator Nash does not want to hear the truth that is fine-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02000"><p>This is the truth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02100"><p>That is fine with me.  I will not be bullied by Senator Nash-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02200"><p>This is spin from-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02300"><p>I will not be bullied by Senator Nash-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02400"><p>It is misleading of the Government to renege on a deal-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02500"><p>Senators-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02600"><p>The Government will not hear the uncomfortable truth and Fine Gael will not want to accept it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02700"><p>I ask Senator Nash to please resume his seat-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02800"><p>They do not give a toss about the lower paid workers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L02900"><p>Senator Nash will please resume his seat-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03000"><p>-----be it Defence Forces members or school secretaries or anybody else who has increased their work-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03100"><p>The Senator has put me over my limit-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03200"><p>I gave my colleagues free rein and I did not interrupt them.  The Government has increased the health budget by quite a substantial amount over the past years.  We need to ensure we can develop a healthcare sector-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03300"><p>It is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03400"><p>The Senator has made his point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03500"><p>-----and develop the sector in a cost-effective way.  We are doing that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03600"><p>I too will lend my voice in support of the health service workers.  They have been treated disgracefully.  There was a job evaluation, which is being ignored.  What is the point of these things if the Government does not live up to it?  Consider the jobs being done by these workers.  I have a friend who works in a Dublin hospital and there is intimate contact such as taking patients to the lavatory, assisting people in the evacuation of bowels and showering people.  They administer to them in all of these ways.  Health services workers do a very remarkable job.  There is a two-tier system where the judges get their pay.  The increase for some judges is as much as the annual income of some low-paid workers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03700"><p>That is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03800"><p>That is a disgrace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L03900"><p>Senator Norris and the judges-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L04000"><p>I beg your pardon?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L04100"><p>The Senator is in favour of the judges every week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L04200"><p>Would Senator Norris have supported the referendum on-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L04300"><p>Please allow Senator Norris to make his point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600009#L04400"><p>I believe I have made the point.  The treatment of these low-paid workers is an outrage.</p>  <p>I also draw the attention of the House to the fact that this morning we had the instigation of a group for staff and Members of the Oireachtas who are gay.</p> <p>I think this is quite historic.  I went along and was very glad to see quite a large number of people.  They will present a rainbow flag to the Ceann Comhairle, under whose auspices this meeting took place, to be flown on Saturday over Leinster House.  It is a great day for diversity in Ireland and I congratulate all involved, especially the Leader of the House, Senator Jerry Buttimer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M00200"><p>Across from Buswells Hotel, as we speak, the National Council for the Blind Ireland, NCBI, is holding a pre-budget briefing to outline issues and challenges that blind and visually-impaired people in this country face daily, and their aspirations and hopes about what the upcoming budget will do to help to alleviate some of the many different challenges and issues.  One clear example is where somebody who has a visual impairment, who is not deemed to be legally blind but is medically unable to drive a car, does not get a free travel pass simply because he or she does not meet the criteria of being legally blind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M00300"><p>They definitely should.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M00400"><p>Absolutely.  This affects approximately 200 people in the country and needs to be taken on board and rectified.  There is a range of other issues and challenges.  Great work is being done by the National Council for the Blind.  I encourage Members who have not already gone across to Buswells Hotel to engage with them to consider doing so.  The briefing is taking place until 3.30 p.m.</p>  <p>I will not comment on the health dispute.  Senator Colm Burke outlined the situation.  It is reasonable for any Government to expect the unions to use the apparatus of the Labour Court.  Ultimately, disputes in this country are resolved in the Labour Court.  I cannot understand why Paul Bell and his union colleagues refuse to go into the Labour Court.  The HSE is willing to go there this afternoon and tomorrow morning.  Why is the union not prepared to do that?  I would like it to give a definitive answer to that because it is appalling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M00500"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business.  I am seeking leave to introduce my Bill, the Criminal Justice (Judicial Discretion) (Amendment) Bill 2019.  The Bill seeks to introduce judicial discretion to determine periods of time that a person shall spend in prison for the offence and conviction of murder, which we do not currently have.  I ask that a colleague second my amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M00600"><p>I thank Senator O'Donnell for her brevity and call Senator James Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M00700"><p>I support my colleague, Senator Conway, and remind people that the NCBI is in Buswell's.  It does important work and needs our support.  I support my colleague, Senator Paul Daly and reassure him that this does not just affect rural Ireland.  Last Wednesday, I was in Malahide and the only available space for an electric car that I could find was occupied by a non-electric car.  The same thing happens in Leinster House, where we have two spaces and one was occupied by a non-electric car.</p><p>However, I really rise to speak about Brexit and the fact that we may face a very hard Brexit.  I call on the Minister for Finance to give consideration to the following.  By way of background, Charlie Weston in the <i>Irish Independent</i>talked about the Irish credit unions having &euro;17 billion on deposit but only being able to lend out &euro;4.5 billion.  That is a 27% loan to assets ratio which, in any normal institution, would be 50%.  <i>The Irish Times</i>reported this month that credit unions are now restricting members' deposits, primarily because the credit unions cannot put that money to work via prudent loans.  In October 2018, at the invitation of the 200 year old public bank in Germany, called Sparkasse, which I have raised numerous times here, I visited its headquarters and banking academy where it trains bankers.  It has its own university to do that.  Its successful, sustainable banking model has worked for more than 200 years, including through two world wars, economic downturns and serious recessions.  The bank is available to assist local regions.  It has a long tradition of real banking, not just based on turning over property and profits.  It is an old-style bank whose staff go to visit a person at a business or farm, assess risks and ability to pay, and support a person through the rough as well as good times.</p><p>I call on the Minister for Finance to urgently review the case for setting up a pilot scheme for this bank in the midland counties and in Fingal, County Dublin, to assist businesses with the challenge of Brexit.  We need to provide credit to businesses in difficult times at reasonable rates.  In the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation's report on the cost of doing business, the cost and availability of credit were two of the main challenges that businesses faced with regard to sustainability.  Sparkassen could perhaps partner with credit unions or at least be allowed to come in.  The report, which is good, has been with the Minister for quite a while and we should act.  He needs to come to the House and tell us what he will do.  By his own admission, he has two budget scenarios.  One is for a hard Brexit, which will put this country in serious jeopardy, and we will need finance to sustain our people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M00800"><p>I second Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell's amendment to the Order of Business.  I am conscious of time.  The Government has launched a draft marine planning policy statement.  It is important that we have a cohesive, coherent marine planning strategy relating to development.  I encourage Members to engage in the public consultation.  If they represent coastal communities, they might take it up with their communities and ask them to engage.  The public consultation is now open but the period will close on Friday, 9 August 2019 at midday.  It is an important document that can be accessed on the website of the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M00900"><p>My colleague, Senator Craughwell, proposed an amendment to the Order of Business relating to the publication of the Public Service Pay Commission report.  As the defence spokesperson for Fianna F&aacute;il, I fully agree that this report is long overdue and should be published as a matter of urgency.  However, Senator Craughwell is correct that we need the Taoiseach, who is personally responsible for the Defence Forces, to attend, not the Minister of State.  This is too serious an issue.  I ask the Deputy Leader that within the next week, and certainly before the summer recess, the Taoiseach should come to the House and outline the contents of this report which I believe and agree should be published.  Morale is at an all-time low within the Defence Forces and it is time that their concerns about pay, conditions and allowances are dealt with urgently.  It is long overdue but I think that we should wait until the Taoiseach is available to come in here himself.  Frankly, the Minister of State is not acceptable to me as the defence spokesperson.  He is the Minister of State but we need the man who has the responsibility to come in here and answer questions when he is available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="11:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600010#M01000"><p>We are in fine voice today.  Many issues were raised on the Order of Business.  Senator Ardagh raised the hostel on Thomas Street.  The Dublin Regional Homeless Executive, DRHE, has been using the Br&uacute; Aimsir hostel temporarily since 2016.  The hostel operates on a one-night only basis and has been accommodating 105 individuals.  That property was always available temporarily to Dublin County Council from the Digital Hub Development Agency.  The Dublin Regional Homeless Executive works continuously to ensure there is adequate emergency supply.  The facility will close on 27 June.  However, 120 new beds will be provided to replace those previously provided at this facility and by 10 July, the DRHE will increase the supply of emergency beds by 45, meaning that 165 new beds will be provided.</p> <p>The majority of the new beds being put in place - approximately 95 - are supported temporary accommodation.  The Senator will be pleased to hear that nobody in Br&uacute; Aimsir will be left without accommodation.</p> <p>We all regret the stabbing in the Liberties area and we all want to avoid crime.  The Government remains committed to a vigorous and comprehensive response to knife crime in our cities and generally.  A comprehensive and robust legal framework is in place in respect of knife crime, including heavy penalties for a breach of the law concerned.  An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has an extended power of search without warrant in relation to knives and offensive weapons.  This is an important issue, especially in Dublin, where many of these crimes are occurring.  It could certainly be debated in the House in the near future.</p> <p>Many Senators raised the strike by HSE workers.  The dispute began at 8 a.m. and will have a significant impact on 38 hospital healthcare facilities from today.  I support the comments made by Senators Burke and Conway who noted that &euro;17 billion is now being allocated to the health service, the highest such allocation in the history of the State.  We all differ on various aspects of this issue but I encourage all parties to go to the Labour Court.  The court was established to deal with cases such as these and I am at a loss to understand why it is not being used.  An additional 300,000 people have been taken on in the health service, which adds a huge cost to the bottom line of the HSE.  Genuine efforts have been made by the Government and I encourage all involved to go to the Labour Court.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell raised the issue of the Defence Forces.  The Taoiseach will not come to the House to speak on this issue as he has had a bereavement.  We will arrange a debate on the impact of the Public Service Pay Commission report on the Defence Forces as soon as possible.  It was never officially stated that the report would be published this week.  The Minister of State stated today that it will be available next week.  The issue has been raised in this House on numerous occasions, not least by Senators Craughwell, McFadden and Wilson.  Given that it has been raised for nearly a year, taking another few days to get it right should not make a difference and it will be before the House next week.</p> <p>Senator Conway-Walsh raised the important issue of carers.  Family Carers Ireland has made many laudable suggestions in its pre-budget submission and I expect the Minister for Finance will take many of them on board in advance of the budget.  We will receive many pre-budget submissions in the coming weeks. </p> <p>I addressed the issue raised by Senator Nash.  On the issue of teachers, it is worth noting that the Government has significantly increased the number of special needs assistants.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N00200"><p>I raised the entitlement of special needs assistants who are public representatives to enjoy the same rights as teachers with regard to paid annual leave when attending to council duties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N00300"><p>Given that the matter relates to a particular individual, perhaps the Senator will raise it as a Commencement motion in order to get a satisfactory direct response from the Minster.</p>  <p>Senator Feighan raised the important issue of smuggling, some of which was news to me.  An information campaign would be a very good idea and I hope it would be feasible.  I commend the Senator on raising the issue.</p>  <p>I completely agree with Senators Paul Daly and Reilly that we should come down hard on individuals who choose to park in spaces reserved for charging electric vehicles.  Such behaviour is very irritating for people who need to recharge their car battery, especially as we are trying to encourage the use of electric vehicles.  It is more challenging to use electric vehicles than other vehicles and every measure should be put in place to encourage their use.  This issue should be considered in the context of a debate on the environment or as a Commencement matter.  It is certainly a valid issue and one on which most Senators would agree with Senators Daly and Reilly.</p>  <p>Senator Marshall raised the important report on the future of the beef sector, which has been facilitated by Members of this House who sit on the agriculture committee.  We all want a sustainable beef sector and I commend colleagues on the report.</p>  <p>Senator Mulherin commended the Houses of the Oireachtas on the food event held here last week.  I was unable to attend but there was much positive feedback from the event, if Senators will pardon the pun.  I am sure the Mayo Mountain Blackface Sheep Breeders will go from strength to strength and the event rightly highlighted the group's great achievements.</p>  <p>Senator Colm Burke spoke about the strike by HSE workers and made many of the points I have already alluded to.</p>  <p>Senator Norris highlighted the new LGBT committee.  What is the correct name for the group?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N00400"><p>I am not sure but is it is an Oireachtas group of staff and Members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N00500"><p>That is a welcome development and it is important that a rainbow flag has been presented to the Ceann Comhairle.  I understand Senator Buttimer has led on the issue.</p>  <p>Senator Conway noted that representatives of the National Council for the Blind of Ireland will be in Buswells Hotel today to outline their pre-budget hopes and expectations.  As many Senators as possible should interact with them on their ongoing work.</p>  <p>Senator Reilly eloquently outlined the financial issues arising from Brexit.  The report to which he referred cannot be highlighted enough as it is extremely important.  We cannot debate Brexit enough and I expect we will have a further debate on it before the end of term because the time available for discussing the issue in the new term will be tight.  Much of the Senator's contribution would be very valid in any such debate.</p>  <p>Senator Boyhan highlighted the marine planning policy statement.  No more than the beef sector, we all want to see a cohesive plan when it comes to our marine and wildlife.  The public consultation aspect of this issue is very important to highlight.</p>  <p>Senator Wilson raised the same issue as Senator Craughwell.  As I mentioned, the Taoiseach will not be in position to come to the House today and I do not believe the Senator expected him to do so.  A debate will be arranged on the impact of the report in the near future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N00600"><p>By way of clarification, the Deputy Leader indicated that No. 5, the Criminal Justice (Public Order) (Amendment) Bill 2019, would adjourn after two hours.  Should that read "conclude" after two hours?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N00700"><p>The Bill is to be taken at 4 p.m., or on conclusion of No. 4, whichever is the later, and to adjourn after two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N00800"><p>Is it to adjourn or conclude?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N00900"><p>It is to conclude.  My apologies if I was unclear on that point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N01000"><p>On a further small point of personal interest, I want to put on record my congratulations to Bantry on winning a Tidy Towns award.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N01100"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N01200"><p>I remember that after the Betelgeuse disaster some 40 years ago the town was on its knees.  A Tidy Towns committee, some members of which have gone to their eternal reward, has been beavering away for decades and it finally won the big prize yesterday.  It is nice to acknowledge the tremendous work it has been doing in a remote town like Bantry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N01300"><p>I believe it won two awards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600011#N01400"><p>Yes, it won two awards, including the overall award, which is important.</p> <p> There have been proposals.  Senator Craughwell has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "To provide that a debate with the Taoiseach on the reasons the report of the Public Service Pay Commission has not been released will be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O00200"><p>Of course I want to press the amendment but I have been placed in a most awkward position.  I have just been told by the Deputy Leader, whose word I accept, that the Taoiseach has had a bereavement and cannot come to the House.   Three minutes ago, however, I could see on a television screen the Taoiseach answering questions in the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O00300"><p>He may well be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O00400"><p>I am constantly being pushed off-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O00500"><p>I will not allow another speech.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O00600"><p>This is not bloody well good enough.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O00700"><p>The Senator may either pull the trigger and push the amendment, or sit down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O00800"><p>Should I pull the trigger at this stage and find I do not win because the two main parties in the House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O00900"><p>The Senator can always raise the matter again next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01000"><p>We will raise it the following week, the week after that and the week after that.  The Government has put the Chief of Staff of the Defence Forces-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01100"><p>I take it the Senator is not pushing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01200"><p>-----in the most horrible position.  The Government has undermined the Chief of Staff's position in the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.162" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01400"><p>This is just not on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01500"><p>The question has been defeated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01600"><p>I will call a vote on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01700"><p>The Senator had his chance and he did not take it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01800"><p>This is not on.  You are a most decent man, a Chathaoirligh, but this is not on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O01900"><p>I asked whether the Senator was pushing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02000"><p>I was explaining my position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02100"><p>The Senator should not begin a spiel or we will have to suspend the House for an hour.  I have been tolerant.  Is the Senator pushing the amendment or not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02200"><p>Will the Cathaoirleach let me explain my position, please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02300"><p>There will be no explanation.  The question has been put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02400"><p>This is grossly unfair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02500"><p>I will disallow the amendment and move on otherwise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02600"><p>It is grossly unfair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02700"><p>The Senator is only looking for headlines.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02800"><p>No, it is damned unfair.  The Government the Senator supports has put the Chief of Staff in the most horrible position.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O02900"><p>Amendment No. 2, in the name of Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O03000"><p>The Government has undermined the Chief of Staff.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O03100"><p>What does the Senator hope to gain?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O03200"><p>I hope to get the Defence Forces' self-esteem back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O03300"><p>The Senator is looking for headlines.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O03400"><p>Resume your seat, Senators.  Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 15 be taken before No. 1."  The Deputy Leader has indicated she is prepared to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.184" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.185" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.186" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O03700">Criminal Justice (Judicial Discretion) (Amendment) Bill 2019: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O03800"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend section 2 of the Criminal Justice Act 1990 and to provide for related matters.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O03900"><p>Is there a seconder?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O04000"><p>I second the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.190" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O04200"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O04300"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.193" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 2 July 2019.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.194" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O04500">Criminal Justice (Mutual Recognition of Probation Judgments and Decisions) Bill 2018: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.195" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 32, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.196" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Schedule agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.197" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.198" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.199" nospeaker="true" time="11:55:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="11:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600012#O05200"><p>I acknowledge the support of Senators since Second Stage.  This is a complex Bill, as they will have noted, but it has a straightforward purpose, namely, to allow a person who has been placed under the supervision of the probation service in one EU member state but who lives in another to return home and undergo his or her further supervision here, or there, depending on the circumstances, provided the person's consent is forthcoming.  I emphasise that a person cannot be transferred from one country to another without his or her consent as it would discourage compliance and rehabilitation, which would have the effect of undermining the proposal.  The proposals in the Bill will increase the chances of social reintegration of offenders by ensuring that the probation measures imposed on a person can be followed up on and he or she can be supervised in the country in which he or she resides.  This will allow the offender to: maintain ties with family and community; in some circumstances, to continue in employment or education; and to relate to the support services in his or her home country, all of which are important in the context of rehabilitation and reintegration.</p> <p>Successful reintegration reduces the risk of reoffending, which improves the protections for both victims and society.  The Bill better protects society by improving the compliance framework for probation conditions and reduces unnecessary detention of non-resident offenders by ensuring the enforcement of non-custodial sentences in the person's home state.  This Bill, when enacted, will not affect too many people, but for the small number it will affect, it will have a considerable impact on their lives and for that reason, it is important legislation.  I thank Members for ensuring its concluding Stages were taken this afternoon before our summer recess.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P00200"><p>I thank the Minister for bringing forward this legislation and the officials in his Department for the work they did on it.  It is important that we recognise judgments from other countries and that the same recognition is given to Irish judgments elsewhere in order to ensure the decisions of the courts are implemented regardless of the country in which someone is residing.  It is an important step, particularly from an Irish point of view, given the number of people living here who have come from abroad.  They may wish to travel home and we need to make sure penalties imposed by the Probation Service are followed through in full.  I thank the Minister and the Department for bringing forward this legislation, and I hope it is passed into law as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P00300"><p>I again welcome this Bill, and I am happy to see it completed fairly speedily today.  It is very important legislation.  While it only affects a small number of people, it is important that we support these people and their families, and I thank the Minister for bringing the Bill to the House today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P00400"><p>I echo the words of thanks to the Minister.  We all acknowledge that this is significant and complex legislation, and the uniform support of the House has been worthwhile, productive, and fruitful in ensuring it passes today.  I commend the Minister and colleagues on that.  Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.205" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.206" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P00600">Coroners (Amendment) Bill 2018: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P00700"><p>I informed Senators on Second Stage of my intention to bring forward a number of further amendments.  The amendments I am introducing today include an important new section that will provide a coroner with the power to seek directions from the High Court on a point of law regarding the exercise of the coroner's functions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P00800"><p>We will take individual amendments as the sections arise.  I do not know what the Minister intends to do, but I will go to go through the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P00900"><p>We will do that, but I want to inform the House of my intention to introduce a small number of additional amendments on Report Stage, on which work is being completed.  I will come back to those as we move through the sections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.210" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.211" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.212" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 2 sand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P01200"><p>I am considering a Report Stage amendment on the inclusion of further definitions in section 2, which may result in better functioning of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.214" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.215" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Sections 3 and 4 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.216" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>SECTION 5</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.217" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 5 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P01600"><p>I expect to come back with an amendment to this section on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.219" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.220" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.221" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>SECTION 6</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.222" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 6 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P02000"><p>I intend to bring forward an amendment to section 6 on Report Stage which will include further administrative provisions, updating the provisions in section 13 of the principal Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P02100"><p>The Minister is alerting us to a number of amendments.  Are they primarily technical in nature?  I do not want to pre-empt Report Stage if it is a debate for Report Stage, but perhaps the Minister could give us an indication of whether or not they are primarily technical.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P02200"><p>They are.  They deal with the positions of deputy coroners and the Dublin coronial district.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.226" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.227" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Sections 7 to 13, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.228" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P02600"><p>Amendments Nos. 2 to 8, inclusive, are related and may be taken together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.230" nospeaker="true" time="12:05:00" ><p>Government  amendment No. 2:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600013#P02800"><p>This series of amendments relates to the adjournment of an inquest and the coroner's obligation to direct a post-mortem examination in a case where criminal proceedings are either under consideration or have been initiated into the death of the person concerned.  Section 25 of the principal Act, as Senators will be aware, already provides that the coroner shall adjourn the inquest on request of a Garda officer of rank not less than inspector in either of the following situations.  The first is where the request is on the grounds that criminal proceedings are being considered.  Section 25(1) provides that: "the coroner shall adjourn the inquest for such period as he thinks proper and shall further adjourn the inquest for similar periods so often as a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na not below the rank of inspector requests him on the ground aforesaid so to do."  The second is where the request is on the grounds that criminal proceedings have been instituted.  Section 25(2) provides that "the coroner shall adjourn the inquest until such proceedings have been finally determined".</p>  <p>The group of amendments I am introducing makes provision for an adjournment along identical lines where the lead investigating agency regarding any criminal proceedings in relation to the death of a person is not an Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, but the Defence Forces or the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission, GSOC.  This will only arise in a limited number of cases.  The amendments specify that the Defence Forces are the lead investigating agency only where the death is that of a person who is subject to military law, under the Defence Acts 1954 to 2015.  This will be the case for members of the Defence Forces who die while in active service, or in service custody.  </p>  <p>The amendments also specify that GSOC is the lead investigating agency only where there is a GSOC investigation under Part 4 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 into the death in question.</p> <p>That is provided for in the definition of "relevant Ombudsman Commission investigation" contained in section 2 of the Bill.</p> <p>Section 18 inserts a new section 33A into the principal Act, making more comprehensive and detailed provision on the categories of deaths where the coroner has a duty to direct a post mortem examination.  That section  already makes mandatory provision for a post mortem examination in cases where An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, or the Defence Forces or GSOC as lead investigating agency, so requests.  I am proposing to make several amendments to section 18 to refer more precisely to the scope of Defence Forces and GSOC investigations and for consistency with the other amendments in this grouping.</p> <p>Section 40(3) of the principal Act provides that the coroner is not obliged to empanel a jury for an inquest sitting at which a Garda officer of rank not lower than inspector will apply for adjournment on the grounds that criminal proceedings into the death concerned are being considered or have already been instituted.  These amendments make changes to section 40(3) to avoid an obligation to empanel a jury unnecessarily, where the adjournment is requested by an appropriate officer of the Defence Forces or of GSOC in the small range of cases where that body, and not An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, is the lead investigating agency.  The amendments reflect existing practice, but it is preferable to make express statutory provision in this regard.</p> <p>Amendment No. 2 is the most substantial amendment in this grouping.  It amends section 25 of the Principal Act to provide that the coroner shall adjourn an inquest on the request of an appropriate officer of the Defence Forces or of GSOC in the specific range of deaths where either of those bodies is the lead investigating agency under statute and is considering criminal proceedings in respect of the death or such proceedings have been instituted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.233" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.234" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Sections 14 to 17, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.235" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>SECTION 18</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.236" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 3:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.237" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.238" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 4:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.239" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.240" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.241" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.242" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.243" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.244" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 7:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.245" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.246" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 18, as amended, stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600014#Q01600"><p>I give notice to Senators of my intention to introduce a further technical amendment to this section on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.248" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.249" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Sections 19 to 22, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.250" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.251" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 8:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.252" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.253" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Section 23 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.254" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Sections 24 to 29, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.255" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>SECTION 30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.256" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 30 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600014#Q02600"><p>I give notice of my intention to bring forward an administrative amendment to this section on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.258" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.259" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Sections 31 and 32 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.260" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.261" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 9:</p><p>33. The Principal Act is amended by the insertion of the following section after section 61 (inserted by section 32):
&quot;62. (1) A coroner may, whenever he or she considers it appropriate to do so, apply to the High Court for directions on a point of law regarding the performance of his or her functions under this Act in relation to the death of any person.</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600014#Q03200"><p>This is an important and substantive amendment which inserts into the Bill a new power for a coroner to seek directions from the High Court on any doubtful or difficult point of law arising in the exercise of his or her functions.  While coroners normally determine questions of fact, difficult questions of law do arise occasionally on a range of issues relating to the exercise of their functions.  Such issues might, for example, include the procedural rights of interested parties at inquest or the interpretation of the European Convention of Human Rights on a new or difficult issue.  Currently, coroners have no legal avenue to seek direction from the courts on such points of law.  The main avenue of clarification is judicial review proceedings, which have to be taken by an interested party rather than by the coroner.</p><p>For these reasons, coroners strongly support and have long sought a case-stated facility.  The text used here is similar to the consultative case-stated procedure used in section 4A of the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) (Amendment) Act 1997, as inserted by section 3 of the Tribunals of Inquiry (Evidence) (Amendment) Act 2004<i>, </i>and in the Coroners Bill 2007.  It is a special provision which is to be used at the discretion of the coroner.  Interested parties at inquest will continue to be entitled to seek judicial review if, in their view, a coroner has made a wrong decision as a matter of law.  The case-stated provision has a different purpose.  It is there to enable coroners to seek guidance from the High Court on a difficult or unexplored point of law relating to the exercise of their functions.  I do not expect that it will need to be used frequently, but I do expect that it will be used judiciously by coroners from time to time.  As such, it will greatly assist in clarifying and developing our coronial law.  I ask Senators to support this important amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.263" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.264" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>SECTION 33</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="12:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600014#Q03500"><p>Amendments Nos. 10 to 12, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.266" nospeaker="true" time="12:15:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 10:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:15:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600014#Q03700"><p>These amendments insert into the Bill a further provision for situations where a designated GSOC officer is assisting the coroner, in place of a garda, in a death which is also the subject of a GSOC investigation under Part 4 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005.  Section 33 of the Bill already inserts a new section 101A into the 2005 Act to make express provision for a GSOC designated officer to perform the assistance functions expressly set out for a garda in the Coroners Act 1962 and provide such other assistance to the coroner as would normally be provided by a garda in regard to the inquest.</p> <p>The proposed amendments Nos. 10 to 12, inclusive, add a new subsection to a new section 101A of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 to add, for the avoidance of any doubt, that while performing such functions or providing such assistance, the GSOC designated officer continues to have all the powers, immunities and privileges, and all the duties and obligations of a member of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, whether statutory or common law.  Such immunities and privileges should be expressly provided to avoid any possible risk of purely technical legal defects in the officer, for example, entering on private property to serve a summons.  I ask for support for the amendment.</p> <p>Amendment No. 11 is a technical amendment.  Amendment No. 12 is the substantive amendment in this grouping.  As I have already outlined, it adds a new subsection to a new section 101A of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 to add, for the avoidance of any doubt, that while performing statutory functions of assistance to the coroner&rsquo;s inquiry into a death or otherwise assisting the coroner in relation to the inquest into that death in place of a garda, a GSOC designated officer will have all the powers, immunities and privileges enjoyed by a member of an Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, whether statutory or common law.  Again, I ask that the amendment be supported.</p> <p>For the benefit of Senators, in particular Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile who raised this matter, I have a small number of further amendments which are being finalised, subject to the advice of the Attorney General, and which I hope to table on Report Stage.  These include a possible provision to extend the retirement age of coroners from 70 to 72 years; a possible further administrative updating of provisions regarding, in particular, the Dublin coroner district; and a provision setting out general rules and guiding principles for the making of detailed regulations on appropriate and respectful treatment of human tissue or organs removed for post mortem or inquest.  I am keen that we move to Report Stage next week and I do not expect that there will be any delay in finalising these decisions.  The amendments will be circulated in advance of the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.269" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.270" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 11:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.271" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.272" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 12:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.273" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.274" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Section 33, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.275" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Sections 34 to 36, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.276" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Schedule agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.277" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.278" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="12:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600015#R00800"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600015#R00900"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.281" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Report Stage ordered for Tuesday, 2 July 2019.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.282" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600015#R01100">Perjury and Related Offences Bill 2018: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="12:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600015#R01200"><p>Before we commence, I remind Senators that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment who may reply to the discussion on the amendment.  Also on Report Stage, each non-Government amendment must be seconded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.284" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600015#R01400"><p>Amendment No. 1 is to provide for the inclusion of tribunals of inquiry and commissions of investigation within the scope of the Bill.  On the application of the offence of perjury and related offences, the legal advice I have received indicates that those particular forms of proceedings are not involved in the administration of justice <i>per se</i>.  One possible problem with the Bill, therefore, is that it appears to define a proceeding as primarily involving the administration of justice and then states that this includes tribunals.  A question might arise if this formula includes tribunals of inquiry as well as decision-making tribunals.  A tribunal of inquiry or commission of investigation does not administer justice.  They are concerned exclusively with the finding of facts.  I am proposing, therefore, with the consent of Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh and others, that the definition of judicial or other proceedings is revised for the purposes of this Bill to remove the reference to administration of justice and to include the tribunals of inquiry as well as decision-making tribunals within its defined legal meaning.  If we adopt this amendment, it will effectively broaden the scope in which a statutory offence of perjury may be prosecuted.  Broadening the scope of this legislation such that perjury may be statutorily prosecuted, both within fact-finding courts and tribunals as well as in tribunals of inquiry, is a laudable objective in pursuit of fact-finding, truth and honesty across all forms of official legal proceedings.  I trust that Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh has no difficulty with this amendment and I welcome his support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="12:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600015#R01500"><p>I strongly agree with this Government amendment and I understand the strategy and aim behind it.  It strengthens the Perjury and Related Offences Bill that my team and I drew up.  I support the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.287" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="12:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600015#R01700"><p>Amendments Nos. 2, 3 and 8 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  However, as none of the signatories to the amendments is present, they will not be moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.289" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.290" nospeaker="true" time="12:25:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 4:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.291" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:25:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600015#R02000"><p>The purpose of this amendment is to bring the penalties provision in this Private Members' Bill in line with those of the Civil Liability and Courts Act 2004, which, <i>inter alia</i>, stipulates penalty levels for false evidence and fraudulent claims.  I propose to amend the relevant section of this Bill rather than that of the 2004 Act in terms of the maximum penalty on indictment for this type of offence because the 2004 Act reflects Government policy in this jurisdiction.  There is the question of the changing value of money over time, given that it has been 15 years since the 2004 Act came into force.  I am satisfied to specify the amount of &euro;100,000 for the purpose of proposing an amendment to this section.  The penalty provision as it stands provides for a coherence within the equivalent penalties provided for in Northern Ireland in terms of the maximum penalty on indictment.  It is somewhat more important and appropriate to ensure consistency of provisions in this jurisdiction.  Assuming this amendment is passed, the maximum penalty on indictment for which a person may be liable on conviction under this legislation is, therefore, imprisonment for a term of ten years, a fine of &euro;100,000 or both.</p> <p> The purpose of this amendment is to send a clear message to would-be abusers of court time that the utterance of deliberate falsehoods and the making of false statements during legal proceedings will, if proven, not go unpunished and may result in very serious consequences for the individual concerned.  I am confident that this measure will go a long way towards deterring those who may be considering providing dishonest evidence in the course of legal proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S00200"><p>Ar&iacute;s tugaim taca&iacute;ocht don leas&uacute; seo.  I support this Government amendment, which was created in consultation with me and my team.  It contains one real, substantive change whereby the maximum sentence for perjury has been increased from seven years to ten.  We originally had a sentence of seven years in order to be in line with the situation in Northern Ireland and the UK.  On reflection, and following conversations and meetings with the Minister's officials, we understand and accept the rationale of changing it to ten years to create consistency with legislation in Ireland.  I am very happy to accept these changes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.294" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S00400"><p>Government amendments Nos. 5 to 7, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.296" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 5:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S00600"><p>These amendments are grouped together as they are technical in nature and correct a cross-referencing error in sections 17(2), 17(3) and 17(4).  I do not believe that there is any great need to have a considered debate on this.  I ask for the support of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.298" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.299" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 6:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.300" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.301" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 7:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.302" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S01300"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p><blockquote>In page 19, to delete lines 21 to 24.</blockquote><p>This was part of a suite of amendments and the earlier ones have not been moved.  I wanted to draw the Minister's attention to a problem that exists in respect of witnesses being sworn in during proceedings.  They are required to justify an affirmation by explaining their religious beliefs.  The Law Society, as I understood-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S01400"><p>I do not wish to impress anything on the Seanad which might not be in conformity with Standing Orders but I am here week after week after week and am pulled up on technicalities all the time.  My understanding was that these amendments were already the subject of an invitation to speak, which was not responded to in spite of the presence in the Chamber of one of the proponents.  I am in the hands of the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S01500"><p>I understand that Senator McDowell has the right to move the amendment at any point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S01600"><p>I just wanted to draw to the Minister's attention the views of the Law Society that there should be an amendment to the law.  That is all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.307" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.308" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.309" nospeaker="true" time="12:35:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.310" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S02000"><p>It is only right that we pay tribute to the person, Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh, who put all the work in.  I congratulate him on something significant.  We are here to pass legislation and this is certainly a very good day.  It is great to see people being able to get Private Members' Bills over the line.  I also thank the Minister for his co-operation with Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh and others in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.311" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S02100"><p>I commend the Senators on bringing this Bill forward.  It is long awaited and we are very proud to support it.  It is a very real piece of the puzzle of solving the high insurance costs that businesses face.  Successive Governments have failed to do this and I am very glad that some Independent Senators took the initiative and put this Bill forward.  I am also very glad it has received such support in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.312" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="12:35:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600016#S02200"><p>This is a very big day for me.  During my time in the Seanad, I have sometimes asked whether I am really making a contribution, although I do give it my best shot.  I suppose that is human nature.  The Bill is the culmination of a personal journey.  It shows how sometimes, even without power, resources or the backing of a Department or the Attorney General, good laws can be formulated by individuals.  It shows the importance of the Upper House and validates the work that Senators McDowell, Norris and others have done to protect its relevance.</p>  <p>We are fortunate to have the support of some excellent drafters.  I availed of this support and I especially thank Kieran Mooney for his contribution to the creation of this robust Bill.  The journey focused on a number of significant stakeholder consultations.  I reached out to the Minister and I greatly appreciate his very active support for the Bill.  I thank An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, the Director of Public Prosecutions, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission, the Law Reform Commission, the Bar Council, the Law Society, the Irish Council for Civil Liberties, the Rape Crisis Centre, the Irish SME Association, ISME, Victim Support and others.  ISME in particular put the prospect of placing perjury on a statutory footing firmly on the public agenda.  I pay tribute to the campaign it ran on behalf of its members, many of whom are penalised through high insurance premiums precisely because of perjury being committed within and outside the jurisdiction of our courts.  Up to now, there have been virtually no prosecutions in respect of this crime.  In the past ten years, there have only been 31 recorded incidents of perjury in our courts.  Placing perjury on the Statute Book is not just about penalising those who commit perjury.  It is primarily about preventing them from doing it in the first instance.  That is a big motivator for changing the sentence from seven to ten years.  Tough sanctions may make someone think twice about lying and diverting the course of justice.</p>  <p>I hope the Bill will have a practical impact on business, especially small businesses.  Over the years, I have personally known scores of small business owners who have suffered significantly because someone knowingly lied in court.  In some cases, their businesses went under as a direct result of people committing perjury.  My initiative to place perjury on a statutory footing as a criminal offence is not just about addressing fraudulent personal injury claims, although it is a very important component.  It is about bringing accountability to all those who lie in our courts, commissions and tribunals.</p>  <p>I wish to pay special tribute to the two officials seated behind the Minister, who have worked very actively with me, my team and my personal assistant, C&aacute;it Nic Amhlaoibh, in bringing this Bill to fruition.  Anyone who has the misfortune of facing into court proceedings or giving jury service knows that every day of the week there are people taking oath or swearing an affidavit stating facts that they know to be false.  As a nation, we have endured multiple tribunals and commissions of inquiry that have taken place while knowing that people have lied.</p> <p>In some cases, we discovered years later that blatant lies materially affected the course of justice without any consequences for the liar.  There are people guilty of heinous crimes such as assault, sexual assault, robbery and extortion walking our streets because somebody went into court and lied on their behalf.  Unfortunately, the innocent parties in such circumstances suffered greatly.  I hope that such suffering will be significantly reduced as a result of the Bill.</p> <p>I wish to thank my Independent colleagues, our researcher, Mr. James Geoghegan, and the departmental officials.  We are privileged to have such good and committed civil servants in the Department.  It gives me great confidence in the Department of Justice and Equality and in the Minister, as its head, in regard to the Bill.  I thank the members of all political parties and none who have supported the Bill.  I deeply appreciate it.  I hope that our colleagues in the D&aacute;il will pass this much-needed legislation in order that the President can sign it into law. I appreciate the cross-party support for the Perjury and Related Offences Bill 2018.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.314" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T00200"><p>On behalf of the Government, I acknowledge the importance of this legislation and the leadership by Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh and his team in this regard.  The Government fully supports the Bill and its intention to provide for the first time a statutory framework to hold to account persons who engage in deceitful activity or fraudulent behaviour in their submission of sworn testimony or statements across various forms of judicial or other proceedings.</p>  <p>I wish to acknowledge the deterrent effect of the legislation.  It will act as a bulwark against vexatious and dishonest evidence.  It is likely to be a very welcome development, particularly in regard to the cost of insurance, as has been stated.  It is part of a package of measures dealing with insurance issues such as fraud and exaggerated claims.  Of course, it will also have a more general application.  It is a clear message to anybody engaged in legal proceedings that they need to be mindful of the need to tell the truth at all times and that any deliberate departure from the truth may have serious consequences in terms of the level of sanctions and penalties which may be imposed at the discretion of the judge or court should that be deemed appropriate.</p>  <p>I again acknowledge the leadership of Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh in particular as the main sponsor of the Bill and, indeed, the members of his background team.  In particular, he mentioned Mr. James Geoghegan - now Councillor James Geoghegan - who I thank for his efforts on the Bill and his influence over the Independent Group-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.315" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T00300"><p>The Minister never misses a trick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.316" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T00400"><p>------which I hope will continue, notwithstanding his election as a member of the Fine Gael group on his local authority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.317" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T00500"><p>I say "Well done" to the Minister.  One must hand it to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.318" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T00600"><p>I acknowledge the input of my officials, who were active in ensuring that the Bill was proofed and who proposed several amendments in order to facilitate the passage of the legislation as we approach the summer recess.  I look forward to further engaging with Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh on the Bill until it is completed in its entirety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.319" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T00700"><p>I join the Minister in thanking Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh for his contribution.  Sorry, I was not aware that Senator McDowell was waiting to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.320" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T00800"><p>I wish to add my words of congratulations to Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh on taking the initiative to start the process which led to the Bill passing through the House.  When he came to our Independent Group with this proposal, it seemed to me that he faced a number of insurmountable odds, but he has, by his industry and persistence, brought all the parties in the House with him.  He brought the Government, the Minister, the Department of Justice and Equality and many bodies in civil society on board as well.  It is a great tribute to him that he has had this success and I warmly congratulate him on his achievement.</p>  <p>As he and the Minister stated, there must be consequences for perjury.  There has been a period during which, on the face of it, many offences of perjury have been committed without sanction.  The great advantage of what the Senator has achieved is that he has extended the prosecutable category of perjury on a clear statutory basis to tribunals of inquiry, commissions of inquiry and other tribunals where, as we have seen shocking deception has previously taken place, apparently without consequence.  That is a sad fact borne out by the Moriarty report, for example.</p>  <p>It is one thing to enact a law; it is another to prosecute for a breach of that law.  I hope that the Department, which has an overarching role in this matter, will bring to the attention of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in particular that this is a serious offence and that resources must be made available when instances become apparent for its proper investigation and prosecution.  As Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh stated, some people who have small businesses and are not insured can be put out of business and made bankrupt by a lie, even if they have CCTV footage to back up their side of the story.  Their businesses and livelihoods and their families' livelihoods are put in peril by such behaviour and mendacity.</p>  <p>I again warmly congratulate the Senator on his courage, initiative, persistence and success in bringing the Bill before the House.  I thank the Minister, his departmental officials and all the other people who have been mentioned, including Councillor Geoghegan, for all of their influence, to use the Minister's phrase,  as well as their co-operation and goodwill in getting the Bill passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.321" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T00900"><p>I concur with fellow Senators and congratulate Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh on the Bill.  It is interesting because it highlights a couple of things, as the Senator indicated, such as the importance of this House and the ability to move this type of legislation.  It also highlights the importance of the fact that legislation needs to move with the times as something that was not a problem a few years ago has become a very significant problem.  The current culture and climate of litigation and claims makes the Bill even more relevant and appropriate.  I applaud the Senator for his endurance, tenacity and persistence.  There were obstacles but, as he stated, the Bill received cross-party support.  Congratulations to all those involved, including the Minister and the staff and officials who worked on the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.322" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:45:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600017#T01000"><p>T&aacute; ardmholadh tuillte ag an Seanad&oacute;ir &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh.  N&iacute; rud furasta &eacute; a leith&eacute;id de reachta&iacute;ocht a chur tr&iacute;d an Teach, fi&uacute; mar bhall de ph&aacute;irt&iacute; polait&iacute;ochta, agus n&iacute; rud &eacute;asca &eacute; do Sheanad&oacute;ir neamhsple&aacute;ch ach go h&aacute;irithe.  Ta s&eacute; d&eacute;anta ag an Seanad&oacute;ir go h&eacute;ifeachtach, mar at&aacute; r&aacute;ite.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam, mar a d&uacute;irt an Seanad&oacute;ir McDowell, go gcuirfear leis an reachta&iacute;ocht seo agus go mbeimid in ann cur i l&aacute;thair &eacute;ifeachtach a fheice&aacute;il i measc an ch&oacute;rais taobh amuigh de na Tithe seo.  I echo the words of congratulations for Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh.  It is not an easy process to bring legislation so effectively and unanimously through the House but, as Senator Marshall rightly stated, Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh has done so with great tenacity and in a great spirit of collaboration.</p>  <p>The core premise of the legislation is to consolidate and simplify the law.  It aims to enable more effective punishment of those who commit the crime of perjury.  I agree with Senator McDowell - worryingly, that is a common occurrence for me in this House - when he states that it is one thing to enact legislation such as this, but another entirely for it to be effectively implemented and enforced.</p> <p>For all of the reasons that have been highlighted by colleagues, that is what we need to see happen beyond the realms of this place.  Molaim an Seanad&oacute;ir &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh.  Go n-&eacute;ir&iacute; leis an reachta&iacute;ocht seo.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.324" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600018#U00200"><p>I join with the previous Senators and speakers regarding the success of this Bill.  I wholeheartedly congratulate my colleague, Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh, for, as someone said, his tenacity, persistence and focus.  I acknowledge the role of the Minister and his Department with regard to this legislation.  With regard to new politics, this proves that when people collaborate and sometimes compromise with each other, we can achieve good things.  This is a good Bill.  Not many Independent politicians get a Bill through these Houses.  Well done to all involved who participated and engaged in this process because that is the important thing about politics, lawmakers and making legislation.  Well done in particular to Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh, who took the initiative, ran with it and stuck with it.  He made it an issue that he was personally involved with.  That is his style.  He champions things and he gets them over the line.  I thank the Minister for his support and co-operation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.325" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="12:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600018#U00300"><p>I join with my colleagues in congratulating my fellow countyman, Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh, for bringing forward this Bill.  I know that this issue of fraudulent claims, etc., goes back a long way in Galway.  The Galway business community will be extremely proud of their local son who has brought this Bill forward.  I congratulate the Senator.  It says much to his character, his ability to bring people onside and to get them behind an idea.  It has shone through in this Bill, which he must be proud of.  Those who engage with him and the business people of Galway will be proud of what he has done.</p>  <p>I will turn to the Minister.  Not every Minister is open to a new Bill being introduced by an Independent Member.  I congratulate the Minister and his staff for their willingness to listen to the arguments from Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh, to offer advice and assistance, and to the Minister for sitting here calmly and working his way through the Bill with the group.  I appreciate what the Minister has done.  I know that when this gets to the D&aacute;il, he will be equally agreeable in trying to move this forward, because I think he too is committed to it.  I am delighted that the Independent Group in the Seanad provided sufficient training for Councillor Geoghegan to make it to the position of councillor for Fine Gael.  If Fine Gael has anybody else who needs training, feel free to send them our way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.326" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600018#U00400"><p>We might even bring Senator Craughwell on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.327" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="12:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600018#U00500"><p>Senator Craughwell was already discussing training on the Order of Business and it did not go too well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.328" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600018#U00600"><p>They trained Senator Craughwell well before he left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.329" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="12:55:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600018#U00700"><p>I join with colleagues in congratulating Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh and his co-sponsor colleagues.  I am aware of his success in business over many decades.  It is quite obvious that if one puts one's mind to something, one can achieve it.  I am glad that that is being extended to politics.  I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.330" nospeaker="true" time="12:55:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.331" nospeaker="true" time="12:55:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.45 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.332" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600019#FF00100">Industrial Relations (Amendment) Bill 2018: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.333" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Sections 1 and 2 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.334" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.335" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.336" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 3 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.337" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600019#FF00700"><p>I accept that our amendment has been ruled out of order, but I hope the Minister of State, Deputy Breen, will note the sentiment behind it.  He referred last week to the review that is being conducted.  He may be aware that we had some lively discussion in this House earlier today on issues relating to the Defence Forces.  We have asked that the Taoiseach come to the Seanad to address our wider concerns in this regard.  The aspects of this legislation relating to the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na are welcome, but we must look now to extending the same courtesy to members of the Defence Forces.  To reiterate, these provisions do not give garda&iacute; the right to strike but, rather, to have recourse to the industrial relations apparatus of the State to resolve issues.  I hope the Minister of State will agree to address our concerns in legislation before too long.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.338" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.339" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Sections 4 and 5 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.340" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.341" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment and received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.342" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.343" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="13:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600019#FF01300"><p>I take this opportunity to convey to the Leas-Chathaoirleach my deepest sympathy on the loss of his mother last week.  Losing a mother, no matter what age one is, is never easy.  I wish to put that on the record of the House in which the Leas-Chathaoirleach has such an important role.</p>  <p>I reassure Senator Mac Lochlainn that it is not the case that no progress is being made in respect of the Defence Forces on the issue of industrial relations mechanisms.  Members of the forces have recourse in law to a parallel complaint and adjudication mechanism to compensate for the limitations on their access to the industrial relations machinery that is available to wider society.  Members of the Defence Forces are unlike workers in other sectors in that they have an important and particular role to play.  They do, however, have recourse to the Defence Forces Ombudsman, Defence Forces representative associations and the conciliation and arbitration scheme for members of the forces.</p>  <p>As the Senator acknowledged, I referred on Second Stage to the independent review that was completed last year.  It recommended that the official side should, with the consent of the Minister, engage in discussions with the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, ICTU, to explore the practicalities of a Permanent Defence Force Representative Association forming associations and affiliations with ICTU while also giving due consideration to any likely conflict that might arise between such an arrangement and the obligations of military service.  Dialogue has commenced between the Department of Defence and ICTU in this regard.  There are a lot of issues to be debated internally before further progress is possible, but it is an important step in that direction.  We should allow the engagement to continue and see what comes out of it.</p>  <p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach and Senators for their engagement with the Bill, which completes a series of amendments to the Industrial Relations Act 1990.  It will enable members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to access the independent industrial relations machinery of the State, namely, the Workplace Relations Commissions and the Labour Court, to bargain collectively with the Garda Commissioner on matters relating to work conditions.  As such, it plays a small part in delivering aspects of the Government's ambitious Garda reform programme.  I acknowledge the invaluable work of the interdepartmental working group, chaired by Mr. John Murphy, which examined the industrial relations structures within the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and made recommendations on the policy underlying this Bill.  It is a complex area and there was a lot of work to be done, which the working group undertook in a collaborative fashion.</p> <p> I also acknowledge the invaluable co-operation of the Garda associations.  I appreciate that the Bill does not deliver all their ambitions but I believe they share my view, which I have stated previously in the House, that garda&iacute; are not simply "workers" in the everyday sense of that word.  We recognise that the police service is exceptional.  We also recognise the unique powers garda&iacute; have as guardians of the peace and our security and the importance of that.</p> <p>The Bill strikes the right balance between ensuring the public need for the essential services provided by the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is met and the right for employees to negotiate for appropriate employment standards.  I hope it can be sent to the President as soon as possible to be signed.  Senators have done good work on the legislation and I appreciate the time the various spokespersons have put into it.  I thank them for their full co-operation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.345" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="13:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600020#GG00200"><p>I commend the Minister of State on the Bill, which is a great job of work.  I would also like to be associated with his words on the Leas-Chathaoirleach's late mother.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach has always been extremely fair.  On behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party, I extend sincerest condolences and sympathy to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.346" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600020#GG00300"><p>I thank Senator Davitt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.347" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="13:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600020#GG00400"><p>I conveyed my condolences to the Leas-Chathaoirleach on the loss of his mother in person but I would like to do so again in the House.  I agree with Senator Davitt that the Leas-Chathaoirleach is highly regarded in this House.  We are very sorry for his loss.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.348" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="13:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600020#GG00500"><p>I, too, commiserated with the Leas-Chathaoirleach privately but I would like to do so publicly as well, both on my behalf and on behalf of the Fine Gael Party.</p>  <p>I commend the Minister of State on introducing the Bill.  It is an important step forward in providing a mechanism for those who lay their lives on the line to keep the rest of us safe.  It is important that they do not have to resort to other methods and that there is a mechanism in place to allow them to air grievances and raise issues.  This is a quantum leap forward on which I congratulate the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.349" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:05:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019062600020#GG00800"><p>I thank the Senators and the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.350" nospeaker="true" time="13:05:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.351" nospeaker="true" time="13:05:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.42 p.m. and resumed at 4.06 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-06-26a.352" nospeaker="true" time="13:05:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>