<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#A00200"><p>I have notice from Senator Thomas Byrne that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br /><br />The need for the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to meet residents of Br&uacute; na B&oacute;inne, County Meath, and to listen and respond to the concerns expressed by them at a public meeting organised by her Department on 26 February regarding the draft management plan for Br&uacute; na B&oacute;inne.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Bradford of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to state whether he will consider the reintroduction of town councils as part of the fabric of local government and local democracy.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#A00350">Heritage Sites</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#A00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Tom Hayes.  It would appear that the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht is busy.  I ask that the Minister responsible for Br&uacute; na B&oacute;inne, whom I understand to be Deputy Heather Humphreys, would meet a delegation of residents from the area.  We are talking here about a very important part of our country and an important site of world heritage, including the Newgrange, Dowth and Knowth areas, which encompasses half of the parish of Slane and almost the entire parish of Donore in County Meath.  A major public meeting was organised last week by the Department which I attended with my party colleague, Councillor Wayne Harding.  It is fair to say that there was bitter anger among the residents at the way they are being treated.  They feel that their entitlement to live in a community and for that community to carry on is being threatened, not just by the actions of the Department but also by the actions of the local authority.  Indeed, my colleague, Councillor Harding, will be raising this matter with the local authority again, having done so previously.</p> <p>Everybody in the Br&uacute; na B&oacute;inne area and in County Meath generally is exceptionally proud of the heritage that has been left to us by our forefathers.  We have some of the most important works of megalithic art and the most important megalithic tombs in the world.  Albeit from a different era entirely, it is the equivalent of the Louvre in terms of the importance of the art there.  The art is of the same standard and of equal importance as that in the Louvre, and the community values that enormously.  In fact, many members of the community in Br&uacute; na B&oacute;inne have worked on the excavations at Newgrange and Knowth or in the interpretative centre, while some continue to work on the bus service that runs between the interpretative centre and the monuments.</p> <p>Enormous restrictions have been put in place through the actions of the Department and the local authority, particularly with regard to planning for one-off houses.  Nobody is looking to develop this area or is calling for mass building or anything like that.  All people are looking for is for the life of the community in that area to continue.  People want their children to be able to live in the area in which they grew up.  We want to preserve this very important heritage but we also want to make sure that the community is preserved there too.  It was the forefathers of some of those living in the community who built these monuments and that is a fact.  Many of the families to whom I refer have been living in this community since time immemorial.</p> <p>I would suggest that the Minister should listen to the concerns of the local people.  I would hate to think that last week's meeting was a box-ticking exercise for the Department.  I hope departmental officials do not feel that the public consultation process is out of the way now and that they can roll ahead with their plans, along with the local authority.  I would like last week's meeting to serve as a starting point for meeting some of the requirements of the residents.  It should be possible to arrive at a happy medium whereby we preserve the important heritage of Br&uacute; na B&oacute;inne while also allowing the indigenous community to thrive.  Nobody is looking for outsiders to be allowed to build houses there, nor does anybody want to build housing estates.  Nobody wants to build a house that would do any damage to any monument or view in that area.  They simply want people to be allowed to live within their own community.  That is a very simple request by people who value and treasure the history and heritage of the area more than anybody.</p> <p>Other concerns raised at the meeting last week related to signage, which has been a disaster for years.  There are still no concrete plans by the Department to mark this very important world heritage site with welcome signs and with signage pointing visitors in the direction of the monuments and the interpretative centre.  Much of the signage there at present is completely wrong and has been for a long time.</p> <p>The other concerns expressed related to the fact that the tourism potential of the area has never been fully developed.  The community, the local authority and the Department, which has a very important role as the State body dealing with UNESCO on the world heritage site status, could work together and come up with a plan that occupies the middle ground.  It should be noted that many members of the community have done a huge amount of groundwork and have an enormous amount to offer.  They can make suggestions that would not be contrary to world heritage status but which would complement it and also complement the life of the community.</p> <p>Will the Minister of State ask the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht to meet a delegation from the community and listen to their concerns in order that last week's meeting does not represent a box-ticking exercise in terms of public consultation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1089" speakername="Tom Hayes" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#A00500"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter and apologise on behalf of the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Heather Humphreys, who is unavailable due to other commitments outside the House today.  However, the Minister is very much aware of the concerns of the Senator.</p> <p>The UNESCO world heritage committee requires every property inscribed on the world heritage site list to have a management plan or other documented management system in place that explains how its outstanding universal value will be preserved.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Tom Hayes:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=1807"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1807&amp;amp;pid=TomHayes&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Outstanding universal value is a fundamental requirement for retaining world heritage status.  The Operational Guidelines for the Implementation of the World Heritage Convention, issued by UNESCO in July 2013, set out the issues that need to be addressed as part of the management plan for a world heritage site.   UNESCO also provides guidelines on what content must go into the plan before it can be submitted to the organisation for approval.</p><p>A new draft Br&uacute; na Boinne Management Plan, to replace the previous plan that dates back to 2002, has been prepared in accordance with the UNESCO guidelines.   The draft needs to be finalised and submitted to UNESCO as soon as possible.  In accordance with UNESCO requirements, the main responsibility for implementation of the plan is shared between the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht and the Office of Public Works.</p><p>The development of the present draft management plan has taken place over the past four years, during which there have been two periods of public consultation, one of which is still ongoing.  Observations were initially invited from the public in April 2011.  Fifty-seven submissions were received by the Department, all of which were considered in the course of the drafting that has taken place since.  A special public meeting was also held on site in June 2011 to improve community awareness of the plan.</p><p>The Br&uacute; na Boinne world heritage site management plan steering committee was established by the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht in 2011 to help oversee the preparation of the management plan.  The steering committee, which the Department chairs, is made up of local interest groups, officials from the Department and the OPW, along with representatives from Louth and Meath county councils, F&aacute;ilte Ireland, the Heritage Council, the International Council on Monuments and Sites Ireland and An Taisce.  Representatives from the Boyne Valley consultative committee and two local elected councillors also sit on the steering committee.</p><p>The draft plan sets out the key objectives and future vision for the management of the world heritage site.  It provides a framework for the proactive management of the site, helping to ensure that its outstanding universal value is sustained and preserved for future generations.  It informs and guides the day-to-day and long-term management of Br&uacute; na Boinne.</p><p>Agreement has been secured, at steering committee level, for the vast bulk of the actions set out in the current draft plan.  One new major initiative is the creation of an enhanced management structure for the Br&uacute; na Boinne site that includes a special community forum and other community involvement and oversight in the decision-making process.  The community forum will meet at least twice a year to oversee the implementation of the management plan and its proposed actions.  The forum will meet at the start of the year to consider and discuss the actions that can be implemented in the coming months, and again at the end of the year, when the Department and the OPW will report on progress made on agreed actions.</p><p>The Minister can understand that there are issues that continue to be of concern to some sections of the local community.  These include planning, with some community representatives looking for a separate planning system to be put in place for the world heritage site.  The draft plan, through consultation, seeks to accommodate all reasonable proposals.  Obviously not all aspirations are resolvable through the plan itself.  That said, two new actions directly related to planning are included in the draft plan.  These mean that there will be special recognition of the world heritage site in the administration of the planning systems in Counties Meath and Louth, with clear, precise and time-bound actions in place in regard to pre-planning consultations with prospective planning applicants.  There will also be specific guidance for potential planning applicants on the site and the design of proposed new developments.</p><p>The present position of the draft plan is that the Department and the OPW have invited the public to make written submissions which can be lodged any time up to and including 20 March 2015.  This is an important process which allows all members of the community to express their views, offer opinions and have their say about what is in the plan.  Apart from updating the general strategy for conserving and managing the world heritage site, the public can also comment on how it should address matters such as visitor management and public awareness, research, education, nature conservation, liaison with the local community and sustainable tourism.</p><p>All submissions received will be carefully reviewed and considered by the Department.  The Minister can assure the Senator that everything that can reasonably be taken on board will be built into the final draft.  That element is important to note in terms of the points made by the Senator.</p><p>As mentioned previously, the steering group is made up of a number of interested parties and, most importantly, includes local representatives.  I urge the Senator, as a public representative, to use this structure, which we do not use often enough.  Public representatives or Oireachtas Members should consult the local public representatives that are part of the group.  The Minister, Deputy Humphreys, encourages all concerned to avail of this opportunity for public input and to take part in the public consultation process.  I will relate the Senator's points to the Minister.  The consultation process that is in place should be availed of first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#B00200"><p>We are afraid that the public consultation process is merely a box-ticking exercise.  The evidence for such a belief is that the project was started back in 2011 and, as the Department's officials admitted at a meeting last week, very little has happened since.  The Department was restructured and there was a move from the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government to the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, etc.  The sections do not seem to have moved offices too much.</p> <p>As I have said already, there was bitter anger at the meeting due to the way this project has panned out.  The local councillors and residents on the consultative committee are not happy.  In fact, some of them are very angry.  As I suggested in my request, which was left unanswered, it would go a long way if the Minister were to meet the people, or even a delegation of those who are or have been members of the consultative committee, and the local councillors.  It would mean a lot if she could meet them and listen directly to their concerns.  Such a meeting would also be an opportunity for her to hear their sincere appreciation for the world heritage site, which is an acknowledgement of the location's beauty, history and art.  Let there be no mistake about that.  If she met them as part of the consultative process it would go a long way.  No reasonable Minister could fail to be moved by the stories of sons and daughters, nieces and nephews having to move out of a community.  The Minister of State would not put up with such a situation in his county of Tipperary or in any rural area.  It is unfair that this parish and a half must put up with such a situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1089" speakername="Tom Hayes" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#B00300"><p>I have listened to what the Senator has said, and I understand his concerns and that of the people.  It seems to me, having listened to him, that the local residents are deeply concerned about the project.  The best process for him to follow is to make sure and encourage residents to put their issues on paper and consult with the local public representatives who are on the committee.  I have a deep understanding of the situation from what he has said.  I will convey his concerns to the Minister and can assure him that she will take all of his concerns on board.</p> <p>At the end of the process there may be a reason for a meeting.  There is a process in place that should not be interfered with and I encourage the local community to participate.  All public representatives can understand that people in a community want to meet a Minister and air their views, but there is a process in place whereby every viewpoint can be listened to and taken on board.</p> <p>I assure people, notwithstanding their fears, that the Minister will look at and read all of their local concerns.  When that process has been finalised there may be room for a meeting.  I urge people not to miss the opportunity that presents itself now to make their concerns known.  I assure the Senator that I will relate his points and concerns about the project.  I live in an area that has the Rock of Cashel, and everyone would love if it were designated a world heritage site.  Br&uacute; na Boinne has been designated a world heritage site, which is unique, and the people of the region should be very proud.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#B00400"><p>I have said so a number of times.  We are extremely proud of the site and we love it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1089" speakername="Tom Hayes" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#B00500"><p>It is in everybody's interest that we work together.  I reiterate that I will relate all of the Senator's concerns that he raised this morning.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.16" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#B00600">Local Government Reform</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#B00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, who is from Tipperary.  It is the Minister from Tipperary who will make the final decision on the future of local government and the future of town councils.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Bradford:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=73"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=73&amp;amp;pid=PaulBradford&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Some people say Irish Water will be the legacy of EU Commissioner Hogan but the legacy with which he will be most associated, and it will be negative unless there are changes, are the new structures of local government.  There were elections to new local government structures in 2013 but those structures are a butchered, slimmed-down version of local democracy.  The public spin was that we were going to manage local politics with fewer councillors so town councils were abolished and replaced by municipal districts.  All of us have served on local authorities and all of us know the importance of localism to local government but we now have local authority areas which, in some cases, are 50, 60 or 70 miles long and that is not local government.  The savings from abolishing town councillors, who were on modest stipends, were cancelled out by creating additional county councillors and it is already apparent in many of our huge municipal districts that the current structures are not working.  </p><p>I am the first to recognise that town councils in some areas were not working well.  There were five town councils in my former constituency of Cork East.  Some worked very well but some less so and such a ratio would be replicated across the country.  On the whole, though, in the past 100 years town councils were the first recourse of politics and representation for tens of thousands of our citizens.  The person who walked up and down the main street of Cashel or Mallow always felt comfortable walking into the town hall to meet town council officials.  Sometimes they met town councillors, whom they often met on a daily basis anyway because they generally worked around the town.  There was great interaction between local politics and the local community.</p><p>I was very pleased to hear at the weekend from certain members of the Labour Party that consideration was being given to putting town councils back in place.  We will have to plan it in a very strategic fashion.  I have said to Senators down the years that if they went into the Oireachtas Library they would find the 1991 Barrington report on local government, which was accepted and agreed by virtually every political party at that time.  It proposed the replacement of town councils across the country by district councils with general populations of between 25,000 and 30,000, small geographical areas where the councillor would be local to his or her constituents.  That is one option, but new supercouncils, such as Cork County Council with 55 members, Dublin City Council with over 60 members and west Cork, which is 70 or 80 miles long and larger than most D&aacute;il constituencies, are not local government.  </p><p>There were difficulties with town councils, though some were excellent.  Some of the larger towns in the country did not have town councils while some small towns had functioning town councils but we need to look afresh at the structure.  It is nearly four years until the next local elections and we need to flag our intentions for local government at an early stage.  At a time when we are lecturing Europe on the need to practise devolution of powers down to smaller countries and communities, in this country we have taken power away from small towns and communities and from local citizens.  </p><p>I appreciate the fact that the Minister of State will not make the political call on this matter but he was aware of the great work done in Cashel, Tipperary, Carrick-on-Suir and other town councils in his constituency.  I hope some serious consideration is being given to the question by the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, and the Government and that it was not just a conference slogan.  Nobody can blame the previous Minister for making the decision he made and if people in politics are wrong it is not a sin.  Such decisions can be reversed.  I hope we will look at local government in a meaningful fashion to restructure it to give the citizens of this country what they need and deserve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1089" speakername="Tom Hayes" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Bradford for raising this issue and I acknowledge his contribution to local government and local government reform generally.  I apologise on behalf of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, who is otherwise engaged this morning.</p> <p>It is over two years since the Government published the action programme for effective local government, which set out decisions for a range of measures to reform and strengthen local government structures, functions, funding, governance and operational arrangements.  During that period, the focus has been directed at implementation of the extensive reform programme and progress has been swift.</p> <p>The Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, would like to make it clear that he will ensure that the fabric of local government and local democracy are fully intact and effective.  He does not consider, however, that the re-introduction of the pre-reform configuration of town councils would be the correct approach.  As the comments attributed recently to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, on this matter acknowledged, reform was needed in this area.  In some ways the system that operated up to last June was a distortion of democracy.  For example, 46% of all councillors represented only 14% of the population.  Residents inside the old town boundaries had double votes at local elections, while the often large population resident in towns but outside outdated boundaries were not served by the town council at all.  Indeed, many large centres of population had no sub-county municipality.</p> <p>Town councils did achieve worthwhile results but their capacity was very limited.  All the 80 town councils combined accounted for only 7% of local government activity and a significant number of them had no revenue-raising powers and no decision-making capacity in key areas such as housing, planning and roads.  It was not feasible to extend the powers, resources and jurisdiction of the town councils without seriously undermining the county councils.  Instead, a new integrated system of governance was introduced.  Municipal districts now cover the entire territory of each county, reflecting European norms, removing outdated boundaries and ending the anomaly of small towns having municipal status and dual representation, while some larger centres and rural areas lacked any sub-county governance.  As well as creating a more rational and comprehensive structural arrangement, the new system will result in more effective and community-focused decision making and implementation.  Moreover, under the new arrangements, there is full integration of local authority resources across each county and elimination of duplication both in administrative and electoral terms.  The status of the town is explicitly recognised in these new structures.  The mayor is appointed by the relevant district, and the title of "Mayor" can only be used in this context.</p> <p>An important benefit of the new system is a more appropriate assignment of local authority functions.  The performance of different functions by members at county and district levels over time will result in greater effectiveness than the previous parallel town and county system, which involved a significant element of duplication.  The division of functions between county and district levels has been determined on the basis of what is most relevant to each level.  Local matters are to be dealt with at municipal district level, while those of wider strategic application are being decided at county level, without duplication between county and district jurisdictions.</p> <p>It is important to bear in mind that we are in the very early stages of a reform process.  The provisions of the 2014 Act only came into effect on 1 June 2014 and 2015 will be the first full year of the operation of structural and other significant changes in the local government system.  However, it is essential to ensure that the new system is being operated effectively and as intended.  The Minister has already emphasised to chief executives the importance of fully supporting the role of the elected members at municipal district level.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Tom Hayes:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=1807"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1807&amp;amp;pid=TomHayes&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Equally, the members must take full ownership of their powers and responsibilities in this area as well as for the other new governance powers such as the statutory audit committees, annual service delivery plans, management reports, approval of new local authority corporate plans and adoption of schedules of municipal district works by municipal district members.  The structured training programme for councillors, which the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government is supporting, will help to ensure elected members are well-equipped to perform their governance functions effectively.</p><p>The Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Kelly, intends to have a review carried out on the operation of the new structures.  In this context, the Department is reconvening a working group for engagement with the Association of Irish Local Government and a broadly based advisory group, both having played an important role in the local government reform process.  The groups will give particular consideration to how the new governance arrangements are impacting on the towns and whether any adjustments are needed in light of experience to date, including civic aspects, such as the status of mayors of borough and municipal districts.  Moreover, these groups will have an important input into strengthening the role of the local government sector in economic development and the particular role to be played by urban centres.  The importance of the role to revitalise the economy of towns and their rural hinterlands has been emphasised in guidelines issued to local authorities by the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government.  The Minister, Deputy Kelly, expects action in this regard to feature prominently in the local economic and community plans that authorities are developing.  The experience of urban centres will be evaluated to ensure urban issues are being addressed effectively through the new structures.</p><p>The thrust of Government policy is to strengthen local government and foster the potential for improved subsidiarity, coherence and efficiency, resulting in greater value for money for the taxpayer and, ultimately, improving the services delivered for our citizens.  The review that the Minister is initiating will provide a sound evidence base upon which to consider any further changes to local government and local democracy, structural or otherwise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#D00200"><p>That there is no point in my shooting the messenger.  I know the Minister of State, Deputy Hayes, is speaking on behalf of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government.  The script represents the biggest U-turn I have heard in a long time.  Clear indications were given in print and oral interviews at the weekend that consideration was being given to having town councils restored.</p> <p>I am keen to raise one point with the Minister of State, although I imagine he is very much aware of it given that he comes from a large geographical county.  I wish to emphasise the importance of local government being local.  The Minister of State remarked in his reply - the script was provided by the office of the Minister, Deputy Kelly - that there was an affinity among the people within municipal districts.  The Minister of State should consider County Cork.  He need not tell me that he could possibly believe people outside Charleville, on the Limerick border, have any sort of political or geographical affinity with the people of the parishes of Conna and Ballynoe, near Tallow, County Waterford, yet, they are part of a single municipal district.  Certainly, I do not believe the people of Millstreet and the surrounding area have any political affinity to the Mallow municipal district in the centre.  What about the areas in west Cork that are 60, 70 or 80 miles away?  A former councillor, Dermot Sheehan, known to all of us through his father, remarked to me after the local elections that it would have been as easy for him to represent the congressional district of New York as the huge sprawling area where he had to contest the election.  We have got it fundamentally wrong.</p> <p>I find it ironic and I am sorry the Minister, Deputy Kelly, is not in the House.  The politics of stitching up these municipal authorities last year into eight, nine and ten-seaters was to save the party that lost all the seats.  That is the ultimate irony.  Leaving aside politics, the people need good strong local democracy.  The town councils were not perfect but they had and have a role to play.  I hope that long before the next local elections there will be a serious dialogue again about the need to restore genuine real local government whereby local actually means local.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1089" speakername="Tom Hayes" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#D00300"><p>Senator Bradford instanced the people outside Charleville <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>the people near County Waterford, and I can understand that.  That is a matter of the drawing of a boundary map.  It is not an argument, however, to bring back local town councils.</p><p>I served on a local authority in Tipperary.  The duplication between county and town councils was unbelievable, as was the waste of time and energy.  Officials at county level would address one meeting in the morning and then go on to address the town council that same night.  The amount of time taken up by officials was unbelievable and totally at variance with the delivery of services.  This is about the delivery of service to the people.  The purpose of local authorities is to deliver a better service.</p><p>Senator Bradford can signal what he likes but I have a real belief that what is happening in the new structures represents a major improvement on what was in place.  For example, let us consider the towns of Cahir and Cashel, which are beside one another.  Cahir was better served by South Tipperary County Council than Cashel.  That is the truth.  I have lived in Cashel and I have an office there and I know all about the duplication of services.  There was a serious waste of money and resources.</p><p>I accept the point Senator Bradford makes about people living outside Charleville not knowing people near Waterford, and that it is difficult for one person to represent all of them.  That is true and I take his point in that regard.  However, going back to the old structures of town councils would be a backward step.  I am not simply sticking to the script when I say that I would be totally opposed to going back there.  I really believe it.</p><p>At the weekend, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin, expressed his view, but that was a personal opinion.  The Government opinion is to move forward with and protect what we have and then improve it.  Senator Bradford is right in his views on the municipal areas and perhaps there could be an argument to cut in half the municipal areas, but the duplication of services and what we had in the past represented a great waste and we should not go back to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#D00400"><p>I fully agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1089" speakername="Tom Hayes" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#D00500"><p>We should not even contemplate it.  It cost ratepayers vast sums of money.  They are taxpayers, the paying public.  Businesses were closing left, right and centre because of the costly rates they were paying.  We need to move away from that.  There is a view within Government of the need to try to bring down the cost of rates to encourage people.  This is a way of doing that and of making local government more effective for the people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.25" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.10 a.m. and resumed at noon.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.26" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00200"><p>The Order of Business is No.1, Workplace Relations Bill 2014 - Committee Stage (resumed), to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00300"><p>I read in newspaper reports last weekend that the expert panel - I use that term loosely - which was looking into the airport pension scheme will meet again to have another look at what might be done to improve the position for the deferred members, in particular, of that scheme.  I have been raising this issue in this House for some time, as well as the fact that existing staff will not sign any waivers.  While the aforementioned meeting has been reported in the media, there has been no official announcement on this.  I have written to the Minister and ask the Leader to use his good offices to encourage the Minister to use the Seanad in the next week or two to provide an update on the situation.</p> <p>I wish to raise a very serious issue which came to light in recent years but which has been put into sharp focus in recent days, namely, the decision by the Government that the Dublin Fire Brigade ambulance service will be put under the effective control of the HSE.  Issues have been raised with regard to the HSE ambulance service although I must emphasise that these issues do not relate to the staff.  I know many of the HSE ambulance service staff in Dublin and they are very dedicated people who do an excellent job.  The Dublin Fire Brigade ambulance service that is provided in the city and county of Dublin is second to none.  If anything, we should be considering rolling out that model across the rest of the country because most of our major towns have fire stations and all of our firefighters are trained to paramedic level, with many trained to advanced paramedic level.  </p> <p>My major concern and that of my party is the fact that the local authority does not want to pay for the Dublin Fire Brigade ambulance service and is throwing that service to the HSE which cannot manage its own ambulance service.  This will be to the detriment of people of Dublin.  The Government should be looking at the option of a combined emergency service, and this will be part of Fianna F&aacute;il policy in the run-up to the next general election.  Such a combined service will ensure that all of our emergency resources are working together.  The situation at present appears to be one of the HSE winning a turf war.  </p> <p>The Minister for Health said on 3 March last that he is a big supporter of the Dublin Fire Brigade ambulance service.  If he was a real supporter he would have been true to the assurances he gave that nothing would happen without prior consultation with those who would be affected, namely, the Dublin Fire Brigade ambulance staff themselves.  There was no consultation whatsoever.  The Government is using last year's HIQA report as an excuse to bring about very significant changes which have not been thought through.  This situation is extremely serious for the city and county of Dublin.  If anything, we should be looking to replicate what is being provided by the Dublin Fire Brigade ambulance service in the other fire brigades all over the country in order to improve response times.  </p> <p>I ask that the Leader invite the Minister for Health to the House to discuss this matter and I will table an amendment to today's Order of Business to the effect-----  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00400"><p>When does the Senator wish to have a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00500"><p>Today, preferably.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00600"><p>We had a debate arranged with the Minister on Tuesday last.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00700"><p>He did not come to the House, as I understand it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00800"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K00900"><p>We should invite him in again.  Perhaps this time he will come to the House and he might even relent.  I propose an amendment to the Order of Business calling on the Minister for Health to come to the House to state Government policy on the ambulance service and to explain why there was no consultation with those affected.  This change should not be allowed to proceed and the Government can step in and ensure that it does not.  I ask that the Minister come to the House for half an hour today to make a statement and take questions from interested parties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#K01000"><p>I welcome yesterday's news of a further drop in unemployment figures.  The unemployment rate is now down to 10.1%, a dramatic fall over a number of years from the crisis peak of 15.1% when Fianna F&aacute;il presided over the economic crash.  This sustained fall in unemployment is very welcome.  We have had a number of debates in this House on job creation but I ask that we have a further debate on the issue before the end of the session to review the progress of the Action Plan for Jobs and to look at the Government's target of achieving full employment by 2018, which no longer seems as over ambitious as it was accused of being originally.  Certainly, the fall to 10.1% is very welcome and today there were more positive announcements concerning an investment by Microsoft and the opening of a new state-of-the-art facility by Glanbia in Kilkenny.  It is wonderful to see the great progress being made on job creation and the falls in unemployment.</p> <p>I also welcome the publication and passage of the Public Health (Standardised Packaging of Tobacco) Bill through this and the other House.  This makes Ireland a leader in tackling the harm associated with tobacco.  I commend the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Reilly and all the Members who supported that Bill.  It received a large amount of support from across the political divide.  </p> <p>I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on mental health in the context of the review of mental health legislation that has been carried out by the expert group commissioned by the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Kathleen Lynch.  The group reported today with 160 recommendations for changes to mental health law.  I note that the Minister of State has said that she accepts the recommendations and hopes to see them brought forward through legislation amending the Mental Health Act later this year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We might have a debate on that issue again in this House.  We have debated mental health and mental health legislation many times, but it would be good to have a debate in this House informed by the recommendations of this report, in particular by the recommendation that a human rights-based approach be taken.</p><p>I wish all colleagues a happy International Women's Day on 8 March.  I commend all the events that are happening throughout the country for International Women's Day.  I launched Trinity women's week on Monday to mark a programme of events for International Women's Day and around gender issues in Trinity College.  I know that other institutions throughout the country are doing the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L00200"><p>I raised the issue of requirements in subjects to enter universities two days ago and I have some updates on those.  There are proposals to remove mathematics and languages as entry requirements, and my correspondence indicates these are gathering pace.  Discussions are taking place in the University of Limerick and in UCC this week.  It is reported that UCD is totally in favour of the proposals and that TCD has dissented.  The Minister, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, said in this House that the report of the expert skills group indicated to her that we needed more language skills in Ireland and not less.  I do not believe she is being kept in the loop on these kinds of proposals.  We are members of a multilingual European Union and we should not be cutting back on languages.  Mathematics is the basis of all our investment in the science, technology, engineering and mathematics, STEM, subjects.  These proposals should be passed for consideration to the education committee chaired by Deputy Joanna Tuffy and the Minister should certainly be advised of them because they seem to contradict what we are seeking to accomplish in the development of this country.</p> <p>On a related aspect of the development of this country, I praise the Labour Party on its decision in Kenmare, or Killarney - I named the wrong town in Kerry-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L00300"><p>Both are very good towns, by the way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L00400"><p>Both are excellent.  The Labour Party took a stand against the British Airways IAG takeover of Aer Lingus.  Its members are looking after the interests of the workers.  We in this House have an interest in the development of this country.  Aer Lingus, in generating 11 million passengers for a population of 4 million people, is doing four times better than British Airways in generating 38 million passengers for a population of 64 million people.  If fellow Senators are interested in developing this country, we do not want a situation to develop where future Ministers with responsibility for tourism and industry have to telephone Heathrow to get flights into this country.  Aer Lingus, as a development agency, outperforms British Airways by a factor of four.  I ask the Senators to bear that in mind when this decision comes before their parties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L00500"><p>I seriously commend Commissioner Hogan on his commitment that by the year end we will have new legislation to eliminate the unfair treatment of suppliers to supermarkets.  As we know, the producers of food have been squeezed dry by the multiples and the large supermarkets over the years.  This is a serious game changer.  It is very significant news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L00600"><p>Does it include the bottles of water?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L00700"><p>I do not want to use crude language but we have talked about scata bull&aacute;n before.  The previous Commissioner failed to deal with this matter.  Commissioner Hogan deserves great credit for his speech and what he has now promised for the producers.  He said that this would happen before the end of the year.  He said that there has been a considerable reduction in the proportion of the margin and profitability going to the producer.  His proposal is that he is prepared to fine retailers up to 1% of turnover for unfair practices.  We must greatly welcome this news.  I commend him on it and on the other good work that he is doing.  I wish him very well today with Glanbia and with the other matters he is dealing with in Kilkenny and Waterford.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L00800"><p>I hope he is better with the milk than he was with the water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L00900"><p>I second the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by the Leader of the Opposition, Senator Darragh O'Brien, to invite the Minister to come into the House today.  If he has time between selling insurance for private companies, he might have an opportunity to drop into to us to report on the important issue that was raised.</p> <p>I draw to the Cathaoirleach's attention that it has been a precedent in this House that we do not refer to Members, whether they are present or not present or whether they have contributed or not contributed to debates.  I had to leave to go to another appointment yesterday.  Senator John Kelly referred to the fact that I was not present for the debate on the plain packaging of cigarettes Bill on Tuesday, 3 March, which was brought forward by the Minister, Deputy Reilly.  The fact is that this Bill was scheduled to be taken at 3.30 p.m. last Thursday, 26 February, when I would have been present and would have participated in that debate and I had my research done.  However, the Bill was pulled and was rescheduled for Tuesday, 3 March, when I was with the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs in London engaged on official business on the future of Europe and Britain's position in that regard.  I returned to Dublin and was in the House at 5.30 p.m. and, following a very short discussion, the Bill was completed.  I am not a very sensitive person about these things and I do not really care very much about them, but I ask the Cathaoirleach, who is a very fair person, if he will deal with that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01000"><p>I did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01100"><p>The Cathaoirleach dealt with it at the time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01200"><p>Senator Mooney made his case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01300"><p>I thank Senator Mooney for doing that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01400"><p>Senator Kelly is making himself heard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01500"><p>I am not a sensitive soul but there is a certain standard in this House to which we must adhere.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01600"><p>I said that the comments were out of order, so the issue was dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01700"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach very much for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01800"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L01900"><p>Will the Leader consider arranging for the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Burton, to come into the House to address another cutback?  As and from 30 March the closure of community welfare services in Keadue, Ballinlough  and Rooskey will take place.  They are being transferred from Keadue to Boyle, from Ballinlough to Castlerea and from Rooskey to Dromod in County Leitrim.  It represents a further withdrawal of services from rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02000"><p>The Senator could raise that matter by way of a Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02100"><p>I cannot understand why Deputy Frank Feighan and Senator Kelly are standing idly by when this Government is pulling the heart out of rural Ireland.  The presence of a community welfare officer is vital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.57" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02300"><p>The Government is withdrawing a service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02400"><p>Senator Kelly would know about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02500"><p>A person who has to go to the community welfare officer is not in a position to travel from Keadue-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02600"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02700"><p>-----to Boyle, from Ballinlough to Castlerea, or from Rooskey to Dromod.  Let us be honest about it.  The Senators opposite had their Ard-Fheis in Castlebar and they talked about rural Ireland and about the withdrawal of services.  The bus service has been withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02800"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L02900"><p>I am, but the Cathaoirleach is a man of the west.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03000"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate on this?  We are not having this debate today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03100"><p>The Cathaoirleach must ensure that this House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03200"><p>I have a clerk as well here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03300"><p>Very well.  The Oireachtas Members are being walked on by this Government.  The Government party Members have no clout.  The Senator opposite was in Tulsk and he knows what rural Ireland is like, so he should know what is happening in rural Ireland.  Community welfare officers are being pulled out of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03400"><p>I must call Senator Mullins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03500"><p>-----Keadue, Ballinlough and Rooskey.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03600"><p>The Senator is repeating himself.  I call Senator Mullins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03700"><p>It is a disgrace.  I want the Minister to come into the House.  I might table a Commencement matter on this issue next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#L03800"><p>I welcome very much the fact that the Minister, Deputy Charles Flanagan, had discussions yesterday with the assistant Egyptian Foreign Minister on the ongoing detention of an Irish citizen, Ibrahim Halawa.  This young man, as we know, was only 17 years of age when he was detained during a peaceful protest in Egypt and he has been detained for over a year.  As we know from correspondence many of us have had from his family, he is obviously in great distress.  His family are anxiously trying to get him home in order that he can continue his studies.  I hope that this will be a first positive move in securing his immediate release.</p> <p>I was present this morning for the launch of the Alcohol Health Alliance, which is a coming together of the Royal College of Physicians of Ireland and Alcohol Action Ireland to support the enactment of the public health (alcohol) Bill.  This alliance is being chaired by Professor Frank Murray.  As we all know, abuse of alcohol in this country is a national crisis with almost half of Irish drinkers engaging regularly in an episode of heavy drinking.  The number of deaths due to liver disease has doubled in the past 20 years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael Mullins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2368"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2368&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMullins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Alcohol abuse is now associated with the occupation of approximately 1,500 beds each night in Irish hospitals, and 25% of all injuries presented to accident and emergencies in our acute hospitals are alcohol related.  Significant legislation is due to come before this House shortly and I ask the Leader if we could get an indication as to when the Bill will come into the Oireachtas for discussion because it is critical that it be enacted during the lifetime of this Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#M00200"><p>I mentioned in the House previously the banking inquiry that is taking place downstairs.  It is going great.  People from all over the world are coming before it to talk about what happened the banks, why it happened and what we should have done differently, but the banks are still doing what they have always done.  They have reverted to type.  They are not only throwing people out of their homes but they are also imprisoning them within their homes in so far as the people are subsisting and not actually living.</p> <p>One has to pay now to go into a bank.  One has to pay for cash and for one's cheque.  One has no return on one's savings, and a crippling interest rate.  I will forget about the case in Vico Road because that is a different situation; it is a more opulent situation.  I am not arguing for that; they can argue for themselves.  I am arguing for genuine workers and families in homes the mortgage on which they cannot afford to pay, or they cannot afford the mortgage the bank is demanding they pay back.  Between cr&egrave;che fees, food and life fees they cannot afford the mortgage.  They are being put out of their homes every day of the week, and the banks continue to hike up the interest rates.  That is very serious because downstairs this major banking inquiry is taking place, and still the banks are reverting to type.</p> <p>Bank of Ireland announced a &euro;900 million profit last week.  I understand that a bank has to make a profit to fulfil its mandate but what will happen that &euro;900 million?  That profit is our money.  It is our universal social charge and our interest hikes.  I would like the Minister for Finance to come into this House and tell me the manners he is putting on the banks for the working people of Ireland.</p> <p>I was in Tulsk last week and I saw what is happening rural Ireland, but one of the most important developments is that young couples had paid &euro;160,000 for a semi-detached house in the middle of Tulsk, with no trees and very few amenities.  The same houses next door were being sold for &euro;49,000.  The banks should be brought to heel over that and told they can wipe out the first &euro;100,000 and let the people start paying at &euro;49,000.  Something must be done about that.</p> <p>I received a letter from a woman, Cait O'Beirne, in Cork.  There were 60 repossessions in the Cork Circuit Court.  These have nothing to do with the house in Vico Road, which everybody is running to with cameras.  There were 30 people in Cork Circuit Court and do the Senators know who they were?  They were people representing the banks because the poor unfortunates were scared out of their wits and did not have the bottle to attend.  They did not know what to do, and they did not have the language of the banking repossessions.  I have had enough of that.  I ask that the Minister come into the House and tell me exactly what manners he is putting on the banks that all of us have mortgages in because we are running to feed ourselves and pay all the bills. Can I have an answer to that question immediately?  This is about the fifth time I have asked for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#M00300"><p>In light of recent calls for a Minister of State to be appointed with responsibility for the implementation of the drugs task force recommendations, I ask the Leader if we could have a debate on the use of illegal drugs.  A recent report in <i>The Lancet</i>indicated that the increasing prevalence of high potency cannabis use among young people in particular is putting people at a much greater risk of developing major mental health problems, despite what I would call some irresponsible public commentators saying publicly that there is no health risk associated with the use of cannabis.  The literature is clear on the matter.  The Leader might arrange for a debate in the House at his convenience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#M00400"><p>I was a little concerned about Senator Paul Coghlan's reference to Commissioner Hogan, who was taking steps at European level to limit the amount of competition between the producers and the supermarkets.  Competition has been of huge benefit to this country, and to the marketplace as a whole.  When I first went into business we were not allowed to cut the price of anything.  If we cut the official price we were refused supplies.  We need an open market, and we need competition.  I disagree with Commissioner Hogan who is planning to introduce at European level a restriction on competition between suppliers and supermarkets.</p> <p>The question of competition is a reminder of how well our economy is doing now.  We are showing signs of getting the unemployment rate down, but there was an interesting development yesterday.  The British House of Commons is now allowing Stormont to set its own corporation tax.  That will be more competition for us on this side of the Border.  It is great competition.  We are all the one island and it will do no harm to have that competition but it is a reminder that we should not become complacent.  We have to continue to ensure we will be competitive in the future.  </p> <p>I refer to Senator Barrett's point about the suggestion that we take the pressure off teaching languages, which seems to me to be outrageously wrong.  We need languages if we want to export, and to take languages off the curriculum would be a huge error.  We must make sure that we do not do that.  Whatever about mathematics, that seems outrageous.  We cannot concentrate on everything but we should not on any grounds take the pressure off teaching languages.  The necessity to do that, if our economy is to continue, is very high.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#M00500"><p>I, too, wish to acknowledge the reduction in the live register figures.  Thankfully, the number of people signing on for social welfare has continued to fall 39 consecutive months in a row.  That is great news.  Unemployment figures are down from a high of 15.1% in February 2012 to 10.1% currently, and the figure is about to reduce to below 10% for the first time in many years.</p> <p>I have no doubt that the Government's Action Plan for Jobs is working.  That must be recognised and appreciated.  There are decreases in all eight regions of the country, and the fastest decrease is in the mid-west region.  In excess of 141,000 people left the live register in the past 12 months.  That is a true indication that the Government's plans for job creation are working, and long may those efforts continue.  I congratulate the Minister, Deputy Bruton, and his team on that magnificent achievement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#M00600"><p>Our colleague in the other House, Deputy Willie Penrose, published a Bill recently to reduce the time to discharge bankruptcy from three years to one year.  Last weekend at the Labour Party conference, and subsequently, the leader of the Labour Party and T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Joan Burton, endorsed this initiative by her colleague.  Speaking with Deputy Penrose it is obvious that this has struck a chord with people across the country, not just with those we might perceive to be wealthy people but people in dire financial circumstances who are unable in many cases to pay their bills.  If we link that with a statistic that was brought to my attention in recent days that this Government has levied some 45 tax increases since it first came to power in 2011, it is no wonder the response to Deputy Penrose's initiative has been so overwhelming.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to outline the position of the Fine Gael Party on this matter.  The Fine Gael Minister is in government.  Towards that end I ask that there would be a debate here, even if it was only statements, to give some indication of the way the Government is thinking because it is obvious from the debate in this House at the time with the then Minister, Deputy Alan Shatter, that the three year rule was not feasible, nor was it practical.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paschal Mooney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1990"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1990&amp;amp;pid=PaschalMooney&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As pointed out to him by me and others, which he refused to countenance, one can go across the Border and if one fulfils the conditions of bankruptcy, one can be discharged after one year.  One can take the ferry to England and do the same, as some have done, but not everybody can afford to do that or to stay within those jurisdictions for the required time.  I believe this is one way, as stated in the newspapers again today by respected commentators who are familiar with the mortgage distress area - one positive way - of resolving the issue of those who are unable to pay their debts.  It would also engage the banks because they would have no choice as they would be faced with a bankrupt and they would get no money.  There is a two-edge sword to this issue, in a positive sense, and therefore it is vitally important that we understand the Government's thinking on it.  Given that the Labour Party now supports the initiative, what is the position of the Fine Gael Ministers?  Towards that end, there is a need for a debate which would allow all Members to discuss the entire mortgage crisis issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N00200"><p>I again add my voice to the call for a debate not just on the banking sector but on the issue of mortgage arrears, a debate I have called for on number of occasions.  As shareholders in AIB, most of us are probably delighted it had a &euro;1.1 billion pre-tax profits in 2014 as opposed to a &euro;1.7 billion loss in 2013.  However, a closer examination of the figures reveals that &euro;188 million is a write-back from amounts it had previously set aside for expected bad debts.  That basically means that the rest of the money is operating profits.  I very much share the concerns of Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell that these profits are being made by exorbitant bank charges, interest rates on variable rate loans that are unsustainable and unacceptable, and, dare I say, a certain amount of a fall in the level of arrears that has been brought about by nothing but pure terror being imposed on people who are in mortgage arrears.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N00400"><p>I am calling for a debate on the Insolvency Service of Ireland and why its output and outcome have been so miserable</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N00500"><p>Abysmal is the word.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N00600"><p>Abysmal and miserable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N00700"><p>Shocking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N01000"><p>We should have that debate as a matter of urgency.  As a member of the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, it is clear there is a tsunami of repossessions coming and people in mortgage arrears are not being properly represented.  There is no level playing field when it comes to the relationship between somebody in mortgage arrears and their bank.  That is an issue the Government will have to address.  I want that debate as a matter of urgency.  I also call for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Joan Burton, to come to the House to address the State scheme which supposedly gives advice to people in mortgage arrears.  It is a joke, to say the least, that people get advice when they have actually been made an offer and they have no choice but either to accept or reject it.  That is not genuine advice.  It does nothing to help people in mortgage distress and is a total waste of money.  I am seeking two debates, one on the Insolvency Service of Ireland and the second on the facilities being made available to people in mortgage distress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N01100"><p>I suggest to some in the Labour Party and Fine Gael that they replay the record of their statements in the House.  Last night, a very good Bill, the Family Home Mortgage Settlement Arrangement Bill 2014, was introduced in the other House by Deputy Michael McGrath, on which I commend him, which would have removed the bank veto.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N01200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N01300"><p>It was unconstitutional.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N01400"><p>That Bill would have solved some of the problems which were identified in this House at the time the then Minister, Deputy Alan Shatter, was ramming through the insolvency legislation.  It was obvious at the time that its provisions would neuter any effectiveness the Bill should have had.  In Wexford 13.09% of people with mortgages are in default.  The level of arrears ranges from 10.2% to 19% across every county.  It is an appalling scenario.  I agree with Senator Aideen Hayden who said there is a tsunami of repossessions coming but what in the name of God is the Government doing about it?  It is in government, not in opposition, but what is it doing about it?  It has the power to change it.  It has the power to give a balance so that people are not removed from their houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N01700"><p>The Senator is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N01800"><p>Does Senator Walsh have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N01900"><p>I am asking for a debate on the issue.  I hope Deputy Willie Penrose will bring forward a Bill, or if not, the Opposition will do so, to reduce the terms for bankruptcy from three years to one year.  In normal circumstances I would not support such a Bill but we are not in normal circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02000"><p>Extraordinary circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02100"><p>Senator Conway is right that we are in extraordinary circumstances.  As a consequence of all of this we now have people who are suffering enormously and who have no hope for the future, neither for them nor their families.  There is an opportunity for us to set this right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02200"><p>What did the Government of which the Senator was a member do for people in mortgage arrears when it was in Government?  Nothing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02300"><p>It is easy to talk.  What we need is action.  We have introduced the action.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02400"><p>Why did the Senator vote for the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Bill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02500"><p>We had introduced the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02600"><p>It was the greatest lesson in capitulation to the banks I have ever seen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02700"><p>The code of conduct on mortgage arrears was voted through in this House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02800"><p>That Government kicked the can and capitulated to the banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N02900"><p>-----and actually ensured it was easier for the banks to repossess.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03000"><p>I thank Senator Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03100"><p>Rather than cry crocodile tears-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03200"><p>The party of which the Senator is a member bankrupted every one of us in the country.  He should sit down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03300"><p>Why is there a mortgage crisis?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03400"><p>-----the Government should be honest with people and take action on the issue.  The Minister with responsibility in this area is in the other House ramming through legislation which will have serious ramifications for children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03500"><p>I call Senator Martin Conway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03600"><p>She is ramming it through in the same way as the insolvency Bill and the water services Bill were rammed through.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03700"><p>The Senator has exceeded his time.  Senator Walsh, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03800"><p>We have seen the consequences for people of doing that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N03900"><p>I call Senator Martin Conway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N04000"><p>Believe me, there are political consequences which the Government will be exposed to in the next 12 months for its failure to act in these areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N04100"><p>It is very difficult in many ways to disagree with Senator Jim Walsh but we will let the history books judge the performance of the previous Government because I do not particularly want to get into revisionism and all that goes with it.  We have a serious problem with repossessions.  What Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell and others have said is absolutely correct.  It needs to be dealt with.  We should not skirt around the edges but deal with it head on and upfront, and the banks need to be dealt with head on and upfront.  There is too much pandering to the banks by everyone in society.  Whatever length of time is left in this Government, it has to deal with the banks and ensure that people are left with their homes, not with &euro;7 million worth of homes, as we saw on television last night.  I commend Mr. Vincent Browne because what he did last night was a fantastic example of public service broadcasting.  Of course, it was TV3 that exposed exactly what is going on and exposed the leadership of the so-called phoney, stupid New Land League.  How anybody can go on national television and justify the actions of an organisation such as the New Land League is beyond me.  The Land League goes back to Michael Davitt, who must be turning in his grave at what is going on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N04400"><p>The Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N04500"><p>Senator Gilroy was a Fianna F&aacute;il man once.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N04600"><p>Of course, we know Mr. Beades' seed, breed and pedigree and where his loyalties lay in the past.  He has some neck to go on national television and display the arrogance he has shown in recent days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N04700"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N04800"><p>Senator Conway, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N04900"><p>It is important that we do not abuse the privilege we have in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N05000"><p>I was about to interrupt the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N05100"><p>My understanding is that we do not name people who are not here to defend themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N05200"><p>This gentleman is well able to go on national television and talk crap.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#N05300"><p>That people are in debt and in mortgage debt is not new.  It has been going for a number of years.  I have been working closely with David Hall in this area on behalf of about 80 families.  There has been some improvement for some people.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fidelma Healy Eames:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2223"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2223&amp;amp;pid=FidelmaHealyEames&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The banks have started to do some good restructures.  The number of people in grave difficulty who are close to repossession has been estimated to be between 26,000 and 30,000 families.  That is sheer devastation.  I support the call made on all sides of this House for us to get together and come up with new solutions to help these people stay in their own homes by whatever means.  Let me remind everyone that there are no other houses for them and the State cannot give them houses.  We have heard the story about mortgage to rent and rental approaches.  Why have they not worked?  New solutions need to be found.</p><p>I wish to raise another issue.  I support the concern expressed by Senator Barrett about the removal of maths and languages as entry requirements in third level colleges.  That is a strange move.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O00200"><p>Such a joke.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O00300"><p>Academic council meetings are likely to take place in UCC and UL in the next few days where these proposals may be pushed through.  This matter is of huge concern.  I wish to state that children with dyslexia are exempt from the language requirement.  I do not know the reasoning behind the proposal to remove the requirement for maths and languages but I ask Senators to let me tell them the reason it should not happen.  First, 70% of the people hired by the likes of Google are from abroad because Ireland does not have enough graduates with languages.   We are not even able to give our own people jobs because we do such a bad job of teaching languages.  I had a conference-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O00400"><p>On a point of order, how come there is such inequality in regard to the time given to speakers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O00500"><p>Sorry, Senator; I am about to make my argument, so please give me a break.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O00600"><p>Some of us only got the statutory one minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O00700"><p>Senator Healy Eames's time is up.  Is the Senator calling for a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O00800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O00900"><p>Other Senators did not get time to read a paper on entrance requirements for universities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O01000"><p>May I sum up?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O01100"><p>Senator Healy Eames, please, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O01200"><p>Qualifications in languages and maths are of concern because, as a country, we rely on those skills to keep up with the best.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O01300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O01400"><p>That fact has been known for years and the situation has not changed.  I ask the Leader to make a written proposal to the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection, which is chaired by Deputy Joanna Tuffy, for immediate discussion.  I also ask him to send a note stating his huge concern about the matter to the Minister for Education and Skills.  It appears the Minister does not know about this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O01500"><p>The Minister is not even listening to teachers, so she is hardly going to listen to the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O01600"><p>I would appreciate if Senators would not interrupt me when I am on my feet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" speakername="Lorraine Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O01700"><p>I wish to raise an issue to do with applying legislative time limits to decisions by An Bord Plean&aacute;la in order to expedite the planning process.  Apple's investment in Athenry, County Galway, is a fantastic news story and it is one that I, as an Athenry native, am thrilled with.  However, I am concerned that the current planning process could end up delaying the development due to the lack of aforementioned time limits when it come to decisions by An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  This means that the decision-making process could be delayed, causing a problem that those rejoicing in the much-desired investment in Athenry could do without, especially in regard to the development of employment opportunities that are badly needed in Athenry and the greater area.  For this reason, I call for the introduction of targeted timeframes for planning decisions as soon as possible.</p> <p>It is important that people have an opportunity to submit their appeals and that they are properly considered.  However, we must also ensure that planning applications do not become stuck through endless appeal processes and delays.  Such a situation affects not just Apple but all developments in general.  Planning decisions must be taken prudently and with the best interest of Irish citizens at their heart.  Target times would bring greater clarity to the system and would streamline the process overall.  Such improvements would make for a better planning process in Ireland.  At a time when new housing is badly required, building is being delayed because of the length of time involved in getting planning permission through the process.  This situation has unarguably added to the housing crisis.  It has also stopped construction workers from getting back to work and thus allowing us, as a country, to make further gains along the road to recovery.  I ask the Leader of the House to allocate time for a debate with the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government in order to discuss time limits for An Bord Plean&aacute;la appeals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02000"><p>I generally support the comments made by colleagues on the housing matter in terms of bankruptcy and the heavily indebted citizens all across the country, but we must ask ourselves why.  The answer to the "why" question is the property crash and the policies that brought about that market.  The crash did not happen by chance.  Policy went in the wrong direction.  We put the construction industry in a league of its own, and it was about profit, not housing or looking after the needs of the Irish people.  I am concerned that we could see a repeat of this.  We read again today about private meetings - and they are not secret meetings - taking place between property developers and the Minister.  That scenario is a replica of what we saw in the Celtic tiger era, when one group in society almost set the Government's policy agenda.</p> <p>I have called in this House previously, as have many of my colleagues, particularly Senator Hayden, for an urgent debate on housing policy.  We should have a housing policy debate and not a construction industry policy debate.  The purpose of the construction industry should not be to turn millionaires into billionaires; it should be to provide decent accommodation for every stratum of Irish society.  Housing was provided in the much tougher times of the 1930s, the 1940s, the 1950s and also in the 1970s and 1980s.  That is what our agenda should be.  If people want to lobby then let us arrange a public forum on housing which would allow us to hear from developers, auctioneers and the people who are trying to buy houses.</p> <p>I remember the comments the former Taoiseach Bertie Ahern made when people were critical of property people and developers.  He said that people had no entitlement to criticise.  It was that sort of blinkered thinking which ruined this country and brought about much of the banking crisis.  We do not want to go back to that situation.  The Minister of State, Deputy Coffey, has indicated that he will make himself available for a debate.  Therefore, I ask the Leader to arrange an urgent debate on housing policy which will be led by the interests of people looking for housing, not by property speculators and developers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02100"><p>I wish to raise the issue of double standards in the House.  If a Member is absent from the House, can I not mention his name?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02200"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02300"><p>I refer to Senator Leyden's absence yesterday.  In that case, am I not allowed to mention his name?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02400"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02500"><p>Why would anybody want to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.150" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02700"><p>I understand there is precedent that an absent Member's name is not mentioned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02800"><p>That is interesting.  Yesterday, when I was absent from the House, Senator Leyden came in and mentioned my name.  When I came in here to refute what he said-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O02900"><p>Take it outside.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03000"><p>-----I was ruled out of order.  Again this morning, Senator Leyden came in here, in my absence, and raised my name.  I ask the Acting Chairman to explain the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03100"><p>This is not a matter for the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03200"><p>My query is about standards in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03300"><p>Does the Senator have a question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03350"><p>It is about stupidity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03400"><p>Pistols at dawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03500"><p>I would prefer a sword fight.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03600"><p>I cannot allow constituency rivalries to take over business this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03700"><p>Senator Leyden has a habit of coming in here to make his speech and then running out the door.  Perhaps he is auditioning for a television drama.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03800"><p>On a point of order, the Senator has abused his position by what he has said.  Unless he has something to say that is relevant to the Order of Business then he should sit down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O03900"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04000"><p>Senator Kelly keeps referring-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04100"><p>I will make a ruling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04200"><p>The Acting Chairman must extend protection to Members around here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04300"><p>One does not have to outline what is relevant and what is not relevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04400"><p>I have a right to get clarity on this issue for the future, because every time I am absent Senator Leyden mentions my name and every time I mention his name I am ruled out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04500"><p>The Senators should stop upsetting each other.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04600"><p>We are dealing with today's Order of Business.  I ask the Senator to stick to the Order of Business, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04700"><p>I did not refer to Senator Kelly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04800"><p>I still have not got clarity from the House as to what happens in the future should Senator Leyden mention my name again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O04900"><p>What will happen is that the Senator will be ruled out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05000"><p>I shall address my comment to the Visitors' Gallery.  The visitors have seen an example of why we should have more women in politics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05100"><p>Take it outside.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.177" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05300"><p>I ask all Senators to resume their seats.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05400"><p>I did not mention the fact that Senator Kelly was not here this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05500"><p>I shall not allow this matter to be an issue on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05600"><p>Exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05700"><p>The ruling is quite clear that it is not in order to refer to the absence of a Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05800"><p>Maybe I am being unfair on the Acting Chairman, because it was the Cathaoirleach who was in the Chair when all of this happened.  I will raise the matter with him on another day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O05900"><p>What about the closure of community welfare offices in Keadue, Ballinlough and Rooskey?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.185" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#O06100"><p>What the people seated in the Visitors' Gallery have just heard is even more reason there should be more women in politics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.187" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#P00100"><p>Senator Kelly, have you a matter for today's Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#P00200"><p>Senator Leyden raised the closure of CWO offices in Keadue, Ballinlough and Rooskey.  It is regrettable.  I do not believe the way forward is to close satellite clinics or community welfare offices.  We have received categoric assurances from the Department of Social Protection and the Minister that where somebody feels discommoded and cannot travel to a clinic, the community welfare officer will call out to his or her house.  Nobody will be left without a service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#P00300"><p>I do not know what to make of the exchanges that have just taken place.  I am very glad to hear the reassurance from Senator O'Donnell that the female Senators in this House never heckle.</p> <p>We should all welcome the new dairy processing facility in Belview Port announced by Glanbia.  It will create 75 direct jobs in Kilkenny and we might say that the cats have got the cream yet again.  The really good news is the 1,600 spin-off jobs around the country.  It is excellent news for rural Ireland in particular.  It is a reminder, yet again, of how much a driver of progress and positivity agriculture is in rural Ireland.  It is worth &euro;10 billion in terms of Irish exports.  An uplift in dairy production will be required to provide the raw material for the facility.  It is very reassuring for those involved in agriculture in Ireland and for all of those who are keen to see stimulation of the economy in those parts of Ireland, such as smaller towns and villages that have not yet benefitted from whatever good news there has been in recent times.  </p> <p>I am torn between admiration and horror in regard to the news about the money Sinn F&eacute;in has managed to raise in the United States.  I would say, "Good luck to them" in one breath, but when it tells us that none of the money was spent south of the Border and it was all spent in the North I have to say, "Pull the other one."  It is not just North of the Border that Sinn F&eacute;in has so many people working full-time for the party.  I will not quibble at any organisation's fundraising ability, but it is time for us to consider whether we have the mechanisms in place in this country to allow us to scrutinise properly from where political funding comes and is spent.  We have a laughable situation whereby all donations under &euro;600 to an individual politician simply do not have to be disclosed.  That is not a transparent system of fundraising.  We pretend to have accountability in these matters, but in reality there is no accountability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#P00400"><p>Do you have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#P00500"><p>My question is whether he would consider it timely that we would have a further discussion on transparency and accountability on the funding of political activities, in terms of the provenance of the funding, the expenditure that takes place, where it takes place and whether it takes place in accordance with regulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#P00600"><p>I was deeply disappointed this week to discover that the EU has dithered and delayed on the abolition of roaming charges within the European Union.  For the past year and a half people across Europe have been led up the garden path when it comes to roaming and have been told that the abolition of EU roaming charges was imminent, had passed through the Parliament and was about to be enacted.  We now find the measure is likely to be delayed by three years, until the end of 2018, as a consequence of a European Council decision which has extended the deadline by which telecoms companies are obliged to end roaming charges.  </p> <p>Europe has let its citizens down through its dithering, indecision and willingness to give in to special interests.  I am an advocate of the European project as a mechanism through which all of our lives can be made better and I am bitterly disappointed with this retrograde step.  Great work was done during the past decade to make roaming cheaper and break down the invisible telecommunications borders which exist across Europe.  We all know roaming is a significant money maker for telecommunications companies.  Europe set about tackling that, yet now it appears it is not such an urgent issue after all.  People can simply continue to pay through the nose for another three years as a consequence of the Council's dithering and indecision.  </p> <p>I am glad that my colleague in the European Parliament, Mr. Brian Hayes, MEP, plans on raising this important issue in seeking a reversal of the decision of the Council.  What exactly is the Council hoping will change in the next three years?  What is the difference between doing away with roaming charges in 2015 or leaving them in place until 2018?  It seems to me there is little difference, apart from allowing the telecommunications companies to continue to rake in money hand over fist for an extra 36 months.  I call on those who made this decision to reconsider it in the interests of European citizens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#P00700"><p>The Members were very unruly throughout the Order of Business today.  It does nothing for the decorum and dignity of the House to have such occurrences.  People should reconsider, when they come into the House, whether they do things properly.  It would be better if they did not come in if they are going to involve themselves in the type of activity we have seen here today.</p> <p>Senator O'Brien raised the question of the Dublin ambulance service, something which was raised in the past two days on the Order of Business.  It is subject to a HIQA report.  Patient safety is of paramount importance and must be addressed.  There must be consultation and negotiation.  I have been in contact with the Minister's office.  He is willing to come here at 5 p.m., but cannot be here any earlier.  He is booked up.  He cannot give a guarantee he is available next week.  I leave it to the Senator to decide if he wants to be here for 5 p.m. when the Minister will be available.  We will have to decide whether the House wants to wait until 5 p.m. for the Minister.  </p> <p>Senators Bacik and Brennan and several others referred to the unemployment figures.  The latest live register figures show a continuing fall in the numbers of people signing on, marking 39 consecutive months of decrease.  The Minister, Deputy Bruton, has highlighted other positive trends including, on a seasonally adjusted basis, the fact that 4,300 people left the live register in a month.  The standardised unemployment rate is at 10.1%, a decrease of 0.2% in a month, and is down from a high of 15.1% in February 2012 when the Government launched and began implementing the Action Plan for Jobs.  </p> <p>The annual decreases occurred in all eight regions, as Senator Brennan has outlined, with the fastest decrease occurring in the mid-west region.  Some 141,151 people left the live register to take up work during the past 12 months.  The exit rate from the live register into work is running at 40%, up from 33% in 2012.  Every person who leaves the live register to take up employment saves the Exchequer approximately &euro;20,000 per annum in reduced social welfare expenditure and increased tax revenue, and helps to create a reinforcing cycle of positive economic benefits.  Seeing our economy thriving as it is at the moment is something that is to be welcomed by all.  The benefits are filtering down to people in the regions and throughout rural Ireland.</p> <p>Senators Bacik and Mullen referred to the wonderful news from Glanbia, namely, the opening of a plant in Belview Port in Kilkenny.  It will create over 1,600 spin off jobs, as Senator Mullen mentioned.  It is a great investment in rural Ireland, about which we have been speaking on the Order of Business today.  There were some negative but many positive points about the activities in rural Ireland, which need to be highlighted.  I compliment Glanbia on its development.  It will be very important for the dairy industry in the country and the economy in general.</p> <p>Senator Bacik mentioned the review group report on the Mental Health Act 2001.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister of State, Deputy Lynch, has published the expert group report on the Mental Health Act 2001, which review is in line with the commitment in the programme for Government to initiate consultation with service users, carers and other stakeholders on mental health and human rights standards.  We might have a debate on that issue in early course.  </p><p>Senator Barrett, Senator Healy Eames and other Senators raised the issue of the removal of languages as entry requirements in third level colleges.  We need to upgrade our language and maths curricula.  As stated by Senator Healy Eames, this issue should be discussed by the education committee as a matter of urgency.  I hope that members will raise it with the chairman of that committee, Deputy Tuffy, whom I am sure will facilitate that debate.  There is a need for greater emphasis on language and maths skills.</p><p>Senator Coghlan spoke about the unfair treatment of suppliers by multiples.  Senator Quinn had a different viewpoint from Senator Coghlan in that regard and outlined that he would not be in agreement with any plans to limit competition.  Senator Quinn also raised the issue of the corporate tax rate in Northern Ireland and the need for us to be vigilant in that regard.  I agree with him that competition is of paramount importance.  I agree also with the Senator's commentary on the language skills issue.</p><p>Senator Mooney referred to a proposed Private Members' Bill which seeks to reduce bankruptcy from three years to one year.  I am sure it will be debated in the other House and also in this House.  There has already been far-reaching and substantial reform of our bankruptcy law, including by way of the Personal Insolvency Act 2012, which reduced the period of automatic discharge from bankruptcy from 12 years to three years.  That legislation came into effect in December 2013.  There have been drastic changes in this area.  During debate on that legislation, the Minister mentioned that if there is a need for further review of it, that will happen.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#Q00200"><p>He has set his face against it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#Q00300"><p>Let us not forget that the period in respect of automatic discharge from bankruptcy was reduced only two years ago from 12 years to three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#Q00400"><p>I am aware of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#Q00500"><p>It takes time for measures to bed in.  It is unfair to engage in knee-jerk reactions to legislation which only came into effect in December 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#Q00600"><p>It is not impacting on the people who need it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#Q00700"><p>Senators Hayden and O'Donnell raised the issue of profits in the banking sector.  Senator O'Donnell also mentioned that she is not a great fan of the banks in terms of what they are currently doing and called for a debate on the banking sector.  I have asked the Minister for Finance to come to the House for a debate on that issue, although I have not yet been successful.  However, I continue to make that request of him.</p> <p>Senator Hayden also asked that the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton, come to the House for a debate on mortgage arrears and distress, which issue was also referred to by several members.  </p> <p>Senator Walsh referred to the Private Members' Bill introduced in the D&aacute;il this week by Fianna F&aacute;il, which was deemed to be unconstitutional.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#Q00800"><p>That was a big surprise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#Q00900"><p>As I mentioned yesterday, mortgage arrears are putting a great deal of pressure on many families.  The Government is determined to ensure that as the recovery deepens, nobody will be left behind.  We are making headway in terms of improving the situation.  The most recent figures show a significant improvement in arrears, particularly in respect of family homes.  The Central Bank figures underline this progressive trend, with the number of family homes in arrears having fallen for the past five quarters.  Figures from the Department of Finance for the six main banks show that the number of cases of arrears in excess of 90 days, when compared with the situation at the start of 2014, have fallen by over 17,500.  In August 2013, some 2,500 split mortgages had been put in place by the six main banks.  The current figure in this regard is 20,500.  During the same period, permanent restructures put in place by the six main banks in respect of family homes increased from 41,000 to 91,000.  However, the same progress is not being made in respect of those who are in arrears of over two years.  For this reason, the Government has undertaken to review the arrangements put in place to ensure there is a viable route forward for anybody who wants help.  The Government has been working with the banks, which have been meeting the targets set for them by the Central Bank under the MARP process.</p> <p>We will have to consider whether the current approach is the one that will really help to move forward the most difficult cases.  It is not right that people should live with extreme mental pressure in respect of debts they cannot pay.  As mentioned by many Members today, this is damaging the mental health of families and individuals throughout the country.  It is a matter of serious concern to Government, which has thus far been responsible for the most radical overhaul of debt management in this State.  As mentioned earlier, we have rewritten laws on bankruptcy in an effort to move away from the previously draconian-Victorian approach taken to this issue heretofore.  The Government has put in place a range of options to help ordinary people who find they cannot pay their debts, including their mortgages.  </p> <p>The Insolvency Service of Ireland is in place to help people in a practical and understanding way.  We know that people who have gone through the process have experienced great relief.  The ISI has been proactive in encouraging people to use its services.  Following suspension of application fees, the number of people availing of personal insolvency arrangements increased.  These arrangements are a solution to the mortgage problem and more people should be availing of them.  The first step is to make people aware of what is possible and this will be a focus of Government.</p> <p>The issue of bankruptcy was mentioned a great deal today.  In 2014, there were 448 bankruptcy adjudications, 95% of which were sought by debtors.  It is wrong to say that no progress is being made in relation to mortgage arrears and insolvency.  There is more to be done and progress to be made, but the Government is aware of the problems that exist and is doing its best to rectify them.</p> <p>Senator Conway spoke about the New Land League, on which issue I do not propose to comment.  Senator Higgins spoke about the large number of jobs that will be created during development of new Apple facility in Athenry and of her concerns regarding delays in the planning process in this regard.  Senator Bradford called for a housing policy debate.  I will ask the Minister of State, Deputy Coffey, who is responsible for planning and housing to come to the House in the next couple of weeks to address those issues.</p> <p>Senator Mullen spoke about Glanbia and also referred to Sinn F&eacute;in's fund-raising machine inside and outside of this country and the need for greater scrutiny in this regard.  I will try to arrange a debate on that issue in the next session.</p> <p>Senator Noone raised the issue of roaming charges and the delay in abolition of these changes.  There is no question but that what is happening is a retrograde step.  The delay is unacceptable.  We were promised by Europe that these charges would be abolished in many instances but this will not now happen for another three years.  On EU affairs, it was agreed by this House that we would deal with more European affairs matters.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have had a number of meetings of the sub-committees at which all parties were represented and we have decided that, for the rest of the year, we will concentrate on three areas in the work programme, namely, energy, youth employment and agriculture.  We are bringing over people such as Commissioners and Directors General of the European institutions so I hope we have a strong input from Members in the House.  There is no point in these people coming here if there are only five, six or seven people in the House.  If we want this we will have to be proactive ourselves so I urge all Members to get involved and to prepare their questions, some of which we can even give to the relevant people before they come over here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R00200"><p>Before I put the amendment, can the Leader clarify the situation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R00300"><p>I will leave it to the Member who proposed the amendment to the Order of Business.  Does he want to come here at 5 p.m. when the Minister is here?  The Minister is available after 5 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R00400"><p>I was waiting for the Leader to finish before deciding.  I withdraw the amendment.  I accept that the Minister for Health, Deputy Leo Varadkar, will be here at 5 p.m. today and I will certainly be here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R00500"><p>We hope to finish our business at 2 p.m. but we will reconvene at 5 p.m. at the request of Senator Darragh O'Brien.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R00600"><p>At the request of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R00700"><p>The Minister has agreed to come in at 5 p.m and that is the only time he can come in.  We will suspend from when we finish the Workplace Relations Bill 2014.  The Minister for Health will come here to discuss ambulance and emergency services for 30 minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R00800"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R00900"><p>Is the amendment proposed by the Leader agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.213" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.214" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R01100">Workplace Relations Bill 2014: Committee Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R01200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Damien English, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.216" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 83 agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.217" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 84</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R01500"><p>Amendments Nos. 123 to 128, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  Amendment No. 125 is consequential on amendment No. 126. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.219" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 123:

In page 66, line 8, to delete &quot;Equality Authority or the Commission&quot; and substitute &quot;Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R01700"><p>Amendments Nos. 123 to 128, inclusive, further refine the changes that have to be made to the Employment Equality Act 1998 in light of the establishment of the workplace relations commission and the transfer of the functions of the director of the Equality Tribunal to the director general of the commission.  In addition to a number of technical or drafting changes, these amendments propose two substantive additional changes in respect of complaints brought under the Employment Equality Act 1998 as follows.  A complainant will not be permitted to recover redress for discriminatory dismissal in circumstances where a court has begun hearing his or her wrongful dismissal action or an adjudication officer has determined his or her complaint under the Unfair Dismissal acts.  I am in consultation with the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel on this amendment and it may be necessary to introduce a further amendment on Report Stage to further clarify the provision in relation to parallel claims under the Unfair Dismissal Acts and the Employment Equality Act 1998.</p> <p>Transitional arrangements for amendments to the Employment Equality Act 1998 effected by section 84 of the Workplace Relations Act 2015 will not apply in relation to an employment equality complaint referred before the commencement of section 84.  The Minister will return on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R01800"><p>I support the amendment but on Second Stage I made reference to the need to ensure no downgrading or deprioritising of the functions of the Equality Tribunal.  I expressed a concern over whether the new commission would retain all the expertise that had been so painstakingly built up among staff at the Equality Tribunal and I was given assurances about that on Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R01900"><p>I will reaffirm that with the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.223" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.224" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 124:

In page 66, line 36, to delete &quot;Equality Authority&quot; and substitute &quot;Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.225" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.226" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 125:

In page 66, line 42, to delete &ldquo;and&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.227" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.228" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 126:

In page 66, after line 42, to insert the following:&quot;(m) by the substitution of the following subsection for subsection (4) of section 101:&quot;(4) An employee who has been dismissed shall not be entitled to seek redress under this Part in respect of the dismissal if&mdash;

(a) the employee has instituted proceedings for damages at common law for wrongful dismissal and the hearing of the case concerned has begun, or

(b) an adjudication officer has made a decision to which subparagraph (i) of paragraph (c) of subsection (1B) (inserted by subparagraph (iv) of paragraph (c) of subsection (1) of section 81 of the Act of 2015) of section 8 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977 applies in respect of the dismissal.&quot;,and&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.229" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.230" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 127:

In page 67, line 4, to delete &quot;subsection (1)&quot; and substitute &quot;subsection (2)&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.231" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.232" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 128:

In page 67, between lines 9 and 10, to insert the following:&quot;(2) The amendments to the Act of 1998 effected by this section shall not apply in relation to a case referred to the Director General under section 77 of that Act before the commencement of this section.&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.233" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.234" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 84, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.235" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 85</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R03350"><p>Amendments Nos. 129 to 132, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.237" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 129:

In page 67, line 11, to delete &quot;Equal Status Act 2000&quot; and substitute &quot;Act of 2000&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R03500"><p>These amendments further refine the changes which have to be made to the Equal Status Act 2000 in light of the establishment of the workplace relations commission and the transfer of the functions of the director of the Equality Tribunal to the director general of the commission.  In addition to a number of technical or drafting changes this amendment proposes to provide for transitional arrangements in respect of complainants referred under the Equal Status Act 2000 before the commencement of section 85 of the Workplace Relations Act 2015.  The amendments to the Equal Status Act 2000 effected by section 85 of the Workplace Relations Act 2015 will not apply in relation to an equal status complaint referred before the commencement of section 85.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.239" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.240" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 130:

In page 68, line 16, to delete &quot;Equality Authority&quot; and substitute &quot;Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.241" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.242" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 131:

In page 68, line 38, to delete &quot;Equality Authority&quot; and substitute &quot;Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.243" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.244" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 132:

In page 69, between lines 9 and 10, to insert the following:&quot;(2) The amendments to the Act of 2000 effected by this section shall not apply in relation to a case referred to the Director General under section 21 of that Act before the commencement of this section.&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.245" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.246" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 85, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.247" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 86 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.248" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#R04600"><p>I move amendment No. 133:<blockquote><br /><br />In page 69, between lines 19 and 20, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&quot;Accessibility of hearings for those with a disability</b><br /><br />87. Any premises used for the purposes of a hearing by an adjudication officer of the Labour Court or for the purposes of any mediation or case resolution meeting shall be suitable for access by persons with a disability.&quot;.</blockquote>This is fairly self-evident.  There is a general Government policy that all government buildings should be accessible to the disabled.  It is essential that any place where these hearings are held should be accessible to people with disabilities.  It will be interesting to see if the Government accepts it or finds some excuse for not accepting it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Thus far, I have tabled numerous amendments none of which has been accepted, although in one or two cases the Minister of State said he would think about it before Report Stage.  These were submitted by representatives of a well-known firm of solicitors which practises in this area.  I would have thought they would have a fair idea of what they were doing.  This amendment, even to the layman, seems to be inarguable.  I am keen to hear the Minister of State's response.  I see the shadow of a smile.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S00200"><p>I wish to add a word of support for Senator Norris's point.  I imagine this is already covered in some form or other.  I cannot believe that we would have legislation in place that did not enable people with a disability to attend.  I imagine the Minister of State will be able to say to us that there is no need for this for a given reason, but I look forward to hearing it.  I support Senator Norris's amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S00300"><p>I support the amendment.  My colleague, Senator Cullinane, tabled this amendment as well.  It is non-contentious and self-explanatory in terms of accessibility of hearings for those with a disability.  I, too, am keen to hear what the Minister of State has to say and whether it is provided for in other legislation.  There is no harm in having it stated explicitly in this Bill.  It would only serve to strengthen the legislation and the intent behind it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S00400"><p>I am pleased to have the chance to say that, like everyone in the House, we are in agreement when it comes to accessibility of facilities.  Senator Feargal Quinn is correct.  It is already covered.  That is why we do not believe in the need for this amendment.  The amendment seeks to provide that any premises used for the purposes of a hearing by an adjudication officer from the Labour Court or for the purposes of any mediation or case resolution meeting would be suitable for access to persons with disabilities.  The issue raised by the Senator's proposed amendment is already adequately catered for by the Disability Act 2005.  Therefore, we do not need this amendment.  We are fully supportive of what is behind it, but the matter is covered in law already under the Disability Act 2005, and rightly so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S00500"><p>I suppose I will have to accept that, but it would be no harm to stick it in , because it is a signal to people with disabilities that they are properly and duly regarded.  I will have to accept that, as the Minister of State says, it is covered by the Disability Act.</p> <p>On the other hand, the Disability Act does not always work.  There are places where people do not have ready access for a variety of reasons, including historic buildings with exemptions.  There are situations where, regardless of the relevant Acts, people are denied access, including a premises that I take an interest in, 35 North Great George's Street, the James Joyce Centre.  It is an 18th century building and it is rather difficult to provide access to it..  At the moment we are looking at the possibility of putting in a lift, but it is very expensive and it would interfere with fire escapes and so on.  The building is partly publicly funded but at the moment it is not fully accessible.</p> <p>The Disability Act does not always work.  I urge the Minister of State to cater for these situations and, as a signal to our brothers and sisters who are in wheelchairs or otherwise incapacitated, it should be there as a headline.  We should acknowledge it.  I call on the Minister of State to think again and to include it for those two reasons.  I completely accept that the matter is, generally speaking, covered by the Disability Act.  I thank the Minister of State for his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S00600"><p>I will raise Senator Norris's point with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, in advance of Report Stage.  Senator Norris referred to sending out a signal.  In general, in legislation like this, which deals with restructuring, we do not restate existing law.  I know what Senator Norris is saying.  He is trying to push the agenda a little more to make it clear.  I will certainly mention Senator Norris's concerns to the Minister.  Senator Norris suggested the Disability Act is not always implemented.  However, I do not believe restating it in this Bill would strengthen the Disability Act 2005.  I understand what Senator Norris is saying and that he is keen to make it clear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S00700"><p>Many buildings are exempted for historical reasons.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S00800"><p>Yes, but taking Senator Norris's amendment would not solve that problem.  The issue is covered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S00900"><p>It might force those involved to move out of the historic buildings into other buildings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S01000"><p>I will mention it again to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S01100"><p>If the Minister of State would do so, I would be very grateful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S01200"><p>I would be delighted to.  That is no problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S01300"><p>After all that has been said, Senator Norris, do I take it that amendment No. 133 is withdrawn, by leave?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S01400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.264" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S01600"><p>Amendments Nos. 134 and 135 are consequential on amendment No. 136.  Amendments Nos. 134 to 136, inclusive, may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.266" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 87</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.267" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 134:

In page 69, to delete line 30.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S01800"><p>Section 87 provides for an amendment to the Organisation of Working Time Act 1997 to bring it into line with the rulings of the Court of Justice of the European Union in the Schultz-Hoff line of cases regarding how time spent on sick leave should be treated for the purposes of the accrual of annual leave.  It will allow workers who are on long-term sick leave to accrue and retain annual leave for up to 15 months from the end of the year in which it is accrued, thus bringing the Organisation of Working Time Act into line with the rulings of the Court of Justice of the EU.  It is considered that the 15-month period strikes the right balance between respecting the entitlements of employees and minimising the cost to the Exchequer and employers while bringing the legislation into line with EU law.  Amendments Nos. 134 to 136, inclusive, amend section 87 and are required to implement fully the rulings of the Court of Justice of the EU in the Schultz-Hoff line of cases.  These amendments will provide that an employee who leaves employment and who has accrued annual leave entitlement will be entitled to payment in lieu of the leave not taken calculated on the same basis as if the employee had returned to work on the date of leaving the employment.</p> <p>These amendments are being introduced on Committee Stage in the Seanad since it was not possible to have the text ready in time for Report Stage in the D&aacute;il.  We had always intended to include them.  It was simply a question of getting the drafting ready.</p> <p>Amendment No. 137 is in the name of Senator Norris.  We recognise that the language proposed by the Senator is already in use in legislation.  For example it appears in the Safety, Health and Welfare at Work Act 2005, the Employment Permits Act 2006 and, more recently, the Protected Disclosures Act 2014.  The provisions on penalisation in those Acts, including threatening penalisation, were considered in detail in the specific context of those legislative instruments when they were being prepared and enacted.  The language proposed is correct and in use.  However, the purpose of the Workplace Relations Bill is only to provide for the streamlining of structures and procedures that will make the navigation of employment rights and associated compliance and enforcement systems far more user-friendly.  If substantial changes to employment law had been intended to be effected by this Bill, those changes would have been highlighted at the time of the public consultation and people would have been afforded an opportunity to consider them.  Substantial changes to employment rights legislation, such as those proposed by the Senator in this amendment, fall outside the scope of the Bill.  That is not to say they cannot be addressed at a later stage.  It is simply that this Bill is mainly about procedures and structures.  We understand the wording is already used in other legislation.  The wording is correct.  It would have meant far more work at this stage on this Bill and we are not prepared to go back into it, because we want to get this moving along if we can.  We are not going to accept the amendment at this stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S01900"><p>Which amendment are we talking about?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S02000"><p>We are on amendments Nos 134 to 136, inclusive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S02100"><p>Sorry, I may have gone too far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S02200"><p>Which amendment is it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S02300"><p>I added in amendment No. 137.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S02400"><p>The Minister of State anticipated me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S02500"><p>We will cover that when we get there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S02600"><p>My apologies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S02700"><p>That is no problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.278" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.279" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 135:

In page 70, line 6, to delete &ldquo;year.&rdquo;.&rdquo; and substitute&ldquo;year.&rdquo;,

and&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.280" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.281" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 136:

In page 70, between lines 6 and 7, to insert the following:

&ldquo;(c) in section 23, by the substitution of the following subsection for subsection (1):&ldquo;(1) (a) Where&mdash;(i) an employee ceases to be employed, and

(ii) the whole or any portion of the annual leave in respect of the relevant period remains to be granted to the employee,the employee shall, as compensation for the loss of that annual leave, be paid by his or her employer an amount equal to the pay, calculated at the normal weekly rate or, as the case may be, at a rate proportionate to the normal weekly rate, that he or she would have received had he or she been granted that annual leave.

(b) In this subsection&mdash;&lsquo;relevant period&rsquo; means&mdash;(i) in relation to a cessation of employment of an employee to whom subparagraph (i) of paragraph (c) of subsection (1) of section 20 applies, the current leave year,

(ii) in relation to a cessation of employment of an employee to whom subparagraph (ii) of the said paragraph (c) applies, that occurs during the first 6 months of the current leave year&mdash;(I) the current leave year, and

(II) the leave year immediately preceding the current leave year,(iii) in relation to a cessation of employment of an employee to whom subparagraph (iii) of the said paragraph (c) applies, that occurs during the first 12 months of the period of 15 months referred to in the said subparagraph (iii)&mdash;(I) the current leave year, and

(II) the leave year immediately preceding the current leave year,or

(iv) in relation to a cessation of employment of an employee to whom subparagraph (iii) of the said paragraph (c) applies that occurs during the final 3 months of the period of 15 months referred to in the said subparagraph (iii)&mdash;(I) the current leave year, and

(II) the 2 leave years immediately preceding the current leave year.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.282" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.283" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.284" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S03400">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S03500"><p>The Leader wishes to make an announcement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S03600"><p>We had agreed to an amendment to the Order of Business in order that the Minister for Health would come to the House at 5 p.m.  The Minister will be held up until 6 p.m. at least in the other House.  The Minister has agreed to come to the House for half an hour next week to deal with the matter and I have agreed this with Senator O'Brien as well.  Therefore, we will not be dealing with the matter at 5 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S03700"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.288" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S03800">Workplace Relations Bill 2014: Committee Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.289" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 87</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#S04000"><p>I move amendment No. 137:<blockquote><br /><br />In page 70, between lines 6 and 7, to insert the following:&ldquo;(c) in section 26 in line one, after the word &ldquo;penalised&rdquo;, to insert &ldquo;or threaten to penalise&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote>The Minister of State has already spoken on this issue, but I am a little concerned that the Government seeks so narrowly to control the scope of the Bill.  I believe it is within the remit of the House to extend the scope of the Bill somewhat.  We have argued the toss on this.  It is not only a matter of penalising.  The threat to penalise also operates as a disincentive to people and for this reason I believe it should be covered.  The Minister of State has said that the wording is correct and that it is in other legislation and so on, but it is not in this legislation and I believe it should be.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This Bill goes beyond just the general regulations, procedures and so on.  It deals with principles and issues.  It seems extraordinary that the Minister of State would resist taking this on.  If the Minister of State is providing for penalising, then threatening to penalise has the same effect.  As the Minister of State is taking on penalising, that is actually in the Bill and we are not extending the scope of the Bill at all.  It would not bother me if we were, but we are not.  We are addressing a clear point, that it would be not only "penalising", which is in the Bill, but also the threat to penalise.  If somebody comes along and says to an employer that if he or she does a particular thing, we will levy such-and-such in the way of sanctions, then that is an effective disincentive.  It should be addressed in this Bill.</p><p>I will stick to this point, and I will return to it on Report Stage.  It seems the Government is taking a narrow view.  There is an utter reluctance to accept amendments from this House, and there is no need.  Some of my colleagues said this was because the Bill has come from the D&aacute;il and would have to go back to it with any amendments, but the Government amendments we are dealing with will have to go back anyway.  There is no stumbling block.  I appeal to the Minister to take this back urgently and decide not only to penalise but also to provide for a threat to penalise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.292" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T00200"><p>Changes have been accepted.  Some of the Government amendments reflect amendments put forward by the Opposition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T00300"><p>They all are Government amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.294" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T00400"><p>They are not.  Three or four amendments were put forward at an earlier stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T00500"><p>From the Government side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.296" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T00600"><p>No.  Quite a few were taken on board from members of the Opposition, including Deputy Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n.  There are two others that were already taken.  On the first two days of discussion of the Bill, amendments were introduced by the Government on foot of representations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T00700"><p>Exactly.  They were Government amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.298" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T00800"><p>The aim is that we get the amendments we want.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T00900"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.300" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01000"><p>Members should be happy with that.  It is not the case that we are refusing to make any changes.</p> <p>The problem with this amendment is this.  I have already quoted instances where such provisions are in use.  It is not that we are saying Senator Norris is wrong with this amendment.  We are only saying that the scope of this Bill, and the public consultation that went along with it, did not involve changes to employment law.  It involved changes to the structures and the procedures.  It would be unfair to change the scope of the Bill during this debate because it would defeat the purpose of the public consultation.</p> <p>A commitment is being given to Senator Norris now that this will be addressed across all of the primary legislation, not only this one Bill.  It will have effect in a range of areas.  It would not be a case of accepting the amendment - end of story.  There would be a fair bit of work involved, which would delay the Bill, which has taken a long time to get through as it is.  We want to progress with this as it is now and not reopen the consultation on it, but there is a commitment to try to address Senator Norris's concerns at a later stage.  That is the position.  The wording of Senator Norris's amendment is not wrong.  It is just that it is the wrong time to put it in this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01100"><p>I do not accept that for a minute, because "penalise" is already included.  That is clear.  How much consultation does one need on that?  I do not see any need whatever for consultation on that, because it is merely an extension of the idea of penalising.  This is another way of penalising, and it is spelling it out.  The Minister of State agrees with it; it is merely that he will not accept it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01200"><p>The concern is that the amendment changes the nature of this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01300"><p>How does it change the nature of the Bill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01400"><p>It changes the scope of the Bill.  We went out to consultation with one version.  If one completely changes the scope, it defeats the consultation.  That is standard procedure with legislation being brought through here.  Senator Norris is unhappy with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01500"><p>Is the Minister of State saying decisions are made about parliamentary legislation outside the House by interested bodies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01600"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.307" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01700"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01800"><p>The public consultation on this Bill was mainly to do with the structures, not principles.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.309" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T01900"><p>Is Senator Norris pressing the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.310" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T02000"><p>I am reserving it for Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.311" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.312" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 138:

In page 70, line 7, to delete &quot;Industrial Relations Act 1990&quot; and substitute &quot;Act of 1990&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.313" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.314" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T02500"><p>I move amendment No. 139:<blockquote><br /><br />In page 70, after line 12, to insert the following:&ldquo;(4) Section 7(2)(b) of the Payment of Wages Act 1991 shall be deleted.<br /><br />(5) The National Minimum Wage Act 2000 is amended:<blockquote>(a) in section 24(2) by the deletion of the words &quot;referred to or&quot; after the word &quot;be&quot;,<br /><br />(b) in section 24 by the insertion of a new subsection after subsection (2):<blockquote>&quot;(2A)(a) In the event of an employee referring to an adjudicating officer a complaint and being unable to prove to the Director General evidence of having obtained under section 23 a statement of his or her average hourly rate of pay in respect of a relevant pay reference period, or<br /><br />(b) having requested the statement has not been provided with it within the time limit by that section for the employer to supply the information,<br /><br />(c) the Director General shall advise the employee of the requirement to request a statement under section 23 and shall advise the said employee that the said complaint shall be placed on hold for a period of 90 days to enable the employee to furnish evidence under paragraph (a) or (b). For the avoidance of doubt any request made under section 23 within 90 days of receipt by the employee of a request from the Director General under paragraph (c) shall be a valid request under section 23 for the purposes of subsection (2) thereof.&quot;,</blockquote>(c) in section 36(1) by the insertion after the word cause of &quot;or threaten to cause&quot;.&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote>The reason for this amendment is that it is unnecessary that a party wishing to appeal a payment of wages decision must notify not only the entity to which he or she is appealing but also the other party.  Many payment of wages claims that go on appeal fail because of this archaic condition, which is unnecessary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.315" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T02600"><p>I am afraid we are on similar grounds to the previous amendment.</p> <p>The amendments to the National Minimum Wage Act 2000 that have been proposed by the Senator would also constitute a substantial rather than a procedural amendment to that legislation.  As I have already stated in response to the previous amendments, substantive changes to employment rights legislation such as that proposed by the Senator in this amendment fall outside of the scope of the present Bill.  Therefore, I am not going to accept these amendments.</p> <p>In relation to the Senator's proposed amendment to the Payment of Wages Act 1991, I wish to confirm that section 7(2)(b) of that Act relates to procedural matters concerning the appeal of the decision of a Rights Commissioner to the Employment Appeals Tribunal under that legislation.  The Workplace Relations Bill 2014 makes provision for the incorporation of the new appeals structures in the Labour Court in all employment rights legislation, including the Payment of Wages Act 1991, and, as a consequence, the provisions of section 7(2)(b) of that Act have been repealed by this Bill.  Accordingly, this amendment is a procedural rather than a substantive amendment to the Payment of Wages Act 1991.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.316" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T02700"><p>I do not accept the Minister of State's reasoning but I will withdraw the amendment and consider putting it forward on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.317" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.318" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Section 87, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.319" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SCHEDULE 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.320" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That Schedule 1 be Schedule 1 to the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.321" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T03200"><p>I wish to inform the House that I intend to introduce amendments of a technical and drafting nature to Schedules 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 on Report Stage.</p> <p>I also wish to inform the House that I intend to introduce two new Schedules to the Bill on Report Stage.  These schedules are purely of a technical and drafting nature and they will set out the relevant redress provisions in the individual employment enactments and statutory instruments under which redress can be awarded under sections 42 and 45 by WRC adjudicators and the Labour Court.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.322" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.323" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SCHEDULE 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.324" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T03500"><p>Amendment No. 140 is a Government amendment.  Amendments Nos. 140 to 142, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.325" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 140:</p><p>In page 74, between lines 14 and 15, to insert the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>5.       No. 22 of 1993       Unfair Dismissals (Amendment) Act 1993       Sections 11 and 12</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.326" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T03700"><p>Amendments Nos. 140, 141 and 142 are required to ensure that all necessary and appropriate appeals of existing legislative provisions are captured and that no provision that is required in the future is inadvertently appealed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.327" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.328" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 141:

In page 74, to delete lines 31 to 33.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.329" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.330" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 142:

In page 75, to delete lines 28 and 29.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.331" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p><p>Schedule 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.332" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedule 3 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.333" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SCHEDULE 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.334" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T04500"><p>Amendment No. 143 is a Government amendment.  Amendments Nos. 143 to 145, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.335" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 143:</p><p>In page 80, between lines 5 and 6, to insert the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>No. 10 of 1977       Unfair Dismissals Act 1977       Section 14(1), (2) and (4)</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.336" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T04700"><p>Amendments Nos. 143 to 145, inclusive, to Schedule 4 reorder the lists of Acts referred to the schedule in chronological order for ease of use, and make minor corrections to the sections of the Organisation of Working Time Act 1997, non-compliance with which may be the subject of a compliance notice issued by an inspector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.337" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.338" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 144:</p><p>In page 80, to delete lines 10 to 13 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>No. 20 of 1997       Organisation of Working Time Act 1997       Sections 6(2), 11, 12, 13,

14(1), 15(1), 16(2), 17, 18,

19(1), 19(1A), 21, 22, and

23(1) and (2)</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.339" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.340" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 145:

In page 80, to delete line 14.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.341" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.342" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedule 4, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.343" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SCHEDULE 5</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.344" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T05600"><p>Amendment No. 146 is a Government amendment.  Amendments Nos. 146 and 147 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.345" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 146:

In page 82, line 6, to delete &quot;Regulations 4(4)(a) and 13&quot; and substitute &quot;Regulation 4(4)(a)&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.346" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T05800"><p>Amendments Nos. 146 and 147 delete a superfluous reference to a regulation in the European Communities (Protection of Employees on Transfer of Undertakings) Regulations 2003 and delete a duplicated reference to the Minimum Notice and Terms of Employment Act 1973.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.347" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.348" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 147:

In page 82, to delete line 26.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.349" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.350" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedule 5, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.351" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SCHEDULE 6</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.352" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T06400"><p>Amendment No. 148 is a Government amendment.  Amendments Nos. 148 to 199, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.353" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 148:</p><p>In page 83, to delete lines 26 to 36 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the

worker compensation of such

amount (if any) as the adjudication

officer considers just and equitable

having regard to all of the

circumstances, but not exceeding 2

years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of

the worker&rsquo;s employment

calculated in accordance with

regulations under section 17 of the

Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&quot;.</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.354" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#T06600"><p>I am glad the Leas-Chathaoirleach achieved agreement on that grouping anyway.</p> <p>Amendment Nos. 148 to 199, inclusive, to Schedule 6 set out the consequential amendments that it will be necessary to make to other employment enactments and statutory instruments as a result of the new structures for the adjudication of complaints and disputes that will be introduced by this Bill.  Amendment Nos. 148 to 199, inclusive, to Schedule 6 are of a technical and drafting nature and are necessary and appropriate to ensure consistency of language and style in the Statute Book.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.355" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.356" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 149:

In page 83, to delete lines 37 to 44.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.357" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.358" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 150:</p><p>In page 85, to delete lines 23 to 33 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the

employee compensation of such

amount (if any) as is just and

equitable having regard to all of

the circumstances, but not

exceeding 4 weeks&rsquo; remuneration

in respect of the employee&rsquo;s

employment calculated in

accordance with regulations under

section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals

Act 1977.      </p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.359" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.360" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 151:

In page 85, to delete lines 34 to 41.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.361" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.362" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 152:</p><p>In page 88, to delete lines 4 to 6 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(a) complied with a direction under section 6A given in relation to the contravention before the commencement of section 8of the Workplace Relations Act 2015, or</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.363" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.364" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 153:</p><p>In page 88, to delete lines 43 to 45 and in page 89, to delete lines 4 to 11 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(d) order the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 4 weeks&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.365" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.366" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 154:

In page 89, to delete lines 12 to 20.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.367" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.368" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 155:</p><p>In page 93, to delete lines 34 to 38 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) order the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as is just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.369" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.370" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 156:

In page 93, to delete lines 39 to 46.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.371" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.372" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 157:</p><p>In page 94, to delete lines 30 to 35 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) order the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.373" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.374" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 158:

In page 94, to delete lines 36 to 43.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.375" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.376" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 159:</p><p>In page 95, to delete lines 26 to 32 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as is just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.377" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.378" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 160:

In page 95, to delete lines 33 to 41.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.379" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.380" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 161:</p><p>In page 101, to delete lines 15 to 34 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as is just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 104 weeks&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.381" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.382" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 162:

In page 101, to delete lines 35 to 47 and in page 102, to delete lines 4 to 6.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.383" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.384" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 163:</p><p>In page 102, to delete lines 10 to 21 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;(6) A decision of the Labour Court under section 45 of the Workplace Relations Act 2015, on appeal from a decision of an adjudication officer referred to in subsection (5), shall affirm, vary or set aside the decision of the adjudication officer.&rdquo;,

and

(e) the deletion of subsection (7).</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.385" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.386" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 164:</p><p>In page 106, to delete lines 4 to 12 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>14.       No. 19 of 2001       Carer&rsquo;s Leave Act 2001       Section 2 is amended, in subsection (1), by the substitution of the following definition for the definition of Minister:&ldquo; &lsquo;Minister&rsquo; means the Minister for Justice and Equality;&rdquo;.Section 17 is amended&mdash;(a) in subsection (1), by the deletion of the words &ldquo;applies to any dispute between an employee and the employer relating to any entitlement of the employee under this Act (or any matter arising out of or related to such an entitlement) but&rdquo;, and</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.387" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.388" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 165:</p><p>In page 107, to delete lines 41 to 45 and in page 108, to delete lines 4 to 10 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>&ldquo;(1) In proceedings under Part 4of the Workplace Relations Act 2015in respect of a complaint of a contravention of section 8A(5), it shall not be necessary for the employee to show that he or she has at least one year&rsquo;s continuous service with the employer concerned.&rdquo;,</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.389" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.390" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 166:</p><p>In page 108, to delete lines 40 to 46 and in page 109, to delete lines 4 to 32 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 104 weeks&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations under section 17 of the  Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.391" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.392" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 167:</p><p>In page 109, to delete lines 33 to 47 and on page 110, to delete line 4 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(b) by the substitution of the following paragraph for paragraph 2:&ldquo;2 A decision of the Labour Court under section 45of the Workplace Relations Act 2015, on appeal from a decision of an adjudication officer referred to in paragraph 1(3), shall affirm, vary or set aside the decision of the adjudication officer.&rdquo;,</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.393" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.394" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 168:</p><p>In page 110, to delete lines 5 to 23 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) in paragraph 3 by&mdash;(i) the substitution of the following subparagraph for subparagraph (7):&ldquo;(7) In proceedings under Part 4of the Workplace Relations Act 2015in relation to a complaint that section 8A(5) has been contravened, it shall be presumed, until the contrary is proved, that the employee concerned acted reasonably and in good faith in forming the opinion and making the communication concerned.&rdquo;,</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.395" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.396" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 169:</p><p>In page 110, to delete lines 24 to 36 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(ii) the substitution, in clause (a) of subparagraph (8), of &ldquo;a complaint in respect of the contravention shall not be referable to an adjudication officer under section 42of the Workplace Relations Act 2015or a mediation officer under section 39of that Act&rdquo; for &ldquo;such dismissal may not be presented to a rights commissioner under paragraph 1(1)&rdquo;, and</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.397" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.398" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 170:</p><p>In page 110, to delete lines 37 to 46 and in page 111, to delete lines 4 and 5 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(iv) the substitution, in clause (b) of subparagraph (8), of &ldquo;a complaint to the Director General of the Workplace Relations Commission under section 42of the Workplace Relations Act 2015in respect of a contravention&rdquo; for &ldquo;a complaint to a rights commissioner under paragraph 1(1) in respect of a dismissal&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.399" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.400" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 171:</p><p>In page 111, to delete lines 25 to 32, and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.401" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.402" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 172:

In page 111, to delete lines 33 to 40.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.403" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.404" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 173:</p><p>In page 112, to delete lines 43 to 45 and page 113, to delete lines 4 to 34 substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 104 weeks&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&quot;,</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.405" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.406" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 174:</p><p>In page 114, to delete lines 21 to 28 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(d) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment.&quot;.</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.407" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.408" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 175:

In page 114, to delete lines 29 to 36.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.409" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.410" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 176:</p><p>In page 118, to delete lines 26 to 40 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment.&quot;,</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.411" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.412" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 177:

In page 118, to delete lines 41 to 46 and page 119, to delete lines 4 to 10.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.413" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.414" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 178:</p><p>In page 120, to delete lines 4 to 13 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers  just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances.&quot;.</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.415" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.416" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 179:

In page 120, to delete lines 14 to 26.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.417" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.418" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 180:</p><p>In page 121, to delete lines 20 to 40 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 104 weeks&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&quot;,</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.419" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.420" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 181:

In page 121, to delete lines 41 to 47 and in page 122, to delete lines 4 to 9.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.421" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.422" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 182:</p><p>In page 125, to delete lines 11 to 31 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 104 weeks&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&quot;,</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.423" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.424" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 183:</p><p>In page 125, to delete lines 35 to 46 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>&quot;(8A) A decision of the Labour Court under section 45of the Workplace Relations Act 2015, on appeal from a decision of an adjudication officer referred to in subsection (5), shall affirm, vary or set aside the decision of the adjudication officer.&quot;,and

(e) by the deletion of subsection (4), (6), (7) and (8).</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.425" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.426" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 184:</p><p>In page 129, to delete lines 18 to 38 and substitute the following:</p><p>&quot;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&quot;.</p><p>&quot;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.427" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.428" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 185:

In page 129, to delete lines 39 to 47 and in page 130, to delete lines 4 to 9.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.429" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.430" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 186:</p><p>In page 130, to delete lines 26 to 45, to delete page 131, and in page 132, to delete lines 4 to 36 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>30.       

No. 40 of 2011       

Property Services (Regulation) Act 2011       

Schedule 4 is amended&mdash;(a) in paragraph 1, by&mdash;(i) the substitution of the following subparagraph for subparagraph (1):&ldquo;(1) In proceedings under Part 4of the Workplace Relations Act 2015in respect of a complaint of a contravention of section 67(5), it shall not be necessary for the employee to show that he or she has at least one year&rsquo;s continuous service with the employer concerned.&rdquo;,(ii) the substitution of the following subparagraph for subparagraph (3):&ldquo;(3) A decision of an adjudication officer under section 42of the Workplace Relations Act 2015in relation to a complaint of a contravention of section 67(5) shall do one or more of the following, namely&mdash;(a) declare that the complaint was or, as the case may be, was not well founded,

(b) require the employer to take a specified course of action, which may include, in a case where the penalisation constitutes a dismissal, reinstatement or reengagement, or

(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 104 weeks&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&rdquo;,(b) by the substitution of the following paragraph for paragraph 2:&ldquo;2. A decision of the Labour Court under section 45of the Workplace Relations Act 2015, on appeal from a decision of an adjudication officer referred to in paragraph 1(3), shall affirm, vary or set aside the decision of the adjudication officer.&rdquo;,and(c) in paragraph 3, by&mdash;(i) the substitution, in subparagraph (7), of &ldquo;Part 4of the Workplace Relations Act 2015&rdquo; for &ldquo;this Schedule before a rights commissioner or the Labour Court&rdquo;,

(ii) the substitution, in clause (a) of subparagraph (8), of &ldquo;an adjudication officer under section 42of the Workplace Relations Act 2015&rdquo; for &ldquo;a rights commissioner under paragraph 1(1)&rdquo;, and

(iii) the substitution, in clause (b) of subparagraph (8), of &ldquo;an adjudication officer under section 42of the Workplace Relations Act 2015&rdquo; for &ldquo;a rights commissioner under paragraph 1(1)&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.431" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.432" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 187:</p><p>In page 133, to delete lines 29 to 46 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) require the employer or hirer, as the case may be, to pay to the employee or agency worker compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s or agency worker&rsquo;s employment.&rdquo;,</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.433" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.434" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 188:

In page 134, to delete lines 4 to 18.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.435" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.436" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 189:</p><p>In page 139, to delete lines 30 to 45 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>2.       S.I. No. 131 of 2003       European Communities (Protection of Employees on Transfer of Undertakings) Regulations 2003       The following Regulation is substituted for Regulation 10:&ldquo;Decision under section 42of Workplace Relations Act 201510. A decision of an adjudication officer under section 42of the Workplace Relations Act 2015in relation to a complaint of a contravention of a provision (other than Regulation 4(4)(a)) of these Regulations shall do one or more of the following, namely&mdash;</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.437" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.438" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 190:</p><p>In page 140, to delete lines 40 to 49 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment calculated in accordance with regulations made under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.439" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.440" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 191:

In page 141, to delete lines 4 to 20.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.441" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.442" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 192:</p><p>In page 142, to delete lines 14 to 29 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the crew member compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the crew member&rsquo;s employment.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.443" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.444" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 193:

In page 142, to delete lines 30 to 42.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.445" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.446" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 194:</p><p>In page 145, to delete lines 15 to 30 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the employee compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the employee&rsquo;s employment.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.447" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.448" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 195:

In page 145, to delete lines 31 to 43.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.449" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.450" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 196:</p><p>In page 148, to delete lines 5 to 13 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay to the mobile worker compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all the circumstances, but not exceeding 2 years&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the mobile worker&rsquo;s employment.&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.451" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.452" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 197:

In page 148, to delete lines 14 to 21.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.453" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.454" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 198:</p><p>In page 149, to delete lines 8 to 19 and substitute the following:</p><p>&ldquo;</p><p>(c) require the employer to pay the mobile worker compensation of such amount (if any) as the adjudication officer considers just and equitable having regard to all of the circumstances, but not exceeding 104 weeks&rsquo; remuneration in respect of the mobile worker&rsquo;s employment (calculated in accordance with requirements under section 17 of the Unfair Dismissals Act 1977).&rdquo;.</p><p>&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.455" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.456" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 199:

In page 149, to delete lines 20 to 27.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.457" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.458" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Schedule 6, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.459" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>TITLE</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.460" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 200:

In page 9, line 12, to delete &ldquo;functions first instance&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;first instance functions&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.461" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1078" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#X03200"><p>This amendment merely proposes a reordering of the wording to correct an error in syntax, and it involves no substantive change to the Bill's Long Title.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.462" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.463" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Title, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.464" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.465" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#X03600"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.466" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015030500002#X03700"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.467" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Report Stage ordered for Tuesday, 10 March 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-05a.468" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 1.50 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 10 March 2015.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>