<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to address the funding shortfall at Togher family support centre in Cork and to outline the plans her Department is putting in place to rectify this matter.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with special responsibility for defence to make a statement on the amount of money being spent on the purchase of new ships for the Irish Naval Service.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aidan Davitt of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation to address the direct threats to Irish foreign direct investment and jobs growth due to domestic policy decisions, the housing crisis and the current planning process system that are making Ireland an uncompetitive jurisdiction for retaining our current foreign direct investment footprint and attracting new investment.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister<font color="#2F2F2F"> </font>for Transport, Tourism and Sport to provide emergency funding for the repair of the Olympic swimming pool in the University of Limerick.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to confirm the number of fast-track applications submitted to An Bord Plean&aacute;la in 2017; the number of housing units involved; the number of applications granted under the scheme; and if An Bord Plean&aacute;la is ready to roll out an IT interface with the public in terms of online submissions. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection to outline the number of former miners who worked in Arigna and in other mines who have availed of disablement benefit due to work-related illness; and whether there are enough resources currently available to expedite existing applications from former miners seeking disablement benefit.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Buttimer, Gavan and Davitt and they will be taken now.  Senator Byrne has withdrawn her commencement matter which I had selected.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#A00250">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#A00300">Family Support Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#A00400"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Zappone, to the House.  As Leader, I congratulate her on her Galas success.  Grove Cottage, the Togher family support service, is an important community facility that gives access to families who need its services.  Some 77 children and families availed of the service last year.  This group of people fall between private and public funding and cannot afford a service at the prices being asked but are accommodated by the Togher family support service.  The centre is hugely important in the area of family law and child care and caters for estranged parents in a variety of different relationships.</p><p>I received an email from a mother who said:</p><blockquote>I have been availing of their child contact service which allows me to see and build a relationship with my daughter, ... which I would otherwise not have been able to do without this service.<br /><br />There are other private organisations that provide a child contact service in the Cork area, but as I am in receipt of social welfare I am unable to avail of their services due to the much higher cost per visit.<br /><br />If this service closes as planned then I will have a real struggle maintaining a relationship with my 4 year old daughter.</blockquote> <p>I received another email from a person with whom I am well acquainted, who wrote:</p><blockquote>Seeing my child is the hope that was given to me when I needed it.  I am secure in the knowledge that they work directly with &quot;Children First&quot; in mind at all times.<br /><br />It is tragic that the one and only place that can offer this support in Cork is being closed due to lack of funds.  I have no doubt that I would have been at the very least feeling suicidal by now had I still not seen my child.  I dread to think of her growing up without her mother.</blockquote> <p>These are emotional emails.  The Minister has met with representatives of the Togher family centre and I commend her on her proactivity in this regard.  She has a child-centred brief and is very much in control of it and if she visited the centre she would see the quality of the people who work there.  If she went into Grove Cottage she would see the environment - the toys, the furnishings, the care, the support and the safe, child-friendly environment, which are testimony to Jackie Costello and the people who work there.  The centre ensures there is an environment where relationships can be rebuilt, advice and support are offered and professional supervision is provided for our most vulnerable at a critical time in their lives, whether they are recovering from addiction or coming out of domestic abuse or sexual violence.</p><p>The Department of Justice and Equality and the Department of Children and Youth Affairs will be aware of issues with the courts referring people to this service in Togher, which is happening more a more and is further testimony to the work being done at the centre at Grove Cottage.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> This is about children and families.  I recognise that Tusla provides funding to Togher family centre in the area of access, but we must look at the people who fall through the cracks.  I appeal to the Ministers in the Department of Justice Equality and the Department of Children and Youth Affairs to come to an understanding that intervention in the form of provision of extra funding is needed, or perhaps new funding is needed, because this is a very important service.</p><p>I was the Chairman of the committee involved in the pre-legislative scrutiny of Children First and which recognised the importance of the children's referendum.  I do not mean to be patronising but the Minister is bringing a certain and a different emphasis that was not, perhaps, in the role before.  This is about children and their right to have a relationship with their families.</p><p>I would hope that the work of Grove Cottage, which has developed and evolved beyond what was envisaged on day one, will continue.  It provides quality affordable child contact, and I know from going there and meeting with parents and staff that this is an issue that is going arise in other parts of the country, because more referrals are taking place.  The request for funding to expand the service was unsuccessful in the past, but I hope that now, at a time when we have seen an increase in budgets, an accommodation can be found.</p><p>I commend the work that is being done, which the Minister knows about because she has met with the staff there, and I hope that we can find extra funding.  I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for choosing this matter.  He knows that as Leader I rarely put in Commencement matters, but this is one I feel very passionate about.  Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#B00200"><p>I accept that.  Thank you, Senator.  I call on the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#B00300"><p>Thank you.  I love to hear the call of the Seanad each morning, and I am delighted to come here to address and respond to the issue raised by Senator Buttimer, a very special colleague whose legacy on marriage equality hit the shores of Australia last night, so I congratulate him.</p><p>To the matter at hand, the Togher family centre operates as an independent organisation and is governed by a board of management that is representative of the local community.  As Senator Buttimer noted, I have had the opportunity to meet the staff.  I acknowledge that it is a voluntary, community-based service located in the heart of Deanrock Estate, Togher, Cork city, and it provides a range of services, including early years education; integrated support and early identification of need; family support services; family access services; adult education; and early intervention youth work.</p><p>It was not immediately clear from the question if the Senator had a particular service in mind, although it may be clear in light of his contribution this morning.  The centre receives funding from my Department under the early childhood care and education, ECCE, scheme and the community childcare subvention, CCS, scheme.  Funding to Togher family centre under both schemes to date in 2017 comes to a total of just over &euro;295,000.  In 2017, funding of more than &euro;30,000 was also provided by my Department, through the Cork Education and Training Board, for the Togher youth resilience project, which is based in Togher family centre.  Tusla, the Child and Family Agency, has advised that it provided funding of approximately &euro;144,000 to the centre this year.  An additional &euro;26,000 was also provided by Tusla to the centre in recent months, bringing the total funding allocation to more than &euro;170,000 in 2017.  This is an increase of almost &euro;33,000 over 2016.  I understand the centre also receives funding from the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection under the school meals programme, and from various other sources.</p><p>The Togher family centre provides a service in line with the principles of Tusla&rsquo;s prevention, partnership and family support programme.  The main focus of services is on early intervention to promote and protect the health and well-being of children, young people and their families.  The centre, as the Senator has referred to, has also developed an access centre which provides services to children in care and their families.  This provides a safe, neutral and child-focused setting for children to visit with their non-custodial parent.  All visits and exchanges take place under the supervision of trained staff.  Togher family centre can arrange for supervised access through referrals from Tusla.  Supported or fully supervised access is also offered depending on the needs of the particular family.</p><p>I understand that in recent times the access centre has experienced considerable demand from the family law courts, guardians <i>ad litem</i>and other parties, and has provided, where possible, supervised access for referrals from these parties.  It is important to reiterate that the core work of the centre is focused on referrals from Tusla, and it is not always possible for the access centre to satisfy the increased demand from other sources.  I say this while being cognisant of the emails Senator Buttimer shared with us this morning.</p><p>My Department has also received an application from the centre for community employment sustainability funding in the early years sector.  Financial reserves were identified in that process, and my officials requested clarification on the use of these reserves and their relevance to child care funding.  Following a response from the centre, the position is under review, and my officials will revert to the centre in due course.  In situations such as this, decisions with regard to future funding levels for individual service providers are informed by the business case put forward by the provider in question and an assessment of service need in the locality in question undertaken by the relevant funding authorities.  It is important that this process is undertaken and completed in order to allow for an informed assessment to be made on the funding issue raised, having regard to the available resources and competing priorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#B00400"><p>I thank the Minister.  Would the Senator like to respond?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#B00500"><p>I thank the Minister for her reply.  I hope that we can bring a resolution to the issue.  The Minister is also working with the Department of Justice and Equality in this area.  It is a matter that is ongoing in other parts of the country as well.  The work being done here, and the emails I read out, are testimonials from people.  The amount of money involved is relatively small in the overall scheme of things, and I look forward to working with the Department and with the Minister in ensuring that we can continue the service.  There is a fear that the service will close in January, which I think all of us would want to see averted because this is about ensuring that family access continues.  I thank the Minister for her reply and I hope that we can overcome any obstacle to ensure the service continues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#B00700"><p>The case was put forward very strongly by the Senator, resulting from his ongoing commitment to and engagement with the centre.  I reiterate the importance of a strong business case when the funding is being sought, and note that at least one application for funding from the centre is still under review in my Department.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.16" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#B00850">Naval Service Vessels</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#B00900"><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, is taking this Commencement matter on behalf of Minister of State, Deputy Paul Kehoe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#B01000"><p>Go raibh maith agat, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.  The Minister of State is very welcome.  I want to raise the issue of defence spending this morning.  We learned in recent weeks of plans by the Naval Service to purchase a new multi-role vessel, MRV.  In recent years, the Naval Service has purchased three new ships, with a fourth ship on order, for a total of over &euro;250 million.  This additional MRV is likely to cost over &euro;200 million, bringing the cost of five new ships to almost<b></b>&euro;500 million<b>.  </b>Yet at the same time, the Naval Service is selling off its older ships for a pittance.  The <i>L&Eacute; Emer</i>, the <i>L&Eacute; Deirdre </i>and the <i>L&Eacute; Aisling </i>were sold for &euro;320,000, &euro;240,000 and &euro;110,000, respectively.  The point is that these ships could have been refurbished for a fraction of the cost of these unnecessary new warships.  Ireland should only need naval vessels for fishery protection, emergency rescue and prevention of smuggling.  As a neutral state, we have no requirements for aggressive warships.  The misuse of the Irish Naval Service was highlighted when the <i>L&Eacute; William Butler Yeats </i>replaced the <i>L&Eacute; Eithne </i>in the Mediterranean for Operation Sophia, which unfortunately will result in the redeployment of Naval Service vessels from primarily humanitarian search and rescue to primarily security and interception operations.  Indeed, this move has been condemned by M&eacute;decins sans Fronti&egrave;res and others, and is highly inappropriate for a neutral country.</p><p>Taxpayer funding for the Defence Forces is necessarily limited when we have 700,000 people on our hospital waiting lists and 8,000 homeless, including, as I heard this morning, 3,124 children.  What I am trying to do is make sense of what is happening here, because over the years of the ever-growing crisis in housing and health, we have discovered that the Department of Defence has been spending money like confetti on warships.  In my city of Limerick tonight, we will have 154 homeless children sleeping in hotel beds.  We had 719 patients on trolleys in University Hospital Limerick in the month of October.  Can the Minister of State explain why, at the time of the worst housing crisis in the history of the State and the worst health care crisis since the 1940s, her Government cannot sanction the money to build houses or hospital wings, but has been able to sanction almost &euro;500 million in funding for new warships?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Unfortunately, this replacement will result in the redeployment of Naval Service vessels from primarily search and rescue to primarily security and interception operations.  This move has been condemned by M&eacute;decins sans Fronti&egrave;res and others and is highly inappropriate for a neutral country.</p><p>Taxpayer funding for the Defence Forces is necessarily limited since we have 700,000 on our hospital waiting lists and 8,000 homeless, including 3,124 children, as I learned this morning.  I am trying to make sense of what is happening because during the same years as the ever-growing crises in housing and health we discovered that the Department of Defence has been spending money like confetti on war ships.  Tonight, in my city of Limerick, a total of 154 homeless children will sleep in hotel beds.  A total of 719 patients were on trollies in University Hospital Limerick in October.  Can the Minister of State explain why, at a time of the worst housing crisis in the history of the State and the worth health care crisis since the 1940s, the Government cannot sanction the money to build houses or hospital wings but has been able to sanction almost &euro;500 million in funding for new war ships?</p><p>Even if we decide the money has to be spent on defence &ndash; I do not accept that argument &ndash; then other points arise, including low pay and conditions in the Army.  People are voting with their feet.  My colleague, Senator Craughwell has been very articulate on this topic on several occasions.  People are leaving the Army because of low pay.  The Air Corps search and rescue service was in such a state of under-funding that it was unable to support the tragic rescue operation in Blacksod Bay in March.  There is serious under-funding within our defence sector while we are spending vast amounts, hundreds of millions of euro, on new naval ships.  I am obliged to conclude that it must be connected to our ever-increasing complicity in the new EU military battle plans.</p><p>I am seeking answers to these questions.  I am unsure of the position in the constituency of the Minister of State but I have described what it is like in my constituency.  We have a shocking health and housing crisis.  Yet, the Government consistently believes that it is better to spend money on war ships than on housing for people or on their health.  It makes no sense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#C00200"><p>I wish to acknowledge Senator Gavan's commencement matter.  On behalf of the Minister of State with responsibility for defence, Deputy Paul Kehoe, who cannot be present due to other commitments, I wish to take the opportunity to respond to the Senator on the topic he has raised.</p><p>It is a priority of the Minister of State, Deputy Kehoe, to ensure that the operational capability of the Army, Air Corps and Naval Service is maintained to the greatest extent possible.  This is primarily to enable the Defence Forces to carry out their roles as assigned by Government and as set out in the White Paper on Defence.</p><p>The Naval Service is the principal sea-going agency of the State and is charged with maritime defence, fisheries protection, contraband interdiction duties, search and rescue and enforcing Irish and EU law and legislation with the Irish economic zone.  This zone currently extends to 132,000 square miles.  This area is approximately five times the size of Ireland and amounts to approximately 16% of all EU waters.</p><p>The Naval Service currently operates eight ships in a flotilla.  Equipment priorities for the Army, Air Corps and Naval Service to enable them to carry out the roles assigned by Government are being considered in the context of the lifetime of the White Paper on Defence as part of the capability development and equipment planning process.  In this context the principal aim over the period of the White Paper is to replace and upgrade, as required, existing capabilities to retain a flexible response for a wide range of operational requirements at home and overseas.</p><p>The defence capital envelope for the period 2018-21 is &euro;416 million.  This will enable investment in major equipment platforms, including the continuing replacement and refurbishment of Naval Service vessels.  The White Paper underpins the ongoing replacement of the Naval Service fleet.  The most significant investment of recent years by the defence organisation has been on the procurement of the new off-shore patrol vessels for the Naval Service.  The third ship in the programme, <i>L&Eacute; William Butler Yeats</i>, was commissioned into service in October 2016.  The three ships are performing well in operational service and have been a great enhancement to the capacity of the Naval Service.</p><p>A contract for an additional sister ship was placed with Babcock International, a British company, in June 2016.  The fourth ship, to be named <i>L&Eacute; George Bernard Shaw</i>, is scheduled for delivery in mid-2018.  This aligns with the planning process in place under the White Paper on Defence, which will determine the defence organisation's maritime capability requirements.  The requirement for a fourth ship is regarded as urgent and expedient given the age of the older remaining ships in the fleet, <i>L&Eacute; Orla</i>, <i>L&Eacute; Ciara</i>and <i>L&Eacute; Eithne</i>, all of which are over 30 years of age.  In tandem with the acquisition of the new ships, the defence organisation has commenced planning for a mid-life refurbishment programme for the <i>L&Eacute; Roisin</i>and the <i>L&Eacute; Niamh</i>.  The new ship will allow the Naval Service to meet its patrol day targets with due cognisance to the significant additional operational requirements for the naval fleet under the current Operation Sophia and previously under Operation Pontus in the Mediterranean Sea.</p><p>Overall, 17,500 migrants have been rescued since Naval Service vessels were first deployed in the Mediterranean Sea in May 2015 as part of Operation Pontus.  The deployment of Irish naval vessels to the humanitarian mission in the Mediterranean over the past three years to engage in search and rescue tasks has been an important element in Ireland's response to the migration crisis in the Mediterranean.  The operation finished in October 2017.  Since October 2017, the Naval Service is participating in the EU naval mission Operation Sophia.  In accordance with the mandate for the mission, the Naval Service can be involved in surveillance and intelligence-gathering operations, search and rescue operations and disposal of migrant boats and force protection operations.  Operation Sophia has thus far contributed to the apprehension of 117 suspected smugglers and traffickers.  It has removed 497 boats from criminal organisations and it has contributed to 278 safety of life at sea events.  Most important, it has saved the lives of over 41,500 migrants.</p><p>The expenditure on the Naval Service vessel replacement programme has to be taken in context the four new offshore patrol vessels will serve the country for the next 30 years and will provide good value for money given the nature of the assets and associated capacity involved.  The acquisition of these modern new vessels combined with an ongoing maintenance regime for all vessels within the fleet and the continuous process of refurbishment, refit and repair, will ensure that the operational capacity of the Naval Service as the State's principal sea-going agency are maintained to the greatest extent.</p><p>I will address further some of the comments the Senator made in my subsequent contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#C00300"><p>Not for the first time, the Minister of State has been put in a difficult position.  In fairness to the Minister of State, the response from the civil servants does not answer the questions I have put.  I asked how the Government can justify the expenditure of hundreds of millions of euro on new boats when we could have refurbished our existing fleet and put the surplus money towards the health and housing crises that have been ever-present in recent years.  It speaks poorly of the Government that its priority are to please its friends in the EU by increasing military spending rather than looking after our people at home with better health and housing.</p> <p>Another point relates to the disgraceful decision to send the L&Eacute; Samuel Beckett to the biggest arms fair in the world.  God knows what the great man would have thought of that.  Is that what has become of our neutrality?  We are now sending one of our flagship naval vessels to the biggest arms fair in the world at taxpayers' expense to help in selling arms and equipment to gangsters from throughout the world.  It is absolutely shameful.</p> <p>I know the constituency the Minister of State is from.  I cannot believe that her constituents would be impressed by the fact that we can find hundreds of millions for new ships but not for hospital beds or housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#C00400"><p>I do not have a written response to the Senator's remarks but I will give him some information that may be helpful.  The Government is providing over &euro;5 billion for housing in the coming years and is making steady progress.  On a weekly basis, over 100 people are finding themselves housed in new homes.  I believed it is not just to say that nothing is happening, because it is.</p> <p>We have seen the biggest budget ever in the health service in the lifetime of this Government and things are happening in the health service.  It is wrong to say that the identification of people within the health service on waiting lists and people using the service are not being dealt with.  This is happening on a daily basis under the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris.  The new primary care centres throughout the country add to the flexibility of people being able to arrive on the door of a primary care centre.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2186"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2186&amp;amp;pid=CatherineByrne&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Going back to the provision of funding for Naval Service vessels, the Government recognises that the men and women of the Air Corps, the Army and the Naval Service provide a service that protects people whose lives might otherwise be in danger.  They do so without ever complaining about the risk to their own lives on a daily basis.  It is incumbent on us all, particularly those of us in government, to ensure the best vessels and equipment are provided for the Defence Forces.  The Army, the Air Corps and the Naval Service enjoy an excellent reputation at home and throughout Europe.  The efforts of the Naval Service which has lent its vessels and personnel to serve in rescue missions in the Mediterranean have been especially welcome.  I take the opportunity to acknowledge the men and women who put their own lives at risk on a daily basis to protect others.  As parliamentarians and citizens of this country, we support measures that will ensure they will have the best equipment and vessels at their disposal in order that they can continue to save lives and take part in humanitarian missions in the Mediterranean.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.24" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#D00150">Foreign Direct Investment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#D00200"><p>I am concerned that domestic policy decisions, the housing crisis and the planning system are leading to an uncompetitive environment in the State for the retention of foreign direct investment and damaging efforts to attract new investment.  Deputy Niall Collins raised these concerns in the D&aacute;il and has asked the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation to address them at the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation.  She has not yet agreed to appear before the committee to have that discussion.</p> <p>The recently published report by American Chamber of Commerce Ireland, Growing Great Teams in Ireland: The Role of the Residential Rental Sector, clearly illustrates the severity of the housing shortage and how it could lead to Ireland being uncompetitive in the future which could, in turn, be a deterrent to foreign direct investment.  The report states more than 30,000 new one-bedroom and two-bedroom rental properties are needed in Dublin by 2022 to meet the housing demand arising from the new jobs created by foreign direct investment.  The T&aacute;naiste and IDA Ireland must outline the Government's response to this finding from a jobs growth perspective.  The Government can no longer sit on the sidelines and hope the housing crisis will end and house constructions will commence.  All successful projects work from the bottom up.  It is easy to see that the Government's refusal to launch an organised and co-ordinated social and affordable house building programme is endangering further growth and the creation of high-end jobs in Ireland.</p> <p>The housing assistance payment, HAP, scheme is not a housing policy, but it is creating division in the country by pitting marginalised and working class families against each other in the competition for housing.  If it is to take the report by American Chamber of Commerce Ireland seriously, the Government can no longer simply point to its projected figures and state everything will work out and that the targets will be achieved by 2022.  We have had that talk from two Ministers in the past five years but nothing has actually been done.  We must have a co-ordinated plan based on a bottom-up approach.  We have totally neglected social housing.  The Taoiseach delivered a speech at a party conference in Cavan a few days ago which was full of bravado but which included no mention of social housing and no indication of an organised programme of house building.  If this matter is not addressed in a serious way, we will have chaotic problems.  Rents in Dublin are 20% higher than they were at their peak in 2008.  On average, a semi-detached house costs &euro;3,000 per month to rent in Dublin 1.  That is an horrific cost in an area in which many of the people who come to Ireland to work in higher end jobs are located and in which they wish to live.  We have had a lot of talk about solutions but zero substance when it comes to action.  Will the Minister of State indicate whether there is a definite plan in place to commence a house building programme?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#D00300"><p>I am taking this matter on behalf of the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation.  </p> <p>It is helpful to put our current foreign direct investment footprint into perspective by pointing out that 2016 was a record year for such investment in Ireland.  IDA Ireland client companies created nearly 19,000 new jobs during the year across a range of sectors, with every region of Ireland benefiting.  This strong performance has continued into 2017.  Investments approved by the agency in the first half of the year will lead to the creation of 11,000 jobs, compared with 9,000 for the equivalent period in 2016.  It is worth noting that 52% of all jobs created in 2016 were based outside Dublin and that the mid-year results for 2017 show that 54% of all job approvals so far this year are located outside the capital.  This clearly shows that IDA Ireland is committed to increasing investment in every region of the country.  It remains focused on that goal, as do the T&aacute;naiste and the Government.  In addition, IDA Ireland is working towards a number of ambitious targets, including the creation of 80,000 new jobs and 900 new investments in the period from 2015 to 2019.  This would bring total FDI employment in Ireland to 209,000.  The year 2016 marked the second year of implementation of the current strategy and over the first two years the agency is delivering well ahead of these targets.</p> <p>The Government accepts that the adequate supply of quality, affordable housing in the right locations, to buy and to rent, is a contributory factor to Ireland's overall competitiveness.  The link between the cost of housing and wage expectations means that developments in the residential property sector impact on our international competitiveness and ability to compete for mobile talent.  We are now one year into the implementation of Rebuilding Ireland, the Government's action plan for housing and homelessness.  In that time many key actions have been delivered or put in train and it is clear from a range of housing related trends that the supply response is coming on stream.  All key indicators of construction activity show that residential construction is ramping up considerably.  The number of planning permissions is up by almost 50% year on year and the ESRI's latest commentary in October forecast that the number of house completions would reach 19,000 this year and 24,000 in 2018.  On that basis, the Rebuilding Ireland target of 25,000 homes per year by 2020 will be met and quite likely exceeded.</p> <p>In the context of the recent outcome in Athenry, the Government is also taking action to implement an efficient and speedy planning process in order to avoid unreasonable delays in the future.  This may include the designation of data centres as strategic infrastructure developments for planning purposes, which would help to ensure future data centre related planning applications would move more swiftly through the planning process.</p> <p>Ireland's value proposition is based on a highly educated and skilled workforce, an attractive environment in which people want to live and work and a transparent corporate tax regime.  For foreign direct investment in Ireland, 2016 was a record year, both in terms of the number of jobs created and the value of investments won.  We are on track for more strong results in 2017, in a reflection of our continuing success in attracting capital rich foreign direct investment projects to Ireland.  I will cover some of the other issues raised by the Senator when I give my second reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#E00100"><p>The Minister of State has another minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#E00200"><p>Okay.  On the Apple data centre in Athenry, I want to be absolutely clear that while the company has not committed to proceed immediately, it has not abandoned the project in Galway.  The company has insisted that its potential investment remains under active consideration.  Given that the planning issues have now been resolved, we are optimistic that the data centre project will proceed.  I assure the Senator that IDA Ireland is in active dialogue with the company and continues to do everything it can to support the project.  Data centres remain an important aspect of Ireland's foreign direct investment as the strengths we can offer to this type of project, including our climate, energy supply and business environment, remain in place and are well known to potential investors.  I will cover some other issues which the Senator has raised after he responds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#E00300"><p>We are nearly out of time.  I am not sure if the reply hit the spot in respect of the Senator's complaint, but his time is nearly up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#E00400"><p>I appreciate the Minister of State coming to the House.  I know this is not her remit.  This is an issue which is not just important to me or to Opposition parties.  The American Chamber of Commerce Ireland is telling us that we have a serious issue.   On completions, two years ago we were told that we were going to have thousands of social houses.  Something like 67 houses were built.  Some of the figures which Ministers trot out are off the wall.  We are told that we have to be delivering 40,000 or so houses a year.  I do not believe we will even deliver 15,000 this year.  The Minister of State stated 18,000.  In June we were told there could be 11,000 to 12,000 completions.  I just cannot agree with some of the figures.  It is not just me, but the American Chamber of Commerce of Ireland as well.  That is why I am really concerned.  It is a very serious organisation.  It does not get excited too easily, but it is hearing it from the top down.  I know the Minister of State is a great believer in social housing.  I firmly believe that unless we start a real programme of social housing, which has to start from the bottom up building houses, we are going nowhere.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#E00500"><p>We are running out of time but I am sure this matter will arise again.  I thank the Minister of State.  I believe it is a case of "never the twain shall meet", but the Minister of State is only doing her job on behalf of the line Minister so I thank her for her response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.32" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.15 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.33" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Water Services Bill 2017 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 12.45 p.m.; No. 2, motion regarding an earlier signature motion regarding the Water Services Bill 2017, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, statements on health, to be taken at 3.30 p.m. and to conclude no later than 5.30 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be given no less than five minutes to reply; No. 4, Civil Liability (Amendment) Bill 2017 - Report Stage (amendments from D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann) and Final Stage, to be taken at 5.30 p.m.; and No. 57, motion 16, Private Members' business, to be taken at 6 p.m. with the time allocated to this debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00300"><p>The previous Taoiseach, Deputy Enda Kenny, used to talk about a scorecard for Ministers but he got rid of it because the scorecard did not show the results he wanted, which tells us a lot about how the Ministers were performing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00400"><p>The Senator would be a good judge of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00500"><p>We should avoid a "Kramer versus Kramer" situation, with Kerry versus Kerry in this instance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00600"><p>We hear that Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin has a scorecard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00700"><p>If Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael were like Kramer and Kramer, it all ended in divorce 100 years ago.  As regards the scorecard on housing, over 120,000 households are on the waiting lists but only 1,000 units have been provided.  There are 3,124 children and 5,250 adults in emergency accommodation awaiting housing, on top of those households on the waiting lists, which shows the size of the issue.  There has been a success rate of 0.65% which, even using Senator Coghlan's mathematics, is not a pass.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00800"><p>Senator Coghlan is a financial whizzkid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#G00900"><p>A pass rate would be 40% but the Government is nowhere near 40%.  In the Leader's county, 38 houses were provided and there were 59 in Cork city for a waiting list of 6,005 households.  As Senator Coghlan will be well aware, only 11 houses were provided in Kerry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00100"><p>The Senator is obsessed with Senator Coghlan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00300"><p>Despite this, 4,166 households are waiting.  I do not know, Senator Coghlan, whether you believe that is success but in my mind that is not success.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00400"><p>Through the Chair, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00500"><p>I do not think we can believe much from Senator Daly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00600"><p>For the benefit of Senator Coghlan, these are the Government's figures.  If he believes that we cannot believe the Government's figures-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00700"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00800"><p>-----then I do not know where we can go next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H00900"><p>Look it-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01000"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il must not have figures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01100"><p>Possibly of more importance are the figures that have come from <i>The Irish Times</i>which, as Senator Coghlan knows, is the paper of record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01200"><p>The more interruptions the longer the delay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01300"><p>We will keep interrupting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01400"><p>I must give another minute now as there have been three interruptions, and consistently so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01500"><p>Give the Senator another minute.  We will keep interrupting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing injury time on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01700"><p>The Senator should have been given a red card.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H01900"><p>Senator Mark Daly is injured.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02000"><p>Senator Conway, b&iacute; ci&uacute;in le do thoil.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02100"><p>I want to wish the Danish soccer team the best of luck, as we have talked about red cards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02200"><p>Do not go offside, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02300"><p>Senator Mark Daly is well offside.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02400"><p>There is no offside in Gaelic football and that is all I have to go by.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02500"><p>There is a square ball.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.67" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02700"><p>I wish the Danish soccer team the best of luck.  I thank the Irish team for entertaining us over the years.  It would have been a high point for the players on the Irish soccer team to go to the World Cup and we hope that there will be brighter days ahead.</p> <p>Unfortunately, there are not brighter days ahead when it comes to Brexit.  In fact, there are 499 days to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02800"><p>The Senator has gone from discussing soccer to discussing Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H02900"><p>At 11 a.m. on 29 March 2019, the UK will leave the European Union.  President Obama used to talk about hope one can believe in and certainly one could believe in that kind of hope.  The British Government's policy seems to be simply hope.  However, it is not hope one can believe in because they do not have a plan.</p> <p>Tomorrow, the British foreign affairs committee will come here and its chairman will visit the Border for the first time.  The British have no plan when it comes to Brexit.  They seem to be going against the customs union and the Single Market that would allow the Border to remain open.  They do not want a special status for Northern Ireland and yet somehow they hope that magically it will all work out.  In 499 days that policy of hope, without anything to back it up, will certainly not work. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03000"><p>The extra time is up, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03100"><p>I want to give an example-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03200"><p>Penalties, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03300"><p>-----of how hope is not a policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03400"><p>Go away now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03500"><p>Honda manufactures cars in England.  As many as 320 trucks arrive at its factory every day.  Honda only has 15 minutes worth of stock at any one time so a delay of one hour in production will cost &euro;880,000.  How does the British Government think that having no Border policy-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03600"><p>The Senator's time is up and he has scored nothing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03700"><p>-----for the North, or any border policy, is a policy?  Hope is simply not a policy.</p> <p>We welcome the Irish Government's policy of 100 points that Leo Varadkar has put out.  The Government needs to send a message to the British Government that it has not done enough to clarify the issues on the North and that discussions cannot be moved forward until such time as the North is sorted first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03800"><p>Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H03900"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H04000"><p>The Senator got penalty time and injury time.  I call Senator McDowell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H04400"><p>There was no score.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H04500"><p>Senator Daly is obsessed with Senator Coghlan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H04600"><p>Le do thoil, Senator McDowell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H04700"><p>Senator Daly has repeatedly made the same point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H04800"><p>They are not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H04900"><p>In recent days newspapers have covered further publicity about the question of having a single mayor for the greater Dublin area and four county councils or local authorities.  I noticed, also in the newspapers, a reference to the annual budget for Dublin City Council which is now close to &euro;1 billion a year with 6,000 staff.  Then I considered in that context the appalling squalor which existed in Crumlin as exposed by the &quot;Prime Time Investigates&quot; programme where people are being housed in subhuman conditions with bunk beds in tiny bedrooms for want of inspection by the local authority.  All of that makes me very cynical about the standard of local government in the Dublin area.</p><p>One particular issue from which local government has withdrawn was that of refuse collection.  I have recently received a communication from one councillor in Dublin called Councillor Keith Redmond.  He has told me that he has followed up the issue of what he considers to be <i>prima facie</i>evidence of a cartel among the waste collection companies whereby they are dividing the city, geographically, and not really competing with each other.  If the whole idea of privatising waste collection and introducing pay-by-weight and deregulating charges was to increase efficiency, it would be a complete travesty if it turned out that there is not any effective competition and that the companies involved are engaging in geographical division and no-go areas.</p><p>The alarming thing that Councillor Redmond told me was that he had been engaged in a phone conversation, on behalf of one of his constituents, with a particular company.  The person he dealt with at the end of the phone, and I will not mention the company or the person, indicated that there was such a territorial divide.  So surprised was Councillor Redmond to hear the news that he decided to record the balance of the conversation and has, apparently, clear evidence of such a divide up.  If that is the case then the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Murphy, or his Minister of State, Deputy English-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H05000"><p>And Deputy Naughten.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H05100"><p>-----should come to the House to explain to us what procedures are in place to prevent the total absence of competition in waste collection and the emergence of cartels and market division among the waste collection companies.  If the Government is going to rely on competition to keep prices down and if competition is allowed to wither away by secret deals among the waste collection companies, then the only people who will pay for all of this are the householders.</p> <p>Finally, with Dublin City Council's budget approaching &euro;1 billion, more and more of its services privatised, 6,000 employees and no inspectors to stop the exploitation of people in housing standards then surely it is about time that somebody asked the following questions.  Are we getting value for money from local authorities?  Is Dublin City Council that spends close to &euro;1 billion of taxpayers' money every year and not doing its job fit for purpose anymore?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#H05200"><p>I, too, wish to raise the issue of housing.  With reference to my own city of Limerick, this Friday we will see a new budget struck by the Fianna F&aacute;il-Fine Gael coalition.  Yes, I am afraid that we have a local coalition comprised of both of the parties as well as a national coalition.</p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in's council team reviewed the figures last Monday.  We learned that there will be nothing of substance to address the horrendous housing crisis in Limerick city.  There are 315 people homeless in Limerick, of which 154 are children, and there are thousands of people on the waiting list.  Let us consider the most telling figures.  Of the 2,443 additional tenancies that local councils provided in the past three years, more than 1,900 of them have gone to the private sector.  In other words, almost all of the so-called work of providing housing is throwing money at private landlords.  That is the solution provided by Fine Gael and, I am afraid to say, Fianna F&aacute;il.  That coalition has failed the people of Limerick day after day, which is a disgrace.  When will we realise that councils used to, in the worst of times, build housing?  When will the Government supply the money to make sure there is sufficient housing build in the pipeline?  I ask because we now know it is not.</p> <p>I wish put on the record something that we all know.  This crisis it not getting better; it is getting worse.  The figures in Limerick are proof.  Month after month the homeless figures continue to increase.  The number of people given notice by landlords, who are greedy unscrupulous landlords in many cases, continues to increase.  As Senator Byrne acknowledged yesterday, rents in Limerick have increased by 11% over the past year.  That is the failure of a Fine Gael-Fianna F&aacute;il coalition both locally and nationally.  I call on the Leader to arrange a debate on the issue.  It is not good enough for Fine Gael to keep believing in the mantra of a privatised solution for the housing problem.  It is a failure of politics and the party has had seven years to sort this out. </p> <p>The second issue I want to raise relates to the football match last night.  As we all know, we suffered a huge disappointment last night.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Our brothers and sisters in the North had an equally sad disappointment on Sunday night.  Despite our recent success in both qualifying for the European Championships and the heroic effort from players over the past 20 years, typically our teams have not managed to qualify.  I hope that there might be some wise heads in both organisations - the IFA and, in the South, the FAI - who might look at the prospect of having a conversation about a united Ireland football team.  Lord knows we could use it.  We could have used Jonny Evans last night in defence.  It is time to have a debate on the issue.  We need to look forward in football.  We know that we can have a united Ireland rugby team and have seen its tremendous success.  I am asking for a debate with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport because it would be good if the Government were to initiate such a project.  Let us see if we can have wise heads on both sides so that we can try to build a better future for football, North and South.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J00200"><p>This morning I read an article in <i>The Irish Times</i>by the director of the Dublin Region Homeless Executive on volunteers.  I was very disappointed with the language used in it.  Basically, it states that it is not helpful for volunteers to be giving out food and clothes to the homeless.  I do not believe such comments are helpful to volunteers who give up their time in the evening, after their own day's work, and leave their families to give out food and clothes.  The article made me think of all the volunteers who, over the years, came into the hospitals in which I worked.  They got to know the long-term homeless, who were mainly men, and paid attention to the type of clothes they liked to wear and the football teams they supported, etc.  One man who I still visit insisted he only liked to wear a certain brand.  Volunteers, when going through buckets of clothes, took the time to ensure that those men had something they liked wearing and not just anything out of a bag.  They paid attention to their personalities and who they are.  Such gestures might not break the long-term cycle of homelessness but I do not think that is what volunteer groups are trying to do.  They are trying to show a level of human empathy and compassion to people who are on the streets and in long-term homelessness.</p><p>Years ago, in the lead-up to Christmas, I remember collecting black bags full of presents for people in two hostels where I worked.  I remember two women skiving loads of them down the side of sofa.  I asked them about three bottles of perfume that were in a packet but they did not want them.  They said that they could not afford presents for their loved ones and that they had been used to the cold and living in those standards but that the stockings, gloves, scarves, perfumes and gift sets that they were receiving served them psychologically because they were able to give them to their loved ones at Christmas to show them that they were thinking of them.  </p><p>Volunteers are hugely important.  It may be that they are never in a position to break the cycle of homelessness, but that is up to us, as legislators, Dublin City Council and various other organisations.  To dismiss the work of volunteers is unacceptable.  Instead we should be thanking them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J00400"><p>The instinctive nastiness of the Taoiseach's politics has been laid bare over the past 48 hours and the Government sank to new depths when issuing rhetoric around the homelessness crisis.  I think every Member of the House would agree that homelessness is the biggest issue this country must face.  When dealing with a serious issue, one would assume no Minister or Government would engage in victim blaming.  However, over the weekend and this week, we have had the suggestion that our homelessness levels are normal, last night it was suggested that talking about homelessness is bad for our international reputation, and now we have the deplorable suggestion that homelessness is down to the bad behaviour of those who are homeless.  This is the inevitable consequence of the nasty rhetoric of defending those who get up early in the morning and saying that, for those who are vulnerable, it is in a way their own fault at the end of the day.  It is outrageous.  Rather than having a Government which holds its hands up and states it is doing its best but that it is a difficult and complex problem on which it will work harder and better to find solutions, we are told that our homelessness rates are normal if one considers the international comparators and that we might have a better international reputation if we stopped talking about it.  Inevitably, other people working in the sector are saying that it is their own fault at the end of the day.</p> <p>The rhetoric from the communications unit is outrageous.  What is worse about the unit is that &euro;5 million is nothing compared to the price of demonising the most vulnerable people in this country of ours.  I genuinely do not want this to turn into party political football.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J00500"><p>The Senator just made it that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J00600"><p>However, this is the inevitable consequence.  I am blue in the face from listening to demands in this Chamber for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to come in here.  It is a waste of all our time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J00700"><p>Who is criticising it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J00800"><p>We need the Taoiseach in here to account for his comments and to tell us his vision for ending homeless.  It is outrageous that we have two members-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J00900"><p>Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01000"><p>Hold on.  This is the party that gives the rest of us lectures about social issues and Christianity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01100"><p>Here we go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01200"><p>This morning two members of the Catholic church were on the radio.  Brother Crowley and Fr. Peter McVerry are appalled at the rhetoric of this Government.  It is disgusting that we are now blaming the homeless for homelessness. It is unbelievable.  I am asking the Cathaoirleach and the Leader quite respectfully-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01300"><p>The Senator has not been, so far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01400"><p>Most of us have been reasonably calm up to this point.  However, we are now being told that giving tents and food to the homeless on the side of the street is wrong, that it is their bad behaviour that is causing the problem and that we should stop talking about it because it is bad for our international reputation.  It is beyond time we had the Taoiseach in here to answer for his nasty rhetoric and get back to the substance of the issue and stop blaming those who are the victims of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01500"><p>I am disappointed to be roared at and finger-pointed by someone for whom I have quite a regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01600"><p>I am sorry but the homeless are the ones that are being pointed at and being blamed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01700"><p>The Cathaoirleach should have called order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01800"><p>Is it my bad behaviour now?  Am I behaving badly?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J01900"><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, please take your seat.  Senator Conway, listen to what I have to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02000"><p>I take up-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02100"><p>Senator, please respect the Chair.  You interrupted Senator Mark Daly three times.  Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in was very passionate and the Senator may not agree with what he said-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02200"><p>He is well able to interrupt himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02300"><p>Now the Senator is interrupting me.  I will ask the Senator to sit down if he does not speak to the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02400"><p>I take offence at being pointed at and roared at in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02500"><p>The Senator was entitled to make his point.  I did not see him pointing at you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02600"><p>I did, and I have a problem with my eyes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02700"><p>The Senator has used up a minute already.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#J02800"><p>The point I wanted to make, although I am continuously roared at, is that there is an issue in this city and country with cyclists not using cycle lanes or abiding by the rules of the road.  I would like to see a debate on this.  Overall, cycling is very positive.  It is good to see people out cycling because it is good for their health, mental well-being and the environment.  However, when cyclists are blatantly abusing the roads and not co-operating with the traffic systems and structures in place, we have a problem.  I use taxis quite a bit in Dublin.  Taxi drivers will say that their biggest challenge in terms of road safety is trying to navigate around cyclists.  In my parish in County Clare, we have an excellent cycle lane.  It was the Labour Party's Deputy Alan Kelly who provided the funding for it when he was in government.  It cost &euro;500,000 at the time.  Unfortunately, however, more often than not one will see people cycling on the road and not using the cycle lane.  I would like a debate on cycling to be arranged with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  In addition, the transport committee might examine new protocols and arrangements for dealing with cyclists.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#K00100"><p>Along with other Members of the House, I attended a presentation in the AV Room this morning which was organised by Deputy Stephen Donnelly.  It was given by David Hall of iCare Housing.  I compliment Mr. Hall on his presentation.  I know the Cathaoirleach also attended.  For those who are not aware, iCare is an organisation which was set up to help those who find themselves in mortgage arrears on their family homes and whose properties are in negative equity.  I would encourage those who would qualify to look into it as a solution, because being in danger of losing the family home is a very stressful situation for any family to find itself in.  There is help out there and I compliment David Hall and his organisation for taking the lead and, in many ways, showing up the lack of progress the Government has made in this area.  I encourage those who think they may benefit from this scheme to make contact with iCare.  It would be very worthwhile and I would encourage such people to come forward and make contact.</p> <p>On a more sullen note, we were all disappointed this morning after last night's football match.  I note Deputy Gavan's comments and wholeheartedly agree with them.  I too would encourage the Football Association of Ireland and the Irish Football Association in Northern Ireland to put their heads together.  The GAA has shown great leadership in building bridges in this country in opening up Croke Park and we regularly see the whole country, North and South, without boundaries shouting on the all-Ireland rugby team in the Aviva Stadium.  I ask both organisations to take a lead and play their parts, as I am sure they are well capable of doing, to ensure that one day we can look forward to supporting an all-Ireland soccer team in the Aviva Stadium.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#K00200"><p>I come into this House frequently and I watch Oireachtas TV from the Lower House.  I constantly hear debates on homelessness.  I constantly hear accusations being thrown across the floor from all sides.  Is it not time that we came together on homelessness?  Is it not time that we stood together as one Oireachtas on homelessness, instead of constantly trying to score points off one another?  A country that has been starved of resources for eight years cannot be rebuilt.  It cannot be done.  What we can do is hold those who caused the problem and those who exacerbated the credit situation to account for their actions.</p> <p>This morning I got confirmation in the post that the good days are back.  These are happy days in the banking world.  I was offered a home improvement loan to be paid into my account instantly.  This was printed on a document and when I opened it, my name was printed at the top as part of the graphic design.  These people are offering me a home improvement loan but when a young couple come to me who have &euro;30,000 handed to them by a parent to help them buy an apartment and who have shown an ability to pay &euro;85,000 in rent over the last five years, the bank says that they have no savings record and that they cannot be given a mortgage.  Come on.  Let us be honest with one another in here.  People who can afford to repay a mortgage are being denied loans by banks.  </p> <p>In fairness to the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, I have seen him marched out day after day, but where is he to get the houses from?  There is a housing estate not a stone's throw from my house which is almost complete.  Not one house in it has been sold.  There are barriers up to stop people going in.  Why have no houses been sold?  The developer is waiting until he finishes the estate and will make a serious killing then.  Let us start pointing the guns at those who are causing the problem.  Let us start looking at the banks.  Let us start looking at the actions of the Central Bank.  Social housing needs to be provided by local authorities, but let us stop having a go at one another all the time.  I know what it is like to lose one's house.  I lost mine.  God damn it, it is not the way to talk about it.  I would not have thanked anybody for talking about it.  I wanted action.  I pulled myself out of it.  Let us help people to pull themselves out of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#K00300"><p>The match last night was disappointing, but I wish the IRFU all the best today because at 1 p.m. we will finally know whether Ireland was successful in its bid to hold the Rugby World Cup.  I certainly wish the IRFU well.  I know the Minister, Deputy Shane Ross, and the Minister of State, Deputy Brendan Griffin, have travelled with the IRFU delegation.  We will know the news at 1 p.m.</p> <p>This is world diabetes week.  The Minister, Deputy Harris, launched a report this morning on free retina screening.  The offering of this screening is unique to Ireland.  It will certainly help to reduce the amount of blindness and related eye problems.  I encourage all, especially those with eye problems, to avail of this very worthy treatment and test which is being offered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#K00400"><p>All across the world people have been watching the film, "The Siege of Jadotville".  I have been asked again and again whether it is a true story.  People are actually stunned when they watch the movie.  In any other country, these people would be heroes.  Buildings, schools, hospitals and so on would be named after them all around the country.  For more than 50 years, however, these men had to keep their heads down.  There are veterans of the Defence Forces who did not know, while serving with these men, that they were at Jadotville.  Our men mounted an incredible defence of international values out there all those years ago while representing our country and the United Nations.</p> <p>I thank the Senators in this House who backed the motion to have those heroes, and the family members of those who are deceased, presented with medals.  I am overjoyed that is going to happen.  The medals could not have been presented on Jadotville day, when these men would have been with their fellow veterans and which would have been a wonderful day.  That was delayed for reasons I do not understand.  That was bad enough but I have learned in recent days that the presentation will be in Custume Barracks.  These men will be allowed to have one family member with them while other members watch on from a television screen.  There will be one Army photographer there.  This is absolutely insane.  These men should be on O'Connell Street or at &Aacute;ras an Uachtar&aacute;in.  This should be broadcast across the world.  </p> <p>We know from recently released freedom of information requests that there are people in the Department of Defence who fought against these heroes receiving medals at every stage of the process.  I am grateful that political leadership came through and that they are getting the medals, but those people in the Department of Defence are still ensuring, in their mealy-mouthed way, that these heroes will not get the day they deserve.  Why will RT&Eacute;, the BBC and every television camera in the country not be there?  Why are we not celebrating this event?  Why are we allowing this small group of Department civil servants to take away the day these men should have?  I appeal to the Leader, at this late stage, to speak to the Taoiseach and ensure that we do not make a mess of this thing, having waited 56 years to give the acknowledgement these heroes, who upheld the name of our country and our reputation, deserve.  They should get the day they deserve and these mealy-mouthed civil servants must be stood up to once and for all.  These men must get the justice they deserve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#K00500"><p>I congratulate the people of Australia on the fantastic result in the marriage referendum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#K00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#K00700"><p>For the record, I am absolutely delighted that the Scottish Supreme Court ruled in favour of minimum unit pricing today.  I hope that Ireland will follow suit.  What I really want to talk about today is that, on my way into Leinster House this morning, I heard that the Society of St. Vincent de Paul has launched its annual Christmas appeal and expects to help 50,000 people this year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The charity's president, Mr. Kieran Stafford, has said more families are struggling to put food on the table and heat their homes.  Almost 140,000 children in Ireland are now living in consistent poverty.  These children are forced to skip two essential meals each week.  It absolutely breaks my heart that in a country as wealthy as ours so many people still need to rely on charity just to put food on the table and heat their homes in winter.  People are relying on donations just to be able to give their children a present at Christmas time.  Growing up in a tenement house in the inner city of Dublin I remember the hard times and did not think we would see them again.  It is heart breaking, but there is a context for all of this.  In recent days there have been several soundbites on poverty and homelessness from various official sources.  They include: the poor will always be with us; volunteers offering food are not helpful; the crisis here is not so bad by international standards; the bad behaviour of homeless people is making things worse and journalists covering this crisis are talking down the country.  I am really worried that there is an attempt, conscious or not, to normalise homelessness.  I fear that we are being desensitised to the scale of the tragedy and the perverse inequality that leaves so many with so little.  We should be clear - there is no acceptable level of homelessness.  There is no way to explain away 3,000 homeless children.  Speaking to Se&aacute;n O'Rourke, Fr. Peter McVerry noted that last year the State built approximately 600 social housing units, whereas in one year in the 1980s the figure was 6,000.  I urge the Government to reflect on this and debate the issue with this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L00200"><p>I, too, was disappointed with the result last night, but we have had some great times and next year it will be 30 years undefeated by England.  We should note that fact.  The call for an all-Ireland soccer team is interesting.  In 1880 when the Irish Football Association, IFA, was set up, it covered all of Ireland.  In 1921 the Football Association of Ireland, FAI, was set up following the establishment of the Free State.  A lot of work was done between 1973 and 1978 when players such as George Best, Johnny Giles and Derek Dougan called for an all-Ireland soccer team.  The GAA ban did not help, but things have changed to the point where we would love to see an all-Ireland soccer team.  However, it is not a one-way street but a two-way street.  If we want to get our Northern Ireland colleagues on board, we must do something about it.  I congratulate supporters from Northern Ireland on what happened in France last year.  Supporters from the North and the South worked together and greeted one another on the streets in France.  We have, therefore, come a long way, but ff we want to have an all-Ireland soccer team, we must embrace other aspects of the issue.  We should consider having an all-Ireland team at the Commonwealth Games.  Unless we start to act as if it was a two-way street, we will never have an all-Ireland soccer team, but it is wonderful that we are talking about such issues today.  There is Donegal Celtic and I remember Linfield coming here to play.  Things have changed so much that it is possible for us to dream about having an all-Ireland soccer team, but, as I said, it is a two-way street and if we believe we should have such a team, we should not be afraid to embrace participation in the Commonwealth Games and other such issues because amalgamation will require give and take.  I welcome the initiative which is very positive and shows the space in which we find ourselves today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L00300"><p>I endorse everything Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn said about what happened in Jadotville.  We discussed the issue yesterday on the Order of Business and I reiterate my support for his comments.</p> <p>I wish to comment on the remarks made by Senator Michael McDowell who has brought to the attention of the House some very serious allegations about how waste management is conducted within Dublin City Council.  I echo his calls for a debate on how the council is run, but I would like to extend it to a wider debate on local government and the funding of same.  I would very much welcome having such a debate in the very near future.  The two councils with which I am most familiar are in Cavan and Monaghan and they do an excellent job with limited resources.  It is worth focusing on local authorities, the work they are doing in very difficult circumstances and the lack of funding.</p> <p>I wish to follow on from Senator Paul Gavan's comments on his native county of Limerick.  He castigated both Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael for having the audacity to bring forward a budget.  I remind him that if a local authority does not bring forward a budget, the Minister can appoint an administrator to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L00400"><p>Direct rule.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L00500"><p>We have an example in Sinn F&eacute;in policy of how it deals with budgets when the party stood back, with the Democratic Unionist Party, with which it has been in government in the North of Ireland for more than ten years.  It has stood back and will allow the British Government in the next couple of days to bring forward a budget because it failed to bring one forward as its members were elected to do.  They were elected in the Six Counties to bring forward a budget on behalf of the people who elected them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L00600"><p>Would Fianna F&aacute;il go into government with the DUP?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L00700"><p>I will not listen to Senator Paul Gavan or any of his colleagues in Sinn F&eacute;in in condemning my colleagues on Limerick City Council or those in the Fine Gael Party who take their responsibilities seriously.  They will bring forward a budget for better or worse because that is what they are there to do.  They are doing so mindful of the fact that if they do not, the Minister will appoint an administrator to bring forward a budget-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L00800"><p>We do not prop up dodgy governments in the way Fianna F&aacute;il does.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L00900"><p>----- that will not be voted on by the people who were elected to bring it forward.  That is a gentle reminder for Sinn F&eacute;in.  Perhaps the party might look forward to bringing forward a budget with their colleagues in the Democratic Unionist Party as they have been democratically elected to do in the Six Counties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L01000"><p>Many of the contributions this morning have been about the soccer team's performance last night.  It was a disappointing outing.  I agree that women's participation in sport is something the Government and the Oireachtas need to examine.  We must promote the participation of women in sport and sports bodies.  I say that in the light of the positive news which has come out of Cork in recent hours, that the Cork County Board has elected its first female chairperson.  Ms Tracey Kennedy will become the first female chairperson of the Cork County Board.  That is a very positive statement on women's participation in sport, whether in playing or administration.  However, on a national level we need to have a framework in place to ensure the level of participation of females in sport is increased.  In that context, RTE must examine its policy on those who provide commentaries and are involved on panels.  The coverage of female sport must be intensified.  The appointment of Ms Tracey Kennedy is a very positive step, in particular for the GAA, especially in Cork, in having a female in a leading role.  She is a wonderful character and I am sure she will do a very dynamic job in the years ahead.  It is up to us in the Oireachtas to provide a framework and a strategy to ensure the participation of women is driven forward and that the appointment of Ms Tracey Kennedy is replicated around the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#L01100"><p>Ba mhaith liom tac&uacute; le moladh Sheanad&oacute;ir Robbie Gallagher to have an all-Irish soccer team.  It would be fantastic for the game, both in the North and the South.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2482"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2482&amp;amp;pid=PadraigOCeidigh&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have it in rugby, GAA and other fields.  I also support the passionate contribution by Senator Mac Lochlainn relating to recognition of people who have given their lives for the country and who have given their lives passionately for others to live in a democratic society.</p><p>I wish to discuss the housing crisis, but a different area of the housing crisis.  I am solution-focused.  That is the world I come from.  I am not interested in criticism.  Unfortunately, we get far too much of that here.  I am a supporter of the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Murphy, having met him several times.  I support his passion and commitment as I supported his predecessor as Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney, in respect of this problem.  It is a significant problem.  There is no simple solution but there are levels of solutions.  I will suggest a potential solution to one large aspect of the problem.</p><p>In rural Ireland we have major problems with planning permission and it is getting worse.  Part of the problem is a question of getting finance from the banks, but the greater part is getting planning permission.  People cannot get planning permission on family farms or land.  The rules and regulations coming in are becoming more stringent every day.</p><p>We need a debate in the House.  Will the Leader bring this back to the Minister, Deputy Murphy, to see what can be done in respect of the housing crisis we have in rural Ireland?  In many places there are old houses that people cannot do up because of planning issues.  That is one layer within which we can create effective quick solutions for people so that they can have a house and live in rural Ireland.  Many are working there already and they have land.  This would create greater flexibility so they could live and build there and contribute to their communities.</p><p>I call on the Leader to connect with the Minister, Deputy Murphy, on this issue.  It would be a good idea if the Minister addressed the House on the overall situation on planning permission.  The Apple situation in Athenry is not our biggest issue with planning by a country mile.  We are dealing with it and I understand that the Taoiseach has spoken about this already.  There is a bigger issue.  The people are paying their taxes.  They want to pay their taxes and live in their communities but cannot live there because we are not allowing them to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#M00200"><p>Perhaps Senator Wilson's grandstanding and rhetoric could be turned into decision-making by Fianna F&aacute;il, the republican party, with regard to the Assembly in the North.  What aspects of it would he throw out, given a strong mandate for marriage equality, an Irish language Act and the cash-for-ash scandal?  He would be quite comfortable standing over corruption and allowing that to go on.  I would like that on the record, if Senator Wilson will put it on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#M00300"><p>Speak through the Chair, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#M00400"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in and the DUP brought in that grant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#M00500"><p>No interaction between Senators.  Respect the Chair and address the Chair, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#M00600"><p>I congratulate those involved in the Australian vote for same-sex marriage, especially the 61% who voted in favour of it.  I am proud that some of the Irish method was replicated in the campaign and that it was led by many Irish living over there.  I hope Australia will legislate for it before Christmas.</p> <p>I wish to highlight the alarming rise in attacks on mental health staff, as reported today.  The number has gone from three in 2010 to over 150 thus far this year.  This is violence on our front-line staff.  I know there are challenging environments, especially in mental health settings.  The decrease in staffing levels, ageing staff, younger staff walking away and volatility has contributed significantly to leaving many of our nurses disabled for life.  The volatility has been caused more recently by the intensive laboratory-grown potency of synthetic drugs.  Many cannot go back to work.  I have represented several in the Labour Court while trying to make people accountable for what happens.</p> <p>We need to address the main issues of recruitment and retention of staff, reopening closed beds, adequate step-down facilities and stopping the hundreds of thousands of elderly who have to wait more than 24 hours on trollies or plastic chairs.  This is causing at least 350 deaths per year in medical deterioration.  I call on the Minister to come to the House so that we can ask about the protection of front-line workers, especially in mental health services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#M00700"><p>Once again we are facing into a winter where the only things accident and emergency doctors have are flu jabs and prayers to help them with the inevitable onslaught.</p><p>We have fewer hospital beds now than we had in 1980 and nearly 200 beds are out of action.  These are statements we have all heard before and we can say them until we are blue in the face.  An article some weeks back entitled, This is the winter our health system will finally collapse, should have somehow resonated with the powers that be in the HSE and the Department of Health.  My comments are directed towards those officials in the HSE and the Department of Health and not necessarily towards the Minister.  I have no vendetta against the Minister - that is not my style - and I think he is a good Minister.  His heart is in the right place and I have great respect for him.</p><p>In the article, medical journalist Dr. Muiris Houston warns:</p><blockquote>A slow collapse of the health system this winter will likely look like this: the influenza epidemic begins; attendances at emergency departments increase as the flu hits vulnerable groups; patients with flu complications who require admission will fill up trolleys; some people who develop respiratory and cardiac failure will be moved to intensive care; the already inadequate number of ICU beds will fill up quickly, forcing intensive care specialists to ventilate people in operating theatres and even in emergency departments. There will be no spare intensive care capacity in Northern Ireland or Britain to tap into.<br /><br />As a result, even urgent cancer surgeries will be cancelled, as many patients who undergo major surgery cannot be safely operated on without an intensive care bed to transfer them to post-operatively. All elective surgery is likely to be cancelled for a period of eight to 10 weeks, adding to the already enormous backlog of people waiting to be treated in the public health system. Emergency departments will choke up and some will be forced to close. Already overstretched GPs will not have the capacity, and for seriously ill people, the facilities, to offer treatment.</blockquote> <p>These are not the words of some dystopian novelist.  His comments are accurate, realistic and utterly terrifying.  There are enough faceless Department and HSE officials on large salaries to get on with the work in hand.  I want to see some proactive solutions rather than reactive commentary from them, which we have seen previously.  I look forward to hearing what solutions they come up with in the coming weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#M00800"><p>Today sees the commencement of the global forum on human resources for health.  This is a four-day conference that will begin in the RDS.  No doubt the World Health Organization, which is one of the co-sponsors, will be pointing out to us that the problem of a shortfall in health care workers is worldwide.</p> <p>There are some other issues.  The WHO will also tell us, by reference to reports in advance of the conference, not only that we have a problem with a shortfall of health care workers, including nurses, doctors and so on, but that this can be compounded when Brexit comes.  Basically, we are looking at a situation where there will be a concerted effort on the part of the NHS in England to recruit our nurses and doctors and, in effect, poach them.  That would put us in a critical position with regard to providing the proper health service we need.</p> <p>We know the HSE has published the Health Services People Strategy 2015-2018 in response to the depletion in numbers of front-line health care workers, especially nurses.  We know the executive is having difficulty in achieving targets in recruitment.  This is because people have retired and young graduates are going abroad.  An Irish Nurses and Midwives Organisation study showed that many young nursing graduates intend to work abroad and that the net increase in nursing staff numbers from September to December this year was only a net figure of 13.  Clearly, there is a major problem here.</p> <p>One particular issue of concern is that in response to this departure or planned departure by nursing graduates from the country, the HSE has basically agreed that from now on permanent contracts should be offered to nursing graduates for 2016 and 2017 such that they would have reason to stay and build their lives here.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am very concerned about the operation and implementation of this objective by the Saolta hospital group.  It is not offering permanent contracts despite the need for nursing staff.  Contracts for a maximum of two years is the most which people are being offered.  We all know that anyone who is looking for a mortgage or is trying to establish him or herself needs greater certainty than two years.  I am aware of people in other hospital areas being given permanent contracts rather than for finite periods.  The Saolta group must be taken to task over this and I ask that this matter be taken up with the Minister to ask about recruitment and how nurses who graduated between 2016 and 2017 are being treated, in accordance with Government and HSE policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N00200"><p>Five speakers remain.  Technically, I should draw the guillotine now because the time allowed is 55 minutes.  Today everyone who had two minutes wanted three, those given three wanted four and those who had four wanted five.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N00300"><p>It was not me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N00400"><p>I am not pointing a finger at anyone but as of now I should ask the Leader to respond because the 55 minutes allotted have been used.  There are five speakers left who I will call providing they are brief and to the point and do not blather on with speeches.  If they call for a debate, it can be held when the relevant Minister comes to the House, not during the Order of Business.  I will run through the five speakers who remain.  If they wish to drag the Order of Business on, I will just cut them off and ask the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N00500"><p>Beidh mise gonta le c&uacute;namh D&eacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N00600"><p>Standing Orders clearly state that 55 minutes is allowed for the Order of Business.  That time has elapsed and the Leader is yet to respond.  There is another item scheduled for 12.45 p.m.  People are not cognisant of time and scheduling.  If that continues, every day I will draw the line at 55 minutes, regardless of who is left to speak.  I am making an exception today because I do not wish to cut people short.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N00700"><p>We spoke recently about the Pobal index on deprivation which was published last week.  It shows the areas that are in consistent disadvantage in matters such as employment, education attainment, housing tenure, and lone parent ratio.  It is clear that it has not improved over the years.  I want to connect it with the statement made by the Society of St. Vincent de Paul today, to which Senator Black referred, regarding the 50,000 families who will seek its help during the winter months.  I would hazard an educated guess that most of the families will be in those areas of disadvantage.  It is scandalous that we see so many people who find themselves in such a precarious situation and the fact that the Society of St. Vincent de Paul receives around 125,000 calls annually from people who are in this type of poverty trap.  We cannot accept it, it is not good enough and we need to have a debate around poverty.</p> <p>Many of those families will be experiencing the housing crisis that we spoke about.  I find it ironic that Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in is giving us Oscar-winning performances once a week for the benefit of his YouTube following when his ministerial colleague in government, Deputy Alan Kelly, was very much one of the architects of this crisis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N00800"><p>The Senator is obviously posting the video as we speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N00900"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01000"><p>He is a good actor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01100"><p>The Senator is grandstanding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01200"><p>If the Senators do not wish me to make a ruling, they should stop this interaction.  The Senator should conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01300"><p>We are often accused of not having solutions.  A solution that I suggest for the issue being raised by the Society of St. Vincent de Paul is that the Taoiseach come to the House and discuss the matter, but also that he scrap his strategic communications unit and give the &euro;5 million he is spending on that to the Society of St. Vincent de Paul to prove that this Government is serious about tackling poverty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01400"><p>I call Senator O'Donnell to contribute briefly.  There are four speakers left and we are over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01500"><p>I want to reflect on the result of last night's football match.  The Irish team did not have a single player from one of the top six teams in the English Premiership.  The players at the Ireland team's disposal are good players who give their hearts, but we should look at the type of player we have compared with ten or 15 years ago.  Not long ago, both Ireland and Northern Ireland qualified for the European Cup.  We must see if we can bring synergies by establishing one all-Ireland team.  We had no player of the class of Eriksen in our squad.  He scored two goals.  We did not have a player capable of scoring.</p> <p>On homelessness, all attention and focus must be on the homeless person him or herself.  I am concerned that we are getting into a degree of territorialism between various groups which deal with the homeless.  Everyone who is involved in the area is well intentioned.  The volunteer who goes out to look after homeless people is well intentioned.  What we need is for everyone to work together.  The issue is not funding, it is dealing with the issues of particular individuals.  We should deal with the needs of the individual homeless person and work together, rather than one person saying one thing and someone else saying the other.  The whole focus must be on the person who is homeless.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01600"><p>I was stunned to hear Senator M&aacute;ire Devine refer to the cash for ash issue in her response to my party Whip.  I thought that issue, on which Sinn F&eacute;in recklessly brought down the Northern Ireland Assembly, had gone up in smoke as Sinn F&eacute;in threw up a raft of other problems.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01700"><p>That was about &euro;400 million of public money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01800"><p>I did not interrupt anybody.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N01900"><p>Members should allow Senator O'Sullivan to make his point, whether they agree with him or not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02000"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in has succeeded in moving the goalposts on that again.  I spoke yesterday on how there is no representation as the Northern Ireland budget-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02100"><p>Will the Senator put on record what he proposes to leave out?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02200"><p>-----is being passed by the English House of Commons in a debate with English MPs and there was not one nationalist Irish voice raised for the simple reason-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02300"><p>Will Fianna F&aacute;il take its seats in Westminster?  They are absolute hypocrites, calling themselves the republican party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02400"><p>I did not interrupt anyone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02500"><p>I will not allow this.  I am going to finish the Order of Business and that is it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02600"><p>This is a stand-up comedy act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02700"><p>I never interrupt anyone in this House and I am entitled to continue.  I will not be bullied like people in the Sinn F&eacute;in Party are bullied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.172" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N02900"><p>Senator O'Sullivan should conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03000"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in will not bully me.  It can bully its own.  They will not bully me.  We had no Irish nationalist voice to debate the budget for Northern Ireland.  What an insult to the memory of Daniel O'Connell, Parnell, Redmond, Dillon and the rest of them.  It is an insult.  Sinn F&eacute;in is putting its party before its country morning, noon and night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03100"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in is a republican party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03200"><p>It has become a political cult.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03300"><p>Where is the Senator's mandate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03400"><p>The country must come first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03500"><p>Where is the Senator's mandate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03600"><p>Liam Lawlor, Ray Burke, Charlie Haughey.  Will we go on?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03700"><p>Senator Mac Lochlainn, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03800"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in will not bully me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N03900"><p>Members are pushing me to the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N04000"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in will not bully me.  It will not bully us.  They will not bully anyone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N04100"><p>We had all this yesterday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N04200"><p>I welcome the announcement ----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N04300"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il, the republican party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N04400"><p>Senator Mac Lochlainn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N04500"><p>Look at this.  This is the bullying of Sinn F&eacute;in.  It is driving its own members from the party.</p> <p>I welcome the announcement of &euro;98 million to extend the Luas green line.  It is very important because it is over capacity.  It is a huge investment and I have no problem with it.  However, recently I alighted at the railway station in Clonmel and there is not even a toilet there.  The patrons are dependent on the goodwill of shopkeepers and publicans nearby.  I want to note that in the context of Senator Ray Butler's very good contribution to the House regarding what is happening in Navan and rural Ireland versus Dublin.</p> <p>I will not be bullied in this House by Sinn F&eacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.190" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N04700"><p>The Leader will respond.  Three speakers remain but I am not taking any more contributions.  The Leader will respond.  We have 12 minutes left.  I cautioned the Members but nobody respects the Chair.  I am sorry for those who did not get in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#N04800"><p>I thank the 21 Members for their contributions and the Cathaoirleach.  It is important that we as Members of this House reaffirm our respect and trust in the Cathaoirleach as an impartial chairman.  His generosity is overstretched by Members at times, but I assure him of my support.  He is a very fair man and is doing a good job.</p> <p>Senators Daly, Gavan, &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, Ruane, Craughwell, Wilson, &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh and O'Donnell referred to the issues of housing and homelessness.  It is a pity that Members cannot stay for the reply to the Order of Business.  Some have to go to another place but they have a duty to stay.  It is important that those who go on the platform or the stage that is the Chamber to perform to YouTube or the Gaiety also listen.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We must take the politics out of homelessness and the homelessness sector.  No one of us has all of the information or knowledge.  </p><p>Let me make matters quite clear to Members who have commented on the Fine Gael Party, in particular, and the Taoiseach.  Nobody on our side of the House is in denial about the housing crisis and the human impact it is having on the lives of people and families.  None of us is living in a bubble or cocoon.  I would challenge Members to come into any of our clinics in any of our communities.  We are working with people day and night to try to get them housed, out of hotels and treated as proper human beings.  Members should not come in here and pretend they know everything when they do not.</p><p>We need to deal with the citizens of our republic who deserve to be treated with respect.  As Members of the House, we are obliged to work on their concerns.  Senator O'Donnell is correct.  Those working in the housing sector, local government and the Department need to put aside their territorial issues and work together collectively to solve this crisis.  It is not just about funding.  An increase of &euro;6 billion was provided by the Government in the most recent budget.  An evolving fund is available under Rebuilding Ireland.  A multi-annual fund was created by the previous Minister, Deputy Coveney, which is now being delivered by the current Minister, Deputy Murphy.  </p><p>Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh is correct.  Let us be solution-focused about the issue.  We heard no solutions today from many contributors on the Order of Business.  We in Fine Gael are well aware of the seriousness of the issue.  Senator Daly referred to Cork.  As we speak, &euro;155 million of Government money is providing 634 units social housing units in Cork.  That is a fact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O00200"><p>It is providing money but not building housing.  The money is being handed back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O00300"><p>Members should not come in with cheap, populist rhetoric.  It ill-behoves them-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O00400"><p>These are facts.  The Government's own facts are being denied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O00500"><p>Senator Daly please resume your seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O00600"><p>In Kerry 11 houses were built.  That is a fact.  Programmes are being announced, but houses are not being built.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O00700"><p>There has been an increase in funding for the homeless.  I am replying to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O00800"><p>If this is going to continue, I will suspend for 15 minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O00900"><p>I took 21 contributions.  I take notes every single day.  I have an obligation to respond.  I appreciate from where the Cathaoirleach is coming.  Let us deal with the facts.  Some &euro;6 billion is being provided, a 20% increase in the budget.  It is the largest ever housing allocation.  They are the facts.  This is not fake news or Senator Daly's spin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01000"><p>The money is being provided but the houses are not being built.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01100"><p>With respect, when Senator Daly was speaking there were at least four interventions, including from the Leader.  I had to give him an extra minute.  I am not condoning his intervention.  If one agitates the Opposition, one can expect agitation back.  B&iacute; c&uacute;ramach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01200"><p>In her contribution, Senator Black mentioned normalising homelessness.  Nobody on the Government side is trying to normalise anything about homelessness.  Rather, we are trying to solve the problem.  The use of language in the House or on the airwaves is very important.  That is what the Minister was trying to convey.</p> <p>I agree with Senators Wilson and O'Sullivan on the position of Senator Gavan, who apologised for not being here.  Sinn F&eacute;in is very good at abdicating responsibility.  It must pass a budget in Limerick, as Senator Wilson said.  If it does not, a commissioner will be appointed.  I am certainly not happy to have a commissioner appointed to replace elected councillors who represent the people at local authority level. </p> <p>Members of the Sinn F&eacute;in Party who come in here every day and criticise everything should not engage in opposition for the sake of it.  They should not be cheerleaders and expect others to be responsible and go into government.  I understand there is a motion on the cl&aacute;r of the Sinn F&eacute;in Ard-Fheis about government.  Sinn F&eacute;in should be responsible and pass it.  Its members should man up, come in to and take on the duties of government and be responsible to the people who elect its members, rather than walking off the pitch as it did in the Assembly in the North.  </p> <p>Senator O'Sullivan was correct, despite the protestations of Senator Mac Lochlainn.  There was no voice in the budget negotiations for nationalists in the House of Common this week.  What would Seamus Mallon and John Hume have said?  They started the peace process and were its architects.  Sinn F&eacute;in came on board but the current political landscape means it must fulfil its duties. </p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in Members can make faces at me, but that is the reality.  Those of us who have been in government, including Senator McDowell, took decisions on behalf of the people.  Today, our country is in a better place because of the previous Government.  Let us be real about this.  Politics is about government and being responsible.  It is not about being a cheerleader, waving banners and flags and organising protests.  We can all do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01300"><p>It is about the 700,000 on the waiting lists and the thousands of children who do not have a home.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01400"><p>We understand that.  That is why the budget is being increased.  In his remarks in Cavan, the Taoiseach said our homeless figures were low by international standards.  In addition, he said it was not good enough and we must turn the tide.  I was standing next to him when he said it.  Let us be real about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01500"><p>That is obviously the communications unit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01600"><p>Senator Conway-Walsh's speeches are controlled by the head office in west Belfast.  A single transferable speech is passed around.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01700"><p>I remind Senators that a Minister is waiting to deal with the next matter.  We are well over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01800"><p>I respect that, but I am going to give a reply to the Order of Business because it is about time some of the myths from spin merchants who have a single transferable speech from west Belfast-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O01900"><p>We will have to get a communications unit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O02000"><p>Leo's spin is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.213" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O02200"><p>In conclusion, the Government is well aware of the issue.  We are determined to resolve the problem for everybody.  No one approach will work; it is a complex matter and can only be solved by solutions.</p> <p>I did not hear the remarks made by Eileen Gleeson on the radio today to which Senator Ruane referred.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O02300"><p>They were outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.216" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O02500"><p>The Senator is interrupting his leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O02600"><p>It must have been Ireland's defeat yesterday.  There is something amiss today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#O02700"><p>Her remarks were badly articulated.  I can only interpret what she was trying to say.  In some cases, people who are homeless require myriad services and their best interaction is with the agencies who can help them.  I regret the fact that she made the remarks she did.  We are quick to condemn and judge a person who is trying to do her best.</p> <p>Senators Daly, Feighan, Gavan, Byrne and &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh referred to the defeat of the soccer team yesterday.  We are all upset by the defeat.  A united Ireland soccer team is a matter we would all like progressed, if that is the will of the FAI and IFA.  The result was disappointing from a soccer point of view.  The joy and endeavour of the team deserves to be commended.  The support the fans gave the team is also to be commended.</p> <p>Senator Daly referred to the fact that it is 499 days to Brexit.  I again ask him to come off the horse and take off the blinkers he sometimes wears.  The Taoiseach, the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade and the Minister of State with responsibility for European affairs have been very clear about the approach of the Government.  We are building new alliances and a platform for support for the all-Ireland position and the uniqueness of our country.  We will have a duty to wear the green jersey.  I know Senator Daly does so, but it is important that we continue to do so.  He is correct about the British Government still not having a plan.  That is a worrying problem.</p> <p>Senator McDowell raised the issue of waste collection and the remarks attributed by him to Councillor Keith Redmond.  I have great respect and time for the councillor, who is a very good public representative.  It is a worry if an effective cartel is being created in parts of Dublin.  That should be halted immediately and the situation rectified.  There should be competition, and I am in favour of that. </p> <p>Senator Wilson also referred to value for money.  It is a matter for the local government auditor.  It is a debate we can have in time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have already addressed the issue raised by Senator Ruane.  It would behove Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, meanwhile, to engage with finding solutions rather than-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#P00200"><p>He could turn down the volume for a start.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#P00300"><p>The Senator is probably going for YouTube records at this stage but we are here to find solutions.  Senator Conway raised the issue of cyclists in Dublin and I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House to address that.  Senators &Oacute; Donnghaile and &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh mentioned the former's recent briefing.  I was not at that briefing and was not in fact aware of it but I would be happy to talk to the Senators on the matter.  Senator Craughwell raised the issue of home improvement loans.  It is certainly disappointing that our banks are once again trying to give money to people without due process.  I had hoped that such a thing would not happen.  We bailed out the banks and it is important that such matters be handled in a proper manner.  I commend the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, and the Minister of State with special responsibility for mental health and older people, Deputy Jim Daly, for the launch today of the diabetic retina screening programme.  It is a wonderful initiative and Dr. Diarmuid Quinlan in Cork was very much involved with it.  In line with World Diabetes Week, it is important that we support such a programme.</p> <p>Senator Mac Lochlainn has, regrettably, left the Chamber but in response to his contribution I wish to point out that we discussed Jadotville yesterday and I do not want to repeat what I said then other than to stress that the ceremony will involve full military honours.  If Senator Mac Lochlainn is concerned about this then I would like to point out that the representatives from the Department of Defence I spoke to after yesterday's meeting were certainly not aware of the issues raised by Senator Craughwell.  It is important to recognise, however, that the men of Jadotville are heroes and will be receiving medals and full military honours.  From what I have been told by the Department, there is no ambiguity there.</p> <p>I join with the other Senators in congratulating the people of Australia on their magnificent vote yesterday on marriage equality and I commend Tiarnan Brady, formerly political director of the Yes Equality campaign in this country, for leading the campaign in Australia, others like Craig Dwyer who travelled there to help with that campaign, and the many Irish people living in Australia who played a pivotal role in it.  Today is a wonderful day for the people of Australia and a further sign of progress around the world.  I salute and commend all involved and thank them on their work.  </p> <p>Senators Black and &Oacute; Clochartaigh both referred to the report by the Society of St. Vincent de Paul.  The Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Ring, spoke at committee this morning and raised those very issues, namely, budgetary matters and the need for further improvement in rural Ireland, and I would be happy to have him come to the House to discuss them.  In response to Senator Wilson, I would also be happy to have a debate on the funding of local government.  Senator Lombard raised the issue of women's participation in sport.  I join him in congratulating Tracey Kennedy on her appointment as the first female cathaoirleach of Coiste Contae Chorcaigh, the Cork County GAA board, and wish her well in her new role.  Eithne O'Mahony, a woman from the Cathaoirleach's home town of Bantry, was the first female delegate some time back and it is great that Ms Kennedy has now been appointed chairperson of that board.</p> <p>I join Senator Devine in asking that we all work to tackle the rate of attacks on mental health professionals.  This is a worrying trend exacerbated, as the Senator said, by an ageing staff and by recruitment problems.  We need to work on this.  Senators Swanwick and Mulherin raised health care issues.  The Minister will be in the House later this afternoon and the Senators can raise these matters then.  Finally, I join Senator Ned O'Sullivan in welcoming the Luas extension and agree with him that the current situation in Clonmel train station needs to be taken into account by the Minister.</p> <p>I also thank the Cathaoirleach for his indulgence.  I would hate for him to think that the Members of the House do not respect him because we do, and I would be happy to speak to Members about their behaviour and the language used here.  Listening to some Members one might swear that the Government does nothing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#P00400"><p>F&eacute;ach ar an clog.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#P00500"><p>-----but the facts suggest otherwise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#P00550"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, who has some of his people from west Cork with him, to the House.  The west Cork people are the salt of the earth, as the Minister of State knows himself, so they are very welcome to the Seanad Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.226" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.227" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#P00900">Water Services Bill 2017: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#P00950"><p>I apologise to the Minister of State, Deputy Phelan, for keeping him waiting for ten minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.229" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 6, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.230" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.231" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 7 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#P01300"><p>We in Sinn F&eacute;in are not going to delay the procedures today.  I know that we have been accused of this in the past but the delay on this Bill was due to the negotiations between Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael.  We obviously have several issues with this Bill which will not be taken on board because of the debates that took place in the D&aacute;il and in this House on Second Stage.  I want to put on the record, however, that there is still no clarification on group water schemes and where funding for these schemes will stand in the future; on the excessive use charge; on undiscovered leaks; or on the first fix fee.  We in Sinn F&eacute;in still have serious issues with this Bill but we understand the people want to get paid before Christmas.  We will not delay the passing of the Bill but we will oppose it at this Stage and on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.233" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.234" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sections 8 to 62, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.235" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question, "That the Title be the Title to the Bill", put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.236" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#Q00400"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#Q00500"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#Q00550"><p>Is that agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#Q00575"><p>Not agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.241/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#Q00600"><p>Question put: "That Report Stage be taken now."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 35; Nl, 6.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony; Nl, Senators Paul Gavan and Trevor  Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.241/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2017-11-15" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#Q00600">
            <divisioncount ayes="35" noes="6" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="aye">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="aye">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="aye">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="aye">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="aye">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="aye">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" vote="aye">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="aye">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="aye">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="aye">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="aye">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" vote="aye">Colette Kelleher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" vote="aye">Billy Lawless</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="aye">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" vote="aye">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="aye">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="aye">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" vote="aye">Jennifer Murnane O'Connor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="aye">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="aye">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="aye">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="aye">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="aye">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="aye">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" vote="aye">Keith Swanick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="no">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="no">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="no">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="no">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" vote="no">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.241/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#Q00600"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.242/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#R00100"><p>Question put: "That the Bill be received for final consideration."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 32; Nl, 9.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony; Nl, Senators Paul Gavan and Trevor  Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.242/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2017-11-15" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#R00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="32" noes="9" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="aye">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="aye">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="aye">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="aye">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="aye">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="aye">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" vote="aye">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="aye">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="aye">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="aye">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" vote="aye">Colette Kelleher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" vote="aye">Billy Lawless</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="aye">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" vote="aye">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="aye">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="aye">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" vote="aye">Jennifer Murnane O'Connor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="aye">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="aye">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="aye">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="aye">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="aye">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" vote="aye">Keith Swanick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="no">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="no">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="no">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="no">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="no">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="no">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" vote="no">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.242/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#R00100"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.243" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#T00200"><p>The Minister of State indicated he wished to speak on this Stage.  Does any Member want to contribute?  I remind the House that this is not Second Stage, it is the conclusion of the debate on the Bill.  Members are entitled to make a few comments.  I call on Senator Murnane O'Connor, who is to be followed by Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#T00300"><p>Today was crunch time.  This legislation needed to be passed.  It is refunding law-abiding citizens who paid a charge they were forced into paying.  Hundreds of thousands of people protested against the charges, and hundreds of thousands paid.  They deserve timely refunds.</p> <p>Water is something many of us take for granted, but we cannot survive without it.  Now this legislation is passed, we will work on educating people on water conservation.  This Bill is partly about education.  Everyone needs to be educated about water conservation.  We need to achieve this but we also need to ensure we have an information campaign, including leaflets, and that people will know where to get the information.  This is crucial.</p> <p>It is crucial that, under this legislation, 30,000 cheques per day can be issued.  Considering that 970,000 refunds will have to be completed, the legislation should go to the President for signature as soon as possible.  We must do our utmost to refund the people who have paid because it is so important.  Christmas is only six weeks away.  It would be great if we could issue the refunds before then.</p> <p>On the rural water scheme, we must put incentives in place for people who are paying for water.  I will make sure I work on this personally.  Today is a good day.  Everything has been done well and we are all happy.  I hope the President will sign off on the legislation as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#T00400"><p>T&aacute; s&eacute; n&aacute;ireach ar bhealach go bhfuil an Bille seo &aacute; chur tr&iacute;d na Tithe inniu in aon su&iacute; amh&aacute;in.  N&iacute; ch&oacute;ir nach nd&eacute;anfa&iacute; mionscr&uacute;d&uacute; ceart ar chuid de na himpleachta&iacute; a bhaineann leis an mBille.  Is cinnte nach &eacute; Sinn F&eacute;in at&aacute; ag cur moill ar an reachta&iacute;ocht seo.  We need to be clear that Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael are the parties to blame for the delay in bringing this Bill forward to the Houses and in the making of the payments that are due.  The Bill was due to be published in June but it was delayed so the pantomime of the Fine Gael leadership contest could take place.  It was then due to be published and passed in July but squabbling in the background between Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il delayed it even further.  This is crucial because it proves Fianna F&aacute;il's fingerprints are all over the Bill.  It wanted to make sure that it could design a Bill that would, on the surface, end water charges, yet leave a mechanism in place for their return.  Many people will rightly deduce that a Fianna F&aacute;il return to power may well equal a return to water charges.  If it was such a big issue during the last election campaign and helped Fianna F&aacute;il to win back many seats, why did it not completely abolish the water charges?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#T00500"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in voted against everything today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#T00600"><p>Yes, and I will tell the Senator why.  It is because this Bill-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#T00700"><p>This is not Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#T00800"><p>-----with group water schemes, as I have mentioned.</p> <p>Clarification is still required on future funding and the form that funding or subsidy will take.  We have issues over the excessive use charge.  Will it be measured at the meter or will there be a straight-off fine?  Will there be a first-fix-free policy on undiscovered leaks, or will such leaks incur the excessive-use charge?  All these questions remain and could have been addressed had there been a more comprehensive debate and Bill, and if relevant amendments had been accepted in the D&aacute;il.  Instead, a very flawed Bill has gone through today, and that is why we opposed it.  If Fianna F&aacute;il had any backbone, it would have opposed it also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#T00900"><p>Cuireann s&eacute; r&iacute;m&eacute;ad orm go bhfuil an Bille seo rite ar maidin.  T&aacute; s&eacute; f&iacute;orth&aacute;bhachtach gur f&eacute;idir linn dul ar aghaidh &oacute; thaobh an fadhb m&oacute;r seo a bh&iacute; ann. I am delighted the Bill has been passed today.  I greatly appreciate the work, commitment and considerable effort of the committee in this regard.  As an Independent and one who has come from the outside, I very much appreciate the Government party, Fine Gael, and Fianna F&aacute;il coming together.  Rather than just focusing on negative politics, they said they had got to create a solution to the best benefit of the people.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2482"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2482&amp;amp;pid=PadraigOCeidigh&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If I take nothing else from whatever length of time I spend in this House, it is that I appreciate what both sides of the Houses have done.  Having said that, I am equally disappointed with Sinn F&eacute;in and others, who for the sake of politics and jibing, decided to go against this process at every stage.  There are people who paid money and we decided they should be repaid that money.  It should have been done last summer and not now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U00200"><p>The Senator knows well it is not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U00300"><p>I did not interrupt you, Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U00400"><p>I am correcting the Senator.  He is incorrect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U00500"><p>The Senators should speak through the Chair and not be deflected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U00600"><p>There are some officials here from the Department.  I said the last time I spoke that I really appreciate their contribution.  They made a major contribution, as have personnel from the Commission for Energy Regulation, Irish Water and others.  Irish Water will be a public utility and body of which we all will be proud.  As my colleague, Senator Coffey, said the last day, we will be as proud of it as we are of the ESB and others.  I thank everybody for their contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U00700"><p>I commend Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh on his chairing of the water services committee.  He stepped into the breach, so to speak, and did a fine job in reaching a resolution on this matter.  I join with him in thanking the officials.  When I have been in this Chamber when it was elsewhere, I was not immune to giving out about officials but the officials from my Department have had six water Bills in the past seven or eight years.  I commend them on their efforts, particularly on this legislation, which we are finalising today.  I hope there will be fewer than six water Bills in the next ten years.</p> <p>I was trying to answer Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh's query earlier and yesterday the Senator's colleague, Senator Conway-Walsh, raised the matters to which the Senator spoke relating to section 7.  I refer him to the answer I gave to her yesterday.  I thank all the Members who contributed to the water debate this week and over the years.  This conclusion marks the end of what has been an arduous political and legislative process over the past number of years.  Debate has been robust and although people disagree on aspects of how water services should be funded, the discussion at least has now reached a positive conclusion.  I will be political for a moment.  It is imperative that the citizens of the State who obeyed the law of the State should receive their refund.  As Senator Murnane O'Connor states, I hope as many as possible, if not all, will have this before Christmas.  That was the intention of the this Bill and I hope it comes to pass.</p> <p>I was interested in Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh's reference to the Fine Gael leadership contest.  He said it was pantomime.  I do not know how one would describe the Sinn F&eacute;in leadership contest that ended up with Ms Michelle O'Neill.  There was no contest, as far as I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U00800"><p>It was fantastic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U00900"><p>The army council might be called into action again if media reports are correct about the leadership of the party in the South.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01000"><p>On a point of order, there is absolutely no army council in Sinn F&eacute;in.  I ask the Minister of State to withdraw it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01100"><p>The Minister of State should speak to the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01200"><p>Does the Senator have contact with the leadership?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01300"><p>Is the Senator having-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01400"><p>The Senator has no vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01500"><p>In enacting this Bill we are providing funding clarity and certainty for Irish Water so it can deliver a public water system that provides a safe and secure supply of water to our homes and communities, as well as the water-intensive industries that sustain approximately 400,000 jobs in the country and the wider economy.  We are providing funding certainty so the utility can address major deficits in urban wastewater treatment, which were referred to earlier, and so the public health and aquatic environment are protected.  The Bill supports a strong policy framework for water services so we can aspire with confidence to achieving a modern public water and wastewater system fit for a modern society and economy.  As Irish Water continues to deliver change and progress, securing water quality supplies, reducing leakages and increasing spare supply capacity and wastewater treatment capacity, all of us in the Oireachtas must constructively and regularly engage with the questions of how to improve public water services and manage this extremely important resource into the future.  The public deserves no less.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.267/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01600"><p>Question put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 32; Nl, 10.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony; Nl, Senators Paul Gavan and Trevor  Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.267/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2017-11-15" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01600">
            <divisioncount ayes="32" noes="10" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="aye">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="aye">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="aye">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="aye">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="aye">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="aye">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" vote="aye">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="aye">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="aye">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="aye">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="aye">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" vote="aye">Colette Kelleher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" vote="aye">Billy Lawless</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="aye">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" vote="aye">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="aye">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="aye">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" vote="aye">Jennifer Murnane O'Connor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="aye">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="aye">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="aye">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" vote="aye">Grace O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="aye">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="aye">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" vote="aye">Keith Swanick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="no">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="no">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="no">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="no">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" vote="no">P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="no">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="no">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" vote="no">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.267/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01600"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.268" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01700">Water Services Bill 2017: Motion for Earlier Signature</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01800"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That, pursuant to subsection 2&deg; of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad &Eacute;ireann concurs with the Government in a request to the President to sign the Water Services Bill 2017 on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.270/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01900"><p>Question put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 21; Nl, 7.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony; Nl, Senators Rose Conway-Walsh and Trevor  Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.270/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2017-11-15" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01900">
            <divisioncount ayes="21" noes="7" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="aye">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="aye">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="aye">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="aye">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="aye">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="aye">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="aye">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="aye">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" vote="aye">Billy Lawless</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="aye">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="aye">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="aye">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" vote="aye">Jennifer Murnane O'Connor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="aye">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="aye">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="aye">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="aye">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="aye">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" vote="aye">Keith Swanick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="no">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="no">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="no">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="no">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="no">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.270/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#U01900"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.271" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.272" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#FF00100">Health Services: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#FF00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017111500002#FF00300"><p>I am delighted to have the opportunity to address the House on health matters.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, sends his apologies that he is unable to attend.  I know that some Senators have raised particular matters which I will address later in my opening statement.  I will start by giving an overview of some recent developments.</p> <p>Any discussion will probably start with money and budget 2018.  In October the Minister for Finance announced a total health budget for 2018 of &euro;15.3 billion.  An additional &euro;646 million in current expenditure was allocated, with more than &euro;200 million for new developments.  Budget 2018 will mean additional front-line staff for the health service across the acute, mental health, disability, primary and community care sectors.  This will provide for better access to health services, more help for families and additional supports for people with a disability and mental health issues, as well as for old and vulnerable persons.  Funding is targeted at a number of key areas which include the following: a new access programme from 2017-18; helping families with the cost of medication and care; a shift to primary care services; expanding and developing mental health services; supporting disability services and supporting the most vulnerable.</p> <p>The next step for the HSE after the budget is agreed to is to finalise its service plan for 2018 detailing the actual services to be provided with the moneys allocated.  This process is ongoing between the Department and the HSE and should be concluded shortly.</p> <p>Also in July the Minister announced the following immediate actions to start implementation of the report: an impact study of the removal of private practice in public hospitals to be chaired by Dr D&oacute;nal de Buitl&eacute;ir; a public consultation process on the future alignment of hospital groups and community health organisations; and plans to establish a governing board to oversee the HSE's performance.  These represent the very first steps and a detailed implementation report is due to be submitted to the Government.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jim Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2328"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2328&amp;amp;pid=JimDaly&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> In addition to the steps noted above, work on the health capacity review is progressing.  This will be a comprehensive review concentrating not just on acute but also on primary and social care capacity.  The emerging findings from the review will also inform the development of the new ten-year national capital plan.  I understand the Minister, Deputy Harris, expects to receive the final report before the end of the year.</p><p>The development of primary care is central to the Government&rsquo;s objective to deliver a high-quality, integrated and cost-effective health care system. The Sl&aacute;intecare report also provided strong support for the need to strengthen our services as part of the overall reform of our health services.  The provision of a &euro;25 million primary care fund in budget 2018 demonstrates the Government's ongoing commitment to shifting the model of health care towards a more comprehensive and accessible primary care service in order to deliver better care close to home in communities across the country.  This new funding will enable a range of initiatives to be progressed in 2018 which will focus on disease prevention and early intervention, particularly through the further development and expansion of GP services, community intervention teams and the recruitment of additional therapy posts.  Throughout 2018 there will also be a continued focus on the development of primary care centres and primary care teams.  In regard to GP care, the Minister is optimistic that agreement can be reached with GP representatives in the coming months on significant service developments that can also be introduced during 2018.  As outlined by the Minister for Finance in his budget speech, this will be the start of a multi-annual change process that will enhance the role of primary care as the foundation of a more accessible and effective health service.</p><p>I would now like to talk about some developments in my own areas of responsibility.  The provision of an additional &euro;35 million in budget 2018 will help us to build on the work commenced in 2017 on the enhancement of community teams for child, adult, later life and mental health intellectual disability services.  It will also help us to continue our move towards a full 24-7 service with an initial focus on increasing the provision of services on a seven-days-a-week basis.  Further improvements are also planned to services for eating disorders and dual diagnosis.  It is important, however, that we use this extra funding to ensure that not only are our services of a high quality but that we provide as seamless as possible a service for every service user.  The HSE has been asked to prioritise this in 2018 and a further &euro;55 million in additional funding will be provided in 2019.  This will allow for a multi-annual approach to developing our mental health services, taking account of the review of A Vision for Change which is under way.  It will see total additional funding provided for the implementation of A Vision for Change rise to &euro;105 million over the period 2017-19.</p><p>Improving home care services so that people can live with confidence, dignity and security in their own homes for as long as possible is a key commitment of Government.  Home supports are crucial to helping older people and, indeed, people of all ages with particular care needs to remain where they want to be, at home in the surroundings in which they are most familiar and comfortable.  The current system relies heavily on family carers who play a crucial role in helping older people and others who need help to remain living in their own homes for longer.  These carers not only make a profound difference to the health, well-being and quality of life of those they care for but also make an important, often unacknowledged, contribution to the economy.  This is reflected in the 2016 census results published earlier this month which identified that some 195,000 carers are providing a minimum of 6.6 million hours of care per week.</p><p>In terms of resources, the HSE will spend approximately &euro;370 million on home care in 2017 out of a total budget of &euro;765 million for services for older people.  This figure excludes funding for the nursing homes support scheme.  The HSE&rsquo;s national service plan provides for a target of just over 10.5 million home help hours, some 17,000 home care packages and 190 intensive home care packages, co-funded by Atlantic Philanthropies for clients with complex needs, particularly those living with dementia.  In budget 2018 a further &euro;37 million has been made available for older people&rsquo;s services in order to further strengthen supports for older people, in particular to facilitate speedier discharge from acute hospitals over the winter period.  A significant proportion of this additional funding will go towards home care services.</p><p>The resources available for home care services, while significant, are limited and, with the increase in our elderly population, demand is growing year on year.  Accordingly the services and allocation of resources to individual clients require prudent management on an ongoing basis as demands for services increase.  In this context, those clients who are assessed and approved for home care and who are not being provided immediately with a service are risk-assessed and placed on a waiting list for a resource as it becomes available.  It is important to note that many people also purchase home care services directly from private providers.  While the existing home care service is delivering crucial support to many people across the country, it is recognised that home care services need to be improved to better meet the changing needs of our citizens.  The Department is of the view that a stand-alone funding scheme designed specifically for home care, together with an effective system of regulation, is needed.</p><p>In 2016 the Department&rsquo;s intention to bring forward legislative proposals for the regulation of home care was indicated in the "Better Health, Improving Health Care" report.  A Programme for a Partnership Government signalled the Government&rsquo;s commitment to the introduction of a uniform home care service.  My predecessor as Minister of State with responsibility for mental health and older people, Deputy Helen McEntee, played a key role in advancing this undertaking, tasking the Department with the development of a new statutory scheme and system of regulation for home care.  The new scheme will improve access to home care in an affordable and sustainable way.  It will provide transparency about individuals&rsquo; eligibility for services and about service allocation, and ensure that the system operates in a consistent and fair manner across the country.  The scheme will also result in more effective integration with other health supports, including nursing, therapies and other primary care services.</p><p>A system of regulation will be designed to ensure public confidence in the standard of the services provided and to bring Ireland in line with best international practice.  It will be important to get the balance right in this regard and to ensure that the system of regulation is effective and not overly bureaucratic.  As an initial step in developing the new system, the Department commissioned the Health Research Board to undertake a review of the home care systems in place in four European countries.  The review, which was published in April of this year, will help us to ensure that Ireland&rsquo;s new home care scheme and system of regulation is informed by international experience.</p><p>The Department also launched a public consultation process on the financing and regulation of home care in July of this year.  We received over 2,600 responses to this phase of the consultation process.  The purpose of this public consultation was to enable us to find out about the views of service users, their families and health care workers on current and future home care provision.  Preliminary analysis of the submissions has been undertaken and we would be happy to share details of some of the initial findings, if that would be of assistance to the House.  A full report on the findings will be published early next year which will inform the Department&rsquo;s development of the new funding scheme and regulatory arrangements.</p><p>The nursing homes support scheme provides financial support towards the cost of long-term residential care services in nursing homes and ensures that long-term nursing home care is accessible to everyone assessed as needing it.  Participants contribute to the cost of their care according to their means, while the State pays the balance of the cost.  The scheme aims to ensure that long-term nursing home care is accessible and affordable for everyone and that people are cared for in the most appropriate settings.  The scheme, or fair deal, is now in existence for over eight years.  This year, with a budget of &euro;940 million, the scheme is providing financial support to over 23,000 people and, next year, the budget for the scheme will increase to almost &euro;950 million.  The waiting time on the placement list has been maintained at four weeks since 2015.</p><p>While the care delivered to residents in our community hospitals is generally of a very high standard, many of these services are delivered in buildings that are less than ideal in the modern context.  It is important, therefore, that we upgrade our public bed stock and this is the aim of the five-year capital investment programme for community nursing units which was announced last year.  This provides the framework to allow for an enhanced programme to replace, upgrade or refurbish these care facilities, as appropriate.  Significant work was undertaken to determine the optimum scheduling of projects within the phased provision of funding to achieve compliance with national standards.</p><p>I will now look at some of the matters I understand were raised by individual Senators.  With regard to emergency departments, there is no doubt that too many patients continue to wait on trolleys for admission to hospital on a daily basis within our health service.  The Minister is cognisant of the distress that cramped and overcrowded conditions in some of our hospital emergency departments cause for patients and their families, and that these crowded conditions make emergency departments a very challenging environment to work in for doctors, nurses, hospital staff and hospital managers.  Notwithstanding this, there is an often untold story of achievement within a system working hard to deal with growing demand for health care services.  Last year there was a 2% increase in inpatient and day-case activity over 2015, as well as an approximately 5% increase in emergency department attendances - that is over 57,000 more patients, or the equivalent to the population of County Carlow.  This year emergency department attendances are up over 1.8%, or over 16,000 patients, to the end of September, including a 5% increase in emergency department attendances by people over the age of 75.</p><p>Within this context, overall trolley numbers have remained static when compared to last year, despite these increased attendances.  As of 6 November 2017, HSE data show there were 0.8%, or 625, fewer patients waiting on trolleys this year as compared to the same period last year.  In addition, some hospital sites have made a considerable leap forward in terms of improving their trolley performance.  For example, the HSE end of September TrolleyGAR data for St. Vincent&rsquo;s Hospital in Mayo, Our Lady of Lourdes Hospital in Drogheda and Beaumont Hospital in Dublin, to name but a few, are showing a reduction in trolley numbers ranging from 30% to 50% as compared to the same period in 2016.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-11-15a.276" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>