<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to make a statement on the cases of two Irish families who were refused work visas abroad, the first in New Zealand, on the ground that one of the family's children has Down's syndrome, and the second in Australia, on the ground that the family's son has cystic fibrosis; and to outline whether such discriminatory criteria are used in assessing visa applications of those seeking work visas in Ireland.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Leas-Chathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to make a statement on waiving the fees for naturalisation for British citizens who have been long-term residents of Ireland.  </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Catherine Noone of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to introduce an e-scooter pilot scheme.  </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for mental health and older people to provide an update on the provision of 7-7 child and adolescent mental health services.  </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to make a statement on the processes in place to ensure the provision of sufficient places for students with special needs.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to confirm that plans for the Cork North Ring Road will be included in the Cork-Limerick road development project.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Kieran O'Donnell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to provide an update on the redeployment of garda&iacute; from court security to frontline policing duties as recommended in the report of the Commission on the Future of Policing in Ireland.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to allocate funding to homecare packages to assist families keep their loved ones in care at home.</blockquote><p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Mullen, Clifford-Lee, Noone and Devine and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#B00200">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#B00300">Visa Applications</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#B00400"><p>I raise two cases which are separate but similar to those I raised on the Order of Business on 2 and 17 April.</p> <p>The issue is the treatment of two Irish families - the Suhinthan and Hyde families - at the hands of the immigration authorities of New Zealand and Australia, respectively.  Ms Nilani Suhinthan, an IT consultant, was headhunted for a job in New Zealand and her husband and family decided to move there.  The New Zealand authorities have issued residency permits to Nilhani, her husband and two of their three daughters - Tanya, who is 19, and Saumia, who is 14.  However, they have refused a permit to their third daughter, Bumikka, who is 15.  Shockingly, the reason for this seems to be that Bumikka has Down's syndrome.</p> <p>The New Zealand authorities have told the family that she does not have an acceptable standard of health and would place demands on the health and education systems there.  The family has made it clear that they do not expect the New Zealand state to fund any special health treatment or educational support for their daughter and have offered to fund this themselves since they have well-paid jobs.  Their appeal has been refused and they are in limbo with their family separated.</p> <p>The Hyde family face a somewhat similar injustice in Australia.  Anthony and Christine Hyde moved from Dublin to Victoria in 2009.  Anthony works as a bus driver and Christine is a teacher and assistant principal in a local primary school.  Their son Darragh was born there is 2015 and has never been outside Australia.  </p> <p>The family applied for permanent residency in Australia and, in the course of the application, their son was diagnosed with cystic fibrosis, CF.  Incredibly, this diagnosis led to the family's application being rejected due to the potential cost of the treatment of CF.</p> <p>An administrative appeals tribunal has refused the family's application and they can now make a final appeal to Australia's immigration Minister, but they face possible deportation within a month.</p> <p>Australia and New Zealand are saying that skilled Irish people and their families are perfectly welcome so long as none of them has a condition such as those I have described.  If this is happening, families who have children with these diagnoses are stigmatised and refused entry.  I hope we, in Ireland, would never be so heartless.  I cannot imagine a situation whereby a family from Australia or New Zealand would be turned away from Ireland on the grounds that one of their children was born with a manageable medical or genetic condition.</p> <p>There has been an almost total blackout of media coverage on these cases in Ireland.  One can easily imagine that if Donald Trump, or his United States, had denied visas to children with Down's syndrome or cystic fibrosis, there would be media outrage and extensive coverage.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We would ask where our moral values were.  We would ask where our civilisation and the leader of the free world were at.  One can imagine the rhetoric in the media but there has been no such comment or even questioning in the case of supposedly tolerant and liberal countries such as New Zealand and Australia.  What does this say about the world we are in?  I have been reading a lot about the controversy about Viktor Orb&aacute;n's Hungary and his coining of the phrase "illiberal democracy".  When I read about countries we regard as being, or supposedly being, in the vanguard of best practice in terms of human rights and civil liberties, I must ask whether this is liberal or illiberal democracy.  Is it governance without morality?  Is it conceivable that in modern democracies, the legitimate management of public finance allows such blatant and unjust discrimination against the most vulnerable?  These situations disclose something very scandalous in places where one would not expect to find it yet I am not entirely sure about what would happen in this country in similar circumstances.  </p><p>I know the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, is carrying the brief today for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade.  Is the Government aware of these cases?  Is the relevant Department, presumably the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, doing anything to assist either of these families?  In the case of the Hyde family where an appeal is still possible if there is a process, can the Minister intervene and make representations to the Australian immigration minister?  Can the Minister of State confirm that no such grounds would ever be used to deny a child a visa to enter Ireland with his or her family, all other things being equal?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#C00200"><p>The T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs sends his apologies to the House.  He is unable to be here so he asked me to address the matter.  The T&aacute;naiste thanks the Senator for bringing these cases to his attention.  This is clearly a very difficult time for the families concerned.  I commend the Senator for raising the matter in the way he did.  Unfortunately, the T&aacute;naiste is not in a position to comment on either case.  As the Senator will appreciate, the question of obtaining visas for New Zealand or Australia is a matter for the relevant authorities in New Zealand and Australia.  The T&aacute;naiste understands that the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade has not been asked by the families concerned to raise their cases with the governments of New Zealand and Australia.</p> <p>All countries establish their own procedures and criteria for assessing such applications and there can be broad similarities of approach between like-minded countries.  All visa applications in Ireland are considered on their own merits taking into account all matters brought to the attention of the visa deciding officer.  If an applicant for a visa declared something that could be a burden on the costs of the State such as a medical condition, this would form part of the consideration of the application but it would not mean that it would automatically lead to a refusal.  Non-EEA nationals who register in the State require full medical insurance, which would be expected to cover all current medical conditions.  </p> <p>It can be assumed that similar considerations are taken into account by authorities in Australia and New Zealand.  While recognising the difficulties faced by the families, I hope the Senator can appreciate that it is not possible for the T&aacute;naiste or me to comment on their specific cases or pass comment on the visa procedures applied by other sovereign states.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#C00300"><p>I am disappointed by the response.  If the notion that we cannot comment because this is a matter for another state was to be followed in all situations where something so blatantly unjust and cruel was to be disclosed, we would have zero international engagement.  The reason we have a Ministry for foreign affairs is to conduct relations with certain states.  According to my recollection, Ireland has always seen itself as a country with a moral voice and perspective on world affairs.  What I am hearing from the Minister of State's reply is a "hear no evil, see no evil" approach.  I am not at all reassured that there is also not a "do no evil" commitment because it is unclear from the reply that the Irish authorities would not take a similar cruel approach.  I hoped that the Government's reply would at least have stated that these situations ought to make us think and review our policies just to see whether there could be unintended consequences of such magnitude.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While I accept, as the Minister of State said, that this has not been taken up, I question whether the Government ought to wait to be approached when such troubling cases as these have come to public notice. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D00200"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising these two cases.  I recognise they are very upsetting for the families and I am sorry about that.  It is usual that such families would approach the Minister and the Department to make representations.  That has not happened to the best of my knowledge.  I believe I heard the Senator say that there would be no cost involved to the states concerned because of the medical conditions of the children involved.  If something similar happens here and such people came to work in Ireland they would be required to register for residence permission and the same criteria would apply with regard to their ability to support themselves and have adequate medical insurance.</p> <p>We are not really in a position to comment on the visa application processes of other states.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.16" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D00300">Naturalisation Applications</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D00400"><p>Before I discuss my Commencement matter, I would like to support Senator Mullen in his matter.  I am aware of the Hyde family who have connections in north County Dublin.  The mother of the little boy is from north County Dublin.  I have been in contact with the family and it is an outrageous situation.  I know that when applying for a visa or asylum in Ireland, weight is given to the fact that children born here in Ireland should not be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D00500"><p>The Senator is eating into the time for her own item.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D00600"><p>I will be very quick on my own matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D00700"><p>What should happen, in fairness-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D00800"><p>This is a very serious matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D00900"><p>It is, but hold on now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01000"><p>We show leniency in Ireland-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01100"><p>I am going to rule now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01200"><p>----- in similar situations to this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01300"><p>In that case the family and hopefully Senator Mullen will take it up with the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01400"><p>I will be in touch with Senator Mullen on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01500"><p>It is a separate matter from the Senator's item.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01600"><p>I just wanted to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01700"><p>The Senator is using up her own time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01800"><p>-----raise my own disappointment on that matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D01900"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D02000"><p>I also want to talk about immigration matters.  I refer to the naturalisation fees charged.  There is a &euro;175 application fee and a fee of &euro;950 for certification of naturalisation, a total of &euro;1,125.  I have come across many UK citizens living in my area and across the country who are very fearful about their situation with Brexit looming.  Approximately 300,000 British citizens live in Ireland and approximately one third of them do not qualify for citizenship through lineage by way of having either an Irish parent or grandparent.  Therefore they would need to go through the naturalisation process to obtain an Irish passport.</p> <p>In 2016, a total of 98 British citizens applied for naturalisation.  That jumped up to 529 in 2017 and in 2018, a total of 665 British citizens were naturalised.  That is obviously because of Brexit.  I have spoken to people on doorsteps in my area and they are very fearful of what might happen.  They cannot afford the naturalisation fees.  These are people who may be married to an Irish citizen and may have been living here for many years.  I spoke to one lady who has lived here for 40 years and has adult children who are Irish citizens but she cannot afford this outrageous fee of &euro;1,125.  That fee of &euro;950 for certification of naturalisation is waived in the case of a recognised refugee or stateless person.  I am asking for the fee to be waived for a defined period for our friends and neighbours from the UK who have been living here for a defined period of time.  These people have contributed so much to this country and deserve a bit of a break at this point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#D02100"><p>I am happy to discuss the matter of naturalisation fees with the Senator on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, who sends his apologies.</p> <p>Citizenship is a unique privilege bestowed on an individual that confers, among other rights, the protection of the State.  The granting of Irish citizenship through naturalisation is governed by the provisions of the Irish Nationality and Citizenship Act 1956, as amended.  All applications for a certificate of naturalisation are processed and assessed individually in accordance with the provisions of the Act.  A determination on whether an applicant satisfies the statutory criteria for naturalisation can only be made after an application is received.</p> <p>The fees to be paid by an applicant for a certificate of naturalisation are governed by the provisions of the Irish Nationality and Citizenship Regulations 2011, SI 569 of 2011.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The application fee is stipulated at &euro;175, payable on application for a certificate of naturalisation, and a certification fee is payable on the issue of a certificate of naturalisation.  The standard certification fee is set at &euro;950, while a reduced fee of &euro;200 applies in the case of an application made on behalf of a minor or, in certain cases, where the application is made by a widow, widower or surviving civil partner of an Irish citizen.  In the case of recognised refugees and stateless persons, the certification fee is nil, as the Senator pointed out.</p><p>While the fee is reduced in the cases outlined above, the fee is waived in its entirety only in respect of refugees and stateless persons.  Any review of fees would have to consider other categories of applicants, such as EU nationals, and the impact any changes would have on the level of fees for all other applicants.  It is important to bear in mind that, under the terms of the common travel area, British citizens resident in the State enjoy unrestricted residence rights within the State, as well as associated rights and entitlements, including access to employment, healthcare, education, social benefits and the right to vote in certain elections.  Indeed, for the first time, these rights have been placed on a more solid basis with the newly-signed agreement between the Irish and British Governments signed by the T&aacute;naiste last Wednesday.</p><p>I also remind the Senator that Ireland already operates a less onerous regime in regard to citizenship by naturalisation compared with many other countries.  There are no formal language or civic knowledge tests and a straightforward residence requirement applies to non-nationals.  The naturalisation fee, as it stands, is comparable to other jurisdictions and is less than that applied by the British authorities, which currently stands at over &euro;1,200.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State but the reply is less than satisfactory from my point of view.  I understand there is a fee structure but, for a defined period, we should allow for those who have been here for a significant amount of time and have contributed so much to Ireland, their own communities and their families.  There are practical considerations, for example, in the case of a British mother and her Irish children travelling through passport control and having to separate families as they are having their passports checked.  These people feel Irish and European, and they want to remain so.  If the &euro;950 fee can be waived in respect of certain individuals, in this once-off instance it would create a great deal of goodwill, which is what we need to foster in the future.  I would like the Minister of State to give more consideration to this suggestion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#E00300"><p>I remind the Senator that Ireland is a welcoming country and has granted citizenship to more than 100,000 individuals since citizenship ceremonies were introduced in 2011.  In total, nationals of 181 different countries have become Irish citizens since that time.  The fee is a part of the process and is common practice internationally.  The standard fees payable by an applicant are designed to reflect the effort and cost involved in processing applications for a certificate of naturalisation.  The Senator will be aware that formal citizenship ceremonies have been introduced at no extra cost to applicants.  These have been universally well received by participants as the ceremonies provide a sense of dignity and occasion that serves to underscore the importance to both the State and the applicant of the granting of Irish citizenship.</p> <p>Any further changes to the naturalisation fee regime would have to be carefully considered given there are many non-nationals of various nationalities in the State who may be eligible for citizenship and to single out one nationality could be considered preferential treatment.  For this and the other reasons already outlined, granting a waiver of the naturalisation fee in respect of British citizens who are long-term residents of Ireland is not something the Minister is currently considering.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.38" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#E00350">Electronic Scooter Pilot Scheme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#E00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, for dealing with this matter.  I received an email from the Minister, Deputy Ross, to say the Minister of State would be taking it because the Minister is unavailable, and I understand it is not an issue on which the Minister of State would necessarily be very focused.  Nonetheless, he will have a response for me and we can take it from there.</p> <p>The issue speaks for itself in the sense that I am asking the Minister to initiate an e-scooter pilot scheme to test the viability of e-scooter sharing as a means of clean transport for locals and visitors, and its potential for larger cities.  I acknowledge the Department's position is that the Road Safety Authority is currently looking at the safety and other implications of having e-scooters used in our cities and on our roads.  We should be embracing innovation that exists and the idea that we would move to make these illegal makes no sense at all.  Are we complete dinosaurs or what?  We need to look at the National Transport Authority's strategy of achieving zero carbon transport.</p> <p>Our colleague, Deputy Rock, has done a lot of work on this matter.  It is because I have been speaking to a few people who are involved in this area and have looked into the issue a bit more that I am supporting Deputy Rock in his efforts to try to get policymakers to see some sense on this.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have heard that the Garda is setting up checkpoints to confiscate these scooters, which cost people &euro;500, &euro;600 or even more.  They must then pay a fine to get their scooters back.  That is unacceptable.  There is law in place.  To my legal mind, though, there is an issue with its interpretation.  It depends on whether the scooter needs to be pushed to get it started or whether someone can just get on and start it straight away.</p><p>The technology exists to make these safe for use on our roads and limit the speeds at which they can travel.  There was a time years ago when cyclists were told to get off roads because they were a danger to cars.  We need to embrace this innovation.  Other cities have done so.  It should be done in a way that is organised, suits our cities and operates in conjunction with cycling.  The more ways that we can find to have people out of their cars and not using pollutants, the better.  It would also take pressure off public transport.  If it can be done in a way whereby helmets are provided, the scooters are parked in specific spots and whatever else is deemed to work well for the NTA's national strategy is done, we should not just leave the issue in a grey area.  That would be unacceptable.  We cannot be complete dinosaurs.  We must examine this issue and sort it out.  Legally, it does not make any sense to suggest that the Garda should confiscate them.  I do not understand that.  We must put a pilot in place in an organised way so that we can see how it works and what its potential pitfalls and problems are.  Irish providers need to be involved.  Irish individuals and companies can, in conjunction with city and county councils, the National Transport Authority, NTA, and the Road Safety Authority, RSA, put these in place throughout the country in a safe way.  That would make sense.  In this way, the scooters would not be a nuisance to anyone and people could use them to get around effectively.  I would welcome a response from the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#F00200"><p>I thank Senator Noone for raising the issue of electric scooters.  I apologise on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, who cannot be present to take the matter himself.  He thanks the Senator for raising this issue and providing him with an opportunity to discuss it.</p><p>The Minister is aware of the increasing number of electric scooters, electrically powered skateboards and similar small vehicles on our footpaths and roads, and he asked me to start by outlining the current legal situation relating to such vehicles.  The Road Traffic Act 1961 defines a mechanically propelled vehicle as:</p><blockquote>A vehicle intended or adapted for propulsion by mechanical means, including-(<i>a</i>) a bicycle or tricycle with an attachment for propelling it by mechanical power, whether or not the attachment is being used,<br /><br />(<i>b</i>) a vehicle the means of propulsion of which is electrical or partly electrical and partly mechanical,</blockquote> <p>Electric scooters and powered skateboards fall into this category and are therefore considered to be mechanically propelled vehicles.  Any user of such vehicles in a public place, as defined in the 1961 Act, must have insurance, road tax and a driving licence, with penalties under road traffic laws, including fixed charge notices, penalty points, fines and possible seizure of the vehicle, for not being in compliance with these requirements.  As it is currently not possible to tax or insure electric scooters or electric skateboards, they are not considered suitable for use in a public place.</p><p>The Minister has asked the RSA to research how electric scooters and other such vehicles are regulated in other countries, particularly EU member states.  He is keen to understand the road safety implications of the use of such vehicles on public roads, especially when interacting with other vehicles.  He is due to receive the outcome of the authority's research within the next few weeks.  He will need to be satisfied that permitting such vehicles on our roads will not give rise to safety concerns for the users themselves as well as all other road users, including cyclists, pedestrians and motorists.  However, the Senator should note that, should the Minister decide that the benefits derived from the use of electric scooters outweigh the risks associated with using this type of transport, an amendment to primary legislation would be required.  He will not be supporting a pilot scheme for the use of electric scooters in our cities while the use of such vehicles in a public place, as defined in the Road Traffic Acts, is <i>ultra vires</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#F00300"><p>I will make a brief response, although I could respond all day.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have alluded to the fact that there is an interpretation problem in the sense that one could argue that the fact one must manually propel some of scooters before the electric element kicks in indicates there is a grey area here.  The fact that e-scooters and powered skateboards are deemed to fall into the category covered by the two paragraphs and are considered, therefore, to be mechanically propelled vehicles, MPVs, meaning users must also have insurance, road tax and a driver's licence, while at the same time we are unable to provide that option to people if they wish to get these vehicles, outlines how crazy and grey the situation is for everybody, including the Garda and the Minister.  I have spoken to the Minister about this matter and know that he does not wish to make these vehicles illegal.</p><p>The Minister of State said that the Minister "will not be supporting a pilot scheme for the use of electric scooters".  In the context of the foregoing, of course the Minister is not going to support a pilot scheme.  We need to sort out the legal situation and then we can have a pilot scheme.  That can be done pretty quickly.  I hope that the Minister of State will encourage the Minister along those lines and I will speak to him as soon as I get the opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#G00200"><p>I thank the Senator.  Does the Minister of State wish to respond?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#G00300"><p>Yes.  Again, I am sure that Senator Noone will make her views known to the Minister.  I note that he awaits a report on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#G00400"><p>That is fair enough.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#G00500"><p>I hope the report is imminent and that clarity will be brought to this matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.48" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#G00600">Child and Adolescent Mental Health Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#G00800"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  Obviously he is standing in for the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Jim Daly, as this matter comes under the mental health portfolio.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#G00900"><p>Yes, that is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#G01000"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming here to give me a response.  I am running a campaign called the 31 Days of May where my colleagues and I and communities do something every day to raise awareness about mental health and well-being.  It can be something very small all the way up to something bigger like stopping traffic, which we did on Meath Street on Saturday with community dancers - young girls dancing with a green ribbon.  It is promoting conversation that will reduce stigma.</p> <p>The Minister of State will know about the escalating seriousness of the situation regarding mental ill health and how the lack of well-being in our communities is escalating and is in quite a crisis.  Not a week goes by that I do not know of at least three or four people who have completed suicide.  One instance that took place the weekend before last involved a 12 year old child.  It is just insupportable and quite upsetting.</p> <p>I ask the Minister of State to discuss the statement in the HSE's service plan for 2019 that it is working to develop a seven-day per week service for child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS, to ensure supports for vulnerable young persons in line with connecting for life.  The response to a parliamentary question that was submitted asking about this was shocking in that it stated in black and white that there was no planned date for completion of costs and implementation plans for providing 7-7 child and adolescent mental health services.  The cost of the implementation plan is the first step.  We have all agreed within these Houses, the HSE and among Ministers to deliver the 24-7 services that have been requested.  However, 7-7 services are the initial ask and task for us.  It is essential that we follow the service plan for 2019.  The HSE does not seem to be meeting its commitment to develop such services.  When will these vital services be delivered?  I guess the HSE needs a reminder.</p> <p>We all know the importance of services that are provided from Monday to Friday.  However, crises do not happen that neatly between Mondays and Fridays.  It has been repeatedly proven throughout Europe and in Ireland that crises occur between Thursday evening and into the early hours of Sunday morning.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is where the 7-7 services are required, prior to the excellent care that will be provided under the 24-7 system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#H00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue in mental health services.  I welcome any campaign that deals with stigma.</p> <p>On the issue raised by the Senator, the HSE service plan for 2019 commits to developing all aspects of child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS.  This includes developing a seven-day per week service for CAMHS to ensure improved support for vulnerable young people, as well as related initiatives in enhanced early intervention and day hospital care.  Community based CAMHS teams provide specialist mental health services for young people up to the age of 18 years and operate on a five-day per week basis.  Expanded CAMHS provision will be in line with adult services where a seven-day service is being developed.</p> <p>Where a child has a mental health crisis, the initial consultation should be with the child's general practitioner, GP, and if the GP assesses that the child requires an urgent mental health assessment, the GP should contact the local CAMHS team.  Where a person under 18 years of age presents to an emergency department following self-harm, it is important that he or she receive a compassionate and empathic response.  He or she should receive a bio-psychosocial assessment from a suitably qualified mental health professional prior to discharge from hospital.  It is recommended that children under 16 years of age be admitted overnight to a paediatric ward.  The paediatric team should ensure the child receives a bio-psychosocial assessment prior to discharge from hospital, thus following international best practice.  In some hospitals the child will be assessed by a non-consultant hospital doctor, NCHD, who can discuss the case with the on-call CAMHS consultant.  In other services, there might be no on-call CAMHS consultant and the paediatric team will be advised to wait until the CAMHS consultant is available.</p> <p>The HSE national clinical programme for the assessment and management of patients presenting to an emergency department following self-harm aims to ensure all such patients receive a bio-psychosocial assessment.  The programme is being extended to include the three paediatric hospitals in Dublin.  Three clinical nurse specialists, one for each of the three Dublin paediatric hospitals, are being recruited.  The addition of a specialist in each of the hospitals will improve follow-up care.  In addition, all three Dublin paediatric hospitals provide a comprehensive liaison psychiatry service.  In Temple Street Hospital it is provided in conjunction with the local mental health service 24 hours a day, seven days a week.  In Crumlin and Tallaght children's hospitals the liaison psychiatry service is available Monday to Friday, from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.  Outside these hours, children are assessed by paediatricians and admitted to a paediatric ward.  In Cork University Hospital there is a liaison psychiatric nurse available Monday to Friday, from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m.  This nurse is supported by a consultant from CAMHS.  Outside these hours, a NCHD completes assessments and CAMHS consultants provide input, as appropriate.</p> <p>CAMHS inpatient units currently operate a 24-7 tertiary model of care for young people with severe or complex mental health issues.  There are 74 CAMHS inpatient beds in four units in Dublin, Cork and Galway.  The new children&rsquo;s hospital will have an additional 20 CAMHS beds.  There will be ten CAMHS beds in the new forensic mental health complex which is due to open at Portrane next year.  It will be the first such unit nationally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#H00300"><p>I do not wish to thank the Minister of State.  First, only 50 of the 74 CAMHS inpatient beds are operational.  In his reply the Minister of State gave me an education on CAMHS and the services already available, but he did not address the importance of having seven-day services for children, from the peak time of Thursday to Sunday.  As for waiting in an emergency department for a CAMHS consultant, they do not exist.  Many children leave with their parents before they are assessed having waited for hours and days for a consultant to arrive.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Many child patients leave with their parents before they are assessed, having waited hours for a consultant to come.  The day hospital at Linn Dara is also still closed.  It has been closed for the last eight months and I cannot get a response from the HSE as to the plans for that facility.  It is a white elephant.  It is lying empty.  It was state-of-the-art when it was opened two or three years ago.  </p><p>The Minister of State's answer does not touch on 7-7 service provision at all.  What is available for our children now is just not good enough.  We are failing them.  We know the difficulties.  It was pledged that we would have services seven days out of seven, moving towards 24 hours a day, seven days a week, but nothing is happening and the HSE is not responding to its plans in this area for 2019.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#J00200"><p>On behalf of the Minister of State, Deputy Daly, I will say that the Senator can rest assured that this Government and the HSE remain firmly committed to developing all aspects of our CAMHS services.  This involves a more holistic approach to CAMHS overall than was taken in the past and includes out-of-hours provision, enhanced primary care, and disability supports for those vulnerable young people for whom these would be more appropriate than specialist CAMHS care.  The Minister of State is also strongly supportive of developing new initiatives such as e-mental health supports, which have been proven to work abroad.  These supports can either be used for early intervention, thus helping reduce service pressures on CAMHS, or can be an aid to CAMHS teams in progressing individual cases.  In addition, the new capital initiatives for the new children's hospital in Portrane, which I have already outlined to the Senator, will increase the number of CAMHS beds nationally from 74 to 104.</p><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Daly, and the Department of Health will continue to closely monitor CAMHS activity nationally in the context of implementing agreed HSE service plan targets for this year.  I will, of course, bring the Senator's concerns back to the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#J00300"><p>The Minister of State did not mention 7-7 service provision at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.58" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.10 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.59" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re Sectoral Employment Order (Construction Sector) 2019, to be taken without debate at the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2017 - Committee Stage (resumed), to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and adjourned at 6.20 p.m., if not previously concluded; and No. 3, Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2018 &ndash; Second Stage, to be taken at 6.20 p.m., with the time allocated to group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes each and to all other Senators not to exceed five minutes each.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#N00300"><p>I refer to the autism spectrum disorder, ASD, units attached to schools and the lack thereof.  There is a serious lack of these units in schools in Dublin 6, Dublin 6W, Dublin 8 and Dublin 12.  I asked my colleague Deputy James Browne to table a question to the Minister to ask how many persons were diagnosed with autism spectrum disorder in the south central area of Dublin.  We received a reply from the HSE stating there was no comprehensive national or local children's disability database that gathered data for children with autism spectrum disorder or other diagnostic groups.  That is remarkable, especially when huge funds are allocated to autism services.  It is most important to find out where the children who need these services are in order that funds can be directed accordingly.  There is a huge demand for ASD units in the Dublin 6, 6W, 8 and 12 areas.  The lack of statistics alone shows how low this issue is on the Government's agenda.  Will the Leader bring this matter to the attention of the Minister to ensure accurate statistics will be gathered and that we will allocate funding on the basis of those statistics to ensure the children who need these services will receive them?</p> <p>The second issue I would like to raise concerns the early childhood care and education scheme.  This fantastic scheme was introduced by Fianna F&aacute;il.  One of the problems with it is that it is so fantastic that many cr&egrave;ches are closing their new baby wards such that families are finding it very difficult to find childcare places for babies aged from six to 12 months.  This is creating problems.  Cr&egrave;ches are closing their baby rooms because their toddler rooms are so successful under the scheme.  I ask the Minister to take a look at this and look at ways by which we can ensure people will have access to childcare places for very young babies.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The final issue I wish to raise concerns WhatsApp.  I was extremely surprised to learn there had been a hacking of WhatsApp and that spyware or malware has infiltrated the application.  It is an application many of us use on a daily basis and we all have many groups on it.  I encourage people to ensure they download the update.  We all must be careful of the applications we use on our phones and ensure they are secure.  Perhaps we need to consider the introduction of further legislation to ensure that what has occurred in this instance does not happen again and to heighten awareness among people to ensure their phones are constantly upgraded and the apps downloaded on phones are renewed to ensure they are not vulnerable to malware or spyware.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#O00200"><p>On the final issue adverted to by my colleague concerning WhatsApp, we should always be aware of the fact that all software is constantly under threat from criminal elements.  They are working ahead of us all the time and the problem for us is that we have to catch them.  Our cybersecurity network structure is excellent at the job its does, and we should acknowledge that at this time.</p><p>I wish to raise two points with the Leader.  We heard yesterday that the cost of renting an apartment in Sandyford is &euro;2,100 per month.  The cost of a mortgage for the same apartment is &euro;1,350 per month.  That indicates there is quite a bonanza for those who can afford to buy a number of apartments.  I acknowledge there is no Member of this House who is not concerned about the issue of homelessness and the various other problems with respect to housing.  I have raised previously the possibility of easing the banking rules.  A relation of mine has spent &euro;87,000 on rent in the past seven year.  That person could have bought an apartment and be well into the repayments of the mortgage at this stage had there been access to a mortgage but the problem is this person cannot save the deposit.  Where will this person get the deposit when paying out that sort of money on rent?  From that point of view, could the Leader arrange for the Minister for Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform to come to the House to debate this issue and outline what influence can be brought to bear on the Central Bank with respect to the rules that apply.</p><p>The second issue I wish to raise concerns the Defence Forces.  First and foremost, I want to acknowledge the report in today's edition of <i>The Irish Times </i>that there is some ease for the Defence Forces with respect to their pay claims.  I compliment the Public Service Pay Commission, the Defence Forces, the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform and the Chief of Staff, in particular, for the work they have done in trying to secure this.  I hope other public servants would not see this as a bonanza for everybody to jump on the bandwagon.  The Defence Forces have been at the bottom of the heap for quite some time.</p><p>Yesterday the Minister told the D&aacute;il that 200 members of the Defence Forces had availed of sick leave.  It has been seen as an extraordinary high number.  I ask people to bear in mind that members of the Defence Forces are constantly working in very physical roles.  It is not uncommon for people to break their legs, have back injuries or various other injuries.  The problem is that we do not have the infrastructure within the Defence Forces to treat those members and, in many cases, they have to go on to the public waiting list.  That is where the differential kicks in.  Commissioned officers have access to private health insurance whereas 85% of the members of the Defence Forces who are service men and women, enlisted men and women, non-commissioned officers, etc., do not have the funding to afford private healthcare and, as such, they are dependent on the public health system.  God be with the days when I was in the Army where if one got sick there were the hospitals one could attend and one was treated totally by the Defence Forces.  Sadly, that is not the case any more.  I do not want the message to go out that we now have malingerers in the Defence Forces.  People need to realise that members of the Defence Forces abseil out of helicopters, engage in extremely physical activities and quite a number of them are involved in sporting activities.  By their very nature, these activities bring injuries with them and, as such, there is a backlog of cases to be treated.  I will leave it at that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#P00100"><p>At the weekend we heard the Minister for Finance and for Public Expenditure and Reform comment on the national broadband plan.  When asked about possible knock-on effects of the spend on the national broadband plan, he rejected any notion that Government plans for tax breaks would be affected.  He effectively said, no matter what the cost of the national broadband plan, money would still be found to cut taxes.  In other words, we should not worry, the money would be found.  That is an extraordinary statement.  I call on the Minister for Finance to come to the House to discuss this obsession with tax cutting above all else.  Terse answers have been given to the likes of patients waiting for life-saving drugs.  Schoolchildren are waiting on the delivery of proper school buildings.  Older citizens have had their home care hours slashed in recent years while people are desperately waiting on housing lists, yet the priority, as stated again at the weekend by the Minister for Finance, is tax cuts.  The ideological obsession with tax cuts at the expense of everything else is completely at odds with the reality for so many people today in terms of the health and housing crisis.</p> <p>There is a striking contrast in terms of the experience of the 17,000 SIPTU members in the health service, who will complete a ballot for strike action this week.  These people are porters, chefs and support staff who have honoured the Lansdowne Road agreements, who have gone through a job evaluation process and who have been awarded money through that process but are now being snubbed by the Minister for Finance.  The Minister sits in breach of his own Lansdowne Road agreement.  He cannot find money for those workers, but he will find money for tax cuts.  Last night I met childcare workers in Clare, as part of SIPTU&rsquo;s Big Start campaign.  They are people on abysmally low wages who have campaigned for years but the Minister can find no money for them either.  What does that tell us about the priorities of Fine Gael in government?  They are tax cuts, tax cuts and tax cuts.  The health service is in crisis and housing is in the worst crisis of the history of the State, but the Minister can only make one guarantee, namely, regardless of what else happens in the State, he will deliver tax cuts for his wealthy friends.  It is high time for a debate on this issue.</p> <p>I was very struck by the comments of a Fine Gael spokesperson on TV last night on the rent crisis.  He said that if it is given time, the rent crisis will work itself out.  People who are renting simply do not have time.  Every month expensive rental accommodation sees them further away from ever having a home of their own.  This evening in the D&aacute;il there will be a debate to enshrine the right to a home into the Constitution.  Sinn F&eacute;in is proud to take that stance today.  I do not wonder what position Fine Gael will take; it will oppose it.  Perhaps we need a real debate on the ideological chasm that exists in this Chamber.  Fine Gael and its obsession with tax cuts are costing the people of this country far too much.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#P00200"><p>Before I make my main point I wish to pay my respects to Fidelma Doonan, an usher in the Houses, whose brother died suddenly yesterday.  He happens to also be my nephew's grandad.  That is how I became aware of it and I thought it would be nice to pay my respects to Fidelma.</p> <p>I wish to move an amendment to the Order of Business, that No. 19 would be taken before No. 1.  Today, I intend to introduce the Electoral (Civil Society Freedom) (Amendment) Bill 2019 to the Seanad.  The Bill aims to fix an urgent problem with the Electoral Acts, which currently sees valid political advocacy by civil society organisations and community groups treated as electoral activity by the Standards in Public Office Commission.  As a result, it attaches disproportionately high, stringent and unfair financial declaration requirements to the work.  The interference by the State in the political lobbying activities of civil society groups was an unintended consequence of an amendment made to the Electoral Acts 18 years ago.  The amendment was made to the Bill responsible in the Seanad during a Committee Stage debate on 14 June 2001.  It is an urgent issue that has seen some civil society groups forced to close their doors in the face of the high compliance standards required, such as Education Equality, a group of concerned parents who came together to work for secular education.  We must support groups of ordinary people who want to organise together to agitate for positive change and yet the laws just get in the way.  Ireland is a world leader in civil society advocacy, including to the UN Human Rights Council and the European Union, yet European Union fundamental rights agencies and the Standards in Public Office Commission criticise the law domestically.  It undermines us internationally and opens us up to charges of hypocrisy and needs reform.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Ruane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2481"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2481&amp;amp;pid=LynnRuane&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In a Commencement debate in the Seanad on 29 November last year the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, admitted that he was aware of the problem and the concerns expressed and saw its potential resolution within the process to set up a new electoral commission.  However, this process could feasibly take years to come to fruition, whereas the current issue needs to be resolved in a timely fashion.  That is why I am tabling the Bill today.  I thank colleagues in the Civil Engagement group, the Independent group, Sinn F&eacute;in and the Labour Party for co-sponsoring the Bill which I hope to see receive cross-party support in the House in the near future.  The problem has been caused by bad legislation and has damaged Ireland's vibrant civil society space.  It is our responsibility as legislators to fix it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#Q00300"><p>I second Senator Ruane's proposed amendment to the Order of Business.</p> <p>The issue I want to raise is the spiralling cost of insurance.  I know that it has been discussed in the House, but it is urgent.  Last week we heard, for example, that the Ballina Salmon Festival was not being run this year because of the high cost of insurance.  Just today I was contacted by the principal of St. Teresa's special school in Ballinasloe and told that the cost of insurance had risen last year from &euro;3,221 to &euro;19,199, a colossal increase.  The school contacted the school governance board and the database section of the Department of Education and Skills, but it got nowhere.  It used money it had fundraised to meet the bill, but on Friday last it received an email from the patron to say Allianz Insurance's quote for this year had risen again, this time to a staggering &euro;26,317.  The Department suggested the school try to negotiate with the insurance company and offer to pay in monthly or other instalments, but the insurance company flatly refused to negotiate with the school and stated it had two days to make up its mind.  The school made up its mind, but it has no way of paying the cost of the insurance.  It is going to have to close.  The issue is really urgent and I ask the Leader to raise with the Minister for Education and Skills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#Q00500"><p>I am reading with concern about the appointments that may be made in the Football Association of Ireland, FAI, and about how some influence might be brought to bear by what are perceived to be Government agencies, if not by the Government itself.  It is important that every organisation in the country maintain its independence.  I am not saying there is interference, but I understand some people within the organisation are concerned that if it is perceived to be the case, the governing body at international level may decide to cease giving the FAI the financial support it requires.  I am sorry about being a little vague, but I am concerned that I have received a number of calls about the matter.  The last thing we need is for funding for any organisation to be withdrawn because of a perception, rather than what is actually happening on the ground.  It is important that that be made clear.  I understand fully that there is a need for full and thorough oversight of every organisation that is receiving state aid, including the FAI, which is accountable for that funding and making sure it is assigned to the areas for which it was given on the first day, but that does not give any Government agency or the Minister the right to interfere in how an appointment is subsequently made.  It is important that a clear message be sent that the FAI does retain its independence and that the only concern we have is in respect of Government funding and making sure it is used in the appropriate way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#Q00700"><p>I raise an issue in Bagenalstown, County Carlow, where there is an ongoing protest.  Last week Irish Rail confirmed that it was going to downgrade the service provided in Bagenalstown train station to use of an automated machine.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2470"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2470&amp;amp;pid=JenniferMurnaneOConnor&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It states it will no longer have a stationmaster on site and will subcontract maintenance of the station.  The stationmaster will be relocated to another station which already has adequate staff.  In 2017, the station was thought so beautiful that An Post captured it on a commemorative stamp.  We now hear Irish Rail plans to lease it out.  To say it is not busy enough to keep it manned is unacceptable in a rural town.  People in towns such as Bagenalstown matter.  This issue is so important.  We speak about rural areas but Bagenalstown, which has one of the most beautiful railway stations in Ireland, is now being told the man who runs the station will be going somewhere else.  That is unacceptable.</p><p>Irish Rail has told us 80% of users avail of online ticketing and that only 20% of passengers go into the station to buy tickets.  That does not matter.  What about the 20%, who need to have the service in the railway station?  I have been informed by Irish Rail that a staff member will disembark at all stations to help with machine tickets and acceptability issues.  I worry that we are slowly destroying rural Ireland and its way of life.</p><p>Transport poverty and accessibility are social and environmental issues.  More than one in four people living with a disability do not use public transport due to accessibility reasons.  What we are now seeing will further prevent the use of public transport at a time when we need to be considering ways to reduce our carbon footprint.  I am very concerned that, without a staff presence in Bagenalstown, there will be an increase in anti-social behaviour.  The issue of maintenance needs to be examined but we also must consider the requirements of people who need help - the 20%; they matter.  They include older people who do not use online services and those with disabilities.  My office telephone has been ringing for the past week.  I have been contacted by older people, in particular.  They are so concerned about this.  Individuals with disabilities are also ringing me.  A disability rack may be pulled out for wheelchairs users.  College and schoolgoing children also use the services in the station.  What is occurring is unacceptable.  Irish Rail cannot afford to be turning away customers.  I fear this is what is going to happen.</p><p>I will talk to the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport about this.  I believe what I describe is happening across the board.  It is happening in Athy and it has happened in Thomastown.  It is unacceptable that rural Ireland is being forgotten.  We have to ensure that we provide the services to the people.  God be with the days when one said, "Hello", to everyone.  One went into the train station and people said, "Hello", and asked how things were.  Are we changing all this?  Are we going to live in a society in which we will be going online for everything?  That is unacceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#R00200"><p>The declaration of a national emergency in Ireland owing to climate change is welcome.  We can declare all these emergencies but we have got to stay focused and on target.  We are aware that we have a global problem and we need global solutions.</p> <p>I wish to allude to the meeting of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly that took place over the past three days.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach was present.  We had an excellent presentation from the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Richard Bruton.  The meeting was interesting because of the considerable engagement and the questions.  The Minister responded to all the questions, and queues of additional people wanted to engage with him on them.  We would benefit by having the presentation here, if possible.  The Minister was exceptional.  Everyone from all the jurisdictions talked about a Minister who was totally on top of his brief.  He was asked many questions and had no idea what questions would be asked.  He responded very well.  It would be good to see him here.</p> <p>I attended the beef summit in Galway last week.  There were many parliamentarians there, as there were city and county councillors, particularly from Galway but also from other parts of the country.  One of the points arising in the environmental debate is that of a just transition.  We need to concentrate on that.  I would like to hear more from the Minister on it.  There has to be a just transition.  Certain groups will suffer more than others.  We have to guard against that.  Just transition is a really important aspect.</p> <p>Let me refer to agriculture, producers and farmers in regard to just transition.  This issue is important.  If we want to achieve targets, we have to incentivise.  We have not used the word "incentivise".  I believe in incentivising people.  I would like to hear more about just transition and how we can incentivise people.  We have a plan and targets but we have to incentivise people  to succeed.  If it all possible, and if it fits in with the schedule of the Minister, whom I realise is busy because he has a lot going on, he should be invited to make his presentation to the Seanad.  Senators would benefit from it and perhaps from the opportunity to ask a few questions.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach will agree the presentation was very positive.  There was a lot of engagement.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is an important issue that should also be aired in Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#S00200"><p>I echo the remarks made by my colleague, Senator Murnane O'Connor, about unmanned train stations.  It is not only a feature of rural Ireland as many of the railway stations in Dublin have been unmanned for quite a long time.  That has led to a degree of anti-social behaviour at those stations because the person who manned the station acted as an early-warning signal.  He or she could see what was happening at the station, who was getting on the train and if there was a problem.  A passenger could step off the train and tell the person manning the station of a problem happening on a train.  We need to be cautious.  The Government is working out the cost of everything and the value of nothing.  There is real value in manning railway stations.</p> <p>I wish to raise a matter close to the Leader's heart.  I welcome the Cork area transport strategy that was announced today.  It has the potential to change Cork for the better over the coming decade but I have slight concerns.  I hope the National Transport Authority, NTA, has learned lessons from community engagement in Dublin.  Many people from the Labour Party in Cork have been on to me today voicing their support but they also want an extension of the consultation period which currently runs until 28 June.  Cork is in the middle of local and European election campaigns and a plebiscite about whether there will be a directly-elected mayor for Cork.  Those Labour Party representatives feel it would benefit the city if the consultation period was extended.  I echo their calls and ask the Leader to engage with the Minister to see if he will extend the consultation period.  The citizens of Cork need to have ownership of the transportation plan for the city.  They need an opportunity to input their ideas.  I hope we do not end up in conflict with communities as has been the case in Dublin.</p> <p>Consultation can be done well and properly.  An extension to the consultation period at this stage would benefit any transport strategy for the city.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#S00300"><p>Recent figures released by the Department of Health show that the number of persons awaiting a child and adolescent mental health service, CAMHS, appointment stood at 2,738 at the end of March 2019.  That figure represents an increase of 6% on the previous month.</p> <p>More worrying is the fact that the number who have been waiting more than a year for an appointment has jumped to 336.  That figure represents a leap of 13.5%.  I know one young family in County Monaghan which has been waiting somewhere between three and four years and are still awaiting an appointment.  It is vitally important that we remember that there are real people behind those figures - children, their parents and families, who are left suffering while waiting for an appointment.</p> <p>Something needs to be done about this.  I ask that the Minister comes to this House to advise us of the strategy he intends to adopt in order to alleviate this serious problem so that families and children will not be kept waiting for an appointment that is needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#S00400"><p>I join with Senator Ruane in offering our sympathies to Ms Fidelma Doonan on the very sad death of her brother.</p> <p>I welcome Ms Rose Barford from County Wicklow who is a transition year student on work experience in the Seanad Office.  I wish her well and hope she has a pleasant experience.  She will learn a lot in the course of her week working here.</p> <p>I thank the ten Members of the House for their contributions on the Order of Business.  In response to Senator Ardagh, and linked to Senator Gallagher's contribution, the Government is committed to ensuring that every child with special educational needs receives a thorough and proper education.  That is why the budget for meeting special educational needs has increased to &euro;1.75 billion, a 43% increase since 2011 and 18.79% of the overall education budget.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Since 2011, the number of special needs schools has increased in Dublin and throughout the country.  There are 37 special schools and 235 special classes.  There has been an increase in ASD special classes in County Dublin from 66 to 195.  There are issues that Senators Ardagh and Gallagher raised that need to be tackled, particularly CAMHS.  It is a source of worry that there is a waiting lists and that there are issues around CAMHS.  Perhaps some of it relates to the way we categorise and diagnose people now.  There is a need for more resourcing, but it is not as simple an issue as resources.  It is not just that one-dimensional point about which the Senator spoke.</p><p>Regarding the early childcare matter raised by Senator Ardagh, I would be happy to have information on that given to the Senator.  Through the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, the Government is very much targeting the early childcare sector because, as we all know, early intervention-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#T00200"><p>I am saying that there are not enough places for newborns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#T00300"><p>I will come back to the Senator about that.  I do not have the reply to hand but I will give it to her.  Early years formation is important in terms of early intervention and early investment is critical but I will get the information on that for the Senator.</p> <p>Regarding the issue relating to WhatsApp raised by Senators Ardagh and Craughwell, it is important that the Data Protection Commissioner, who is working with the organisation, counteracts any type of infiltration of our data.  It is a source of worry and highlights the dangers posed by the new forms of technology we have.</p> <p>The Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government will be here later on to answer Senators Craughwell and Gavan.  In respect of his one-dimensional Sinn F&eacute;in speech, Senator Gavan always comes in and talks about the philosophy of Fine Gael.  The philosophy of Fine Gael is to give people a society in which they can live, grow, develop and flourish.  That is what we are about, which is why we have more people back at work and the highest housing budget, about which the Senator spoke.  Construction is taking place.  It is slower than we had hoped.</p> <p>Senator Gavan has a one-dimensional approach to housing, which is to have everything in the public domain.  That does not work and has not worked.  It has never worked.  We need a combination of everything.  We will have that debate with the Minister later on and I look forward to hearing more from Senator Gavan about his proposals and policies relating to housing that can help address the matter.  Putting down simple motions does not address the issue of building and moving people we meet every day of every week through our work from bedsits, family hubs or hotel rooms into proper accommodation.  We all accept that it is slow.  None of us is hiding the fact that we have a housing need that needs to be addressed, but it cannot happen just like that.  We have seen an increase in investment in the housing budget.  If the Senator travels to my city of Cork, I will bring him to many sites where social housing is being constructed, where people are being taken out of homelessness and where the budget for housing and homelessness has increased.  I will gladly bring the Senator to Cork to show him those sites.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#T00400"><p>Why are the figures getting worse every month?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#T00500"><p>Senator Craughwell also raised the issue of the Defence Forces.  We will have that debate with the Minister of State, Deputy Kehoe, in due course.  We all look forward to the publication of the report of the Public Sector Pay Commission on the matter.  I would be happy to accept Senator Ruane's amendment to the Order of Business.  I thank her for bringing forward her Bill.</p> <p>Senator Norris raised the issue of insurance.  The Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, has been in the House a couple of times recently to address the matter.  The Government is committed to tackling the issue of insurance.  There is the political will to solve the issue raised by Senator Norris.  We need to address a compendium of matters in terms of the costs being awarded by the courts.  The Government is bringing forward four pieces of legislation, particularly the Judicial Council Bill, that will have a positive effect on insurance.  The Minister of State and the Government are determined to solve the problem.  I think we must all agree that the level of awards is one such worry.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to address the compensation payment culture from both a legislative and cultural point of view.  The Personal Injuries Commission made 44 recommendations.  The level of payments for soft tissue injuries at 4.4 times those in the UK is a source of concern.  I understand a case over monopoly in the insurance industry will come before the European courts this week.  The insurance companies also have a critical role to play and cannot be let off the hook.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U00200"><p>Will the Leader contact the Minister about St. Teresa's school?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U00300"><p>If the Senator passes me on the details on St. Teresa's school I will personally take the matter to the Minister on his behalf.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U00400"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U00500"><p>Senator Colm Burke raised the issue of the Football Association of Ireland, FAI.  I do not want to stray into the internal issues of that organisation.  Those of us in this House who are sports people and are interested in the welfare of all sports, but in this case soccer, recognise that the FAI has a job of work to do to clean up its house and to restore confidence in the way in which it manages its affairs.  Outside influence from political or other quarters is not helpful.  There is concern that UEFA payments could be suspended.  I understand that represents about &euro;16 million to the FAI.  I hope all of us involved in politics, in government and in the wider Oireachtas, will allow the FAI to appoint its own CEO and get its house in order by appointing a new board and by bringing in new governance structures.  The work being done on the ground is of enormous benefit to many communities across the country.  We all want to see a vibrant strong FAI with proper governance and that means working with UEFA.  I hope that will happen because the suspension of further funding will not help the sport of football at grassroots level.</p> <p>Senator Murnane O'Connor raised the issue of Bagenalstown rail station and Senator Humphreys raised the issue of unmanned stations.  I am not familiar with the situation.  I know that an additional 7.10 a.m. service from Bagenalstown was added which showed that Irish Rail is committed to the route.  The Senator did not mention that in her contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U00600"><p>I did not have time; I was cut short.  I had to highlight the main points only.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U00700"><p>I am sure the Senator will have another outing on it.  I ask the Leader to continue without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U00800"><p>I agree with Senator Murnane O'Connor that there is a movement away from the interpersonal communication which applies when calling any organisation.  Eircom has become appalling in its customer care, as have the banks.  There now seems to be no interface with a person; it is all through a machine.  Over the phone customers are put on hold for an inordinate amount of time with no resolution.  I hope we will not lose that personal communication.  I share the Senator's concern over self-serve kiosks.  There are people in a hurry who do not have the capacity to use the machine.  It is an issue we should address as a society.  On a number of occasions I have made the point that banks do not want to see people inside their buildings.  I am a Bank of Ireland customer and I refuse to go onto Banking 365 because I want to be able to go in.  I know I am probably old-fashioned-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U00900"><p>Quite rightly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U01000"><p>The Leader is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U01100"><p>----- but I want to be able to go in and speak to somebody rather than going through a machine or dealing with them online.  I know it might be the way to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U01200"><p>The Leader is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U01300"><p>Many people like me prefer to go into the bank.  I make no apology for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U01400"><p>Based on the Leader's contribution, I can understand why the bank would want him to go on Banking 365 online.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.95" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#U01600"><p>The Senator could very well be right.</p> <p>Senator Boyhan raised the very important issue of climate change and I would be happy to facilitate having the Minister, Deputy Bruton, coming back to the House.  Senator Humphreys had a very good suggestion about a rolling debate on climate change, something we did prior to the Christmas recess.  We will come back to that again.  I will arrange to have the Minister, Deputy Bruton, come back to the House because the issue of climate change is very important.</p> <p>Senator Humphreys welcomed today's publication of the new ambitious metropolitan transport strategy for Cork, which I welcome.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=14"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The &euro;1 billion light rail network proposed for Cork is both innovative and necessary.  I hope we can see the period of consultation extended, as Senator Humphreys said, and I exhort all involved to extend it.  This is about the future of Cork.  It is going to 2040 and the more engagement we can have the better the outcome will be for our metropolitan transport strategy.  It is an investment of &euro;1 billion in light rail and &euro;545 million in BusConnects.  We are extending the routes from 14 km to 100 km and increasing walking and cycling propositions to the people of Cork.  I welcome it and commend those involved in the draft publication.</p><p>We need to get this right.  If that means extending the consultation period, let us do that, given we saw the benefit of this in Dublin.  I know Anne Graham was on the "News at One" today making comments about listening to people and it is important that people are listened to.</p><p>I answered Senator Gallagher on CAMHS.  I am happy to accept Senator Ruane's amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V00200"><p>Senator Ruane has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 19 be taken before No. 1."  The Leader has indicated he is prepared to accept this amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V00300"><p>I am.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V00400"><p>Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.101" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.102" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V00600">Electoral (Civil Society Freedom) (Amendment) Bill 2019: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V00700"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the Electoral Act 1997 to protect the right to freedom of association and expression for civil society organisations in Ireland and to provide for related matters.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V00800"><p>Is there a seconder?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V00900"><p>I second the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.106" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V01100"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V01200"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V01300"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.110" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 21 May 2019.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.111" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V01500">Sectoral Employment Order: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#V01600"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft: Sectoral Employment Order (Construction Sector) 2019a copy of which has been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 9th May 2019, be referred to the Joint Committee on Business, Enterprise and Innovation, in accordance with Standing Order 71(3)(<i>k</i>), which, not later than 16th May, 2019, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.&rdquo;</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.113" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.114" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.15 p.m. and resumed at 4.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.115" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD00100">Judicial Appointments Commission Bill 2017: Committee Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.116" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>SECTION 50</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.117" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Debate resumed on amendment No. 97a:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD00300"><p>Amendment No. 97a is in the names of Senators McDowell, Boyhan and Craughwell.  Senator McDowell has possession and reported progress on the last occasion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD00400"><p>This amendment is similar to several other amendments, both to this section and to others.  We agreed on the last occasion that they could all be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD00500"><p>It has been agreed that amendments Nos. 97a to 97e, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD00600"><p>Exactly, and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD00700"><p>I do not wish to interrupt the proceedings.  Have we dealt with section 49 in its entirety?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD00800"><p>Yes.  We have moved on to section 50.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD00900"><p>On the section?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD01000"><p>I think we have passed section 49.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD01100"><p>We are discussing amendments No. 97a to 97e, inclusive.  We will be voting on amendment No. 97a first, but the discussion concerns all of those amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD01200"><p>I am very grateful to the Minister.  He took me by surprise on the last occasion by acceding to the amendment we tabled in respect of the superior courts.  Rather than delay the House we did not debate it.  This may have implications for other bits of the Bill which will have to be revisited on Report Stage.  I will go no further than that.</p> <p>This amendment simply proposes to insert the word "experience" into section 50 as one of the qualities or characteristics making up the definition of "requisite skills and attributes".  The related amendments do likewise elsewhere in the Bill.  In my view that is one of the deficiencies of Part 8 of the Bill.  It does not really bring experience, which I consider to be of great significance, into play in determining a person's suitability for recommendation for judicial office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD01300"><p>These amendments are all more or less the same.  They all insert the word "experience".  It is the only thing they do.  I completely agree with Senator McDowell.  It is astonishing that experience was not called for in the Bill in the first place.  I would have thought that was a prime requirement of someone being promoted to these senior positions.  There is no doubt that experience in court is a very substantial asset for any judge and I would have thought it important to include it.</p> <p>As it currently stands, section 50(1)(b) states: "requisite skills and attributes" means skills, competencies, personal attributes and characteristics that a person must possess in order that he or she may be considered to be suitable for selection (and the foregoing references to skills, and other matters, include those matters that, with any suitable adaptation, would be listed in the document commonly referred to as a "role profile")."  This is actually quite vague.  What are the "skills, competencies, personal attributes and characteristics that a person must possess"?  That is very vague, while experience is a very solid, factually based and well-grounded idea and it is very important that it is included in the Bill at this juncture.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019051400002#DD01400"><p>The first three of these amendments are to section 50, which provides for interpretation for the purposes of Part 8 of the Bill.  I wish to briefly deal with an issue that arose since we last met.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-05-14a.130" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>