<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Paul Daly that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the boarding out payment rates payable to householders under the HSE boarding out scheme for elderly people. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the transport charges for people with disabilities accessing services in community healthcare organisation, CHO, area 1. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science to make a statement on compliance by professional bodies with European Commission Recommendation (EU) 2022/554 in recognising the qualifications of Ukrainian refugees in Ireland. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lynn Boylan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for heritage and electoral reform to make a statement on the carrying out of testing for secondary poisoning in raptors by the National Parks and Wildlife Service, NPWS. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to ensure that the Port of Cork is a designated port for the importation of non-EU fresh produce. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Loughlin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to provide an update on the provision of a second bridge for Newbridge. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the regulation of jet skis. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth to make a statement on the core funding model and the support it offers to medium and small early childhood care and education programme providers. </blockquote> <p>have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of Health to provide an update on the payment of the pandemic bonus payment to community-based carers. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on the review to be conducted under section 18(3) of the Inland Fisheries Act 2010 in respect of the functions of Inland Fisheries Ireland. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Paul Daly, Gallagher, Ward and Boylan and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator O&rsquo;Loughlin on the grounds that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  I regret that I also had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Maria Byrne on the grounds that it is a repeat of a statement on childcare provision taken in the Seanad on 17 May 2022.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#A00400">Care of the Elderly</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#A00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#A00600"><p>I also welcome the Minister of State.  I thank her for taking the time to come in and deal with this issue.  For the record, the question is to ask the Minister of State whether the rate of pay for those who use their homes for the HSE boarding out scheme for elderly people under the boarding out regulations of 1993 could be increased in light of the increasing cost of living and associated costs of running this type of accommodation.  It is pretty self-explanatory from the conversation we have on a daily basis in every sector of society with the increased cost of living.</p> <p>I ask this question this morning specifically on behalf of Lisa and John Corroon in Ballinagore, who have a boarding out home that facilitates six residents.  Their residence is somewhat rural and would be five miles from the nearest town.  The cost of ferrying their residents to chiropody, physiotherapy and medical and dental appointments has, with the increase in diesel alone, not to mention those relating to food, heating the residence, etc., gone through the roof.  This is something of which we are all very much aware.</p> <p>The regulations were reviewed in 1993.  While they have been reviewed since, there has been no change to them.  The Corroons rate of pay from the HSE went nine years ago from &euro;90 per week to &euro;110 and then three quarters of the pension.  They are getting somewhere in the region of &euro;270 to &euro;280 per person per week.  That is one night in an average hotel with breakfast and none of the facilities they are covering.  They are unable to survive and continue.  That is evident by the fact that very limited numbers of people have availed of the boarding out scheme in recent years.  The numbers have dropped off.  These people take the maximum six residents, but some very quick and simple sums will tell the Minister of State that the saving by having those six people in this environment as opposed to in a nursing home is approximately one eighth of the cost, depending on what calculations one does.  We are looking at a difference of somewhere between &euro;8,000 to &euro;9,000 to &euro;50,000-odd per annum.  When you go to look this up, and when I was doing my research this morning, you find there is either very limited or very little information on the HSE website.  It is as if it is a secret.  It is almost as if it is not wanted because one must go trawling and scratching way below the surface to even find out the basic information.  It is as if it is not being promoted or literally not wanted.</p> <p>Another issue I encountered when I was doing my research is the fact that different community healthcare organisations, CHOs, have different policies and different payment rates.  This can cause a major issue for people who are on the borderline and maybe have residents who fall under the jurisdiction of two different CHOs.  They will actually be on different rates in the one residence or house.</p> <p>The kernel of the issue and the key question is that there would be a review of the payment structure.  As I said, there is a saving to the State.  The fact that it is a smaller facility with a maximum of six residents is very beneficial for our elderly people to be in those kinds of environments.  The people who approached me in the case I am using as an example are just one example of this kind of well-run, tight ship.  Their residents remain Covid-free.  That has been the acid test in all such environments over the last couple of years.  They are doing their very best.  As I said, they actually kept Covid-19 out of their residence.  That is how tight a ship they run.  For less than &euro;300 per week, however, they are finding it very hard to survive.  They are not making any money out of this; some of their own money is actually going in to keep the show on the road.  The matter needs to be reviewed.  I hope the Minister of State can look on my request favourably.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#B00100"><p>I am taking this Commencement matter on behalf of the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, who sends her apologies for not being here this morning.  I would like to thank the Senator for raising this issue, which is a key priority for the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, and for the Government.  It will allow more people to engage in services that will allow them to remain independent and to live in their own homes with dignity and independence for as long as possible.  Where this is not feasible, the health service supports access to quality long-term residential care, where this is appropriate.  We will continue to develop and improve health services in all regions of the country to meet this objective and to ensure both quality and patient safety.</p> <p>The 1993 regulation provided a framework for the operation of a boarding out scheme.  The regulation included specific conditions relating to maintenance, care and welfare of an older person in a private home.  The intention of the scheme was to provide social and personal care to older people who did not want to or who were not able to live on their own but who wanted to remain living in their community.  The phrase that is important here is &ldquo;local community&rdquo;.</p> <p>Under the regulations, the HSE must be satisfied that the house is suitable and that the householder is fit to look after the person who is being boarded out.  The householder must provide suitable and sufficient care, nutritious and varied food and adequate attendance, having regard to the needs of the person.  The householder must also respect the privacy of the person who is being boarded out.  Not more than six people can be boarded out in one house.  The regulation also sets out standards as to the suitability of the accommodation, including cleanliness, safety and other related matters.  I am reading all this into the record because perhaps not too many people know about this.  I genuinely believe that this, until I read it before the House morning, was one of the best kept secrets.  I personally also thank the Senator for raising this issue.  </p> <p>The regulations provide that the HSE may pay to the householder an amount not exceeding half the weekly rate of the non-contributory State pension which is payable at the time in respect of each person being boarded out.  In addition, the person who is being boarded out must pay to the householder an amount which is agreed between the HSE, the householder and the person who is being boarded out.</p> <p>The boarding out scheme has diminished over time.  It is now only available in a limited number of areas across the country.  At present, it is understood that there are only 17 boarding-out facilities across three community healthcare organisations.  The HSE completed a review of the scheme in 2017, which concluded that an expansion of the scheme was warranted.  While the use of the boarding out scheme by the HSE has traditionally been small, there is value in exploring it further.  I would go so far as to say that this relevant not just for older persons, but that we could also look at within the area of disability.  </p> <p>The pandemic has highlighted the continuing importance of the need to support older people living in our community who wish to remain in their communities where they may otherwise be accommodated in residential care.  I am pleased to advise the House that my colleague, the Minister of State with responsibility for mental health and older persons, Deputy Butler, has requested that officials in the Department consider this model of care and the regulation for the scheme, as well as the rate of pay and implications of the raising costs associated with running these accommodations in the context of our overall commitment to enhancing opportunities for older people to stay in their homes and in their communities for longer.</p> <p>What the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, has committed to doing is very welcome.  I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#B00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I appreciate that she is here on behalf of the Minister of State, Deputy Butler.  I welcome in her statement the commitment by the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, to review this.  However, my specific question was about pay rates, which should be addressed sooner rather than later.  The regulations were introduced in 1993.  In her statement, the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, said that is now being recommended that we would look at enhancing this model.  The numbers are dropping off.  She mentioned that there are only 17 registered care homes at the moment.  Why is this so?  It is because people are not able to financially to maintain them.</p> <p>In theory, we might be saying that this is a brilliant model that we would love to expand but if we are not rewarding the people who are providing these fantastic facilities, there will be more and more dropping off.  If the pricing model alone is not dealt with immediately, the next time we are back before the House having this conversation, I can guarantee the Minister of State that the figure of 17 that she quoted will have decreased and not increased, irrespective of how the Department or the HSE may value the model or think that it needs expanding.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#B00300"><p>I thank the Senator again.  It is important to say the Government is committed to trying to establish schemes which are focused on prevention and early intervention in respect of appropriate care settings.  The point that the Senator has just made is fair.  The cost of this scheme is one eighth of the cost of going into a nursing home.  It is also keeping people in their community.  What the Senator described to me is a family network.  However, at the end of the day, costs are rising.  I will discuss it further with the Minister of State, Deputy Butler.  There is also the fact that within the gift of the HSE locally we do not need to stand behind legislation.  There is a word called &ldquo;discretion&rdquo;.  If there is a need to support that particular house or any of the 17 houses, it should be looked at in the light that we look at all other providers in the areas of disability and older persons.  We treat all equally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#B00400"><p>The HSE is on record as saying that this needs to be done through legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#B00500"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.16" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#B00650">Disability Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#B00700"><p>At the outset I thank the Minister of State most sincerely for her recent visit to Monaghan, which was very well received.  The feedback has been extremely positive.  I wish to take this opportunity to thank her for her ongoing work within her portfolio.</p> <p>This morning, I am urging the Minister of State to get the HSE to reconsider the transport charge that is being levelled at several juniors who are attending HSE day services in the community healthcare organisation, CHO, 1 area, which includes the counties of Monaghan, Cavan, Donegal, Sligo and Leitrim.</p> <p>As the Minister of State will know, disability is unfortunately strongly associated with poverty in this country.  Among people who are unable to work due to long-standing illness, one in three live on an income below the poverty line.  Among those who are able to work, many people with a disability are unemployed.  This is a classification where more than four in ten people live in poverty.  People with a disability are twice as likely to be unable to afford to heat their home.  Much help is needed in that regard with rising inflation costs.</p> <p>In fact, a study that has recently been compiled by Indecon on behalf of the Department of Social Protection has found that the cost of having a disability is between &euro;9,482 and &euro;11,734 extra per year, on top of everyday expenses.  As the Minister of State will be aware, disabled people and the households that include people with a disability have to spend more on items such as fuel and light, transport, therapeutic equipment, medical expenses, domestic services, equipment aids and appliances, mobility and communications, daily living costs and care and assistance. </p> <p>It therefore seems inexplicable that a transport charge has been applied to service users who are attending HSE day services at &euro;4 per trip or &euro;20 per week, particularly when this levy is being applied exclusively to the CHO 1 area, which includes the counties that I mentioned earlier.  These five counties are arguably the most isolated counties with regard to transport infrastructure in the entire country. </p> <p>The daily charge of &euro;4 amounts to a total of &euro;960 per annum for a person with a disability.  Naturally, there is now a genuine fear in families that their loved ones may not be able to avail of the service simply because of the cost.  That would be heartbreaking.  I am aware of one case locally where there are two attendees in a family.  That will cost them almost &euro;2,000 per annum, which is a huge amount of money.  On top of that is the aforementioned cost of living with disability.  I feel that this charge is very unfair.  Apparently, the charge has been levied because the routes are deemed to be closed routes or exclusive routes.  People who are using an open route can use their free travel pass, for example, on Bus &Eacute;ireann.  Unfortunately, this does not apply to this particular service.  The problem with the CHO 1 area is that the routes are deemed to be closed.  </p> <p>The simple answer would appear to be to extend the free travel pass to include these particular routes.  Maybe that is too simple and I await the Minister of State&rsquo;s response on that.  There is no issue with the service.  The service is top class but unfortunately, it is now getting to the stage where many families simply cannot afford it.  I acknowledge that since the Minister of State has come into office, she has been a champion for people with disabilities.  I now ask her to champion this cause on behalf of the service users of Monaghan, Cavan, Sligo, Leitrim and Donegal.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#C00100"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue and there is no pressure attached.  It is important to state that the HSE has no statutory responsibility for providing transport to day services and that transport to day services is not usually provided for service users.  At the same time I would preface that by saying that the HSE, under disability, spends in excess of &euro;40 million every year on transport, while it provides no transport.  I am trying to work that out myself and that is why I have taken ownership of the chair of the transport committee where I have put everybody around the table to look at all available routes.  It is not only that but it is also to look at the primary medical certificates, the blue badge and everything.</p> <p>There is an inequality in CHO 1.  It charges &euro;4 per day and the Senator is right that it is a closed route option.  It is not part of the open routes and if it was part of that, there would be no charge whatsoever on it.  On the other hand I have to compliment CHO 1 for doing this.  It meant that no service user lost a day service.  In other CHOs they have paid for the transport and reduced the service users' attendance at the day services whereas in Donegal, Sligo, Leitrim, Cavan and Monaghan they came up with the &euro;4 per day charge in order that people would not lose access to their day services, which was a balancing measure.  I do not think that was right and transport is being provided for people attending day services in other CHOs, so why would it not be provided equally and on the same basis in all CHOs?  It is the only CHO in the country where you have to pay &euro;4.</p> <p>In Leitrim, the Local Link has been running a pilot, which has been positive, and we need to see that expanded.  We need to move away from closed routes to open routes and those open routes have a benefit for the climate and the locality.  Such a HSE open routes model could be used for older persons as well as for persons with a disability.  It could also possibly be used for people who need to access a medical appointment.  They could all be accommodated within the same running time as opposed to running the bus first thing in the morning just for the disability service, then running it later on in the day to go to the day centre with older persons and perhaps running it later on in the day for people who need hospital appointments.  A little bit more collaboration and joined-up thinking is what is required in order that we can have open routes, which would be funded through the Department of Transport.  The Department of Transport needs to do that because there needs to be equitable access to all routes, regardless of location.  To be fair to the Department of Transport, it has done phenomenal work since I have come into office in expanding its Local Link service and in making its fleet far more accessible and better integrated.  Perhaps this is something I will take further.  One of the reasons I have had these conversations is to see how we can address the inequality of the &euro;4 charge in CHO 1 versus the other eight CHOs that do not have a charge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response.  I join with the Minister of State in complimenting all those involved in the Local Link service.  It is a fantastic service and there is serious potential to expand that even further, as the Minister of State outlined, and I look forward to that.  I am heartened by the Minister of State's comments on her input into having a look at the charge being applied in CHO 1 only.  It is unfair to the service users involved and I would welcome, that on their behalf, the Minister of State would do all in her power to ensure that citizens living in CHO 1 are treated no differently to citizens elsewhere and that this unfair charge will be removed as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#C00300"><p>It is important to say that the reason that charge is in place is to ensure that there is a service.  That was the decision that was taken at an executive level and within the HSE at a local level a number of years ago.  The Senator clearly outlined the challenge this is putting before families that have more than one family member who needs to attend a day service.  It is on my agenda, I chair that committee and I work closely with Edel Quinn, with whom I have had those conversations.  I compliment the local HSE as it did not remove the service for the service users and it did not find other ways of trying to pay the bill.  It was totally upfront and it has been transparent but at the same time it is allowing people to have their full five-day service, as opposed to giving a five-day service where only four days can really be provided because the fifth day is being used to pay for the bus.  As that goes on too, it is important to have an open conversation on this but I do not like the fact that we pay for it in one CHO and we do not in others.  That is an inequality and the solution is to have more open routes.  By having more open routes we have more accessibility for the inclusion of other people, not just disabled people, to access the service.  Older people and people who need to go to appointments could access these routes as well.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.21" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#C00400">Qualifications Recognition</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#C00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking the time to come in to respond to this issue.  I am proud of Ireland's response to the crisis in Ukraine and to the invasion by Russia.  We can also be pleased that there has been a cross-continental and global response to that and as members of the European Union, we can be proud of how our political Union has responded.  In Ireland the Government deserves credit but so do communities and at the local level people deserve credit for how they have welcomed Ukrainians into this country and done whatever they can to assist them.  There is still a lot of work to be done on that front and there are a number of actions that need to be taken.</p> <p>I am conscious of Resolution 2436 of the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe and what it has set out as a checklist of things we should be doing.  First is legislating for the crime of aggression, something that is contrary to the European Convention on Human Rights and something that was part of the Kampala amendments to the convention in 2010, led by Liechtenstein and which Ireland signed up to in 2018.  That followed the UN General Assembly resolution which stated that aggression includes, for example, the bombing of another country, invasion and the blockading of ports, all of which we see happening in Ukraine.  It would be appropriate for Ireland, therefore, to legislate for that crime as well.  Other measures would include a universal civil jurisdiction that would allow us to freeze and confiscate foreign assets, particularly Russian assets in Europe and Ireland, to allow them to be put towards the reconstruction of Ukraine after the invasion concludes.  Now that Russia has essentially been put out of the Council of Europe, we have a limited window within which we can bring a suit against Russia for breaches of the convention under Article 33.  That window closes on 16 September and Ireland should be looking at that as something to do in order to put down a clear marker.  I am also conscious that the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, and the Government have earmarked &euro;4 million of support for the International Criminal Court, ICC, which I support.  Some &euro;1 million of that has been delivered and &euro;3 million is yet to be delivered.  I wonder if consideration should be given to that remaining &euro;3 million going to the Ukrainian prosecutor on the ground.  As counsel before the ICC but also as somebody who has spoken to the prosecutor in Ukraine, I believe they have a greater ability to affect that on the ground.</p> <p>In following the recommendation of the European Commission on the recognition of professional qualifications, this is a key area where Ireland can deliver for Ukrainian professionals who have come here and to any other European state.  It covers education, healthcare, engineering and law and includes people who come here with a particular qualification or skill set.  In accordance with the 2001 directive on the minimum standards for people enjoying temporary protection, for example, we must facilitate them in working here, either in an employed context or in a self-employed context.  Although the recommendation may not be legally binding, it sets out a clear statement and in the first instance I would like Ireland to confirm if we are totally in accordance with that recommendation.  What are we doing as a State to say to professional regulatory bodies that we must implement this recommendation, facilitate Ukrainians coming here and ensure that they can work and be part of the community for as long as is needed?  They should be able to integrate into a professional environment here with the greatest possible ease and the least possible bureaucratic resistance.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What this is about is facilitating people who do not particularly want to be in Ireland.  They are here because a conflict has exploded in their home country.  When they come here, they should be facilitated in continuing their lives in as normal a way as possible, however perverse that might be in the current circumstances.  That involves the Government putting pressure on those regulatory bodies to ensure that the recommendation of the Commission is followed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#D00200"><p>Before the Minister of State responds, I am under strict instructions from Senator Clifford-Lee to give a warm welcome to very important guests in the Visitors Gallery, the students from Ardgillan Community College in Balbriggan and their teachers, Mr. Walsh and Ms McGuinness.  You are very welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1563" speakername="Joe O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#D00300"><p>I, too, welcome our guests from Ardgillan Community College.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  The Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Harris, and his Department are committed to providing every support possible for Ukrainian citizens who are seeking the recognition of their qualifications in Ireland, be it to further their education, to pursue employment opportunities or to practise a profession that is regulated.  Through the National Academic Recognition Information Centre, NARIC, Ireland, a service hosted and operated by Quality and Qualifications Ireland, QQI, advice can be readily obtained, free of charge, on the academic recognition of foreign qualifications.  This service compares foreign qualifications to major award types and levels on the Irish national framework of qualifications, NFQ, which sets these foreign qualifications clearly into an Irish context.  QQI's NARIC database currently lists 18 Ukrainian qualifications, comparable to levels 3 to 10 on the NFQ, which includes general professional, further and higher education qualifications.  NARIC Ireland is working with the wider NARIC network across Europe to continue building the list of Ukrainian qualifications, and this is a current priority.</p> <p>When NARIC receives a request for the recognition of a previously unlisted qualification, once it is assessed, it is added to the list of published qualifications and is made readily available online.  A guide to NARIC has been translated into Ukrainian and has also been made available in a wide range of other languages spoken by Ukrainians.  The service provided by NARIC Ireland helps to inform employers if an applicant holds the academic qualifications necessary for a particular job or employment opportunity.  Where a profession is unregulated, there is no formal barrier to prevent someone from continuing to practise his or her profession in Ireland.  However, where a profession is regulated, such as the professions of doctor, nurse or teacher, for example, the decision to recognise qualifications rests with the national regulator or competent authority in question, such as the Medical Council, the Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland or the Teaching Council.  In these cases, the competent authority compares qualifications against the Irish regulatory standard to ensure the holder has the necessary skills and competencies to practise in Ireland.  Ireland has over 45 such authorities covering a range of professions.  A list of these professions, alongside the relevant contact information for each authority, is available on the Department's website.</p> <p>Any Ukrainian citizen who wishes to practise a regulated profession in Ireland is advised to engage with the relevant competent authority with responsibility for that profession to seek the recognition of his or her professional qualifications.  This is crucial to ensure Ukrainian people can pursue opportunities in their profession of choice.  Indeed, many of these authorities have already reached out to engage with the Ukrainian community in Ireland and have published dedicated material on their websites to assist Ukrainian applicants.  The Department has been providing critical support to the work of these competent authorities by sharing best-practice material supplied by the European Commission on recognition of Ukrainian professional qualifications.  This includes working with and supporting these authorities as they implement the recently published Commission recommendation on the recognition of qualifications for people fleeing Russia's invasion of Ukraine.  This Commission recommendation was published last month and provides competent authorities with guidance and practical advice to ensure a quick, fair and flexible recognition process for Ukrainian refugees. In addition, these competent authorities have been advised of further information resources from NARIC Ireland that will assist in their work, alongside toolkits and resources developed by the EU and UNESCO to assist in dealing with cases of where refugees do not have complete evidence or documentation of their qualifications.</p> <p>The Minister and the Department are continuing to work with our national competent authorities, their parent Departments, the European Commission and other member states on the recognition of professional qualifications of Ukrainian people and the implementation of the Commission recommendation to ensure an appropriate EU-wide response.  I will bring the Senator's points regarding the Council of Europe and the International Criminal Court to the attention of the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#D00400"><p>I appreciate what the Minister of State said about what Ireland is doing.  I welcome the fact that progress is being made in this area.  I also welcome the fact that some professions are specifically moving in this direction to facilitate Ukrainian refugees.  Others are not, however, and I am aware of specific individuals in Ireland who are having difficulty having their Ukrainian professional qualifications recognised here.  The Minister of State is quite right to say that each professional regulatory body has to deal with that in the way that is appropriate.  That is included in the recommendation from the Commission.  However, it is also important for the Government to send out a clear message to all professional regulatory bodies that this is important and is something that must be pursued and advanced in a concrete way in the coming weeks and months.  It is not something they can wait for many months to implement.  Let us implement the recommendation from the Commission and ensure that Ukrainian nurses, doctors, lawyers and engineers who come to Ireland can make use of their professional qualifications and skills, work here and contribute here in the way we know they want to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1563" speakername="Joe O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#D00500"><p>I thank the Senator for his contribution on this issue.  As I said, the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science is committed to providing every support possible for Ukrainian citizens who are seeking the recognition of their qualifications in Ireland, be it to further their education, to pursue employment opportunities or to practise a profession that is regulated.  The Department is committed to continuing to work with the national competent authorities, their parent Departments, the European Commission and other member states on the recognition of professional qualifications of Ukrainian people and the implementation of the Commission recommendation to ensure an appropriate EU-wide response.  I will speak to the Minister directly about any professional regulatory bodies that are tardy in their response to the need that exists.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#D00600">Wildlife Protection</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#D00700"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  I am raising the issue of rodenticide poisoning of raptors, particularly barn owls.  Our bird populations are collapsing due to habitat loss but also as a result of deliberate and accidental poisoning.  There is no need to tell the Minister of State that our native birds of prey are key indicator species of the health of our ecosystems and they are a critical part of our natural heritage.</p> <p>The recording and addressing persecution and threats to our raptors, RAPTOR, protocol, which was introduced in 2011, was welcome.  It set in place a formal procedure for investigations of bird of prey deaths and it has allowed us to build up a database of information on the causes of death of raptors through the collection and handling of carcases and evidence, toxicological testing, post mortems and X-rays.  The most recently available report I could find is from 2019.  What is very worrying about that report is that it shows the highest number of deaths of birds of prey.  Rodenticide poisons were the most prevalent poisons found in birds of prey.  The RAPTOR protocol 2019 report clearly states that the protocol includes the monitoring of incidents of poisoning in species vulnerable to secondary poisoning by rodenticides.  There is particular concern about the barn owl, the kestrel, the buzzard, the red kite and the long-eared owl.</p> <p>The reason I raise this today is that those who are involved in wildlife rehabilitation and the Barn Owl Project are concerned that testing for secondary poisoning is not happening or is not happening at a consistent rate.  In Britain, where monitoring for secondary poisoning is taking place, it has been found that 88% of barn owls are likely to have been affected by rodenticide poisoning.  Ireland has a much higher rate of use of rodenticide so if it is 88% in our nearest neighbour, it is more than likely much higher in Ireland.  Can the Minister of State confirm that the RAPTOR protocol is being fully implemented in terms of testing for secondary poisoning?  Could he consult with his colleagues in the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine on the broader issue of the use of rodenticides?</p> <p>We have dealt with this general issue previously.  I have spoken in the House about metaldehyde in slug pellets.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The real issue is that members of the public can get their hands on very dangerous chemicals.  I do not doubt for a second people are doing this deliberately.  In the vast majority of cases, people put out poison to kill slugs because they love their garden plants or to reduce the number of rodents about the place.  However, these poisons have serious implications for wildlife.  Can the Government arrange a public awareness campaign about the damage that can be done by using these poisons?  For example, one cannot buy a box of cigarettes without an image on the box that shows the damage that cigarettes do to one's health.  When people walk into a hardware store, we need them to know full well the possible implications of using these chemicals and offer alternatives.  We know that barn owls can eat up to 1,000 rodents a year, so it would be far better for farmers to have one on their land than use rodenticide.  Of course, there are inconsistencies in terms of the use of rodenticide and farmers' obligations under the Common Agricultural Policy.  I look forward to hearing the response of the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for her Commencement matter.  It is always good to talk about biodiversity in the Seanad even if it is a negative issue.  It is important to highlight important points, particularly the poisoning of raptors.  I take on board the specific points she made about testing and a public awareness campaign, which I will address in a follow-up response.</p> <p>Ireland is home to more than 14 species of breeding raptors.  Some species are largely resident, for example, the kestrel and the barn owl, with others visiting Ireland largely in winter, such as the snowy owl, or on passage in early spring and late summer, such as the hobby or osprey.</p> <p>Various natural, environmental and anthropogenic factors lead to mortality incidents within the populations of Ireland's raptor species and can affect their conservation status.  These include: sub-optimal prey availability and habitat suitability that is compounded by prolonged periods of inclement weather; collisions with traffic on road and rail networks, wind turbines, etc.; disease, including avian influenza; persecution via direct shooting or deliberate poisoning; and environmental pollution, for example, by their feeding on dead or moribund rodents that have ingested rodenticide, which is the issue being discussed here today.  This particular factor can lead to what is known as secondary poisoning as the bird does not feed on the poison itself directly.</p> <p>Since 2011, my staff have worked collaboratively with the regional veterinary laboratory service of the Department of Agriculture Food and the Marine, and the State Laboratory, to determine the cause of death of raptor carcasses that have been recovered from around the country under the RAPTOR protocol, which is the Recording and Addressing Persecution and Threats to Our Raptors protocol.  The protocol already includes testing for secondary poisoning in raptors.</p> <p>As part of the protocol, liver and stomach samples are routinely taken from each viable carcass.  The samples are subjected to a range of toxicological testing to identify and quantify, where possible, the concentrations of particular analytes or components in the samples.  These analyses allow for the detection of substances that are used to deliberately target raptors and also substances that may be prevalent in the wider countryside such as second generation anticoagulant rodenticides, SGARs, that are used to control rodents.  As the Senator mentioned, rodents constitute part of the diet of many raptor species such as barn owl.  The suite of substances that are routinely tested for include those used to deliberately target raptors such as carbofuran, alphachloralose, methiocarb as well as a whole suite of SGARs, which are rodenticides, including brodifacoum, flucomafen and difenacoum.  It should be noted that raptors are the most effective way to control rodents.  The Senator rightly said that many farmers are now seeing the benefit of having barn owls on their farms in terms of bringing a balance both to nature and habitats.</p> <p>With relevant stakeholders, my staff are looking at the breadth of potential testing concerning the current monitoring of contaminants in raptors.  Furthermore, my staff are working to update the existing service level agreement with the State Laboratory and the regional veterinary laboratory service.  This will allow the current RAPTOR protocol to continue to operate, and allows us to effectively detect and monitor a range of environmental contaminants, including rodenticides, which are prevalent in the organs and tissues of these top predators.  It is vital to have this information not just for national purposes, so that we understand the impact of such poisoning on our raptor populations, but also in the European-wide context, with the aim of reducing chemical risks to raptors,   to the wider environment and to human health.  Reports on the protocol are prepared annually and made available on the website of the National Parks and Wildlife Service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#E00250"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  I welcome the confirmation that the protocol will continue and that the service level agreement is being updated.  I ask him to confirm a timeline for the completion of that process.  I ask him to confirm also whether testing will be expanded so that we can have a complete picture of the current state of the raptor population and thus address the issue of poisoning.  I ask him to touch on my idea of the Government arranging a public awareness campaign that informs people who may be unaware of the damage that is done to wildlife due to people having access to these very dangerous chemicals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#E00300"><p>The Senator's idea to have a public awareness campaign is a good one.  I must advise that any such campaign would need to be led by the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.</p> <p>The Senator mentioned that these toxins are available on the shelves of garden centres and other stores.  Another issue is the storage of carbofuran and other toxins that have been banned because they may still be available on farms.  Perhaps a call for people to deposit these products at a secure facility would be a really useful way to address the amount of toxins that are out there.  We will raise the issue of a public awareness campaign with the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine and I will get back to the Senator about a timeline for the service level agreement.</p> <p>Finally, I reiterate that it is illegal to persecute or poison a raptor either directly or indirectly.  My Department takes wildlife crime very seriously and in a number of instances there has been a successful outcome to cases that were brought to court over the direct poisoning of raptors.  We take the issue very seriously and I welcome the fact the Senator raised this issue today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.34" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 11.17 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 11.32 a.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 11.17 a.m. and resumed at 11.32 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#G00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Protected Disclosures (Amendment) Bill 2022 - Second Stage, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and adjourn at 2.45 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply; No. 2, Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill 2022 &ndash; Committee Stage (Resumed), to be taken at 3 p.m. and to adjourn at 6.30 p.m. if not previously concluded; and No. 3, National Minimum Wage (Payment of Interns) Bill 2022 &ndash; Second Stage, to be taken at 6.45 p.m., with the time allocated for this debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#G00300"><p>I agree with the Order of Business as set out by the Acting Leader.  This morning, she and I have both come from the gates of Leinster House on Kildare Street where we joined with fellow Senators, Deputies, activists and the National Women's Council of Ireland to celebrate the anniversary of the referendum to repeal the eighth amendment, which took place this day four years ago.  Many of us were involved in that campaign.  I feel I got involved at the 11th hour because the campaign began 35 years before that date and many of the women involved then are still involved today.</p> <p>We envisaged that there would be some difficulties in implementing the will of the people and ensuring equality of access for women across the county to these legally available services.  Some of those problems persist today and they are part of what we will be looking at in the review of the legislation to ensure we get it right for the women and girls of Ireland.  We stand with fellow Members, activists and women across the country in once again pledging our support to ensure the legislation is properly and fully implemented, there is equality of access and we address any additional and outstanding concerns.  We will work with colleagues across parties on those issues in the coming weeks and months.</p> <p>I also want to speak about the horrific mass shooting that happened yesterday in a primary school in the United States.  It is the 27th such shooting this year.  My heart goes out the families of the victims, to the other students who witnessed it, to the two teachers lost and to that community.  I have no doubt that people across the United State are heartbroken at what has happened.</p> <p>It is with utter disbelief that we listen to the commentary from some public representatives, both Congressmen and Senators, suggesting that the issue is not gun control.  They have moved on from wanting to arm teachers and some are now suggesting they should have armed police on school grounds.  I listened to Larry Murphy on the radio this morning.  His views were very strong and I concur with his remarks.  It is abhorrent to suggest putting an armed police force in schools rather than changing the gun laws in the United States.  There is a majority view among the public that there should be tighter gun controls, as well as from many public representatives, yet the National Rifle Association seems to have a vice grip on a majority in American politics.  I concur with the remarks of President Biden on this.  We hope these representatives will act and that this will be the straw that breaks the camel's back, but there is pessimism across the United States that anything will actually happen.  There will be an outpouring of grief and solidarity and then people will just move on and it will be forgotten about and consigned to the history books.  It is shocking.</p> <p>President Biden was correct in pointing out that lots of countries have mental health issues and other challenges, such as civil unrest and different issues that pop up from time to time, but no other country in the world is dealing with mass shootings in schools like the United States is.  The issue is gun control, not those other issues.  I extend our support, solidarity and deep sympathies to the families and communities of those who have lost loved ones this morning, those very young second, third and fourth graders.  It does not bear thinking about but it is important that we speak about this issue, highlight it and advocate for change. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#G00400"><p>I join with the Senator in expressing our sympathies to the families who have, over the last number of hours, gone through the most unimaginable horror to befall any parent, which is the loss of a child.  As the Senator has pointed out, it is an unnecessary loss.  This is a failure of politics at its worst.  This is a world superpower.  If it cannot protect its own children then the solution is not more police; it is more politics and people working together to make sure they protect their children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#G00500"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach and his office, the Clerk and his team and all involved in the very successful visit yesterday by Congressman Richard Neal.  By all accounts, it was an amazing and historic day.  It was a great privilege to be here and to share in the exchange.  Based on the media coverage last night, it resonated with a lot of people.  I know it was a personal choice of the Cathaoirleach's and something he wanted to see happen.  I also thank the administration here in Leinster House that dealt with all the security issues and other matters that come with such a visit to this House.  We were greatly privileged and I again thank everyone involved.</p> <p>I raise the issue of An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  I am conscious that there is litigation going on that would not be appropriate for me to talk about.  That said, An Bord Plean&aacute;la plays a very important - indeed, critical - role in our planning process and the public must therefore have every confidence in the governance procedures of the board and how it and its members conduct themselves.  We in these Houses are all aware that the former Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government commissioned a report called the Mulcahy report, which I will address in a minute.  We are also very aware that our current Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage appointed Remy Farrell SC to provide his opinion on a number of planning decisions and a report is awaited.  As I said, it would not be appropriate for me to comment on his work or any ongoing issues around An Bord Plean&aacute;la.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A report by Rory Mulcahy SC into alleged corruption in County Donegal remains unpublished almost five years after it was sitting on the desk of the then Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Eoghan Murphy.  He said the report was on his desk and that it needed some consideration.  There were many issues of alleged serious misconduct in a planning authority, which gave rise to questions.  We are going to talk about confidence in the planning authority, in local government planning procedures and in our appeals board, An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  Let us not waste money and time commissioning reports unless we are also committed to putting them in the public domain.  I have already issued a statement today calling on the Minister to publish the Mulcahy report and lay it before the Houses of the Oireachtas, so we can at least tease out the issues and learn from the recommendations.  Having reports that spell out wrongdoing, but not learning from them, is simply and quite frankly not good enough.  I ask the Acting Leader for a debate at some point on planning, planning governance, confidence in planning and how we can instil greater confidence in the planning process.  I will leave it at that because these reports will hopefully be forthcoming.  Today, my call is on the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to publish Rory Mulcahy SC's report.  Let us look at it, see about it and let us debate those issues in these Houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#H00200"><p>This morning I wish to raise two outstanding pieces of legislation.  As Senator Chambers pointed out, it is now four years after that momentous day when we repealed the eighth amendment of the Constitution, but we know that there is still a lack of provision, which affects in particular people living in rural areas, people with disabilities, the working class, migrants and people living in direct provision.  The three-day waiting period is also an issue.  Quite frankly, it is paternalistic nonsense.  I am concerned that this House has passed the legislation on safe access zones, yet we still do not have any progress from the Minister for Health on the issue.</p> <p>This morning a very worrying interview was carried out on the fact that not all maternity hospitals are offering abortion services.  More damning is the fact that only one in ten GPs is signing up to provide abortion services.  It is very concerning for one community where a GP has had to stop having any clinics whatsoever on a Saturday morning because of protests that were occurring on Saturdays.  Now, not only are the women who are in need of healthcare for abortion services affected, but also the wider community cannot get access to their GP on a Saturday because some people think it is appropriate to protest outside a GP's office and prevent women from getting the healthcare access they need.  We need safe access zones.  If it is not Senator Gavan's legislation, which has been supported by many Members across this House, then the Minister, Deputy Donnelly, needs to act fast so that women are not prevented from accessing the healthcare to which they are entitled and that we fought hard to achieve.</p> <p>The second piece of legislation that we are awaiting is my own Bill that was brought to the House in February on jury selection, in particular in connection with the Stardust inquest.  We know that the coroner, Myra Cullinane, wants the inquest to proceed in September.  These families have been waiting for decades for justice.  She wants no further delays.  We already had a judicial review in the High Court, which has delayed proceedings.  It is essential that the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, brings forward legislative proposals and fulfils the commitment she gave to the families who were in this House.  She said that she was aware that their concerns were warranted, that we must have independent selection of jurors and that their income must be protected in some way to allow them to sit for a number of months on jury service.  We have a matter of weeks left before the summer recess.  If the Minister does not bring the legislation before the two Houses before the summer recess, we will not be back here until late September, which means the inquest will not be able to proceed then, as the coroner wants it to.  It is completely in the hands of the Minister, Deputy McEntee, to prevent any further delays and hurt to the families of the Stardust fire.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#H00300"><p>I rise again today to raise a very serious matter about my local hospital and that of the Acting Leader, Naas General Hospital.  It is the second time in just over a year that "RT&Eacute; Investigates" has disclosed horrific allegations of sexual abuse of patients by medical professionals who were working in the hospital.  In last night's case, it was outlined that a doctor who worked at Naas General Hospital was removed from the Irish medical register in 2015 after two patients alleged they were sexually assaulted by him.  The allegations relate to a doctor who was found guilty of professional misconduct by the Irish Medical Council.</p> <p>Naas General Hospital has apologised for the way it communicated with the two patients in the aftermath of their complaints.  In a statement to "RT&Eacute; Investigates", Naas General Hospital said on the day it received the first complaint the hospital convened a serious incident review meeting and decided to suspend the doctor from duty with immediate effect, pending the outcome of a trust-in-care process.  The hospital went on to say that the doctor has never returned to work since his suspension.  Last night's programme outlined that An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is currently carrying out an ongoing criminal investigation and it is co-operating with Interpol and other police authorities.</p> <p>Last year, "RT&Eacute; Investigates" also revealed three separate investigations were under way into a series of complaints of suspected sexual abuse of unconscious patients by another doctor at Naas General Hospital.  Those allegations involved up to four patients.  Again, I thank Aoife Hegarty and "RT&Eacute; Investigates" for their work in highlighting these important and very worrying matters.</p> <p>I want to pay tribute as well to the young man referred to in the programme last night as "Ryan" for his bravery in coming forward in what must have been a very difficult investigation and a very difficult time for him and his family.  I ask the Acting Leader to arrange a debate in this House with the Minister for Health on hospital safety.  We must be able to assure patients that when they are at their most vulnerable from a health point of view, the professionals treating them care for them as they are supposed to do.</p> <p>I welcome the news from yesterday that the Permanent Defence Force Other Ranks Representative Association, PDFORRA, has been allowed to affiliate with ICTU, albeit on a temporary, two-year basis.  This is very good news for the members of PDFORRA, allowing its representatives to partake in the forthcoming pay talks.  This opportunity must also be extended to the Representative Association of Commissioned Officers, RACO.  I hope we all get the chance to raise this important point again with the Minister for Defence when he is next in this House.  We have all called for a debate on the report of the commission.  The Acting Leader and colleagues throughout the House have done so.  I ask that such a debate would be convened in the quickest possible time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#H00400"><p>Last week in this Chamber I spoke about the murder of Shireen Abu Akleh and the shameful attacks on her funeral procession.  I said that it was part of a pattern of Israeli violence and repression employed to suppress the voices of those highlighting human rights abuses in the region.  I called for accountability and meaningful repercussions of the violation of international law.</p> <p>There is an update to this saga.  A European Parliament delegation to Palestine, which includes Irish MEPs, Chris McManus and my good friend, Grace O'Sullivan, has been blocked by Israel, making it necessary for them to call off their visit.  Israel created this situation by refusing to allow the delegation to travel to Gaza, and by refusing the leader of the delegation, Manu Pineda MEP, access to the country, when he arrived in Tel Aviv on Sunday.  Impeding the delegation in this way is outrageous behaviour which warrants a robust response.  There are precedents to follow here.  In the past, when Russia and China took actions against MEPs, diplomatic and trade repercussions were imposed on them.  The suspension of a massive EU-China trade deal is evidence of how seriously these matters should be taken and it is clear that the same standard needs to be applied in this case.  This is what Mr. Pineda and my former Civil Engagement Group colleague, Grace O'Sullivan, have called for.  Whenever calls are made in this Chamber for action against Israel, in light of its human rights abuses, the standard response is that maintaining diplomatic relations between Ireland and Israel is important so that Ireland can press for better treatment of Palestinians and the importance of upholding international law.  I do not doubt the sincerity of this argument, but it is becoming increasingly untenable.  It is very clear that Israel refuses any kind of meaningful scrutiny of its treatment of the Palestinian people.  It refuses to be held accountable for its crimes.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The only diplomacy that Israel is interested in is a stage-managed version, where criticism is muted and figures who express solidarity for Palestine's struggle for freedom are excluded.  Ireland must stop validating this sham.  If Irish and European diplomacy are unable to highlight the real issues on the ground, then it is not worth engaging.  The restrictions that are being imposed on Members of the European Parliament who are carrying out their duties warrant a response from the European Union.  I want this House to be briefed on what the position of the Irish permanent representative to the European Union will be on this issue.  Will he echo the calls from Grace O'Sullivan MEP and Manu Pineda MEP for material consequences for Israel's restrictions on the work of the European Parliament?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#J00200"><p>I echo the compliments to the Cathaoirleach and the staff at the Seanad on the address by US Congressman Richie Neal and the warm welcome that was extended to him by this House.  I compliment the Cathaoirleach on his ongoing engagement with the United States.  Yesterday's interaction was important.</p> <p>I also welcome the decision to allow temporary associate membership to PDFORRA of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, ICTU.  It is important that members of our Defence Forces have a voice in the forthcoming pay talks.  I appreciate that this is only a first step but it is welcome.  I think that should be communicated.  I congratulate the executive of PDFORRA for its work in that regard.</p> <p>I am conscious that we have often debated China in this House.  Yesterday saw a leak of police files that further prove the appalling treatment of the Uyghur minorities in Xinjiang by the Chinese Communist Party.  We know that China is continuing to engage in systematic abuse and in a genocide against the Uyghur minorities.  While our attention is rightly focused on what is happening in Ukraine, we cannot avoid what is continuing to happen in China.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#J00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#J00400"><p>We are seeing the ongoing repression of human rights in Hong Kong, in Tibet and of other minorities.  Yet, the images that have now emerged of the Uyghur community are particularly frightening.  I ask again that this House communicate those messages to the Minister for Foreign Affairs in order that he in turn communicate them to the Chinese ambassador.  Once again, we should express our abhorrence at the ongoing abuse of human rights by the Chinese Communist Party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#J00500"><p>This afternoon I raise the issue of the crisis in our rental car industry.  We are all very much aware of the inflation in prices.  This morning I got a quote to rent a car for ten days.  The sum of that, if I were to take it up, would be &euro;1,800.  That is quite extraordinary to see the inflation in the rental car trade.  Some 20% of visitors who come to Ireland use rental cars.  This inflation imposed upon our tourism market will have a huge knock-on effect on our credibility as being an affordable place to go on holidays.  We need to look over the next few weeks at how we can ensure that our rental car trade will be competitive.  That would require engagement with the motor trade and with the Minister.  I respectfully ask the Leader of the House to organise a debate with the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, on how she will move in the next few days and weeks to curb the inflation that is being seen at present in the rental car trade.  More importantly, how will she make sure that our tourism industry will not be grossly affected by this inflation?  This could undermine our entire tourism industry, as 20% of tourists use cars.  They go to rural locations, such as Kerry or west Cork.  They will not go to west Cork unless they have the opportunity to get an affordable rental car.  We need to have a real, genuine debate in this House on how we will solve this issue as otherwise, the tourism industry unfortunately could be undermined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#J00600"><p>First, I join with my colleague, Senator Wall, and I am sure with the Acting Leader, in welcoming the accession of PDFORRA to ICTU.  However, it is outrageous that RACO has not been granted the same permission.  I call today on the Minister for Defence to immediately address that.  There are pay talks ongoing right now and they need to be there.</p> <p>There has been much talk recently about mental health for children and mental health issues for children.  One wonders about the way business is done in this country.  I brought this report before this House last week.  It is 415 pages in length and is the Air Corps's pitch to take part in the search and rescue, SAR.  This would result in &euro;378,661,302 in savings to the Exchequer.  I guarantee the Leader that no Minister has read this or has been asked to read it.  Furthermore, the critique of that report is three pages in length.  There is not one technological, empirical or statistical piece of evidence to support this piece of nonsense.</p> <p>The Secretary General was invited before the Oireachtas joint committee on a number of occasions to discuss this process and has refused to come.  If the Departments are not answerable to the Oireachtas and the Ministers appear to not be in control of their Departments, where the hell do we go?  It is outrageous there is no way to question this process.  This process is banging ahead like a steam engine.  There would be almost &euro;400 million in savings over ten years and nobody will explain why it is not happening.</p> <p>We talk all the time about the pride we have in the Defence Forces in this House.  There is no pride in the Defence Forces.  This weekend an RAF aircraft was called in to do top cover without the knowledge of the Air Corps.  I am told it was RAF, but it was English and that is for sure.  This fits neatly into the desire of the Irish Coast Guard to have top cover provided by somebody other than the Air Corps for the next three years. </p> <p>Who is running this State?  Is it the faceless civil servants who are so God-damned powerful at this stage that they are answerable to nobody, not even to the Houses of the Oireachtas?  To compel a Secretary General to come before an Oireachtas committee, you need the Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight of both Houses to agree.  That is way too cumbersome, as far as I am concerned.  This is an outrage.  I understand that the tender will be going out today.  That tender will be going out in contempt of this House, of the Lower House and of the Oireachtas joint committee.  That is simply not good enough.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#J00700"><p>I will speak today about a very positive day that we had in Limerick on Monday.  The Minister of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Harris, and the Minister of State, Deputy Niall Collins, visited Limerick.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell will be interested to know that Limerick College of Further Education made an announcement on the purchase of three buildings for a digital and media hub.  That is most fitting, given their expansion by working with the likes of Troy Studios.  Limerick is now becoming one of the biggest areas for film studios in the country.</p> <p>We also learned about the retrofitting programme through the Limerick and Clare Education and Training Board, LCETB.  There we met many trainees and apprentices who are almost ready to go out and work in the workplace on the retrofitting programme.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.51" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#J00900"><p>Senator Craughwell knows the rules of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#J01000"><p>The other visits we had was to Technological University of the Shannon: Midlands Midwest, TUS, and with the apprenticeship programme for the Coonagh campus.  There is the expansion of the apprenticeship programme, where 800 places will be offered to apprentices from next year, once the building is complete.  Monday was a very welcome day.  We also had a visit to the University of Limerick.  It was a very productive day for education and for training.  That is important to note.  The more positive days and the more collaboration we see between education and industry, the better.</p> <p>Finally, I visited members of the Ronald McDonald House in Buswells Hotel today.  I pay compliment to them for the wonderful work that they do with families.  I would encourage anyone who has not been there to go and visit them.  They had three asks.  The first of these was to advocate on their behalf, the second was to follow and support Ronald McDonald House Charities Ireland on social media and the third was to help them to share the story of the new 52-bedroom house, which will be at the new children&rsquo;s hospital when it is built.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->At the moment, they have only 25 rooms.  Doubling that number is to be commended.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#K00200"><p>I would like the Ministers for Finance and Agriculture, Food and the Marine to come to the House for a debate about what Ireland is doing to prepare for a possible recession.  Economists have for months now been warning of the prospect of a recession in late 2022, an assertion echoed earlier this month by the UK's National Institute for Economic and Social Research.  The chief executive of Citigroup, one of the world's largest banks, said on Monday that she believes Europe is sliding into recession as it grapples with the consequences of war in Ukraine and a resulting spike in energy prices.</p> <p>Headline inflation in the eurozone hit an all-time high of 7.4% in April, even by measures which account for volatile food and energy prices, which still point to inflation far exceeding the ECB's 2% target.  We do not need to be reminded of the role that is played in the global financial markets by the economy of the United States.  Much will depend in coming months on how the US Federal Reserve conducts its rate-hiking strategy as inflation soars even higher.  Wall Street has been voicing its concerns for months.  Since the 1940s, every time inflation has exceeded 5%, a recession has soon followed.</p> <p>There are, of course, things in life which matter more than money.  At a material level, money often buys us the essentials of clothes, food and shelter.  Shortages in those materials are more immediately noticeable than percentage point downturns in GDP.  While many a debate has been had in this House on our shortage of shelter, food could be worth keeping an eye on.</p> <p>The economic forum in Davos, Switzerland, heard on Monday that the anxiety about access to food at a reasonable price globally is hitting the roof.  We were warned of the spectre of global food shortages in the coming months.  The UN estimates that in the past year, global food prices have risen by almost one third, fertiliser by more than half and oil prices by almost two thirds.  Globally, more than 500,000 people are experiencing famine conditions, an increase of more than 500% since 2016.</p> <p>Today's Ireland is highly interconnected and heavily interdependent.  No longer does each household have a potato or cabbage patch.  The supermarket shelves are the sole source of food for most of our population.  A discussion on national food security could reveal some steps we should be taking.  We need regular updates from both Ministers on these pressing matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#K00300"><p>I pay tribute to the Cathaoirleach on the success of yesterday when Congressman Richie Neal shared his words with this House.</p> <p>I support the call of Senator Craughwell for the Representative Association of Commissioned Officers, RACO, to be included in the pay talks.  It is extraordinary that we made a decision about PDFORRA but did not include RACO in that reimagining.  I hope we can change that and that RACO can be included in those pay talks.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne referenced the issue of Ronald McDonald House, which briefed us interestingly and informatively this morning.  Those of us who have been in the existing Ronald McDonald House and have seen the benefits of the support, love and infrastructure, and the warmth of the people there, should be prompted to support the new facility in the national children's hospital.  "The house love will build" is the name of the campaign.  It is about ensuring that the families of young children receive support away from home.  That is a cause we should all support.</p> <p>The Cathaoirleach might not have heard me at the beginning of my contribution.  I compliment and congratulate him on yesterday, which was a positive day for relations between Ireland and America and, more importantly, between friends.  I hope we can build on that.</p> <p>I welcome to the Gallery the boys and girls I had the pleasure of meeting on my way to the Chamber.  I nearly bumped them out of the way.  I apologise because I did not get much time to say hello, but they are welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#K00400"><p>I thank the Senator for his kind words about Congressman Neal's address yesterday.</p> <p>I also welcome the boys and girls of sixth class at St. Sinneach's National School in Colehill, Longford, whose local Senator is Senator Carrigy.  I welcome the principal and the sixth class teacher, Ms Lavelle.  I am told that Senator Carrigy's wife, &Uacute;na, teaches in the school so our guests will have to be on their best behaviour.  We will pass a resolution so the students all get off homework whenever they want.</p> <p>I also welcome the students and teachers from Gaelscoil an Chuilinn in Tyrrelstown in Dublin.  I am delighted they were able to come to Seanad &Eacute;ireann and see democracy in action.  I thank them for being with us here today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#K00500"><p>I almost knocked down one or two of our guests when I was racing to the Chamber too but they kindly left me a gap.  I welcome the kids from Longford and acknowledge their local Senator and the work he does for education in this House.</p> <p>It is timely because my question relates to my own primary school in Grange.  I would like a debate with the Minister for Education.  Schools around the country have been lucky in terms of the funding available for extensions and the building of new primary and secondary schools.  We in Grange made a successful application to the Department of Education.  However, because of rising costs, the expense involved in the application have increased.  The school went back to the Department of Education with a small increase and have been waiting some time for a decision to be made.  By the time the decision has been made, costs will have risen again.  The principal, Marie Keating, along with the board of management, has done phenomenal work.  The teachers are phenomenal in the work they do and the commitment they give.  This is an important extension for the school in Grange.  I ask the Minister to speed up that process in any way possible.  I know there are schools across the country that need funding but it is important that it is done as quickly as possible.  It would be timely to have a debate with the Minister for Education on that subject anyway.</p> <p>I have asked in the past for a debate with the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Humphreys, about all the schemes she gives to rural areas across the country, including my county of Tipperary.  Those schemes include CL&Aacute;R and the town and village renewal scheme.  Those schemes serve an important purpose for areas such as mine in Tipperary.  To give one example, the village of Drangan in Tipperary has put forward a CL&Aacute;R application to do up bits of the playground and to resurface the road.  It is an important application.  My colleague, Councillor Mark Fitzgerald, has been working hard on this issue.  People in the community, such as Ailish O'Brien and others, have done an awful lot of work on this application.  It is important to get decisions made as quickly as possible on those applications.  We are lucky that we are able to fund so many of these kinds of playgrounds and community projects but we need decisions to be made as quickly as we can to get those projects over the line.  That was a very good playground and it needs to have work done to fix equipment and things like that.  I would be very grateful if we could get a decision as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#K00600"><p>I, too, welcome the representatives of St. Sinneach's National School.  I welcome the principal, Ms Glynn, sixth class teacher, Ms Lavelle, and all the students to the House.  I hope they enjoy their trip to Dublin.  I concur with the Cathaoirleach's comments that there is a homework pass for this evening and perhaps for the rest of the week.  It is a fantastic school in south Longford.  Senator Ahearn mentioned the CL&Aacute;R scheme.  I know St. Sinneach's was successful in getting a grant last year through that scheme.  Those schemes are invaluable throughout the county.  I have been involved in a CL&Aacute;R application this year on behalf of a neighbouring school in south Longford, Lenamore National School, which I hope is prioritised.  It has applied for funding to provide a sensory area for kids with needs.  There are a significant number of kids with those needs in many schools throughout the county.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MichealCarrigy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I hope the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Humphreys, will look favourably on the application.</p><p>I concur with the comments made by Senator Buttimer and I apologise to him as I was giving someone details while he was speaking.  I pay tribute to the Cathaoirleach for inviting Congressman Neal here yesterday.  It was a fantastic day for this House.  The United States of America has made a massive contribution to the Good Friday Agreement and, ultimately, peace in this country.  It was an honour for me to be here when Congressman Neal spoke and to be in the presence of other members of his committee.</p><p>I pay tribute to the Cathaoirleach on the work he has done for Irish-American relations.  It is extremely important that we create links, which he spoke about, with, say, local authorities and state legislators throughout the US to make sure Ireland is always at the top of the agenda in America because many people in the House of Representatives and Senate have strong Irish-American links.  If we do not maintain those links, they will weaken over time.  We see how important those links are every St. Patrick's Day.  Ireland is one of very few countries that gets the opportunity to meet the US President and we want that to continue.  I pay tribute to the Cathaoirleach for the work that he has done, and continues to do, to foster links.  I look forward to working with him to create links with my own county of Longford and, in particular, I wish to mention state of Maryland as it has very strong links to County Longford.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#L00200"><p>I thank the Senator for his contribution and kind words.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#L00300"><p>I welcome the school groups, in particular the group from County Longford.  I know Senator Carrigy's wife, &Uacute;na.  The latter group has a link to Ballinasloe as &Uacute;na Boland is from the town of Ballinasloe.  We must give all of the children a big wave because we need them to come here.  They will be here in a few years' time.  Do they know that women only make up 40% of Senators?  We need a few more girls to join us.  What do the girls think?  Can I have a thumbs up?  Yes.</p> <p>I invite everybody to Ballinasloe because the Heritage Boat Association is hosting an event to showcase barges, including a barge that dates back to 1847.  Many barges will come from Dublin and Kildare.  The River Suck branch of the Inland Waterways Association of Ireland is newly established in Ballinasloe.  I wish to thank the IWAI branches in Kildare and Athlone for donating money and gifts to help the new branch get started.  As a member of the new branch, I can say we need new members and I encourage everyone to join.  The event will be a special occasion because the marina in Ballinasloe is a wonderful amenity.  The River Suck is the largest tributary of the River Shannon so people can rent a boat at Athlone, Shannonbridge or Banagher and sail to Ballinasloe.  If people come to Ballinasloe this weekend, they will see numerous barges or really long boats.</p> <p>On Saturday, 28 May, the fleet of boats will arrive in Ballinasloe between 2 p.m. and 4 p.m.  The barges will transport barrels and kegs just like in the past along the Grand Canal into Ballinasloe.  They will transport kegs of very nice stuff that children, unfortunately, cannot have yet.  On Saturday, 4 June, as part of the Cruinni&uacute; na n&Oacute;g national events, there will be children's celebrations and family activities between 2 p.m. and 6 p.m.  Of course children are very welcome to come along to that event and perhaps their muinteoir, Ms Boland or Carrigy, might bring the schoolchildren to Ballinasloe for that day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#L00400"><p>Unfortunately, Galway County Council has reached the bottom of the league in terms of State funding <i>per capita</i>in terms of county council funding.  I am not surprised because Galway County Council has been one of the most under-funded councils for a number of years.  Unfortunately, it is official that Galway County Council has reached the bottom of the table.  Galway County Council was second last for a number of years but Meath County Council has now overtaken us but is still in the relegation zone.</p><p>Galway County Council is way behind comparable counties of the same size such as Mayo, Donegal, Tipperary and Kerry.  This situation has been known for some time and the Department officials have been very aware of same.  Many promises have been made at Department and ministerial levels to rectify the situation, yet we still await a solution.  We are being fobbed off with the excuse that a review of the local property tax is taking place.  While recognising the situation in Galway and providing a certain amount of additional funding through the former Minister of State at the Department, Deputy John Paul Phelan, the current Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, and the current Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, the situation has not improved and it is increasingly difficult to get budgets passed.  I call for a debate on local authority funding to be arranged because we need to find solutions for counties like Galway which have huge ambitions in terms of the delivery of services by local authorities, and there is a huge demand for services by residents.  For years it was debated whether the local authority would be amalgamated with Galway City Council.  Whether right or wrong, the option to amalgamate is off the table.  We still need to arrange a stable level of funding for Galway County Council to enable it deliver services that the residents, taxpayers and local property tax payers in the county deserve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#L00500"><p>I agree with the comments Senator Kyne made about securing funding for Galway County Council.  I am well aware of the efforts the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, and the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, have made to solve this situation but we need a general debate in this House.</p> <p>Today, I want to concentrate on the N5 route from Strokestown to Ballaghaderreen that, unfortunately, has seen huge loss of life over the years.  As a result of the war in Ukraine, the roads contract has fallen through due to the fact Roadbridge is no longer functioning.  I am confident, having met the Taoiseach and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Michael McGrath, that the project will be up and running.  However, in the meantime, there are huge concerns about safety in the town of Strokestown, on the outskirts of Tulsk village and in Ballinagar.  I understand Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, may do something about part of the route at Frenchpark after many politicians made representations over many years.  People are really worried about safety on these roads.  I ask the Acting Leader to ask the Leader to contact the Minister for Transport and arrange a debate so we can discuss the route, particularly the fact that the present contract has been held up due to the worsening situation in Ukraine.  I reiterate the case for inviting the Minister to attend a debate in this House to discuss many roads issues, particularly issues with the N5 route.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#L00600"><p>Earlier I tabled a Commencement matter in respect of Ukraine and the mutual recognition of professional qualifications.  There are many other things we need to do at a legislative level to support Ukraine.  I refer to Resolution 2436 of the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe and to a number of points it made about actions that can be taken to support Ukraine at a legislative level.  For example, the first is legislating for the crime of aggression, something that is recognised now in the European Convention on Human Rights through the Kampala amendments, to which Ireland signed up in 2019.  There is an avenue there for us to talk about what is happening there, with the blockading of ports being the most simple one.  The bombing and invasion have been recognised pursuant to the Kampala amendments.  That is something we could do.  Other measures include the creation of a universal civil jurisdiction that would allow us to say that we know there are Russian assets, not just Russian state assets in Ireland but personal assets of people who are and are not the subject of sanctions.  A universal civil jurisdiction would allow us to start to seize those assets and put them towards the reconstruction of Ukraine or provide Ukraine with assistance rather than allow a situation to continue where assets are merely frozen here by actions of the Government.</p> <p>We now have a window in which we can take action against Russia.  Yes, Russia has been excluded from the Council of Europe but until 16 September we have a small window within which we can take an action against Russia in the European Court of Human Rights for breaching the European Convention on Human Rights.  Ireland should step up to the plate and make sure that we take this action.</p> <p>Finally, I welcome the fact the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, put forward &euro;4 million towards the International Criminal Court to help in the prosecution of war crimes that have been committed.  Some &euro;1 million has been delivered but I wonder if better use can be made of the remaining &euro;3 million.  Can that sum be directed specifically to the Prosecutor-General in Ukraine?  I have met her staff in Ukraine and they are very together.  As Members will know, this week they have achieved a conviction or a guilty plea in respect of one tank commander.  I think the remaining &euro;3 million might be better directed at the people on the ground who are doing this work.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As counsel before the International Criminal Court, I have nothing but praise for it but it takes time and it seems that it could be more effectively directed on the ground in Ukraine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#M00300"><p>I find myself in the unusual position that I am directing my response only to the Government side of the House.  Senator Chambers opened proceedings and spoke of the anniversary of repeal.  It is hard to believe that it is four years since we had the referendum on repeal.  She noted that it actually started 35 years ago.  We as legislators need to ensure that the will of people around equality of access is upheld and we need to ensure that there are safe access zones and that legislation is brought in.  Senator Boylan also addressed that issue.  I was pleased to stand with other Members of the Oireachtas at the Kildare Street gates to commemorate that day.</p><p>Senator Chambers also raised the mass shooting in the US.  We were all shocked last night and this morning to hear the testimony as it broke on our newspapers, radio and television about 19 children and two teachers.  It is just shocking.  That is the 27th shooting there this year.  On behalf of the House I wish to express all our condolences to the families, teachers and the communities and the people of America.  Some of responses from public representatives were abhorrent.  They said that guns were not the problem.  It was people that were the problem and we should teach teachers to use guns.  They said there should be armed police at schools rather than dealing with the whole area of guns and the fact that a young man could walk in on his 18th birthday and buy two guns, shoot his grandmother and then go on to the school.  </p><p>One of my brothers was in Texas for work last week.  He sent a photograph to the family WhatsApp after he walked into a shop and saw guns for sale because he was shocked.  Little did I think we would see something like this happen in Texas a little over a week later.  We have to do everything we can to condemn the attack and stand in solidarity with the devastated community in Texas.  We are lucky that we have very stringent controls on firearm certificates and conditions here and that is how it should be.</p><p>Senators Boyhan, Buttimer and Malcolm Byrne spoke about Congressman Richard Neal's visit here and what a historic day is was in Leinster House.  It is the one day that I was jealous that I was not here.  I was abroad on Council of Europe business.  From everything I saw and heard it really was a very significant day so I add my congratulations.  I believe that Miriam Lord covered it very well in her piece.  I did not read it but I heard something about it on the radio.  It is really important that we do everything we can to commemorate and celebrate those connections.</p><p>Senator Boyhan also raised the issue of An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  There are issues that are <i>sub judice</i>but he is correct in saying that people need to have confidence in the whole system.  We should certainly look for the publication of the Mulcahy report.  It is five years since its completion.  Money and time are spent on reports.  They must then be published and debated and we must look at the recommendations.  I agree that we need a debate on planning.  I would like to include in that the matter of unauthorised developments and how our planning laws deal with them because we need to do far more.  I raised that here two weeks ago.  We will certainly look for that debate.</p><p>Senator Boylan spoke about the jury selection for the Stardust inquest.  She referred to the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, having made a commitment that she would bring forward legislative proposals to ensure that the jury would commence.  That is important and we will write to the Minister on that issue.  </p><p>Senator Wall raised Naas General Hospital and the &quot;RT&Eacute; Investigates&quot; programme about sexual misconduct by doctors there.  He spoke of garda&iacute; carrying out the investigation.  We listened to the testimony of &quot;Ryan&quot;, which is not his real name.  I was struck by his bravery and integrity in talking about what he went through.  We must be very mindful of the anguish he has suffered as a result.  We do need to have a debate on patient safety and the procedures in place because part of Ryan's story was what happened when he did speak to other hospital staff.  We are very conscious of how overworked hospital staff are but we need to have proper procedures in place and to ensure they are followed.</p><p>Senator Wall also raised the welcome news yesterday for PDFORRA as did Senators Byrne, Craughwell and Buttimer.  I agree that RACO should be included but to be fair, PDFORRA started this campaign a long time before RACO joined the debate.  I want to compliment Ger Guinan and Mark Keane.  They have done excellent work in a very respectful way.  Many of us would have had meetings with them over the years.  It is high time this happened and it is really important.  I want to compliment them in particular for their sustained campaign and I add my voice to those calling for RACO to be involved.</p><p>Senator Black spoke of the shocking scenes at the funeral of the Palestinian journalist Shireen Abu Akleh and how Israel has refused access to MEPs.  I think that is wrong.  They should be allowed in.  The Seanad should ask the Minister for Foreign Affairs to write to the Israeli ambassador.  Diplomatic relations are important, as Senator Black said, but there are areas where we must take a stand.  This is one.</p><p>Senator Malcolm Byrne also spoke about the leak of police files about the Uyghur community in China and the systemic abuse and genocide being carried out there.  He is correct that sometimes when things like Russia's war against Ukraine happen we can lose sight of other human rights abuses happening around the world.  We just cannot do so.  What is happening to the Uyghur community is absolutely shocking.  We will write to the Minister for Foreign Affairs to share our shock about the abhorrent human rights abuse by China against the Uyghur community.</p><p>Senator Lombard spoke about car rental for tourists.  He mentioned how he got a quote of &euro;1,800 for ten days.  Coincidentally, I spoke to an official coming here next week for a Council of Europe meeting where representatives from 48 countries will come to Dublin.  He has a connection with Ireland and he wanted to hire a car for four days.  He was having a problem finding a hotel for two days.  I had recommended hotels in Kildare to him previously.  He was quoted &euro;1,500 for four days.  For that he could have bought a car, sold it on and made a profit.  Now he is not renting a car and is staying with a friend rather than staying in a hotel outside Dublin.  It is shocking.</p><p>One reason for this situation, and I do not know why, is that the car rental fleet is 40% of what it was in 2019.  Why?  Is it because the price of second-hand cars has gone up?  I really do not know.  It must be investigated, I completely agree, because it is important that Ireland has a reputation for value for money.  For the first time in three years we are able to open our country and our world-renowned hospitality to people.  We want to ensure that they have easy access to accommodation and car hire and not at exorbitant prices.  We cannot have our tourism undermined.  We should look for a debate with the Minister on that issue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Craughwell also raised the matter of the tender process and said the Secretary General had refused to meet the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence.  He also spoke about the Air Corps being slighted.  We will certainly write to the Minister regarding that and will request the Secretary General attends the committee.<br/><br/>Senator Maria Byrne spoke about Limerick College of Further Education, UL and the expansion of courses there around film apprenticeships and retrofitting, in addition to Ronald McDonald House.  Senator Buttimer also attended the presentation this morning.  The fact a new 52-bedroom house for families has been opened is phenomenal.  The emotional and financial stress on families when they have a very sick child is huge on so many levels.  It is wonderful to see the extra supports that are being given.<br/><br/>Senator Keogan raised the spectre of inflation and the issue of access to food and food security that is being discussed in Davos.  While she is correct that for far too long a lot of food in this country has been sold below cost, which has caused a major problem for producers, we should also be doing everything we can to encourage allotments and community gardens for people to grow their own food where they can.  Maybe we could look for a debate with the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine on that.<br/><br/>Senator Ahearn spoke about the primary school in Grange, Tipperary, and rising costs.  My understanding is the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform made an announcement about two weeks ago that due to inflation the Department will step in, rightly so, on capital grants.  Following that, I received a number of phone calls, as I am sure Senator Ahearn and many Members did, to see if the sports capital grants could be included in that.  I contacted the Minister's office and, while they will not be included, it is looking at doing something.  I agree that when extensions are needed, they are needed immediately, generally speaking, because we are playing catch-up all the time in this regard.  The Senator asked for a debate with the Minister for Rural and Community Development on CL&Aacute;R schemes.  Tipperary is very lucky to get CL&Aacute;R; I wish Kildare could.  It is important to have clarity on timelines relating to decisions and when funding can come through.<br/><br/>While welcoming the visitors in the Gallery from Longford, Senator Carrigy spoke about the importance of the Irish influence in American politics.  I remember a book I read by Conor O'Clery, <i>The Greening of the White House</i>, which was an excellent book on the influence Ireland brought to bear on the White House.  In that context, it is important to mention Ms Trina Vargo, who was foreign affairs adviser to the late Senator Ted Kennedy.  She set up the US-Ireland Alliance based on that premise because the late Senator Kennedy felt there would be a time when Ireland would not have the influence it has and he wanted to ensure young people on campuses across America would have the opportunity to learn about and understand Ireland, with the hope they would one day be influential in their own country and in politics.<br/><br/>Senator Kyne spoke about Galway being bottom of the league for <i>per capita</i>council funding and looked for a debate on local authority funding.  We need that debate and I will certainly write to both Ministers involved in that.  That is where key funding is needed in all our county and city councils throughout the country.  We need a sustainable level of funding for all our local authorities to be able to carry out the very important and significant work they do.  We should look for that debate and for accountability and transparency in funding.  I have often heard from executives in Kildare County Council that it is one local authority but has two D&aacute;il constituencies, and it certainly does not get enough funding either.  I agree with that.<br/><br/>Senator Murphy asked for a debate on the N5 route from Strokestown to Ballaghaderreen and spoke about the major safety concerns that are there.  Road safety is absolutely an issue but he has spoken to the Minister and the Taoiseach specifically on the N5 issue and the Senator believes the project will be back on track.  Maybe it is worthy of a Commencement debate also.<br/><br/>Senator Ward spoke about mutual recognition of qualifications from Ukraine.  I completely agree.  There was a Commencement debate in the House last week, during which this matter was asked about in respect of pharmacists, for example.  Pharmacists will say otherwise, but I have no doubt there is a shortage of pharmacists in this country.  Ukraine is not one of those countries that is allowed a fast-track into pharmacy here and I believe it should be.  I agree with the Senator that we should certainly look at that mutual recognition.  He also addressed the avenue through the Council of Europe declaration in respect of how we can support Ukrainians and that small window where we could look at Russian assets that are in Ireland, and the possibility of seizing them and using them to finance for the reconstruction of Ukraine.  His final suggestion related to the &euro;4 million given to the International Criminal Court by Ireland and the suggestion the remaining &euro;3 million might be of better use on the ground.  I do not disagree.  We certainly will write to the Minister and make that suggestion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#N00200"><p>I welcome to the Visitors Gallery Senator Malcolm Byrne's brother, Ronan.  He and his partner Amanda are most welcome.  We are delighted to have them here.  As he knows, his brother works very hard on behalf of all the people who elected him in addition to the people of Wexford.  We are delighted he is making such a valuable contribution, but Ronan can tell us all the other stories later when we meet him outside.  Is the Order of Business agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#N00300"><p>Ask the Opposition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#N00400"><p>It is agreed on this side of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 12.37 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 12.45 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 12.37 p.m. and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.74" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#O00100">Protected Disclosures (Amendment) Bill 2022: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.75" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#O00300"><p>I am pleased to present the Bill to the House.  This Bill provides for significant enhancements to the statutory framework for the protection of whistleblowers in Ireland.  It updates the Protected Disclosures Act 2014 to provide for the transposition of the EU whistleblowing directive into Irish law, the establishment of a new office of the protected disclosures commissioner and to strengthen and clarify a number of areas of the 2014 Act where issues have arisen since enactment.</p> <p>There can be no dispute about the importance of providing robust statutory protections for whistleblowers.  Freedom of speech, including the freedom to speak up about wrongdoing without fear of retaliation, is the one of the cornerstones of an open, fair and democratic society.  We are all aware of a whole range of matters of vital public interest that would not have come to light were it not for the bravery of those who spoke up.  Sadly, there are still too many instances where raising a concern has come at a great personal cost to whistleblowers and their families.  This Bill represents a big step in the right direction in this regard.</p> <p>The Protected Disclosures Act was innovative legislation for its time.  When it was enacted in 2014, Ireland was only the sixth country in the EU to introduce comprehensive legislation for the protection of whistleblowers.  The Act remains highly regarded internationally as one of the strongest laws of its type in the world.  Many of the provisions of the EU directive are in place in Ireland courtesy of the 2014 Act.  The Act provides for multiple channels to report wrongdoing so that if one channel fails for any reason, there are other options for workers to speak up in safety.  The Act also prohibits any form of retaliation against a worker who makes a protected disclosure and provides protection from any civil or criminal liability for any disclosure of confidential information necessary to report a wrongdoing.</p> <p>The directive goes a number of steps further, however.  It significantly widens the scope of persons entitled to protection for speaking up.  It requires medium and large enterprises to establish formal internal reporting channels for their employees.  It sets out very clear steps that must be taken within clear timelines in respect of following up on all reports that are made.  All of these changes are to be welcomed as they will further strengthen our legislation and ensure that Ireland remains a leading country in terms of the legal protections we provide to whistleblowers.</p> <p>The publication of the initial proposals for the EU directive coincided with the statutory review of the 2014 Act, which was published in 2018.  A decision was taken at that time that any recommendations for legislative change would be addressed during the transposition of the directive and this is what we are doing.  Development of the legislation has also been informed by the public consultation on the transposition held in the summer of 2020.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The statutory review found that the 2014 Act was broadly operating as intended but a number of implementation issues were identified.  A key finding was the need for clearer direction for recipients as to what to do with the reports they receive.  The new requirements in this regard, arising from the directive, go a long way towards addressing this.</p><p>The statutory review also raised significant concerns about how disclosures made to Ministers under section 8 of the Act should be handled.  The Bill proposes a number of changes to the operation of the ministerial channel to address these issues, and the concerns raised in the third interim report of the disclosures tribunal.  Key to this is a proposal in the Bill to establish a new office of the protected disclosures commissioner who will, among other things, take on responsibility for directing reports to the most appropriate persons to address the matter concerned.  This will ensure an independent and thorough follow-up of all disclosures made to Ministers.  The commissioner will also take on the role of a prescribed person of last resort, ensuring there is always an independent external person for workers to report to, if needed.  This role will be taken on by the Ombudsman. This is in line with trends in other jurisdictions where national ombudsmen have been given similar responsibilities in this area.</p><p>The general scheme of the Bill was published May 2021 and the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach, published its pre-legislative scrutiny report in December 2021.  The committee, which includes a number of Members from this House, clearly put a significant amount of time and effort into hearing submissions from witnesses and into preparing the report.</p><p>The pre-legislative scrutiny process has proved very valuable in bringing all parties together in supporting the development of the Bill.  This will be a model for how the pre-legislative scrutiny process adds value to the legislative process.  I commend all members of the committee in this regard.</p><p>The Bill was published in February 2022, and it took on board many of the recommendations in the pre-legislative scrutiny report.  On Committee Stage in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, a number of amendments to the Bill were made to implement a number of outstanding recommendations from the pre-legislative scrutiny report.  These included: a provision allowing persons who made protected disclosures prior to the coming into force of this legislation to request and obtain feedback on the actions taken or envisaged to be taken on foot of their disclosures; a provision allowing reporting persons to request and obtain further feedback at three-month intervals, in addition to the initial feedback required under the directive; an amendment to the conditions for reporting to a prescribed person under section 7 of the principal Act to ensure no conflict with a non-regression clause in Article 25.2 of the directive; a provision requiring that when a prescribed person or the protected disclosures commissioner needs to transmit a report to another prescribed person for action, that this be done in a secure manner and in accordance with data protection law; a provision requiring that a statutory review of the legislation be carried out five years after enactment; and a provision for the protected disclosures commissioner to make an annual report on the operation of the legislation.  All of these amendments arose from the recommendations in the pre-legislative scrutiny report, or from suggestions made when the Bill was debated in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.</p><p>I will now turn and main provisions of the Bill.  As this is amending legislation, some sections need to be read in conjunction with the principal Act, which is the Protected Disclosures Act 2014.  Some sections of the Bill are also quite technical, and in this regard I will make my officials available to any Member if any further technical briefing on this Bill is required.</p><p>I will outline the Parts of the Bill.  Part 1, comprising sections 1 to 3, inclusive, contains a number of standard legislative provisions concerning the Short Title and commencement and, as amending legislation, identifies the Protected Disclosures Act 2014 as being the principal Act being amended.</p><p>Part 2 comprises six chapters, each of which in some way amend or extend the principal Act.  Chapter 1, comprising sections 4 to 7, inclusive, sets out the scope of application of the legislation.  Of particular note in section 4 is the amended definition of "worker", which provides for the expansion of the scope of the Act to include volunteers, board members, shareholders and job applicants, as these are required by the directive.</p><p>Section 5 is a standard provision concerning the making of orders and regulations under the Act.  Section 6 amends the definition of a "protected disclosure" to explicitly cover any breaches of the EU laws specified in the directive and for the insertion of a new section 5A into the Act, which provides that the Act does not apply to personal employment grievances, in order to address last December's ruling of the Supreme Court in the Baranya case.</p><p>Section 7 provides that persons who make anonymous disclosures are still entitled to the protections of the Act if their identity is deduced and if they suffer retaliation.</p><p>Chapter 2, comprising sections 8 to 13, inclusive, concerns the design and operation of internal and external reporting channels to employers and prescribed persons.  Section 8 provides that private sector entities with 50 or more employees must establish formal whistleblowing channels.  A derogation until December 2023 is provided for medium-sized enterprises with between 50 and 249 employees.  This section also provides that the Minister can lower this threshold in certain sectors where there is a high risk of serious wrongdoing, if required.</p><p>Section 9 sets out how the internal channels should operate and requires that all reports be acknowledged within seven days, the manner in which reports should be followed up, and that feedback be given to the reporting person within three months.  These rules are at the core of the directive and, therefore, are restated and reaffirmed throughout the Bill.</p><p>Section 10 similarly requires prescribed persons to establish reporting channels for workers in the sectors they regulate and section 11 provides, again, that prescribed persons must acknowledge, follow up and give feedback to reporting persons in respect of the reports they receive.</p><p>Section 12 concerns reports made to Ministers of the Government and sets out new conditions for making these reports.  It requires that Ministers shall transmit all reports they receive to the new protected disclosures commissioner.</p><p>Section 13 amends section 10 of the principal Act and sets out new conditions for the making of public disclosures.  These conditions are significantly simplified compared with the original provision in the principal Act.</p><p>Chapter 3 concerns the office of the protected disclosures commissioner and comprises sections 14 and 15, inclusive.  Section 14 inserts six new sections, sections 10A to 10F, inclusive, into the Act after section 10.  Section 10A provides for the establishment of the new office of the protected disclosures commissioner in the Office of the Ombudsman.  Section 10B provides for the commissioner to have formal channels and procedures for handling disclosures in the same manner as apply to prescribed persons.</p><p>I can continue or come back in later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#P00200"><p>The Minister of State will have another opportunity to come back in again later, if he would not mind.  We will take some Senators now, as I am conscious of time.  The Minister of State will have time at the end to complete his statement and he might want to hear the questions now.  Is the Minister of State happy with that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#P00300"><p>That is absolutely fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#P00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House.  I welcome his work on the Bill.  It is great to see the legislation updated.  It has been there since 2014.  The Bill is very important.  Of late, we have lots of experience of whistleblowers, what they can and cannot do, and how their lives are destroyed.  Sergeant McCabe, of course, comes to mind, as well as others.  I really welcome the Minister of State's work on the Bill.  It is very important.  We have seen the huge importance that protected disclosures legislation has had in Irish life since it was introduced.  We think of all the big cases but it is also important to remember that hundreds of disclosures about issues big and small have been made in the years since the legislation was enacted.  The improvements and protections in this amending Bill are hugely welcome and would have made a huge difference to people in the past, including Sergeant McCabe, if we had had them sooner.  It is great that the Minister of State is the one who saw the need to do this and has improved it vastly.  It was badly needed.</p> <p>Just last week I met Ms Mary Lawlor, the UN special rapporteur for human rights defenders - I am an ambassador with Front Line Defenders - and she raised a few interesting issues.  An element in this Bill might be very good for what she was looking for.  One provision of the Bill extends the scope to volunteers, unpaid trainees, board members, shareholders and job applicants, none of whom had any protections before.  This is a huge one.  Front-line defenders are, in most cases, volunteers and it is very important that we have included them.  As a person who has volunteered a lot, I am aware that there are often no protections for volunteers in this regard.  It is very important that the Minister of State has included this.</p> <p>Cases have been documented around the world by Irish companies.  In one example, Moneypoint power station changed a supplier as a result of a complaint made about it accessing coal from the Cerrej&oacute;n mine in Colombia.  That mine was absolute carnage when it came to human rights abuses.  Thanks to the legislation, the ESB is not getting coal from there now.  Unfortunately, it is still getting coal, and we are working on that as well, but at least it is no longer from the most inhumane coal mine in the world.  It just shows the importance of this type of legislation.</p> <p>Thankfully, the EU has been looking at this and has released a draft directive on due diligence, about which I have also been having meetings.  It is looking at the supply chain, ethics, and human rights abuses on the supply chain.</p> <p>Will the Minister of State indicate if there is anything we can do to strengthen provisions in our national legislation with regard to whistleblowing that could help people to draw attention to abuses in the supply chain by Irish companies?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RoisinGarvey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is just something to think about taking further.  We import goods from companies that have very questionable human rights and pay standards.  I will not mention any in particular - or I might.  Fair trade was one thing, but now we also have images of sweatshops, child labour and so on.  We have not yet gone far enough in Ireland to look at that and at what we allow in.  I know that the Minister of State is doing lots of good work on the circular economy, carbon emissions and much tighter procurement, but we have to look at the ethics around procurement and what we import as well.  If we have this really good legislation here in Ireland, we should demand the same of Irish companies working abroad.  I will give the House two examples.  There is the case of Smurfit Kappa.  It has scored zero on Trinity Business School's human rights due diligence indicators.  That is worrying because we expect Irish companies to have the highest standards not just in Ireland but everywhere else as all humans are equal, so it is important we look at that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#Q00200"><p>We should not name individual companies-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#Q00300"><p>Sorry.  I withdraw that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#Q00400"><p>It is a matter of due process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#Q00500"><p>I am just wondering how the law can support us in making sure that our companies when they go abroad have the same respect for human rights as other countries do.  This is not <i>Animal Farm</i>.  We are all equal.  If people are to be paid properly in Ireland, they should be paid properly in other countries as well.  We have to have proper standards in the workplace on pay, clean air etc.  We have to take care of the workers no matter where they are in the world.</p><p>This is outside the scope of the Bill, but I wish to put one case on the Seanad record.  It relates to an Irish citizen in Togo who has been in prison without trial for the past three and a half years.  I know that this does not fall under the Minister of State's remit, but it is important to highlight.  When I met with Mary Lawlor, the UN special rapporteur-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#Q00600"><p>Senator, will you stick to the Bill, please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#Q00700"><p>Yes.  This links into it, if you will just let me finish, Acting Chairperson.  Mary Lawlor is the UN special rapporteur on human rights defenders.  She highlighted to me the need to include human rights defenders as stakeholders in the EU directive.  I think this Bill will help us strengthen the EU directive.  As a country, since we have this strong improvement to the law around volunteers being protected, perhaps we could look at bringing that to EU level.  I will probably work with our MEPs on this as well.  This law will help us to bring the case to EU level to make sure that the directive is watertight in protecting people such as the front-line defenders, who are volunteers and who are now protected in the amendment the Government is bringing in.</p> <p>This is very relevant in some ways because we are talking about human rights.  We all know that if one puts one's head above the parapet, often one gets into trouble.  In Ireland we are very lucky in some ways because, as countries go and protest goes, it is a very safe place for freedom of speech, speaking out and calling out issues around employment and companies, whereas in other countries one sees people such as the girl in Togo who has been in jail for the past three and a half years.  She is an Irish citizen and nothing is happening.  There are no supports for her at all.  That would not happen in Ireland.  We can give out about this country all we want but it is a really safe place to be a protestor and to be a worker who stands up for one's rights, compared with other countries, where people get jailed just for asking questions.</p> <p>That is why this Bill is so important.  If we want to set the standards, as we are doing today with this legislation, improving Irish law to protect volunteers, including people such as front-line defenders, we could take that to the EU directive and maybe look at strengthening the wording of this directive to make it watertight for people.  As someone who has never been able to keep her mouth shut in calling out problems from a very young age, I feel the need to speak up for others who do so on much more serious cases.  The human rights abuses that go on in other countries are appalling, as we know.  We do not always think about it when we spend our money, unfortunately, but it is really good that we have this in place today.  I hope we can set the standards higher for the EU.  I am sorry for mentioning one Irish company, but I hope that all Irish companies, no matter where they are in the world, be it Russia, Colombia, Togo or South America - Irish companies are very successful - see all the humans they deal with as equals and treat them as we would want our own to be treated.  This legislation makes it such that everybody is treated well and their human rights are respected.  We should expect the same from every Irish company anywhere in the world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#Q00800"><p>The Minister of State is welcome to the House.  I thank him.  It would have been good to hear his presentation in full.  This is a very comprehensive piece of work.  Clearly, the Minister of State has engaged right across all sectors to try to bring forward the best possible legislation in this area.</p> <p>Protected disclosure is something that has bothered me quite considerably since I came into this House because I think there is a massive misconception out there as to what precisely protected disclosure is and how one should go about making a disclosure.  Members of this House and of the D&aacute;il constantly receive blanket emails from members of the public who have an issue with an employer, a public service or whatever else.  They always front up such submissions as protected disclosures.  They have contacted everybody in the world to tell them they are making a protected disclosure, thereby doing away with any chance of protecting their own good names.  Very frequently the issue that is raised with Members of the Oireachtas is not really conducive to protected disclosure.  I am delighted that the Government is putting a commissioner in place and that that will allow people who are uncertain as to how to go about making a disclosure to go through the office of the commissioner, who will then direct them to the correct place.</p> <p>My colleague, Senator Garvey, made reference to people on the front line and voluntary groups.  There is no doubt, from recent evidence that has come to Oireachtas joint committees and to Members of the Oireachtas individually, but that there is a desperate need within the voluntary sector for an avenue through which to pursue a protected disclosure where people believe their personal safety or the safety of their colleagues is at stake.</p> <p>Moreover, when it comes to improving organisations, all of us - none of us are immune from this - when we are in management positions in organisations sometimes believe that the protection of the organisation is more important than the protection of the individual worker.  I think that that is addressed in the Bill.  Workers will have an avenue to go down to make their disclosures and, because of the reporting mechanisms that have been built in, once a disclosure is made there is a feedback sequence that can be followed.  From that point of view, this will be really important.</p> <p>Section 16, which protects the individual's identity, is an excellent piece of work.  We have all come across situations that needed rectifying.  I have done so, particularly in my trade union background, in my teaching background and in industry before that.  Sadly, the tendency is to isolate the person who identifies the problem and to make him or her seem to be the demon rather than somebody who is trying to improve the workforce for everybody.  From that point of view, the Bill will go a long way, particularly with the use of the commissioner.</p> <p>Employers need a bit of education here.  Not everybody who makes a protected disclosure does so for malicious purposes.  Even as a trade unionist, I can appreciate that some people will be malicious in seeking to use this legislation in order to inflict some sort of pain on their employer.  Protections are needed for the employer or for named people, shall we say, such that the legislation is not used for malicious purposes.  In fairness, I think 99 out of 100 people would never do that, but the important thing is that we look at the person making the disclosure as having given an honest and fair disclosure and that it is up the employer to prove that that is wrong.  From that point of view, the Bill is really welcome.</p> <p>Alongside protected disclosures, and in the same general area, is bullying in the workplace.  One of the real problems for somebody making a disclosure is that he or she will be subjected to bullying in the workplace.  By its very nature, bullying in the workplace is a cowardly one-on-one act that most people are not aware of.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Most people will know that bullies have a street image and a private image, and in the private image they are horrible people who attack others, not personally but psychologically or mentally.  There are several instances of people who have taken their own lives as a result of bullying in the workplace.  It is something we have to examine in the context of protected disclosures because the release of a person's name can lead to that person being identified, even by colleagues.  Consider a situation where there is a safety issue and the safety issue has been brought to the management.  Everybody has been happy enough working with it, but there is one guy who insists that, for example, the safety rope is in place before the job starts or the like.  He can be seen to be a crank when, in fact, he is trying to protect everybody else.  There is an opportunity with this legislation to ensure that such information gets back.</p><p>I have three suggestions for the Minister of State.  One is that we educate employers with respect to their responsibilities for protected disclosures.  Having the legislation in place is one thing but to educate people as to how to process it is vital.  Second, we should educate the general public.  A member of the public should be able to make a protected disclosure against an organisation about a particular thing he or she observes without fear of reprisal of any sort.  Third, we must get into the public domain what is not a protected disclosure, more importantly, than what is a protected disclosure.  If we do that, we will go a long way.</p><p>I compliment the Minister of State for bringing this legislation forward and I am grateful to him for his decision to make his officials available as this Bill goes through the House.  If there are issues that we wish to query or on which we want to have more information, his officials will be available to us.  I hope the Bill passes through the House smoothly and that we get it implemented as quickly as possible.  I thank the Minister of State for his time today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#R00200"><p>I welcome our guests from Ardgillan Community College in Balbriggan to the House.  I hope they enjoy their day and I am delighted they are listening to our exchange on this legislation.  I thank them for coming.</p> <p>To clarify for Members, we are governed by the Order of Business which was agreed by the House this morning.  It sets out the speaking roster and the times.  It was clearly indicated that the Minister of State would have ten minutes, but he will have more than ten minutes to wrap up.  That is what the Members agreed to on the Order of Business in respect of this legislation going through the House today.  I am in their hands; it is not my decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#R00300"><p>On a point of order, in future when we are setting out times on the Order of Business for a legislative measure as large as this the Minister needs more time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#R00400"><p>That is a matter for you on the Order of Business.  I call Senator Wilson.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#R00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and his officials to the House.  I join the Acting Chairperson in welcoming the young people and their teachers in the Visitors Gallery.</p> <p>Senators Garvey and Craughwell have covered most of the points I had intended to cover.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#R00600"><p>Great minds think alike.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#R00700"><p>On behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party, I am happy to welcome this Bill which will enhance and strengthen protections for whistleblowers in Ireland.</p> <p>The general interpretation of a protected disclosure is a written communication of a concern made in good faith which discloses or demonstrates information that may make evident an unethical or improper activity.  I am conscious that we have a Member of the House who, 21 years ago, disclosed a very important issue and it is only recently that it was vindicated, so I look forward to hearing what Senator Clonan has to say.  If one thinks it is difficult for people to make a protected disclosure now, can one imagine what it was like 21 years ago in that particular organisation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#R00800"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#R00900"><p>I am very anxious to hear what Senator Clonan says.</p> <p>As the Minister of State has outlined, Ireland is one of a small number of EU countries that had a regime in place prior to the European directive.  The 2014 Act has afforded vital protection to whistleblowers, but it is not perfect and we have learned much since the Act came into operation.  There have been a number of high-profile cases in recent years, as has been mentioned by colleagues, which showed that we can never be complacent about the protection of those who are reporting wrongdoing by either public or private sector organisations.  It is important that we take the opportunity now to improve our legislative framework to continue to deal with protected disclosures in a fair and proper manner.  The implementation of the EU directive and the amendments proposed in the Bill before us will further strengthen protections for whistleblowers and maintain Ireland's position as a leader in this area.</p> <p>The Bill will extend the scope of the legislation by providing protection for volunteers, and I cannot understand why they were not protected initially under the 2014 Act, shareholders, board members and job applicants by transposing the EU whistleblowing directive into law.  Are there any other job titles that are not protected under the legislation?  I realise that it is difficult to legislate for everything in a list form, but I am concerned about what professions are not protected.  The legislation will lead to the establishment in private sector organisations with 50 or more employees of formal channels and procedures that will permit their employees to make protected disclosures, as is currently the case in the public sector.  This will mean that employers and prescribed persons who receive protected disclosures will be required to acknowledge them, follow up on the allegations made and give feedback to the reporting person within three months of the disclosure.  These changes will be monitored and enforced by the inspectorate of the Workplace Relations Commission.  This will give greater certainty to both employers and whistleblowers as to what will happen when a protected disclosure is made.</p> <p>The establishment of the new office of the protected disclosures commissioner in the Office of the Ombudsman to support the operation of the new legislation is to be welcomed.  It will allow the commissioner to direct protected disclosures to the most appropriate body when it is unclear which body is responsible.  It will thus ensure that all protected disclosures will be dealt with appropriately.  The commissioner will also have responsibility for transmitting all protected disclosures made to Ministers to the most appropriate authority for assessment and thorough follow-up.  A further change that I welcome is that in civil proceedings the burden of proof will be reversed so it will fall to the employer to prove that any alleged act of penalisation did not occur because the person made a protected disclosure.</p> <p>We have a comprehensive whistleblowing law in place in the form of the Protected Disclosures Act 2014, and the transposition of the whistleblowing directive will require some amendments to that Act.  As I said, the other points I had intended to raise have been dealt with by my colleagues and I look forward to the Minister of State's reply to them.  However, I have some brief questions.  What protections are there for employers, be they State or private, from vindictive complaints?  There is no doubt that they will occur.</p> <p>I also have a concern about anonymous complaints.  I can understand why they are anonymous due to the reality of the situation, and I have experienced it with people who are related to me.  When one makes a protected disclosure one becomes a whistleblower, which is a term I do not like to be frank, and one is targeted.  I can understand why people would wish to make anonymous complaints, but there is a danger in that as well.  I am concerned about it, in that anybody can make a complaint about anybody and the person does not have to put his or her name to it.  There is a difficulty in that.  I can understand the reason for it, but I believe it could be open to abuse.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Diarmuid Wilson:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2017"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2017&amp;amp;pid=DiarmuidWilson&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I would be interested in seeing what job titles are not covered by this legislation and what the reasons for that are.</p><p>I welcome the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#S00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and congratulate him on progressing this important legislation.  It is always important that legislation be reviewed and improved as time goes on, given that situations change.  Even though 2014 was not that long ago, the Act was groundbreaking legislation for the time and, as the Minister of State mentioned, one of the strongest Acts on whistleblowing across the EU.  However, it is important that we always consider how to strengthen it.</p> <p>"Protected disclosure" or "whistleblowing" can have an array of meanings.  Widely defined, it applies to the following: the commission of criminal offences; a failure to comply with legal obligations; endangering the health and safety of individuals; damaging the environment; a miscarriage of justice; a misuse of public funds; oppressive, discriminatory, grossly negligent or grossly mismanaged acts or omissions by a public body; and the concealment or destruction of information about any of the above wrongdoings.  This array is important to note.</p> <p>The original Act covers employees, former employees, trainees, people working under contract for services, independent contractors, agency workers, people on work experience and garda&iacute;.  For whatever reason, it does not cover volunteers, although public bodies can, if they wish, investigate reports of wrongdoing from volunteers.  The new amendments to the Act will include protections for board members, which is important, shareholders, volunteers, unpaid trainees and job applicants who make protected disclosures.  Board members do an important job and they come across information on which they have a responsibility to act, so being brought under the protection of whistleblower legislation is important.</p> <p>One of the foundation stones of whistleblowing is the retention of anonymity.  Our problem is that we are in a small country.  While I will not say that everyone knows one another, people know, people hear and people talk in local authorities and State agencies.  Gossip is currency.  No matter how anonymous a protected disclosure is, it will get out there.  We have seen this in high-profile cases and how the impact is not just on the whistleblower, but on his or her spouse, partner and children.  If the State closes ranks on a person, it can be a lonely place for the whistleblower-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#S00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#S00400"><p>-----and his or her family.  We have all seen instances where someone in a company or public body is not even whistleblowing, but is instead just challenging or looking for improvements.  That can be unwelcome at times, and it can be a very lonely place for a person in those circumstances.</p> <p>I note the protections as regards information.  Information leaks, so it is important that there are safeguards relating to encryption and so on within the Bill.  Once upon a time, one would have had to hand someone information physically.  Nowadays, it can be done electronically, for example, by copying something on one's phone and sending a WhatsApp message.  I am not in any way an expert on encryption security, but I am concerned about how easy it is to pass on information.</p> <p>The Minister of State mentioned a threshold of 50 to 249 employees, with some leeway for companies to improve their data protections and so on.  What responsibilities do companies with fewer than 50 employees have?  While I appreciate that we do not want to overburden any employer with costs, what would happen with a protected disclosure in such cases and what responsibility would the employer have to ensure privacy?</p> <p>It is important to note that grievances may also be protected disclosures.  If someone has a concern or complaint about selection criteria or a promotion and feels that there are questions to be answered &ndash; I have concerns following questions raised with me about a certain public body &ndash; such issues need to be examined.</p> <p>Regarding the formal channels and procedures for making protected disclosures, it is important that workers know what they have to do and how to do it, and that the information they provide is protected and secure.</p> <p>It is important that the protected disclosures commissioner be located within the Office of the Ombudsman.  We do not need a new body.</p> <p>Section 8, which amends section 6 of the principal Act, relates to a person employed by a public body who makes a protected disclosure prior to the enactment of the Bill.  This is important and welcome.</p> <p>Section 17 inserts section 16A in the principal Act and relates to the protection of the identities of persons named in the report.  In a situation I am dealing with, an anonymous complaint was made and received in a certain Department.  It led to an investigation and the suspension of the person.  I have received follow-up letters from employers within said organisation &ndash; again, anonymously &ndash; naming people even though they are under investigation and stating that the Garda would be investigating the matter in the coming weeks.  I am concerned about the level of confidentiality.  This comes back to how we are a small country.  Be they all in one building or scattered around the country, employees in public bodies talk and know what is happening, so the level of privacy in such cases is not as high as one would imagine.  Legislating for this is difficult, though, because gossip is currency and everyone loves a bit of gossip.  When a complaint is made in the fashion we are discussing under this legislation, it is a serious issue and needs to be investigated seriously.  People need to be confident that, when they make such a complaint, the information is secure and they and their anonymity are protected insofar as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#S00500"><p>It is good to see the Minister of State.  He is welcome.</p> <p>The Bill is to be welcomed for the most part.  My colleagues in the D&aacute;il have played a key role in terms of amendments to the Bill.  Improving the existing legislation is long overdue.  Down the years, we have heard all too often of the horror stories and treatment of whistleblowers when they came forward and spoke out.  Attempts by authorities to protect their reputations have often resulted in destroying the whistleblowers' reputations.  There is usually a circling of the wagons and a casting of aspersions on the characters or motivations of the whistleblowers.  However, whistleblowers play a vital role in our society.  It is well known that whistleblowing is one of the most effective ways of stopping wrongdoing.  Many cases of corruption and fraud are exposed by workers reporting same to their employers, regulators or the press.</p> <p>It needs to be said that the Bill only came about because of the EU&rsquo;s whistleblowing directive and its mandatory reporting requirements as opposed to a desire by the Government to improve our existing legislation on protected disclosures.  However, from what we have seen in the D&aacute;il debates and the extensive work completed by the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach, the Minister has worked well with all parties and none and has taken on board some of the issues raised by academics and groups such as Transparency International and the Irish Council for Civil Liberties.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There was engagement with bodies representing the legal profession and those working within mental health services.  All of this engagement played a valuable role in helping to shape the 60 recommendations of the pre-legislative scrutiny report.  I would also like to acknowledge all of the work my Sinn F&eacute;in colleagues, Deputies Mair&eacute;ad Farrell and Buckley, have put into this Bill.  They worked as constructively as possible with the Government parties at each stage.  They had introduced legislation to amend the Protected Disclosures Act 2014 last December and, I believe, many of Deputy Mair&eacute;ad Farrell's proposed amendments were accepted.  However, there are still a few concerns I would like to raise with the Minister of State.</p><p>Removing the right to make protected disclosures directly to a Minister under section 8 is a retrograde step.  Experts who appeared before the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform and Taoiseach were also of this view.  The Office of the Parliamentary Legal Adviser had similar concerns.  There are legitimate concerns that this could violate the non-regression clause in the directive, which states that the transposition must not be used as an opportunity to lower existing standards.  New restrictive conditions are introduced which must be met before a public service worker can make a disclosure to the Minister.  This means that these workers will generally have to exhaust the internal procedures in their workplace before making a protected disclosure to the Minister.  Our amendments in this regard propose the deletion of the entire section on the new stepped procedure.</p><p>I differ with my good colleague, Senator Wilson, on explicitly exempting relevant organisations from accepting anonymous disclosures because there are very real reasons why someone may need to make an anonymous disclosure.  In the case of an instance of child abuse or something of that nature, a person may wish to hide his or her identity.  Certain organisations should not be able to refuse to accept such disclosures.</p><p>On rejecting protected disclosures that can be characterised as interpersonal grievances, if a protected disclosure can be characterised as deriving from an interpersonal grievance, for instance, if bullying was involved, the employer would be able to channel this complaint down the road of a respect and dignity complaint rather than a protected disclosure.  This would lower protections for someone making a genuine protected disclosure which has been misclassified as a bullying complaint.  If there is serious wrongdoing that someone wishes to reveal, the motivation of the discloser should not be grounds to prevent acceptance as a protected disclosure and to deny the worker the protections he or she would receive as a result of having made one.</p><p>My fourth concern relates to the introduction of criminal penalties for knowingly making false reports.  This is likely to be used as a deterrent by employers to discourage people from making protected disclosures.  For example, as part of the information employers must provide to employees, a warning that employees could face criminal sanction could be included, which could have a chilling effect.</p><p>I have a couple of other points to make.  On the resourcing of the new office, some concerns have been raised with regard to making sure this resourcing is adequate.  There has been talk of this new office having three staff members, which would clearly not be adequate.  I would welcome any assurances the Minister of State can give in that regard.  I support the point Senator Garvey made with regard to including human rights defenders and front-line defenders.  I wonder if the Senator would consider submitting an amendment on this matter on Committee Stage and how the Minister of State would feel about such an amendment.</p><p>There is an opportunity here in the Seanad to look at these issues further before the Bill goes back to the D&aacute;il, which it will as the Minister of State has indicated that he proposes amendments to it, which are also welcome.  I acknowledge that there are difficulties with the issue of the retrospective application of the Bill but, if anything can be worked out in order to expand protection for whistleblowers who fall through the cracks, that would be very worthwhile.  Sinn F&eacute;in is happy to support the passage of this Bill.  We hope the Minister of State will continue to engage constructively with us, particularly with regard to the amendments we intend to table on the points I have raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#T00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the Chamber.  I very much welcome this Bill.  As has already been alluded to, the Government is late in transposing the directive.  The Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform and Taoiseach carried out really good pre-legislative scrutiny of the Bill, however.  I understand that the Minister of State has signalled in the D&aacute;il that he is very much open to amendments proposed in the Seanad.  That is to be welcomed.  I will put on the record that we owe great thanks to a number of groups that came before the committee during its meetings on the pre-legislative scrutiny.  I refer to Transparency International, the Irish Council for Civil Liberties, the journalist Mick Clifford and others who contributed.</p> <p>Any of us who have dealt with, advocated for or represented people who hold information about wrongdoing will know the frustration and the enormous personal, physical and mental toll those individuals and their families face in trying to vindicate their allegations, protect their own integrity and, ultimately, protect the public interest, or a private interest, as the case may be.  The broadening and deepening of the scope of this Bill is very much to be welcomed.  It is very important that Senator Clonan is here in the Chamber.  I am delighted to have him as a Senator and I look forward to his contribution because listening to personal experiences is extremely important.</p> <p>It has already been said that Ireland is one of a small number of countries that has legislation in this space.  Of course, it was my colleague, Deputy Howlin, who brought forward the legislation in 2014.  I am glad that we are updating and reforming that legislation now.  I will talk about some of the concerns in a second but first I will note that it is positive that we are seeing the protected disclosure legislation extended to unpaid trainees, volunteers, shareholders, board members and job applicants.  These are people who may be on the margins of organisations but still very much part of them.  It is also positive that we are putting in place more defined timelines and that a protected disclosures office is to be established.  I have dealt with two cases of protected disclosure.  Any of us who has personal experience of dealing with individuals who have lodged a protected disclosure or who have listened to Michael Clifford will know of the exceedingly and excruciatingly long time it can take for a protected disclosure to be processed.  I was struck by something Michael Clifford said, which was that it was only when he published information surrounding a protected disclosure that an investigator was appointed, often after the investigation having been delayed for months or longer.  In that respect, establishing a protected disclosures office is really important.</p> <p>Others have mentioned the need to resource that office.  That will be absolutely crucial given the public agencies and Departments that new office will be up against.  I am struck by one case in particular I know of in which the buck has effectively been passed between two Departments.  They both have responsibility for this particular issue but neither is willing to take it on.  This new office is going to come up against very powerful forces so we need to see it adequately resourced when it is established.</p> <p>With regard to concerns about the Bill, an issue that came up as very important during pre-legislative scrutiny, and which also came up in the D&aacute;il, is the issue of retrospective application of the Bill for investigations that have been commenced but left uncompleted.  The very nature of many of the protected disclosures is that they have been left hanging for a long period.  I am reassured that the Minister of State is going to table amendments in this regard in the Seanad.  We look forward to the detail of those.  It is really important that we see as wide a scope as possible with regard to that retrospective application.</p> <p>My second main concern relates to the organisations to which the provisions will apply.  I have read the arguments justifying the minimum threshold of 50 but I must say that I do not buy them.  It is important to say that the responsibilities imposed by the Bill are to ensure that a process is in place for an event which is usually rare but which is very important.  There seems to be a presumption that the making of a protected disclosure is very common or frequent but we know that it is not.  There are many people who decided previously not to make a protected disclosure when they should have but, by and large, this is not an everyday occurrence.  When we talk about the costs to businesses, we need to put things in perspective.  Particularly for smaller organisations, it is precisely because they are more informal and less structured that the potential for victimisation and penalisation is all the greater, as is the deterrent to making a protected disclosure.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is for that reason we need to have formal processes in place in all organisations and that staff are made aware of them.  I am struck because Transparency International talks about how only 30% of private sector employers have some sort of process in place.  To me, it is not necessarily about the process itself; it is about the clear message that is sent to every member of staff that there is a facility to be able to lodge a protected disclosure if they see wrongdoing.  It has been said that the absence or presence of an internal process does not diminish a worker's right to report wrongdoing.  I recognise that there is a distinction between the right of a worker to report versus the mandated responsibility of a firm to have systems in place but again, we must go back to what kind of message is sent if there is no formal process in place within an organisation.</p><p>I also note that four sectors have been expressly excluded from that minimum threshold provision.  It is too narrow.  I do not think it is good enough that we name some sectors and then say we are going to take a risk assessment in the consultation with regard to others.  I would like to see evidence as to why a professional services firm like an accountancy firm has to be treated differently from, let us say, a financial services firm.  I would very much urge the Minister of State to broaden that list and ensure it is hardwired into the legislation.</p><p>The last issue I want to raise in the few seconds available is the lack of civil legal aid to whistleblowers.  Many of us on the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach are very frustrated by the cap on compensation for penalisation.  We know that a person who takes his or her case to the higher courts does so with a very significant element of personal risk.  Given that a protected disclosure is being made in the public interest, which is why we have this legislation, and not in the personal interest, it is incumbent that we do as much as possible to ensure that we protect and look after those who have gone to considerable risk in making a protected disclosure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#U00200"><p>As the Minister of State outlined, the context of this legislation is the transposition of the EU whistleblower directive and the amendment of the Protected Disclosures Act 2014.  There are many positive elements within this legislation but there are also concerns.  Given that we are entering the period of legislative scrutiny, I will highlight some of the concerns.</p> <p>I know Transparency Ireland will have contacted the Minister of State outlining its belief that there are elements in the way and manner that the transposition of the directive is proposed in the current Bill, which could directly or indirectly weaken some of the existing protections for Irish whistleblowers.  That would be in violation of Article 85.2 of the EU whistleblower directive.  There is a requirement under the whistleblower directive for a progressive strengthening of protections whereas there are certain components within the legislation, as proposed, that could constitute a weakening, again, either directly or indirectly.  Therefore, we really hope that as the legislation goes through the Seanad, this can perhaps be addressed and strengthened so that we are not putting forward legislation that could face legal challenge either in Ireland or the European courts.</p> <p>There are a few core areas in terms of weakening this, one of which is the limitation or removal of the right to make protected disclosures directly to a Minister.  The standard for the legislation to protect under section 8 is reasonable belief.  Under section 8, it is proposed that public servants would be required to report to their employer in most circumstances, thereby removing the automatic right of public servants to make a public disclosure directly to a Minister.  Again, we have the danger whereby disclosures are getting captured within the hierarchy of an employment system and, indeed, within the power dynamics of that system, when it may be an issue of quite significant national concern that should be allowed to be disclosed directly to a Minister.  This also dilutes existing legal protections for public servants in terms of prosecution, penalisation or detriment if they choose to make a disclosure directly to a Minister.  The danger is not just in terms of that route not being open, therefore, but that many people will not be aware there are a set of steps they need to have taken.  As we have heard very eloquently across this House, many people who are motivated to make a disclosure in this regard do so out of public concern and for the public interest.  In doing so, and there are other measures within this Bill, they should not face a situation whereby they effectively find themselves excluded from the provisions and protections of this legislation.  Many of them will never read this legislation.  They will see an issue in their area of expertise or area of concern and look to highlight that to the person they see as the key decision maker.  Therefore, it is a real concern if, effectively, those who go directly to a Minister may end up not activating the protections under this legislation and somehow fall outside the loop.</p> <p>Another very significant concern is the exemption in terms of relevant organisations accepting anonymous disclosures.  At the moment, there is an exemption for organisations for an obligation to accept or follow up on disclosures that are made anonymously.  Again, it allows that the recipients may do so if they give appropriate notice but that requirement is really a big get-out clause in having to follow this up.</p> <p>I will point out that the 2014 Act did not say anything about anonymous disclosures.  The current legislation explicitly states that anonymous disclosures can be disregarded.  That is a regressive step and, again, brings us back to that concern around Article 25.2 of the EU directive.  It is a really important issue because this is not to say every single anonymous disclosure needs to have a full investigation.  There are already filters and mechanisms within the Bill whereby if a disclosure is made, there is an examination as to whether it is, in fact, relevant under the Protected Disclosures Act and whether it merits an investigation and so forth.  The point is that the Bill at the moment basically allows for a summary disregard, so the issues that have been raised anonymously do not have to be thought about at all rather than examining the issues on their merits, which, bear in mind, are issues for the public concern - they are not issues for the individuals involved.  The issues should basically just be examined and then organisations can say they have been told about this concern and they can see if that is a valid issue.  If it is, they can proceed through the process as such.  In fact, it is an immediate get-out clause and, again, we know the levels of penalisation that have been experienced by whistleblowers.  People should not have to choose, as many whistleblowers have had to do, between their personal well-being, the next ten years of their life and what that will look like, the security of their family and doing something they believe to be in the public interest or that raises a flag of concern.  I am really worried about that provision with regard to a summary right to disregard anonymous disclosures.</p> <p>I am also concerned about the interpersonal grievances piece because I think there is a blurring of the line.  Yes, of course, we need to guard against the blurring of the line but we also know there are situations where people who complain, and who many times will complain long before they make a protected disclosure, can be targeted within their workplaces.  Therefore, they may well have interpersonal grievances or be subject to grievance procedures or other actions from, for example, a manager against whom they have complained or challenged at the same time as they may also wish to make protected disclosures.  It is really important that it is made clear that if it is an interpersonal grievance, then it is not a protected disclosure, because at the moment it is very vague.  It needs to be made very clear to people that they can do both.  At the moment, there is a danger of a chilling effect on protected disclosure for anybody who may separately be involved in an interpersonal matter with his or her employer.</p> <p>There are quite strong criminal sanctions for false reports.  There are not similar sanctions for false information with regard to those against whom a complaint is being made.</p> <p>Finally, there is another really big issue, which has been discussed, about retrospective complaints.  In a way, I do not even like using the word "retrospective" because for many of those who have been involved in these processes, I would regard them as being current procedures.  The effects and impacts they have suffered in terms of penalisation are ongoing.  Many of them, in fact, have never received anything in terms of payments in respect of penalisation or other payments.  They basically never had that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Many of them have never received information about what the resolution or outcome of the disclosure they made was.  I would regard a large number of those past protected disclosures as current protected disclosures and I believe these people should be entitled to any protections, measures or compensation available under this legislation.  When we look to the people who have done that public service, it is vital that that be reflected and that they be included.  It is retrospective in terms of when someone made the disclosure but the process, the penalisation and the lack of resolution is ongoing.  This legislation is a chance to address that.  I also support the points made by Senator Sherlock about the threshold of 50 employees.  Someone could have a very small company, sometimes a brass plate company, and that company may be the window into quite a significant issue of public concern.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#V00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State and his officials for being here.  I have some concerns about the legislation.  I am delighted to see another whistleblower, Peter Behan, here.  I am sorry Antoinette and Noel McGree and other whistleblowers cannot be here.</p> <p>My first concern is about section 8, which removes the right to make protected disclosures directly to a Minister.  This applied to me back in 2000 when I finished my PhD.  It was not a solitary act of whistleblowing but a piece of research supervised by Dublin City University, right up to the level of its registrar and its solicitors at the time, Arthur Cox.  I was also supervised up to the level of Chief of Staff within the Defence Forces and had to seek written permission to continue the research.  What I found was the systematic and systemic sexual assault and rape of female soldiers.  You can make a moral argument for theft, lying, even killing.  That is the premise upon which we use force in the armed forces and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  However, there is one thing we as a species cannot tolerate and that is sexual assault, sexual abuse and rape.  That organisation did everything in its power to destroy me as a person and my family.  It sent the military police to my house to intimidate me, my wife and our young child.  This was not Shanghai or Myanmar or Beijing.  This was D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown, a place the Minister of State is familiar with.  Removing the right of a person to approach the Minister is a retrograde step and reduces protections for whistleblowers. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#V00300"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#V00400"><p>Ireland has a very particular and toxic culture when it comes to whistleblowing.  The 2014 Act, for example, contains within it the assumption that the person who calls attention to wrongdoing will lose his or her job.  We need to think about that.  There is no mention in this legislation of those who engage in reprisal against whistleblowers.  My sin or crime was calling out sexual violence and sexual assault.  If that is a crime, take me out and hang me.  The people who actively engaged in that reprisal have now been promoted to very senior rank in our Defence Forces.  They have never faced any scrutiny, questioning or interrogation about their actions.  There has been no sanction, only reward.  In Ireland, if you tell the truth and speak out about wrongdoing you will be punished.  If you defend the organisation, whether in health, the voluntary sector or any other area of Irish life, you will be rewarded and promoted, perhaps even given a big job in Europe.  That sends a very mixed message to our children and our youth.  If one of my children or a neighbour came to me and said he or she had experienced wrongdoing, my advice would be to see a solicitor immediately and protect himself or herself, notwithstanding what is contained in this legislation.</p> <p>Back in 2001, I was threatened with criminal prosecution for breaching the Official Secrets Act.  I was told by my former comrades that a file was being sent to the Director of Public Prosecutions and that I would face criminal prosecution.  Press statements were released saying I had fabricated the research and falsified its findings.  Ireland is not a safe place to tell the truth.  I have to disagree with the honourable Senator who said so.  It is not a safe place.  Ask Maurice McCabe, Peter Behan or Noel McGree.  Ask their families about the suffering they endure.  The people who engage in the reprisal face no sanction.  There is nothing in this legislation to deal with that and there ought to be, instead of criminalising people for making allegedly false disclosures.  What saved me was Michael Smith, the Fianna F&aacute;il Minister for Defence at the time.  When I approached him directly, he put in place an independent Government inquiry.  He did not allow the Defence Forces to investigate themselves.  That is something every person who brings forward a disclosure should be able to rely on.  Such people should be able to talk to the Minister .  What else are we here for?  Why is Deputy Smyth a Minister?  Why would anybody be a Minister, save to take responsibility for what happens within his or her Department?</p> <p>The other provisions I have concerns about are those exempting relevant organisations from accepting anonymous disclosures in the proposed new section 5A(1).  After what I have said, and after what my good friend Maurice McCabe experienced, where they not only tried to destroy him existentially but tried to destroy his relationship and his family, the Government expects people to dispense with their anonymity?  The Government must listen to whistleblowers and to Transparency International because we are the people who know what we are talking about, notwithstanding any advice the Government may have been given, legal or otherwise. </p> <p>By removing wrongdoings involving interpersonal grievances, organisations will be able to use these as a stick to beat people who bring forward disclosures.  Whistleblower reprisals involve a very personalised, systemic and systematic attack on a person to completely destroy his or her character, reputation and identity.  In my case, they tried to destroy my reputation as an ethical researcher, as an officer with service overseas for my country and as a citizen.  They tried to take my job as a lecturer on probation in the institute of technology sector away from me.  I was informed that because I had fabricated my research, I was going to lose my job.  I thought I was going to lose my job and my liberty.  That is personal.  Consequently, by putting in a clause removing anything involving interpersonal grievances, the Government is providing organisations engaged in wrongdoing with a defence and a stick with which to beat vulnerable whistleblowers.  That must be removed.</p> <p>Introducing criminal penalties for knowingly making false reports will also be used as a mischievous way of targeting whistleblowers.  It is, by definition, what constitutes whistleblower reprisal.  Irish organisations will accuse the person who brings forward disclosures of wrongdoing of making false allegations.  That was the case for me.  Katie Hannon's documentary, "Women of Honour", which was broadcast on 11 September 2021, showed that, 21 years after I made my disclosures, there is still the same problem in our armed forces.  That is even though oversight was imposed on them.  This is typical of Irish organisations.  I have been contacted over the past two decades by whistleblowers from all aspects of Irish life, including the Law Library, charities, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, religious orders, hospitals, the ambulance and fire services, corporate entities and banking.  It is everywhere in Irish society.  This legislation does not provide people with the proper protections to make a disclosure and be free from the type of reprisal I experienced.</p> <p>While I welcome this Bill, I urge the Minister of State to listen to whistleblowers and to Transparency International and other international whistleblowing expert groups.  I ask him to please remove the provisions I have mentioned because I am still experiencing the existential harm of reprisal 22 years later.  In the aftermath of the "Women of Honour" broadcast, over 30 young people - mostly women and some young men - made fresh disclosures to me of the full spectrum of sexual harassment, assault and rape in the Defence Forces, that is, in the Army, Naval Service and Air Corps.  The level of pushback is indicative and symptomatic of a culture that has a problem with truth-telling and naming harm.  We have to change the culture and the narrative.  The four issues I have raised breach Article 25.2 of the EU whistleblowing directive, in that they reduce the level of protection already afforded by member states in the areas covered in this directive.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tom Clonan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=TomClonan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I thank the Acting Chair for giving me leeway.  I apologise to the Minister of State for having to hear this level of emotion but I wanted to communicate that it is a categorical imperative that he deals with this.  I ask him to please listen to us.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#W00200"><p>Well done, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#W00400"><p>I thank the Senator.  His contribution was very powerful.  It was important that we listened to him today.  Well done.  I also want to welcome Mr. Peter Behan to the Gallery.  I ask the Minister of State to respond to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#W00500"><p>I thank all Senators for their contributions.  I will continue my contribution where I left off by describing some of the main provisions of the Bill.</p> <p>I had been discussing Chapter 3, section 14, which inserts the new sections 10C and 10D into the principal Act.  These sections concern the handling of disclosures made or transmitted to the commissioner.  In the first instance, the commissioner shall attempt to identify either a prescribed person or another suitable person with the competence to follow up on the matter reported and transmit the report to said person for further action.  If no person can be found, the commissioner shall apply the standard rules as regards acknowledgement, follow-up and feedback, as required by the directive in respect of prescribed persons.</p> <p>It also inserts section 10E, which provides that where a report is transmitted to a third party who is not subject to the requirement to have formal reporting channels, that person shall follow the standard rules as regards acknowledgement, follow-up and feedback.  It inserts section 10F, which provides for powers of investigation for the commissioner in the event that direct follow-up of a report is required.  </p> <p>Section 15 inserts a new schedule to the Act concerning a number of standard provisions regarding the keeping of accounts and the staffing of the office of the protected disclosures commissioner.</p> <p>Chapter 4, which comprises sections 16 to 20, inclusive, transposes a number of provisions of the directive that are applicable to internal reporting to employers and external reporting to prescribed persons and the commissioner.  </p> <p>Section 16 obliges persons responsible for handling protected disclosures to keep the identity of reporting persons confidential, overhauling a similar provision in the principal Act.  Section 17 introduces a new requirement to similarly keep confidential the identities of other persons named in a disclosure.  Section 18 provides for the restriction of certain data subject access rights to prevent these rights being abused to out a whistleblower or to frustrate or to impede effective follow-up on a report.  </p> <p>Section 19 specifies how records of protected disclosures shall be kept.  Section 20 imposes a similar restriction on the Freedom of Information Act as that provided for in section 18.  Again, it is intended to protect reporting persons&rsquo; identities and to prevent attempts to impede or frustrate follow-up.  </p> <p>Chapter 5 comprises sections 21 to 25, inclusive, and it concerns the enhanced protection measures that are required by the directive.  The key changes are introduced in this chapter.  They include, first, the extension of interim relief to acts of penalisation other than dismissal.  Second, there is the reversal of the burden of proof in civil cases concerning penalisations, so that employers will have to prove that the alleged act of penalisation was not taken because the worker made a protected disclosure.  Last, there is the provision of a set of offences for contraventions of the Act.  </p> <p>Chapter 6, which comprises sections 26 to 33, inclusive, provides for a number of incidental and supplementary measures, including the removal of the restriction on public disclosure of taxpayer information for certain types of records; the provision for the Minister to issue statutory guidance to assist public bodies, prescribed persons and the commissioner in best practice in the handling of reports; the provision of freely available information on how to make a disclosure and the protections afforded by the Act; enhanced provisions as regards the provision of statistical information to the Minister on the numbers of protected disclosures made and for the publication of said information; and finally powers for the Workplace Relations Commission inspectorate to monitor and enforce compliance with the requirements on employers to have internal reporting channels. </p> <p>Finally, the Bill inserts two schedules into the principal Act.  These are Schedule 5, which is a set of standard provisions as regards the keeping of accounts and staffing at the office of protected disclosures commissioner, and Schedule 6 reproduces the annexe to the directive, listing all of the EU laws that lie within the material&rsquo;s scope.  </p> <p>I will now address some of the points that have made by Senators here today.  I thank them all for their contributions.  I thank all Senators who support the strengthening of the legislation and who have engaged with it.  I want to thank Sinn F&eacute;in for sending representatives to my office to discuss the amendments, for tabling those amendments and for working constructively to try to advance this legislation.  I know it is difficult to do that.  </p> <p>Before I wrap up, I also want to mention one issue that was raised during the debate of the Bill in the D&aacute;il that remains unresolved.  The pre-legislative scrutiny report recommended that the new protections of the Bill be extended retrospectively to persons who reported wrongdoing prior to its enactment.  The Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Michael McGrath, gave a commitment to the House that he would examine the issue in consultation with the Attorney General.  The Minister had hoped to bring proposals in this regard before the Bill passed in the D&aacute;il, but this did not prove possible.  Work in this area is now at an advanced stage.  Amendments will be brought before this House for consideration when the Bill moves to Committee Stage.  </p> <p>In closing, I reiterate my thanks to Members of both Houses who worked on the pre-legislative scrutiny report on this Bill, which has greatly influenced its development.  I also thank the various stakeholders who have contributed to the development of Bill, including those who took the time to make submissions to the public consultation when the general scheme of the Bill was being developed, as well as those who attended the pre-legislative scrutiny hearings at the committee.  Their input has also provided great help in the preparation of the Bill.  Finally, I thank all Members of this House for their attention.  We had a positive debate on the issues in the D&aacute;il and I hope that will continue in the Seanad.  I commend this Bill to the House and I look forward to hearing the views of Members on Committee Stage.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.115" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#W00600"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#W00700"><p>Next Tuesday.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#W00750"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#W00800"><p>  Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 31 May 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.120" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 2.07 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 3.05 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 2.07 p.m. and resumed at 3.05 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.121" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#CC00100">Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill 2022: Committee Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.122" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Debate resumed on amendment No. 103:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#CC00300"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House for another round of debate.</p> <p>Amendment No. 123, which is in the grouping under discussion, aims to broaden the scope of the provision that the coimisi&uacute;n would effectively ban the marketing of salts and sugars by adding infant milk formula.  We are asking that this amendment would apply to all children and not just those who have digital access.  There is an inconsistency because the provision we are seeking to amend recognises that there is a harm in the marketing of fats, trans fats, salts and sugars, but there is a failure to recognise that there is a harm in the very aggressive marketing of infant milk formula.  I referred on the previous occasion to the fact that there has been much research into this, the most recent coming in the form of a report published by the WHO and UNICEF earlier this year.  That report refers to formula milk companies using manipulative marketing tactics that exploit parents anxieties and aspirations by purporting to be a trusted friend and advisor.  It also refers to formula milk companies distorting science and medicine to legitimise their claims and push their products.  The report argues that these companies are making false and incomplete scientific claims as to the health benefits of their products and that formula milk marketing undermines parents' confidence in breastfeeding.  As I said previously, anybody who has a newborn, especially a first child, knows all about the anxiety of trying to feed a baby.</p> <p>On the last occasion, Senator Lombard asked whether it would matter if the Minister were to accept this amendment.  We believe that it would matter because the research suggests that the choices of families are being undermined by aggressive marketing tactics.  We can also point to countries like Norway where there have been positive changes in breastfeeding rates.  The key issue here is the choices families make.  This is about not inflicting a viewpoint on any family around how they want to feed their child.  It is about helping families who have decided they want to breastfeed their babies and to allow them to do that without being aggressively targeted.  Maternity health data from the Department of Health shows that in 2020 some 62% of babies were breast fed at birth but that fell to 58.5% upon leaving hospital.  We know that within six months the rate falls to approximately 15%.</p> <p>I want to respond to some of the other points Senator Lombard made.  He talked about the other supports that need to be put in place.  He is absolutely right with regard to lactation consultants and peer to peer support.  Interestingly, the day he spoke marked one year to the day that the Government announced funding for 24 new lactation consultants to work in communities throughout the country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We put in a Commencement matter last week and the Department of Health confirmed that none of those lactation consultants has even been recruited yet, let alone begun working in the community.  The full complement of 10.5 lactation consultants announced in 2020 has yet to be appointed.  I say this to the Minister as a member of the Cabinet.  While making this argument about marketing tactics and how to improve breastfeeding rates, we must also look at those other issues.  Commitments have been made and they have not been followed through on.</p><p>As a last point on this issue, I am conscious there was correspondence from the Minister's office to the Baby Feeding Law Group Ireland about these amendments.  As we see it, it effectively seeks to hide behind the regulation of the  quality of the product itself as opposed to addressing head-on the issues of the marketing of the product as well as saying this is a Department of Health issue.  If the Minister's Department believes in the importance of outlawing the marketing of fats and sugars in the public health interests of children, I do not see why it would not include outlawing the marketing of infant formula to babies up to the age of 36 months.  It is interesting because in the question I posed last week about the lactation consultants, we also got a reply back from the Department of Health about regulating the marketing.  That Department hides behind the EU regulations governing the content and quality of the product itself and not the marketing.  That is simply not good enough.</p><p>We ask that the Minister consider the amendments we are putting forward.  We believe they are reasonable and that they would have an impact.  My final word on it is this is about giving public health messaging a fighting chance.  In the face of enormous money from companies whose only interest is profit, that messaging does not stand a chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#DD00200"><p>I thank the Senator.  Before I call the next speaker, it is my great pleasure to welcome a distinguished former Member of this House, and one who was very popular.  I welcome former Senator, now Deputy Richmond, to the Gallery.  It is great to have him back here.  Accompanying him are his friend Mr. Jamie Mahon from Leopardstown and his family.  I welcome them also.  It is good to have them all here.  I know from the reaction of colleagues that I echo the sentiments of everyone here.</p> <p>I call Senator Higgins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-05-25a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022052500002#DD00300"><p>I want to follow up on something.  I think Senator Sherlock mentioned it.  There is a little bit of a red herring at play in some of the responses we have been having in this debate with this reference to the EU regulations.  Regulation (EU) 2016/127, which supplements Regulation (EU) No 609/2013, relates to the compositional and information requirements for information on infant formula and follow-on formula.  That regulation specifically relates to the product and how it is composed, such as what the acceptable level of pesticide is.  That was one of the debating points when the regulation was being debated, because apparently there is an acceptable level of pesticide.  It deals also with other information requirements having to do with packaging.  It is absolutely not related to the area in question, namely, online promotion, marketing and commercial activity around breast milk substitutes in all their forms.  We must be clear we do not have a red herring thrown in here.  Even if it was an EU directive, it would not have prohibited us from having appropriate standards in many areas.  We see many countries in Europe are often ahead of each other when it comes to health and safety standards.  Certainly, it in no way constrains us from regulating here.  I worry this debate would send a signal to an incoming commission that it was constrained from regulating or, indeed, prohibiting breast milk substitutes in whichever form.  It is important we are clear on that.</p><p>It is important to focus on the relevant piece of international guidance, that is, the WHO code.  It has been there since the 1980s and has a number of very specific provisions the WHO highlighted as being not applied and not respected.  Again, this is not simply around the content but also the content delivery.  Some of the provisions in the WHO code are really clear.  They state things about not seeking direct contact with pregnant women.  They mention not having commercial communications presented as information.  Some of the things we know about are directly in breach of the WHO standards.  I refer to the baby clubs and the online chat with an expert mum who is employed by a company promoting a commercial product.  There are also the advertising campaigns people are encouraged to enter before they even give birth and where they then must give permission for follow-up emails to come in week by week encouraging them to engage.</p><p>We need to be clear that this is not an opinion.  It is not about the choice issue that everybody agrees with.  The question is about what is getting promoted and what the impacts are.  The WHO has been clear to the point it has stated that it believes that if there is not regulation of the advertisement or promotion of breast milk substitutes, then states are breaching the Convention on the Rights of the Child.  We have in the Bill a provision that mentions high-fat and salty foods as something with a direct effect on children.  We know breast milk substitutes, and certainly their promotion, has an impact on children.</p><p>On the argument this is providing some kind of service, we must be clear, as Senator Sherlock outlined, that we absolutely need greater supports, not just in the form of lactation consultants but also midwives.  The latter group needs to be better supported and resourced within our health system in general.  Many other supports are needed there, including longer follow-on times for those who might need that.  There are many supports that should and could be offered, including, as I mentioned, something available in the North of Ireland that we do not have here, namely, a public breast milk bank.  That does not get promoted as an option for those who cannot breastfeed because it makes nobody any money.  What it does is support women who need support at that time.</p><p>There are many public health measures we should be doing better but the core point is that does not argue against this regulation because they should not have to compete with a huge commercial advertising budget.  Marketing happens for a reason.  Companies do not commercially promote and advertise for no reason.  They do it because it increases sales.  It literally has a direct effect.  Internationally, about 10% of global sales, about $6 billion, is spent on promoting breast milk substitutes and formula milk.  That is equivalent to the entire budget of the WHO.  The WHO and, indeed, our own health service should not be up against that level of competition over who can reach people with those messages and who can give those supports.  That is key.  I wanted to bring in the WHO aspect because we were focusing a lot on Ireland because we have such extraordinarily low levels of breastfeeding.  Only 6% of women are breastfeeding to six months exclusively.</p><p>I will finish on the international responsibility because it is important.  This is not just about what we do here and how we give supports and things.  This is around the message we send internationally.  <i>The Lancet</i>estimated 800,000 infant deaths could have been avoided internationally if the WHO's code had been respected and applied with respect to formula milk.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>