<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from the following Senators that they propose to raise the following matters:</p> <p>Senator Lynn Boylan - The need for the Minister for Finance to introduce a levy on private jet departures.</p> <p>Senator John Cummins - The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the expansion of the Cro&iacute; C&oacute;naithe towns and villages scheme to include rural one-off derelict properties and other vacant properties.</p> <p>Senator Jerry Buttimer - The need for the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth to make a statement on the timeline for the re-opening of the early childhood care and education, ECCE, class in Morning Star National School, Ballyphehane, Cork.</p> <p>Senator Malcolm Byrne - The need for the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science to make a statement on Ireland&rsquo;s potential membership of the European Council for Nuclear Research, CERN.</p> <p>Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy - The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the provision of two palliative care beds at St. Joseph's Care Centre, Longford.</p> <p>Senator Tim Lombard - The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the current level of podiatry care for older people in west Cork.</p> <p>Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne - The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on the staff replacement process within the educational and training boards, ETBs.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne - The need for the Minister for Social Protection to make a statement on the proposed new means test for the fuel allowance for the over-70s.</p> <p>Senator Paul Gavan - The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the application from Limerick City and County Council for a dedicated affordable homes team.</p> <p>Senator Mary Seery Kearney - The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on the Drinkaware education programme.</p> <p>Senator Martin Conway - The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on his plans to deliver a package of appropriate health care supports and compensation package to Thalidomide survivors.</p> <p>Of the matters suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Lynn Boylan, John Cummins and Jerry Buttimer.  Senator Malcolm Byrne has withdrawn his Commencement matter which I had originally selected.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#A00350">Aviation Industry</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#A00400"><p>I welcome and thank Minister of State, Deputy Sean Fleming, for coming into the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#A00500"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it go dt&iacute; an Teach.  We know that aviation's climate impact is disproportionate and it continues to grow quickly.  Emissions from private jets are growing even faster than the rest of the aviation industry with a 31% increase in CO2 emissions between 2005 and 2019.  In just one hour, a single private jet can emit 2 tonnes of CO2 whereas the average Irish person emits 12.3 tonnes of CO2 over the course of an entire year and that is high by EU standards.  </p> <p>We know from the Oxfam carbon inequality report that flights are a major contributor to the carbon footprints the rich and famous.  Footprints from aviation alone were found to be in excess of 1,000 tonnes per year for some celebrities.  This summer the twitter account @CelebJets was used to highlight the outrageous carry-on of celebrities like Taylor Swift, Drake and Kylie Jenner and their absurdly short journeys by private jets from as little as ten minutes.  People were rightly outraged because it points to the deep hypocrisy that currently exists around climate action where wealthy people seem to be exempt from any sort of change.  </p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in believes that not all emissions are created equal.  Climate justice scholars have long distinguished between luxury emissions and subsistence emissions.  The latter arise from people meeting their basic needs in the absence of alternatives, while the former are produced by wealthy people who demonstrate just how wealthy they are.  For too long, climate action has been about punishing ordinary working-class people and heaping guilt on them for living in a society that has locked them into a carbon-centric lifestyle and makes it very difficult and expensive for them to change.  At the same time the wealthy seem to be exempt and continue to live carbon-intensive lifestyles.</p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in believes luxury emissions need to be pursued, not only because it is the right thing to do to tackle climate change, but because it demonstrates to wider society that we are serious about a just transition.  It would also help to bring people along in the enormous challenge for society of tackling climate change.  Sinn F&eacute;in proposes a tax of &euro;3,000 on the departure of private jets from this State should be introduced.  Canada has recently imposed a luxury tax on the sale and importation of high-value cars, planes and boats, while Switzerland has proposed taxing private-jet flights.  According to data collected by the NGO, Transport &amp;amp; Environment, 5,998 private jets departed from the State in 2019 and in its paper, Private Jets: Can the Super-Rich Supercharge Zero Emission Aviation?, Transport &amp;amp; Environment proposed a &euro;3,000 levy on private jet departures to account for the environmental damage that they cause.</p> <p>These are genuine behavioural taxes because, as we all know, feasible more environmentally friendly alternatives are available to individuals to choose instead.  The same cannot be said for the general carbon tax which does not distinguish the luxury from the necessary, nor consider the alternatives.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Such a tax shows there is an alternative to generating the revenues needed to fund the wider fight against the climate crisis but I urge the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, to consider a tax on luxury emissions.  This is just one example of them, namely, to try to get a handle on the completely unjustified depletion of the world's scarce remaining carbon budget by those who have very, very deep pockets and who are well able to fund the decarbonisation process.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#B00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter in the House today.  First, I wish to apologise to Senator Boylan and to the House for the non-availability of the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, or myself yesterday, or of a Minister of State to speak on our behalf.  I appreciate the forbearance of Senator Boylan in agreeing to speak on the Commencement matter today.  I thank her for that.</p> <p>At the outset it should be noted that neither the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, nor the Minister for Transport, Deputy Eamon Ryan, have given consideration of a levy on private jet departures to date.  However, it is noted that Switzerland is well-advanced with such a proposal, although it is understood that it has not been commenced yet and neither has the levy rate been determined.  The Swiss proposal would apply to private non-commercial flights departing from an airport situated in Switzerland and provides for a list of exemptions, including emergency medical service flights, military flights, flights operated under a public service obligation, etc.  It is understood that France is giving consideration to the introduction of such a levy as well as in an effort to make transport greener and fairer.</p> <p>In this regard, it should be noted that the issue may be raised by the French minister for transport at the upcoming informal Transport Council that will take place in Prague in the coming days, 20 to 21 October.</p> <p>Before consideration could be given to any proposal of this type, we would need to gather information about the accurate number of private jets departing from Irish airports and I note the figures Senator Boylan mentioned.  We need this on a yearly basis to establish the feasibility of such a measure.  Private flights is a broad term without a specific definition, which can capture many different types of flights such as privately owned jet aircraft, to which the Senator refers, business aviation, fractional ownership by multiple owners, to name a few.  At present the Department of Transport does not hold complete data on the number of private flights that pass through our airports as non-commercial operations are not required to apply for a flight authorisation prior to landing in an Irish airport.</p> <p>I would like to touch on the taxation of fuel used for aviation, which is the responsibility of the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe.  Ireland's excise duty treatment of fuel used for air navigation is governed by European Union law as set out in directive 2003/96/EC on the taxation of energy products and electricity, commonly known as the energy tax directive, ETD.  The ETD was transposed into national law in the Finance Act 1999.  Under the ETD member states are obliged to exempt from excise duty certain mineralised fuels used for commercial aviation purposes.  In aviation fuels, the scope of the ETD exemption covers jet fuel, described as heavy oil, which is the most commonly used fuel type in air navigation.  The exemption must encompass all jet fuel used for intra-community and international air transport purposes.  A member state may, however, waive this exemption for intra-community flights but only where it has entered into a bilateral agreement with another member state to tax the fuel.  Ireland has no such agreement at present and, therefore, the exemption from taxation is applied to all jet fuel used for commercial intra-community flights.  The ETD provides that member states may opt to fully or partially exempt from taxation jet fuel used for commercial, domestic or air navigation.  Currently, Ireland's mineral oil tax law provides that a fuel relief to apply to jet fuel used for all commercial air navigation, including domestic intra-community and international.  </p> <p>With regard to aviation fuel for commercial international transport, the scope for a member state to take a unilateral approach on taxation on aviation fuel is limited not only by the ETD but by international law and a range of bilateral and multilateral agreements that operate under the 1944 Convention on International Civil Aviation, also known as the Chicago Convention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I call on Senator Boylan to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#B00400"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.  I also thank the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, for the apology, which I accept completely.  I am glad he was able to take the matter today.  I see a glimmer of hope in the response he gave.  It is interesting that again France seems to be leading the way in innovative approaches to climate action.  I had a Commencement matter last week looking at the ban on fossil fuel adverts which again France is leading the way on.  I would like to know the Government's position ahead of that Transport Council meeting because we know that is what is critical.  It is all well and good for France to bring the proposal to the Council meeting but will Ireland back it up and support it?  I would be interested to hear, the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming's view on that.</p> <p>According to the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming's response, it is interesting to note the State is not collecting the necessary data in order to do that tax.  This is another example of why Ireland needs to get its head around collecting data on wealth.  Apparently, we do not have the data from the Government when it comes to a wealth tax and we are being told we do not have it when it comes to private jets.  Of course the Sinn F&eacute;in proposal would allow for exemptions for emergency medical service and military flights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#B00500"><p>I thank Senator Boylan.  The Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, will have the final word.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#B00600"><p>Under the current legislative framework there is effectively no scope for Ireland to unilaterally tax commercial aviation fuel used by private jets.  I have given the Senator the background and once there is agreement with another countries, it could be done.  Senator Boylan mentioned that France is considering the introduction of this as well as a debate at the Transport Council in Prague on 20 to 21 October.  We have not seen any specific details but closer to the time, the Minister for Transport, Deputy Eamon Ryan, will certainly respond to that, if that is on the agenda that particular day.</p> <p>The House may be aware, however, that a proposal to revise the energy tax directive is currently being negotiated at EU level and Ireland is actively engaged in these discussions.  One area under consideration during these negotiations is the taxation of fuel used in commercial aviation which would, by definition, include private jets.  There is still a long way to go with this proposal.  However, as one of its essential purposes is to support faster uptake of cleaner fuel by taxing fuels on the basis of energy content, the environmental performance, rather than by volume, it is likely that aviation fuels, including those used by private jets, will fall within the scope of those discussions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#B00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State and Senator Boylan.  </p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.18" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#B00750">Vacant Properties</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#B00800"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.  I also thank the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, for coming to the House this morning to take this Commencement matter.  I am sure he will agree with me that tackling vacancy and dereliction across our cities, towns, villages and rural countryside is something of great importance.  It is a passion of mine.  I have worked constructively since my election to this House and my appointment to the Joint Oireachtas Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage to engage with Department officials and the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy O'Brien, and the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, on a number of proposals, some of which have been acted on and some of which are still under consideration.  I hop that by tabling this Commencement matter this morning, we can move the dial on one particular scheme which has the potential to do a whole lot more.</p><p>In my county of Waterford<i>, </i>we have had tremendous success with schemes such as the repair and lease scheme, the buy and renew scheme and, to a lesser extent, the Living City initiative, which has been extended in budget 2023 to the end of 2027 and which is a welcome move.  The benefits of bringing vacant and derelict buildings back into productive use are huge.  It cleans up streetscapes, provides much-needed homes and is environmentally sound because it results in less carbon as it reuses what is already there.</p><p>The Cro&iacute; C&oacute;naithe towns and villages fund has been very well received across the country.  I understand that local authorities have had very strong interest from prospective property owners looking to bring vacant and derelict properties back into productive use.  With success of television programmes, such as &quot;Room to Improve&quot;, &quot;The Great House Revival&quot; and &quot;Cheap Irish Homes&quot;, we have seen what is possible when we think outside the box in delivering our dream home.</p><p>The obvious difficulty with vacant and derelict properties is that one does not know what is going to be there when one opens the property up.  That is why this scheme, which provides a grant support of up to &euro;50,000, is so welcome.  The fact that it can be combined with measures such as Sustainable Energy Authority of Ireland, SEAI, grants gives people the potential to have a significant portion of the costs of renovation covered through grant aid, which is very important for young individuals and couples in particular who are trying to get their foot on the ladder.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=JohnCummins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Not everybody wants to own or can afford to own a brand-new home in a city or a town.  The target under the scheme of 2,000 properties by the end of 2025 is not ambitious enough.  We should be aiming to deliver a multiple of that but we will not do that if we do not expand the scheme to rural one-off houses and to cities and suburbs.  I hope the Minister of State will be able to give a positive response as to the direction of travel in this space.  The benefit of supporting rural one-off vacant and derelict properties is huge.  It benefits rural communities, brings people back into the areas and supports the services, clubs and schools in those areas.  The ideology within the Department that we should not support the renovation of rural one-off houses, in particular, needs to be consigned to the dustbin, to be quite frank.  We need to be more ambitious with this scheme.  It is an excellent scheme that is there to support first-time buyers in owning their own houses but we need to expand it to our cities and suburbs and to rural one-off houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00200"><p>Thank you Senator Cummins.  I call on the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Fleming, to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00300"><p>I thank Senator Cummins for raising this important issue and allowing me the opportunity to provide an update on this matter.  Pathway 4 of Housing for All sets out a blueprint to address vacancy and make efficient use of our existing housing stock.  Many areas of cities, towns and villages of all sizes face the blight of vacant properties, which, if brought back into use, could add real vibrancy to, and provide new accommodation in, those areas.  The Cro&iacute; C&oacute;naithe towns fund is a key initiative that underpins the policy objectives set out in pathway 4 of Housing for All.  Schemes under this fund, which are delivered by local authorities, will provide new choices for people to live in towns and villages in Ireland through the provision of a grant to support the refurbishment of vacant properties and by providing serviced sites in towns and villages to people in order to build their own homes.</p> <p>On 14 July this year, the vacant property refurbishment grant, funded by the Cro&iacute; C&oacute;naithe towns fund, was launched.  The scheme will be of benefit to those who wish to turn a formerly vacant house or building into their principal private residence.  It is important to note it is not for rental purposes; you must live in the house.  The grant of up to &euro;30,000 is available for the refurbishment of vacant properties for occupation as a principal private residence, including the conversion of a property which was not previously used as residential.  An additional maximum top-up grant of &euro;20,000 is available where the property is confirmed to be derelict, bringing the total grant available for a derelict property up to a maximum of &euro;50,000.  On that, if the house is on the council's derelict register, that is sufficient.  If it is not on the register, the applicant can get a commercial consultant to provide a report stating it is derelict and the local vacant homes officer will then come out and inspect it.  Once that is agreed, it can fall under the scheme.  It does not have to already be on the derelict register.</p> <p>On 21 September, the ready-to-build scheme, also funded by Cro&iacute; C&oacute;naithe towns fund, was launched.  Under the scheme, local authorities will make serviced sites in towns and villages available to potential individual purchasers to build their own homes.  These sites will be available at a discount on the market value of the site for the building of the property for occupation as the principal private residence of the purchaser.  When the fund was launched, a commitment was made to ongoing review of the scheme.  Feedback on the vacant property refurbishment scheme to date has been overwhelmingly positive, with 169 applications submitted up to the start of September.</p> <p>Given that the key objective of pathway 4 of Housing for All is to ensure that houses we already have are being fully utilised, a decision has been made to extend the eligibility of the vacant property refurbishment grant to vacant properties in both our cities and rural areas.  This is a significant development.  I want to take the opportunity to confirm this.  The Minister announced it at the National Ploughing Championships recently.  Both schemes under the Cro&iacute; C&oacute;naithe towns fund will continue to be only for those who intend to occupy the property as their principal private residence.  Officials in the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage will work with the vacant homes officer in each of the local authorities in the coming weeks to update details of this grant, with a view to expanding the scheme.  We hope to have that major expansion available in November of this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I call Senator Cummins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his very positive response to this Commencement matter.  I stand corrected but my understanding from what the Minister previously said in relation to this was that it would be expanded to cities.  However, it was not actually stated that it would be expanded to rural one-off houses.  The fact the Minister of State is confirming that this morning is hugely welcome.  It will be welcomed by local authorities right across the country and by young individuals and couples who are seeking to get their foot on the property ladder.</p> <p>The Minister of State also referenced the flexibility in the top-up amount of &euro;20,000.  That is really positive as well, because there was a misconception at the start that it had to be on the derelict sites register.  The fact that you can get a structural engineer to state that significant structural works need to be carried out to access the additional top-up is hugely welcome.</p> <p>I really want to thank the Minister of State for the positive response.  The fact that it will be open to all derelict and vacant properties across the State will enable us to expand on that 2,000 target up to 2025.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00600"><p>I thank Senator Cummins.  I call on the Minister of State for a final word on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00700"><p>I want to join the Senator in welcoming this good news.  When I was asked to stand in for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage this morning, I spoke at length with officials to confirm the details.  Like everybody in rural areas, as soon as the scheme came out and was extended to villages of 400 or 500 people, we were immediately asked about the derelict houses in rural areas.  This announcement by the Minister that it will be extended to rural areas is fantastic.  They are now working with the vacant homes officers.  Some 25 of the 31 local authorities have full-time vacant homes officers in place; the others need to get one in place urgently.  I would advise people to work with the vacant homes officer in the local authority to progress this scheme.  Discussions are ongoing.  It will be November before the final details are available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00800"><p>I thank the Minister of State and Senator Cummins.</p> <p>While we await the Minister for Senator Buttimer's Commencement matter, I would like to welcome the young people and their teachers in the Gallery.  It is wonderful to have them here.  They are witnessing the part of the day, known as Commencement Matters, where Senators raise particular issues with Ministers and get responses.  They are in the Houses of democracy and I hope some day one of them will be here representing their community.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00825">Early Childhood Care and Education</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00850"><p>I welcome the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#C00900"><p>I would like to welcome the students.  The Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth who is present is responsible for many aspects of their lives.</p><p>The issue I am raising is to do with young children, specifically, the pre-school in the Morning Star National School, Ballyphenane, County Cork, and the fact the pre-school has not be reopened.  I thank the Minister for being here.  It is a testament to the importance of this issue that he is here.  I accept it is not the Minister's direct responsibility, but Tusla's, as I will explain later.  That the Minister is here is a credit to him and underscores the importance he attaches to the matter.  I thank him for that most sincerely.</p><p>I have been contacted by the parents of 15 young boys and girls, aged between three and four, who are waiting to attend pre-school.  As the Minister will know well, early childhood development is very important.  This pre-school has been doing huge work in the area for young children.  I have spoken to the parents and to Mary, the manager of the pre-school.  To say they are frustrated is an understatement.  A small cohort is affected.  As I said, it is 15 students.  However, it is 15 young children who, in some cases, have developmental needs in terms of early development that needs to be progressed.  The issue has been ongoing with Tusla since April of this year.  As the Minister knows, Tusla is required to make the decision.</p><p>What has made the whole matter frustrating and disconcerting is that the pre-school in the exact same room was open until mid-April of this year.  Due to a change of management and a change in use of a room in another school, the existing pre-school in Morning Star National School had to change its <i>modus operandi</i>.  Mary, the manager, used to be based in Glasheen, but that had to close as the room was required.  The opportunity arose for this pre-school to continue in Morning Star National School.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The person in charge is of high calibre, great competency and much experience.  Many of the parents just cannot comprehend the frustration being experienced now with what seems to be bureaucracy by Tusla at one level.  I know the Minister is aware of the situation.  I will describe the situation encountered by a parent whom I will not name.  This person said they were concerned for their child's well-being and his mental health and understands, as a primary schoolteacher, the importance of school for his development.  The communication continued by saying this person's son also has a speech and language delay, that he had made great progress since he had started preschool last year and that it is vital he returns to the school as soon as possible so he does not regress.  This is the core of this issue.  It is about progression and not regression.<br/><br/>I have spoken to many parents who have come to talk to me about this issue, and I thank them.  It is hard to come by places in preschools.  There had been an issue in this case with fire safety, health and safety risk assessment and planning permission.  All those requirements have now been fulfilled and complied with by the management.  Therefore, I hope we can see progress.  Tusla is well aware of this matter and the issues with the building and the fire safety certificate.  I believe there is an exemption from planning permission, an engineer visited the building to undertake a risk assessment, the fire brigade found adequate fire certification and fire exits are <i>in situ</i>.<br/><br/>This is a one-room classroom.  There has been no change of use and it has a planning permission exemption from the city council.  I have spoken to people in City Hall about this issue.  The start date has been pushed back.  We are in the first week of October and there is an urgent need to expedite this matter.  I again thank the Minister for being here and I appreciate his genuine interest.  I am speaking on behalf of the parents and the young boys and girls they are advocating for.  I am also advocating for them in this important matter.  I hope we can see this situation resolved for the sake of the young people themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#D00200"><p>I welcome our guests in the Public Gallery as well and I hope they find their trip to the Oireachtas very interesting.  I thank Senator Buttimer for raising this important issue, for advocating on behalf of the parents of the children attending the Morning Star preschool, and for emphasising the importance of this early education for those children as well as the support it provides for their parents.</p> <p>Tusla is an independent statutory regulator for the sector.  It is wholly responsible for the registration of all early learning and care and school-age childcare services.  Approximately 4,000 early learning and care services and 2,200 school-age childcare services are registered with and inspected by Tusla.  While my Department is responsible for the legislation governing the sector and we do work closely with Tusla, obviously the implementation of the regulations is solely a matter for Tusla.  I am also restricted from intervening in specific cases.</p> <p>It is a legal requirement under the Child Care Act 1991 regulations for those proposing to open an early years service to submit an application for registration with Tusla at least three months before it is proposed to commence operations.  This is to allow sufficient time for the processing and approval of such applications, in line with the relevant statutory requirements.  It is the responsibility of the providers of early years services to ensure they have all the documentation required in place, including fire certificates and planning compliance documents.  Providers should also ensure they are ready for Tusla's fit-for-purpose inspection, if required.  Registration of early years services can be granted only where Tusla is satisfied that the premises, operation and location of the services pose no unmanaged risk to children.  We can all understand why those regulations need to be adhered to.</p> <p>Tusla cannot process applications that do not contain all the required documents, but it does inform providers who submit incomplete applications of any missing documents.  The service then has an extra ten days to submit any outstanding documents.  If it is not possible to provide the documentation sought in that timeframe, the application is closed.  Open applications that are not being updated by providers are a drain on the resources of the early years inspectorate registration team, and this is made clear to all services seeking to apply for registration with Tusla.  Therefore, although the onus does rest with prospective service providers to ensure their applications for registration are fully completed on submission, the inspectorate does work closely with applicants to help new services to open as soon as possible and to allow existing services to grow their capacity.  The requirements and associated timelines for the processing of new registrations to ensure opening by September 2022 have been clearly communicated to the sector.  In the interests of having a fair and transparent policy, therefore, Tusla will only review applications in the order they are received.  This is in line with the organisation's registration policy.</p> <p>My understanding of this case from Tusla is that some documentation was missing when the original application was submitted in August.  Some of those documents remain outstanding.  A revised application for registration was received on 30 September, however, and that is now being progressed based on Tusla's registration process.  Therefore, it is important to say the application is now in train.  It is hoped all relevant documents will now have been submitted.  I suggest, though, that the management of the preschool double-check with the Tusla inspectorate and the city and county childcare committee in Cork that all those documents have been received to ensure there is no delay in this application being addressed and that it can be processed.  It is to be hoped we will soon be able to see this facility for young people in the area reopened for them to resume their ECCE programme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister for being here and for his response.  I accept there was an ongoing issue with some of the documentation.  My understanding, however, is that all this has now been rectified.  Issues were addressed in respect of fire safety and planning and all the requisite documents were submitted.  From talking to the people involved, I believe all these aspects were addressed.  I welcome the Minister's reply.  Notwithstanding that, however, I ask if the application could be backdated to when it was originally submitted rather than having the clock starting at the end of September.  This would help to expedite the situation.</p> <p>As the Minister said, though, it is important there is engagement with Tusla.  I appreciate this.  There is a great need for this to happen.  I will talk again to the people involved to ensure all the relevant documentation has been submitted and that there is clarity in this regard.  The important point here is that I hope Tusla will expedite this matter.  I say this because I think it is a bit unfair to the 15 students and their families that we have a situation where there is now a lacuna in the provision of these education services, when the documentation clearly illustrates there are no health and safety issues and no planning permission is required.  I again thank the Minister wholeheartedly for his reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#D00400"><p>As Senator Buttimer said, it would appear we now have a full application containing all relevant documentation.  This is important and will allow for the application to be processed.  Tusla is aware of the need to work expeditiously to ensure applications are processed, and the agency understands children will not be able to access education until this is done.  Tusla's early years inspectorate is all about providing for the best form of education.</p> <p>Additionally, that we are also now beyond the late summer period when the inspectorate was dealing with a great many registrations will mean it will now have the scope to focus on this application and to get it done.  It is, however, important there is engagement in this regard and that it is clarified that all documents have been provided.  Once that is the case, this application can be processed as expeditiously as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 11.08 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 12 noon.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 11.08 a.m. and resumed at 12 noon.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#K00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#K00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Road Traffic and Roads Bill 2021 &ndash; Second Stage, to be taken at 1.30 p.m. and to adjourn at 3 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the Minister's opening speech not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, with the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 2, Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) (Amendment) Bill 2022 &ndash; Committee Stage (resumed), to be taken at 3 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#K00400"><p>Yesterday, at the Wild Atlantic Words festival hosted in Castlebar, I met a remarkable young woman who I went to school with, Geraldine Lavelle.  Geraldine sustained a very serious injury in an accident a number of years ago and is now paralysed from the neck down.  She was an active fitness person and she cycled and went to the gym regularly.  She was a fantastic athlete as well as being a scientist and an exceptional young woman.  She remains all of those things and has fought her way back from what was a devastating injury.  Yesterday, she published her book entitled <i>Weathering the Storm</i>.  I have not yet had the pleasure of reading it.  It is on my list to read very shortly and I encourage others to purchase it as well.  If ever there was a story of getting through adversity, barriers and everything that could be thrown at someone, this is it.  She lost so much on that particular day and has come back to show that anything is possible if one puts one's mind to it.  I was in college with her sister while Geraldine was the year below me and I know the family very well.  She is an inspirational young woman and has come through so much.  Yesterday, she was rightly acknowledged for her fantastic new book <i>Weathering the Storm</i>.  Geraldine is a regular columnist with <i>The Western People</i>and teaches in the Atlantic Technological University Sligo.  She is, as I said, a scientist as well.</p><p>I congratulate Geraldine on her fantastic success - no doubt the first of many.  She has dedicated much of her time since her injury to helping other people who have acquired a similar injury or paralyses.  She has dedicated her time to helping others to come through the most difficult and devastating thing that can happen to anyone.  I wish her well and congratulate her on the publication of her book.</p><p>A separate matter is the issue around school transport, concessionary and eligible tickets and all that comes with that.  Every year, every single public representative is contacted - particularly in rural areas - by people who do not qualify for the bus because they are not going to the closest school and whatever.  We make it really difficult for people.  In this time of trying to get people out of their cars and onto public transport, we need to move to a system where there is no such thing as eligible or concessionary tickets.  Any student that wants to take a bus should be given the option to do so.  It is simply not safe in many parts of the country to cycle or walk to school, even if one lives quite close, because the cycling and walking infrastructure is not there yet.  Some day it will be.</p><p>I request a debate at the earliest opportunity with the Minister for Education, Deputy Foley, to have a discussion about the future of school transport and how we might move away from concessionary and eligible tickets and move to a system where any student who wants a school bus, can get one.  In my own county of Mayo, we have had particular difficulties as did every other part of the country.  Straide in Mayo was a good example, among others, where people who had a concessionary ticket for many years did not get one this time but are now on a list to do so.  I commend and thank the Minister, Deputy Foley, for securing the extra funds in budget 2023, to bring on stream additional capacity of more buses and more drivers.  I also welcome the decision made by the Minister, Deputy Foley, and the Cabinet to prioritise those students who previously had a concessionary ticket and always availed of the bus service, and to deal with them first.  That was the right decision to make.  I would welcome such a debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#K00500"><p>I welcome our Acting Leader to the House.  Yesterday, the Independent Broadcasters of Ireland held a briefing in Buswells Hotel for Members of the Oireachtas around the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill and the medium-term Future of Media Commission report.  I think we all recognise that local radio plays a huge and important role in urban and rural communities across Ireland.  I commend all those involved in local radio and ask that we as a House have a debate with the Minister on the future of local radio.  We have had the Bill which is going through the Houses of the Oireachtas but yesterday's briefing spoke about a number of very important issues around the broadcasting levy and the implementation of the Future of Media Commission report recommendations on the funding of local radio.  We gave huge acknowledgement to local newspapers with the reduction of VAT so surely it is time, in the context of the broadcasting levy, to look at how we support local radio.  As a Government, we gave money in the budget to RT&Eacute; and TG4 all of which we support, but there is a need to have a look at how we can support independent local radio.</p> <p>My second request is that the Minister of State at the Department of Education with responsibility for special education and inclusion, Deputy Madigan, would come to the House to have a debate on special schools.  Special schools, to my understanding, are not sanctioned for the post of home school liaison officers.  We must give consideration to expanding this position to special schools, which require home school liaison officers far more than any other school community.  It is important.  If we look at why, and who attends our special schools, then the whole issue of home school community is one that we can debate.  Those attending do not have a community of their own.  They come from a myriad of communities.  Again, it is about the scaffolding of support we put around the school, the child and the families of those with special needs.  These pupils deserve the same support as those in a regular school.  I hope the Minister of State will come to the House as a matter of urgency for this very important debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#K00600"><p>I want to thank the Estonian ambassador, H.E. Kairi K&uuml;nka, who set up a visit for me two weeks ago to a number of interesting cybersecurity places in Tallinn for the Louth Meath Education and Training Board to go out and see how a cybersecurity centre of excellence actually operates.  With that in mind, I want to thank the NATO centre which brought us in and showed us its system.  CR14 brought us in and showed us its system.  I also thank CybExer and the Tallinn University of Technology.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What we saw was out of this world and only showed me that we are light years behind a tiny little country such as Estonia.  Sadly, because of other commitments I was not around to engage with the Minister, Deputy Coveney, on defence issues.  I agree with my colleague Deputy Berry that we are a defenceless nation.  We have so much data coming through our economic zone in the Atlantic and who is responsible for it?  It is the Garda.  The Garda does not go to sea.  We do not have a Naval Service that is capable of monitoring what is going on.  We do not have an Air Corps that is capable of monitoring what is going on.  We are, for all intents and purposes, the talk of Europe with our failure to defend not only ourselves but the assets of the European Union that come through our economic zone.</p><p>We also have a situation where soldiers are walking out.  My colleague, Senator Buttimer, is aware that an entire class of Naval Service apprentices has been bought out and they have gone to work for a private company.  This could not happen if we were paying people correctly.  A simple thing that could have been sorted out months, if not years, ago is the working time directive.  People are sitting on their hands doing absolutely nothing about it and we are slowly watching our entire force implode.  It has to stop.</p><p>We have to start taking a serious approach to our defence.  What will happen is the foreign direct investment we are so proud of, and rightly so, will walk out of this country when there is a serious attack one day.  If any one of them is hit and it is found to be our problem, they will walk out of this country and it will devastate places such as my home county.  I know how hard the acting leader works in Galway visiting places and making sure resources are made available.  We have to step up to the plate on defence.  The Garda cannot protect cables under the sea.  We speak about the data being in the cloud.  The cloud is actually under the sea and that is the truth of the matter.  Unless we wake up and start taking care of the assets that are keeping this country front and centre we will lose all of this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L00200"><p>This morning I met a wide-ranging group of community employment supervisors who, because of their plight, had taken the time to come here to meet Sinn F&eacute;in.  I know the acting leader is very familiar with this because, unfortunately, Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il Governments have refused to give any pay increase to these workers for 14 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L00300"><p>No pensions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L00400"><p>They have no pensions.  The starting rates of pay for an assistant community employment supervisor is &euro;11.01.  It will actually be less than the minimum wage come the beginning of next year.  What is most regrettable is that government after government has taken the line handed to it by the Civil Service and repeated it parrot like, that the State is not the employer and that it is up to the employers to give the community employment supervisors a pay rise.  At the same time, if employers dared to give community employment supervisors a pay rise they would be penalised financially.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L00500"><p>Who pays the money?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L00600"><p>Last week we had the budget.  I think the Government told us it spent approximately &euro;11 billion.  Fair play.  The issue with the community employment supervisors would take a fraction of a fraction of that money to resolve.  Once again Government Deputies and, unfortunately, Senators decided they would not do this.  This is a political choice.  This is the point I made to community employment supervisors this morning.  A political choice is being consistently made by Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael to deny these people a pay rise.  Then we think about the work they do.  These people are the glue that holds our communities together.  They began to list all of the work they do and they could have spoke for the rest of the meeting.  They provide meals on wheels services.  These are the workers who were at the front-line during Covid.  They tripled their output during Covid to ensure people got decent hot meals.  Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael were very happy to applaud them but not to give them a pay rise.  That would be going too far.  After 14 years of denial they have been left on poverty pay with no prospect of change.</p> <p>Let us be clear.  This is an eminently solvable issue.  What it is lacking is the political will from the Government to finally tackle it.  What is lacking is recognition of the crucial work these people do not only with meals on wheels but with the Irish Wheelchair Association, in community childcare where they play a massive role, with Enable Ireland, with Cheshire Ireland homes, in recycling, in housing associations and in hospices and hospitals.  This is only the tip of the iceberg in terms of the work they do.  I want the acting leader to acknowledge that this and previous governments have made the wrong political choices with regard to community employment supervisors.  I ask for an urgent debate on the matter.  I want to hear what people have to say on this topic so we can pressurise the Government to do the right thing.  Frankly there is no excuse for 14 years of denying pay rises to some of the most important workers in our communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L00700"><p>Did Senator Gavan acknowledge that the pensions issue has been resolved?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L00800"><p>It was not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L00900"><p>It was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L01000"><p>Talk to the community employment supervisors.  It was a gratuity.  It was pointless.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L01100"><p>Wrong again.  The Senator is misleading the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L01200"><p>They have no pension.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L01300"><p>Senator Sherlock without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L01400"><p>The first thing to say is that it is disgraceful that it has been 14 years since community employment supervisors and all those working in section 56 and section 39 organisations have had a proper pay increase.  It behoves the Government to act urgently to address this long-running sore for those who are providing vital services in our communities.  We all speak at length about how important these services are but these people do not feel respected or appreciated because of the many years since they last saw a pay increase.  I support Senator Gavan's comments in this regard.</p> <p>I welcome the comments made last Saturday by the Minister, Deputy O'Brien, on reviewing and dramatically reforming the build-to-rent planning conditions that exist in this country.  This is a long overdue announcement.  It is something for which we have been calling for a long period of time.  While it may not have huge relevance outside the main urban centres, here in Dublin it is massive.  The only show in town with regard to building anything at present, particularly in the centre of Dublin, is building to rent.  This excludes anybody who wants to buy a home from ever being able to do so.  We have 5,000 build-to-rent units under construction, approved or going through the planning system at this point in time in the small area comprising Dublin 1, Dublin 7 and Dublin 3.</p> <p>My main call this morning is to ask that the Minister come to the House sooner rather than later to set out to us very clearly what he intends to do to bring to an end build-to-rent and to set out the timing.  In September 2020 a report landed on the Minister's desk on bringing to an end the co-living model that was introduced in 2018 under the former Minister, Eoghan Murphy.  It took the Minister until days before Christmas to eventually sign the order.  This gave well over three or four months of a long lead-in time for anybody to rush in a planning application.  In the area I live in, planning applications for co-living that were rushed in during that period have yet to be built.  We cannot have a situation where we have a long lead-in time on making an announcement to reform build-to-rent and then leaving it for many months before it is put into action.  I want the Minister to come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#L01500"><p>This morning I want to discuss again the latest narrative on potential energy shortages.  The Minister with responsibility for energy needs to come to the House for a debate on the issue.  I would like to see the debate focused on the role of the energy companies in this potential and threatened crisis.  I can give a number of examples.  I have been contacted by somebody who installed solar panels and is prepared to supply energy to the grid.  To get this energy accepted and paid for is an unbelievable task.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2464"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2464&amp;amp;pid=PaulDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The power generation company in question has no interest.  It is putting up hurdle after hurdle.  It has changed the format of one form, which has already been submitted and now a new form has to go in.<br/><br/>I have another example of a factory that put a great many panels on its roof and would be in a position to supply an enormous amount of power back into the grid.  That industry closes down at 1 o'clock on Fridays.  One of the directors noticed on his phone, which shows the graph of how much power is being generated, that the line dropped to a straight line across the bottom at 1.30 p.m. on the first Friday the panels were <i>in situ</i>.  When he went to research what was going on, he realised that, unbeknownst to himself, since this was the first time he had ever done anything like this, he had signed a contract containing something called a kill switch.  Therefore, when his machines stopped running and drawing energy, the power company cut off the power.  The power that was then being generated was being dumped.<br/><br/>Do the energy companies want this energy?  We hear about potential shortages and then we hear stories like those.  Why is there even such a thing as a kill switch in such contracts, irrespective of whether or not the person reads the small print, if we are potentially faced with an energy shortage?  The latest narrative is that smart meters would solve all this, that we should all have solar panels and that anyone with a smart meter would be able to put power back into the grid.  Now the narrative on the smart meter is that it will be used only to measure peak-time electricity and that there will be peak-time charges.  Now people are refusing to take smart meters.  The narrative is totally wrong.  The Minister needs to come in and discuss this, but he also needs to sit down with the energy companies because they do not seem to want the power that, according to the story they keep peddling, they do not have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#M00200"><p>I rise today to raise a number of issues.  First, I congratulate the artist Mr. Roger McCarthy, a Limerick-born Cappamore artist, on his contribution to the Limerick Art Society on its 80th anniversary.  He was awarded a silver medal recently at the society's 80th birthday celebrations for his contribution not only to life in Limerick but also to the greater mid-west and to Ireland.  He had a number of students.  I myself was honoured to be one of his students over many years.  He has given his love for arts and culture to many of them.  I congratulate him on the receipt of his medal last week.</p> <p>The second matter I wish to raise is the good news Ryanair announced at Shannon Airport today.  It is good news for the mid-west region.  The airline announced two direct routes from March 2023, one to Newcastle-upon-Tyne and one to B&eacute;ziers, France.  I compliment all at Shannon Airport on the Trojan work they are doing in developing flights from Shannon.  I remind people that Shannon is a fantastic experience and that passengers can go through security and come out the other side in less than 20 minutes.  There are great facilities between parking and everything else on site.</p> <p>Lastly, I know that Senator Kyne is representing the Leader today.  Something I had asked the Leader to follow up on related to the Revenue Commissioners.  Only today I again received an email from a fellow constituent in his 70s who cannot get through to the Revenue Commissioners.  It is a disgrace that a public organisation or a public service is not open to the public.  The Revenue Commissioners have opened up for appointments in both Dublin and Cork.  That should be spread out to the rest of Revenue offices.  It is not good enough that people who want an appointment have to travel to Dublin or Cork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#M00300"><p>This year, Ireland's population will increase by about 90,000 people, the fourth highest annual increase since the Famine.  Some 27,700 of that figure will be due to natural change.  More than 61,000 of the figure is net migration.  This figure, massively inflated from our yearly average, is obviously due to the intake of Ukrainians fleeing the war.  According to figures released by the Government this week, 79% of these people have notified the Government that they will require accommodation.  It is right and honourable that we as a country should help those in need and do all within our power to assist those we can.  It is also the case that attempting to do that which is outside our power ends up serving no one and it is past time we acknowledged the inconvenient truth, rather than accusing anyone voicing it of not caring about Ukrainian people.  These people need long-term homes, secure jobs, education for their children and grassroots ties with their local communities.  There is a limit to how many people we can provide that for, and that limit has already been passed.  There are 10,800 people in emergency accommodation, 60,000 households on local authority housing waiting lists and tens of thousands of young people frozen out of the housing market.  I am not sure what jigsaw the Cabinet is looking at but unlimited inward migration does not appear to fit into the picture the rest of us are looking at.  Today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i>contains a very worrying article.  It relates to thousands of asylum seekers arriving into Dublin Airport with no travel documents.  Between January and July this year, 2,915 people travelled into Dublin Airport and did not produce travel documents to border management officials, meaning they were refused leave to land.  Of those, 2,232, or 77%, then claimed asylum.</p><p>Lastly, many of us have huge concerns about the Department of Defence's misnamed Building the Ecosystem event happening today in the Aviva Stadium, which is actually a military event with international representatives from the arms industry.  The event subheading, &quot;Identifying connections for collaboration in security, defence and dual-use technologies&quot;, does not serve to ease the concerns of many people in this country who sense that our military neutrality is being gradually eroded.  Just whom is Ireland to collaborate on its security with, and to what end?  I caution anyone with ambitions for Ireland to be a key player in the military field that our size and our power makes us more likely to be a pawn than any other piece.  Ireland's neutrality has served us well, and I, alongside many in this country, do not want to see it undermined in service of special interests half a world away.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#M00400"><p>There has been a big increase in antisocial behaviour in Clonmel and the surrounding areas in recent weeks.  This has been brewing for a number of years.  Garda&iacute; are doing their best but their resources are limited.  We have now got to the stage where a young farmer was beaten so badly this week that he almost died.  There is a fear within the community, across Clerihan, Lisronagh and Powerstown, about this and about the inaction there.  Members of the Garda are under pressure themselves but there is a real fear within the community now.  We try to promote stronger, safer communities and this is a prime example of good rural people who need to be protected and safe in their community.</p> <p>A big meeting is to be held tonight at Moyle Rovers GAA club, in Moanroe, that everyone is asked to attend.  I have been working with Councillors John FitzGerald and Michael Murphy and we have been talking to a great many of the concerned residents of the villages and the surrounding area.  Members of the Garda, public representatives and members of the public will be there.  I suggest that, following that meeting, along with me and Councillors Michael Murphy and John FitzGerald, the Minister might meet a delegation of the group that will be there tonight.  There is real concern.  This is a beautiful area just outside Clonmel.  The residents should not have to be in fear of their lives because of the actions of a minority group of people.  Everyone in the area knows who is involved in these acts of terrorising and assaulting people.  We really need the opportunity to meet with the Minister, Deputy McEntee.  I ask Senator Kyne, in his capacity as acting Leader today, to support me in arranging a meeting with the Minister and a select delegation of the group that will be at the meeting tonight, along with Councillors Michael Murphy and John Fitzgerald.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#M00500"><p>I ask that the acting Leader invite into the House the European Commissioner with responsibility for regulation of the medtech area.  Most Members of the House had a meeting yesterday with the Irish Medtech Association and IBEC regarding the approval of medical devices in Europe.  There is a huge backlog in respect of the approval of all these medical devices.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paddy Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1866"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1866&amp;amp;pid=PaddyBurke&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It will have a major effect on the European population because EU regulation systems put patient access to medtech at risk.  These devices are not being approved, and others are being approved at a very slow pace.  A lot of start-up companies are now looking to the USA where FDA approval is much quicker.  This will have a significant effect on Ireland.  In Mayo, we have Baxter, Allergan, Hollister and Meissner, to name just a few.  In the Cathaoirleach's area of Galway, there are a huge number of medical device companies.  This is putting jobs in Ireland, the people who need to use the medical devices and hospitals at risk.  I ask that we consider inviting the Commissioner with responsibility for this area to the House so that we can determine where the backlog or hold-ups are regarding the approval rates which are one in four.  It will take up to 2024 before the backlog is approved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#N00200"><p>I want to raise two issues today.  I wish to flag with the Acting Leader the possibility that we could have statements on a committee report on dog welfare.  People will know that I regularly raise issues around dog welfare in the House.  The Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine will produce a report next week which has nine powerful recommendations.  I would welcome a debate on the report in the House.</p> <p>I also wish to raise the fact that this Saturday is migratory bird day.  The theme for this year is light pollution, something that is very close to my heart because we are seeing a proliferation of LED billboards around Dublin city.  One in Rathmines made the airwaves recently because of how bright it is.  These billboards have an impact on migrating birds.  Ireland lies on the east Atlantic flyway for migrating birds.  Natural darkness has a conservation value to them in the same way as clean water, air and soil.  This year's migratory birds day is to raise awareness of light pollution and its negative impact on those birds.  We know it is increasing, with the number of artificially lit outdoor areas rising by 2.2% per year from 2012 to 2016.  </p> <p>There are solutions to reducing light pollution, which include ensuring that environmental impact assessments are conducted for projects that can result in light pollution.  Some cities have taken the step of banning LED billboards and are looking at the type of public lighting they have.  We need to update outdoor lights to ensure they are fully shielded so that the light shines down rather than up towards the sky.  We need to invest in lights that are on a timer and motion detector to reduce their overuse, as well as minimising blue light emissions by switching to warm coloured light bulbs.  These are measures that I hope we will take on board in this country, given Ireland's importance as part of the pathway for migratory birds.  We are in the middle of a biodiversity crisis.  We have a citizens' assembly on it and we need to do everything we can to protect nature.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#N00300"><p>I would like to ask for a debate with the Minister for Education regarding the Access programmes rolled out in our schools, and the suitability and vetting of the programmes and the persons running, facilitating and funding them.  Schools throughout the country are currently availing of a programme run by Drinkaware.  While it has good and useful material on its website, it is a charity funded by the drinks industry.  It is going into schools and putting out a programme that is about education on alcohol and alcohol reduction.  However, there is no transparency as to the content of that programme.  The fact it is going into schools has in the past 24 hours been condemned by the Taoiseach and the HSE, as well as organisations such as the Irish Community Action on Alcohol Network, ICAAN, which is funded by the HSE.  ICAAN is headed up by Paula Leonard and provides great supports to drugs and alcohol task forces around the country, and would be well placed to run programmes in schools.  There seems to be automatic access.  The detail of the programme which has been rolled out has been sought on several occasions and is not being provided.  There needs to be transparency about the programmes that are run and the suitability of the organisations which run them and have access to young people.</p> <p>I am involved with the Dublin 12 drugs and alcohol task force which, along with Canal Communities, put out a video earlier this year and did a research project on the availability of alcohol in various areas.  The availability of alcohol has increased by over 100% or 200%.  For people who are recovering, a simple walk between where they go to for support and their home may involve passing several outlets selling alcohol.  The proliferation in the sale of alcohol is enormous. </p> <p>It is not appropriate that Drinkaware runs programmes in school without transparency.  We had an issue with inappropriate autism sentiments in schoolbooks last year and the books were withdrawn.  There does not seem to be any regulation in the Department of Education as to what and who has access to our schools.  I would like a debate on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#N00400"><p>I would like to raise the issue of the victims of thalidomide, the effect it has had on their lives and the fact that they have never received an apology or compensation from the State.  This is one of the scandals that will eventually be dealt with, but the sad reality is that the community which has been affected is getting smaller and smaller all the time.</p> <p>These are people who were born to women who took the drug during pregnancy.  There are two tragedies.  The first is the women who took the drug and the guilt they felt and still feel as a result of what happened to their children.  The second tragedy is the thousands of lives that have been destroyed throughout the world and the people left with no compensation, apology or recognition.  I call on the Acting Leader to organise a debate in the House with the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, so that, for once and for all, a pathway can be put in place for a State apology, compensation and access to proper medical supports such as medical cards and other supports which these people need.  </p> <p>These people are getting older.  Some have died and many others are very unwell.  We have a moral responsibility to deal with this issue.  I commend the Scottish Administration which has addressed the issue.  Let us be a leader and let Ireland be the next country to apologise and put the necessary supports in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#N00500"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#N00600"><p>It is five weeks since we discussed children returning to school and the lack of school transportation.  The matter has not yet been solved and is a major issue for many people throughout rural Ireland.  In my part of the world, children in Rossmore, Newcestown, Dunderrow, Nohoval and Ballinhassig have all contacted us in the past week seeking clarification on the Minister's announcement last week regarding putting money aside to put in place a scheme that ensures children can get to school.  There is a complete vacuum of information.</p> <p>It is coming up to the mid-term break at this stage.  Families are struggling trying to get kids to school.  Children need access to education.  A lady emailed my office yesterday to tell us she was unable to take her child to school because her husband was working abroad and she was not in a position to travel.  That child did not go to school yesterday because of the lack of a school bus ticket.  The child has been on the school bus for the past three years.  </p> <p>There are issues with three cohorts of children.  The first comprises those who applied in February, but then received a subsequent email because the scheme had changed and, as a result, they did not get onto the list.  The second are first years, who are considered to be in a different bracket because they were not previously on a bus.  The third cohort comprises late applicants.  This is all about trying to get kids to school in an appropriate and safe manner.  </p> <p>We have changed the rules and taken school bus passes from children who had them.  Families are struggling.  We need a solution.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If nothing will be done, we need to tell the parents.  If there is a policy change that needs to be enacted, let us enact it but we need to have a timeline.  We have no timeline and because of that, kids all over the country are waiting at a crossroads for a bus that will never turn up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#O00200"><p>I thank the Senators for their contributions.  We started and finished with Senators Chambers and Lombard, respectively, regarding school transport issues.  Both request a debate with the Minister, Deputy Foley, on this.  We welcome the &euro;13 million additional funding in the budget for school transport.  I agree that there are many children and parents not knowing where they stand.  Senator Chambers talked about getting rid of the whole issue of concessionary tickets and eligibility and ensuring that there is a bus place for all school-going children who want one.  Senator Lombard talked about people who are still none the wiser five weeks after the announcement that something will be done.  I am dealing with those cases myself, so I certainly call on the Minister, Deputy Foley, to come in before us to discuss this at the earliest opportunity.  Senator Chambers also talked about her friend and neighbour, Geraldine Lavelle, and wished her well on her new book, titled, <i>Weathering the Storm</i>.  I will look out for that as well in bookshops.</p><p>Senator Buttimer spoke about independent broadcasters, the broadcasting levy and the future of radio.  I will request that we have a debate on this issue.  All of us, particularly rural Senators, would know the importance of local radio stations.  At times of Covid, local radio was important for everything, whether it be Sunday Mass, the death notices, sports results or coverage of local sporting games.  Local radio is hugely important across the regions.  The levy they pay is a regulatory levy.  There is some concern that if you scrap it entirely it will not be fair to other bodies, whether it be teachers or others, who also pay regulatory levies and there is a principle there.  It is certainly a burden on local radio.  If it can be reduced, at the very least, that would be welcome.  Senator Buttimer also called for a debate on disability matters and I will request that from the Minister of State, Deputy Madigan.</p><p>Senator Craughwell raised cybersecurity and defence.  Unfortunately, he could not make the debate during the week on the Defence Forces because he was abroad.  The Minister, Deputy Coveney, was here and gave a good outline of the present status of the action plan, the commission report and what Cabinet has agreed.  I note that in the past 24 hours, at the PDFORRA conference, he announced measures to increase the pay rates for private three-star naval seamen in the first three years of service, starting at &euro;34,798 in year one, &euro;36,128 in year two and &euro;37,253 in year three of service.  He also referenced the recently agreed extension to the Building Momentum pay agreement which, if ratified, would further improve members&rsquo; pay and allowances to the order of 6.5% over 2022 and 2023.  In recognition of a particular concern raised at the conference, that Defence Forces personal daily ration allowance should be raised to reflect present-day inflation prices, the Minister, Deputy Coveney, announced an increase in the daily ration rate of 52%.  All of that is welcome.  Senator Craughwell raised a number of other issues.  As I said, the action plan on the report that has been commissioned will see priority in relation to radar and increases in personnel within the Naval Service and our forces.  I certainly welcome that.  On cybersecurity, obviously, the Minister is aware of the matter.  Reference was made to the underground cables.  It is hugely important that we are able to defend them.  If he has any particular issues in mind, the Senator might be able to raise these in a Commencement debate.</p><p>Senator Gavan talked about community employment, CE, supervisors having had no pay increase for 14 years.  In February, the Government welcomed the decision of the CE supervisors and assistant supervisors on voting in favour of ending the long-running dispute regarding pensions.  They will receive an <i>ex-gratia</i>payment at an overall cost of &euro;24 million.  I know there is still an issue with the rural social scheme, RSS, and T&uacute;s, but I will contact the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, for a debate on the area.  Obviously, no more than the section 39 organisations that I raised here myself recently, not having a pay increase for 14 years for any sector, particularly very important community sectors and all those involved in disability services, such as Ability West, is not good enough.  I will request debate on that.</p><p>Senator Sherlock requested that the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O&rsquo;Brien, come into the Chamber to discuss issues regarding build-to-rent planning and reforms in that.  I will certainly request an overall debate in housing.  We have not had the Minister in for a while to discuss housing and Housing for All.</p><p>Senator Daly spoke about energy issues, which are absolutely crucial and vital.  The EirGrid report stated there is a shortfall of supply over demand for the next decade.  The statement published described the situation as stark and serious.  EirGrid&rsquo;s chief executive talked about a tight winter ahead and could not guarantee that there would be no blackouts.  There are a number of issues, including the performance of existing power plants as poor.  Some 590 MW have been taken out of the system.  Some 630 MW of power, which was contracted to come from new plants, has failed to materialise, as developers have pulled out.  There have been technical and planning difficulties causing delays.  Senator Daly also talked about something I had not heard of, the &ldquo;kill switch&rdquo;.  The Senator can table a Commencement matter on that.  However, I will request the Minister to come in to discuss issues related to that.  That makes no sense.  There may be technical reasons involved relating to storage, but I do not know what they would be.  If power has been generated and not collected and stored in the grid, that makes no sense.</p><p>Senator Maria Byrne congratulated Mr. Roger McCarthy on his service to the Limerick Art Society.  She also welcomed the two new direct Ryanair routes from Shannon to Newcastle and Beziers.  I agree that Shannon is an excellent airport.  It has a quick throughput, whether it be for pre-clearance to the United States or for general security.  It is very handy.  Together with Ireland West Airport, it is certainly my first port of call, if possible, for a break away.  They provide an excellent service.  The Senator also asked that we contact Revenue regarding the opening of public offices.  There are some things that are still delaying a resumption on normality post-Covid.  People being able to meet with Revenue officials to discuss their issues in public should be provided in all offices, particularly outside of Dublin and Cork.</p><p>Senator Keogan talked about the intake of Ukrainians, long-term homes and limits to how many people we can accommodate.  I am proud of the response of the Irish people in government on a humanitarian issue where people had to flee their homes.  We have all seen the television footage of what is going on in Ukraine and the atrocities that have been committed in Bucha and other areas.  I am proud that the European Union and Ireland have stood up and welcomed people.  People have welcomed others into their own homes and offered accommodation.  I do not think we are taking away from Irish people, as the Senator put it.  There is a housing situation and I accept that but it is not caused by Ukrainians.  They have been welcomed into people&rsquo;s homes.  They have been provided with accommodation in hotels and other buildings.  We need long-term solutions and the Government is looking at modular homes.  However, I agree that we need to also provide, as far as I am concerned, modular homes to deal with the housing situation across the board.  We do not need to have a &ldquo;them versus us&rdquo; fight.  Many good people have come to this country.  In addition, we have shortages of people.  We are crying out for nurses, home care assistants and staff for nursing homes up and down the country.  We need people, thankfully, because we have full employment.</p><p>Senator Ahearn talked about the big increase in antisocial behaviour in Clonmel and said the people involved are known.  That is good in one way, but it is about trying to ensure they are apprehended.  There is a meeting tonight on that.  I certainly will convey his request to the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, to meet with a delegation from the public meeting to discuss issues of antisocial behaviour.  Obviously, allocations of Garda within the country is a matter for the Garda Commissioner.  In the recent budget, we increased the funding for new Garda as well, which is important, by more than 800, excluding retirement.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There will be a net increase in the number of garda&iacute; allocated and deployed across the country.</p><p>Senator Burke talked about the Irish medtech meeting yesterday, which I also attended, and called for a meeting with the European Commissioner to discuss the issue.  I will certainly ask that the issue be raised with the Commissioner although it might be more appropriately discussed at the Joint Committee on Health or the Joint Committee on Enterprise, Trade and Employment.  Certainly, I would be concerned that jobs are being put at risk.  There is a new European directive on licensing.  All existing products have to go through a new approval process so there is a backlog and I agree that it has to be resolved.  The deadline is March 2024 but there is a backlog.  Innovative medtech companies are concerned about the impact here.  </p><p>Senator Boylan talked about the fact that the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine will be producing a report on dog welfare and I look forward to that.  Perhaps we will get an opportunity to discuss it at a later date.  She also talked about the impact of light pollution on migratory birds.  This is an interesting issue and one that could be debated in the Seanad or at the relevant Oireachtas committee in the context of our heritage and additional resources for the National Parks and Wildlife Service, NPWS.  </p><p>Senator Seery Kearney called for a debate with the Minister for Education on the vetting of programmes rolled out in schools.  She referenced Drinkaware, a charity funded by the drinks industry, and argued that there is no transparency regarding what it does.  I will certainly request that debate.  I agree with the Senator's point about the numerous outlets selling alcohol.  A former Minister of State at the Department of Health, Marcella Corcoran Kennedy, put in place legislation regulating the visibility of alcohol products in off licences and supermarkets.  It is now less visible than it was previously but it is still visible.  There is no doubt that the ease of access to alcohol is of concern around the country.  I will ask the Minister to look at this in the context of Drinkaware and other bodies that have access to schools and to the minds of our children.</p><p>Senator Conway raised the important issue of thalidomide.  RT&Eacute; aired a "Scannal" documentary on the issue during the week, which I have not seen yet but I will watch it on the RT&Eacute; Player.  There are a small number of survivors of thalidomide - approximately 40, I believe - and very few of their parents still survive.  I can only imagine the guilt that parents felt, through no fault of their own.  Thousands of lives have been impacted.  I understand that there is a big possibility of a legal bill to defend cases.  It would be a shame if we spent millions upon millions of euro to defend cases rather than using that money to provide some comfort to the affected families.  Perhaps there could be stand-alone legislation to provide supports for people who suffered because of thalidomide.  There were no medicine licensing boards at that time but nevertheless, people were impacted through no fault of their own and the State should acknowledge that and provide support to the survivors and those impacted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.70" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.71" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 12.54 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 1.30 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 12.54 p.m. and resumed at 1.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#T00100">Road Traffic and Roads Bill 2021: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.73" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#T00300"><p>I am honoured to bring the Bill before the Seanad.  It is a substantial Bill that addresses a wide range of necessary areas of legislation and meets a number of commitments in the programme for Government.  The Bill will contribute a great deal to improvements on our roads and, above all, to greater safety for all road users.</p> <p>In the programme for Government, we committed to legislating for e-scooters and e-bikes.  We also committed to addressing the menace of the anti-social use of scramblers and other vehicles.  The Bill will address all of these issues.  It does a great deal more as well.  Among the major issues addressed are necessary legislation to underpin delivery of the BusConnects project and to enable the introduction by Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, of dynamic traffic management on the M50.  It also has measures which address uninsured driving by significant and necessary amendments to existing legislation on the database of insurance policies.  It updates the law in areas such as driving instruction, medical fitness to drive and the system of fixed-charge notices issued by traffic wardens.</p> <p>I wish to acknowledge the role and contribution of the many people and organisations who have contributed to the development of the Bill.  In particular, it benefited from the work of the Oireachtas joint committee through the pre-legislative scrutiny process, and from the debates in the D&aacute;il.  I note the very constructive advice received from the Data Protection Commissioner in our efforts to ensure that measures such as those on the motor insurance database comply with data protection requirements.</p> <p>All road traffic law is ultimately intended to contribute to safety on our roads.  We have made great progress on road safety in the past 25 years.  In 1997, the last year before our first national road safety strategy, 472 people died on Irish roads.  In 2021, there were 137 deaths, the lowest on record.  Inevitably, there have been ups and downs.  Some years have seen increases on the preceding years and it is getting harder to reduce deaths further.  Last December, we published our new road safety strategy, covering the years from 2021 to 2030.  In line with the programme for Government, this strategy has a focus on vulnerable road users in particular, and is committed to Vision Zero, the EU target of zero deaths and serious injuries on European roads by 2050.  The strategy aims to reduce deaths and serious injuries by 50% by the end of the decade.</p> <p>I mentioned vulnerable road users.  This applies particularly to people who are walking and cycling.  We want to encourage active and healthy modes of travel, which are not only better for general health and well-being but are also more sustainable as we face the great challenge of climate change.  If we are serious about encouraging active travel, we have to make sure that it is safe.  There is no doubt that one of the biggest deterrents to people switching to active travel is concern about safety.  </p> <p>As regards the contents of the Bill, first, it seeks to deliver micromobility and legalise the system in respect of powered personal transporters.  Road traffic legislation covers a multitude of issues and no Bill can address everything, but anyone who has examined this Bill will agree that it is ambitious and addresses a wide range of issues.  Micromobility options such as e-scooters and e-bikes have an important role to play in a future sustainable transport mix.  E-scooters have become very popular in recent years, both in Ireland and abroad. As a new mode of transport, they have inevitably raised legal questions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Eamon Ryan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2028"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2028&amp;amp;pid=EamonRyanGP&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The questions revolve around, first, where they fit into current road traffic law and, second, how we want them to fit in in future.  The answer to the first question is simple.  Under current law, electric scooters meet the definition of "mechanically propelled vehicles".  This means they cannot be used in a public place without tax, insurance and an appropriate driving licence.  Since it is not possible to tax e-scooters because they are not type-approved, and as there is no appropriate category of driving licence for them, e-scooters are currently illegal for use on the public road.  We want to change that.  We also want to take into account the possibility of other related forms of micromobility options appearing in the future.  To do this, the Bill will establish a new vehicle category, called powered personal transporters, PPTs.  This new category not only captures e-scooters but also allows for other new and innovative micromobility vehicles that may need regulation in years to come.  To be clear, these provisions will not apply to mobility scooters and the existing legislative framework for those vehicles will not be affected.</p><p>The Road Traffic Acts provide definitions of various types of vehicles and provide powers to regulate their construction, equipment and use.  As with other classes of vehicles, the creation of the new PPT class will allow for the regulation of their construction, equipment and use.  Amendments to a number of provisions in existing road traffic legislation will clarify where those provisions do or do not apply to PPTs.  Senators may wish to note that, in some important respects, PPTs will be treated similarly to bicycles.  As with bicycles, registration, licensing, taxation and insurance will not be required.  Once the Bill has been enacted, regulations governing technical standards and use of e-scooters will be made.  The provisions in this Bill relating to e-scooters will be commenced in tandem with the completion of those regulations.  This will ensure a full legislative framework governing e-scooters can be implemented from the day the regulations are signed into law.  Until that time, use of e-scooters in public places will continue to be illegal.</p><p>The regulations will set out minimum vehicle standards for e-scooters to ensure they are safe to use and environmentally friendly.  When technical standards are introduced in EU member states, a minimum 12-week standstill period is triggered to allow the Commission and the other EU member states time to assess the national draft rules in light of EU competition rules.  This process prevents regulatory barriers to the free movement of goods and information services in the Union.  This necessary and binding delay allows Ireland to meet our EU obligations under the Single Market transparency directive but also means regulations cannot be introduced immediately after the passage of the Bill.  My Department is committed to progressing the regulations to publication as quickly as possible.  I am of course aware there is interest in the legislation around e-scooters.  There have been many views expressed on such questions, such as where the use of e-scooters should be permitted, whether there should be an age limit, and whether the use of helmets and other personal protective equipment should be required.  These are all matters that, in line with the way such matters are addressed for other vehicles, will be addressed in the regulations governing e-scooters and not in primary legislation in the Bill.  I add that it is our intention that regulations will provide for e-scooters to be for use by one person only and they will not be permitted to transport goods.  This is a matter of safety for people using them and for others in their vicinity.  Other issues that have raised interest, such as regulation of e-scooter rental schemes, are not appropriate to road traffic and roads legislation.  The Department of Transport has no function in regard to such commercial enterprises.  Instead, the governance of any such schemes would be a matter for the local authorities in question.</p><p>In addition to addressing the regulation of e-scooters, the Bill will also provide much-needed legal clarity for the growing cohort of e-bike users in Ireland by defining the requirements for low-powered e-bikes and high-powered e-bikes.  Low-powered e-bikes, also known as pedelecs, are assisted by pedalling and can reach speeds of up to 25 km/h.  We will continue to treat this kind of e-bike in the same way as an ordinary pedal bicycle, and the rules of the road for bicycles will apply accordingly.  This type of e-bike will not require registration, taxation, or licensing.  High-powered e-bikes, which are those that can be used without pedalling or those that can reach speeds in excess of 25 km/h, will be treated in the same way as light mopeds and therefore will need to be registered, taxed and insured, and used only by an appropriately licensed driver.  This is because these e-bikes are capable of speeds up to 100 km/h in some cases and present much greater danger to the user and to other vulnerable road users.  This approach allows us to take advantage of the existing legislative framework for mopeds and motorbikes in the Road Traffic Acts and in other legislation in respect of registration, driver training and licensing and so avoids the need to establish new bodies to carry out these vital functions.  It also aligns our national rules for e-bikes with the approach taken in other jurisdictions and with the type-approval framework established in Regulation (EU) No. 168/2013, which sets out the rules for two- and three-wheeled vehicles.  As we already have a legislative framework in place for bicycles and for light mopeds, the provisions governing e-bikes will come into effect as soon as the Bill is signed into law and subsequent regulations will not be needed.</p><p>We also committed in our programme for Government to address the antisocial use of scramblers, quads and other similar vehicles.  This is a longstanding problem that can range from a nuisance to a serious danger to health and to life.  People who use these vehicles in shared public amenities can ruin the use of those amenities for the communities the amenities are meant to serve.  We can all agree we want to put a stop to any such behaviour.  Getting the legislation right has not been easy, and I acknowledge the personal input of the Attorney General in arriving at the measures we are proposing.  What we will do operates on three levels.  First, there will be a new power to specify in regulations that certain types of vehicles are banned from certain areas.  This will allow the flexibility needed to deal with this problem on an evolving basis.  Second, there will be a new Garda power to seize and dispose of vehicles, whether at the scene of an offence or at the location where the vehicle is kept.  This is important because it is often the case that garda&iacute; cannot actually intercept a scrambler or quad where it is being misused without risking the safety of bystanders, or indeed of the rider.  Third, we will be amending the offence of dangerous driving so it will apply in all locations and not just in a public place.</p><p>I do not have time to go through the entirety of the measures I have in my speech.  Suffice it to say the legislation is important to give us the powers to give us BusConnects projects around the country.  As I said at the outset, it allows us to introduce enhanced traffic management systems for our motorway operating services, especially variable speeds on the M50, and to put up displays in that regard.  The Bill has significant provisions linking driver licence and vehicle ownership records that will again be of huge benefit in the efficient Garda use of our traffic management and regulation systems.  It will deliver completion of a national motor insurance database that will be hugely significant in reducing the cost of insurance, getting greater certainty and ensuring we operate within the general data protection regulation.  This is significant legislation and I commend it to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022100600002#U00200"><p>This is a great day for road traffic in Ireland.  This is badly needed legislation, especially given the increased use of e-scooters, e-bikes, etc.  I congratulate the Minister and his team on the work to date.</p> <p>There are a few different points I wish to raise around the Bill itself.  Section 56 of Part 15 relates to zero emission vehicles Ireland, ZEVI.  I looked up the website and it looks good and is impressive, but all the information there is about e-cars.  I spent more than 14 years on the modal shift and working with schoolchildren in rural and urban areas throughout Clare, Galway and Limerick.  To think we are going to focus on e-cars replacing petrol and diesel ones deeply upsets me.  We must give space back to people.  It does not matter what a car runs on.  It is not the Green wish.  We are being accused of trying to get everybody into e-cars, but that was never our wish.  The figure of 1 million e-cars was thrown out there way before we got into Government and it is really important to look at what it means to have an electric vehicle and what ZEVI's role might be.</p> <p>I live in the middle of nowhere in rural Ireland but I do not think e-cars are the only solution we have, even in rural areas.  In urban areas especially it is madness because the more urban the area, the more you are fighting for space.  It therefore makes much more sense to think about other things like e-cargo bikes for deliveries.  Outside my office I see DPD has copped on to that.  It has given up on driving trucks around to deliver and is using e-cargo bikes.  This is a game-changer.  That is great in Dublin but in Ennis I still see trucks driving through the small narrow streets.  We have those sorts of streets in most towns and villages and so we need to look at the whole e-cargo bike option.  I see it in some places in Dublin, perhaps in better-off areas and really built-up ones, but we need to look at how we see EVs as part of the solution.  It is not just about cars.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-06a.77" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>