<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500003#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator David Cullinane that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to outline the plans in place to create a level playing pitch for the south east in relation to regional grant aid with the BMW region and the concrete steps taken by his Department in 2014 to help to create and sustain jobs in Waterford city and county.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Thomas Byrne of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to ensure the structure of water charges to be implemented by Irish Water takes account of the extra costs incurred by those consumers with a hard water supply.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Jim D'Arcy of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, in view of the drop in price for beef from the factories in the past few weeks and its implications for Food Harvest 2020 in relation to farmer confidence and stocking levels, to consider bringing all stakeholders together at an emergency beef summit to discuss the situation and find a way to move forward.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Deirdre Clune of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources to address the concerns of the Irish Postmasters Union regarding the future viability of the post office network.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Fidelma Healy Eames of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to ensure Irish homeowners are given first right of refusal and a window of time to buy back their own mortgage from any bank selling its loan book and failing that, to ensure any new foreign bidder buying Irish mortgages has to conform to the Central Bank's code of conduct for mortgages.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators David Cullinane, Thomas Byrne, Jim D&rsquo;Arcy and Deirdre Clune they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senator Fidelma Healy Eames may give notice on another day of the matter she wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500003#B00200">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500003#B00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 46, motion No. 7, on the Supplementary Order Paper, a Private Members' motion, which is in substitution for No. 46, motion No. 7 on today's Order Paper, to be taken at 3.45 p.m. and conclude not later than 5.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500003#B00400"><p>I have endeavoured to get the Minister for transport to come into the House.  We are all aware of the specific issue with the Aer Lingus pension scheme which is ongoing.  All of us hope industrial action can be averted in this instance, but the Minister's response to the chairman of the Retired Aviation Staff Association, Mr. Arthur McSweeney, who represents thousands of retired workers in Aer Lingus, the Dublin Airport Authority and what was SR Technics was not helpful.  The RASA wrote to the Minister on 11 January seeking a meeting with him to put forward its case and the Minister's private secretary wrote back on 20 February.</p> <p>The letter stated:<blockquote><br />I refer to your letter dated 11<sup>th</sup>January 2014 regarding your request for a meeting.  [There was no apology for the almost eight-week delay in responding.] <br />Due to a heavy schedule of existing commitments, the Minister is not in a position to facilitate a meeting.<br />Yours sincerely,</blockquote>No wonder we are in this difficulty in regard to Aer Lingus and the pending industrial action when the Minister will not even meet the stakeholders involved.  Will the Leader request that the Minister meet the Retired Aviation Staff Association?</p><p> Before the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, puts his two big feet in it again in regard to his new tax, universal health insurance, which will cost every adult in this State &euro;1,600 per year, can we have a proper debate in the House?  I know a paper has gone from the Minister to his Cabinet colleagues and I understand from media reports, whether true or not, that it has not met with a favourable response from many of them and that it lacks the detail required.  I remind Members that people are already paying for health insurance and for access to the health system through their normal taxes.  I cannot understand how the Minister can say adults should pay &euro;1,600 extra per year for what is, effectively, compulsory health insurance.  When he is ready, the Minister needs to come forward with a plan to be discussed in the House.  Will the Leader request that of him?</p><p> I raise a specific and important matter in regard to the drug payment scheme and I ask that the Leader, through his good offices, support my request in this regard.  I received a letter from a 50-year-old woman who has been suffering from multiple sclerosis for the past eight years.  She said that a year and a half ago she was put on a trial drug called Fampyra by her consultant, which aids walking.  She said she has found this drug very beneficial and that it helps her to lift her foot and prevent her from falling.  She said she and her husband recently learned the shocking news that the HSE will not fund this drug from July 2014 and, to add insult to injury, it will not be available under the drug payment scheme but that it will be available privately at an approximate cost of &euro;280 per month.  As she has had to give up nursing and as her husband-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C00200"><p>That is more suitable for an Adjournment debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C00300"><p>-----is her carer, she asks how can they be expected to fund this from their own restricted means.  She said she finds it very stressful to deal with this on top of having a debilitating illness that has devastated their lives.  This is the reality of what is happening in our health service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C00400"><p>You are way over time.  You have to be fair to every Member of the House.  Do you have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C00500"><p>I will conclude.  This is the reality of what is happening in our health service.  This 50-year-old woman has multiple sclerosis and cannot afford a drug which improves her quality of life and standard of living.  All I ask is that the Leader use his good offices to impress on the Minister the importance of including this drug, Fampyra, in the drug payment scheme from July 2014.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C00600"><p>Last week, as Deputy Leader, I dealt with a number of issues around the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission, the response of the Government to the GSOC controversy and, on Thursday, the dossier that was provided by Sergeant Maurice McCabe.  I said at that point that we should have a debate on policing generally and I would like to renew the call for such a debate.  I know they have not yet been confirmed but I would like to welcome the reports today from Cabinet that a barrister-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C00700"><p>It is pathetic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C00800"><p>-----will be appointed to conduct a scoping inquiry into the dossier and the allegations of the whistleblower.  Let us not forget that a similar scoping inquiry by Shane Murphy SC led to the setting up of the Morris tribunal.  It is entirely appropriate that that sort of independent review is carried out now without ruling out the possibility of a commission of investigation under 2004 Act in the future if the claims made, which are very serious, are warranted to be serious and substantiated enough to be investigated.  These go back many years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C00900"><p>The Minister has had the complaints for two years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500004#C01000"><p>I recommend that colleagues who did not see last night's "Prime Time" programme on this issue watch it, because it really clarified a number of issues, and Maurice McCabe was very impressive in providing the transcript, which the "Prime Time" team showed.  Serious allegations have been made and I am really glad to hear reports from Cabinet that an independent review will be conducted as a sort of scoping inquiry without ruling out a fuller commission of investigation in the future, as we saw with the Morris tribunal.</p> <p> In addition, I welcome the result of the Constitutional Convention at the weekend.  It was a real pleasure and privilege to be there for the final weekend session of the Constitutional Convention.  There was a good attendance of all citizens and political representatives and it was great to see 85% of the convention delegates voting in favour of strengthened protection for economic, social and cultural rights in the Constitution.  A recommendation will go to the Government regarding a referendum on that issue and I very much hope it will be supported by the Government.  I again ask the Leader, who I acknowledge already has agreed to do this, for a debate on the final report of the Constitutional Convention as soon as it is published.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500005#D00200"><p>I am happy to take up where Senator Bacik left off by acknowledging with her and, I am sure, other Members of the House, the extraordinary work of the Constitutional Convention.  I particularly welcome its decision to recommend to the Government, by 85% as the Senator noted, the strengthening of the protection of economic, social and cultural rights in the Constitution.  My experience of being there this weekend is that we are in a new era called the human rights era.  There was very little effort to work towards that recommendation.  People, both citizens and politicians and regardless of party or political affiliation, understood that all basic human rights are to be protected.  One point I learned in particular and which was highly persuasive in respect of presentations was that were the people to vote to incorporate a strengthening of these rights into the Constitution, that largely would be a guidance for lawmakers.  It would be a guidance for them, again regardless of from what political ideology one comes, to ensure greater protection for these basic rights and I really welcome that.</p><p>The other point I wish to make is how much I admire the tenacity with complexity and the openness of mind, especially of the citizens, as well as their participation in those debates.  These characteristics of tenacity and openness of mind are great characteristics for politicians to emulate and as Senator Bacik mentioned, I wish to confirm with the Leader that this report from the Constitutional Convention will be debated in the Seanad.</p><p>Second, I refer to a question I will have for the Leader.  I echo the dismay expressed by allies, institutions and governments all around the globe and state categorically that I regard the long-threatened anti-same-sex legislation signed into law yesterday in Uganda as institutionalising hatred and sabotaging efforts of human rights and health work.  For example, in the case of life imprisonment if one marries someone of the same gender, were I in Uganda I would be heading to prison.  Similarly, in respect of seven years' imprisonment for directors of lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender, LGBT, advocacy groups, I note that were one a member of the Gay and Lesbian Equality Network, GLEN, LGBT Noise or even of the Irish Council for Civil Liberties, ICCL, or the Free Legal Advice Centres, FLAC, one would be heading to prison for seven years in Uganda.  Consequently, I ask the Leader to convey to the T&aacute;naiste the desirability of amplifying Ireland's voice at the Human Rights Council in this regard and of formulating a response to extreme legislation of this sort at international level.  As the courage to speak of sexual and gender diversity increases in hostile societies, so too does the incidence of extreme prohibitive law-making, as seen in Russia, Nigeria and now Uganda.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500005#D00300"><p>I agree with what my colleague, Senator Bacik, had to say about the possibility of a scoping inquiry being a good idea.  I certainly do not believe one should rush into commissions of inquiry until there has been a chance to get greater clarity than has been achieved to date regarding what precisely has been going on.  Everyone agrees the reports from whistleblowers and indeed about whistleblowing within the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na are extremely concerning.</p><p>I wish to raise a parallel issue and welcome Senator Bacik's call for a debate on policing and the work of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in this regard.  Were concerns expressed within the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na about the closure of rural Garda stations and the impact that might have on rural crime?  Many people are extremely concerned about the capacity of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to provide people with the security in their lives to which they are entitled, particularly in rural areas.  I wish to know whether there was much discussion at local level about the impact of closing Garda stations and whether it was thought by individual garda&iacute; that it would have an impact on their ability to prevent and investigate crime.</p> <p> I also defend Senator Darragh O'Brien for raising concerns about access to drugs and health services.  I was in contact with a family recently about a person who had three times been deemed to require important surgery and had been brought in a bus from County Donegal to a Dublin hospital only to be sent back each time because the surgery could not be organised for that day.  That is an appalling way to treat people.  I am also very concerned, as one of the 2 million who hold private health insurance, about what it is proposed to do in the future.  Are we looking at a situation where 30% of the population will have to subvent health insurance for the other 70%?  I believe most people would be happy to do this provided they were guaranteed a quality health service, but it will be another oppressive tax, with no return in necessary health services if matters do not change radically.</p><p>I ask that we have the debate which I know some colleagues in the Government parties have requested on sustainable energy.  I ask that we have a debate on the need to reassess our aspirations for renewable energy projects.  We had a building boom because we rushed headlong into poorly thought out tax reliefs and bad planning policy.  Is it possible that the massive wind farms planned for the midlands will see the same process repeated?  We have not seen financial viability plans for the scheme to export wind power to the United Kingdom.  At the start of February in Spain all subsidised electricity prices were cut in the case of schemes built before 2004.  Investors in Spanish wind energy projects were lured into the industry by the Government's promise that it would maintain generous feed-in tariffs for 20 years and now the United Kingdom and Germany are planning to engage in the same process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E00200"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E00300"><p>I ask the Leader if we can have this debate because people are wondering whether we are rushing into a massive plan to build wind farms with no certainty in terms of there being a market for the power generated and no clear return on investment.  Will we have thousands of ghost wind farms in ten years to match the ghost housing estates?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E00400"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E00500"><p>Will farmers be saddled with ugly wind turbines that they were lured into investing in only to find there is a get-out clause in the contract for the wind turbine developers, as well as tax implications for farmer in changing the use of their land?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E00600"><p>I call Senator Tom Sheahan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E00700"><p>We need to question whether this will end up like the eircom debacle, with people-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.30" nospeaker="true" time="14:55:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E00900"><p>I have called Senator Tom Sheahan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" speakername="Tom Shehan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E01000"><p>I raise the issue of rural post offices and refer to the motion to be taken in the other House today and tomorrow.  First and foremost, this is political opportunism, although perhaps we might find a better word to describe it.  Essentially, it is an attack on rural Ireland, but I direct the blame at one source, namely, the board of directors of An Post.  If it were the board of directors of any other company, it would have got the bullet, so to speak, years ago because if one looks at a graph of the service provided by An Post, it is only in one direction and the directors have done nothing to stop it.  They never dealt with anything until it became a problem.  They never sought efficiencies and have not done their jobs.  They have not chased new business, as any board of directors and any body else would do.  Regarding applications for social welfare payments, etc., I have seen a copy of a letter sent by a social welfare office to an applicant requesting their bank details.  People are being corralled in order to receive their payments, but the banks do not want this.  We must, therefore, be very careful in this regard.  In the light of the debate that will take place in the other House tonight and tomorrow, I ask colleagues to consider the ramifications of what could happen in the future.  In my county alone - I have spoken to many postmasters - anything up to 50 rural post offices could close.  The board of An Post should either resign or the Minister should give the directors their marching orders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500006#E01100"><p>I refer to the ongoing whistleblowers saga and the lack of confidence in the politburo of the Garda and the Minister for Justice and Equality.</p> <p>I call for a debate on this issue as a matter of urgency.  I will not propose an amendment to the Order of Business today, but I ask the Leader to set aside two or three hours in the next week or ten days for a debate on the issue.  </p><p> We are hearing all sorts of stories.  We had the bizarre set-up with penalty points.  We had the alleged bugging of GSOC and still do not know if it was bugged.  There is a lack of trust in the Garda Commissioner and the top echelons of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, which is regrettable and not good for public confidence.  Even more worrying is the suggestion today by the Taoiseach and the Cabinet that a senior counsel be appointed to examine issues that have arisen.  This is ludicrous.  This is a slow burner and has been for two years.  Somebody needs to grasp the nettle.  If only 20% of what was said on last night's &quot;Prime Time&quot; programme by the serving sergeant, one of the whistleblowers, is true, it raises serious questions about the situation <i>vis-&agrave;-vis </i>the Commissioner.  If it is true, it is bizarre that the two principal complainants were not asked to give evidence to Assistant Commissioner John O'Mahony in his investigation.  There are many issues which are eroding the confidence of the Garda and doing it huge damage.  Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen spoke about the closure of Garda stations, an issue we have raised in the House on several occasions, but we face this debacle of a lack of trust in the Garda and the issue of the whistleblowers.  On the one hand, whistleblowers are being enticed and supported by legislation, while, on the other, they are not wanted by the Government.  It is basically stating it wants to have a whistleblower system in place, but it will not give whistleblowers any credence, chance or credibility.  That is why I ask the Leader to arrange an urgent debate in this House on the issue.  This House is owed a full debate on this debacle, irrespective of whether there is the sideshow of a senior counsel investigating papers which have been out for so long that they must be getting mouldy in being passed from one hand to the other.  This is one of the most serious issues the State has faced in the past 30 years and we need to address it, rather than kick the can down the road.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500007#F00200"><p>Will the Leader ask the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to come back to the House to continue the debate on A Vision for Change and mental health services, in particular adolescent and youth mental health services?  I have raised this issue continually since becoming a Member.  In my first speech in the House almost three years ago I raised the question of children being placed in adult psychiatric units.  It is totally unacceptable that 68 children were admitted to adult psychiatric units last year.  While I recognise much work has been done and commend the Minister of State for what she has done, there is huge scope in this regard.  Can we concentrate on the 16 to 18 year old age group, in particular?  Some 2,500 children were waiting for an appointment with the adolescent mental health service.  In my region, the north east, staffing levels in child and adolescent mental health services were only 61% compliant.  There is a huge amount of work to be done.  I refer, in particular, to the adolescent mental health service for children in the 16 to 18 year old group.  This group is being left out.  Last week a constituent contacted me about a 16 year old boy whom the paediatric service had refused to see because he was over 16 years of age, while the child and adolescent mental health service had stated it could not help because he was over 16 years and had an intellectual disability.  The GP said this meant he would have to be sedated.</p> <p>My question is whether we must sedate someone between 16 and 18 years of age until the person is old enough to have access to adult mental health services.  I find this totally unacceptable and I call on the Leader to have an urgent debate on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500008#G00200"><p>In view of the debate on post offices in the D&aacute;il this week, I refer to the regret of the Minister, Deputy Rabbitte, that the interest rate on savings paid by post offices was reduced because of pressure from the banks suggesting that post offices were engaged in unfair competition.  That should be examined if we are trying to save post offices, because the banks were bailed out by the taxpayer and they were the ones engaging in unfair competition.</p><p>Of 725 motorists tested early on Sunday morning in Killarney, Newcastle West, Thurles and Waterford, only two were found to be over the alcohol limit.  This is a compliment to the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and to the motorists for behaving so responsibly.  We all face the problem of the 190 people killed on Irish roads last year and the need to reduce this number.</p><p>I congratulate UCC on winning the Sigerson Cup, which was established by one of the predecessors of the Cathaoirleach, Dr. George Sigerson, who was the Chairman of the First Seanad of the Irish Free State on 11 and 12 December 1922 before the election of Lord Glenavy.  I pass on my best wishes to the intervarsity competition that is taking place nearby this week, the Collingwood Cup.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500008#G00300"><p>I welcome the decision by the Cabinet to appoint a barrister to carry out a scoping exercise on the many allegations in the public domain against members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  It is essential that this be done as a matter of urgency.  I support and agree with much of what was said by Senator Denis O'Donovan.  We must have a discussion on the administration of justice in because it is essential that confidence is restored in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na as a matter of urgency.  It is essential that there is confidence in the management of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and that whistleblowers are protected.  The public must have confidence that if the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na does wrong, a whistleblower has recourse to an avenue to bring it to the attention of the powers that be so that the issue can be addressed as a matter of urgency.</p><p>I support Senator Zappone in condemning the appalling legislation enacted in Uganda yesterday.  I support the call for the T&aacute;naiste to raise the issue at the UN Human Rights Council.</p><p>There has been scaremongering in the media recently in regard to driving licences.  Driving licences are now administered by the Road Safety Authority, RSA.  Applications that are in order are processed in 12 days or fewer.  In the case of applications that are not in order, where the applicant must be contacted, it will take longer.  The RSA is on course for a ten-day turnaround by the end of February and a five- to eight-day turnaround by the end of March.  I appeal to public representatives not to scare people or transmit misinformation.  They should check the facts before they go on national radio and television.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500008#G00400"><p>I join Senator Bacik and Senator Zappone in commending the work of the Constitutional Convention and calling for a debate in the House on the final report, which will be furnished to the Taoiseach by the chairman, Mr. Tom Arnold.  If we have a debate, the Taoiseach should come to the Chamber.  It would be a worthwhile debate with the Taoiseach.  Many of the citizen delegates at the convention felt a second Constitutional Convention could and should be put in place to deal with a range of outstanding issues that the convention was unable to deal with.</p><p>I refer to the Garda whistleblowers and the issues that will not be resolved unless there is a full, independent inquiry.</p> <p>The Taoiseach has had in his possession for almost a week a dossier from the Garda whistleblower, Sergeant Maurice McCabe.  By his admission, the Taoiseach has indicated this raises very serious policing and justice issues.  It has also been stated that the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, was aware of this dossier and these allegations and cases for over two years but failed to act.  I must go against the grain with respect to the comments made by the Government Senators that the appointment of a barrister to examine these claims is the appropriate way to do this.  I do not believe so.  This is the Government circling the wagons, protecting its Minister first and foremost rather than the public good or confidence in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Department of Justice and Equality.  The only credible way to proceed is a full independent inquiry allowed for under the Commissions of Investigation Act 2004.</p><p>Whatever about the issue of full or partial independent inquiries, the Garda whistleblowers were wronged in the first instance by the Minister for Justice and Equality when he stated in the D&aacute;il that they were not co-operating with inquiries; that was not the case.  They were also wronged by the Garda Commissioner when he used the word &quot;disgusting&quot; with regard to their activities and coming before Oireachtas committees.  That is despite the fact we now know they were invited before Oireachtas committees by the Department of Justice and Equality.  The whistleblowers were wronged by the Garda Commissioner because of that and other comments, and by the Minister for Justice and Equality, so both should apologise.  If the public is to have continued faith in the justice system and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, there must be a full independent inquiry and no half-measures will suffice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500009#H00200"><p>I support what is a very reasonable request from Senator Darragh O'Brien to impress upon the Minister the need for drugs to treat people suffering from multiple sclerosis.  If somebody gets cancer or has a heart condition, we all sit up and take notice but in most cases people can be cured or get better.  There is no cure for this neurological disease and this is a debilitating condition from which people will not recover.  The drugs in question are a lifeline to a semblance of normal life.  It is incumbent on the State to provide such drugs.  The Senator mentioned a figure of &euro;280 and ultimately, that could keep a person out of hospital and long-term care.  It would be a cheap option for the State if we are honest.</p><p>I will go a step further and ask the Leader to request the Minister to come before the House.  We can have a debate on long-term illness cards and eligibility, and he can have a chance to give a good reason for this drug being unacceptable in the long-term illness scheme.  If we do not use trial drugs, there will be no progress in medical science.  Will the Leader ask the Minister to come before us so we can debate the issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500009#H00300"><p>Last Friday night Mr. Aog&aacute;n &Oacute; Fearghail became the 38th Uachtar&aacute;in-Tofa of Cumann L&uacute;thchleas Gael, and this time next year he will take over as the 38th president of the GAA.  In doing so, he will become the first Cavan man to hold this position in the 130-year history of the GAA.  He will be only the seventh Ulster man to hold the position and one of only four people in the 130 years to be elected on the first count, getting over 170 No. 1 votes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500009#H00400"><p>He beat a Kerry man.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500009#H00500"><p>He is a very proud Cavan and Droim Dh&uacute;in &Eacute;ire &Oacute;g man and he is a proud Gael.  I take this opportunity to wish him well in his presidency.  Coming from Cavan, we are guaranteed one thing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500009#H00600"><p>All-Ireland tickets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500009#H00700"><p>From next year a Cavan man will hold aloft the Sam Maguire Cup for at least three years in a row.  We hope that for one of those years at least, he will present the cup to the Cavan senior football team, which is doing very well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500009#H00800"><p>Do not go mad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500009#H00900"><p>On Sunday evening, along with Oireachtas colleagues, Deputies Joe O'Reilly and Brendan Smith, I attended a reception at GAA headquarters in Cavan at Kingspan Breffni Park to welcome the president-elect.</p> <p>During his address he said the GAA was a community of volunteers and that community was at the heart of everything we did.  He went on to refer to the four Fs - fixtures, finance, facilities and family - which will become the cornerstone of his presidency when he takes over this time next year.  As a Cavan man and on behalf of Senator Kathryn Reilly, a very proud Cavan woman, I congratulate Aog&aacute;n and his family and wish him well in his presidency in the year ahead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500010#J00200"><p>Well done.  I add my congratulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500010#J00300"><p>The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Leo Varadkar, and the Minister of State at the Department, Deputy Michael Ring, confirmed recently that Hugo McNeill, an ex-Ireland rugby international, had agreed to chair the working group established in conjunction with their Northern colleagues, Minister Arlene Foster and Car&aacute;l N&iacute; Chuil&iacute;n.  The Rugby World Cup working group will comprise representatives from North and South, Departments, agencies and other key bodies.  It will examine some key issues to assist the two Governments in their decision on whether to set out a roadmap for a potential bid and will report later in the summer.  I wish those involved well in their deliberations.  What a boost it would be for Irish rugby and all-Ireland tourism interests if we were to decide to bid, and be successful, to hold the Rugby World Cup on the island of Ireland in the near future.</p><p>I wish to call, too, for an urgent debate with the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Pat Rabbitte, on the future of post offices, particularly in rural areas.  Many post offices are in fear of being closed down.  I am deeply concerned and would like to hear the Minister's future proposals for the post office network.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500010#J00400"><p>I would like the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, to come to the House for a broad-ranging debate on mortgage and debt solutions.  Last night I hosted a public meeting in Oranmore.  There was a public element, as well as private one-to-one consultations with personal insolvency practitioners.  Mr. David Hall, whom we all know, was present and approximately 90 people attended.  It takes a lot of courage for people in debt and under severe stress to come out.  They had mortgage, personal and business debtts and more than 70 had one-to-one meetings.  The demand was so great that the exercise must be repeated.  What struck me most was that people were suffering in silence.  Some disclosures were made which showed that the lives of some were at risk.  The more we talk about the issue and come up with solutions, the better.  It is clear that the answer lies in negotiation, write-downs and the intervention of trusted third parties acting as intermediaries between those who are in severe debt and the banks.  The banks are in a state of paralysis, except for AIB which is waking up to reality.  The sooner they sort out their own problems and get on and address the issue the sooner we will return to normality.  I cannot stress enough the seriousness of the issue.  I have read in the newspapers how the position is improving, but I exposed the myth being created.  That is not true.  The level of debt is a serious issue.  People are under severe stress and I fear for their lives.  I have said my piece.  I urge the Leader to bring the Minister for Finance to the House.  There is a myriad of problems which are too broad for me to raise on the Order of Business.  Suffice it to say a debate is needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500011#K00100"><p>I call on the Leader to contact the Minister responsible - perhaps the Minister of State, Deputy O'Dowd - for Waterways Ireland.</p><p>  I am not sure if many people remember the <i>Naomh &Eacute;anna</i>, but there was a wonderful programme about it on Radio 1 which featured a speech by the late Se&aacute;n Lemass.  It was a proud moment when this then state-of-the-art boat was built in a Dublin dockyard and launched.  It served the Aran Islands for many years, is an iconic vessel, is one of the few remaining fully riveted vessels in the world and has all of its original machinery.  It is because of an ownership dispute that it has been left idle since 1986 in Grand Canal Dock and is now in a somewhat distressed state.  A group that has already had success in restoring marine vessels wants a six-month moratorium on its sale.  Apparently, Waterways Ireland is determined to sell it for scrap and as we speak, the boat is being stripped.  I heard today that the brass portholes are being removed for scrap.  This is appalling.  All we are asking for is a six-month delay so that the interested group can put a proper plan together.  The boat is being dismantled currently, but every scrap of it should be kept so that it can be reassembled.  It would be a tourist attraction and would display Irish craftsmanship of which we can be proud.  Will the Leader get in touch with the relevant Minister on this issue?</p><p>  On another issue, I am not sure whether anybody has mentioned Sharon N&iacute; Bheol&aacute;in today.  What is going on is horrendous.  I realise I am, to a certain extent, taking my life in my hands saying this, because newspapers are so utterly vengeful and poisonous and if one dares to criticise them, they will go after one.  I am not afraid, but I am involved in legal proceedings - four legal cases - and must be a little careful.  The editor of the most offensive newspaper apologised, but there was much talk about the women in the office being more or less responsible.  The blame was shifted onto them.  I heard a lot about -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500011#K00200"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate on this issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500011#K00300"><p>I have been called a misogynist in this House, but I would like to know where people are when there is real misogyny going on.  If the apology made was sincere, the images would have been taken down off the Internet straight away.  The fact they were not tells us how hollow the apology was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500011#K00400"><p>I support Senator O'Brien's call for more Government interaction to deal with the pending Aer Lingus situation.  Anyone who subscribes to a pension would feel that after so many years' work, their pension entitlement should be there for them.  We need to distinguish between average pensions people contribute towards all their working lives and the astronomical gold-plated pensions of senior public servants we have seen over the years.  People who work hard and contribute towards an ordinary, decent pension should not at this stage of their lives have concerns that their pension provisions will be completely dismantled.</p><p>I understand that negotiations at the DAA with Aer Lingus are fraught.  These negotiations also cover Shannon Airport and former workers there.  I would like to see a reinvigorated effort on the part of all parties to come up with a fair and equitable solution to the issue, including for people with deferred pensions who were encouraged to take early retirement and to go and pursue other careers in the knowledge their pension was deferred until they were 65.  I have a major issue with people who have deferred pensions being made scapegoats, because they no longer have union or company representation.  There is an issue in that regard.</p><p>I beg the Chair's indulgence to make one further comment.  It has come to my attention today that there is an issue with regard to the staff of county enterprise boards transferring to local enterprise offices of county councils.  People who have been acting in positions for a number of years are finding they are being downgraded several steps in the promotional chain.</p> <p>It is only fair and reasonable that the small number of staff in county enterprise boards who are transferring to local authorities should keep the entitlements they have on the day of transfer.  Any self-respecting Department would see the fairness and merit in that proposal.  Will the Leader communicate to the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, as well as the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L00200"><p>The Senator is way over time.  I call Senator Quinn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L00300"><p>-----which might be the line manager in this case, that these entitlements should continue when the staff transfer to local authorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L00400"><p>I congratulate Senator Wilson on the appointment of a Cavan man, Mr. Aog&aacute;n &Oacute; Fearghail, to the presidency of the GAA.  When I spoke to the Thirty-two Counties president last year in Croke Park, I pointed out my first visit to Croke Park was to watch Cavan versus Cork in an all-Ireland semi-final.  I offered a prize to the first person who could tell me what year it was.  Cavan won, by the way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L00500"><p>Oh good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L00600"><p>My father, who was from County Down, told me to support the men in blue as against the men in red, as they were from Ulster.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L00700"><p>We have trounced them in Croke Park since.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L00800"><p>There have been calls to ensure we maintain rural post offices.  While we have not planned a debate on them, it will be a matter on the Adjournment later today.  We should have a debate on how to keep our town&rsquo;s main streets alive.  It is not just An Post services that are threatened but other service providers.  Some towns are doing very well but others are not.  It just means exercising our minds.</p><p>In Britain, it has become law that one can park on double yellow lines for 15 minutes in towns in a bid to put life back into them.  It was noted that when one wants to drop into a local shop for a newspaper or a small item, one could not park outside it because of a double yellow line.  This is one of many ideas with which we might be able to come up.  It would be worthwhile having such a debate on this area as retail in towns across Ireland is threatened.  The Seanad could do something about it here without any cost to the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L00900"><p>As schools have just reopened following the mid-term break, I wanted to raise an issue relating to it.  I was interested to see UK MPs debating whether there should be a relaxation of the rules on half-term holidays.  This was triggered by an e-petition, signed by 200,000 people, condemning the hugely inflated prices charged by holiday companies during the break.</p><p>Many hardworking parents here also want to get away during half-term.  It seems, however, travel companies increase prices from 40% to 300% for holidays during the break.  Accordingly, a rising number of parents are taking their children out of school during non-holiday times which will affect their children&rsquo;s education.  In some countries, there is an idea of staggering holidays while regional states in other countries take holidays at different times to counteract this problem.  It would be worthwhile implementing such a system here as many are caught in a parent trap with this matter.  This was an issue I wanted to raise although I would not necessarily want a debate on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500012#L01000"><p>Last week, I called for an urgent debate on what was then the crisis on the streets and cities of the Ukraine.  Obviously, events have moved on but, in a sense, they have become much more serious with threatening language from the Russian side.  Will the Leader arrange, as soon as he can, that we hear from the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade on this matter and to ascertain the official Irish and EU position?</p> <p> I have listened to some comments on post offices and from Senator Quinn on the question of local business.  In that context I want to highlight a media report I read at the weekend on the Government's proposal to fast-track the development of up to 70,000 houses in the Dublin region.  All the evidence appears to suggest there is a shortage of housing supply in certain Dublin areas and that needs to be addressed.  However, let this House not ignore the fact that there are tens of thousands of vacant units of accommodation in towns, townlands and villages all over the non-Dublin part of this country.  The non-Dublin part of this country is not an irrelevant place.  Previous Governments tried unsuccessfully, by way of spatial strategies and decentralisation of all descriptions, to regenerate rural and provincial Ireland and it has not worked.  We have probably just one last opportunity to reflect on the possibility of rebuilding and regenerating our rural villages, towns and communities.  There is social and economic capital in doing so.  Although it is a long-playing record not just from me but from every other Member of the Oireachtas, we should have another debate on spatial strategy, rural development and the regeneration of rural communities.  That will help, not hinder, Dublin and the Dublin hinterland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500013#M00200"><p>The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation recently had a very interesting presentation from Mr. Sean O'Sullivan, whom the Cathaoirleach probably knows from "Dragons' Den".  He presented to us the report of the entrepreneurship forum that the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, asked him to establish and lead.  It is a valuable document that we should debate in this House.  There is a lot in it.  It would be an opportunity to examine the whole area again with the Minister, Deputy Bruton, or the Minister of State, Deputy Sherlock.  It encompasses education as well.  One of its primary recommendations is that we have a focus on entrepreneurship across our education system from primary right through to third level.  The whole area is not being addressed adequately at third level.  We expect business schools in our universities or our IT sector to teach business, whereas it should be taught right across all sectors, including engineering, the sciences and computer science.  That way we can encourage people to start their own businesses.  I use the word "entrepreneurs" and we all use it a lot, but we should probably use a plainer expression such as "people who start a business".  This very important document also focuses on research.  So much money is spent on research in our universities and IT sectors, yet we are not realising the value of that by bringing it to commercial fruition.  Senator Quinn was also at the committee meeting and I am sure he would agree that we could and should discuss this report with the Minister in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500013#M00300"><p>Last weekend I had the pleasure of visiting the Cooley Peninsula.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500013#M00400"><p>Thanks for the invitation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500013#M00500"><p>I was there for Operation Bush4mation in co-operation with "Operation Transformation", which has been on television for the last six weeks, and which has been drawing tremendous attention to the fitness and well-being of people here in Ireland.  I was impressed with Bush Post Primary School and the facilities available for the local community.  Not only does the school have a magnificent athletics track and gymnasium, but it is well floodlit and it has allowed the secondary school to be used by the general community in the Cooley Peninsula.  While I was there I began to think about how the Irish Sports Council and the National Sports Campus Development Authority being merged into Sport Ireland.  The heads of the relevant Bill have been produced.  Having witnessed how the school has opened its facilities to the community in the Cooley Peninsula, I think of all the facilities in schools throughout Ireland that could be made available for the general community in those areas but, unfortunately, are not due to insurance or management issues.</p> <p>This might be the ideal time to invite the Minister for Education and Skills and the Minister of State with responsibility for sport to the House, individually or together, to discuss how the proposed new Sport Ireland body can help schools throughout the country manage the utilisation of these facilities.  Schools are usually only open from 9 a.m. to 4 p.m. and are free after that.  We should have a debate on how to utilise and manage these facilities for the communities throughout Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N00200"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien spoke about whom the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, should and should not meet.  That is a matter for the Minister.  He is quite capable of deciding with whom and when he should meet.  With regard to the Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, and universal health insurance, a matter that was raised by other Senators, I understand it will be the subject of a White Paper and we will have a comprehensive discussion on it at the appropriate time.  Again, I advise the Senator not to believe everything he reads in the newspapers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N00300"><p>I do not believe everything, but I think he is under a little pressure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N00400"><p>With regard to the query regarding a specific drug, like the Cathaoirleach I suggest that the Senator table an Adjournment matter about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N00500"><p>That is disappointing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N00600"><p>Senator Bacik called for a debate on policing.  When the reports are completed it would probably be an appropriate time for a debate, but we could possibly have a debate on it before then.  This matter was also raised by Senators O'Donovan and Mullins.  The question of confidence in the Garda and GSOC is a matter of paramount importance that must be addressed, and the Government has every intention of addressing it in the best possible way.  There will a scoping exercise and if an inquiry is necessary, I am sure that will happen.</p><p>Senator Bacik, as well as Senator Zappone and others, also referred to the completion of the Constitutional Convention.  Mr. Tom Arnold appeared before the House previously and agreed to return to debate the full report when it is complete.  We will have that debate when the report is published.</p><p>Senator Zappone spoke about the protection of basic human rights in the Constitutional Convention and mentioned that the public consultation committee will also deal with the issue of human rights.  I note her point about Uganda, a point also raised by Senator Mullins.  I share her concerns regarding the extreme legislation, which is reprehensible in my view, introduced in Uganda.  I will bring the matter to the attention of the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade.</p><p>I note Senator Mullen's comments on the health service and universal health insurance, which I have addressed.  In respect of wind energy, time was allocated for public consultation on that matter.  I am sure we can have a debate when that period is complete.  I have already asked the Minister on a number of occasions to come to the House to discuss this matter.</p><p>Senator Sheahan and others raised the issue of rural post offices and the need for post offices to attract new business and so forth.  Last week there was a request that we would deal with the 2013 report of the Joint Committee on Transport and Communications on promoting a sustainable service for the post office network.  The report will be discussed in the other House tomorrow.  I remind the House that we had a debate on that report on 4 July last year, so we are well ahead of the posse.  We dealt with the report at that point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N00700"><p>It is a little more relevant now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N00800"><p>There is no Government plan to close post offices.  There are 1,147 post offices in the country and in the last three years there have been 17 closures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N00900"><p>There were 600 in total.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500014#N01000"><p>If Senator Norris allows me to complete my comments, I might answer his query.</p> <p>This is in contrast to the trends during the period between 2006 and 2010 when 197 post offices were closed.  Members on the other side of the House who raised the matter should consider their record in that regard.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500015#O00200"><p>The research office has been working overtime.  Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500015#O00300"><p>There are dramatic changes occurring in the postal service and revenue in An Post has fallen as mail volumes have dropped.  In contrast, the business being done across post office counters has increased in recent years.  An Post and the postmasters have worked closely together to win new business for the network.  Banking services, bill payments and foreign exchange are just a few of the post office counter services that are growing.  I assure the House that if we need a further debate on the issue then we will arrange one.  This House debated the report from the Oireachtas joint committee on 4 July last year.</p><p>  Senator Moran called for a debate on mental health services, particularly services for 16 to 18 year-olds.  We have already had four debates on mental health services.  The Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Lynch, has always been very helpful and has made herself available for the debates.  I shall ask her again to come in here to address the matter that Senator Moran raised.  </p><p>  I note the points made by Senator Barrett on the fact that over 700 people were tested for drink driving over the weekend in various areas, and only two people were found to have a positive result.  That highlights the fact that the message has got across that people should not drink and drive.  </p><p>  Senator Mullins mentioned driving licences and the RSA.  He outlined the fact that driving licences are being processed within 12 days or less.</p><p>  Senator Moloney called for a debate on long-term illness cards.  I hope to have the Minister for Health in here soon to discuss the health service plan and many other areas of health.  </p><p>  Senator Wilson congratulated the new president of the GAA, Mr. Aog&aacute;n &Oacute; Fearghail, who is from Cavan.  It is good that we will again see a Cavan man with his hands on the Sam Maguire Cup.  It is a long time since that has happened.  We congratulate Mr. &Oacute; Fearghaill who is a cousin of the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes.  That is another string to his bow. </p><p>  Senator Brennan mentioned the Rugby World Cup working group that will be chaired by Hugo MacNeil.  We commend the group on its forthcoming work.  It would be wonderful if Ireland could host a Rugby World Cup. </p><p>  Senator Healy Eames mentioned mortgage arrears and other points in that regard.  I can advise here that the Minister for Finance shall attend here to debate the economy, economic growth and job creation next Tuesday, 4 March.  </p><p>  Senator Norris referred to inland waterways and the <i>Naomh Eanna</i>.  This is an appropriate time to raise the issue because tomorrow we will debate inland waterways for over an hour with the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Deenihan, at the request of a number of Members.  There will be an opportunity for the Senator to raise the question of the <i>Naomh Eanna</i> during the debate.  </p><p>  I also noted the point made on bullying by the Senator.  Bullying in any form is reprehensible.  </p><p>  Senator Conway mentioned problems with the Dublin Airport Authority's pensions and I noted his points in that regard.  He also asked that staff transferred from enterprise boards to local authorities would retain the same conditions.  I shall bring the matter to the attention of the Minister.  </p><p>  Senator Quinn, when we spoke about post offices, mentioned the need to keep the main streets in towns alive.  That is a very important issue throughout the length and breadth of the country and is possibly something that we should debate. </p> <p>Senator Paul Coghlan tabled a Private Members' motion on car parking charges for out-of-town centres, but we probably should have an overall debate on the issue.</p><p>I note Senator Noone's point about the inflated price of holidays abroad by travel agencies during school holidays.  It is a matter that has been raised on a number of occasions.</p><p>Senator Bradford called for a debate on the situation in Ukraine.  I will ask the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to come in here to give an update on that serious issue.  I also note the Senator's points on the shortage of housing in Dublin and the fact that there are so many vacant houses elsewhere, and that we could have a debate about rural regeneration in that context.</p><p>Senator Clune called for the recent report by Mr. O'Sullivan presented to the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to be debated in the House.  I will try to make arrangements for that.  It is an important issue which should be addressed and I will ask the relevant Minister to come into the House to debate that report.</p><p>Finally, Senator Eamonn Coghlan raised fitness and well-being and his visit to the Cooley Peninsula.  He sought a debate on the new Sport Ireland set-up with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Varadkar, and the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn.  I will try to facilitate those debates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.86" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.87" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500017#Q00100">Community Courts: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500017#Q00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Joe Costello.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500017#Q00300"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That Seanad &Eacute;ireann - recognises that a community court could effectively deal with low-level offences, focusing primarily on criminal anti-social behaviour by responding to the underlying problems of offenders;<br />- recognises that a community court may further develop a collaborative working approach among service providers and apply a problem solving approach in respect of each defendant in a timely fashion;<br />- commends the work of the National Crime Council and notes the publication in 2007 of its report on the case for community courts in Ireland;<br />- notes the experience and positive outcomes associated with the use of community courts internationally and requests that the potential of such courts in the Irish context be further examined; andcalls on the Minister for Justice, Equality and Defence to consider the issue of community courts in Ireland and to establish a community court in Dublin city centre as a pilot project to provide for a problem solving approach to addressing criminal anti-social behaviour and to offer further alternatives to imprisonment for such offenders.</blockquote>It is a real privilege to move a motion on the issue of community courts.  For many years Members have heard a debate, discourse and discussion on the prison system, its overcrowded state and the need to consider a new way to do business.  For too long they have heard of custodial sentences being imposed on those who really should be engaging in a different form of punishment.  In this context, even &quot;punishment&quot; is the wrong word and I would consider it to be better described as engagement with the State at a different level.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Joe Costello.  He represents a city constituency and while Members obviously would have wished for the presence in the House of the line Minister with responsibility in this area, namely, the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, his views in this regard are known to all Members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500017#Q00400"><p>The Minister is otherwise engaged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500017#Q00500"><p>Similarly, all Members are aware that the Minister probably has immediately pressing matters with which he is dealing expeditiously and efficiently and, I am sure, to the satisfaction of most.  That said, in his absence, the Minister of State is eminently appropriate because he is familiar with city life, as well as the challenges faced.  Moreover, he is aware of how people can fall into the wrong company and that many first or second and third offences for which people are convicted can be as a result of falling into the wrong company.</p><p>The concept of community courts was born in 1993 in New York City, where people were dealing with a situation in which Times Square effectively was a no-go area.  Similarly, large parts of the city, particularly in Manhattan, as well as parks, Grand Central Station and other locations with which all Members are familiar and which they tend to love when they visit New York were also no-go areas.  A decision was made at the time that there was a need to consider doing business in a different way and investigate alternative methods of justice.  To the best of my knowledge, the concept of community courts was born in that part of New York.  It spread to other parts of the world and now operates successfully in Canada, numerous cities in the United States, New Zealand and, to a lesser extent, the United Kingdom.  However, each jurisdiction is different and the results depend on the resources made available and the engagement and willingness to make it happen.</p><p>At the end of January I had the privilege of attending a function on St. Stephen's Green organised by the Dublin City Business Association, to which it had invited people who had been involved in the New York experience to share their experiences.</p> <p>I was delighted that eminent persons such as the then Lord Mayor of Dublin, Ois&iacute;n Quinn, and hundreds of people from the legal and business professions had attended a half-day seminar on the concept of community courts.  It was followed in the afternoon by a sitting of the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality which heard testimonials from the eminent people from New York who attended the function.  Representatives of the Law Society of Ireland, Blackhall Place, also attended and gave their views on the concept.  What was even more striking about that session was that the Minister for Justice and Equality sat in as an observer.  That is the seriousness with which he is taking the need to do business in this area differently.  The day ended with a very successful meal in Leinster House which was attended by stakeholders and people such as Judge Michael Reilly who had been promoting this concept for many years.  To quote the Chairman of the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, there is now a fair wind behind the concept of community courts.</p><p>The community court I want to see established as a pilot project is what was recommended in a report produced in 2007 by the National Crime Council which had carried out extensive research on the concept.  It made several recommendations, one of which was that a pilot community court be established in Dublin city centre adjacent to the Sheriff Street and Pearse Street Garda divisional districts.  It is an exceptionally good idea.  It would be a community court that would look at alternatives to sending people to prison.  It would be co-located alongside professionals who deal with anger management problems, drug and alcohol addictions, community employment and welfare issues, family disputes, parenting courses and so on.  Effectively, the community court would be part of an overall one-stop-shop to ensure people who found themselves before the courts would have immediate remedies.  The notion behind community courts is that in the case of offences such as assault, petty crime, prostitution, shop-lifting and so on, we would examine an alternative concept and way of doing business.</p><p>In many cases, people fall into the wrong company as a result of being in the wrong environment.  To a large extent, it is because they are in the wrong place at the wrong time.  They deserve a second chance in our society.  They deserve to have the vehicles of State that are willing to help engage with them at an early stage.  All of us talk about early interventions, whether in medicine or education, but early interventions in the area of justice are equally as important.  When somebody finds himelf or herself at the wrong end of the law, he or she should be brought into a court within his or her community that is a fabric of his or her community to come up with common-sense community responses in terms of remediation to get him or her back in action, so to speak.  That is an essential element of what should be our future justice system, coupled with restorative justice, an issue we have debated in the House and on which we unanimously agreed a motion.  Where restorative justice practices are in place on a pilot basis, there has been a dramatic fall in the numbers of second and follow-on offences.  Community courts would have an equally successful outcome if the pilot programme were to go ahead.</p><p>The motion is timely because there is a fair wind behind this concept.</p> <p>Will the Minister for Justice and Equality set up an implementation panel immediately as recommended in the 2007 report?  In six or 12 months time when all of the stakeholders, including the Judiciary, the District Court, the Law Society and those involved in various addiction treatments, have been properly consulted, we should set up a community court on a pilot basis in Dublin city centre.  This Minister and Government are committed to alternative and better ways of doing business.  Community courts are a better way to do business.  The whole notion of lock them up and throw away the key is not working.  Our prisons are jammed and are simply not working.  The Minister is deeply committed to this alternative.</p><p>What better way to acknowledge the third anniversary of the 2011 general election than for this motion to be unanimously supported by Seanad &Eacute;ireann in the hope that before the end of the lifetime of this Government we see a community court in Dublin running successfully?  Hopefully, we will then see them rolled out on a regional basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500019#S00200"><p>I second this motion and welcome the opportunity to speak on this important issue.  In an associated way, I commend the Minister for Justice and Equality on his intention to deal with the court poor box issue.  It was a practice with no statutory footing and opaque rules and it had no place in our system of criminal justice.</p><p>I fully support this proposal which seems to have two main advantages.  If done correctly, there will be a reduction in crime rates and recidivism and a reduction in custodial sentences for low level crime.  It is rather staggering that on one day in November 2012, not one incidence of violent crime was reported in New York city.  Many put this down to the establishment of community courts.</p><p>On a practical level, a local court where all the local services and authorities have an input would be a fantastic development.  I will give one concrete example.  Imagine a local court where the local authority and its planners are involved in and aware of the local geographic or urbanisation issues contributing to crime in a given area.  There was an issue in a local estate in Galway recently where the local authority, after much pressure from local representatives, closed off certain passageways in an estate at night to prevent those potentially participating in low level crime from gathering.  If the local authorities were aware, from participation in local community courts, that these issues were arising from their planning decisions, then it would allow them to future proof building and planning in a way to mitigate against anti-social behaviour.</p><p>I caution on a direct comparison between a potential system here and one already operating in New York, for instance.  With due respect, American justice at what we would call District Court level is harsher than in most of mainland European countries.  Incarceration is not the be-all and end-all of the criminal justice system here.  We deal comparatively leniently with low level crime.  I would hope the idea here is not so much having a more lenient sentencing regime but that we would have joined up thinking across the public service and community involvement.</p><p>I would have one caveat only with the proposal.  Senators should be aware that a long-standing pilot project in Liverpool was closed.  The Government in the UK was not satisfied that the moneys invested were yielding results.  It costs considerable sums to establish and fund such a system.  Proponents of the system in the UK freely admit that it requires a large amount of funding.</p><p>We should, therefore, ensure that the potential cost is weighed in the balance before deciding on this issue.  We should insist on fully costed proposals as we do not have funds to throw away. I hope that any project - presumably, a pilot project at the start - will be subject to a very careful cost benefit analysis.  </p><p>I support the proposal but I do not wish to see money being poured into the service annually without proper supervision, auditing and stringent cost benefit analysis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500019#S00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Costello.  Sometimes I think his rightful place is in the Upper House.  He is a bit lost where he is but I wish him well.</p> <p>My party supports the concept of community courts.  International experience, particularly in the US and the UK, has been drawn on and it is not unusual for us to look at situations abroad.  In particular, we looked at juvenile liaison officers and trying to ensure young people do not end up in court.  We looked at the Australian model in New South Wales and in New Zealand, and we acted, reacted and introduced legislation, which is helpful.  It should be tried out on a pilot basis to test how it will work in our area.  Some of what I read refers to neighbourhoods, which is an American, New York, Boston or Chicago phrase, and in Ireland I see it operating on a parish basis or in boroughs in the cities.  In order to be dealt with in the community courts, a defendant must indicate a guilty plea.  Defendants who comply with orders in the community courts avoid a criminal conviction.  There is major scope for this kind of system.</p><p>Last Sunday night, I was visiting someone and I saw a documentary on an open prison system in Norway.  I was gobsmacked to note that only 30% of those who had gone through the open prison system were re-offenders.  If that is the case, we should consider that set-up.</p><p>Community courts mandate punishment or help for defendants or, in a minority of cases, a combination of both.  The punishment imposed must include community work.  It is a wonderful system for people involved in minor drug offences, public order offences where there is no serious injury, petty theft and vandalism where someone does minor damage to property.  Community courts are guided by four basic principles, namely, restoring communities, bridging the gap between communities and courts, building partnerships and solving problems.  If it does not solve the problem, it is of no use.</p><p>The National Crime Council has already been alluded to and it has studied the issue and produced a detailed report in 2007 recommending the establishment of community courts in Ireland.  In supporting the motion, I concur with Senator Conway that a pilot scheme should be introduced by the Minister sooner rather than later.  We should try it out for six months or 12 months.  Within the right framework and in the right areas, this can only be successful.</p><p>It is wrong that people are thrown into prison for relatively minor crimes.  I know someone from a remote part of County Kerry.  His tractor or digger broke down and he had to drive to Navan, a four and a half hour drive, to get a part.  He is a retired farmer and he does not travel up the country very often.  When he got there he found a parking space but the parking meter was out of order.  He got his part and he came back and it was still out of order.  He was prepared to put in money and walked around and saw no one on duty on this Saturday morning.  Lo and behold, he was issued with a &euro;60 ticket.  He refused to pay it and the matter ended up in court.  He was not represented in court and he was fined &euro;600.  After 15 months, he was brought from a remote part of Ireland, accompanied by a garda.  The Department hired a taxi to bring this guy some 400 km to Mountjoy Prison to serve a seven-day sentence.  He was innocent because in his view he had committed no crime.  Later that evening, he was let out and had to get the train back to Kerry.  It cost the State &euro;1,000 and because he spent three hours in Mountjoy Prison he purged his contempt of court and the fine will never be paid.  It is the stupidity of the system.  If the man was asked to do something small in his local community, in his village or in his GAA club, he would be glad to do it and it would have saved this shenanigans.  His wife was very upset and rang me and asked me whether this was the right way to go and whether this constituted justice in Ireland.  I could understand her position but the system had gone so far that I could not row it back, nor could the Minister in that case.</p> <p>It is particularly important for there to be an ongoing and rigorous follow-up on the court's orders to ensure defendants adhere to remedial orders and are not taking advantage of them.</p><p>Research is also an important component in ensuring that courts adhere to best practice and test the effectiveness of sentencing and the overall role.  This should be conducted by the Law Reform Commission or a section of the community court.  A regular format to consult with the community and gauge the impact of the new court model is vital in securing public approval and support, as if the public does not buy into the process, the proposal will collapse, which would be a pity.  The community should also have the opportunity to benefit from any community work completed by those who have appeared before the community court.</p><p>Where it is possible, the community court should aim to ensure that any community work imposed would be linked to the committed offence and completed in the area.  This would provide restitution for the offence to the community and makes those who have appeared before the community court accountable for their offending behaviour in their own community.  There is no point in bringing a fellow from west Cork to do community service in some part of Dublin; that would not make sense and would defeat the purpose of this idea.  Experience from other jurisdictions suggests that community courts work has the most positive benefit for the defendant when he or she works along with voluntary community groups or other non-offenders.  In Ireland this would equate to groups like the tidy towns or sporting bodies which may need an extra hand locally.</p><p>Without any reservation I support this motion, which is a wonderful idea.  I wish it well and I hope a pilot scheme can be introduced.  In five or ten years people can look back and see that a small step was taken to prevent even 5% of young offenders who are not serious criminals from going into the court system.  That can be a revolving door process, with people coming out tarnished with a criminal record, so we should use the prisons as a last resort to incarcerate people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500021#U00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Costello, to the House.  I know the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, wanted to be here and as Senator Conway mentioned, he sat through the full hearing of the justice committee on 29 January when it discussed the topic.  He is otherwise engaged today but I know the Minister of State has a particular interest in the area.  I welcome him to the House.  I commend Senator Conway and his colleagues on putting forward this motion, and it is exciting to think that we may see on foot of this motion and the Minister's commitment to the issue the establishment of a community court on a pilot basis in Dublin city centre.  The hearing of the justice committee on 29 January indicated the strong support of this concept coming from a range of stakeholders and interest groups.  Senator O'Donovan has expressed his support and we will have cross-party support for it in the Chamber.</p><p>The justice committee hearing built on the 2007 report of the National Crime Council to which Senator Conway has already referred.  Those who gave a presentation at the committee included the Lord Mayor of Dublin, as mentioned by Senator Conway, but also the Irish Penal Reform Trust, the Dublin City Business Association, the Association for Criminal Justice Research and Development, the CityWide drugs crisis campaign, the Probation Service and a range of other stakeholders.  Many of the points raised by these groups have been touched on already by speakers today but I will try to make a few key arguments.</p><p>The idea of establishing a community and the general concept is very much in keeping with the strategy recommended by the justice committee to the Government last year in our report on penal reform, for which I was rapporteur.  We reported in March 2013 that prison should be a sanction of last resort and we favoured the idea of penal moderation, where we should seek as far as possible to divert those persons convicted of minor non-violent offences away from prison.  In its submission to the committee on 29 January, the Irish Penal Reform Trust made a very strong argument for the concept of penal moderation and that initiatives such as the community courts can help to address our current overuse of imprisonment for minor offences and shift response to minor offending towards the underlying social causes of the behaviour.  That group is very supportive of the community court model.  It is very much in keeping with the approach to penal strategy and policy, of which the Minister also approves.</p><p>What does a community court involve?</p> <p>As the Dublin City Business Association says, it is a case of a problem-solving approach taken by a judge in a court.  The advantages for Dublin would be immense if we look at the models from elsewhere, in particular the models that have been mentioned of the Midtown Community Court in New York city which was set up in 1993 but which built on the experience of drugs courts across the United States from the 1980s onwards.  There is also a well known model in the Red Hook centre in Brooklyn.  Others have referred to the north Liverpool model to which I will return.  The advantage of such courts is that they provide a local neighbourhood-based court system to deal generally with minor offences.  They are not trial courts, they are sentencing courts.  The Midtown court is one such example; it is just a sentencing court and does not deal with trials.  A court in Santa Monica in California deals only with first-time offenders.  Some community courts are very limited in terms of the type of offence and the type of offender with which they will deal.  In some cases the courts deal with the offender on the basis that no conviction is recorded once a guilty plea has been made.  Offenders are then given a form of community service which is usually combined in a hybrid sense with a therapeutic or educational programme.  One often has a means of addressing the underlying causes of behaviour.  That is very much part of the community court model but there are many different examples.</p><p>Senator Naughton referred to the north Liverpool community court.  As she pointed out, that is due to close in March this year.  She mentioned the prohibitive cost of the centre but that was a particular model and rather different to the Midtown model.  The north Liverpool court was a trial court as well.  It dealt with a much broader range of offences than those dealt with in the New York model and it did not just deal with guilty pleas, it also dealt with trials.  To be positive about it; the business of that court will transfer to a larger court complex that is nearby and there is a commitment that a number of the good practices that were developed in the north Liverpool model will be transferred to the larger court too.  It is not as if the model failed or that the cost was prohibitive because it was a community court.  It was a very particular type of community court and very different to that which we would see adopted in this country.</p><p>I ask the Minister of State, Deputy Costello, to bring to the attention of the Minister, Deputy Shatter, that we have received excellent submissions in particular from the Association for Criminal Justice Research and Development, ACJRD, and the Probation Service which set out the type of model that would be more likely to be successful in an Irish context.  One of the points made was that we already have neighbourhood courts to a much greater degree than in the United States.  Our District Courts are very much community based and they serve a much smaller jurisdiction than courts typically do in the United States, even courts dealing with minor offences.  They also make the point - in particular the ACJRD - that the successful community courts in the United States, especially the Midtown court in New York, is only part of a package of measures.  In 2002 in New York city an entire package of measures dealing with early intervention and crime prevention was adopted and the community court was just part of it.  There would need to be a commitment to ensure the provision of a range of supports around the community court model.</p><p>The Probation Service says that costs could be minimised by using the existing District Court structures, adopting the procedures currently adopted in the District Court and by limiting the application of the new community court pilot base to, for example, those who have pleaded guilty to summary offences only.  A single designated judge should be appointed.  The design of the court room would be important, so that the setting is more informal than the typical District Court trial.  Post-sentence there would need to be commitment to have both the application of some kind of community service under the supervision of the Probation Service but also access to therapeutic or educational sessions as in the New York model.</p><p>In Ireland we do have a number of successful models on which we could build.  As Senator Conway mentioned, we have quite a number of restorative justice programmes, for example in west Dublin in Blanchardstown and also in Nenagh.  The Le Ch&eacute;ile programme operates in Limerick.  The Cornmarket project is in operation in Wexford.  All of those involve multidisciplinary approaches to tackling offending and to try to reduce re-offending.  We have the Childrens Court, the Drug Treatment Court and the juvenile diversion programme, which in a way is similar to what is proposed except that this would also apply to adults.  It is a very exciting proposal.  It is great to see the Minister agree to the establishment of a community court on a pilot basis in Dublin city centre.  We will see immense benefit straight away from the establishment of such a court, particularly if it is established based on the successes of models elsewhere and if we learn from models such as the north Liverpool model, which was probably over ambitious in the scope of the offences and offenders it took on.</p> <p>As the Dublin City Business Association, DCBA, has stated, in terms of tackling quality of life, antisocial behaviour and public order issues on the streets of our cities, a community court could have a real impact.</p><p>The Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality is currently examining the issue of domestic violence and how we can improve our services and our legal response to domestic violence issues.  Senator Zappone, Senator Conway and I will attend the committee tomorrow for a second set of hearings on the issue.  One of the concerns of front-line service providers in the area of domestic violence is that there are problems with the District Court in terms of inconsistency of service.  There are some pockets of good practice, where there is a joined-up approach to victims and survivors of domestic violence, but there are also problems and inconsistencies.  The advantage of establishing an effective community court model would be where we see it move beyond a pilot programme.  We have had too many pilot programmes in the criminal justice arena.  What I would like to see is a modest but effective community court developed in Dublin city that could be rolled out across Ireland within a short space of time.  That would make a real difference to our criminal justice system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500023#W00200"><p>Senator Barrett and I are sharing time.</p><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House, particularly because of his commitment to the inner city.  It is very exciting, and I hope it is true, that we have the prospect of a community court as a pilot scheme in the centre of Dublin.  I note there is no amendment to the motion and it will, therefore, be passed unanimously.  I hope that strengthens the hand of the Minister of State in the matter.  I am aware of his commitment to the issue and of his involvement with former prisoners and his involvement in the north inner city.  He always gets my No. 2 vote, after Deputy Maureen Sullivan, who as an Independent Deputy and a wonderful successor to Tony Gregory must get my No. 1 vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500023#W00300"><p>That is what one would call a double-edged compliment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500023#W00400"><p>I believe the situation in the country is improving a little.  Some of the older Members will remember Nell McCafferty's newspaper articles, "In the Eyes of the Law", which described the appalling injustices that were done.  Justice was handed down on a class basis.  I do not need to rehearse the old clich&eacute; that 90% of the people in Mountjoy jail come from the same Dublin postal districts.  Therefore, this is a question of poverty.</p><p>Each Government has resolutely set its face against channelling money back into this area.  I remember discussing this issue with Tony Gregory and submitting an amendment on a Bill proposing that drugs money recovered by the CAB be spent in this way.  The setting up of the CAB came about after first being mooted by Tony Gregory, although he got little credit for it.  The Government would not use the drugs money as suggested and put it back into the communities.  Instead, it wanted to ring-fence the money for other use.</p><p>Various governments have boasted about building prisons, but that is an idle boast.  Building prisons is a farce and a waste of time.  The Government should be closing prisons.  The only people who should be in prison are those who are really dangerous and a threat to society or who have committed heinous crimes.  I remember railing here about a mother in Limerick who was snatched up and put into Limerick jail for not paying her television licence.  The current Minister for Justice and Equality has addressed this issue in the Fines (Payment and Recovery) Bill, but we need to look at better ways of dealing with this kind of situation.  Mild offenders who are imprisoned for trivial offences are likely to come out much worse.  Our prison system has virtually no remedial effect.  What remedial effect exists depends on the character of the individual rather than the justice process.</p><p>Once or twice I visited Mountjoy gaol at the suggestion of my friend Brendan Kennelly, who was wonderful and used to teach there and introduce prisoners to literature.  I met one of those prisoners afterwards, a heroin addict who had been in serious trouble, who had managed, with help from the people in Mountjoy, to get himself out of the situation he was in.  He was managing a big catering event in Trinity College when I met him.  It would be wonderful if we could get this sort of initiative going. </p> <p>I want to pay tribute to the Prison Service, its prison officers, some of whom I have known in the past, and, particularly, enlightened governors such as John Lonergan.  I am sure he would say we would be better off closing prisons and making the kind of arrangements proposed in the motion.  I congratulate the movers of this motion and I hope the Minister will issue a pilot scheme for community courts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500024#X00200"><p>I agree with Senator Conway&rsquo;s description of the community courts system in New York.  I was learning all through Senator Bacik&rsquo;s account of the system with anger management as an alternative to prison, bringing in more social science expertise and restorative justice.  All the ingredients are there to reform the system.  Senator O&rsquo;Donovan said that in Norway 70% of offenders dealt with by alternatives to prison do not re-offend.  Alternatives to prison and a criminal record are very commendable.  Great credit is due to Fine Gael Senators for putting this motion down which has support from all sides of the House.</p><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Costello, knows from his constituency the problems that arise with detaining low-level offenders in prison.  Alternatives to this are worthwhile experiments and I hope we proceed with the recommendation from the National Crime Council to start up a community court system on a trial basis.</p><p>I had some experience of people getting into trouble in the university system.  It is all small, except where it concerns examination offences which are serious.  Even then we had procedures in place so that people did not acquire a criminal record.  Immense assistance was given in setting this up by the former President, Mary Robinson, the judges Tom Finlay, Maureen Harding Clark, Henry Barron, Peter Charleton and Gerard Hogan, as well as the late Brian Lenihan.  Finding non-judicial and non-court based systems to resolve disputes and putting people back to square one to get on with their lives is immensely valuable.  I wish the Minister and his colleagues every success in that endeavour and thank Senator Conway and his colleagues for putting down this motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500024#X00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Costello, a fine Deputy and Minister for his community, as Senator Norris so eloquently outlined.</p><p>I enthusiastically support and welcome this motion and congratulate Senator Conway and other Fine Gael Senators who have argued for it with such conviction and evidence.  Senator Bacik pointed out this proposal can be part of a cohesive approach to the overall governmental and Oireachtas justice strategies.  It is critical we see our policies and programmes in that more cohesive way.</p><p>Crimes are multifaceted and most of them are the result of a complex range of social, economic, health and educational disadvantages.  We must address crime in a multifaceted way, accordingly.  As many Senators pointed out, the justice committee had many submissions on this issue, several of which I wish to highlight.  The Inspector of Prisons, Judge Michael Reilly, powerfully illustrated how the Judiciary has a limited set of options and how difficult it is when low-level repeat offenders come before the courts.  He stated judges would welcome if other options were available to them than simply custodial sentences or the use of the Probation Act.  I was particularly impacted by his example of how a person addicted to drugs or alcohol can be sent to prison where he or she will receive a certain amount of help.</p> <p>However, the underlying problems are not at all addressed in a three-month sentence.  It is insufficient for a person even to begin to come to grips with some of the issues or problems that bring that person to offend and to be placed in prison.  Other options must be available to the judges to address the range in a holistic way which complements that cohesive and comprehensive approach we need in terms of policies across the board.</p><p>As Senator O'Donovan and others have identified, instead of sending people to prison, a typical community court punishment could comprise a combination of community restitution assignment and mandated social services.  Reference was already made to evidence that was given to the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, particularly from successful community courts such as the Red Hook Community Justice Centre, which reduced the use of jail sentences by 35% and issued alternative sanctions to 78% of offenders.  This in turn reduced reoffending levels - and that is what it is all about - by 20% among young offenders and by 10% for adults.  The evaluation of the project concluded that it saved more money than it cost to implement a community court, and Senator Naughton referred to this notion.  As experts pointed out to the committee, good results do not automatically come.  They emphasised that local consultation and collaboration, along with good planning and implementation, are key to the success of the system.</p><p>I am particularly committed to the concept of community courts because of my experience over the years in west Tallaght communities, especially in the context of the Tallaght West Childhood Development Initiative, of which I was privileged to be one of the founders and leaders.  It is one of three prevention and early intervention programme sites, initially funded under the Department of Children and Youth Affairs and now moving into the Government's area-based childhood programmes in terms of anti-poverty strategies.  Over the past number of years in that first phase of Government support in west Tallaght we were able to implement a community safety initiative supporting local resident interaction and promoting collaborative responses to addressing local safety initiatives.  The initiative sought to improve people's perceptions of safety, improve neighbour relations and promote a safe and healthy environment for children and families.  In particular, it sought to engage wide community involvement and co-operation with the local Garda.</p><p>That initiative incorporated a restorative practice programme, as Senator Conway referred to regarding some of the programmes that are being implemented throughout the country.  The programme promoted dialogue between wrongdoers and harmed persons, bringing communities together.  Again, it was a collaborative process bringing different agencies and generations and people of different backgrounds together and having a positive impact on inter-agency collaboration and on the approach to conflict management.  I make this point because I want to suggest that, as Senator Conway said, a community court system could be a very effective complement to the work that is already going on in that initiative in west Tallaght and, no doubt, in other local authority contexts throughout Ireland.  A community court system could also be a great complement to the area-based childhood programs being rolled out throughout the country as part of the Government's anti-poverty strategy.</p><p>It is important that we remind ourselves and are aware of the context that is being created by support for policies from within the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, the Department of Children and Youth Affairs and the T&aacute;naiste's office.  Community courts could be a great fit within the seedbeds of local communities already engaged in anti-poverty strategies.  I support the development of a pilot initiative.  Dublin city centre is fine but Tallaght is another possibility.  That is my last shot.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500025#Y00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute; &aacute;thas orm a bheith in ann tac&uacute; leis an moladh seo go gcuirfidh c&uacute;irteanna pobal ar bun, c&eacute; go bhfuil s&eacute; &iacute;or&oacute;nta go bhfuilimid ag iarraidh tuillidh c&uacute;irteanna a chur ar bun ag am go bhfuilimid ag d&uacute;nadh c&uacute;irteanna ar fud na gceantar tuaithe, ach sin sc&eacute;al do l&aacute; eile.</p> <p> I welcome the advent of community courts.  This is a positive and progressive step that places the emphasis on retribution in a community context, as opposed to incarceration and the penal system.  Dealing with less serious offences, the community courts model emphasises treatment, understanding and community service.  Solicitors and prosecutors remain central throughout the process, although there are opportunities to avoid criminal records and prison in a way that should, in theory, benefit society by reducing repeat offending and educating offenders by making them engage with the community.</p><p>In 2007 the National Crime Council, NCC, recommended their introduction, starting with the Dublin pilot.  The NCC believes that the community court model would bring a range of benefits to offenders and communities which are not currently available in Ireland.  These benefits include: a pre-trial assessment in every case; a wider range of available sanctions; the targeting of underlying issues which may cause offending, such as substance abuse or homelessness, so as to reduce re-offending; an element of restitution to the community in appropriate cases; offenders who comply with the community court avoid a criminal conviction; renewed confidence in the criminal justice system; gains in public safety and perceptions of safety; and swift and visible justice for low level offences.  The types of crimes covered could include general public order offences such as intoxication, disorderly conduct, threatening and abusive behaviour, minor assaults, drug use, theft and criminal damage.  Services available as solutions would include addiction counselling, education courses, social services, parenting programmes and anger management courses.</p><p>Community courts are already in use in Britain, Australia and Canada, as outlined by my colleagues, as well as in the US, where they started over ten years ago.  There are approximately 40 such courts in the US.  In New York, which has courts in midtown Manhattan, the Bronx, Brooklyn and Harlem and a fifth one in the course of being established, the system has been credited with reducing the once infamous levels of crime, especially in Manhattan.  The Yarra community court in Melbourne, Australia, found that between 2007 and 2009 rates of recidivism dropped by 7%.  The system has also been adopted in South Africa and Canada.  Community courts are, of course, less costly than traditional courts and they offer a quicker resolution to what is often a once-off offence.</p><p>Sinn F&eacute;in welcomes this motion.  We consider it an important first step in the modernisation of what is a very outdated penal system.  We also welcome the move away from the incarceration model.  As has been repeatedly highlighted by the United Nations Human Rights Council, UNHRC, the Irish Penal Reform Trust and others, the Irish prison system is in urgent need of reform.  Virtually all of our prisons, especially Limerick Prison, Mountjoy Prison and Cork Prison, are not fit for purpose.  In such places, prisoners must still slop out, and overcrowding, violence and drug use are endemic.  The D&oacute;chas Centre, otherwise known as the women's prison, is also overcrowded, while most of the women there are serving sentences for petty crimes and have serious problems related to addiction, abuse and violence.  In spite of this, the services we offer incarcerated men and women for education, health care, drug addiction and mental health are appalling.</p><p>I saw just how bad conditions are in our prisons when I recently visited my friend Margaretta D'Arcy in Limerick Prison.  Such was the lack of educational resources at the prison that Margaretta, now in her 79th year, took it upon herself to make a public appeal for books for the prison library.  Even more shocking is the fact that prisoners are locked up for up to 23 hours per day in a state of virtual isolation.  I realise it is not the subject we are discussing today, but I would welcome if the Minister of State made a statement in support of Margaretta D'Arcy and if he would tell the House that he will call for her release.  She should not be imprisoned for campaigning on human rights issues.  If the community courts system had been in place, I wonder if she would be where she is at present.  I trust and hope not.  She should not be there anyway.</p><p>Educational, sensory and emotional deprivations are the chief characteristics of our penal system.  This is not good enough by any standards.  If we must lock people up, we must also recognise that such people are human beings with needs and rights.  Our prison population is overwhelmingly composed of poor people, mostly young men under the age of 25 years from working class backgrounds.  Any initiative that seeks to reduce the number of those in prison is most welcome and makes for a sensible penal policy that is fit for a modern democracy.</p><p>Finally, while I and my party support this motion, it is somewhat ironic that while the Minister for Justice and Equality is about to introduce community courts, his colleagues in the Government have slashed the budgets of community youth groups and dismantled the community support infrastructure across Ireland.</p> <p>Keeping people, especially young people, out of prison and away from the criminal justice system requires a co-ordinated effort across the services.  A properly resourced and well-funded community sector is central to that effort.</p><p>I cannot let the matter go without noting that the impact of austerity has seen an increase in petty crime.  Anybody who goes to or reads the reports prepared by joint policing committees will see that there has been an increase in the number of thefts on the person, thefts from shops, etc. and the incidence of domestic violence.  All of that has been linked to increased alcoholism, drinking, anti-social behaviour, etc. and the austerity policies that have been put in place so we cannot have one without the other.  </p><p>F&aacute;ilt&iacute;onn Sinn F&eacute;in roimh agus taca&iacute;onn muid leis an r&uacute;n seo.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il againn gur chun feabhais a bheidh an c&oacute;ras ag dul.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500027#AA00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and I support the motion.  It is time that we looked at how we deal with minor offences.  I am someone who has briefly practised in the District Court in that area and found that one does not need to send people to prison to educate them about crime.  All one needs to do is attend the District Court on any morning where one will see people learning the ropes and how to go further down that road to crime.  I have large numbers of young people congregate there making friends with people who are involved in crime.  It would be much better to move young people away from that scenario.</p><p>A number of years ago I was involved in a project.  I was chairman of a board of directors and was asked by a community group to help out in a centre that was attended by 50 young people who had dropped out of the education system.  The vast majority of them had been referred to the place by the Garda who had gotten involved at a very early stage because they wanted to make sure that the young people did not go down the road of crime.  It was interesting when I worked with the young people to discover their difficulties; the reason they had taken the wrong route was due to a lack of literacy and numeracy skills.  The project cost &euro;650,000 on average and we had full-time teachers plus support staff.  We also made interesting discoveries when we carried out a survey on a group of young people who had left the centre five years earlier.  We commenced the project to see what progress they had made after we helped them onto the first step of the ladder.  We found that 70% of the people who had attended the centre five years earlier were in full-time employment which would not have been the case but for early intervention by community garda&iacute; and their work with young people.  Their intervention led to these young people discovering a better way of doing things.  </p><p>Unfortunately we discovered that a large number of the young people had come from families where neither the father nor grandfather had ever worked.  Those young people got involved and changed their work culture for themselves.  Their success is attributable to the people who worked with them, the garda&iacute; and the local community.  The project had originally been established on a voluntary basis by local community people who felt a need to approach the problem from a different angle.  Likewise with community courts we must work towards a solution and ensure that people do not go deeper into the criminal world.  People working together is part of the solution.  A local community can benefit from minor offences being dealt with appropriately and not in the abstract manner that the District Court tends to use to deal with the matter.  </p><p>I welcome the decision by the Minister to establish a pilot project.  Perhaps we might look at establishing a similar project in Cork city.</p><p>Senator Norris mentioned that poor areas have not benefited from Government funding over the past number of years but I think that they have.</p> <p>We introduced a reduction in the pupil-teacher ratio in the primary schools, from 27-28 students to one teacher to 15 students to one, and that had a benefit.  Likewise, there are new projects now being put in place in a number of areas around the country where it is about working with parents and children together and ensuring that the parents get the benefit of the education system that the they did not get in their younger years.  Those are the policies that can make a significant contribution to reducing the number getting involved in crime.  There have been many projects over the past few years and we should not let them go unrecognised.</p><p>I welcome this proposal.  The Minister is correct to set up the pilot project, but he should not confine it to Dublin.  We should also look at setting up one or two projects in other parts of the country as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500028#BB00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it agus roimh an r&uacute;n seo &oacute; Phairt&iacute; Fhine Gael.  Is &aacute;bhar an-t&aacute;bhachtach &eacute; an t-&aacute;bhar seo agus is ceart d&uacute;inn &eacute; a phl&eacute; sa Seanad.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il  agam go rachaidh an tionscnamh p&iacute;ol&oacute;tach seo amach &oacute; Bhaile Atha Cliath ar fud na t&iacute;re.</p><p>Fianna F&aacute;il is happy to welcome this motion of the Fine Gael Party.  We support the concept of community courts.  Where this approach to what one might call petty lawlessness which has an impact on the quality of life in a community has been deployed, it seems to have had good results, and that is the most important aspect.  Interestingly, the successful British Prime Minister, Mr. Tony Blair, realised that voters saw anti-social behaviour as a really serious problem and it had to be dealt with effectively.  Anything one can do to deal with such issues, petty theft, drugs, public order and vandalism in a community, will have an enormous impact on a the general quality of life in a neighbourhood and on the victims of those crimes.  If the community courts can help that, then they are to be welcomed because the impact on people of these low-level crimes is enormous and disproportionate to the level of the crime.  If someone is making noise, is drunk and disorderly, or is smoking, as opposed to dealing, soft drugs in a neighbourhood, those are really serious annoyances for people even though they may not seem so on an individual basis.  If a crime occurred once, it would not have that much of an impact, but it does if it is happening all the time.</p><p>The concept of community courts is a welcome one and I am certainly happy that there is a pilot project in place.  However, as I stated as Gaeilge, I would like to see the project roll-out across the country.  We will see how the pilot works.  Presumably, as the models are there, it will be successful and will work, and it will be rolled out throughout the country.</p><p>Another point I would make, from my experience of courts, is that courts are difficult places for non-professionals.  They are, I suppose, formal places.  They are intimidating.  Whether one is the victim or the defendant, a different system could help.  A less formal way, while still recognising that wrongs have been done and need to be righted, could help to address the overall crime rate in the country and the overall enjoyment of life in communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500028#BB00300"><p>I am delighted to support this proposal, which is sound educationally and socially.  Its intention is positive and it could have a profound impact on society.</p><p>I am supporting this for a few reasons.  First, young people can be vulnerable and if they get on the wrong side of the law early, it can start a dangerous pattern.  I am encouraged by the model of a community because it may not turn young people off the law.</p> <p>It could show them how the law can be on their side and understand them.  The motion contains many positive points, one being the proposal to work in a cross-agency way with other service providers to perhaps use the misdemeanour in which the young person was engaged, be it petty theft or whatever else, to introduce him or her to other providers that could help him or her.  Ultimately, if such persons go into prison, they will be a huge cost on the State and as Members are aware, there is a high level of reoffending, as they can come out in a much worse state.  A number of years ago I produced an early school leaving study in the Oireachtas and this could easily have been one of that report's recommendations.  I compliment Martin Senator Conway on it.  In the course of the study we visited some of the prisons, including Mountjoy, and met some of the young people concerned.  They truly had been let down by society.  In many cases, they had been let down by their families, albeit not intentionally, as many of those families were well intentioned but did not know how to parent.  They were not understood by their schools, had dropped out of school early and were lost.  Thereafter, such persons definitely will show up, as they will be caught by the Garda and show up in the courts system.  I do not believe a heavy duty court is the place for them.  I agree completely with Senator Thomas Byrne's observation that much of the time they are petrified of courts.  Consequently, a model is required that is softer, fairer and more understanding and I believe Senator Martin Conway may have put his finger on it in this regard.  The point is to take it forward, which is not to say a person should not receive his or her medicine or be punished.  It is a question of how it is done.</p><p>I also wish to support the motion for another reason that concerns a category of persons whom I found to be in need.  Members may or may not believe it, but there is a little understood category of young person with impulsive behaviour, particularly those with attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, ADHD.  Quite a large proportion of such persons end up in prison.  I suggest they are wild but not bad.  However, they can be made very bad by having a record.  Another category for whom this measure would be extremely helpful and which all Members are aware is at risk is those young people at risk in respect of mental health issues.  Some young people, once they get into trouble for a minor offence, become fixated on it and cannot deal with anything else and in a reasonably caring society everyone is worried they might take their own lives.  I can tell Members that throughout the country parents of teenagers and young people are extremely worried about mental health issues, which makes the job of parenting so much harder.  I acknowledge that I am deviating slightly, but it is equally relevant because it can be traumatising to have a court date in front of one.</p><p>I wish Senator Martin Conway well and he has my complete support.  I support his call on the Minister for Justice and Equality to initiate a pilot project for community courts in Ireland.  While the Senator has sought to have the pilot project take place in Dublin, I believe any city would be appropriate.  I believe limiting it to Dublin city would be unwise and there is no reason not to have one in four major cities as there is social disadvantage in each.  However, such courts are not merely to deal with social disadvantage.  Any kid can get into trouble and every kid deserves the chance to be saved.  Everybody deserves one chance and this could be the vehicle to lift him or her out of that trouble and to show him or her a more positive way to behave.  </p><p>I thank Senators and the Acting Chairman and will leave matters in the Minister of State's capable hands.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1006" speakername="Joe Costello" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500029#CC00300"><p>In the first instance, I thank the ten Senators for their contributions.  They were all excellent and I compliment Senator Martin Conway and his colleagues on tabling the motion which was presented to the Cabinet this morning by the Minister, Deputy Alan Shatter.  He asked members of the Cabinet for their approval, which they gave.  Consequently, the motion has been accepted by the Cabinet and everything else will flow from there.</p> <p>I am speaking today on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Shatter.  He would like to thank the Senators for raising the matter today.  It is an important topic which the Minister has been considering alongside the many other reforms of our courts system that are already under way.  That reflects some of the remarks made by many Senators that it should not be taken in isolation and that other measures and supports should be considered.</p><p>Community courts are locally focused courts that attempt to harness the power of the justice system to address local problems.  They can take many forms but all focus on creative partnerships and problem-solving.  They strive to create new relationships both within the justice system and with external stakeholders such as residents and the business community.  Such courts are innovative in their approach to public safety and to addressing problems in the communities.</p><p>As Senators will be aware, a number of jurisdictions have developed what are sometimes referred to as &quot;problem solving&quot; courts.  Models include community courts, drug courts and restorative programmes.  These courts can vary in character but generally incorporate a combination of sanction for the crime, assistance in rehabilitation and reparation to either the victim or the community in which the offence took place.  They combine punishment with help such as drug treatment or mental health counselling.</p><p>The community court model in the United States works on the basis that courts should be problem-solving, and should not merely be administering justice.  In general terms, there are five key elements to the problem-solving approach: a tailored approach to justice; creative partnerships; informed decision-making; accountability; and a focus on results.</p><p>Members are aware that in 2007, the National Crime Council published a report entitled Problem Solving Justice - The Case for Community Courts in Ireland to which many Senators referred.  The report examined the position in the United States and in the United Kingdom to see how these courts work in practice and made recommendations for the establishment of a court on a pilot basis.  To date, these recommendations have not been implemented; this may have been due, in part, to the fact that such courts are potentially resource intensive.</p><p>However, the Minister, Deputy Shatter, believes it is now time to fully explore whether community courts can be of benefit within the Irish criminal justice system.  The Minister is not alone in this view.  Members will be aware of the recent work of the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality, which held a public consultation process on community courts on 29 January last to which many Senators referred.  I would like to commend the committee's Chairman, Deputy David Stanton, for his excellent work in pursuing the idea of a having a community court in Ireland.</p><p>Earlier that same day, the Dublin City Business Association held a seminar on community courts.  Invited international speakers with experience in the establishment and operation of community courts participated in both events, and their input proved to be very informative.  The knowledge gained from those presentations and the surrounding debates will be further considered.  It is very beneficial to draw on international experience which can help to broaden insights we might have on what works and what does not work.</p><p>The Dublin City Business Association must be commended for its proactive approach, and it is also good to know that the business community is open to a partnership approach in dealing with anti-social behaviour in the city centre.  It is also important to state that, generally, Dublin city centre is safe and it is a small number of offenders, usually those with particular problems such as alcohol or drug abuse, that give rise to a significant portion of the anti-social behaviour.  The community court approach will provide an integrated problem solving solution to dealing with such repeat offenders and will also provide a rapid response to dealing with the type of one-off offending that can occur in the city such as public order offending.</p><p>The Minister, Deputy Shatter, has already given this topic some thought.  In December 2013, he sought the views of the President of the District Court on his proposal to establish a community court in Dublin city centre and she has indicated that the Judiciary is positively disposed towards such an initiative.  She also welcomed the opportunity for further judicial engagement in developing an appropriate model in Dublin.</p><p>An initial project is envisaged in Dublin city centre operating on a pilot basis where stakeholders will engage in partnerships, in conjunction with the local business community, to progress the project.  The project must operate in a fully integrated way.  I am informed that the Minister, Deputy Shatter, is initially suggesting a pilot in the Dublin city centre because he wants to evaluate how the community court model will work in the Irish context.</p> <p>Not all community courts have been a success.  In the recent seminars, we heard that where such courts are not successful, it can be difficult to establish why that may be the case.  The Minister is interested in hearing more about such experiences so that we can analyse the various reasons they were not successful and benefit from lessons learned. </p><p>The Minister believes appropriate planning is the key to getting an effective court in place.  Therefore, before moving to establish the court, a considerable amount of preparatory work needs to be undertaken in collaboration with all stakeholders.  In the current climate, each of the stakeholders involved is operating with fewer resources so the preparation and planning stages of the project are essential to ensure that the resources involved are used effectively.  The Minister is conscious that scarce resources must be used wisely and effectively.  In addition, following the establishment of a pilot project, it would be important to have proper monitoring and robust evaluation so that we can see if the community court is delivering the necessary results.</p><p>Part of the planning process will involve determining the type of offences and offenders suitable to be dealt with by a community court model.  In its 2007 report, the National Crime Council considered the type of offences that might be dealt with, such as drunk in public, disorderly conduct, illegal street trading, certain assault cases, criminal damage, theft, drug use and handling stolen property cases.  In line with the Minister's own thinking, the council also recommended, in the first instance, that a community court be established in the inner city of Dublin to deal with quality of life offences.  It was recommended that the caseload be built up on an incremental basis.  It was also considered essential that all services, such as drug and alcohol addiction counselling, be available on site.  The co-operation of the stakeholders providing the necessary services, such as education, health and treatment services, will be essential and a full review of the necessary supports that need to be in place will have to be undertaken in consultation with stakeholders.</p><p>Members will be aware that we already have a Drug Treatment Court operating in Dublin.  This court was designed as an alternative measure for dealing with less serious and non-violent drug offenders.  The Drug Treatment Court shares some similar characteristics to the community court model but the community court would involve a more integrated response from State agencies to offending and it also places an emphasis on community restitution.</p><p>While a community court represents an innovative collaborative approach to dealing with offenders, it is a prerequisite that whatever model is decided on must conform to Ireland's constitutional requirements and must also respect the constitutional standards of due process. </p><p>I mentioned earlier the importance of the planning stage of this project and it will be essential to fully consider: what kind of court we want; what types of offences we want to be dealt with in this way; what type of offender can benefit from the community court and how should the selection process be managed to ensure effective operation of this resource intensive option; where should the court be located and can the necessary facilities be harnessed by co-ordination measures or do they need to be located in close proximity; how should the court be funded and should the Exchequer fund the traditional criminal justice aspects of the court's facilities and should the business community, which is advocating the establishment of these types of courts, contribute towards the provision of some necessary services, such as counselling or mediation; and if would it be desirable to have legislation to underpin the courts' operations.</p><p>I stress again the importance of proper planning and ensuring that the resources which will need to be dedicated to this project by the various stakeholders will used effectively.  We also need to ensure that we get the right type of court to deal with the particular issues which need to be addressed in the Dublin city centre area.  The Minister looks forward to working with interested stakeholders, including the Judiciary, relevant agencies as well as with the Joint Committee on Justice, Equality and Defence in developing this initiative.  Further research will be necessary and the Minister intends to request officials in the Department of Justice and Equality and the Courts Service to look at other community court models, in particular those operating in similar environments to the Irish justice systems, so as to identify the key elements required to establish a successful court in this country.  When the matter has been fully examined, the Minister intends to bring forward proposals on the development of a pilot community court in Dublin city centre.</p><p>This was an extremely interesting debate.  I agree fully with the thrust of the motion and the decision of the Cabinet in regard to this matter.</p> <p>As well as the other items mentioned, it is something we might look at in terms of community policing.  In 2005, we introduced community policing on a legislative basis.  We located it with local authorities through joint policing committees.  We established community policing forums and involved the local communities in the structure.  It is extraordinarily successful in the north inner city, where Senator Norris and I are based, and Store Street station, in particular, has championed it..  I see it as an organic development to move from community policing to community courts and from community policing to community sanction and other areas of administration and treatment.  A connection can usefully be made so that it is truly a local initiative.</p><p>The Minister's reply refers to the business community.  I am associated with the reply and I am now adding a few words of my own.  We introduced the local authority into community policing as a mainstay and all the meetings that take place are held under the auspices of the local authority, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the local community.  With new initiatives on local authority development after the next elections, perhaps this area can be usefully explored with real local authority participation in local issues so that there is a local initiative its own right.</p><p>I generally agree with Senator Norris but I disagree in respect of the Criminal Assets Bureau, which was not the creation of Tony Gregory but of myself and Deputy R&oacute;is&iacute;n Shortall.  We came up with the idea and we were about to hold a press conference on the afternoon that Veronica Guerin was killed.  I was chairman of the policy committee of the Labour Party at the time.  We passed on the material to Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, who was then Minister for Finance, and Nora Owen.  The Proceeds of Crime Act and the Criminal Assets Bureau were included in the next legislation that arose.  It is a small matter.  I thank Senators for their excellent contributions and I commend Senator Martin Conway on the work he has done in putting in place an exciting and innovative initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500032#FF00200"><p>Does the Minister of State have any comment on Margaretta D'Arcy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1006" speakername="Joe Costello" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500032#FF00300"><p>I will leave that for another time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="17:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500032#FF00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for a comprehensive reply delivered in his usual style, in which he adds words to the prepared reply and it only enhances it.  His experience on the ground in Dublin city centre is most beneficial.  I agree with the contention of the Minister of State about involving the local authority as a central aspect of community courts.  As late as yesterday evening, I attended a joint policing committee in County Clare.  Over the past decade, we have seen more co-operation between the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, local communities and local authorities.  It encapsulates local policing and community policing.  That is good.  The 2005 legislation providing for joint policing committees has been successful.  It could be more successful and perhaps it is a matter for another day when we can increase and develop community policing and co-operation between various stakeholders.  Some joint policing committees are working very well, while others could be doing much better.  As a society, we could be doing much better and there is significant scope for the Garda Reserve to develop awareness training programmes, school programmes and programmes to assist old people with regard to their knowledge about protecting themselves.</p><p>I am pleased that the Cabinet has endorsed the motion.  A pilot project in Dublin is extremely important.  It will test the idea, but that will only happen if resources are made available.  The implementation group needs to be established sooner rather than later; I am talking about weeks or months.  Whatever stakeholder engagement needs to happen can happen as part of an implementation group.  All stakeholders will be involved in the implementation group.  I want to see the community court established in Dublin in the lifetime of this Government, which is a timeline of less than two years.  I would like to see official timelines at this stage.  I will use the facility of the Adjournment debate to request specific timelines in the coming weeks and months.  There is momentum at Government level within the Oireachtas, and it is great that the motion has received unanimous support.  I thank the members of the Opposition for constructive contributions.  We have a role in bringing the public with us and getting it behind the concept of community courts.</p><p>At local authority level in this city, Councillor Ois&iacute;n Quinn, the Lord Mayor of Dublin, is so dedicated to the concept and principle of community courts that there will be involvement of the local authority in the community court, to which the Minister of State referred at the end of his contribution.  With regard to the business community, the fact that the Dublin City Business Association was prepared to fly over speakers from New York means the association is putting its money where its mouth is.  We have significant buy-in from the community.</p><p>With regard to education and research, any pilot community court must have a dedicated research aspect.  The research unit should be set within the complex housing the pilot programme.  I am talking about the principle of a one-stop shop.  We have spoken about local authorities being a one-stop shop for local services but we should let the community court, which will be piloted in this city, be a one-stop shop for bringing people who lose their way and end up on the wrong side of the law back to where they would like to be.  Many renowned educational institutes have a significant role to play.  Six Senators in the House represent educational institutions.  There is a significant role for them to play but I believe the way to drive this forward is a one-stop shop under one roof or as part of a cluster.  The community court can act as a hub and it can be part of the fabric of the community, owned by the community and in the bloodline of the community.  It will work but it must be given a chance.  As a country we have a unique culture and unique ways of doing business.  Any community court must be reflective of the city and what is good and bad about the city.  There is enormous potential but it will require tweaking, as we will not get it right on day one.  As it evolves it will improve, which is why the research element is so critical.</p><p>This is a good day for the Seanad and has proven, in respect of the ten Senators who spoke and the Minister of State, that we are a Chamber that can tease out problems, develop motions and find solutions.  I would like to see it happen more in a reformed Seanad.  I am delighted the motion has received unanimous support.  I thank Senators from across the Chamber who spoke and I look forward to hearing about the timelines and seeing the pilot programme up and running.  It will bear enormous results for the citizens of this city and of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.123" nospeaker="true" time="17:50:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500033#GG00200"><p>When is proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500033#GG00300"><p>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.126" nospeaker="true" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500033#GG00400">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.127" nospeaker="true" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500033#GG00500">Job Creation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500033#GG00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  He may be aware that a couple of weeks ago there was again an announcement of more job losses in Waterford city from Honeywell Process Solutions.  The unemployment figure in Waterford and in the south east is still way above the national average.  It is over a year since I published the Southeast Economic Development Strategy, or SEEDS report, which was endorsed by all parties, published in Waterford and supported by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  The report called for a suite of Government interventions by a number of different statutory and non-statutory agencies to support the creation and retention of jobs in Waterford city and county and across the south east.</p><p>Unfortunately, many of the key recommendations have not been delivered.  If we are to allow the region to properly grow and develop economically, culturally and socially, we must create a level playing field.  An obvious area to consider is regional aid.  Currently, the south east is not on a par with the Border, midlands and west, BMW, region.  If a multinational company has a choice of investing in Waterford or Galway, there are more attractive grant aid rates available in Galway, which puts Waterford and the south east at a big disadvantage.  It is important that there be a level playing field.  The regional aid guidelines are being reviewed this year so there should be a progressive move, with Waterford and the south east brought to the same point as the BMW region.  Any reverse of this would not be a net gain for the State but instead would be a step backwards.  At least there would be a level playing field for the south east.</p><p>There are a number of other necessary interventions.  We still do not have a regional IDA office, a regional IDA director or a regional strategy.  We do not have a university.  All of these issues must be resolved if Waterford and the south east are to be put on a level playing field.  The Government must not drags its heels on any of the recommendations in my report or the report published by the new city and county council in Waterford calling for very similar proposals, including the roll-out of the dark fibre network, better broadband connectivity and the upgrading of systems, as well as investment in the regional airport, a regional director of the IDA and a proper joined-up regional strategy.  There should also be an educational attainment strategy to consider the issue across all levels and how we can increase educational attainment in the region, where the level is among the worst in the country.</p><p>The Minister of State would agree there is no silver bullet or panacea for solving the obvious problem in the south east, where the entire region is underperforming.  There is no reason for this but it is accepted by the Government that the south east is underperforming for the wrong reasons.  If we can get the interventions we need from the Government and State agencies, I have no doubt the people in the south east can turn things around.  We can and will create jobs but we need the tools and Government support to do this.  One of the clear recommendations I made in the report is to create a level playing field with regard to regional aid, and I ask the Government to follow through in that regard.  We cannot continue with the position where Waterford is unfairly treated in comparison with Galway or other cities and counties in the BMW region when unemployment figures for Waterford city and county are so high.  I ask the Government to consider the issue and deliver the recommendations made by the Oireachtas committee and the newly-merged local authorities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="17:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500033#GG00700"><p>I thank Senator Cullinane for raising this important issue.  The House is aware that the guidelines for regional aid, also known as investment aid, enable the State's industrial development agencies to pay grants at enhanced rates to business in order to support new investment and employment in productive projects in Ireland's most disadvantaged reasons.  This helps in the convergence of these regions with the more advantaged regions.  All such grants come from the Exchequer, and there is no EU or other external funding.</p><p>The guidelines for 2014 to 2020 were adopted by the Commission on 19 June 2013 and will enter into force on 1 July 2014.  At present, Waterford and the wider south-east region qualify for regional investment aid at the rate of 30% for small companies with fewer than 50 employees, 20% for medium sized companies with 50 to 249 employees and 10% for large companies.  The companies in the BMW region can currently be aided at rates 5% higher than these rates but this is a transition arrangement from 2007 to the end of June 2014.  Due to the BMW region moving ahead of the status it had between 2002 and 2006 as one of the most deprived areas of the EU, for 2014 to 2020 the regional aid guidelines stipulate that all Irish areas designated for aid will have the same rates from 1 July 2014.  The same rates will apply in Waterford as the BMW region from 1 July this year.</p><p>Departmental officials are currently compiling the most up-to-date economic data for each county in order to determine which counties will qualify for inclusion in a revised regional aid map for Ireland.  Once the data has been compiled and analysed, qualifying regions, to a maximum of 51.28% of total population, will be included in the new map.  This will be agreed by the Government and submitted to the Commission by the end of June 2014.  The most regional employment data from the Central Statistics Office indicates that in the 12 months to the end of September 2013, an additional 10,000 people were in employment in the south-east region, including Waterford, and the unemployment rate fell by 2.8% in that period.  This is a very positive development, representing a significant improvement in the numbers at work in the region, and it reflects the success of Government policy, especially the Action Plan for Jobs and various initiatives to enhance competitiveness and boost economic activity.</p><p>The IDA south-east region comprises counties Waterford, Wexford, Carlow, Kilkenny and south Tipperary, and I visited Waterford twice recently.  IDA Ireland is focused on advancing the economic development of the region, primarily through the gateway of Waterford city, with the other key centres being Wexford, Kilkenny, Carlow and Clonmel.  In the region as a whole there are 63 IDA Ireland client companies employing 10,712 people in full-time jobs, with a further 1,207 in part-time employment.  That amounts to approximately 12,000 people.  IDA Ireland has a long relationship with these companies and works closely with them to ensure their long-term sustainability and encourage growth, development and continuing reinvestment.</p><p>Following the closure of TalkTalk in Waterford in 2011, the Government put a particular focus on the region and the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, published the south east employment action plan and established a forum of all State agencies and local players to set out actions to increase employment in the area.  The Minister has regularly met representatives of IDA Ireland, Enterprise Ireland and the forum to review progress.</p> <p>Work is ongoing on the implementation of the south-east employment action plan recommendations, with the agencies and stakeholders working together to maximise benefits for the region.  The south-east forum, established to oversee the implementation of the action plan, will continue to examine options that will lead to job creation and investment opportunities in the south east.  There have been significant gains for the region, including a major investment by Glanbia in Belview on the Kilkenny-Waterford border which will provide 1,600 direct and indirect jobs, as well as an additional 450 jobs during the construction phase.  In February 2013, Sanofi announced plans to invest &euro;44 million in Genzyme's biotechnology campus in Waterford.  This investment will increase the site's diversity of products and comes on top of an investment of &euro;150 million just over a year ago.  This investment ensures that the Waterford facility, which currently employs approximately 500 people, can produce the company's latest products and gives an indication of the Waterford site's value to the company.  In March 2013, Nypro Healthcare announced plans to establish an additional state-of-the-art medical device facility in Waterford, which will result in the creation of over 200 high quality jobs in the coming years.  Eishtec, the call centre operator, has in the region of 750 staff between its Waterford and Wexford centres.  The company aims to bring that total to approximately 900 by the summer of this year.  A further 65 Enterprise Ireland-supported new jobs were created by Dawn Meats in Waterford as a result of a five year, &euro;300 million contract with McDonald's restaurants.  Danone baby nutrition in Wexford announced an investment in its manufacturing facility which will create approximately 45 new jobs.  The two local Waterford County and City Enterprise Boards have created 59 new jobs, while IDA Ireland has announced plans to build new advance, open-plan manufacturing facilities in Waterford in order to enhance the offering in the area to win new business.  I am informed by IDA Ireland that the proposed new advance building facility, which the agency is funding in Waterford, will be 2,348 m&sup2; and will be located at the IDA technology park on the Cork Road in Waterford.  I understand that the procurement process has commenced, with the outcome expected within the next month.  </p><p>The Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton, has asked IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland to work with the Department to explore what further initiatives can be taken to ensure a better approach to enterprise development in the region.  The Minister has done extraordinary work on behalf of the region.  I have met the regional directors of both IDA Ireland and Enterprise Ireland, whose commitment to the region is also very evident.  This exercise will complement an indepth analysis of our foreign direct investment, FDI, strategy which is currently being undertaken by Forf&aacute;s and will take account of factors such as the key trends emerging in FDI best practice internationally, Ireland's strengths in attracting FDI as well as state aid rules.  The results of these two exercises will form the basis of IDA Ireland's strategy from 2015 onwards.  All of the key State players have been actively pursuing initiatives to facilitate development and job creation in the south east and with continued co-operation and collaboration, it is hoped that further benefits will accrue to the region.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500034#HH00200"><p>I do not doubt the Minister's support for the south east and know that he is aware of the problems in the region.  However, the people who live in the south east and particularly in Waterford, will not be clapping the Government on the back, given the very high levels of unemployment in the county.  I spoke about levelling the playing field and making sure that a number of promises contained in the programme for Government are delivered upon.  These need to be driven over the Cabinet line by Ministers who live in the constituency, particularly Deputies Hogan and Howlin, who have a responsibility to ensure that we get a university, investment in broadband provision and a regional IDA office with a regional director who is working to a regional strategy.  There must also be a level playing field in the context of grant aid.  This is what the south-east region needs and such developments will need Cabinet support from Ministers who live in the constituency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1081" speakername="John Perry" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500034#HH00300"><p>The Senator will have to admit that there is a lot of straight talk in the reply I have given him.  Action is being taken and it is yielding results, as is clear from various job creation announcements, the plan by IDA Ireland to build an advance manufacturing facility as well as the enormous investment by Glanbia on the Waterford-Kilkenny border.  A lot of new jobs are being created in the region, irrespective of the location of the offices of the IDA.  This Government has delivered a considerable amount for the south-east region in the short time it has been in office and the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation is determined to deliver more.  No Government has been as committed to the south-east region as this one.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.133" nospeaker="true" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500034#HH00350">Water Quality Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500034#HH00400"><p>T&aacute; &aacute;thas orm deis a bheith agam labhairt ar an &aacute;bhar t&aacute;bhachtach seo agus cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire freisin.  I thank the Minister for coming to the House to discuss an issue which is significant in County Meath, particularly in those areas where hard water is a feature.  Many of County Meath's residents who are new to the area are not used to hard water; we are talking about a sizeable number of people, given the fact that 60% of the population was not born in the county.  In various parts of County Meath, the water is very hard, as has been acknowledged by Meath County Council.  The council has produced an information leaflet outlining to people what to do about hard water.  The practical reality for those who have hard water is that it is very costly.  They incur costs through, for example, having to replace kettles regularly.  At a more serious level, however, costs are incurred through having to replace boilers, tanks and so forth.</p><p>I attended a public meeting in Ashbourne a number of weeks ago which was organised by a completely non-political group of concerned residents.  I was very impressed because normally such meetings have a political angle, particularly in the run-up to elections but this one did not.  The aim of the group was to put pressure on politicians of all hues to raise and address this issue.  I attended the meeting with my party colleague, Mr. Sean Smith from Ashbourne.  </p><p>People have had to spend huge sums of money dealing with the consequences of hard water.  It was interesting to note at the meeting that very few people were saying that they were not going to pay the water charges.  Most of those who attended were more concerned with making sure that the charging structure would be fair and would reflect the extra costs incurred by those living in hard water areas because those costs are huge.  I am not asking for a subsidy for the installation of water softeners, although some people at the meeting did suggest that.  Most people would be happy if there was a recognition in the charging structure of the extra costs incurred in hard water areas and it is worthwhile exerting political pressure in this regard.  The Commission on Energy Regulation, CER, is engaging in a consultation process where this matter can be raised but it is also important to raise it in these Houses.  I look forward to the Minister's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/967" speakername="Phil Hogan" time="18:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500034#HH00500"><p>The programme for Government includes a commitment to introduce water charges based on usage above a free allowance.  The Government considers that charging based on usage is the fairest way to charge for water and it has decided that water meters should be installed in households connected to public water supplies.  The Water Services Act (No. 2) 2013 provides for the transfer of water services functions from the local authorities to Irish Water.  The Act also provides that the Commission for Energy Regulation, CER, will be responsible for the independent economic regulation of Irish Water.  The CER has been given statutory responsibility for protecting the interests of customers.</p><p>Under the European Communities (Drinking Water) (No. 2) Regulations, 2007, a copy of which is available in the Oireachtas Library, suppliers of drinking water are required to ensure that the water supplied is wholesome and clean.  Water which is wholesome and clean is defined as water which is free from any micro-organisms and parasites and from any substances which in numbers or concentrations constitute a potential danger to human health, and which meets the quality standards specified in the schedule to the regulations.  Hard water is not included as a parameter in the quality standards specified in the regulations as it does not pose a threat to human health.  The Environmental Protection Agency, EPA, is the supervisory authority with responsibility for monitoring Irish Water's compliance with these regulations.  </p><p>I have listened to what Senator Byrne had to say and would suggest that the group to which he referred makes a submission to the CER and to the EPA to draw attention to the specific issue of hard water in Ashbourne and other parts of County Meath.  </p> <p>I suggest the group involved makes a submission to the regulator and the Environmental Protection Agency, EPA, to identify some of the specific issues regarding hard water in Ashbourne and many other parts of County Meath.  As you know, a Chathaoirligh, I know County Meath is more renowned for hard men than hard water.  The consultation process with the regulator will begin in April and, by making a submission, the regulator will decide measures on charging for water.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500035#JJ00200"><p>I am grateful to the Minister for his answer.  The fact this emerging issue is being taken seriously by him and the head of the Commission for Energy Regulation, CER, is welcome.  I am making no claims about the safety of hard water.  It is perfectly safe.  I am glad Meath is built on strong foundations but it has consequences.  I, as well as other public representatives, will advise the residents to make a submission.  I get complaints on this emerging issue from Ashbourne and Dunshauglin while my colleague, Deirdre Smith, is having a public meeting in Ratoath tomorrow evening.  While I thank the Minister for his reply, I will not accept this is the final world on this significant issue and we will continue the fight.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.138" nospeaker="true" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500035#JJ00250">Beef Industry Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500035#JJ00300"><p>I thank the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Simon Coveney, for taking time from his busy schedule to address the issue of the drop in beef prices in meat factories over the past weeks.  This will have implications for Food Harvest 2020 and farmer confidence in stocking levels.  Will the Minister consider bringing all the stakeholders together in an emergency beef summit to discuss this issue and find a way of moving forward?  Following a meeting with the IFA, the Minister met with a delegation from Meat Industry Ireland.  Have there been any developments from this meeting?</p><p>The beef market is challenging at present.  Prices are still very low which could put some farmers at risk of going out of business.  Will the Minister consider a slaughter policy for male calves?  Will he also consider waiving the &euro;10 export inspection fee on calves?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="18:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500035#JJ00400"><p>I thank the Senator for giving me the opportunity to discuss this matter in the Seanad.</p><p>The value of beef exports was estimated at &euro;2.1 billion in 2013.  This export performance, based on wide portfolio of customers, has contributed significantly to higher returns for Irish beef in recent years.  It also reflects the success of Bord Bia&rsquo;s marketing strategy which focuses on the key attributes of Irish beef such as environmentally sustainable, grass-based production systems, full traceability, quality assurance at all stages and superior eating quality.  I am committed to developing a policy framework that fosters innovation and promotes efficiency and improved performance at all levels of the beef supply chain.  These export figures are underpinned by the high quality output from our primary sector.  I fully agree with those who advocate for a strong suckler sector.</p><p>Under Food Harvest 2020, the original target for the beef sector was to increase the value of exports by 20% by 2020.  This was increased on the recommendation of the beef activation group to 40%.  The various targets under Food Harvest 2020 are regularly monitored and reviewed by the high level implementation group which I chair.  Obviously, any factors which may significantly affect beef prices or which lead to a fall in production would be of concern and it is important that beef farmers have confidence in their sector.  However, it would be premature to consider any adjustment in the target for the beef sector on the basis of the recent drop in prices.  It would not be prudent to change targets on the basis of temporary price adjustments in the context of a strategy which has another six years to run.</p><p>The average R3 steer price per kg, excluding VAT, the benchmark price for cattle, increased by 42% between 2008 and 2013.  It is too early to say if the current drop in prices will continue and I hope this will just be a short-term drop.  Aggregate cattle supplies at Department-approved meat plants to early February 2014 are up 7% on the corresponding period in 2013 with strong increases recorded in the steer, heifer and cull cow categories.  This higher throughput has led to factories giving preference to certain types of stock that are better suited to the requirements of their retail customers.  Prices for prime steers and heifers have remained relatively stable but the young bull trade is challenging at present as age and weight issues continue to affect demand.  I note, however, that the young bull kill has increased by 60% between week 1 and week 6 of 2014.  Up to 6,000 bulls are being killed a week to get through oversupply.</p><p>The beef industry is dependent on exports and the need to ensure that it is producing efficiently for overseas markets cannot be ignored.  One of the main difficulties in marketing young bulls older than 16 months is that these animals are outside the specifications preferred by the UK market.  This is a major disadvantage at present because the UK market has effectively become the highest-priced beef market in the EU.  Delays in young bull slaughtering undoubtedly put pressure on producer profit margins.  Neither I nor any European agriculture Minister can interfere in a trade that is cyclical in nature and prone to short-term price fluctuations.  I am, of course, entirely sympathetic to those farmers facing difficulties in getting their cattle slaughtered.  Cattle prices are determined, however, by the interplay of supply and demand.  I have no function in commercial transactions between the meat factories and their suppliers.</p><p>In response to resent issues in the beef sector, I met last week with the IFA and Meat Industry Ireland, comprising the main beef processors in the country, to discuss the situation.  I had a constructive and focused meeting with both parties on this issue.  At my request MII member company members agreed to have their livestock offices available to deal with any cases where producers had queries or concerns about the marketing of their stock.  Lists of contact telephone numbers for all the main beef processors have been published in the farming press.  It is important farmers with concerns make direct contact with their factories to discuss any issues they may have regarding their supplies.  I have had anecdotal evidence that some farmers simply cannot get rid of their animals but factory owners tell me they will take animals.  Of course, farmers want more money for their animals.</p> <p>There is a responsibility on the beef industry to think in the medium and long term about beef supplies and the need to maintain confidence in this sector but they can only do that within reason if they a have problem selling on this product afterwards because it is out of specification.</p><p>It is the responsibility of the industry &ndash; processors and farmers working together &ndash; to manage the type and volume of cattle being brought to market so that the supply chain operates for the benefit of both parties and does not undermine the viability of bull beef production systems for either winter finishers or suckler farmers.  It is essential that all parties communicate with each other and understand the needs of the market for quality animals produced to an agreed specification.  I urge the various farm bodies, the Irish Farmers' Association, IFA, Irish Creamery Milk Supplier Association, ICMSA and Irish Cattle and Sheep Farmers&rsquo; Association, ICSA, and Meat Industry Ireland, MII to continue to meet, as they did in January, to resolve any outstanding issues so all parties can benefit from the opportunities available to the Irish beef sector in other EU member states and in emerging third countries.</p><p>Since my appointment as Minister I have been very active in developing relationships in new and expanding international markets for the beef industry, raising Ireland's profile and increasing international confidence in our production and control systems.  These initiatives have led to a number of notable successes last year in securing new markets for Irish beef in Japan, Singapore, Egypt, Lebanon and Iran.  I am hopeful this year will also see significant progress in gaining access to the US, Canada and, perhaps most exciting, the Chinese market.</p><p>I fully recognise the importance of maintaining confidence in the beef sector and earlier this month I announced the operational details of an investment package worth up to &euro;40 million for beef farmers in 2014.  This package will include &euro;23 million for a beef genomics scheme - which is exciting new thinking about paying farmers to buy into a new genomics breeding programme - &euro;10 million for the beef data programme, &euro;5 million for the beef technology adoption programme and &euro;2 million in residual payments under the suckler cow welfare scheme.  The Government&rsquo;s investment is a continuing strong vote of confidence in the suckler beef sector.  It exemplifies the smart, green growth initiatives envisioned in the Food Harvest 2020 strategy.</p><p>I am very cognisant of the fact that, regardless of the overall macro figures in terms of beef exports being significantly up last year on the previous year and the numbers of beef animals also being up going into this year, there is an issue for some beef farmers, particularly around bull beef, who were producing what they would see as very good animals but which factories tell me are outside the spec of their customers.  That is why farming organisations and factories must work together on this to clear out an oversupply of animals that are not in demand in the marketplace at the moment.  That can be done in the next three to four weeks at current slaughter rates of bulls in that category.  This has been ramped up to 5,000 to 7,000 per week.  If that continues for the next three to four weeks, we will get back to normal pricing.</p><p>A farmer who produces bull beef must do it in consultation with a factory that will buy it so that the farmer produces it to a spec the marketplace wants.  The problem has arisen when farmers seek to sell animals into a factory that does not want them because they are outside of the spec of what is being demanded in the marketplace.  There are a number of examples of farmers producing bull beef at 18 to 22 months and selling them for good prices to the factory because they have been negotiating and talking to the factory about that and the company involved has found an outlet, whether in Italy or somewhere else, for that spec of beef.  However, one cannot expect to come to a factory with something nobody wants and expect to get a top price for it.  We must learn some lessons from this and I hope we will get a response from the industry that will maintain confidence in this sector into the medium term.  Ultimately this is a sector in which we want to facilitate growth and expansion.  We want farmers to get a fair and good return that will facilitate that expansion but that will also facilitate meat factories making the margin they need to survive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500036#KK00200"><p>I thank the Minister very much for his response.  If things do not work out over the next three or four weeks perhaps the Minister would consider a slaughter-out policy of male calves.  Farmers are under pressure and there is a danger they will not continue to produce bull beef in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500036#KK00300"><p>No policy around young male calves, particularly those born in the dairy sector, will provide any instant solution around getting a better price for beef.  We can produce much more beef in Ireland, get a good price for it and sell it into markets, but it must be produced according to the spec customers want.  Most farmers understand that but, unfortunately, some farmers in the bull beef category have been caught out because of a changing market in this area.  We need to learn lessons from that.  We will see less bull beef, more steers and more heifers in the future but there will be some specialist bull beef farmers who will produce for factories and they will negotiate spec with those factories.  That is a profitable business.  However, producing bull beef without knowing one has an outlet for that, and expecting to sell 24 or 26-month-old animals is a very challenging area.  We need to get through this immediate problem.  We need understanding from the factories on that regarding pricing and taking bull beef, but for next year and for future planning we need to learn the lessons from what has happened over the last few weeks.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.144" nospeaker="true" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500036#KK00350">Post Office Network</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="18:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500036#KK00400"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting this item.  I appreciate that the Minister is here to respond.  The Minister is probably hearing a lot about the concerns communities throughout the country have about the future of the post office network.  The issue has been raised on many previous occasions.  The concern from the post officer workers, the network and the Irish Postmasters' Union, IPU, is that a plan be prepared as was committed to in the programme for Government, as to the future of the post office network.  I come from an urban area and I completely understand the value of my local post office, as well as in rural areas.  They play a very valuable role.  That is their strength and they are playing to that.  The network employs 3,000 people and in 2012 there were 1,152 post offices located throughout Ireland.  Grant Thornton recently produced a report on the future viability of the network and it claimed that 450 to 500 post office could close between 2013 and 2017.  I do not understand that because in the years 2006 to 2010 197 post offices closed, but since then only 17 have closed.  That question should be addressed.</p><p>My local postmistress told me they wanted to pitch for driving licences and motor tax.  The local post offices could provide many services.  They are concerned about the move to electronic payments.  Electronic payments are the future and in today's world one cannot stop that because this is about making it easy for consumers and service users.  Nonetheless there are areas within which the post office network can develop expertise and provide additional services.</p> <p>Post bank services are an example.  People could be encouraged to use them.  If they are concerned about the service they are getting from their local bank, they could move to a post bank.</p><p>This is not simply about the Government preparing a plan.  That is important, but people must realise, as consumers and customers, that if they wish to retain their local post office, they must support it.  That strong message should be conveyed.  Perhaps, however, the Minister might respond to their concerns.  Will a plan be put in place or is the Government committed to addressing this issue?  As he is aware, post offices play a very valuable role in terms of community supports.  The postmistress to whom I spoke told me she was the third generation of her family in the post office; therefore, she knows her customers well.  It is a valuable and unique support and we should protect it in so far as we can, given all of the constraints.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500037#LL00200"><p>I thank the Senator for giving me the opportunity, on the same evening as the sustainability of the post office network is being debated in the D&aacute;il, to address in this House the concerns raised by the Irish Postmasters Union, IPU, about the viability of the post office network.  The post office has a unique standing.  Its social role is highly valued, perhaps most highly in rural Ireland, where 64% of the network serves 38% of the population.  I was disappointed to read recent headlines asserting that 557 post offices were to close.  The impression is given that somewhere, somehow, the Government has announced a plan to shut down post offices.  There is no such plan.  In fact, as the Senator said, although 197 post offices were closed between 2006 and 2010, only 17 closures have occurred since 2010.</p><p>An Post has not escaped the challenging environment brought about by the economic collapse in 2008.  More challenging still are the diminishing mail volumes due to technological advances.  Of course, as a network of commercial enterprises, the post office network is also subject to EU competition law.</p><p>From where did the headlines about post office closures emerge?  The origins are a consultancy report that presumes the loss of the social welfare contract, worth &euro;50 million to An Post, and calculates that such a loss would, in the worst case scenario, lead to the closure of 557 post offices.  However, the point is that An Post did not lose the social welfare contract.  In fact, it won it in a tender process as recently as last year.  The Irish Postmasters Union is prudently asking about what the situation might be in 2019.</p><p>There is every reason to be optimistic about the new opportunities that lie ahead for the post office network in the digital age.  The retail network has actually grown in the past five years, even as the mail business has been contracting sharply.  The over-the-counter business today offers very different services from what was offered in the past, including foreign exchange, passport, bank agency and tax payment services.  These services are provided in a competitive environment for customers who can choose to do business in other ways.  The professionalism of the postmasters, the unions and the board and management of An Post has served the network well through the years.  An Post is a trusted brand and has the largest retail presence in the country, with over 1,100 outlets nationwide reaching almost 1.7 million customers.</p><p>While operational matters and the development of commercial strategies are for An Post, as a shareholder, I have a strong interest in and concern about the sustainability of the company.  This is backed by the commitment in the programme for Government to ensure the sustainability of the post office network.  I am, therefore, pleased to announce that the Government has agreed to a whole-of-government consideration, encompassing central and local government and the wider public service, of the nature and extent of services that can be provided for the public using the post office network as a &quot;front office of government&quot;.  This will afford an opportunity to have an holistic review of the range of services which could be provided by the post office network and could perhaps yield synergies among the various agencies.</p><p>There is no doubt that further challenges will present in the years ahead.  I am convinced, however, that An Post possesses the capacity and drive to adapt to the changing needs of customers, as well as the necessary commitment and resolution to continue to develop the post office network.  In doing so, it will have my active support and that of the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500037#LL00300"><p>I welcome what the Minister said, particularly about the proactive approach the Government is taking in addressing the issue across a range of Departments, encompassing central and local government.  I am sure that as a result, it will be possible to provide services through the post office as a front office of government.  That would be a very welcome development which I am sure would be welcomed by the Irish Postmasters Union and workers in post offices throughout the country.  I appreciate the Minister's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/947" speakername="Pat Rabbitte" time="18:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2014022500037#LL00400"><p>Working together, the Government and the IPU, notwithstanding the inexorable progress of the digital age and digital enterprise, can ensure there is a future for the post office network.  This is a unique retail outlet.  No other organisation has 1,150 outlets throughout the country and there is the capacity to win new business and create new products.  My view on the fear expressed about the future of the social welfare contract is that the IPU should make common cause with the Irish League of Credit Unions and seek to develop the basic bank account that could be used for this transfer if and when it goes electronic.  There are a number of such things that could be done that could prove very useful.  The Government's social policy sub-committee will pull together the different strands and consider how to proceed from here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2014-02-25a.150" nospeaker="true" time="18:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 26 February 2014.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>