<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#A00200"><p>I have notice from Senator Marie Moloney that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br /><br />The need for the Minster of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works to outline whether he would consider changing the tendering procurement process to allow for funding by region only to ensure jobs are kept in regional areas in light of the emphasis being put on the Action Plan for Jobs in regional areas.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh of the following matter:<blockquote>An g&aacute; go nd&eacute;anfaidh an tAire Comhshaoil, Pobail agus Rialtais &Aacute;iti&uacute;il soil&eacute;iri&uacute; a thabhairt maidir le l&iacute;on na n-iarratas ar chead&uacute;nais bainte feamainne at&aacute; le cinneadh ag a Roinn faoi l&aacute;thair agus cathain a mheasann an Roinn a dh&eacute;anfar cinnt&iacute; ar na hiarratais at&aacute; ar feitheamh.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health and the HSE to outline details of the financial contribution made by fair deal recipients from their pensions to the overall cost of their nursing home care and the percentage of the total cost that this comprises.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by Senators Moloney and &Oacute; Clochartaigh as suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.  I regret that I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Burke on the grounds that it is a repeat of a similar Commencement matter raised on 30 April 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#B00100"><p>It is a totally different question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#B00200"><p>Unfortunately, the Cathaoirleach made the ruling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#B00300"><p>I understand.  I just want to emphasise that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#B00400"><p>The Senator might raise the matter with him tomorrow morning.  I did not pick the matters and am representing the Cathaoirleach as Leas-Chathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.11" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#B00500">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.12" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#B00650">Public Procurement Contracts</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#B00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to take this matter.  In anticipation of his answer, I know what he is going to say about cost savings in the public sector and note that I appreciate the need for that.  Surely, however, it should not be at the expense of the small local operator.  The procurement and tendering process has squeezed the lifeblood out of small operators in local areas.  The contracts they had for Government and State agency buildings were their lifeblood.  I refer also to caterers and suppliers to the HSE of foods, etc., stationery and office supplies to local authorities, and cleaning contractors to Garda stations and Government buildings.  All of those people are suffering and the life is being squeezed out of them by the big operators with whom they cannot hope to compete.  The big operators can buy all their supplies in bulk, reduce their costs and tender lower.</p> <p>In line with the regional dimension to the Action Plan for Jobs, our aim is to keep jobs and create them in regional areas.  This is an area where we are killing jobs in the regions.  They have no hope.  I have one man who employed 25 people.  He lost a contract to clean a Government building and had to let ten of his 25 staff go.  The Minister of State will probably say the new contractors will take people on, but they are taking them on at a different cost.  They are paying them lower wages.  I know for a fact that some people cleaning Government buildings - we are standing over this - are not paid bank holiday rates.  Local contractors were available at short notice to the organisations and buildings involved and could come in if there was a flood or something else happened.  They were there on the spot to deal with these things.</p> <p>While we are claiming to make savings in the public sector by doing this, it must be asked if this is true in the longer term given that people who are let go from their jobs must claim social welfare payments.  The revenue was circulating locally whereas the contractors doing jobs in the Kerry area, for example, who got the contracts through the tendering process are in Dublin.  Once again, the revenue will be circulating in Dublin inside the Red Cow roundabout.</p> <p>I ask that we look at this and instead tender by region.  We should keep the tendering process within the regions thereby maintaining regional jobs.  I understand that we must make savings.  I am not naive.  However, we should not squeeze the life out of the small operators in our local areas.  I await the Minister of State's reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#B00800"><p>I thank Senator Marie Moloney for raising this matter.  It is timely to do so as we have put in place a new structure, the Office of Government Procurement, for which I have responsibility at ministerial level.  While 2014 was the year of the establishment of the office, 2015 and 2016 will be about ensuring that we have the structures right and that we put as many measures as possible in place to help SMEs.  Any thoughts the Senator has in that regard - she has raised some today - will be given serious consideration.  We may be able to consider that in a moment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The main purpose of the EU public procurement regime is to open up the market and to ensure the free movement of supplies, services and works within the EU having regard to Treaty of Rome principles including transparency, proportionality and equal treatment.  This is the rationale that shapes the detailed rules set out in the EU directives governing the regime.  It would be a breach of the EU rules for a public body to favour or discriminate against particular candidates on grounds such as nationality, geographic location or organisational size, and there are legal remedies which may be used against any public body infringing these rules.</p><p>The new model for procurement was approved by the Government in September 2012 and envisages common goods and services such as utilities, professional services and marketing, print and stationery being procured by a new central sourcing organisation, in this case the Office of Government Procurement, with sectoral specific goods and services and minor works being sourced through the sectors health, education, local government and defence.  The aim of the reform is to deliver overall reductions in the cost of goods and services, better procurement services, introduction of technical standardisation, greater levels of professionalism among staff responsible for procurement and increased performance management of the central procurement function.</p><p>Taxpayers demand that Government secures value for money in all of its spend.  The fragmented procurement arrangements across the public service have enabled suppliers to charge different public service bodies different prices for the same goods and services.  This is not sustainable as the State cannot afford to continue to purchase works, goods and services in a manner that undermines the level of services it can deliver.  Reforms are being carried out in a manner that recognises the clear importance of small and medium-sized enterprises in this country's economic recovery.  </p><p>We have to be transparent and equitable in our treatment of all suppliers.  We spend approximately &euro;8 billion per year on public procurement, some &euro;23 million per day.  If we are serious about economic recovery we need our SMEs to get involved and to have an equal chance in procuring and that is why I am not closing any doors in terms of measures we can put in place to help our SMEs.  A couple of weeks ago there was a very useful Private Members' debate in this House when I accepted an Opposition Bill on social clauses.  Nobody has a monopoly on good ideas and I am always eager to hear them.</p><p>The guidance to contracting authorities contained within circular 10/14, which we put in place to help SMEs participate and which was launched by my Department in April 2014, encourages those bodies to break large contracts down into lots where reasonable to do so.  This enables smaller businesses to compete for these smaller elements of a larger contract.  This has to be done in a way, however, that does not expose the State to undue risk or significant management overheads.  The OGP appreciates that, as it centralises more, there is always the risk that people feel crowded out.  The OGP, therefore, is working with bodies like Enterprise Ireland and InterTrade Ireland to help educate suppliers around building consortia in order that smaller businesses may come together and win larger offerings that the State may put to the marketplace.</p><p>Aggregation arrangements can be implemented in a manner that achieves value for money with a minimal impact on SMEs.  The greater use, where appropriate, of multi-supplier frameworks can address local supplier issues while also ensuring the ongoing cost competitiveness of the framework itself.  Such multi-supplier frameworks may also offer SMEs the opportunity to participate in national level contracts, thereby offering valuable reference work when competing for public procurement contracts in other jurisdictions.  Although changing the tendering procurement process to funding by region only is not allowed under the EU public procurement regime the sourcing strategies developed by the OGP sourcing teams will be based on a full understanding of the supply market in question and the impacts that any new supply arrangements may have.  That is where we may be able to progress the concerns made by the Senator.</p><p>The OGP sourcing teams are made up of procurement professionals specialising in a spend category supported by customer representatives appointed by category councils.  Before the OGP sourcing teams decide how they will go to the market for goods or services they will carry out a full supply market assessment.  This will include consideration of three main elements: current supply arrangements, supply market competition and, crucially, direct consultation with suppliers.  In evaluating current supply arrangements the sourcing teams will consider items such as customer and stakeholder requirements, supplier types, who the suppliers are, regional supply structures and arrangements, a supplier's share of public sector bodies' business, suppliers' locations, structures and sizes, and scope and length of contracts.</p><p>In evaluating supply market competition the sourcing teams will consider items such as level of competition in the local and regional supply market, existence of barriers to entry, potential for substitute goods and services or new innovations, supply chain risks and issues, other customers buying the same items and PESTEL, which stands for political, economic, social, technological, environmental and legal trend analysis, so as to gain an understanding of opportunities and threats that might exist to competition.</p><p>Direct consultation with suppliers is also a key means through which the sourcing teams may gain market insight through the issue of requests for information sent to all suppliers in a given category registered on e-Tenders, and through bidders' briefing sessions and-or consultation with trade and industry representative bodies.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->On the basis of this research, the sourcing team will have a full evidence-based understanding of the market.  This will allow them to make an informed decision about how to go to market and the sourcing strategy, in such a way as to deliver the optimum balance between value for money and risk.</p><p>I would be the first to admit that we need to do more.  We are actively trying to pursue more measures to help SMEs.  It is not all about value for money, although it is absolutely about value for money for the taxpayer, but not just at a headline rate.  We need our SMEs to be involved.  We have put a range of measures in place and I look forward to building upon them. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00200"><p>Is the Senator satisfied with that reply?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00300"><p>Yes and I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive answer.  I was delighted to hear him say that it was not all about value for money.  Sometimes people can tender lower, but they do not do a better job.  We had proof of that in my locality where a person tendered for a local sewerage scheme, but half way through he found he could not do it.  They took my parish out of the scheme.  We discovered later that he had made a terrible mess of another job, yet he still got the job because his was the lowest tender.  Therefore, the lowest tender is not always the best.</p> <p>I have been informed that while two people were working on some jobs in a local government building, that number has now been reduced to one.  Yet they are trying to get the same work done in the same time, so corners are obviously being cut.</p> <p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply which I will circulate to the local people who raised the issue with me.  Hopefully we can come to some arrangement to ensure that jobs are kept in the locality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00400"><p>I again thank Senator Moloney for raising this important matter.  When discussing the issue with local suppliers, she and other public representatives should bring to their attention a number of new measures we have put in place to try to help SMEs.  For example, we are currently considering social clauses whereby unemployment and disadvantaged areas can be factored into decisions.  We will shortly have progress in that regard, as the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin, established a working group on that last year.</p> <p>In addition, we have put in place "meet the buyer" events providing opportunities for SMEs to meet the big public sector buyers face to face.  They can thereby have human conversations, rather than just talking to a machine.</p> <p>InterTradeIreland is working on a cross-Border basis to provide supports and even grants for upskilling SMEs.  I recently launched a new tender advisory service, which guarantees SMEs a quick turnaround answer to a query within a certain number of working days.  Crucially, local enterprise offices have all been given training on procurements.  The LEOs are the interface for all our businesses with the State and I want to see them playing a greater role.  I look forward to LEOs holding many training and information days for SMEs in various communities.  I would be interested in trying to bring one to the Senator's county in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00500"><p>Have these face-to-face meetings taken place yet?  If not, when is the timescale for all these meetings?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00600"><p>We had two last year - one in Belfast and one in Dublin.  It is done on a cross-Border basis.  Approximately 1,000 businesses were represented at the one in Dublin.  I want to see them take place on a more regional basis though.  I am examining how to roll them out to the regions, while working with LEOs.  I will report back to the Senator in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00800"><p>The Senator has had a good run for her money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00900"><p>It is not as if we are overcrowded today.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.25" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D00950">Seaweed Harvesting Licences</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D01100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Coffey, to the House.  I now call Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh.  Ar aghaidh leat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#D01200"><p>Cuirim c&eacute;ad f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute;im an-s&aacute;sta gur eisean at&aacute; tagtha isteach leis an cheist seo a phl&eacute; mar tuigim gur eisean at&aacute; ag pl&eacute; l&eacute;i go d&iacute;reach.</p> <p>I am happy that the Minister of State, Deputy Coffey, is dealing with this Commencement Matter because I know this is his direct area of responsibility.  We have discussed this issue previously and it would be good to get an update on it.  The Minister of State will be aware of the background situation.  In recent years, there has been much discussion about harvesting seaweed along our coasts.  In a previous scenario, a State-owned seaweed company called Arramara Teoranta was under the auspices of &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta.  In recent months, however, that company has been sold off to a private company.  That is fine in one sense, but there are concerns within the industry over how the resource itself will be managed in future.</p> <p>About a year ago, I attended a meeting with the then Minister of State, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, on the seaweed licensing regime.  Concerns were raised and we met with departmental officials who told us that a number of outstanding licence applications were pending.  I am not sure if any of those have been granted or turned down in the meantime.  Since then, there have been quite a number of applications for licences.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2363"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2363&amp;amp;pid=TrevorOClochartaigh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I seek clarification through this mechanism on the number of applications that are with the Department.  In fairness to the officials, I know that they work very well with those making applications to make sure all of the information is available and that the t's are crossed and the i's dotted before an application is formalised and posted on the Department's website.</p><p>On the number of outstanding applications to be adjudicated on, I appreciate that the Department has a mechanism whereby a vetting committee goes through applications, following which there is a final sign-off by the Minister.  The Minister of State might be able to enlighten us on the number of applications outstanding and the timescale envisaged for the processing of applications, be it positive or negative.</p><p>There are concerns about some of the applications being submitted in that there may be blanket applications covering a broad spread of the coastline but along the west coast, in particular.  I have been a proponent from day one of the idea that the licensing regime should recognise the rights of those who have been cutting seaweed for a very long time.  I have also proposed that these seaweed cutters come together to form a co-operative or to work with a not for profit organisation in applying for licences.  I understand a number of such applications have been or are in the process of being submitted.</p><p>This is still a live issue along the west coast.  I am sure the Minister of State is very aware of it, but it appears we have not had much action on it on the part of the Department in the recent past in the issuing of licences.  I ask him to outline where we stand on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue which I know he has raised previously.  I am happy to provide clarification on some of the queries raised by him.</p> <p>My Department plays a role in regulating the harvesting of wild seaweed.  It is necessary to ensure this valuable resource is managed appropriately both to ensure it remains sustainable and that the marine environment is protected.</p> <p>There are 13 applications for licences to harvest seaweed before my Department under section 3 of the Foreshore Act 1933.  Foreshore applications, including those for seaweed harvesting, are dealt with in accordance with a scheme of prioritisation and the scale of applications varies considerably.  Even within the category of seaweed harvesting the applications are quite varied, being made by both individual and commercial harvesters.  The applications in hand range from very small scale harvesting of niche species to large-scale commercial harvesting.</p> <p>The applications are at different stages of processing.  Some were received very recently and are undergoing preliminary review, while others are at a more advanced stage.  Within this overall context, it is not possible to give an accurate indication of when determinations will be made on the outstanding applications.  However, I can assure the Senator that all applications are being progressed and will be finalised as soon as possible.</p> <p>Each application is being assessed in the context of the relevant regulatory framework, including the obligations that arise under the European Union birds and habitats legislation.  The process includes a public consultation process and any person can make his or her views known to my Department during the public consultation stage of each application.  I urge anyone with an interest to make his or her views known as part of the public consultation processes.  All applications, once deemed complete by my Department, will be available to view on the Department's website.</p> <p>I am sure the Senator will appreciate that it would not be appropriate for me to comment directly on any specific application that will ultimately come before me for determination.  My Department is examining the implications of legal advice received from the Attorney General's office on the interaction of appurtenant rights with the Foreshore Act and the European Communities (Birds and Habitats) Regulations 2011.  It is also engaging with the Property Registration Authority to establish the extent of appurtenant or folio rights to harvest seaweed that may apply.  I assure the Senator and the House that any established right in law will not be interfered with by my Department if the applications in hand are ultimately approved.</p> <p>As I have stated previously, the specific issue of licensing wild seaweed harvesting is under review in the context of the forthcoming maritime area and foreshore (amendment) Bill and the advice of the Attorney General's office.  Pending publication and enactment of the Bill, my Department will continue to process applications under the provisions of the current Foreshore Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#E00300"><p>I welcome the detail provided in the response, which is to the point.  The main aspect is that the Minister has received legal advice from the Attorney General's office on the appurtenant rights.  That was the outstanding issue being raised.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2363"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2363&amp;amp;pid=TrevorOClochartaigh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Will the Minister of State indicate the timescale for the Department taking the advice on board and coming to a position on folios and the appurtenant rights in the harvesting of seaweed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#F00200"><p>The Department will take account of any established legal right as part of the applications process.  As required, we have taken advice from the Attorney General's office.  Folios on all parcels of land within one mile of the part of the foreshore that is the subject of a licence application must be identified.  A folio must be examined to ascertain whether it contains an entry showing a right to take seaweed from that part of the foreshore.  The process is ongoing and the Department is working with the Property Registration Authority.  The process is time consuming and expected to take several months more to complete, but I assure the Senator that people's rights will not be interfered with by my Department if the applications in hand are approved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.33" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.55 p.m. and resumed at 3.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.34" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#O00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#O00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 64, motion 15, to be taken at 4.45 p.m., with the time allocated for the debate not to exceed two hours; and No. 1, statements on the spring economic statement, to be taken at 7 p.m. and to adjourn not later than 9 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#O00300"><p>I acknowledge the good debate we had yesterday evening on Seanad reform and the work done by the group headed by Dr. Maurice Manning.  I hope that some of the group's recommendations will see the light of day and that we will have an opportunity to discuss proposals in detail as they are brought forward.  I also acknowledge the Leader's efforts to facilitate debates on a variety of topics, which reflect well on the Seanad.</p> <p>Today the Cabinet discussed the issue of Irish Water and the additional powers for the collection of moneys owed to a utility company.  This takes us down a dangerous road.  It is one thing to give those powers to a State agency such as the Revenue Commissioners but it is an entirely different matter to give them to a utility company, albeit a semi-State body, which could ultimately be privatised.  This proposal undermines the role of the State and gives alarming powers to an agency that lacks democratic accountability.</p> <p>This evening's debate on the Spring Economic Statement will be useful but we need a wider debate on the issues arising.  I ask the Leader to provide an opportunity for the House to reflect on a vision for Ireland over the next ten years.  This would include where we go as a country, how we spend any money saved from the economic recovery and how we deal with public and private debt.  Households throughout the country are dealing with the alarming consequences of private debt.  Even individuals who are not in negative equity are finding it difficult to manage other types of debt.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2261"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2261&amp;amp;pid=BrianODomhnaill&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are in a country which is coming out of an austerity programme but a large proportion of the population are not sharing the fruits of economic recovery.  It is being felt here in Dublin but it not being felt across the rest of the country.  Job creation is not being appreciated or seen in many parts of our country.  Towns are on their knees and shops are continuing to close in rural areas.  We have to define a vision for Ireland and the Seanad could play a role in that.  I ask the Leader to reflect on it and perhaps over the coming weeks to have a day long debate on that particular issue.  It would be an open ended debate with each Member being given at least 20 minutes to make a contribution which the Government would find informative and which would play a part in defining the Seanad and its role.  It is a new recourse but it is one that should be used.  </p><p>I apologise for going on, but tomorrow's election in the North and in Britain is a defining election and it will have massive implications for this State.  I ask the Leader to facilitate a debate in the coming weeks on the outcome of that election, when a new Government is formed, given its implications for the European project and North-South relations.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#P00200"><p>I also commend the Leader on organising the debate last night in the House on Seanad reform.  It was an excellent debate and one in which so many people wanted to participate resulting in us having to extend the time by 15 or 20 minutes.  What came out of the debate was a desire to look into and scrutinise in more detail the legislation that Dr. Manning, Mr. Joe O'Toole, Mr. Pat Magner and their committee are preparing and which they announced yesterday they were publishing.  This is the detailed legislation to give effect to the recommendations of their working group on Seanad reform.  I would very much like to have the opportunity in early course to debate the Bill, once we have all seen a copy of it.  I am sure the Leader will facilitate that further debate.  The big concern we all had, as Senator Cummins put it so eloquently, was that we want this to be the last report on Seanad reform.  We want to see its recommendations acted upon and given effect.  I would therefore like us to have that debate in the coming weeks.</p> <p>I also welcome the debate tonight on the spring economic statement.  That sort of openended debate is important.  </p> <p>I want to ask the Leader for a debate on the report that has come out today on the projections for obesity levels in Ireland.  Quite a number of colleagues have spoken eloquently on this issue for some time now, but this report sets out starkly the projected rise in obesity levels in Ireland.  There are some very troubling figures, particularly when we compare Irish projections to the projections of other European countries.  The Netherlands is a leader in terms of reducing levels of obesity among current generations and is projected to reduce them in the future.  There are some very clear issues on which focus is required at a legislative and policy making level.  These include exercise levels, physical education for school children and teenagers, access to junk food and easy access to food with high levels of sugar, fats and salt.  We have already done good work in the Seanad, in the public consultation committee, on lifestyle factors and their effect on cancer prevention.  We should also have a debate in early course on this particular report and on what can be done to tackle obesity and, in particular, to prevent this dreadful rise that is projected to happen among our children.  </p> <p>I ask the Leader for another debate on commemorations in the coming months.  We have had some debates on this already but it would be useful to have another debate, perhaps in the early part of the autumn, as we see the Government's programme for commemorations for 2016 taking shape.  I am minded to ask for the debate in light of yesterday's moving and poignant ecumenical service in memory of the children killed during the Rising.  It seems no one is quite sure how many children were killed during the week of the Easter Rising in 1916 but, thanks to the work of Joe Duffy and others, we know that it was approximately 40 children.  These children had been largely written out of history.  No photographs remain of them.  It was moving to see the remembrance service for them yesterday, which the President and Sabina Higgins both attended.  I would like us to have a debate on commemorations which takes into account the tragedies of those who were killed, particularly the children, but also the social and economic context for the Rising as well as the military endeavours during it.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#P00300"><p>I ask for a debate on the performance and evidence given by Monsieur Trichet last week.  It was the most extraordinary performance by Tricky Dicky Trichet.  He was elevated up on a platform.The subservient minions of the banking inquiry were seated much lower.  He had no difficulty looking down his nose at them.  He was introduced in the most submissive and obsequious way as Monsieur le Pr&eacute;sident.  He was totally supercilious.  He did nothing wrong; he was not responsible for anything at all.  He was just an outside observer.  Who on earth would believe that hogwash?  Then there was a kind of laudatory editorial in <i>The Irish Times</i>.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is someone who did nothing wrong.  He just landed this country in the manure.  That is what he did and let us talk about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#Q00200"><p>Let us remember that he is a Frenchman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#Q00300"><p>The man gave advice.  Anyone giving advice with a bludgeon visible behind him and carrying a blunderbuss in the other hand, one would be inclined to take his or her advice.  He said that he said nothing about the bondholders, but he did say the world knew and every central banker knew.  Why did he keep his mouth shut?  Does anyone believe he kept his mouth shut?  I certainly do not.  The late Brian Lenihan is on record as saying that he was told by the ECB that he could not burn the bondholders.  Mr. Trichet said there was no phone call and that he does not know how he spun such a line.  I do not believe Mr. Trichet, nor do I believe a single solitary word from his mouth.  It is time we analysed what he did have to say in this country.  Basically, it appears that he changed his mind.  He told Brian Lenihan in the morning that he could burn the bondholders but by the evening he said no he could not, but that was to save the German and French banks.  Of course it was; even an idiot could see that.</p> <p>On the continuing saga of the referendum, there was more debate on it on television last night.  The "Yes" side put up a fine performance but I did not know where the "No" side were coming from because there was a lot of guff spoken about single fathers.  Apparently, there are 500,000 of them according to Mr. Waters, which sounds a bit odd but I do not know.  I am not guilty.  I am not a single father.  The participants spoke about equality and said everyone should relax because there were equality provisions in the Constitution.  Indeed, there are.  I know about them, do I not?  They were there when I sued this country on the subject of the criminalisation of homosexual behaviour between adults in private.  Those equality provisions existed but they did not prevent the High Court and the Supreme Court saying that despite these equality provisions, there was nothing whatever wrong with putting persons like myself in jail for periods ranging between ten years to life imprisonment.  How much use were the equality provisions on that occasion?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#Q00400"><p>I will follow on from what Senator Bacik said about the obesity epidemic.  I am one of the people who has bored everyone for the past four years with talk of this matter.  As the Senator said, the latest figures released by the World Health Organization show Ireland is on course to become the most obese country in Europe by 2030.  Professor Donal O'Shea, whom most people will have heard speak on this issue, has said that Ireland is in a worse health crisis than HIV-AIDS in the 1980s and cholera in the 1800s.  The new figures predict that 89% of Irish men will be overweight or obese by 2030 which puts them at the top of an overweight table of 53 countries.  In the same category, it is predicted that 85% of Irish women will be overweight or obese.  Even though it is a forecast, the figures are startling even if they are halfway correct.  As far as childhood obesity is concerned, Irish children, especially in the lower socio-economic groups, are in effect being poisoned with high fat, high salt and, above all else, high sugar content in their foods.  Legislative action must be taken as a matter of urgency to tackle this time bomb.</p> <p>When the plastic bag levy was introduced, it immediately changed consumer behaviour.  The use of plastic bags decreased by approximately 90% and well over &euro;200 million was generated.  The funding was subsequently invested in additional bottle banks and other environmentally friendly measures.  By the same token, the introduction of a health related food and drinks levy would have a positive impact on the consumption of junk food.  International surveys and research have shown this to be true.  Meanwhile, the tax would generate much needed revenue for additional medical services and therapies for patients who suffer from chronic obesity related illnesses such as diabetes.  As a State, we cannot afford such a situation to continue and I predict it will only get worse.  I would welcome, as suggested by Senator Bacik, a debate on the issue in general but in particular on policy and the need for legislative measures to be introduced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#Q00500"><p>Will the Leader of the House consider arranging a rolling debate on the proposals contained in the 2015 Seanad reform document?  The time allotted yesterday to discuss the document was limited.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->No one had any great satisfaction in having four minutes or six minutes to outline a complex Bill, the hard copy of which was circulated yesterday, which meant there was not much time to study it.  The Association of County and City Councils represents 1,000 councillors.  The councillors are the most disenfranchised group in this.  The association was established in 1947.  The rights were developed over that period and they have exercised them with great caution, as everyone elected from the panels to the House knows.  To get a vote is worth 1,000 votes in power.  I ran for the Seanad in 1992 on the administrative panel and in 1997 I ran on the industrial and commercial panel, but failed to get elected on both occasions.  I was elected to the D&aacute;il when I first ran in 1977 and was elected five times subsequently.  Comparing the D&aacute;il and Seanad, in my experience it is much more difficult to get elected to this House.</p><p>Since Senator Cummins took over as Leader of the House, he has done his utmost to expand and develop the role of the House, including innovations with the Leas-Chathaoirleach, with people making submissions and other ideas the Leader has regarding European legislation.  Those are all very positive things that can be done within this House.</p><p>With respect to the diaspora, my five siblings went abroad.  My eldest sister died, but I have another two siblings in England and two brothers in America, who vote.  My sister, brother and their families will be voting in tomorrow's general election in Britain.  That is where they pay their taxes.  Their local MP represents them, comes to their houses and canvasses them, as Deputies do here.  In all the years I have been talking to them, they never once asked to be represented here.  They are represented by us anyway.  Let us be honest about it.  Many Senators get calls, letters and other representations from abroad, and what do they do?  They act on them.</p><p>There are grounds to have a rolling debate.  As Senator Bacik said, the Bill that is to come should be debated.  I do not know who is introducing it because they have no rights themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#R00200"><p>They are just publishing it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#R00300"><p>To publish it, even.  Perhaps the Leader of the House is to publish it.  I would recommend to him that we should analyse that Bill in detail before it is published.  The most charming part of the Bill is the proposal for an ongoing committee, sitting every month, reporting to the Government in perpetuity, this great group with Dr. Maurice Manning, Mr. Joe O'Toole and others.  That is rather nice job creation for someone.  It is rather inventive, to say the least, to put that in, but that would be a matter for the Government to decide.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#R00400"><p>I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#R00500"><p>I certainly admire their dexterity and determination and their willingness to create another little State board to look at the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#R00600"><p>I again very much welcome the living city initiative.  I may have asked the Leader this already.  It might be useful in due course when we have some more information about these special regeneration areas in Dublin, Cork, Limerick, Galway, Waterford and Kilkenny and we have the maps to have a debate if Members were interested.  It is a tremendous initiative for owner-occupiers of properties originally built for use as residences prior to 1915.  Many of these are well worth preserving and enhancing and for that reason alone it is welcome.  There is also a retail-commercial element, which I would like to see spelt out more.  I note the scheme will last for five years.  I would like to see the scheme extended to many other towns and cities if possible, but those details can wait for a debate if the Leader thinks well of it and if there is enough demand for it.</p> <p>I agree somewhat with Senator Bacik in regard to the proposed Seanad ballot paper - perhaps not the ballot paper.  I was amused that we might have to download the ballot paper.  I think they could get into trouble on that one, but enough of that.  In regard to the Bill that the three wise men - it is a committee of more than the three wise men - have proposed for publication, without discussing the Bill, because I presume the Bill will need to be sponsored by the Government, I would like a discussion which might be a follow-on from yesterday, as Senator Bacik suggested, because we were curtailed somewhat on time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Coghlan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We might want to speak more on that subject.  I did not have the time to mention a few items that I wanted to include.  The former Senators' objective is worthwhile.  The report is generally good but I see two huge snags in what it proposes.  They could be spelled out further together with other snags other Members may have with a view to directing the measure if we were to have a discussion on the proposed Bill without dealing formally with it.  I recommend that to the Leader.  Also, a debate in due course in the autumn on the proposed commemorations would be worthwhile.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#S00200"><p>I remind Senators that the Leader gave a clear commitment yesterday that there will be further debate on the Seanad reform proposals.  In fairness to him, as he has made those commitments, he will honour them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#S00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh na molta&iacute; a d'fhoilsigh an tAire Oideachais agus Scileanna, an Teachta O'Sullivan, agus an tAire St&aacute;it, an Teachta Joe McHugh, inn&eacute; maidir le c&uacute;rsa&iacute; oideachais Gaeltachta.  N&iacute;l iontu ag an bpoinnte seo ach molta&iacute; ach f&aacute;ilt&iacute;m rompu.  T&aacute; na molta&iacute; at&aacute; ann dearfach agus t&eacute;ann siad cuid mhaith den bhealach i dtreo na ruda&iacute; at&aacute; ag teast&aacute;il &oacute; phobal na Gaeltachta &oacute; thaobh ch&uacute;rsa&iacute; oideachais.  T&aacute; s&eacute; t&aacute;bhachtach go mbeadh an pobal ag labhairt faoi na molta&iacute; seo ach s&iacute;lim go mbeidh s&eacute; f&iacute;or-th&aacute;bhachtach go mbeidh acmhainn&iacute; agus taca&iacute;ocht ar f&aacute;il &oacute;n Roinn nuair a bheas na molta&iacute; sin pl&eacute;ite leis an bpobal.</p> <p>I would like us to have a debate on how it would be possible to dismantle Irish Water.  We have seen the carrot and stick approach adopted by the Government to Irish Water.  The second part of the process, namely-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#S00400"><p>I would say that is mission impossible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#S00500"><p>-----the carrot of offering people a conservation grant has not worked and now the Government is using the stick and saying that if people do not play ball that it will put its hands into their pockets and take the money out of their bank accounts or social welfare payments.  What is missing in its approach is an understanding that many people do not have the means to pay this unjust charge.  That is the reality the Government does not seem to want to consider.  It is disgraceful that the Minister, Deputy Kelly, and the Government are examining the possibility of taking these costs from people through the draconian means proposed.  It would be much more suitable for us to have a debate on how to dismantle Irish Water and put in place a proper public utility that can deliver the needs of the Irish people, rather than putting in water meters at a huge expense to the public.  I note that the plan for installing them in Galway city will be rolled out during the next few weeks.  Instead of jailing people, the Government is now talking of putting its hands in the pockets of people who cannot afford to pay any more.  The reason people have not signed up to Irish Water is that they do not have faith in it, they do not have faith in the Government's Irish Water policy and, in many cases, they are unable to pay for the extra costs of water, having paid for it through other mechanisms in the taxation system.  A debate on the abolition of Irish Water would be a useful one to have in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#S00600"><p>I am not sure where to start or how to address what I am about to talk about but I will follow on from the comments of Senator Bacik said and Senator Noone on the report from the World Health Organization that came out this morning.  I was mad as hell when I read it this morning and I have listened to commentaries on the radio today about obesity levels and where they are headed in Ireland.  The report cited a likely increase from 23% to 57% in the incidence of obesity among women and a likely increase from 26% to 48% in the incidence among men.  The incidence of obesity is likely to explode in 2030 not only in Ireland but throughout Europe and rest of the world.  Senator Bacik spoke about having a debate on the issue but we do not need another bloody debate.  We have had report after report, including Healthy Ireland; Health Eating Active Living; Action for Life - Action for Everybody, Growing Up in Ireland, Senior Cycle Physical Education and Junior Cycle Physical Education and my own Points for Life initiative which I introduced in this House three and a half years ago.  Where did I get with it?  Probably nowhere, other than that I got the NTSC and the Department of Education and Skills to allow me to run a pilot programme at primary level involving four schools.  My report proved what we already know, not only for the past four years but for the past 15 years, which is how the health of this nation is going.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eamonn Coghlan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2382"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2382&amp;amp;pid=EamonnCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=06"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Department of Health is spending up to &euro;15 billion a year, but what will the figure be in 2030?  It will probably be &euro;20 billion.  We do not have a clue what we are doing to address the issue of physical activity and well-being and the obesity epidemic about which we have been told today.  According to the report, there are too many obstacles and road blocks and it is time for action, not words.  It has been proved in all reports that physical exercise reduces the level of cardiovascular disease and increases mental well-being, yet we are doing nothing to deal with the issue.  In the Healthy Ireland initiative the need for cross-departmental support is mentioned.  To be honest, that is an absolute joke.  The Sport Ireland Bill 2014 is passing through the House and perhaps will be passed tomorrow.  It is an opportunity to take some action under the umbrella of Sport Ireland.  One invests to succeed.  Sport Ireland could help us to deliver in communities, schools and voluntary clubs a really good action plan.  I receive letters and e-mails on a regular basis, including one today, from schools which are dealing with problems with gymnasiums and have halls, perhaps, 9 m by 19 m, for 600 schoolchildren.  They are on the following lines: "Eamonn, we have been applying for sports capital grants for the past 15 months or perhaps 15 years and cannot get anywhere."  We really have to take action on this issue.   The problem should be nipped in the bud in the case of children, as otherwise we are facing a lost generation.  If serious action is not taken now, we will be in serious trouble by 2030.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#T00200"><p>I seek a debate on the issue of online gambling and betting as a number of young people are in serious debt as a result of this facility being available to them.  The betting companies do not care how much money a person loses or how much debt he or she gets into.  On the other hand, if a person was to win a large amount of money online, they could shut down his or her account but do not mind bankrupting him or her.  There is no watchdog to protect people and we have no way of knowing how big the problem is.  I seek a debate on the issue in the House.  With cross-party support, perhaps we might arrive at solutions and recommendations to alleviate the pain of some of those affected by it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" speakername="James Heffernan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015050600002#T00300"><p>Following on from what Senator Eamonn Coghlan said about the level of obesity among the population, I draw the attention of the House to an incident that occurred at the weekend.  Prior to the under-21 football final between Tipperary and Tyrone the intermediate ladies football final took place between my county of Limerick and Offaly which Offaly won.  It is the treatment of the ladies involved prior to the game that I wish to highlight.  They show the same dedication in training as everybody else, yet they had to tog out at a location ten minutes away from the pitch by bus.  They were not allowed to bring their gear bags into the ground.  The half-time team talk took place in a hallway in which people were preparing food.  The ladies concerned who have given so much of their time to playing for their counties did not receive as much as the match programme, even though they were playing in an all-Ireland final.  That is not good enough at a time when we have such good female role models in sport.  Katie Taylor is an obvious one, as is Anna Geary, the captain of the Cork camogie team who has received four all-star awards and has four all-Ireland medals and who announced her retirement at the weekend.  I wish her the best of luck.  What I have mentioned does not encourage anybody to become involved in sport.</p> <p>What I really want to talk about is the march that took place at the weekend involving foreign language students in Ireland to learn English.  There are English language schools located all over the capital city to which we invite people from all over the world to come to learn English and then relate their positive experiences here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-05-06a.60" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional text to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>