<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Paul Gavan that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to make a statement on the imprisonment of Catalan political and civil society leaders.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Keith Swanick of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the allocation of hours under the HSE home support service, and the complaints procedure in place under the scheme.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Leas-Chathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Maura Hopkins of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on plans for the site of the former St. Brigid's Hospital, Ballinasloe, County Galway.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the review of the inclusion of the FreeStyle Libre in the reimbursement of medical devices under the community drug scheme.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Kevin Humphreys of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to make a statement on the purchase by Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann of additional carriages for the Intercity network.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the consultation process undertaken by his Department following applications for aquaculture licences in a special area of conservation.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on the acquisition of a new site for Gaelscoil Chionn tS&aacute;ile, Kinsale, County Cork.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Anthony Lawlor of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the funding to be allocated for the development of the endoscopic unit in Naas General Hospital, County Kildare.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the appointment of a sarcoma specialist for St. Vincent's University Hospital, Dublin.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Aidan Davitt of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on the provision of maternity leave for local authority elected members.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerald Nash of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection to make a statement on whether she plans to defer the recommended national minimum wage increase due to come into effect on 1 January 2020.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice to provide an update on the planned upgrade of Tubbercurry Garda station.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the status of the HSE and Respond group home in Carrickmacross, County Monaghan.</blockquote><p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and I have selected those raised by Senators Gavan, Swanick and Hopkins and they will be taken now.  Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in has withdrawn his matter, which I had selected for discussion.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#B00175">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#B00250">Catalan Referendum</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#B00275"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to reply to this matter.  I ask him to imagine a situation where the Leas-Chathaoirleach was arrested and put in prison for two years and was then sentenced to 11 and a half years for the crime of arranging a parliamentary debate.  This is what has happened to the speaker of the Catalan Parliament.  We all know the history of what has happened over the past couple of years and how the Catalan people voted in their millions for independence on 1 October 2017.  We were all shocked at the scenes of Spanish state police brutally destroying polling booths and hitting elderly frail people.  My party had four witnesses who saw that first hand.</p> <p>After that shocking display of state violence and repression, a number of Catalan leaders were put in pre-trial detention.  We heard on Monday how nine of them have been sentenced to between nine and 13 years in prison.  The former speaker, Ms Carme Forcadell, faces 11 and a half years in jail for allowing a debate on Catalan independence in parliament.  The former vice president, the equivalent of our T&aacute;naiste, Mr. Oriol Junqueras, faces 13 years for peacefully seeking independence for his nation.  Several ministers have been sentenced to at least nine years.  We now have a new warrant for Carles Puigdemont, who has been living in exile for the past few years, as are others who have been involved.  The Spanish state has tried to have them arrested and extradited but it keeps losing these cases because the charges they face have no basis.  They are ridiculous charges of sedition and rebellion.</p> <p>The European Union is supposed to stand for certain important values, such as democracy, freedom and human rights.  Recently, we heard the European Commission quite rightly condemned the Polish Government for interfering with its judiciary and we have heard it speak out directly against the awful migration policies of the Hungarian Government.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, there is a conspiracy of silence when it comes to what is happening in Catalonia.  No one wants to say anything.  Peaceful people have been imprisoned and sentenced to between nine and 13 years.  All they did was arrange a peaceful referendum.  The equivalent of the Leas-Chathaoirleach has been imprisoned for arranging a debate in a parliament.  This is a watershed moment for the EU.  How can it have any credibility to speak about freedom, dignity and human rights when it turns its backs on the Catalan people and this horrific repression?</p><p>The Minister of State is standing in for another Minister today, but I hope that he will agree that dialogue is the way forward.  Currently, we are consumed by Brexit and are hopeful of a good outcome.  That hope is based on dialogue.  The Spanish state has set its face against dialogue and has set itself on a course of imprisonment and repression of the Catalan people.  Where is our Government in all of this?  What message can the Minister of State give to the people of Catalonia?  What message speaking of human rights and freedom can we hear from him?  It would mean much to the Catalan people if he were to acknowledge that dialogue must be the way forward.  I hope that he will give a message that, at least here in Ireland, we remember the values of free speech and democracy and that we value the right of the Catalan people to have their say on their future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1260" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  The Government follows closely developments in Spain, which is an important EU partner and a good friend of Ireland's.  Irish people know Spain well.  After Britain, it is the country to which we travel most.  Furthermore, cities and towns across Spain are home to many Irish people and many Spaniards visit and live in Ireland.</p> <p>Upholding the rule of law in all its respects is a key underpinning of all democracies.  The question of Catalan independence remains a deeply divisive and contentious issue in Catalonia and the rest of Spain.  Yesterday, the Spanish Supreme Court announced its verdict in the cases of 12 Catalan pro-independence leaders.  We are all aware of reactions across the spectrum of opinion in Catalonia and elsewhere in Spain.  We also note the Spanish Government's statement on the matter.  We respect the separation of powers in Spain as in Ireland and it would not be appropriate for me to comment on a case ruled upon by the Spanish courts.</p> <p>More generally, the Government's position regarding Catalonia remains that the constitutional and political arrangements in Spain are matters to be determined by its own citizens through its own institutions in keeping with the rule of law.  The Government respects the constitutional and territorial unity of Spain, and just as we would expect other countries to respect our courts, we respect the decision taken by the Spanish courts.</p> <p>Our ambassador and officials based in the Irish Embassy in Madrid continue to monitor developments.  They are in constant contact with our Government and are monitoring the situation as regards demonstrations so as to provide suitable travel advice to Irish citizens.  We respect people's right to gather and express freely their opinions, but we share the calls for calm, moderation and respect for others so as to allow those who live in Catalonia and its many visitors, including from Ireland, to go about their daily lives without disruption, including being able to travel freely to and from airports and train stations or by car.  The freedom to express contesting views is essential in any democracy but differences of opinion must be contested with full respect for the law and the rights of all citizens.  This is the foundation that underpins and protects most modern democratic societies.</p> <p>The Government continues to support a resolution to the current situation that is based on democracy and the rule of law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#C00300"><p>I am disappointed with the Minister of State's response.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Democracy cannot by its nature be seditious.  The Minister of State called for calm and moderation and for respect for others.  I support that call but if we are going to respect other people then surely we need to call out that it is wrong to imprison people for arranging a debate in a Parliament or for expressing their will peacefully within the state in which they live.  If we cannot call out what is happening in Spain in terms of the open repression of the Catalan people then where are we in terms of the values we seek to preach and believe in?  I call on the Minister of State to at least acknowledge the need for dialogue to resolve this situation.  Surely he can agree with me on the need for dialogue between the Spanish state and the Catalan Parliament to resolve this situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1260" speakername="Se&aacute;n Canney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#D00200"><p>As I stated in my opening remarks, the question of Catalan independence remains a deeply divisive and contentious issue in Catalonia and in the rest of Spain.  It is through democratic processes in full respect of the law that differences of opinions must be contested.  Upholding the rule of law is the foundation that underpins and protects our democracies.  The problem presented to the Spanish Supreme Court was a legal and constitutional issue.  We should be wary of simplifying a complex issue.  As we expect other countries to respect our legal system, we respect the independence and integrity of the Spanish courts.  What happens in Catalonia matters to us here in Ireland, as evidenced from Oireachtas interest in developments there.  The Government supports all efforts aimed at facilitating reconciliation.  We remain of the view that it is for all Catalans and Spaniards to arrive at a shared view of what steps within their laws and domestic institutions best support a process of resolution of divisions.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.17" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#D00300">Home Help Service</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#D00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, to the House.  The home help scheme is under pressure.  As the Minister of State will be aware, two weeks ago the <i>Irish Independent</i>reported a harrowing story regarding a 70 year old woman who spent 105 hours on a trolley in Limerick hospital and her family's expressed fears that she would die if a fire started.  This is the direct result of a lack of investment in home help hours and step-down nursing support facilities.  The HSE figures reveal that 79 patients have been stuck in public beds for six months due to a lack of step-down facilities and home help hours; by mid-September 745 patients had not been discharged despite being medically fit, which is staggering, and that over 1,000 people were added to the home help waiting list in the last four months, with the waiting list now at 7,300.</p><p>As recently as the last two weeks, local Councillor Joe Flaherty and I met representatives of a newly-formed carers group in County Longford who passionately articulated the frustration of carers, their families and the wider community.  The system is broken and the patients and their loved ones are paying the price.  The group provided me with details of several cases where additional hours have been approved but the families have been told the additional hours cannot be commenced before Christmas owing to an embargo.  The hours have been approved but they are not being provided which, in the main, is the issue.  </p><p>There are two distinct groups of carers in crisis.  There are patients who have access to family carers and patients who do not have families to care for them.  The latter cohort is the worst affected as in many cases they receive no care.  We routinely hear, as I do in my practice, of patients left soiled or lying on a floor, perhaps unconscious or with a broken limb after a fall, until such time as a neighbour or a good samaritan calls to the House.  In regard to family carers, the real risk for them is the absence of an effective home care structure and, subsequently, family burn-out which, in turn, leads to further illness in the home and additional expense on the system rather than a saving.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Keith Swanick:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2459"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2459&amp;amp;pid=KeithSwanick&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These families are tired, frustrated, upset and disillusioned with a system that has failed them.  The most troublesome and worrying trend about which the new carers' advocacy group told me was that they had been warned not to complain or their existing hours would be cut.  It has reached the stage where many carers are afraid to speak out.  If that is true, it is a fundamental injustice and extremely worrying.  I seek clarification on the matter from the Minister of State.  </p><p>There is a clear and obvious need for an advocacy group for family carers, independent of the HSE.  It should be positioned to articulate and champion their concerns.  As I mentioned, I met the group in Longford two weeks ago.  I met a woman by the name of Majella Meade who has been battling illness since 2014.  She tried to balance her recovery with her work in caring for her patients.  However, the toll was too much and she had to give up the job she loved.  Sadly, her father passed away in May this year but not before living an additional 18 months with his family.  The priceless extra time was thanks to the care and love of his family.  The health of Majella's mother, Mary Jane Meade, deteriorated after her husband's death.  She has vascular dementia and requires full-time care and supervision in the home.  The family has a carer who calls for one hour each day, five days a week.  If Majella wants to go to the shop or see the doctor because she has her own health needs, she has to rely on a neighbour to help.  The community nurse in Longford has provided great support for the family.  </p><p>The family have been assessed and it was proposed that they receive three calls per day and two over the weekend, but that has not happened.  If it had, it would have meant a major improvement.  However, the family heard that there was an embargo on extra hours and, therefore, a delay because of budget overruns and overspending on the national children's hospital.  We need to ensure that once hours are allocated, they are honoured and that people receive the care they need.  There is a shortfall in the number of carers, but we need to ensure the qualifications of carers are up to speed.  The most important point on which I need clarification concerns families being threatened with the loss of hours if they do not put up and shut up.  If that is true, it is a disgrace.  We need clarification on that matter and perhaps an investigation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  I will respond to some of the issues raised and also follow up on them.  I share the Senator's views on the valuable work carers do in our society.  Home supports enable older people to remain in their own homes and communities, as well as facilitating timely discharge from hospital.  The Government has made investment in home support services a priority.  Progress in this area is reflected in the additional funding made available in recent years, with the budget growing from &euro;306 million in 2015 to nearly &euro;446 million in 2019.  More than 50,000 people benefit from this service at any one time.  As outlined in its national service plan for 2019, the HSE maximises the utilisation of current resources.  It prioritises those who require discharge from acute hospitals.  Significant resources and services in 2019 have been targeted to facilitate timely egress.</p> <p>In winter 2018-19 the focus was on reducing the number of delayed patient discharges through mobilising the additional resources made available and ensuring social care measures were deployed effectively to enable older people to move to a more appropriate care setting, including step-down or transitional care in their own home, with the requisite supports.  </p> <p>When talking about home support, we must also recognise the support provided for people with a disability.  That area is part of my portfolio.  The HSE is fully committed to maximising the provision of health and personal social care services for people with disabilities, including home support services, within available resources, empowering them to live independent lives.  In its national service plan for 2020 the HSE expects to deliver 3.08 million home support hours to more than 8,000 people with a disability.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is an increase of 150,000 hours on last year's target.  Therefore, it is a significant investment.  I also acknowledge that in some cases access to home support services may take longer than we would like.  However, the HSE has assured the Department that people on the waiting list are reviewed as funding becomes available to ensure individual cases continue to be dealt with on a priority basis within the available resources and as determined by the local line staff who know and understand the client's needs and undertake regular reviews of those care needs to ensure the services being provided remain appropriate.</p><p>The HSE welcomes and encourages feedback from its clients on home support delivery.  I emphasise that it is not HSE policy that a client's existing level of service be reduced on receiving a complaint.  If a client's needs change, the client or the carer can request a review by contacting the local health office.  In line with the commitments given in the programme for Government, we have made improved access to home support services a priority in budget 2020.  An additional investment of &euro;52 million is being made in 2020 which will support the provision of over 19.2 million hours of home support.  That is 1 million hours more than the 2019 target and represents a substantial increase in service provision.</p><p>While the existing home support service is delivering crucial support to many people across the country, it needs to be improved to better meet the changing needs of citizens.  The Department of Health is developing plans for a new statutory scheme and system of regulation of home support services for older people and adults with a disability.  Included in the investment is dedicated funding for the testing of the new statutory home support scheme in 2020.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#F00200"><p>I appreciate what the Minister of State said about the figure of &euro;446 million and the 50,000 people who are benefiting from it.  However, the population is getting older and people have more complex health issues that require more care.  Will the Minister of State give a commitment that vulnerable persons for whom home care is sanctioned will be allocated hours and receive them within a dedicated timeframe, be it three or six months?  Can we put something down in that regard?</p> <p>I know that it is not HSE policy to penalise carers' families when they complain, but the reality is that they are afraid to complain because they have been threatened with this.  It is not HSE policy, but it is the reality.  I implore the Minister of State to examine the matter in further detail.  I can give him more details after this debate, if he wishes.  The issue is that it is a bullying tactic being used by some who work in the HSE.  I would hate the most vulnerable persons in our society to be disenfranchised if that is the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#F00300"><p>I accept the Senator's point about carers.  Home supports enable older people and people with disabilities to live as independently as possible, as well as facilitating timely discharge from hospital.  The Government has made improved access to home support services a priority in the budget.  In 2020 an additional investment of &euro;52 million is being made which will provide over 19.2 million hours of home support.  That is a crucial investment.</p> <p>To respond on the two issues raised by the Senator, having a dedicated timeframe is a sensible proposal which I will convey to the HSE and the Department of Health.  If we are putting in &euro;52 million and providing 19.2 million hours, we must see results and a timeframe for families and carers.  That is something I will include in the follow-up on this matter.  While the home support service is delivering crucial support for many throughout the country, we accept that it has to be improved to meet the changing needs of citizens, including the complex needs mentioned by the Senator.  Because this is a debate I have in the disability sector, I like the way the Senator spoke about the two categories - family carers and those who do not have any family member at all.  I have the same problem with adults with intellectual disabilities.  I have to bring those who receive no home support to the top of the queue when it comes to fighting for funding.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While the administration of the scheme will be centralised, the delivery of services will be co-ordinated at a local level in line with the person's assessment of need.  A core component of the scheme and testing phase will be the implementation of interRAI as a standardised system tool for determining need under the new scheme.</p><p>With regard to the Senator's remarks about bullying, bullying is unacceptable in any service, whether a service for those with a disability or a service for senior citizens.  We cannot tolerate it.  When people have legitimate complaints, they have to feel free and relaxed about making such a complaint.  This is particularly true for people who are looking for services relating to care, disabilities, or senior citizens.  Those are very important things.  That is a second issue on which I will return to the HSE in order to see what is going on on the ground in some places.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.25" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#G00150">HSE Properties</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#G00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy McGrath, for coming to the Seanad on this important issue.  On Saturday last I attended the Architecture at the Edge festival.  It took place on the campus of the former St. Brigid's Hospital in Ballinasloe, County Galway.  I sincerely thank all those involved in that really fantastic event.  Professor Oonagh Walsh provided a really great insight into the history of the hospital and the hugely significant role the Connacht Asylum, or St. Brigid's Hospital, played in the development of the town and region after its opening in 1833.  At its peak, the hospital accommodated more than 2,000 patients, before the main campus eventually closed in 2013.</p> <p>That is the history part; our focus now needs to turn to the future.  Having taken the opportunity to walk around the grounds at the weekend, I was really taken aback at the rate of deterioration of the hospital buildings, particularly over recent months.  It will not take too much more vandalism before we begin to lose these buildings forever.  It is important to say that the people of Ballinasloe are very proud of the role St. Brigid's Hospital played in supporting people and in the history of their town.  The current state of the premises, however, is of major concern to the people of the area.  It is against that backdrop that we need to work on repurposing these buildings and the land in order to see St. Brigid's campus once again become a key part of the economic development of the town and wider region.  That is a really important point in terms of its history.  St. Brigid's Hospital was important to the economic development of the town and wider region.  We need to now ensure that these buildings are brought back into use so that they can contribute to the economic development of the town and wider region.  </p> <p>Our immediate priority needs to be securing the old buildings.  As I have said, with each month that passes, their conditions deteriorate.  This will ultimately lead to higher restoration costs.  In the longer term, we need to have an achievable vision for the future of the campus.  We have a very good example in the redevelopment of the Grangegorman campus, of which I am sure the Minister of State is very aware.  We need to see a similar priority given to the St. Brigid's site.  I look forward to hearing from the Minister of State in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#G00300"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this very important issue and for giving me the opportunity to outline to the House the future plans for the site of St. Brigid's Hospital, Ballinasloe.  I also thank and commend the Senator for her work on health and disability issues more generally in the Seanad over recent years.  Over recent years, the Health Service Executive, HSE, has consolidated the services on the St. Brigid's Hospital site as part of the transition to community-based mental health services in line with A Vision for Change.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A development programme has focused on vacating the main building complex and developing fit-for-purpose facilities on lands adjacent to, but separate from, the main campus.  This has resulted in a significant portion of the St. Brigid's Hospital site and lands being surplus to HSE requirements.  Oak Grove House is the last building on the campus still in service but I understand that replacement purpose-built accommodation is currently being developed.  Once this last building is vacated, the HSE intends to proceed with the disposal of parts of the St. Brigid's Hospital site and lands that are surplus to requirements.</p><p>The HSE is a prescribed stakeholder under the protocol for the intra-State transfer of State property assets and the protocol for the intra-State sharing of property assets, as advised by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  These protocols set out three options for disposal of assets: the transfer to another public body or State agency; open market sale, subject to favourable market conditions; or other uses such as community and voluntary use will be considered only if points one and two do not materialise.</p><p>Any proposals for the disposal of surplus property assets must be considered in the context of the capital funding available to the Department of Health and Government policy relating to the use and management of State property assets.  In this context, the HSE is required to obtain value for money when disposing of surplus property assets and the proceeds are reinvested in delivering much needed healthcare infrastructure.  In preparation for the disposal of the assets, in 2018 the HSE invited expressions of interest, together with business plans, from relevant State bodies, stakeholders and local authorities.  The Office of Public Works, OPW, requested an extension to the deadline in order to complete a report on the potential future use of St. Brigid's Hospital site and lands.  I understand the report has recently been completed and is currently being reviewed by the property management section of the OPW.  Pending the outcome from this process, the intention would be to develop a proposal and seek approval to proceed with the transfer or disposal of the asset, in line with State property protocols.</p><p>The use of the sales' proceeds from the disposal of St. Brigid's Hospital will be subject to sanction from the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  It would be intended that the proceeds of the sale of this property will be invested in much needed mental health and other facilities in addition to the very significant Exchequer funding required to maintain and improve health infrastructure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#H00100"><p>I have a number of questions arising from the Minister of State's response.  We are aware there is a shift in providing community mental health services.  Similar to the issue raised in the previous Commencement matter there are challenges with the staffing of these community mental health services.  I ask that the Minister of State would note this, especially in the context of the Roscommon-Galway services.</p><p>Is there a timeframe with regard to Oak Grove House being the last building on the campus, and which is still in service?  Replacement accommodation is being developed and perhaps the Minister of State will indicate the timing for that.  The Minister of State said the report is currently being reviewed by the OPW.  Do we have a timeframe for that report and will its content be made public?</p><p>These buildings are very important for what could be an economic regeneration of Ballinasloe and the wider region.  Ballinasloe is very well located.  It is near to two motorways.  It has access to Dublin and to Shannon Airport.  It has rail links and high-speed broadband.  Surely, the State should be trying to bring those buildings back into a place where they can support the economic development of the region.  I ask the Minister of State to raise it at Cabinet level that this is an important priority for our region.  It is important the Minister of State does whatever he can to emphasise this with the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe.  We need those buildings to be repurposed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maura Hopkins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2478"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2478&amp;amp;pid=MauraHopkins&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We also need to ensure they remain within State ownership to allow for the economic regeneration of the town.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#J00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  The HSE has made a significant investment in community-based mental health services in the Ballinasloe area to facilitate the reconfiguration of services away from the acute setting of St. Brigid's Hospital, in line with A Vision for Change.  This has resulted in a significant portion of the site and lands being surplus to the requirements of the HSE.  Pending the outcome of engagements with the OPW on the potential future use of the site and lands, the intention is to proceed with the transfer or disposal of the asset in line with State property protocols.</p> <p>I take the Senator's point on the shift and the challenges with staff.  These are important issues.  I do not have the details on the timeframes but I will follow up with her.  She has raised important issues, particularly that of Oak Grove.  We need to see where we are going with that.  I need to get more clarification on that from the Department and the HSE.  Government policy, as set out in A Vision for Change, is that the proceeds from the sale of the older mental health assets, such as St. Brigid's Hospital, will be reinvested in new developments in the area of mental health.  That is important.  I understand the new replacement accommodation is being developed for the mental healthcare services previously provided on the St. Brigid's Hospital campus.</p> <p>Another important point the Senator raised, which has to be taken into consideration, is economic regeneration, particularly in the Ballinasloe area, and the repurposing of buildings.  These issues will be taken into consideration as well and we have to ensure this happens.  These developments are in line with the best international practice for the reorientation of assets from a hospital-based focus to the modern structures and facilities required for enhanced community-based service provision.  I will raise the issues the Senator mentioned about the site and the plans and timeframes for same with the Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Moran, the Minister for Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe, and officials from the OPW and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.32" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.12 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.33" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, the Wildlife (Amendment) Bill 2016 - Report Stage (resumed) and Final Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to adjourn at 6.45 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#N00300"><p>I welcome Senator Mark Daly.  He has the floor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#N00400"><p>It is always great to get a warm welcome from a fellow Kerry man.  I thank the Leader for outlining the Order of Business today.</p> <p>At present, it is all things Brexit and Brexit-related.  I know the Government has made strong representations to the British Government on the court case yesterday.  The matter has been raised many times in this House by Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile, among others.  I refer to the entitlement in the Good Friday Agreement of every citizen on this island to identify as British or Irish, or both, as a person so chooses.  The verdict in yesterday's court case stated that one would automatically be a British citizen in Northern Ireland, whether one chose it or not.  That is not within the spirit and certainly not within the letter of the Good Friday Agreement.  The situation must be rectified.  Otherwise, those in Northern Ireland who would classify themselves as being Irish must go through a legal process to say that they are not, in fact, British.  When one puts it in the context of Brexit, it outlines the need for clarity to be brought to the issue because identity has been highlighted as one of the key concerns on both sides when it comes to the future of this island and a united Ireland, as Senator Norris and others have pointed out.  We must respect identity and make sure people are protected.  The court case and this ruling are of concern to everybody on this island and must be challenged.</p> <p>Brexit is ever with us.  We have had numerous debates on it.  In the past 15 minutes, the chief negotiator of the EU, Michel Barnier, has pointed out that the British proposals to leave the EU are simply not good enough.  He said they are not there yet.  He makes a good point when he says it is high time to turn good intentions into legal text.  He points out that it must be done by this evening in order to be ready for it to be ratified at the meetings of the Heads of State and of Government on Thursday and Friday.  There is also next week and there is also an opportunity for the UK to seek an extension, despite its domestic issues, in order for this to be done correctly, because when the UK leaves, it will do so permanently.  Moreover, it must also leave in a way that makes sure that the peace on this island is sustained and maintained.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As pointed out by the Chief Constable of the PSNI and others, we know that in the event of a return to a hard border, there will be a return to violence of this island.  The only issue will be its scale.  I hope we all agree that this is not something we wish to return to.</p><p>I welcome to the Visitors Gallery my niece, Cliona Daly, and her friend, Freddy, who are here on work experience.  They have been working very hard all week and will continue to do so, as will we.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#O00200"><p>We will keep them busy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#O00300"><p>We will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#O00400"><p>Sweatshop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#O00500"><p>Will the Leader clarify that, on the Wildlife (Amendment) Bill 2016, we will be taking Report Stage, resumed, and Final Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#O00600"><p>Report Stage, resumed, and Final Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#O00700"><p>I thank the Leader.</p> <p>The next speaker is Senator Gavan.  There is nobody here from the Independent benches.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#O00800"><p>It is not like them, to be fair.  I got a distress call this afternoon from University Hospital Limerick.  The Leader will know this is not the first time I have brought up the issue of the hospital.  There were 80 people on trolleys there this morning.  A month ago, the head of nursing declared to staff that having trolleys in corridors was a red-line issue for her, yet this morning she was forced to instruct the location of three trolleys on every corridor of the hospital.  Worse than that, the patient dispatch unit also has trolleys in its corridor.  My colleague, Ger Kennedy, from SIPTU, who asked to be quoted so people would understand the gravity of the situation, described University Hospital Limerick as akin to Beirut.  We have spoken about this on so many occasions.  Staff morale is at an all-time low.  This is really saying something.  God knows, the staff have had a hard time in the hospital in recent years.</p> <p>There is genuine despair over the lack of Government action and over the Government acting at times as a roadblock to progress.  I will give a specific example.  It was put to me this morning on the train as I came here.  There are a number of new nursing graduates, including seven midwife graduates.  There is a serious shortage of midwives across the country, particularly in University Maternity Hospital Limerick, yet the seven midwives are unemployed because the maternity hospital in Limerick does not have permission to hire them.  The Minister likes to play with terms.  He says there is no moratorium.  One can call it a pause or moratorium, or whatever one likes, but the fact of the matter is that our hospitals are in crisis and University Hospital Limerick is in no position to hire.  That decision rests with one person alone, the Minister for Health, the same Minister for Health who slipped in for one morning and slipped out again without telling anyone in advance what was happening.</p> <p>I see colleagues from the mid-west present.  To be fair to them, they have also highlighted the crisis in University Hospital Limerick.  I am acting not on a party-political basis but on the basis that we have had enough.  In Limerick, Clare and across the mid-west, we have had enough of our hospitals failing our people, of people dying in corridors and of the crisis getting ever worse.  Let us not forget it is only 14 October.  Limerick holds the record of 82 people on trolleys.  What will the record be in another month, December or January?  Is it any wonder that the Government is seeking a quick election?  It knows it will only get worse.  It is time for action.  How long will it take?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#O00900"><p>I am sorry I was not in my seat when my turn arrived.</p><p>I welcome two young men from Cork, namely, Ben Quigley and Adam Hallissey, both of whom are authors with <i>progressivebrief.com</i>.  They are both students from Cork.  The blog <i>progressivebrief.com</i>contains political commentary.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is wonderful to see people from university here.  My colleague, Senator Buttimer, will agree with me that is good to see young people in college engaged in political comment and I welcome them.</p><p>I also want to welcome my fellow county people from the Presentation Convent, Tuam, County Galway, as it is always good to see a Galway representation here.  The ladies are welcome today and I hope they enjoy Leinster House.</p><p>As for Brexit and the current position, I again compliment the Government on the way it has behaved itself right through the Brexit negotiations to this point in time, where the last thing we need are leaks.  Thankfully, nobody on this side of the country is providing these.  As we draw closer, there is a possibility that some of our brothers and sisters on the unionist side may feel that they are being hard done by.  I am unsure what way things will work out but listening and watching Sky News this morning, there is a possibility that there will have to be a change to the position that gave the unionists the level of comfort they think they currently have.  We must be extremely careful because there are young men and women in Northern Ireland who may not take that too well.  For that reason in particular, I compliment the Government in being extremely sensitive.  It is a very dangerous time in our history.  I ask that we maintain the level of secrecy, if one wishes to call it that, as we lead up to the final days of whatever will emerge.  I hope, as I know everybody in this House does, that we will finish up with a deal that will satisfy all sides.  There can be no winners here.  It has to be an agreed solution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P00200"><p>I refer to the invasion of Syria by Turkish troops at the direction of Mr. Erdogan.   This is clearly the responsibility of Mr. Trump, whose withdrawal of American troops gave the green light to invade.   It is a piece of massive hypocrisy that he then announced what he has called the worst sanctions ever seen against members of the Turkish Government and regime.  This measure was not Trump's but was because of pressure from Congress and from people within his own Republican Party, who have at last woken up to the type of clown that they have leading them.  The Kurds are the most badly treated national minority-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P00400"><p>-----that I can think of.  They have been spread between different countries that have refused to give them human or civil rights.  They are not allowed, in many places, to speak their own language.  The people who will be taken over by this move will also not be speaking Kurdish but will be taught in Arabic.  We in Ireland ought to understand the meaning of the deprivation of language.  They are a wonderful people.  The women, children and other civilians, however, are being mowed down and bombed into filth by the Turkish army assault.  It is tragic that in all of this mess, the one person to come out with an advantage is Mr. Putin, who is another stinker.  We have handed Mr. Putin a triumph on a plate, which is a pity.  I ask the Leader to arrange that a strong protest be made by this House and Government to the Turkish ambassador to let him know our views.  It is not much but it is something we can do to show solidarity with the unfortunate Kurdish people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P00500"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P00700"><p>I thank the Senator, despite his use of a word I did not think was parliamentary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P00800"><p>What word was that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P00900"><p>We will leave it alone now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P01000"><p>Was it "stinker"?  The word "stinker" is very parliamentary.  There are plenty of stinkers around.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P01100"><p>I call the Senator to order, please, and call Senator Conway to speak now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P01200"><p>I share Senator Norris's outrage and sentiments, which will be shared by most decent people.  President Donald J. Trump has an awful lot to answer for-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P01300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#P01400"><p>-----in what he has done.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->His actions are appalling.  Last week was positive with regard to Brexit.  I wish all the parties well and I hope that there is no leaking.  The last thing we need is a leak from any quarter.  Hopefully common sense will prevail in the United Kingdom and among the DUP, to make people realise that they have many responsibilities.</p><p>I share Senator Gavan's concern about Limerick hospital.  We have raised it many times here.  I would not question the Minister's motivation in going to visit the hospital.  He was called on by people across the floor in both Houses to make an unannounced visit and he did that in good faith.  He did not tell anybody he was going because that would defeat the purpose.  A modular unit is being built as we speak.  The money has been provided.  There were no roadblocks in providing the money for the modular unit.  Within five weeks of it being requested by the Mid West hospital group, the money was sanctioned.  That will be a 60-bed unit.  It will not solve the problems.  I call for the 93-bed additional unit that has been committed to in the Project Ireland 2040 capital plan to be fast-tracked.  That would certainly alleviate the pressures in the hospital in Limerick.  We need to be mindful of the people who are on trolleys.  It is not acceptable.  I have great sympathy for them and for the staff who are working in those dreadful conditions.  All that we can do is call on management to escalate its discharge policy.  The slowness in discharging patients from the hospital into step-down facilities is a problem that needs to be dealt with.  The Government can only do so much.  I believe that the management in University Limerick hospital group needs to improve the flow of early and fast discharges, otherwise we will see a repeat of the current situation.  I accept that it is only part of the problem and that capacity is another significant part.  A solution to that capacity problem is on the way, which I consider a partial solution.  The ultimate solution is a 60-bed modular unit coupled with the 93-bed unit that is committed to under the capital investment programme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q00200"><p>I would like to talk about An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Following pressure from Fianna F&aacute;il, there is increased funding of &euro;81 million for Garda numbers in budget 2020, which will deliver up to 700 new Garda recruits.  However, I need clarity about something that the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, announced earlier this year, namely, that 800 recruits would join the ranks at the Garda Training College in Templemore this year.  However, the budget states that up to 700 are being recruited.  The newspapers are calling it a U-turn and another broken promise, caught up in a web of spin and empty announcements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q00300"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q00400"><p>I want clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q00500"><p>Sorry, Senator.  I have to take a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q00600"><p>On a point of order, it is 700 garda&iacute; and the rest are civilian staff.  If the Senator read the report-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q00700"><p>That is not a point of order.  I must ask Senator Conway to resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q00800"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q00900"><p>If the Senator read the budget in detail, she would know it, bearing in mind that she and her party closed Templemore-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01000"><p>Senator Conway is out of order.  That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01100"><p>The Minister, Deputy Flanagan-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01200"><p>Does Senator Murnane O'Connor want me to keep going?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01300"><p>Is it not amazing how Fianna F&aacute;il closed Templemore?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.73" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01500"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il closed the college for five years.  Not one garda was recruited for five years.  Fianna F&aacute;il closed Templemore.  It was a disgrace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01600"><p>I ask for one Senator to speak at a time.  Senator Lawlor will get his turn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01700"><p>Senator Murnane O'Connor should get her facts right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01800"><p>Will Senators behave please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q01900"><p>The newspapers are calling this a U-turn and broken promise-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q02000"><p>That will not get the Senator elected in Carlow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q02100"><p>-----along with spin and empty announcements.  I am giving the facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q02200"><p>The fact is that Fianna F&aacute;il closed Templemore.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q02300"><p>Will Senator Murnane O'Connor address her remarks through the Chair please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Q02400"><p>Did the Senator not sort this out before the budget with Deputy Michael McGrath and her Fianna F&aacute;il colleagues?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00100"><p>There will be garda&iacute; going to Carlow because we reopened Templemore.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00200"><p>I have risen here-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00300"><p>Senator Lawlor is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00400"><p>-----to speak about the lack of resources for our garda&iacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00500"><p>They do not like the facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00600"><p>That does not matter.  The Senators will get their turn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00700"><p>The figure of 15,000 by 2021 was a key demand of Fianna F&aacute;il, in a confidence and supply agreement with Fine Gael, which has not been easy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00800"><p>Who closed Templemore?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R00900"><p>Is that speech is from the third floor?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01000"><p>Please, Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01100"><p>A boost in numbers would mean a better system.  There are people the length and breadth of rural Ireland living in fear because there are not enough garda&iacute; visible in our towns and villages.  They want more garda&iacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01200"><p>Who wrote the script?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01300"><p>Every week, I receive complaints about Garda vetting and how people must be vetted for each sports club, educational facility or youth organisation.  In one case, a man was vetted 18 times across various sports clubs.  He was waiting weeks for authorisation to volunteer for a small club which needed his services because there was too much paperwork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01400"><p>Is the Senator against vetting?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01500"><p>There should be one vetting per person which would carry through.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01600"><p>For how long?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01700"><p>There should be only one vetting for every activity, a kind of behaviour card, which would feature the Garda's vetting information.  Shockingly, people are slipping through with devastating consequences.  It simply not working.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01800"><p>Does the Senator want more vetting now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R01900"><p>We cannot keep asking for more and more from our police force when we are not giving it the resources.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.103" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R02100"><p>The Senator is in injury time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R02200"><p>The Minister was in the House last week and I spoke to him about resources.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.106" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R02400"><p>The Minister agreed with me about resources.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R02500"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R02600"><p>That was well read.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R02700"><p>We need more resources for our garda&iacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R02800"><p>I thank the Senator.  She should resume her seat.  She has made her point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R02900"><p>I also wish to note-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.113" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R03100"><p>The Senator has gone over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R03200"><p>This is an amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.116" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R03400"><p>Order.  We will hear the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R03500"><p>Senators are being very unfair here.  I am only speaking the truth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R03600"><p>Will the Senator move the amendment please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R03700"><p>I want to move an amendment to the Order of Business that No.12 be taken before No.1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R03800"><p>I thank the Senator and call Senator Marshall.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R03900"><p>What is No. 12?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R04000"><p>I will check that for the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R04100"><p>Order.  Senator Marshall to speak without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#R04200"><p>On a more sombre note, 28 years ago, veteran journalist, David McKittrick, BBC journalists, Chris Thornton and Seamus Kelters, political commentator, Brian Feeney, and later David McVea, sat down to write a book.  The book would record the stories of every man, woman and child killed during the Troubles, a book that would stand in isolation as the only record of the fate of every one of the 3,700 lives destroyed by the Troubles, including Members of this House and victims of the Dublin and Monaghan bombings.  It took an arduous and painstaking eight years to complete the task and in 1999 they duly published their work, <i>Lost Lives</i>, as a testament to remember those individuals, every man, woman, child and baby, lest they were forgotten.</p><p>The impact this book had was monumental.  It included revelations to many families regarding the loss of a loved one, details and circumstances that many had never been aware of.  The book has been read and referenced by academics and students, it has been shared and studied in churches and chapels, with many readers moved to tears by the sheer scale and loss of human life and families destroyed by the horrors of conflict.</p><p>However, that is not why I speak today.  Last night I attended the Queens Film Theatre in Belfast to watch &quot;Lost Lives&quot;, the film, 20 years on from the book.  A film best described as &quot;a requiem for those killed in the Troubles&quot;.  The film is the work of Belfast directors, Dermot Lavery and Michael Hewitt of DoubleBand Films.  For 90 minutes, it weaves together an intricate tapestry of archive footage, music and powerful visual imagery to a backdrop of bombs, gunfire, devastation and destruction.</p><p>Probably most strikingly and hauntingly, the voices behind the narrative are not the victims but rather a who's who of Irish acting talent.  Apparently none needed to be asked twice to participate.  All were willing participants, no doubt seeing the value of this work.  They make up a list comprising household names such as Liam Neeson, Kenneth Branagh, Adrian Dunbar, Bronagh Gallagher, Stephen Rea, James Nesbitt, Brendan Gleeson, Roma Downey, Susan Lynch, Martin McCann, Ian McElhinney, Michael Smiley, Bronagh Waugh and Br&iacute;d Brennan, all lending their voices to the stories of the lost lives, accompanied by a very moving, emotive score performed by the Ulster Orchestra.</p><p>What it demonstrates is the futility of conflict; the hurt, the pain, the loss and suffering of conflict.  It is a recognition and a stark reminder that there are no winners, only losers.  No one escapes the horror, no one has a monopoly on pain and no one should ever forget because its by remembering the hell that we all have a responsibility to ensure this never happens again.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ian Marshall:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2486"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2486&amp;amp;pid=IanMarshall&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Probably the most the most moving moment was at the end credits when every Troubles death is listed year by year on screen, name after name, line after line, concluding with the single name in 2019, of Lyra McKee, murdered by dissident republicans earlier this year.  The list is a truly horrifying demonstration of the monumental loss of life.  As the credits finished and the lights went up, last night was the first time in my life that I left a cinema when absolutely no one spoke.  Not a word was being uttered, highlighting the power of this film, and the painful emotions and memories it evoked.  It reminded me of a funeral cortege or that silence associated with the respect and reverence of remembrance. </p><p>This film is a very important piece of work.  It premiered at the London Film Festival last week and at Queen's Film Theatre, Belfast from Friday, 10 October.  It is planned that "Lost Lives" will be screened by the BBC later this year.  I urge that this film should be seen across the Twenty-six Counties and not just the Six Counties.  Someone needs to make sure people can see it.  It should be screened in order that we all reflect, and that we all dispel any notion that this was a proud or glorious moment in our history on the island of Ireland because it certainly was not.</p><p>The pain and hurt etched on the faces and families destroyed by grief and suffering in this film should serve as a reminder that we never glorify this or go back to these horrors.  Everybody on the island needs to view this piece of genius.  Everybody needs to ensure these horrors never happen again.  I urge the Leader and this House to use their influence to ensure everyone has the opportunity to see this work and to understand that we never veer into idle chat about identity, culture and nationality in Northern Ireland or the Republic of Ireland without understanding the hell and hurt so many have suffered.  All need to see this work, because we all have a responsibility to never repeat the past especially in these turbulent political times.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#S00200"><p>The report in today's newspaper about University Hospital Limerick makes very stark reading.  I have had contact from people who were there as patients in the past 24 hours and from staff.  Eighty people are on trolleys and it reached a national all-time high of 82 in the past month.  It is frightening to think that we are not into the winter months and yet 80 people are on trolleys.</p> <p>A person with a family member who is very seriously ill contacted my office.  While I appreciate the patient had to be moved to another hospital because of the nature of their illness, the centre of excellence for the person's illness is actually in University Hospital Limerick.  While I know it was for the person's safety, it is not acceptable that they were moved.</p> <p>The injury units in Nenagh and Ennis are open from 8 a.m. to 8 p.m. and the unit in St. John's is open from 8 a.m. until 6 p.m.  However, we need to look at making better use of the other complementary hospitals to University Hospital Limerick because every day, the numbers are increasing.  It is quite serious at this stage and is at breaking point.</p> <p>I asked the Minister to visit the hospital unannounced because I always felt when his visits were announced in the past, certain things were hidden.  I understand from speaking to him that he discovered things that might not have come to light, had he announced he was going.  There needs to be a plan.  The matter was raised at the recent Oireachtas Joint Committee on Health.  I understand the extra scanner is under way.  It might be a portable one, but anything that will ease the plight of the staff and really ill patients is welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#S00300"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business to take No. 13, the Industrial Relations (Joint Labour Committees) Bill 2019, before No. 1.</p> <p>I wish to reflect on the points so articulately and eloquently put by Senator Marshall.  We should never forget what the conflict inflicted on far too many people on this island, on our neighbouring island and elsewhere.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I absolutely agree that "Lost Lives" should be essential viewing for all citizens of this state, the United Kingdom and elsewhere.  We must always remember the horror inflicted on our people in those dark days from the late 1960s through to the Good Friday Agreement, not forgetting the tragic loss of Lyra McKee who was murdered this year.  Peace is fragile.  We must remember that one of the central tenets of the Good Friday Agreement and one of the things that will make sure we will never return to those dark days is recognising the right of all individuals to their identity as British, Irish or both.  As a consequence of a judgment by the British Home Office yesterday, the right of Emma DeSouza to be Irish and have her Irish identity recognised by the British state was not upheld.  This afternoon the Taoiseach recognised her as an Irish citizen and somebody who has, as a matter of fact, an Irish passport.  He has said the issue will be raised again by the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Coveney, in meetings with the British authorities and Ministers this week.  With respect, tea and sympathy are not what is required.  We need strong action by the British Government to make sure that, as co-guarantor of the Good Friday Agreement, the right of citizens in the North to identify as Irish will be protected, as is the right to be considered British, and that they will have the full protection of the law in that respect.</p><p>I agree with the statement made by my colleague Senator Norris on the behaviour of the Turkish regime towards the Kurdish population in northern Syria.  It is absolutely outrageous and unacceptable.  The Kurdish people are among the most tormented of races on the planet and this has been the case since time immemorial.  The actions of Turkey must be condemned by the House.  I know many Turkish people living in Ireland who are good friends of mine, who do not accept what is happening and who find themselves at odds with the decision made by the Erdoan Government to engage in these horrific and reprehensible acts which do not reflect the wishes of the Turkish people I know who want to live in peace and respect the rights of the Kurdish people.  We know that this genie was allowed to emerge from the bottle by the actions of the US President, Donald Trump.  It is entirely unacceptable.  I support the proposal of my colleague Senator Norris that we protest to the Turkish ambassador about the behaviour of the Turkish regime in what is happening in northern Syria.  It is absolutely unacceptable and should be deplored by everybody in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#T00200"><p>I second Senator Nash's amendment to the Order of Business.</p> <p>This morning I attended a presentation made by Senator Freeman in the AV room on the Children's Digital Protection Bill which we discussed last year and has reached Committee Stage.  Its purpose is to safeguard children exposed to legal but harmful and age inappropriate web content and place responsibility on the hosts for the distribution of the information and making it available to children.  People can go on the dark web to get step-by-step instructions every day for 50 days on how to self-harm.  At the end of the 50 days they will be told how to complete suicide.  This is affecting young children aged ten years and younger.  We are still in mental health and well-being week.  These online forums are seen as normal.  It is seen as normal behaviour to be promoted, but it is so damaging.  Some sadistic individuals are capturing young children and, after 50 days of induction, asking them to complete suicide.  I would certainly not allow a child to enter a room alone with one person not knowing what the conversation was going to be about.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This particular conversation is frightening.  There are also special forums on how to be the best anorexic in the world.  It is a normalisation of dysfunction.  The forums' effect on our children's health and well-being is renowned.  At 1 p.m. tomorrow, the community groups Hug and Mental Health Warriors will gather outside the gates of Leinster House to protest for more fit-for-purpose services for our children and for us as legislators to protect our children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#U00200"><p>I concur with Senator Marshall on that most wonderful book, <i>Lost Lives: The stories of the men, women and children who died as a result of the Northern Ireland Troubles</i>.  It is the best historical journalism that this country has ever seen.  It shows that there are human stories behind the statistics.  It is a book of remembrance and one that I have taken out of the Oireachtas Library many times.  Seemingly, buying the book would cost between &euro;200 and &euro;400.  However, I would tell students, public servants, politicians or anyone else to take out the book.  If we do not remember our past, we will be doomed to fail in future.  I am delighted to see that it will now be shown on screen.  It is horrific and harrowing.  We sometimes forget that there were 3,700 or so deaths.</p><p>On the issue of events preceding matters, partition was conceived in this country on this day 100 years ago.  It was the first meeting of the committee that effectively recommended two parliaments, North and South, on the island of Ireland and a council of Ireland.  We are in a state of historical analysis.  The UK Government has been told to submit by midnight proposals to replace the backstop or else the deal will be off.  I was delighted by what happened with Prime Minister Johnson and the Taoiseach last week, as the situation is moving in the right direction.  It is a pathway that could allow the UK to leave the EU without crashing out.  What we have always said is that we must avoid a hard border and protect our place in the Single Market.  Most importantly, the Good Friday Agreement can never be touched or threatened.  I hope that, in the coming days, we will devise a proposal and work together so that, whatever happens with Brexit, the agreement will work again.</p><p>Brexit has damaged relations on the island of Ireland and between Ireland and the EU and the UK.  As politicians, we must work twice as hard to try to repair that damage.  There were never going to be winners out of Brexit, but we must ensure that, whatever happens, there is a deal with which everyone is satisfied.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#U00300"><p>I second Senator Murnane O'Connor's proposed amendment.  I agree with the sentiments she expressed regarding Garda resources.  I attended a meeting of the Monaghan joint policing committee last weekend at which the chief superintendent outlined his concerns about the lack of resources with which he had to work.  I believe he stated that, by the end of the year, he would be down to eight patrol cars to cover his division.  He outlined that he had a serious problem and stated that, when he picked up the phone to look for help, he was told that there was no money.</p><p>I wish to raise two issues relating to the farming community.  Today is the final date for the spreading of slurry.  The deadline needs to be extended to accommodate those farmers who are trying to put slurry on their lands.  There has been an exceptional period of heavy rain, so much so that lands across the country are impassable to machinery.  In some cases, it is not even possible to have livestock out on lands.  I understand that many farmers throughout the country have been forced to house cattle because of the ground conditions.  The farming community needs the deadline to be extended.  I have written to the Minister expressing that sentiment and I hope that the Leader will use his good offices to implore the Minister to extend the deadline.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The other issue relates to the beef exceptional aid measure, BEAM, which is the &euro;100 million fund introduced by Government to compensate hard hit suckler farmers in regard to beef prices.  I was disappointed but not surprised to learn that only half the suckler farmers in the country have applied for this scheme.  This illustrates that the scheme is not working and is not attractive to farmers in the first instance.  The problem, in part, is that one of the criteria pertaining to this scheme is that farmers must commit to a reduction in their stocking numbers by a minimum of 5% for the following year.  The lack of uptake in the scheme highlights that there is a problem with it.  Again, I implore the Leader to use his good offices to bring back to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Creed, the message that suckler farmers are hard pressed with beef prices and ground conditions and they need a break.  The Minister needs to review this scheme with a view to making it attractive for farmers to apply for the funding which they so badly need.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#V00200"><p>I thank the 12 Senators who contributed to the Order of Business.  The issues of Brexit and the DeSouza case were raised by Senators Daly, Craughwell, Conway, Nash and Feighan.  All of us in this House stand united in the twin declaration of the need to ensure there is no return to a hard border on our island and to protect our place in the Single Market.  Rather than add to the rhetoric, as parliamentarians it is best that we allow the negotiations to continue such that a deal and a solution can be found in the interests of all of us on this shared island.  </p> <p>The Taoiseach referenced the DeSouza case and he said that he will raise the matter with Prime Minister Johnson again next week.  It is an important case.  In my opinion, it goes against the spirit of the Good Friday Agreement and it gives further hostage to different sides to argue particular points.  The important point is that British citizenship laws are, as the Taoiseach said, out of step with the spirit of the Good Friday Agreement.  In keeping with the comments of many Members here, as co-guarantors of the Good Friday Agreement, there is a responsibility on both sides to honour and uphold it.  The Taoiseach and the T&aacute;naiste, as part of their engagements, will make that position clear.  To make a distinction between national identity and citizenship is an incorrect reading of the Good Friday Agreement.</p> <p>In regard to Brexit, the comments today by Mr. Barnier are worth noting.  The Taoiseach and the T&aacute;naiste have and will continue to negotiate in food faith.  As stated this morning by the T&aacute;naiste, this is not a time for pessimism or optimism, but rather a time for all of us to hold firm in the national interest.  </p> <p>Senators Gavan, Conway and Byrne raised the vexing issue of trolley numbers in University Hospital Limerick.  All Members have raised this matter repeatedly in the House.  As Senator Gavan knows the Government is committed under the capital plan to the 60-bed modular unit.  We all understand that one person on a trolley is one too many.  There is a need for management and the HSE to come together to put in place a real plan that will eliminate the use of trolleys.  Equally, there is a role for the Irish Nurses and Midwives Organisation, INMO, and SIPTU in regard to the operation of emergency departments and trolley counts, including what counts and does not count.  As a Member of the Oireachtas and a citizen of this country it is my view that one person on a trolley is one person too many.  However, I have not heard Senator Gavan offer a solution, other than-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#V00300"><p>Hire staff.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#V00400"><p>-----the hiring of staff.  The Government is committed in the capital plan.  Senator Gavan is party to the regime that proposes to spend its way out of everything.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That does not often work. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W00200"><p>We will spend more getting them back in four years' time from London.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W00300"><p>That poses the question as to how we view our health system.  That is especially the case, give the highest ever expenditure announced in the budget last week.  There is also the question as to why the accident and emergency department is our first port of call.  Where is our primary care system?  Why is that not functioning to the level and capacity needed to have people perceive it to be the first point of contact?  Why is that the emergency department?  We will have that debate with the Minister in due course.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell welcomed two people from Cork and I join with him in that.  Senators Norris and Nash raised the issue of Syria.  It is a source of distress and concern and we all join in the condemnation of what is happening there.  The vacuum being created by the policy of the American Administration is being filled by Russia and Assad.  It is unacceptable.  The geopolitical landscape has changed in the space of a week because of the policy of the American Administration.  It is extraordinary that President Trump's own party, the Republican Party, is fundamentally disagreeing with him on this matter.  It is not good.  As Senators Nash and Norris stated, we all protest and condemn the actions occurring in Syria.  In a serious of interviews in the last few days, the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Coveney, made the Government's position very clear.  I would be happy, however, to have a debate on this matter in due course, with the Minister in attendance.</p> <p>Senators Murnane O'Connor and Gallagher raised the issue of Garda numbers.  While I do not wish to engage in political crossfire with the Senators opposite me, they have a very short memory.  It was their party, when it was in power, that closed Templemore Garda College, reduced Garda numbers, failed to fill vacancies, put a moratorium in place on recruitment, hiring and promotion and cut the pay and conditions of members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  That is their legacy.  Under this Government, new members of the Garda have been recruited, the budget for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has increased by &euro;190 million to include funding for 700 new garda&iacute; and additional staff.  Moreover, civilianisation of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na has taken place, meaning that more garda&iacute; are out in the community.  Senator Gallagher may shake his head with disbelief but I will bring him to Cork to meet the garda&iacute; who are now in community policing.  Members of the Garda are moving out of stations to be replaced with civilians.  Just last month, Commissioner Harris-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W00400"><p>How do they get around, having moved out?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W00500"><p>By bus.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W00600"><p>There must be a good bus service down there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W00700"><p>A good bus service is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W00800"><p>I will explain.  It is very simple-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W00900"><p>We are not going to have a renewed debate on this matter.  I call the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W01000"><p>Senator Buttimer was obviously in the fiction section of the library again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W01100"><p>The fiction section of the library is the one that we see the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.149" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W01300"><p>The Leader to respond without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W01400"><p>It is a bit like the "Buy and Sell"-style magazine that Fianna F&aacute;il produce.  Here is our budget-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W01500"><p>The Leader cannot promise something and then not deliver on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W01600"><p>-----but how are we going to pay for this?  I remind Members opposite, many of whom were public representatives from 2007 to 2010, what happened then.  I will leave things at that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.154" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W01800"><p>On a point of information-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W01900"><p>On a point of information-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02000"><p>What we need-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02100"><p>I will hear the point of information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02200"><p>There are no points of information in reply to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.160" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02400"><p>On a point of order, the Leader reminds me of the man in the race-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02500"><p>Is this a genuine point of order?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02600"><p>It is very much so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02700"><p>Of course it is not genuine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02800"><p>It is very genuine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W02900"><p>I will decide that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W03000"><p>If we hear him out-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.168" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W03200"><p>There are no points of order during the reply to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W03300"><p>The Leader and this Government remind me of the man in the race-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W03400"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W03500"><p>-----who is so far behind the rest of the field that he thinks he is leading.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.173" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W03700"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W03800"><p>I did not hear it.  Will Senator Gallagher repeat that please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W03900"><p>He thinks he is in the lead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.177" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04100"><p>I ask the Senators to resume their seats.  I ask the Leader to continue without being provocative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04200"><p>In the immortal words of a former colleague and friend, Denis Cregan, who served in this House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04300"><p>I served with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04400"><p>-----it is a long game, played slow.  Senator Gallagher should remember that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04500"><p>The Leader's colleagues mentioned waiting lists, but we have never had so many people on trolleys.  I could also mention housing, homelessness-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04600"><p>We are hearing the Leader now.  We are not hearing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04700"><p>I remind Senator Murnane O'Connor that the architect of the present dysfunctional health system-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04800"><p>Leader, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W04900"><p>-----is her party leader, the former Minister of Health, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin.  Until her party-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W05000"><p>Through the Chair-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W05100"><p>The Leader always brings that subject up-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W05200"><p>Until Senator Murnane O'Connor's party-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W05300"><p>It would be more helpful for order, were you to direct comments through the Chair, rather than to the Members opposite.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#W05400"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00100"><p>If it was not for Fianna F&aacute;il, the Leader would be speechless.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00200"><p>Order, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00300"><p>Senator Murnane O'Connor's party leader founded the HSE and then ran out of office to leave Mary Harney embedded there for almost a decade.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00400"><p>Nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00500"><p>That is Fianna F&aacute;il's legacy and the Senators cannot hide it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00600"><p>The Taoiseach ran out of the Department of Health.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00700"><p>The Leader to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00800"><p>I remind Senators Murnane O'Connor and Gallagher of the Garda Vote.  There is an increase of &euro;122 million to pay for pay, recruitment costs and the recruitment of 700 new garda&iacute;.  Fianna F&aacute;il closed the college.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X00900"><p>The Government promised 800.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01000"><p>There are new resources for a range of issues.  I will be happy to have a debate on justice with the Members opposite any time they wish.</p> <p>I admit to a  lack of knowledge about Senator Murnane O'Connor's question about vetting.  She either wanted vetting or she did not.  I am not quite sure.  We can never-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01100"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01200"><p>Let me finish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01300"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01400"><p>We can never err on the side of caution regarding the protection of children and minors in the State.  I will be happy to have a debate on vetting but if the Senator thinks it would be more expeditious to deal with it as a Commencement matter, she should do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01500"><p>On a point of order------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01600"><p>Points of order should not be raised on the concluding remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01700"><p>The resources are not available and the Garda is put to the pin of its collar.  People are not being vetted in enough time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01800"><p>The Senator can hold that for the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X01900"><p>There are not enough resources.  It all boils down to resources and that is where the Government is falling down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X02000"><p>Is the Senator listening?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X02100"><p>She never does.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X02200"><p>Hold it for the debate.  The Leader might conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X02300"><p>Senators Marshall, Nash and Feighan raised the Lost Lives book.  If we do nothing else as a result of today's Order of Business, we could reflect on the contributions of Members who spoke about the film based on the book.  We can never go back to the dark days of the past.  We have a hard won peace.  It is fragile and we can never take it for granted.  We must always remember.  As Senator Marshall eloquently said, nobody escapes the pain and nobody has a monopoly on pain, but we can never allow this to happen again.  I endorse the view that the film should be essential viewing for all members of society.  I commend the Senators on that.</p> <p>In response to Senator Devine, the Committee Stage debate on Senator Freeman's Bill will take place tomorrow.  Some of the amendments from the Government seek to ensure that children are safeguarded.  I hope we can work together to make the Bill better so we can achieve its overarching aim, which is to protect and safeguard children.  Some of the points the Senator made today relate to challenges many parents face every day in how they deal with and have interactions with their children on the use of the Internet, social media and particular websites.  The points she made are important.  I was unable to attend the briefing earlier, but a member of my staff was there.  We can never be complacent about this important issue.  The debate will be held in the House tomorrow.</p> <p>Senator Gallagher raised the spreading of slurry.  The Minister of State, Deputy Doyle, said in the D&aacute;il today that the matter would be kept under constant review.  The points made by the Senator are valid.  On the beef exceptional aid measure, while I welcome the &euro;100 million, I do not have the answer as to why or whether it is necessarily the way he says it is, but let us have that debate with the Minister, Deputy Creed, or the Minister of State, Deputy Doyle.</p> <p>I welcome Senator Mark Daly's niece and her friend to the House.  I believe his niece's name is Clionadh, but I did not get her friend's name.  They are both welcome and I wish them every success in their visit.  I hope his niece is as successful as her uncle and that she travels as far as he does.</p> <p>Mar fhocal scoir, I am happy to accept the amendments to the Order of Business proposed by Senators Murnane O'Connor and Nash.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#X02400"><p>Senator Murnane O'Connor has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 12 be taken before No. 1".  The Leader indicated that he is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed.</p> <p>Senator Nash has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 13 be taken before No. 1".  The Leader, again, indicated that he is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.216" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.217" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y00100">Housing (Housing Assistance Payment Waiting Times) (Miscellaneous Provisions) (Amendment) Bill 2019: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y00200"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009, Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2014 and subsequent regulations to reduce social housing and housing assistance payment scheme assessment times.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y00300"><p>I second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.220" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y00500"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y00600"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y00700"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.224" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 22 October 2019.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.225" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y00900">Industrial Relations (Joint Labour Committees) Bill 2019: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y01000"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the provisions relating to the constitution of joint labour committees, so as to provide for cases where organisations of employers or of workers fail or refuse to engage in consultation with the Labour Court prior to the appointment of representative (employers) members or representative (workers) members, as the case may be; and to provide for connected matters.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y01100"><p>I second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.228" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y01300"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y01400"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y01500"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.232" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 22 October 2019.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#Y01700"><p>It will be a crowded day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.234" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.25 p.m. and resumed at 4.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.235" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#CC00100">Wildlife (Amendment) Bill 2016: Report Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#CC00200"><p>I move amendment No. 9:</p><blockquote>In page 4, line 3, after &ldquo;maintaining&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;raised&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>This is the same core issue we have discussed repeatedly, of which I hope there is reconsideration happening, namely, the inclusion of blanket bogs in what was originally envisaged, designed and prepared as legislation in respect of raised bogs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The 12-year period of consultation and research on raised bogs did not sufficiently address issues such as carbon capture or pollination and elements of it are out of date, as the Minister acknowledged with his amendments and by accepting mine.  Nevertheless there was, at least, a process and we may be able to fix the issues retrospectively.  By accepting my amendment No. 4, the Minister has given some regard to my argument and he has also introduced the issue of biodiversity.  There was not the same period of consultation and research for blanket bogs and they have not undergone the same process.  Blanket bogs, a particularly vulnerable environment, were introduced at the last Stage in the D&aacute;il, effectively doubling the remit of the Bill.  This meant that a whole new ecosystem was brought into the realm of the Bill, affecting things like designation and dedesignation procedures which we will talk about shortly.</p><p>This is a final appeal to the Minister to accept amendment No. 9 and further amendments which will narrow the scope of the Bill specifically to raised bogs and will allow for better and more up-to-date legislation.  This would be preceded by appropriate consultation and scientific research processes on blanket bogs.  If we have a Bill on apples it would not make sense to throw oranges in at the last minute.  This is another issue which was added to a Bill that was designed for one particular environment.  The debate has moved on since Fianna F&aacute;il made the case for the inclusion of blanket bogs, to which the current Minister agreed.  Our understanding of peatlands has moved on and is reflected in some aspects of the Government's narrative around the budget in terms of rewetting and increasing employment in bog restoration under just transition.  The future for peatlands in Ireland is going to be more in the area of restoration than resource exploitation.  I urge the Minister to narrow the focus of the Bill to produce fit-for-purpose legislation in respect of blanket bogs in the future, instead of the awkward stretch we have at the moment.  I hope the Minister is able to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#DD00200"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1314" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#DD00300"><p>The effect of this amendment would be to limit the provisions of the Bill to raised bog habitats only.  The Wildlife (Amendment) Bill 2016, as initiated, has been amended in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, following debate in committee.  It provides for the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, at his or her discretion, to conduct a review or reviews of the blanket bog natural heritage area, NHA, network and to continue and complete the 2014 review of the raised bog natural heritage area network.  The Bill gives the Minister the power to conduct the review at some point in the future without obliging the Minister to do so.</p> <p>As I have previously emphasised, such a review of blanket bog natural heritage areas would not be done in a vacuum but would involve public consultation and would not necessarily lead to proposals for the dedesignation of blanket bog NHA sites.  There are principles and criteria in the Bill to guide the Minister in conducting a review and in making a decision to carry out a strategic environmental assessment, a screening for an assessment or, as the case may be, an appropriate assessment in accordance with the Habitats Directive.  If required in the public consultation, there will be a linking of the achievement of nature conservation objectives for bog habitats to the favourable consultation status of these habitats.</p> <p>Section 18A(5) of the 2000 Act sets out that the Minister for Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht cannot make an order to dedesignate an NHA, whether it be a raised bog site or a blanket bog site, without first having had regard to any environmental assessment undertaken, and observations and submissions received during the public consultation.  As set out in the Bill, the heart of any review will be nature conservation, in terms of maintaining bog habitats at, or restoring bog habitats to, a favourable conservation status.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Any review must also take cognisance of our EU nature conservation obligations.  Therefore, unfortunately, I will not be accepting the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#EE00200"><p>What the Minister of State has described in terms of public consultation and consideration of our European obligations is a process that may happen regarding the effects on the environment of proposals arising from a review.  All of the processes &ndash; the consultation, the consideration of our European obligations and so forth &ndash; concern proposals that arise from a review.  They do not precede a review.  In effect, the Minister of State is saying that if a review is conducted that comes up with proposals for the de-designation of a natural heritage area, including both raised and blanket bogs, then there would be public consultation.  My point is that it is not really the same as what happened to raised bogs in that the consultation and research was not in consideration of a specific proposal on the designation or de-designation of specific natural heritage areas.  There were overall scientific conversations, audits and public consultations regarding raised bogs, as to what our public policy should be in that area and, for example, if de-designation should even be a consideration in respect of raised bogs.  We looked at what factors should be considered in de-designation and in generating a proposal for de-designation.</p> <p>While I said the issues the Minister of State has identified were not addressed, he is correct to say they do come into play, but they do so in response to a proposal for designation or de-designation.  As the Minister of State correctly said, there is no obligation on a Minister to have a blanket bog review.  It is something a Minister may do.  Again, it is a little akin to putting the cart before the horse.  We should have an overall national audit of blanket bogs and consider how they fit into all our different national strategies and then consider the appropriate policy proposals in respect of them, rather than what we have here, which is simply that a specific proposal on the designation or de-designation of a specific blanket bog may go to a public consultation.  It is not the same.  In that sense, I am disappointed the Minister of State is not able to accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.242/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#EE00300"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 11; Níl, 13.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Alice-Mary Higgins and Colette Kelleher; Níl, Senators Maria Byrne and Maura Hopkins.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.242/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2019-10-15" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#EE00300">
            <divisioncount ayes="11" noes="13" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="aye">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="aye">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" vote="aye">Alice Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" vote="aye">Colette Kelleher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" vote="aye">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="aye">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="no">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="no">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="no">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" vote="no">Anthony Lawlor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="no">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="no">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="no">James Reilly</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.242/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019101500002#EE00300"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-10-15a.243" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>