<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Colm Burke that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br /><br />The need for the Minister for Health and the HSE to establish community intervention teams in each area of the country so as to reduce the number of admissions from nursing homes to hospitals.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Thomas Byrne of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to explain the eviction, without formality, by the HSE of a disabled man (details supplied) from Caridas House, Drumconrath, Navan, County Meath, and to set out proposals to rehouse this man.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh of the following matter:<blockquote>Go dtabharfaidh an tAire Eala&iacute;on, Oidhreachta agus Gaeltachta le fios an bhfuil s&eacute; i gceist ag an Rialtas maoini&uacute; a chur ar f&aacute;il do thionscadal b&oacute;ithre pobail faoi sc&aacute;th na Ranna, i gcomhair le h&Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta n&oacute; aon ghn&iacute;omhaireachta&iacute; St&aacute;it eile, le obair fheabhs&uacute;ch&aacute;in a dh&eacute;anamh ar bh&oacute;ithre pobail na Gaeltachta.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator David Cullinane of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to outline what Government funding has been allocated in Waterford city and county under the school completion programme annually since 2011, what funding is being allocated in 2015, if he is aware of the impact funding cuts is having on service provision and if he will make a statement on the future of the school completion programme.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#B00050">Community Care</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#B00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Joe McHugh.  The matter before the House this morning relates to the need for community intervention teams in each area.  The reason I raise the issue on the Commencement debate is the need for the health service to reduce the number of people admitted to hospital, particularly from nursing homes.  I understand Nursing Homes Ireland has had detailed discussions with the HSE on this matter.  I also understand there has been a slowdown in the process of introducing community intervention teams.  The idea is that more services would be delivered within nursing homes or to people living in their own homes rather than in hospitals.</p> <p>A simple example of where we are falling down relates to the provision of dietitians.  If someone in a nursing home needs to see a dietitian, he or she has to go into hospital, as HSE dietitians are not available to go to nursing homes.  More intervention at local community level would mean that fewer people would have to go into hospital or attend outpatient clinics.  That approach is especially important in cases in which a number of people are gathered, as in nursing homes, and that is the context in which I raise this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#B00300"><p>I thank Senator Burke for raising this issue.  An overarching principle of our health service is to provide patients with the most appropriate care and service in the most appropriate location provided by the appropriate health care professionals.  Patients should not have to attend hospital unnecessarily, with all the added stresses and possible complications that such attendances involve.</p> <p>It is preferable that patients receive treatment in the community where this has been clinically approved.  As part of the phased implementation of the principles outlined in the primary care strategy, a number of national priorities have been set for the development of community-based services.  One of these priorities is the development of community intervention teams.  The main focus of teams is to reduce hospital attendances and admissions and to facilitate early discharge from hospitals.</p> <p>A community intervention team is a nurse-led health professional team.  The team provides a rapid and integrated response to a patient who becomes acutely ill and needs enhanced services, or acute intervention for a defined short period of time.  This may be provided in the community or the home, as deemed appropriate.  Community intervention team staff liaise with hospital and community clinicians.  They provide services in the person's home and in public and private nursing homes.  The community intervention teams provide a safe, cost-effective health service to patients in their homes that would ordinarily require hospital attendance and, in most cases, hospital admission.</p> <p>In 2014, more than 14,600 patients were treated by community intervention teams.  At any one time, to date in 2015, approximately 220 patients are being managed at their place of residence.  The service the programme provides to its patients includes but is not restricted to the following: intravenous cannulation and administration of intravenous antibiotics at home; acute anticoagulation care; acute wound care and dressings, including negative pressure dressing; enhanced nurse monitoring following fractures, falls or surgery; care of patients with central venous catheters; urinary-related care; care of patients with a respiratory illness, including nebuliser care, peak flow measurement and intermittent pulse oximetry; bowel care, including ostomy care; short-term older person support and care; and other medication management and administration as part of the patient's acute intervention package.</p> <p>The community intervention team programme has met with representatives of Nursing Homes Ireland and is working with them in developing direct referral pathways for nursing home residents.  There are currently nine teams in operation, in Dublin north, Dublin south, Galway, the mid-west, which includes Limerick, Tipperary and Clare, Carlow and Kilkenny, Cork city, Wicklow, Kildare and Louth.  The Wicklow service was established in 2014 and the services in Kildare and Louth both commenced in January 2015.  There is clear and strong evidence from various studies and bed utilisation reports demonstrating that a cohort of all hospital admissions can be treated in a non-acute setting, many through services provided by community intervention teams.  The strategic priority is to realise national coverage and to make a community intervention team service available to every person in the country if needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#B00400"><p>An bhfuil an Seanad&oacute;ir s&aacute;sta leis an bhfreagra sin?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#B00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his detailed reply, which I welcome.  Approximately 14,000 patients were treated by community intervention teams in 2014.  That is a very small number in comparison to the number that could be treated.  I know the area does not come within the responsibility of the Minister of State, but could he convey to the relevant Minister the need to expedite the implementation of the process?  Given that attendance in accident and emergency departments in hospitals every year is more than 1.1 million, which is approximately 22,000 per week, and a high percentage of those who attend are elderly people who are referred from their own homes or from nursing homes, community intervention teams are essential.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#B00600"><p>I am sure the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, will convey the message to the Minister for Health, Deputy Varadkar.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.13" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#B00750">Services for People with Disabilities</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#B00800"><p>This is a very serious issue.  A gentleman has been effectively under the care of disability services in a place called Caridas House in Drumconrath, Navan, County Meath, since 2007.  At times he has been illegally asked to pay rent to the HSE, although I understand that was stopped when the HSE decided it was illegal, as it was not allowed to be a landlord.  However, there is doubt about the fact that the man in question is under the care of disability services.  A number of weeks ago this gentleman, whom I have not named but whose details I have given to the Minister, was told that a health and safety issue had arisen in Caridas House, which was the case, but he was told that he would be allowed to go back there as soon as the matter had been rectified.  That has not turned out to be the case.  Since being unceremoniously evicted - I repeat the words of a HSE member of staff who acted as a whistleblower - the man has been put in temporary accommodation, and he has been told he will be put on the homeless register in Navan and put into temporary homeless accommodation.</p> <p>The man is autistic and has severe difficulties living his daily life.  I have sought legal advice for him on the issue.  No private landlord would be allowed to get away with what has happened.  No nursing home or residential care facility would do that to anyone, yet it has happened in County Meath that an autistic man under the care of the HSE has been thrown out.  He is getting some help from various members of staff of the HSE, but there seems to be a determination to move him on.  There was a suggestion that he would be given an alternative place to live, but I understand the offer has been withdrawn.  I seek clarity in that regard because if that is the case I would like to see some action.  What happened the man is unfair.  I would like the Minister to investigate the issue.  I understand the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, cannot be present.  It was suggested that the discussion of this matter might be postponed until tomorrow, which I would have preferred, but her office suggested that the Minister of State, Deputy Joe McHugh, respond instead, and I accepted that approach.  The man in question must be given his rights.  He has been treated absolutely appallingly by the HSE.  What happened was really disgusting.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Thomas Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2203"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2203&amp;amp;pid=ThomasByrne&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->He is a man who causes no harm to others, as I have discovered from talking to people in the village in which he lives.  He spends a lot of time by himself due to his autism.  He needs the accommodation, which was effectively sheltered accommodation for disabled persons.  He was kicked out of it.  I would like answers.</p><p>I sent a fax to the chief executive of the HSE, the relevant person in Meath, the Minister for Health and the Ombudsman last Friday.  I have received no response from anybody and have decided to raise the matter here today.  I would not have raised it had I received some kind of response, but I have not received an acknowledgement from anybody of this serious situation.  I do not like raising the matter publicly, but I have received the man's permission to do so.  I do not want to name him, but it is a very serious situation.  I have not come across anything like it before.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Byrne for raising this issue today and I am pleased to outline the Health Service Executive's position on the person concerned.  I understand the person has a diagnosis of Asperger's syndrome and suffers from associated anxiety.  He was offered temporary use of a vacant HSE property, known as Caradas, in Drumconrath a number of years ago when he became homeless.  Caradas was an unused former group home.  It was in a state of disrepair.  The former residents were moved to more modern accommodation.</p> <p>The HSE has informed the Minister's Department that the individual has lived in the property independently without residential staff.  He was, however, receiving a small amount of home support while at Caradas.  He was informed by representatives of the HSE on 19 January this year that he would be required to move out of the property by 20 March.  He remained in the property until that date.  Renovation works were being undertaken in the house.  The individual was informed and aware that he could stay only until these works were complete.</p> <p>The HSE and Meath County Council have been working in the meantime to source alternative accommodation for him.  Meath County Council was willing to offer him tenancy of an alternative council owned property in Drumconrath.  However, he was not willing to complete the relevant application forms.  Unfortunately, that property is no longer available.  The Meath County Council settlement officer and a representative of the HSE Meath disability services have met the individual.  They explained to him the necessity of completing the application forms in order that he would be eligible for rent allowance for alternative properties.  The HSE has informed the Minister's Department that he has commenced this process.</p> <p>A section of the roof of Caradas collapsed recently.  Thankfully, the individual was not injured.  The HSE carried out an inspection immediately.  The property was deemed unsafe for habitation.  The individual moved to local guest lodgings.  The HSE has informed the Department that officials met him, in the company of his sister, on 13 March 2015.  He was informed that he could not return to Caradas.  The HSE paid for guest lodgings for him to provide the opportunity to source his own accommodation.</p> <p>The HSE Meath disability services continue to provide health related supports to him to support him to live independently.  He had availed of up to four hours of home support per week while living at Caradas.  He has been offered additional home support hours to assist with his transition to new accommodation and attendance at hospital and dental appointments.  While the HSE Meath disability services provide group homes for people with moderate and severe intellectual disabilities, this type of accommodation is not suitable for him.  The HSE has assured the Minister's Department that it will continue to work with the individual and relevant housing authorities to provide the appropriate health supports to assist him to live independently.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#C00300"><p>I am very disappointed with the Minister of State's response.  I plead with the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, to examine this case.  In the reply the onus has been put on the applicant, and he has been told he did not fill out the forms.  The man has Asperger's syndrome which creates serious difficulties.  That is why he is under the care of the HSE disability services, which has been looking after him and providing a home for him since 2007.  They now seem to be abdicating their responsibilities and making this into a housing issue.  It is a care issue.  It is an unusual situation, but he has been provided with a level of care that the HSE now seem determined to end.  The reply states that he was offered an alternative property but this is no longer available.  As I understand it, the offer of the property was withdrawn.</p> <p>The man concerned is probably not entirely capable of making these decisions, and that is why he is being provided with disability services.  He has not been dealing with Meath County Council on an ongoing basis, rather he has dealt with HSE officials.  That is the difficulty.  I want some answers because I am referring the file on his behalf today to a solicitor who specialises in this area.  Passing the buck on the care of a disabled person with Asperger's syndrome cannot go on.  The man was told when the roof was fixed that he would be able to return.  He left on that basis, and was then told he would not be able to return.  It appears to me that, having talked to him, he was tricked.  He is in a state of extreme stress and anxiety over this issue, and many people who have no relationship whatsoever with him, but who are deeply concerned, have contacted me about him.  I would like a serious message to go back to the Minister of State, Deputy Lynch.  I hope she will read the Official Report, that my letters to the Minister, Ombudsman and the HSE will be responded to, and that something actually happens because it is outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#C00400"><p>Senator Byrne made a very compassionate case and I am sure the Minister of State will convey his deeply felt concerns to the line Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#C00500"><p>I appreciate that the Senator did not want to raise this issue publicly.  If he contacted the HSE or local authorities formally, a response is the least he should have received.  If that did not happen, that is not acceptable.  I suggest that he could sit down with local representatives from the HSE and the local authorities.  It is a very sensitive case.  I will convey the Senator's strong words to the Minister.  I appreciate and share his observations on the support systems available for people who are unable to fill out forms on their own.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.20" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#D00100">Sc&eacute;imeanna B&oacute;ithre</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#D00200"><p>Cuirim c&eacute;ad f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute;im ag ard&uacute; ceiste maidir le b&oacute;ithre pobail sna ceantair Ghaeltachta.  Bheadh eolas maith ag an Aire St&aacute;it seo ar an gceist seo os rud &eacute; go bhfuil s&eacute; f&eacute;in ina ch&oacute;na&iacute; gar do cheantar Gaeltachta agus b&iacute;onn s&eacute; isteach agus amach ann an t-am ar fad.  Bh&iacute; sc&eacute;im ann a bh&iacute; &aacute; fheidhmi&uacute; faoi sc&aacute;th &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta ina raibh s&eacute; ag f&aacute;il taca&iacute;ochta &oacute; na sc&eacute;imeanna s&oacute;isialta tuaithe n&oacute; na sc&eacute;imeanna fosta&iacute;ocht pobail le deisi&uacute;ch&aacute;in agus obair fhorbartha a dh&eacute;anamh ar na b&oacute;ithr&iacute; pobal seo sna blianta a chaitheadh.  Bh&iacute; an sc&eacute;im seo teoranta do bh&oacute;ithre nach b&oacute;ithre contae iad, b&oacute;ithre nach raibh faoi sc&aacute;th na comhairle contae, agus d&aacute; bhr&iacute; sin nach raibh ag f&aacute;il aon ch&uacute;namh &oacute;n gcomhairle contae le haghaidh deisi&uacute;ch&aacute;in.  Cuireadh b&oacute;ithre si&uacute;l&oacute;ide, b&oacute;ithre rotha&iacute;ochta, b&oacute;ithre cois chladaigh, b&oacute;ithre go c&eacute;anna beaga, b&oacute;ithre go reilig&iacute; agus b&oacute;ithre go portaigh sna ceantair Ghaeltachta san &aacute;ireamh.  Bh&iacute; an Ghaeilge mar cheann de na crit&eacute;ir mheas&uacute;naithe a bh&iacute; leagtha s&iacute;os faoin sc&eacute;im sin agus bh&iacute; suas le &euro;10,000 an cilim&eacute;adar mar uasmh&eacute;id le n-&iacute;oc le tabhairt leis an obair seo a dh&eacute;anamh.  Bh&iacute; an obair seo f&iacute;orth&aacute;bhachtach agus t&aacute; s&eacute; f&iacute;orth&aacute;bhachtach.</p> <p>Bh&iacute; an sc&eacute;im imithe i l&eacute;ig le cupla bliain agus bh&iacute; an arg&oacute;int ann go raibh gantannas airgid ins an t&iacute;r agus nach bhf&eacute;adfaidh ruda&iacute; den chine&aacute;l seo a dh&eacute;anamh.  Idir an d&aacute; linn, t&aacute; b&oacute;ithre i mo cheantar f&eacute;in imithe in olcas ar fad.  Bh&iacute; cruinni&uacute; ann o&iacute;che D&eacute; Domhnaigh seo caite maidir leis an b&oacute;thar go portach Seanamhach i gConamara, agus t&aacute; a fhios agam go bhfuil b&oacute;ithre eile ag dul s&iacute;os go c&eacute;ibheanna agus mar sin de at&aacute; i ndrochchaoi.  Is b&oacute;ithre iad seo a bhfuil deis iontach iontu chomh maith c&eacute;anna &oacute; thaobh si&uacute;l&oacute;ide de, &oacute; thaobh turas&oacute;ireachta de, &oacute; thaobh acla&iacute;ochta agus mar sin de.  T&aacute;imid tar &eacute;is borradh a fheice&aacute;il faoi Shl&iacute; an Atlantaigh Fhi&aacute;in.  Bh&iacute; muid ag caint faoi sin roimhe anseo.  T&aacute; na b&oacute;ithre seo ag imeacht &oacute; na b&oacute;ithre at&aacute; liost&aacute;ilte ar Shl&iacute; an Atlantaigh Fhi&aacute;in agus is &aacute;iteanna maithe iad dul ag si&uacute;l d&aacute; mbeadh daoine ag iarraidh stopadh ar an mbealach.  D&aacute; bhr&iacute; sin, t&aacute; s&eacute; f&iacute;orth&aacute;bhachtach go nd&eacute;anfa&iacute; deisi&uacute;ch&aacute;in ar na b&oacute;ithre seo.</p> <p>I l&aacute;thair na huaire, deirtear liom go bhfuil cuid mhaith de na b&oacute;ithre seo nach f&eacute;idir taisteal orthu ar chor ar bith, go bhfuil siad i ndrochchaoi, go bhfuil g&aacute; le draen&aacute;il a dh&eacute;anamh le na taobhanna, le banc&aacute;il a dh&eacute;anamh ar na b&oacute;ithre agus mar sin de agus le dromchla nua a chur ar ghiota&iacute; maithe de na b&oacute;ithre seo.  T&aacute;imid ag cloiste&aacute;il &oacute;n Rialtas go bhfuil ruda&iacute; ag feabhs&uacute;, go bhfuil f&aacute;s ag teacht ar an eacnama&iacute;ocht agus nach bhfuil c&uacute;rsa&iacute; airgid chomh dona agus a bh&iacute; siad.  N&iacute; buis&eacute;ad ollmh&oacute;r at&aacute; i gceist anseo.  Is d&oacute;cha go nd&eacute;anfadh c&uacute;pla c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le euro an bheart &oacute; thaobh na b&oacute;ithre &eacute;ags&uacute;la a bheadh i gceist ins an rud seo.  Choinneodh siad na b&oacute;ithr&iacute; seo i gcaoi mhaith idir an d&aacute; linn go dt&iacute; go mbeidh n&iacute;os m&oacute; airgid ar f&aacute;il chun iad a uasghr&aacute;d&uacute; mar is ceart.  Bh&iacute; an sc&eacute;im seo faoi sc&aacute;th &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta roimhe seo.  An bhfuil an tAire St&aacute;it ag smaoini&uacute; ar an sc&eacute;im seo a mhaoini&uacute; ar&iacute;s, go h&aacute;irid don samhradh seo le gur f&eacute;idir an obair riachtanach seo a dh&eacute;anamh chomh luath agus is f&eacute;idir?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#D00300"><p>T&aacute; m&eacute; bu&iacute;och don Seanad&oacute;ir as an &aacute;bhar seo a ard&uacute; inniu.  Faoi na sc&eacute;imeanna a bh&iacute;odh ag an Roinn go stairi&uacute;il, bh&iacute;odh deontais chaipitil ar f&aacute;il chun muiroibreacha sa Ghaeltacht a fhorbairt, chun b&oacute;ithre sa Ghaeltacht a fheabhs&uacute;, agus chun &aacute;iseanna ar n&oacute;s halla&iacute; pobail, p&aacute;irceanna imeartha agus &aacute;iseanna eile a chur ar f&aacute;il n&oacute; a fheabhs&uacute;.  Tr&iacute; fheabhs&uacute; an bhonneagair, bh&iacute; s&eacute; de chusp&oacute;ir ag na deontais seo cur le saol s&oacute;isialta, cult&uacute;rtha agus eacnama&iacute;och na Gaeltachta chomh maith leis an Ghaeilge a neart&uacute; mar theanga pobail sa Ghaeltacht.</p> <p>In 2004, leanadh leis an gcl&aacute;r oibre seo agus mar gheall ar na socruithe &uacute;ra a bh&iacute; aontaithe ag mo Roinn ag an am leis an Roinn Airgeadais faoin gcreatlach infheist&iacute;ochta caipitil, bh&iacute; mo Roinn ag an am in ann plean oibre dh&aacute; bhliain a chur i bhfeidhm leis na h&uacute;dar&aacute;is &aacute;iti&uacute;la chun b&oacute;ithre, c&eacute;ibheanna agus bailte Gaeltachta a fhorbairt.  Rinneadh &eacute; seo sa bhreis ar an infheist&iacute;ocht a dh&eacute;anann na h&uacute;dar&aacute;is &aacute;iti&uacute;la agus Ranna eile agus is c&uacute;namh faoi leith a bh&iacute; ann d'fhorbairt an bhonneagair sa Ghaeltacht.  Bh&iacute; sc&eacute;im na mb&oacute;ithre &aacute;ise agus sc&eacute;im na mb&oacute;ithre portaigh ach go h&aacute;irithe ag mo Roinn ag an am.  Bh&iacute; na sc&eacute;imeanna seo &aacute; bhfeidhmi&uacute; chun cuidi&uacute; le pobal na Gaeltachta feabhas a chur ar bh&oacute;ithre &aacute;irithe a bh&iacute; mar &aacute;is rochtana d&oacute;ibh.  I gc&aacute;s na mb&oacute;ithre &aacute;ise, bh&iacute; s&eacute; mar choinn&iacute;oll den sc&eacute;im go gcaithfeadh an b&oacute;thar a bheith ag freastal ar theach c&oacute;naithe amh&aacute;in ar a laghad ina mbeadh buanch&oacute;na&iacute; ann agus ar ghabh&aacute;ltas amh&aacute;in ar a laghad nach le h&uacute;in&eacute;ir an t&iacute; &eacute; agus a mbeadh rochtain chomh fada leis ag brath ar an mb&oacute;thar amh&aacute;in.</p> <p>C&eacute; go bhfuil s&eacute; deacair tomhais a dh&eacute;anamh ar an tionchar a bh&iacute; ag na sc&eacute;imeanna b&oacute;ithre ar an nGaeilge, meastar den chuid is m&oacute; gur beag tionchar a bh&iacute; acu ar neart&uacute; na Gaeilge mar theanga pobail sa Ghaeltacht.  Nuair a fhoils&iacute;odh an Staid&eacute;ar Teangeola&iacute;och ar &Uacute;s&aacute;id na Gaeilge sa Ghaeltacht i 2007, ba l&eacute;ir nach leor an cur chuige forbartha r&eacute;igi&uacute;nda gur ghlac an St&aacute;t chuige f&eacute;in chun dul i ngleic le ceist sochtheangeola&iacute;och sa Ghaeltacht a thuilleadh.  Mar at&aacute; a fhios ag an Seanad&oacute;ir, t&aacute; mo Roinn i gcomhar le h&Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta ag forbairt an phr&oacute;isis plean&aacute;la teanga sa Ghaeltacht faoi Acht na Gaeltachta, agus beidh deis ag pobal na Gaeltachta d&iacute;ri&uacute; isteach ar na riachtanais at&aacute; acu &oacute; thaobh buan&uacute; agus l&aacute;idri&uacute; na teanga ina gceantair f&eacute;in.  T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam go dtuigfidh an Seanad&oacute;ir mar sin nach bhfuil s&eacute; i gceist ag mo Roinn maoini&uacute; a chur ar f&aacute;il do sc&eacute;imeanna b&oacute;ithre sa Ghaeltacht i gcomhth&eacute;acs an tosa&iacute;ocht at&aacute;thar ag tabhairt don phlean&aacute;il teanga sa Ghaeltacht.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#D00400"><p>Caithfidh m&eacute; a r&aacute; go bhfuil m&eacute; an-d&iacute;om&aacute;ch leis an bhfreagra.  Bh&iacute; m&eacute; ag s&uacute;il go mb'fh&eacute;idir go mbeadh d&oacute;chas &eacute;igin ag an Aire St&aacute;it d&uacute;inn.  C&eacute; go gcreidim go bhfuil t&aacute;bhacht leis an bplean&aacute;il teanga, t&aacute; t&aacute;bhacht freisin le pobal beo beith&iacute;och a choinne&aacute;il sna ceantair Ghaeltachta.  T&aacute; an cine&aacute;l deontais a bh&iacute; faoi sc&eacute;im na mb&oacute;ithre pobal f&iacute;orth&aacute;bhachtach le rochtain a thabhairt do dhaoine dul ar an bportach, dul ar si&uacute;l&oacute;id, dul ag na c&eacute;ibheanna agus mar sin de sna ceantair Ghaeltachta.  N&iacute;l uasghr&aacute;d&uacute; agus mar sin de &aacute; dh&eacute;anamh air mar is ceart.  T&aacute; an turas&oacute;ireacht chult&uacute;rtha sa nGaeltacht bunaithe ar dhaoine a bheith in ann rochtain a bheith acu sna h&aacute;iteanna seo.  Is ar an mbun&uacute;s sin a raibh cead ag an Roinn cheana a leith&eacute;id de sc&eacute;im a chur ar bun.  Iarraim ar an Aire St&aacute;it dul ar ais, athmhachnamh a dh&eacute;anamh ar an gceist seo, go h&aacute;irid leis an bpr&aacute;inne at&aacute; ann &oacute; thaobh an chaoi at&aacute; ar na b&oacute;ithre faoi l&aacute;thair.  T&aacute;imid ag cailleadh deis iontach turas&oacute;ireachta, deis si&uacute;l&oacute;ide agus deis a thabhairt do phobal na Gaeltachta le fanacht ag maracht&aacute;il sna ceantair Ghaeltachta mar phobal beo beith&iacute;och.  Muna dt&oacute;gann an tAire St&aacute;it an deis seo, s&iacute;lim gur dul am&uacute; an-mh&oacute;r ar an Rialtas seo &eacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#D00500"><p>T&aacute; m&eacute; ar thaobh an Seanad&oacute;ir maidir leis an g&aacute; at&aacute; an an pobal a choinne&aacute;il beo.  Beidh g&aacute; m&oacute;r ann f&aacute; choinne infheist&iacute;ocht a mhealladh isteach sna ceantair Ghaeltachta.  Mar a bh&iacute; an Seanad&oacute;ir ag r&aacute; faoi na deiseanna a bhaineann le Sl&iacute; an Atlantaigh Fhi&aacute;in, t&aacute; deiseanna m&oacute;ra ann agus beidh go leor tr&aacute;chta ann freisin agus beidh br&uacute; m&oacute;r ann ar na b&oacute;ithre sna ceantair Ghaeltachta.  T&aacute; na ceantair Ghaeltachta ag cro&iacute; Sl&iacute; an Atlantaigh Fhi&aacute;in.  Aonta&iacute;m go bhfuil fadhbanna agus deiseanna ann agus beidh m&eacute; i dteagmh&aacute;il leis an Aire, an Teachta Paschal Donohoe.  T&aacute; dualgas air f&aacute; choinne na b&oacute;ithre a chosaint.  T&aacute; an ceart ag an Seanad&oacute;ir freisin go bhfuil c&uacute;rsa&iacute; eacnama&iacute;ochta ag feabhs&uacute;.  T&aacute; fadhbanna ann, cinnte, ach t&aacute; ruda&iacute; ag feabhs&uacute; agus b'fh&eacute;idir go bhfuil acmhainn&iacute; breise ann.  B'fh&eacute;idir go mbeidh deiseanna ann anois airgead a chur isteach sna ceantair Ghaeltachta agus sna ceantair iarg&uacute;lta.  Chaithfinn an airgead d&aacute; mbeadh s&eacute; agam.  T&aacute;im freagrach mar Aire St&aacute;it as an Ghaeilge a chur chun cinn agus na limist&eacute;ir agus l&iacute;onra&iacute; plean&aacute;la teanga a chur i bhfeidhm.  T&aacute;im freagrach as an teanga a choinne&aacute;il beo ach aonta&iacute;m leis na ruda&iacute; at&aacute; r&aacute;ite ag an Seanad&oacute;ir inniu agus beidh m&eacute; i dteagmh&aacute;il leis an Aire amach anseo.  Bh&iacute; m&eacute; i dteagmh&aacute;il leis an Aire Iompair, Turas&oacute;ireachta agus Sp&oacute;irt cheana.  Bh&iacute; s&eacute; i dT&iacute;r Chonaill c&uacute;pla seachtain &oacute; shin agus d'ardaigh m&eacute; ceist na mb&oacute;ithre i gceantair Ghaeltachta at&aacute; i gcro&iacute; Sl&iacute; an Atlantaigh Fhi&aacute;in.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.25" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#D00600">School Completion Programme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#D00700"><p>I thank the Minister for taking this Commencement motion himself.  I tabled this motion after meeting a number of school completion programme, SCP, co-ordinators in Waterford city in recent weeks.  They have been lobbying elected representatives from all parties and none on cuts to the SCP over recent years.  This programme was established in 2002 to have a significant positive impact on retention levels in primary and secondary schools and the number of pupils who successfully complete the senior cycle or equivalent.  All the studies show that the SCP programme has had very positive results, that more people are completing both the junior and leaving certificates and that more people are seeing through their time in primary school, which is positive.</p> <p>There have been cuts to these programmes in recent years, however, which are having a direct impact on the services that the programme co-ordinators are in place to provide.  At the moment, surveys of SPCs are taking place throughout the State which seek to ascertain the impact these budget cuts have had to date in the running of individual programmes.  Some of the initial feedback I have seen reveals trends in the following areas: reductions to or cutting of specific supports and interventions, reductions to project workers hours, redundancies, instances of project workers and local co-ordinators finding themselves forced to take unpaid leave to maintain service provision within the allocated budget.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Cullinane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2357"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2357&amp;amp;pid=DavidCullinane&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Also, programme co-ordinators note that preventative interventions have suffered as a result of cutbacks to funding while the demand for administrative procedures has increased exponentially since the SCP was reassigned to the Child and Family Agency support called Tusla.  In recent years, SCPs have been requested to desist from offering counselling by the funding agency.  However, crisis situations have arisen in schools, particularly threatened suicide, where SCP has been requested by schools to provide counselling urgently.  There seems to be very real issues of concern.  I am sure that many co-ordinators of SCPs from across the State have been in contact with the Minister's office to express their concern about budget cutbacks.</p><p>The reason I tabled this motion is twofold.  First, I wanted to get information from the Minister about the levels of funding which have gone into SCP programmes in Waterford city and county over the past three years so that we can look at the trends and at where cuts have taken place.  Second, I wanted to impress upon him the impact such cuts have had on the SCP programmes.  If we want to maintain the very successful figures the SCPs have been part of achieving in retaining people in primary education, then we need to maintain the levels of funding.  If we cut back on funding we may drift backwards in terms of the success of the projects and programmes.</p><p>I appeal to the Minister to listen to what the co-ordinators who work on the ground have said.  I hope he is in a position to make a statement on his future intentions for this programme, and that of the Government, to fund these programmes into the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#E00200"><p>The school completion programme aims to retain young people in the formal education system to completion of senior cycle and to generally improve the school attendance, participation and retention of its target cohort.  It is a targeted intervention aimed at those school communities, identified through the DEIS action plan for educational inclusion run by the Department of Education and Skills.  It involves 124 locally managed projects and related initiatives operating across 470 primary and 224 post-primary schools to provide targeted supports to approximately 36,000 children and young people.</p> <p>Since 1 January 2014, the Child and Family Agency has operational responsibility for the school completion programme, including the allocation of funds to local projects.  In 2014, an allocation of &euro;24.756 million has been provided for the school completion programme.</p> <p>The programme is one of three service strands within the continuum of education welfare service being implemented by Tusla, the Child and Family Agency, to support children, their families and schools.  The other service strands are the home-school-community liaison scheme and the Educational Welfare Service.</p> <p>Three school completion programme projects operate across Waterford city and county, namely, Waterford SCP which encompasses Ballybeg Community Education Project, Na Si&uacute;ire SCP and Dungarvan SCP.  Between the three projects, they were allocated &euro;775,380 for the academic year 2011-12, &euro;724,933 in 2012-13,  &euro;698,904 in 2013-14, and &euro;635,000 in 2014-15.</p> <p>The agency has approved local projects' school retention plans for the 2014-15 academic year.  The amount provided for 2014-15 for the school completion programme takes account of the savings requirements in the comprehensive review of expenditure 2012-14.  The first two instalments of the 2014-15 funding have issued to local projects, with a third instalment planned for May 2015.</p> <p>The estimate for the Child and Family Agency for 2015 is &euro;635 million which is a 4.3% increase on its 2014 allocation.  My Department has recently issued a performance statement to the agency under section 45 of the Child and Family Agency Act 2013.  This includes my priorities for consideration in the development of the agency's 2015 business plan.</p> <p>The business plan will set out the agency's proposed activities, programmes and priorities for 2015, including provision for the school completion programme in light of the moneys available.  I have advised the agency of my commitment to ensuring that there is no diminution in the school completion programme services.</p> <p>A review of the school completion programme is under way.  It is being carried out by the ESRI and will include a review of the governance and delivery structures of the programme.  The review will assist in identifying the reforms necessary to consolidate the programme on a sustainable footing for the future.</p> <p>The review will, among other things, examine the structures of the school completion programme, and how they can best support an integrated approach to address early school leaving.  It will analyse the interventions provided and make recommendations for evidence informed supports designed to secure the best educational outcomes for young people.</p> <p>The review will capture the views of a range of stakeholders, including staff and all those involved in the organisation and administration of the school completion programme.  It includes a survey to gather the views of project co-ordinators and chairpersons of the 124 local school completion programme projects throughout the country, case studies of projects involving staff and participating schools and interviews with national stakeholders who have a direct interest in the programme.</p> <p>Preliminary information gathered on the programme indicates that the school completion programme encompasses a broad and diverse range of measures and interventions that have been developed by local projects over the years.  The review will aim to capture learning from the most successful of these.  Another aim is to ensure that available funds are targeted at those services that provide the greatest contribution to good educational outcomes for children and young people at risk of educational disadvantage.  The review is expected to be completed shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#E00300"><p>It is laudable for the Minister to advise the agency of his commitment to ensure there is no reduction in school completion programme services.  The problem with his statement is that co-ordinators on the ground have said budget cuts have had an impact on services.  The figures outlined by him clearly demonstrate that there has been a significant cutback in funding to these programmes in Waterford city and county.  In the academic year of 2011-12 funding amounted to &euro;775,380 but in the current year it is &euro;635,475.  That means there has been a cut in funding of over &euro;130,000 which must have an impact on service provision.  Only so much savings can be made in the overall overheads in terms of staff costs, rent, etc.  When there is that level of cutbacks in funding it is the front-line services which suffer the most.  That is the information that I have received from people who work on the ground.</p> <p>I accept that there is a review under way.  I hope the review goes well.  Whatever about structural reforms that may be recommended, the Minister also needs to be conscious of the need to maintain levels of funding.  He must ensure that, whatever structural changes the agency and he may put in place, the co-ordinators and programmes on the ground are in a financial position to provide the services that people need so that these projects continue to be successful into the future.  I imagine that is what the Minister wants to see as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#E00400"><p>I am pleased that the Senator has acknowledged that these programmes work and have an impact.  Of course they do not work in all cases and that is why I pointed out, in my main response to him, that we are continually reviewing to see whether we are getting the desired outcomes from our inputs.  Where things are working well we want to see those replicated in other areas.  Where things are not working then it is not sensible to continue with them.  We need to put in place the policies, structures and services that result in the outcomes we want which is more children completing their secondary education.  That is our aim because education is a great determinant of how well one does in life in terms of employment prospects and living standards.</p> <p>Yes, over the fiscal crisis that we had to endure, which is one this Government inherited, there had to be some cuts made.  I am happy to say that the cuts in regard to my Department have ceased and this year its budget has been increased.  We have not closed any schools in the region.  We have built more schools and added services in those schools.  As the Senator will be aware, his party in the North of Ireland has closed over 100 schools in the past number of years.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.31" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.20 a.m. and resumed at noon.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.32" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#K00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#K00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution (Marriage Equality) Bill 2015 &ndash; Second Stage, to be taken at 1.15 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed 12 minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed eight minutes; and No, 2, motion re Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution (Marriage Equality) Bill 2015, to be discussed in conjunction with the Second Stage debate but not to be taken until the Report and Final Stages of the Bill have concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#K00300"><p>I noted with interest yesterday and this morning the remarks of the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, on the Government announcement of free general practitioner care for over 70s.  It would be welcome if we knew when it was going to happen and if we did not have a scenario like the free GP care for children under aged six, which was announced over two years ago but which still has not actually materialised.  Is this something the Government intends to keep re-announcing?  The Minister of State, Deputy Lynch, said this morning that there was no agreement with GPs either on children aged under six or people aged over 70.</p> <p>I would have thought the priority for the Government was to ensure that those who require medical cards and treatment get them as opposed to promising things that will never happen in future.  As the Leas-Chathaoirleach remarked yesterday, there are still people over 70 who are having their medical cards removed.  There are still children with serious illnesses who cannot get the treatment they require.  There is still a situation in Dublin where there are no early intervention teams for children with special needs who require needs assessment and occupational therapy.  Since June 2012, not one child has been added to the waiting list for needs assessment.</p> <p>What is the position with free GP care for children aged under six?  Is there a date for this to start, or are we to have it announced again in the pre-election budget in October with a view to getting it up and running before the general election?  What is the position with the over 70s free GP care that the Government is referring to?</p> <p>This situation needs to be cleared up once and for all.  It has been announced on several occasions.  With that in mind, I will provide assistance to the relevant Minister, whether the Minister for Health, Deputy Varadkar, or one of his Ministers of State, by  proposing that the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, come to the House today and give an update on the position of free GP care for children under six and Government plans for over 70s free GP care.  I propose that amendment to the Order of Business and that an hour be set aside for that debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#K00400"><p>I welcome the announcement yesterday by the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, of the provision of 2.5 hours per week for up to 1,000 children who suffer from Down's syndrome.  This issue has been going on for many years.  I protested with the families of children with Down's syndrome outside this building last summer.  I am pleased that the Minister has recognised the situation and provided the necessary hours to help alleviate the difficulties.</p> <p>Everyone acknowledges that it is not the complete package but it will help to alleviate the issues.  It has been broadly welcomed by Down Syndrome Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Denis Landy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2349"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2349&amp;amp;pid=DenisLandy&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I also welcome the T&aacute;naiste's announcement that the Cabinet yesterday approved a settlement for the Waterford Crystal workers who have struggled for eight years to get payment for the pension scheme that went into thin air when the company closed down.  The average payment per worker will be a lump sum of &euro;40,000 plus a pension per annum.  It is important that the settlement has included the spouses of many of the workers who have died since the company closed eight years ago.  After a long and protracted campaign, in which I participated on behalf of the people in my town of Carrick-on-Suir and the surrounding areas of Rathgormack, Tullahought and places like that, the people who worked in Waterford Crystal for many years have at last got a settlement.</p><p>I am heartened by comments made by the Minister, Deputy Howlin, a number of weeks ago regarding town councils.  He said that the decision which accounted for a significant decrease in the number of councillors is one of the biggest regrets of the coalition's term of office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L00200"><p>Is this the one the Senator voted for?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L00300"><p>Senator Landy is going in the right direction and Senators should give him a chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L00400"><p>If only he voted the way he talks, we would be grand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L00500"><p>Senator Landy, without interruption.  He has a minute to finish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L00600"><p>I was very vocal in this Chamber on the matter.  I probably spoke longer than other Senators who suddenly got an interest in it when they discovered that some of these people who had been town councillors are now county councillors and have a vote in the next Seanad election.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L00700"><p>Did the Senator vote with them?  He did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L00800"><p>We will check that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L00900"><p>I was always of the opinion-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01000"><p>The vote is what counts.  Talk is cheap.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01100"><p>Senator Landy, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01200"><p>I was always of the opinion and still hold the opinion that town councils should never have been abolished.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01300"><p>Hear, hear.  No need to divide on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01400"><p>Can Senator Landy point out which way he voted?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01500"><p>Let Senator Landy conclude.  We are running out of time and have a very busy day ahead.  I have to give the Senator another minute now because he has been interrupted twice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01600"><p>I refer to people who worked in that service and in particular I want to mention Ms Helen Phelan who will retire from Carrick-on-Suir Town Council after 47 years' service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01700"><p>Is that the town council that the Senator's Government abolished?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01800"><p>That is the type of person I am talking about.</p> <p>I am delighted to be the first person in the Seanad today to welcome the retirement of Henry Shefflin, announced at noon.  As a Tipperary man, I can say that he was the greatest hurler that ever graced the hurling field.  As his former Kilkenny colleague, Michael Kavanagh, said this morning, he was a slow burner and did not get his first medal until playing on the under-21 team and he actually started on the intermediate team.  He is a little bit like the Government, a slow burner, burning the dead wood of the previous Administration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L01900"><p>It is burning stuff all right - mostly bridges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02000"><p>I call Senator van Turnhout.  Perhaps we might get back to real issues, notwithstanding the great-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02100"><p>It is a big issue where I come from.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02200"><p>I concur with Senator Landy on the announcement by the Minister for Education and Skills of the two and a half resource hours for children with Down's syndrome.  I question the continuing need for an assessment and I ask the Minister for Education and Skills to reconsider that.  Why do we need a child with mild Down's syndrome to go through an assessment procedure?  However, it is very welcome.  I sincerely congratulate the parents and Down Syndrome Ireland who advocated on behalf of these children.  As I so often say, children's rights are parents' rights because it is so often parents who advocate on behalf of their children.</p> <p>I welcome the announcement that Diageo is stepping down from the Stop Out-of-Control Drinking campaign.  It is an overdue announcement.  I do not think it had a role on the board of the campaign.  I have remaining questions over the secretariat and the names collected to date.  Who owns those names?  That may be a question for the Data Protection Commissioner.  I concur with the Minister, Deputy Varadkar, who on the announcement of Diageo's withdrawal said, "I don't think it's appropriate that the drinks industry should be actively involved in campaigns around public health for the obvious reason".  I agree with him on this point.  Alcohol Focus Scotland has stated: "The industry uses partnership working to gain public support and credibility for ineffective policy measures, whilst at the same time misrepresenting and distorting evidence on effective regulatory interventions."</p> <p>An advertisement has recently been placed by Drinkaware.  It is hiring a small team for its ambitious strategic plan.  Critical to that is its new focus on education.  One of the roles advertised is an education programme manager for developing Drinkaware's education programme targeted at young people, parents and teachers.  It wants to work and develop an education programme for delivery as part of the SPHE curriculum in secondary schools.  This curriculum has recently been revised and the HSE has given input on alcohol related harm.  There is no role for the drinks industry in our schools.  Drinkaware is funded by the drinks industry.  It is reprehensible that it even considers going into our schools to educate our young people on drink.  Would we allow representatives of manufacturers of other products to go into schools and educate them on why they should have less of the product?  I find it reprehensible.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to ask the Minister for Education and Skills if she or her officials have been approached by Drinkaware.  I hope we get a categorical "No" that Drinkaware has no role in our schools.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02300"><p>I call Senator Naughton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02400"><p>I wish to raise-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02500"><p>I accept your ruling, a Leas Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02600"><p>Even though she is seated on this side-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02700"><p>She is seated on the side of God.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02800"><p>-----she is seen as in opposition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L02900"><p>Really? She is in opposition?  My God almighty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03000"><p>That is the grouping system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03100"><p>I wish to raise some positive news on the jobs front for Galway and the west.  This comes soon after Apple's major jobs announcement for Athenry.  IDT911, a data protection company, will establish its European headquarters in Galway, creating 60 jobs in the area.  This company credited its move to the very good pool of talented graduates available locally and also due to the support it got from State agencies, such as IDA Ireland.  This new jobs announcement comes as a Deloitte report stated that 7,000 ICT jobs in Ireland remain open.  Its study, Tech Trends 2015: The fusion of business and IT, stated that an absence of skilled individuals was of significant concern in the tech sector.  That such a large number of jobs remain available is of some concern.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the matter with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Bruton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03200"><p>I think I have heard everything now after this ruling that a Member from Fine Gael, the main Government party, is a member of the Opposition.  "Ha, ha, ha" is all I can say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03300"><p>Senator van Turnhout was-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03400"><p>A Fine Gael Member is not a member of the Opposition until and unless he or she applies to be and leaves Fine Gael.  It is complete nonsense-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03500"><p>Senator, you are-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03600"><p>-----to say that Fine Gael is the Opposition - that the bloody Government-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03700"><p>Senator Norris is misunderstanding me.  The Opposition speaker was Senator van Turnhout, who is in a grouping that has been there for four years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03800"><p>But you said that Senator Naughton was.  Anyway I forgave the Leas Chathaoirleach.  It does not matter a damn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L03900"><p>No.  I said I could not call two Opposition-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#L04000"><p>It just highlights that the Order of Business is becoming increasingly a nonsense.  Look at us here.  There are half a dozen Fine Gael and Labour Senators, an Independent and two Opposition Members.  It is a complete nonsense.  We experimented with it, but the time has come to review the matter again.</p> <p>I strongly welcome the announcement by the Association of Catholic Priests that it will not take a position on the referendum.  This is a mature, balanced and humane approach and one I wish the hierarchy would also adopt.  On the other hand, they are a great advantage to the "Yes" campaign because they appear more and more like episodes of "Fr. Ted" every time they open their mouths.</p> <p>I agree with what has been said about Down's syndrome.  It has always seemed to me obscene that there should be a test for mild Down's syndrome and then children who are not as disadvantaged are punished for having greater talent.  This is utterly wrong, undemocratic and discriminatory.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Finally, with regard to Waterford Crystal, like Senator Landy I was one of those who brought this matter up regularly and I welcome what has happened, but it shows an extraordinary contrast between the way in which Waterford Glass workers are rightly treated in a situation where both the company and the pension fund went bust and Aer Lingus-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M00300"><p>-----where the company is thriving-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M00500"><p>-----and should sustain a situation where people are properly compensated by their pensions.  To hack off 60% of someone's pension when they reach their declining years is an obscenity.  I do not think the State should stand over this.  We have a 25% holding in Aer Lingus and we should step up to the mark and look after those people.  If not, I hope the case goes to the European Court of Human Rights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M00600"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M00700"><p>I, too, welcome the announcement yesterday by the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, on children with Down's syndrome.  It is something that is long overdue.  It is a matter on which the association has canvassed and lobbied over a number of years.  It is money that will be well spent in catering for those children.</p> <p>In the context of children, I am somewhat concerned about the HIQA report on access to social workers by children who are at risk in the Cork region.  HIQA issued a report that was carried out last October which revealed that approximately 1,000 referrals are waiting for a social worker to be assigned.  I am involved in a facility which has 45 children who have dropped out of the education system and we only receive a total of &euro;47,500 from the Department of Education and Skills.  We fall between two stools where, on the one hand, the Department of Children and Youth Affairs states it is not its responsibility but, on the other, the Department of Education and Skills states it is not its responsibility.  We must deal with the situation.  The response from Tusla this morning was to the effect that it is currently recruiting an extra 193 social workers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M00800"><p>That is nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M00900"><p>That is something which must be expedited and addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M01000"><p>The Government should be ashamed of itself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M01100"><p>We cannot ignore the HIQA report.  I would welcome a statement from the Minister in that regard and to ensure that a timeline is put in place for when the recruitment will be completed in order that the existing 1,000 referrals can be addressed.</p> <p>In fairness to Tusla, it has outlined that priority cases are being addressed, in the sense that the children most at risk are dealt with immediately, but that does not deal with the backlog of referrals that need to be urgently reviewed.  It is important that a timeline is put in place for the appointment of social workers and that an adequate number is recruited especially in the Cork region.  I would welcome a statement from the Minister on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M01200"><p>I second the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by my leader, Senator Darragh O'Brien.  I concur with my colleague, Senator Denis Landy, who quoted what the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, stated recently on town councils.  I welcome the conversion of the Minister, Deputy Howlin, and the Labour Party, although not all members of the Labour Party, because Senator Landy was an advocate for the retention of town councils in this Chamber, as were many colleagues on this side of the House also.  I would like to see those comments put into legislation for the next local government elections.  People are only now beginning to realise the result of the loss of town councillors to their towns as they have nobody to make representations on their behalf.  That has imposed a heavy workload on the reduced number of county councillors who have been elected to represent towns in addition to the wider catchment areas.  I very much welcome the Minister's comments, even though it is a case of closing the stable door after the horse has bolted.</p> <p>I wish to briefly comment on and commend the Seanad Public Consultation Committee on its hearing last Monday on farm safety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M01300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M01400"><p>I was present for the entire four and a half hours, as were many Members on the other side of the House, and indeed the Leader.  It was an excellent opportunity for 14 different organisations to outline the concerns and proposals they have on farm safety.  I wish to mention one young man in particular from County Monaghan, a neighbouring county of my own, Patrick Duffy, who made an excellent presentation and has proposals for the education sector by way of a board game he has developed.  It was an excellent opportunity for the general public to come to their Chamber and outline to their representatives in this House concerns on farm safety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M01500"><p>I add my voice to those who have welcomed the announcement by the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, yesterday on people with Down's syndrome.  That is something I never agreed with from the very beginning and many of my colleagues felt the same.  We always felt what happened was unjust and wrong.  That is the reason we have continually lobbied the Minister to make provision in schools for children with Down's syndrome.  Thankfully, she has listened and moved in the right direction.  We could do with some more hours but it is a step in the right direction.</p> <p>Another issue that has come to my attention is a funding scheme under the community and voluntary support section of the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, which is administered by Pobal.  Last year, the support scheme for national organisations omitted 23 health and disability organisations from funding under the scheme.  Bridging funding was put in place but it will expire in June of this year.  At present, the organisations do not know where they stand and if they will receive funding for the coming year.  Could the Leader organise a debate in the House with the Minister so that we can get clarification for the organisations in order that they will know where they stand?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" speakername="James Heffernan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#M01600"><p>I echo the comments made by Senator Landy.  Today, we have witnessed the retirement of one of the greats of Irish sport.  Nobody in any code will match the feats of Henry Shefflin.  It is incumbent on the State to devise an honours system for people who have represented their counties or country at the highest level of sport.  Henry Shefflin is a legendary figure.  He won the player of the year award three times.  He has ten all-star awards and all-Ireland medals to beat the band.  I do not think he will be matched.  While he was a fantastically gifted and skilful player, he did break a few hurleys along the way.</p> <p>That leads me to calling for a debate on the situation regarding the ash dieback disease, which is a matter I raised in the Seanad many moons ago with a previous Minister.  Neither the Government nor clubs and county organisations grasp the scale of the ash dieback disease and the potential it has for hurleys, hurley makers and the native ash species.  I am aware of some hurley makers who are importing ash from Scandinavia.  Ash dieback has become a major problem across Europe.  I know of other hurley makers as well who manufacture hurleys in Poland.  I congratulate the Minister of State, Deputy Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, on organising the Polska&Eacute;ire festival this week, which was a tremendous success in showing solidarity and celebrating the positive impact Polish people have had on Irish society.  Last night, I was very happy to take part in a football match involving an Oireachtas selection against a Polish selection.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00100"><p>I am sure the Senator was.  Senator Gilroy also played.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00200"><p>We heard Senator Heffernan did it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" speakername="James Heffernan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00300"><p>It was not me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00400"><p>A group from St. Patrick's De La Salle school in Kilkenny is in the Gallery.  The school principal, Brian Cody, was to be here today but is unavailable for obvious reasons.  I will let Senator O'Neill explain why and make a comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00500"><p>I would like to be associated with the Leas-Chathaoirleach's remarks welcoming St. Patrick's De La Salle.  I thank Senators Landy and Heffernan for their kind comments about Henry Shefflin.  It is great to see a Tipperary man acknowledging a Kilkenny man at last.  Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" speakername="Denis Landy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00600"><p>Absolutely.  100%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00700"><p>Hopefully, some of these young people will don the black and amber at a future date.  Henry Shefflin is a role model for any young person in Ireland through his longevity and example.  Any person should model himself or herself on what he has achieved in sport.  It is not about whether one is good at sport but dedication in one's life to one's work and interests.  I encourage everybody to do as much as possible and I congratulate Henry Shefflin on what has been a magnificent career in the GAA.</p> <p>Although the newspapers have reported that the price of crude oil had decreased to $50 per barrel, the oil companies said they could not reduce prices because they had forward bought.  However, in the past three weeks, the price of petrol and diesel has increased by almost 20 cent per litre because the euro has weakened against the dollar.  This is a consumer affairs issue and I do not know what Department it comes under, but I would like a debate on how consumers are being affected by this and other consumer issues.  What is happening in the oil industry is a rip-off.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00800"><p>As a proud Cork man, I confess that while Henry Shefflin often broke our hearts, he is probably one of the finest sports people the country has ever seen.  I wish him luck in retirement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N00900"><p>While I did not hear Senator Landy's observation on town councils and local government, I heard Senator Wilson's intervention.  Following reported comments at the Labour Party conference, or perhaps on the margins of the conference, by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Brendan Howlin, and the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, that there was a possibility that town councils would be reintroduced, I had a Commencement debate here on 5 March.  Although the Minister, Deputy Alan Kelly, was unable to attend, the Minister of State, Deputy Tom Hayes, who replied on his behalf, made it very clear that there are no plans in place to reverse the decision to abolish town councils.  His script indicated that a review might be put in place, and I would welcome such a review.  However, we would not want to put the cart before the horse.  All of those here who have worked very closely with local authorities at county and sub-county level recognise that the new structures are posing major challenges, some of which cannot be met, because some of the areas are so big that the concept of "local" has been removed from local government.  I ask the Minister to establish the review at the earliest possible date.  No Minister or Government should be afraid to concede that it probably was a mistake to abolish the town councils in the format in which it happened.</p> <p>The Leader might facilitate a debate here on local government structures.  While local government can very much be the driving force in the regeneration of our towns and villages in rural Ireland, the structures, as newly constituted, may not be ideal.  While I hear from some councils that the municipal districts are working, other councillors are serving municipal districts 40 to 80 miles long, and the concept of local representation has disappeared.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach knows this from his area, west Cork.  I would like to discuss local government structures and see if they need tweaking.  They will need major reform.  In towns where urban councils had worked well, the local population is already beginning to notice the difference.  Although some of the town councils did not cover themselves in glory, others worked very effectively and the baby has been thrown out with the bath water.  Although we are only 12 months from the local elections, it is time to examine how we can plan for the best future for local government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N01000"><p>I welcome yesterday evening's announcement by the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, that the Government has agreed to allocate additional resources to schools to support children with Down's syndrome who are not already being supported through the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, annual allocation process.  I was delighted with yesterday's announcement.  Like many of my colleagues, I have long pushed for support to be available to children who are not provided for.  These interim allocations will provide an additional 2.5 hours per week, pending the introduction of the new allocation model for children with special educational needs.  I hope the interim measures and the introduction of the new allocation model will provide the necessary support and assistance more fairly for children with Down's syndrome.  I regret that they have had to go through so many hoops to reach the decision.  I hope the new model will be announced very soon.  It is going through a pilot scheme.  I hope clarity will be brought on further additional hours for children with Down's syndrome.</p> <p>I would like to highlight the Hope Foundation's SHE IS campaign, which was launched earlier this month.  The campaign aims to fight gender discrimination and demonstrate solidarity on a global basis.  Powerful women across Ireland have lent their voices to the campaign to highlight the gender imbalance in India and around the world.  We have progressed by leaps and bounds in recent decades to rectify the gender imbalances that existed in many countries.  Unfortunately, this task will require our vigilance and attention for some time to come.  Countries such as India remain dangerous places in the 21st century.  In 2012, the United Nations cited India as the most dangerous place in the world in which to be born a girl.  It is upsetting to hear that 47% of girls in India are married before they reach the age of 18.  More than 75,000 people have engaged with the Hope Foundation's SHE IS campaign and I urge my Oireachtas colleagues to support the campaign and bring further awareness to the serious gender inequality in developing countries.  We have an opportunity and a platform to generate a discussion and highlight these important issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N01100"><p>I raise the issue of water charges and Irish Water.  Over recent days, we found out that very important meetings took place between very senior Irish Water staff and the then Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Phil Hogan, at which no minutes were taken, which seems incredible given the major issues that were being discussed.  Sinn F&eacute;in has called for an Oireachtas inquiry into the fact that these minutes were not taken.  For many people, Irish Water has become synonymous with everything that is wrong with the Government.  It has involved cronyism, political manipulation of State boards and threats against people who cannot afford to pay.  It is another charge and tax on struggling families.  Over the weekend, we heard that there were no records or minutes of a meeting that took place between the former Minister and the chairman of Bord G&aacute;is, at which very important issues were discussed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N01200"><p>How many meetings has Sinn F&eacute;in held?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#N01300"><p>Many people would be very surprised at this and given the level of crisis the Government has got itself into as a result of the introduction of water charges and the establishment of Irish Water, I am very surprised that the minutes of those meetings were not taken or that they are not available to the public and public representatives.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Cullinane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2357"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2357&amp;amp;pid=DavidCullinane&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Again, this is another reason to scrap Irish Water in its current form, to scrap water charges and to go back to the drawing board.  I do not think the Government has the confidence and support of the majority of citizens in this State.  Yesterday, it seemed to be stumbling from one crisis to the next on this issue.  Given the revelation that no records of certain meetings exist, the matter merits statements in this House on Irish Water and water services and I again call for this debate in the near future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#O00200"><p>I agree wholeheartedly with the comments of Senator Wilson regarding the meeting of the Seanad Public Consultation Committee that was held on Monday under the chairmanship of the Leas-Chathaoirleach.  It was most useful, timely and comprehensive.  All the submissions were extremely worthwhile and the contributions on the day were excellent.  I agree with the Leas-Chathaoirleach in singling out the young man from Ballybay who was brilliant.  I am very hopeful for the future.  Many very useful proposals came forward that day which, no doubt, will be incorporated in the report.  I believe it is the Leader's intention that we will have the opportunity for a debate in this House when the report is published.  The Leader might indicate when it is hoped this will be available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#O00300"><p>I support Senator van Turnhout's welcome of the announcement by the director of Diageo, David Smith, that he will be stepping down from the board of the Stop Out-of-Control Drinking campaign.  I mirror the Senator's words.  The drinks industry has no place in effecting attitudes in schools or public attitudes on alcohol.  This applies overall not just to the Stop Out-of-Control Drinking campaign but any future work we do around this area.  We will be working on this area shortly.</p><p>I mirror the previous comments of Senators in respect of the welcome announcement by the Minister of Education and Skills this morning that 2.5 hours will be given to children with Down's syndrome.  Again, I struggle with the thought of children with Down's syndrome being assessed or doing examinations to be accepted, because a child either has it or not.  I know there are different levels of it.  I look forward to 2.5 hours becoming four or 4.5 hours, which are the sort of hours we should be looking at.  We have achieved the minimum at the moment.</p><p>I would like us to think about having a debate on vending machines in schools.  Most Senators might have read an article by Kevin Dundon, the celebrity chef, in last week's edition of the <i>Sunday Independent.  </i>I am talking about secondary schools, the education of our young people and their health and well-being, both mental and physical.  We are talking about obesity and the future health of our youth.  The HSE said it would welcome a ban on junk food in schools.  However, a spokesperson for the HSE said it was a matter for the Department of Education and Skills.  In the article, Mr. Dundon said: <blockquote>Every school is almost a culprit of vending machines but I think there are other ways that schools can acquire revenue.  It's not only causing overweight and obesity problems but it's giving hardship to teachers because sugar makes children hyper, more aggressive, lessens their ability to concentrate and makes them more disruptive in class.</blockquote>When I was thinking about speaking this morning, I smiled to myself and thought that Senators should see how they would get on if they tried attending a committee meeting for three hours and then debating here for four hours after having a bottle of Coca-Cola and a couple of sugary bars.  They would have a headache, their blood sugar levels would be on the ground and they would be cross and useless because their brains would be run down.  That is what we are doing to our people.  This is about education.  It is not about a lot of money because it is far easier to make a child a healthier lunch than to give them money to go to the local delicatessen or, worse, stick it in a vending machine.  We need the Minister for Education and Skills to come to the House to talk about this because it is small beer and a no-brainer.  We are allowing our young people to get into terrible habits early on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#O00400"><p>I call Senator Kelly.  My apologies as he should have been called earlier but he was hiding down there so I did not spot him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#O00500"><p>I support Senator Heffernan's point about the sustainability of rural post offices.  I come from a family of three generations that have run a small post office in rural Ireland.  I have also seen the letters that are being sent out by the Department of Social Protection encouraging people to move their pensions and social welfare payments from the post office to the banks for the purposes of so-called convenience when the reality is that it is only in order that it can get greater access to people's bank accounts.</p> <p>We talk a lot in this House about the decline in rural Ireland and tend continually to blame the Government.  Rural Ireland to some degree is in the hands of the people living there.  Where there is a small post office, there is invariably a small shop.  The postmaster-cum-shopkeeper depends on the people of rural Ireland using their shop for convenience purposes such as getting a loaf of bread, the pint of milk and a few groceries.  I know it is very difficult to expect people not to go to Aldi, Tesco and Lidl but if they only contributed a small bit to the rural shop with the rural post office, they would be more viable.  People should not be threatened by letters that come from the Department of Social Protection telling them to do what I have just described, and they should support the local post office.  That will ensure its viability in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#O00600"><p>The announcement by the Minister for Education and Skills of extra resources for children with so-called mild Down's syndrome is very welcome, as others have said.  There are many situations where children have disabilities that call on our special care and attention.  It is fair to say that children with Down's syndrome in particular have a very special place in the hearts of Irish people and this country given the great memories we have of the Special Olympics.  In respect of the ongoing debate about the needs of children with disabilities, people in Ireland want this country to set a standard in the resources it provides.  Like others, I note that what has been offered is also mild in that it is just 2.5 hours of resource teaching per week per child.  The chief executive of Down Syndrome Ireland, Pat Clarke, said that regardless of the level of severity of Down's syndrome, what is needed is between five and eight resource hours.  I hope that this does not act as a delaying tactic in respect of the introduction of a new teaching resource model.  There is concern as people know about the need for a medical diagnosis before resources can be allocated.  I hope this bit of good news does not delay the greater amount of good news that is needed in terms of the provision made not just for children with Down's syndrome but others.</p> <p>I note the announcement this morning from the Broadcasting Authority of Ireland, BAI, that its new guidelines on the coverage of the forthcoming referenda are in force as of today.  Along with a number of colleagues from the Houses of the Oireachtas, I attended a very good briefing by the authority this morning.  It is clear that it is very intent on encouraging the broadcast media to ensure a fair playing field in the forthcoming referenda debates.  Much more credit is due to the former MEP, Patricia McKenna, and Anthony Coughlan for bringing their court cases which more than anything else have brought a measure of respect for balance into the way the media deal with referenda and elections.  From my engagement with the BAI this morning and in respect of broadcasters who up to now have been involved in some very soft-focus presentations of lifestyle issues in a way that really is intended to generate public sympathy for one side of the argument, it is not clear whether the BAI has the teeth to deal with that kind of subtle bias that continues to be a part of our media's coverage of various social issues.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is incumbent on all of us in the Oireachtas to ensure that the debate will be fair.  We must call out anyone in the media, particularly tax-funded broadcasters, who in any way abuse their position so as to advance one side or the other in the forthcoming referendum.  It is really important that issues are not pushed down people's throats.  It is really important that every voter is equally respected and that people are well served by their broadcast and print media in reaching an informed decision.  We must have a debate in which all sides of the argument are properly ventilated and there is equal respect for all views.  Plus, there must be no subtle or unsubtle pushing of agendas by journalists.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P00200"><p>As a proud Galway hurling supporter, I join with colleagues here in congratulating and wishing every good luck and success to Henry Shefflin, who has announced his retirement.  He broke our hearts on many occasions and we have all marvelled at his amazing skills.  We should thank him for the amount of enjoyment that he brought to so many people during his long and illustrious sporting career.</p> <p>I welcome the announcement made yesterday by the Minister for Education and Skills of additional resource teacher support for children with Down's syndrome.  The economy is beginning to pick up and more resources are becoming available.  I hope that those resources will be targeted at children with special needs and people with disabilities.  It is wrong that parents and service providers have had so little certainty down through the years and have had to constantly fight for the minimum resources.  I urge the Government to ensure that as resources become available they are targeted at people with special needs.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to organise a debate in the near future on the excessive variable mortgage rates charged by Irish banks.  The matter has been mentioned in this House before.  We should invite the Minister of State or Minister for Finance here to discuss the matter.  It is one of the biggest issues facing Irish consumers, particularly young people trying to organise a mortgage to buy their first home.  Variable interest rates are 1.79% higher than the eurozone average, which means Irish consumers are paying &euro;1.2 billion more than they should, representing an overpayment of &euro;3,300 per annum or &euro;275 per month.  We must ask ourselves why a Belgian or German borrower can get a long-term fixed-rate mortgage at 3% while an Irish person trying to organise a variable-rate mortgage must pay 4.5%.  As we know, all eurozone banks are subject to the same refinancing rate of 0.55%.  This matter needs to be inquired about.  Mr. Brian Hayes, MEP, has highlighted the fact that the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission has refused to investigate the matter.  What more significant issue faces Irish consumers than the cost of banking?  I call on the agency to reconsider its position and ask it to investigate why Irish banks charge so much more than their eurozone counterparts.   We should also have a full, frank and open discussion with the Minister for Finance on the matter in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P00300"><p>I want to raise the issue of the dramatic cuts being made to Leader funding.  When the European multiannual financial framework and CAP reform package were passed, the Taoiseach and the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine could not wait to tell us that it was a great deal for Ireland and Europe at the time.  The fruits of that rotten, disastrous deal that this Government negotiated with Europe are now apparent.  It is proposed to cut Leader funding for County Meath by 46%.  Leader money was used to fund festivals and many community halls and centres throughout my county, but that funding has been cut in half, which is disastrous.  Shame on Government representatives who have issued press releases the length and breadth of this country welcoming this funding.  The announcement about Leader funding means devastation for many rural groups, communities, festivals, parish centres and community halls that depend on this money.  They depend very badly on Leader funding, and many groups had hoped to avail of it.  This rotten deal was signed by the Taoiseach and the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Simon Coveney.  They could not wait to have tea in the parlour in Germany and in the offices in Brussels.  Their view was that any deal would do.  They did not fight for us hard enough and the cut in funding is the result.  My county will now receive only half the money, and in some counties like Cork there has been a cut of 72%.  That is the reality.  That is the result of the disastrous, polite and too-respectful negotiations that took place in Europe.  When this Government came to power it was mostly concerned about pleasing Angela Merkel and their European counterparts instead of fighting hard for this country.  They have failed to fight hard, and the result is now to be seen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P00400"><p>I wholeheartedly support Senator Mary Ann O'Brien's call to ban vending machines.  I have highlighted the matter on numerous occasions in the past.  I find it hard to believe, in a country in which one in four children are either overweight or obese, that the <i>status quo</i>is that we have vending machines laden with sweets in schools.  They have the potential to create bad habits for children at an early age which they will continue throughout their lives.  It is refreshing to hear statements on the matter from a woman who owns a chocolate company.  In a way she is down on sugar, but she appreciates that vending machines in schools are totally unacceptable.  I join her in her call for the Minister to come here to debate the issue.  What is the Government doing to alleviate childhood obesity if we are willing to leave vending machines laden with sweets in schools?  It beggars belief.</p><p>On a more positive note, I strongly welcome the new ESRI report that predicts a growth in GNP of 4.1% in 2015 and 3.5% in 2016.  According to the report, the increased level of economic activity should see unemployment rates falling to less than 10% by the end of 2015, for the first time since 2008.  The unemployment rate is envisaged to drop even further, to 8.4%, in 2016, which is 1.5% less than at the end of last month.  Moreover, it is predicted that public finances will be boosted by exports and investment, particularly on the consumer spending front.  As a result, the budget deficit should decline to 2.3% of GDP this year, with a further reduction to 0.3% in 2016.</p><p>The report also states that an estimated 16,000 new housing units will be built this year, an increase of 5,000 from 2014.  <font color="#2F2F2F">While the report paints an overall positive economic picture for the coming years, it also puts on record concerns about the mortgage lending restrictions introduced by the Central Bank.  I have previously voiced my concern about these restrictions and welcomed the subsequent amendment to the restrictions for first-time buyers.  Nevertheless, today's ESRI report warns that these restrictions may depress housing prices, which it has reported are undervalued by 10%.  Potentially, this means less incentive to construct houses and, therefore, fewer properties and rising rental rates.</font></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P00500"><p>I suggest that the Senator table a Commencement matter on the subject.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P00600"><p>The report continued:<blockquote><br /><br />The research concludes that the impact of the measures will be contractionary suggesting that, while house price inflation may be reduced due to these new measures, this reduction may come at the expense of fewer houses being supplied and fewer mortgage loans being extended.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P00700"><p>I support my colleague Senator Darragh O'Brien in his views on the issue of medical cards.  I also share his view on the Government's continued perverse policy of withdrawing medical cards from the elderly and children who are in need of assistance but who happen to be over the age of six years while giving them to the sons and daughters of millionaires who are under the age of six.  It is probably the most disgraceful policy to ever be pursued by a government.  I support the call for a debate in that regard.</p> <p>I seek a debate on medicine.  I also seek a debate on the alleged draft report on Portlaoise hospital and the attempt by the HSE to silence critics in the report and to have it edited and changed.  The matter deserves the attention of this House and probably the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Health and Children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P00800"><p>The failures happened when the Senator's party was in office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P00900"><p>Senator Daly, please, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01000"><p>Senator Burke told us HIQA had published a report, instead of saying he was disappointed.  He is like an observer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01100"><p>If Senator Burke thinks it is okay for the HSE-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01200"><p>Senator Burke can see that he has set off a bomb again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01300"><p>If Senator Colm Burke thinks it is okay for the HSE to attempt to silence HIQA, which is critical-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01400"><p>I urge Senator Daly to address the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01500"><p>If the Government is only looking for praise, then it should look to its own press department, because that is the only place it will get praised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01600"><p>I advise the Senator that it is inappropriate to talk to another Senator across the floor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01700"><p>If the Government wants critical analysis and wants HIQA to do its job, which it is doing-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01800"><p>From 2002 to 2010, Fianna F&aacute;il did nothing.  Absolutely nothing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#P01900"><p>-----then it should look at the report and have it published unedited.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q00200"><p>Senator Burke should not draw problems onto me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q00300"><p>If the report is true he does not want to hear it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q00400"><p>The Government did not promise censorship, but rather openness and transparency, which it is not providing.  This report is a crystallisation of that policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q00500"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q00600"><p>I am looking for a debate on that.  Senator Burke would like to show up and defend his-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q00700"><p>Senator Daly, you are here a long time.  It is inappropriate to address another Senator.  You speak through the Chair or not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q00800"><p>Will the Leas-Chathaoirleach ask Senator Burke-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q00900"><p>I chastised Senator Burke for interrupting you.  You do not have to engage for two minutes with the other Senator.  If you have an issue for the Leader, please address it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01000"><p>Perhaps the Leader would ask, when the debate is held on the report that is being suppressed by the HSE, that the Minister would attend the House in order that we can have a full, open and transparent debate on the contents of the unedited report.</p> <p>I pay tribute to Henry Shefflin on his retirement.  I am from a county which has not fallen to his masterful skills and can praise him fulsomely and wholly.  We never lost an all-Ireland hurling final and have a clear track record of winning one out of one.  We then retired and concentrated on football.  Maybe some counties should do the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01100"><p>I appreciate those comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01200"><p>We have won the Christy Ring cup and other competitions.  It will come as news to the Government that I want to thank and praise it and I ask the Leader to give me some indulgence in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01300"><p>The Leader has no say in it at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01400"><p>The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, who is a former Senator, will come to Kerry tomorrow and we will give him a full welcome.  He will visit the Valentia marine rescue coordination centre.  The Members opposite-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01500"><p>That is not a matter for the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01600"><p>It was a matter that was raised here many times on the Order of Business.  There were attempts by both Governments to close it.  A previous Fianna F&aacute;il Minister attempted to have it shut down and the local community and a national campaign, in which Mick O'Connell was involved-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01700"><p>The Senator is well over the time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01800"><p>We managed to keep it open.  I praise all involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q01900"><p>I assure Senator O'Brien that the system for those aged under six and over 70 will be up and running before the end of the year.  The Senator referred to fampridine yesterday.  The HSE received an application for the inclusion of fampridine in the General Medical Services and community drugs schemes.  The application was considered in line with the procedures and timescales agreed by the Department of Health and the HSE with the Irish Pharmaceutical Healthcare Association for the assessment of new medicines.  In accordance with these procedures, the National Centre for Pharmacoeconomics conducted an evaluation of fampridine and concluded that the manufacturer was unable to demonstrate sufficient effectiveness and a fair price for fampridine in the Irish health care setting.  It was unable to recommend the reimbursement of the product.  On foot of this the HSE decided that it was not in a position to add the drug to the list of reimbursable items supplied under the GMS and other community drug systems and schemes.</p> <p>It was open to the supplier to submit a new application to the HSE for the inclusion of fampridine in the community drugs schemes, incorporating new evidence which would demonstrate the cost-effectiveness of the drug by offering it at a reduced price, or both.  The revised application was received by the HSE in July 2014.  It has since engaged with the company, seeking an improved commercial offering.  These engagements have been completed and the HSE is now considering their outcome.  The HSE has also had discussions with clinical experts on this drug, the outcome of which is also being considered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q02000"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#Q02100"><p>Senator Landy and many others welcomed the extra 2.5 hours for children with Down's syndrome.  It is a step in the right direction, as many stated.  It is a first step and it is to be hoped the hours will be increased.</p> <p>Senator Landy also welcomed the agreement at Cabinet on the situation of Waterford Crystal workers.  As he correctly pointed out, it has been an anxious six-year wait for them in Waterford and the south east for the &euro;180 million pension package agreed by the Cabinet and introduced by the Minister, Deputy Burton.  A key part of the package will see lump sum payments based on time served with the company, as opposed to being linked to the Waterford Crystal staff and factory pension scheme.  This increases the lump sum costs by &euro;4 million to &euro;45 million.  Workers will get &euro;1,200 per year in pensionable company service on top of their pensions.</p> <p>As was signalled, there will also be provision for the next-of-kin of deceased workers who were originally denied entitlements when the firm and its pension fund became insolvent.  The total cost of the package will be funded through the Department of Social Protection.  The deal was hammered out after talks began in December between the trade union Unite, Government officials and the consultants Mercer, under the Labour Relations Commission chairman, Kieran Mulvey.  The settlement will bring long overdue peace of mind to the workers and their families.  It is to be hoped that the payments will begin in very early course.</p> <p>Senators Landy, Bradford and Wilson referred to town councils.  As Senator Bradford pointed out, it was stated in a reply to him a couple of weeks ago that there are no plans in place to restore town councils at this stage, but there was a possibility that a review could be initiated.  We will have to wait.</p> <p>Senators van Turnhout and Mary Ann O'Brien referred to Diageo stepping down from the Stop Out-of-Control Drinking campaign, something which was welcomed by quite a number of Members.  They also highlighted that there should be no role for drinks companies in public health matters and schools.</p> <p>Senator Naughton welcomed the recent job announcements from Apple and IDT in Galway, but also pointed out the skills deficit in some areas and the need to address that.  I will bring the matter to the attention of the Minister, Deputy Bruton, and it is to be hoped he can address it.  I also welcome the 50 Sun Life jobs announced in my city today, which will be welcomed by everybody in Waterford.</p> <p>Senator Norris raised the question of Commencement debates and the changes we have initiated.  They have been working quite well but I see his point.  We needed 12 for a quorum, which reduced to six after a short period.  Twenty-three people spoke.  People are coming in at the end of debates when they are practically over, and they drag on.  We will have to examine the situation.  We had Commencement debates and the Order of Business changed to allow people to be present for the Order of Business.  People contribute but do not remain in the Chamber.  A number of people who raise matters on the Order of Business do not have the courtesy to wait for a reply.  We have to look at ourselves when we talk about Seanad reform and the system within the House.  Senator Norris also referred to Waterford Crystal workers and made comparisons with Aer Lingus.  They are two very different matters.</p> <p>Senator Burke referred to waiting list backlogs and the need to recruit social workers.  He said a timeline should be put in place.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I agree with him and will endeavour to have the Minister come to the House to address that matter.</p><p>Senator Diarmuid Wilson raised the matter of town councils which I have addressed.  There is no doubt the workload of county councillors has increased significantly since the abolition of the town councils.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#R00200"><p>True.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#R00300"><p>That additional work is being carried out without additional resources and additional allowances for councillors.  That issue should be taken into consideration.  If it was any other walk of life there would be uproar in respect of the increased workload for councillors.  It is practically a full-time job at present.  I note the Senator's points in respect of the Seanad Public Consultation Committee and thank him for his presence.  Like some other Members, he was in attendance for the entire session.  Senator Paul Coghlan also asked a question in respect of that issue.  We would hope to have the report published within a number of weeks and to have the Minister come in for a debate on its contents and recommendations.</p> <p>Senator Marie Moloney mentioned the community and voluntary support scheme and the 23 organisations excluded last year.  I suggest she table that issue for a Commencement debate with a view to getting answers from the relevant Minister.  </p> <p>Yesterday, Senator James Heffernan raised the matter of rural post offices and the letter that issued to a customer from the Department of Social Protection.  I have secured a debate, as requested by the Senator, for Thursday, 2 April 2015, immediately following the Order of Business, where we can discuss the letter that issued in respect of paying people's pensions into banks and so on.  The Senator also raised the issue of ash dieback disease.  We had a debate on the issue about two years ago but I will investigate the possibility of having another debate on that matter.  The Senator welcomed the Polska&Eacute;ire festival which was held on Sunday last and was a great success.  I think solidarity will be suspended on Sunday next when we play Poland in the European Cup game.</p> <p>Senator Pat O'Neill and other Senators mentioned Henry Shefflin's retirement.  Being from Mullinavat, which is close to my own city, he was certainly a thorn in our side for many years.  We all wish him well in his retirement.  He is a wonderful sportsman.</p> <p>Senator O'Neill expressed concern at the price of petrol and diesel and asked that the issue be examined by consumer affairs and that the Minister be invited here to discuss the matter.  I will try to arrange that debate.</p> <p>Senator Paul Bradford raised the issue of town councils and local government structures.  I am sure we will have further debates on that issue.</p> <p>Senator Mary Moran highlighted the Hope Foundation's campaign on gender equality, called SHE IS.  It is to be recommended.</p> <p>Senator David Cullinane raised the matter of Irish Water and Bord G&aacute;is.  That matter was raised by Senator Gerard P. Craughwell yesterday and responded to.  On the issue of whether the Government has the confidence and support of the majority of citizens in the State, that issue will be decided by the people of the State next year in a general election, a State which the party of which the Senator is a member refused to recognise for many years until recently.</p> <p>Senator Paul Coghlan raised the issue of farm safety.  I have outlined when that report will come before the House.  </p> <p>Senators Mary Ann O'Brien and Catherine Noone raised the matter of vending machines and the whole question of overweight and obesity.  I hope Members will not take up Senator O'Brien's suggestion of a sugar fix before the Order of Business; they are bad enough already.  I take the point in respect of vending machines.</p> <p>Senator John Kelly raised the issue of rural post offices.  As I have said, the letter from the Department of Social Protection will be dealt with on 2 April 2015.</p> <p>Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen raised the issue of balance during the referendum campaign.  I can assure him there will be fairness and balance in this House and that is all I can answer for.  </p> <p>Senator Michael Mullins highlighted the variable mortgage rates being charged by Irish banks and the excessive charges at the expense of the consumer.  I will endeavour to have the Minister for Finance come to the House to address that matter and the whole area of banking.  A debate on that matter is overdue.</p> <p>Senator Thomas Byrne mentioned the cuts to Leader funding.  I accept there have been cuts to Leader funding but increased funding has been provided for the LEOs throughout the length and breadth of the country and much more money will be coming through local authorities.  </p> <p>Senator Catherine Noone raised the ESRI report and the good news on employment and the economy.  </p> <p>Senator Mark Daly raised the issue of medical cards, and called for a debate on the HIQA report which he said is being suppressed by the HSE.  The latter matter was raised by Senator Whelan yesterday to which I gave a comprehensive reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#R00400"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That a one hour debate with the Minister for Health to update the House on the proposals to provide free GP care to those under six years and over 70 years of age be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#R00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.155/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#R00600"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 13; Nl, 24.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paschal Mooney and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.155/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-03-25" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#R00600">
            <divisioncount ayes="13" noes="24" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="no">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.155/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#R00600"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.156" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.158" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#T00400">An Bille um an gCeathr&uacute; Leas&uacute; is Tr&iacute;ocha ar an mBunreacht (Comhionannas P&oacute;sta) 2015: An Dara C&eacute;im - Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution (Marriage Equality) Bill 2015: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#T00450"><p>We move on to the Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution (Marriage Equality) Bill 2015 - Second Stage, and No. 2, motion pursuant to section 23 of the Referendum Act 1994 in regard to the proposal to amend the Constitution which is contained in the Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution (Marriage Equality) Bill 2015, will be debated in conjunction with Second Stage of the Bill but will not be moved until Fifth Stage is concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.160" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Tairgeadh an cheist: "Go l&eacute;ifear an Bille an Dara hUair anois."</p><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#T00600"><p>I am honoured to introduce the Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution (Marriage Equality) Bill 2015 into Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  The Bill sets out the proposed constitutional amendment on the issue of marriage equality to be put to the people in the referendum on 22 May 2015.  If the referendum is approved by the people, couples will have a right to marry without distinction as to their sex.</p> <p>The Government agreed on 5 November 2013 that a referendum should be held in the first half of 2015 on the question of enabling same-sex couples to marry.  The Government's decision was in response to the report of the Constitutional Convention.  The convention's third report, "Amending the Constitution to provide for same-sex marriage", issued in June 2013, recommended that an amendment be made to the Constitution to provide for same-sex marriage.  Obviously, I would like to acknowledge the contribution to these deliberations of the Senators who were members of the convention.</p> <p>The Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution (Marriage Equality) Bill 2015 was published on 21 January 2015 following Government agreement on the proposed wording.  The Government has since agreed, on 3 March 2015, the general scheme of the marriage Bill 2015, which sets out the legislative changes that will be undertaken if the referendum is passed by the people.  That scheme was circulated by me to Senators on 9 March 2015.  The proposals provided for in the general scheme are, of course, conditional on the decision of the electorate on the referendum.</p> <p>The Thirty-fourth Amendment of the Constitution (Marriage Equality) Bill 2015 provides that, if the referendum is passed, a new section will be inserted after section 3 of Article 41 of the Constitution.  That section, Article 41.4, if approved by the people, will contain the following wording: "Marriage may be contracted in accordance with law by two persons without distinction as to their sex."  No other amendments would arise in respect of Article 41.  The wording is intended to give a right to marry to couples without distinction as to their sex.  If the wording is approved by the people, there will be a corresponding obligation and requirement on the State to respect and vindicate that right in its legislation.  Therefore, it would not be open to the State to maintain in being legislation which prohibits the marriage of same-sex couples.  Legislation would have to be enacted to enable marriages to take place between same-sex couples.</p> <p>I propose to outline the rationale behind the wording proposed for the thirty-fourth amendment.  The first element of the wording, "Marriage may be contracted," draws on the precedent of Article 41, which recognises marriage as an institution.  The wording confirms that the right being proposed in the constitutional amendment relates to the issue of access to the institution of marriage.  The decision to use the term "contracted" is for the following reasons.  It is the term already used in Article 41.3 in regard to marriage.  Furthermore, the term confirms that what is at issue is civil marriage, which is a contract between two persons in the eyes of the State.  The phrase "in accordance with law" has been included in the proposed wording to confirm that marriage would continue, as at present, to be regulated by statute and by common law.  The phrase "without distinction as to their sex" reflects language already used in Article 16 of the Constitution.  Articles 16.1.1&deg; and 16.1.2&deg; use the phrase "without distinction of sex" with regard to the eligibility of citizens for membership of the D&aacute;il and the right of every citizen to vote for members of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  The wording proposed for the thirty-fourth amendment builds on the language of that precedent to provide for a couple, regardless of their sex, to be eligible to marry.</p> <p>There has been some commentary on the decision to use the term "sex" rather than "gender" in the wording of the proposed amendment.  The reason the term "sex" has been used is that it is the term already used in the Constitution.  Furthermore, the barriers which prevent persons from marrying under Irish law are impediments relating to a person's sex rather than to a person's gender.</p> <p>The Irish wording of the amendment was changed on Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il in the interests of further clarity.  The view of the Oireachtas translation service and of the other language experts that I consulted was that the concerns expressed regarding the proposed wording were unfounded.  However, the Government considered it important that the electorate should have absolute confidence in the wording proposed for the amendment in both English and Irish.  As a result, the Government decided to propose a more literal translation of the English wording.  The amended wording, as agreed on Committee Stage in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and based on the recommendation of the Oireachtas translation service, is as follows: "F&eacute;adfaidh beirt, gan beann ar a ngn&eacute;as, conradh p&oacute;sta a dh&eacute;anamh de r&eacute;ir dl&iacute;."  This wording essentially can be translated into English as: "Two persons, regardless of their sex, can contract a marriage in accordance with law".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#T00700"><p>Bravo.  Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015032500002#T00800"><p>What does the proposed constitutional amendment seek to achieve?  What are the people being asked to decide in the referendum on 22 May?  The people will be asked to decide upon a simple question, namely, who should have the right to marry in the eyes of the State.  The answer to that question will determine whether or not the institution of marriage should be opened to same-sex couples on the same basis as opposite-sex couples.  The people will decide if all couples who wish to marry should be able to do so.  They will determine whether or not marriage should be reserved for heterosexual couples.  The people will have the opportunity to decide whether the Constitution should contain a right to marriage equality.</p> <p>Who are the same-sex couples that will be affected by the answer to these questions?  They are our children, our grandchildren, our siblings, our friends, our colleagues, our neighbours and our fellow citizens.  Many waited years to gain the public recognition of their relationships represented by civil partnerships.  Many are now waiting again and hoping to be in a position soon to make the deepest commitment to a life partner, namely, to be able to marry him or her.</p> <p>Marriage is important to us as a society.  It is the foundation of many of our families.  It is the public expression of a profound commitment to another human being.  The referendum, if passed, would not affect existing marriages in any way.  Neither would it have any impact on heterosexual marriages into the future.  The proposed constitutional amendment would not redefine marriage.  What the amendment would do, if approved by the people, would be to enable an additional group of people - same-sex couples who cannot marry at present - to have the right to marry.  The existing structure underpinning civil marriage would remain in place.  Marriages would continue to be registered in the same manner as at present.  The same conditions would continue to apply.  Each person entering a marriage, for instance, would have, as at present, to give full, free and informed consent.  The legal consequences accruing for the couple would be the same for a same-sex married couple as for a heterosexual couple.  Marriage and the family would continue to be protected, as they are at present, by Article 41 of the Constitution.</p> <p>Furthermore, the proposed constitutional amendment would not have any impact on religious marriage, as the amendment relates exclusively to the issue of civil marriage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-03-25a.164" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional text to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>