<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#A00200"><p>I have notice from Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br /><br />The need for the Minister for Health to clarify what is being done by his Department with regard to concerns about the lack of a prompt and efficient ambulance service in the Leenane area of Connemara.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to confirm that the Department of Health will work with the HSE to identify a suitable site for a new hospital in Cork which has been recommended in a report submitted by the south reconfiguration board of the HSE.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Higgins of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources to explore additional funding streams for the roll-out of natural gas in areas of strategic importance.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to comment on an application for an employment permit for a start-up company in County Clare, details supplied.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh and Colm Burke and they will be taken now.  Senators Lorraine Higgins and Martin Conway have withdrawn the Commencement matters which I had selected for discussion.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#A00400">Ambulance Service Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#A00500"><p>T&aacute;im ag ard&uacute; ceiste ar maidin a bhaineann leis an tseirbh&iacute;s otharcharr i gConamara thuaidh.  I raise the issue of the ambulance service in north Connemara, in particular in the Leenane, Maam, Kylemore, Renvyle and Clifden areas.  An ambulance crisis steering group was set up in the area due to the concerns that exist and a number of meetings have been held with elected representatives.  The group has given two examples to underline the seriousness of the situation.  One case related to a young mother who was waiting for more than two hours for an ambulance while haemorrhaging badly a few days after giving birth.  A second case related to a serious cardiac patient who presented himself to the doctor at 2.30 p.m. with chest pains.  The doctor called an ambulance and it arrived at 4.50 p.m., and the man eventually arrived at the hospital at 6.45 p.m.  The response from the National Ambulance Service at a meeting was that the resources are not available to put a workable solution in place.</p> <p>We feel that is totally unacceptable.  The group believes the National Ambulance Service, NAS, the Department of Health and the Government have a duty of care towards people and patients in rural areas such as north-west Connemara as much as to people living in other rural areas.  We all fully understand that living in rural areas creates delays but we take issue with the often two to three-hour delays in waiting for ambulances to arrive to tend to patients.  Their major concern is the waiting time between the call for an ambulance to attend and the arrival of the ambulance at the scene.  Although the group has made numerous requests under the Freedom of Information Act for ambulance response times in the area, it appears the National Ambulance Service is reluctant to give the information.  That is something I might follow up with the Minister.</p> <p>A follow-up meeting was held with the National Ambulance Service at which various issues were raised and options were explored.  It was put to the National Ambulance Service that the current service is totally inadequate with it regularly being the case that people are waiting more than two hours for an ambulance to arrive.  That is the norm rather than the exception.  In addition, people who are very ill then face a 50-mile or 60-mile journey.  We appreciate that air ambulances are available but NAS helicopters cannot fly in darkness and while the Coastguard helicopters are available, they have only limited use.  Both types of helicopter need areas in which they can land safely and an ambulance to transfer a patient to the helicopter, which gives rise to issues concerning that particular option.  I noted the case of a man who was waiting for a very long time.</p> <p>The ambulance crisis steering group has put forward a number of suggestions.  There is a Red Cross ambulance in the area and it has been suggested that a rapid response unit could be developed with two fully qualified and salaried paramedics being put in place to cover the area, but that would require the support of the Red Cross whose ambulance was purchased through fund-raising activities by the local community.  Such an approach would have to work in conjunction with the National Ambulance Service.  To date, the National Ambulance Service has not been open to such an option on the basis that the Red Cross ambulance is not up to the same standard as an NAS ambulance.  People on the ground however say they would prefer a Red Cross ambulance than no ambulance or an ambulance that would take two hours to get to them.  This is a very serious issue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2363"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2363&amp;amp;pid=TrevorOClochartaigh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a remote area of north Connemara.  We appreciate resources are tight, but the length of time people must wait for the ambulance service to get to them is completely unacceptable.  They need a better response.  We need to hear the Government response to this and how it intends to tackle this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#B00200"><p>I thank Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh for raising this issue.  On behalf of the Minister for Health, Deputy Varadkar, I am pleased to outline to the House current developments in pre-hospital services, nationally and in Connemara.  Before doing so, I apologise on behalf of the Minister for his absence.  On behalf of the Government, he is attending a funeral linked to the tragic events in California.</p> <p>The national ambulance service, NAS, is working to ensure high quality and timely emergency pre-hospital care, using all available resources as effectively and efficiently as possible.  As with any pre-hospital service, development and modernisation is a continuous process as technology and clinical standards change.  A significant and ongoing reform programme has been under way in recent years and it is important to acknowledge the progress being made.  The single national control system, with control centres in Dublin and Ballyshannon, is now almost fully operational and is improving control and dispatch performance.</p> <p>The NAS continues to develop the intermediate care service, ICS, which transports non-emergency patients between facilities, allowing emergency vehicles to focus on emergency calls.  The ICS now carries three quarters of non-emergency work.  We are also moving to more efficient on-duty rostering and developing a national rostering system.  The model of service delivery is changing.  The NAS is moving away from the care model where ambulance services are provided only locally from a fixed ambulance base in that area.  It is moving to strategic deployment, with resources used across a region, so that if demand increases in one area, other resources can provide cover as required.</p> <p>Enhancements to the ambulance service in the west include the introduction earlier this year of 24/7 services in Tuam in Galway and Mulranny in Mayo.  Accordingly, in addition to the existing 24/7 coverage for Leenane from Clifden ambulance station, under strategic deployment the new capacity in Tuam and Mulranny stations will provide greater coverage across north Galway and west Mayo in general, including Leenane.  Also in 2015, an additional &euro;5.4 million has been provided to improve technology and clinical audit and to address service gaps, particularly in the west.  Some 50 additional paramedics are being allocated in the west this year under this process.</p> <p>The emergency aeromedical support, EAS, service  is further assisting service provision in the west.  The EAS allows swift transfer of seriously ill or injured patients from remoter areas to the most appropriate hospital.  Over 1,000 EAS missions have been completed since June 2012.  Galway, Mayo and Roscommon have the highest demand for the EAS.  However, as HIQA noted recently, no feasible increase in resources will address all of the access issues in remoter areas.  For this reason, the NAS is working with communities to develop community first responder groups, local initiatives which provide basic life support in life-threatening situations until an emergency response can arrive.  I understand that CFR groups in Connemara currently cover Spiddal, Ahascragh, Moylough, Lettermore, Maam, Leenane and Turloughmore.</p> <p>There has been ongoing investment in ambulances services and in their capacity and coverage, including in the west, in the face of some of the most stringent budgetary restrictions ever seen.  I assure the House, on behalf of the Minister, that the national ambulance service is as focused as possible on addressing and improving services in the west in 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#B00300"><p>I welcome the allocation of additional paramedics to the west but apart from that there does not seem to be much of a change in the situation and it will not assuage the worries of the people in north Connemara.  Would it be possible for the Department to make the information on ambulance response times in this area available to me so that I can pass it on to this group in order that we can undertake an analysis of how serious the situation is in the Leenane, Maam, Kylemore, Renvyle and Clifden areas?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#B00400"><p>I will pass on the Senator's request to the Minister and the Department and check whether it is possible to make the information available.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#B00500">Hospitals Building Programme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#B00600"><p>I wish to raise an issue I have raised previously in regard to identifying a site in Cork for a new hospital.  We have three main hospitals in Cork, the South Infirmary, the Mercy University Hospital and Cork University Hospital.  It is accepted that both the Mercy hospital and the South Infirmary have little space to expand to provide additional services and there is a need to identify a new site.  A group was set up in 2009-10 to work on this and it presented a report to the Minister.</p> <p>In the context of long-term planning, as we have seen in regard to the new children's hospital, which we have been talking about for over 25 years at this stage, we are still in a situation where we are only seeking planning.  I understand it will be at least 2020 by the time that hospital project is completed.  A similar situation exists in regard to this issue in Cork.  We need to work towards a long-term plan for the health service in Cork.  The population of Cork is over 526,000 and Cork is part of the regional hospital structure that includes Waterford, Kerry and South Tipperary and further afield.  However, all of the specialist services seem to focus on the Dublin region.  We need to identify areas where the existing services can be amalgamated and to work towards building a centre of excellence in the Munster region, and Cork is the obvious place for that.</p> <p>In terms of identifying a site, it does not matter whether it is in the docklands, the Blarney area or wherever, but we need long-term planning, and that will mean a plan covering a period of ten to 15 years for delivery.  It is in that context that I raise this matter, calling on the Department of Health to accept the need for a new facility in Cork over the next ten to 15 years.  The first step towards achieving that is to identify a site and we can then work from there.  I am not talking about substantial moneys being spent immediately but a proposed facility should be part of the overall plan for the health service.  It should be accepted that this is essential for the development of the health service in Cork.  I call on the Department to come on board with the HSE to identify a site and move forward on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#B00700"><p>I thank Senator Burke for raising this issue.  Again, I apologise on behalf of the Minister for Health for his absence, as he is attending the funeral of a victim of the tragedy in California.</p> <p>The Minister recently met with the chair of the non-executive advisory board for reconfiguration of acute hospital services in Cork and Kerry to receive the board's final report.  This report is the culmination of an extensive and pioneering process.  The reconfiguration of acute services in Cork and Kerry has led the way for the development of hospital groups and the safer provision of services in smaller hospitals.  Like most ground-breaking projects, it has not been an easy process but it has been the right one.  It both anticipated and reflected developing concerns about smaller hospitals around the State.</p> <p>In 2010 the report, Reconfiguration of Acute Hospital Services, Cork and Kerry: A roadmap to Develop an Integrated University Hospital Network, was published  following wide consultation.  Following the 2009 review of acute services in Cork and Kerry by Horwath and Teamwork, the roadmap provided a practical guide for developing safe and sustainable clinical services in the region.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Dara Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2320"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2320&amp;amp;pid=DaraMurphy&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The plan involved integrating acute services into one hospital across six campuses.  Complex care would be centred in larger facilities, with as much acute care as possible being provided locally.  Professor John Higgins was appointed director of reconfiguration and the advisory board, chaired by Mr. Michael O'Flynn, was established.</p><p>The process has driven unprecedented change in acute care provision in the region.  This has been achieved during extremely challenging economic times, with reduced budgets and staff numbers and increased activity levels.  A major initiative was making the South Infirmary Victoria University Hospital the State's first dedicated elective hospital, in combination with the modernisation and reorganisation of emergency facilities across Cork city from five hospitals to two.  The process is not yet complete.  Since the roadmap, the south-south west hospital group has been established, in line with the hospital groups report.  As the Senator said, the group includes acute services in Cork, Kerry, Waterford and south Tipperary.  Therefore, there is now a need to fully integrate acute services in Waterford and south Tipperary into the wider group.</p><p>The road map recommended a single elective hospital in Cork, amalgamating the Mercy University Hospital and the South Infirmary Victoria University Hospital, to be built in a modular fashion over ten to 15 years.  While the Minister acknowledges the board's recommendation, work needs to be done on assessing options and analysing the cost-benefit of any such project.  Regarding site selection, a significant amount of work needs to be done before any concrete plan emerges that would support a rational and sustainable choice of location.  The question of site selection would be a matter in the first instance for the south-south west hospital group, with input, as necessary, from HSE estates.  The Minister and his Department would not have a direct role in that regard.</p><p>Regarding capital funding and site acquisition costs, the HSE would need to consider the proposal and prioritise the project in the context of other capital requirements around the country.  The Minister and his Department would have no objection to any proposal to undertake an options appraisal for the new hospital, as well as a cost-benefit analysis, as the first steps towards assessing the viability of the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the reply and dealing with the matter in detail.  I am concerned that the Minister and the Department would not have a direct role.  The Minister is the person who develops policy.  We are discussing reconfiguring the Mercy University Hospital and the South Infirmary Victoria University Hospital, which is accepted by everybody.  However, we also need to examine the development of specialist services, in regard to which we are focusing on Dublin.  The Minister can play a part in policy development.  Not all specialist services should be located in the Dublin area.  As part of the reconfiguration, we need to consider the development of specialist services for the entire Munster region.  The Minister has a part to play in this and I ask that the matter be taken up with him, as I intend to do.  The Department can become more proactive in the matter with the HSE.  While the HSE is stating it cannot do anything because the Department has not given the go-ahead, the Department is stating it is not its problem, given that it is up to the HSE to come back to it.  The Department should indicate to the HSE that it needs to progress the matter and that it will give serious consideration to what it states.  The reply does not seem to indicate this, rather it seems to pass the matter back to the HSE.  There is a need for clarification in the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#C00300"><p>As the Senator said, the Minister is clear that, in the first instance, it is for the HSE to identify sites.  I have been involved in the issue, on which I have met the HSE and local doctors.  Contrary to the view the Senator has taken from the response, the crucial element is that the Minister and his Department have no objection to any proposal to undertake an options appraisal, which seems to be very reasonable to start the process, as well as a cost-benefit analysis.  These are obvious and realistic first steps towards assessing the viability of the proposal.  A cost-benefit analysis would almost certainly confirm the Senator's view of needs and requirements in the southern region.  Not all specialised services are to be located in the Dublin area, as the Senator suggested.  On the contrary, there is a strong commitment to the provision of services, particularly in the second most densely populated area of the State.  The Minister, in making the point that, in the first instance, it is not a matter for the Department, leaves an obvious route for local engagement for the HSE and the group in the southern region to pursue with him his support for a cost-benefit analysis and an appraisal of the options for the location of a new hospital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.20" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 10.55 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.21" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#G00200"><p>It is proposed to take No. 1, Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) Bill 2015 - Second Stage, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to be adjourned not later than 3 p.m., if not previously concluded, with contributions from group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes; No. 2, Petroleum (Exploration and Extraction) Safety Bill 2015 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 3 p.m. and to be adjourned not later than 5 p.m., if not previously concluded, with contributions from group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes; and No. 67, motion 18, to be taken at 5 p.m. and to conclude not later than 7 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#G00300"><p>I thank the Leader for outlining the business.  I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, namely that No. 19 be taken before No. 1.  Many colleagues across the House have discussed this.  No one could agree that it is right or proper that a Government agency, Tusla, has cut funding for Rape Crisis Network Ireland and is seeking to introduce quite stringent changes regarding how rape crisis centres operate.  According to what the rape crisis centres and Rape Crisis Network Ireland are saying, the agency is seeking to change the manner in which they do their job.  All of us agree that the statistics are shocking.  One in five girls and one in six boys in Ireland has been a victim of sexual abuse.  In a modern society and republic where we care about our citizens, particularly the most vulnerable and those who have suffered from sexual abuse &mdash; the statistics do not lie &mdash; it is just wrong for a Government to stand over a decision to cut the funding of Rape Crisis Network Ireland.  My motion, which I have signed on behalf of my group, along with colleagues in the Independent benches, whom I thank in this regard, will allow the Seanad to state it does not agree with the cut in funding for Rape Crisis Network Ireland.  We should speak with one voice on this.  I ask the Leader to amend the Order of Business to have No. 19 taken before No. 1 and accept the motion.  I will be pushing this to a vote.  I ask the Leader to assert the independence of the Seanad as a democratically elected arm of the Oireachtas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#G00400"><p>On a point of clarification, is the Senator referring to No. 67, motion 19?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#G00500"><p>Yes.  One would think I would get it right at this stage, having been here for four years, but I am still learning.  Every day is a schoolday.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a very serious issue and we should not stand over cuts to Rape Crisis Network Ireland.  Many Senators from across the House have put their names to this motion and I thank them for doing so.  The Leader should accept it.  </p><p>I looked back at my file and saw that I have been raising the issue of the MS drug Fampyra since February 2014.  I have been writing back and forth to the Minister for Health and to the previous Minister and have raised the issue on numerous occasions in this House, as have Senators Craughwell and Barrett.  Other Members of this House, including my colleagues, have raised it.  After 18 months or more of raising this issue, Fampyra is not available to 3,000 MS sufferers who benefit from this drug.  This is a drug that improves people's mobility and has allowed people to go back to work.  It costs approximately &euro;270 per month.  The Leader has given responses before, that had been given to him by the Department of Health saying that it was assessing the situation and the drugs company was going to send in another submission, which it has already done.  That goes back to April and May 2015.</p><p>We marked World MS Day on 27 May.  The day is about access to drugs and how we can improve the quality of life of people with MS yet the country, Government and Department do not allow 3,000 people who benefit from this drug to access it.  A man in my constituency who brought this matter to my attention is no longer working.  He is back in a wheelchair.  I have heard numerous cases.  The Minister and the HSE know all about it because people are writing to the Minister telling him that they can no longer work, drive a car or walk.  They are telling him that they can no longer do the basic things because the Minister will not allow them access to a drug that is proven to work for about one third of MS sufferers.  I again ask the Leader to use his good offices to get back in touch with the Minister, whom I e-mailed again last week and the week before.  I have been writing to him and the Department since February 2014 but have been getting nowhere.  It is not right and is bureaucracy gone mad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H00200"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H00300"><p>I will raise this issue every day from now on until this drug is released to the people who need it.  The Leader has been very fair on these matters previously so I ask him to use his good offices to get the Government to get the finger out and allow this drug to be given to people who need it to improve their quality of life.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H00400"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien said the motion on the reinstatement of funding for Rape Crisis Network Ireland has the support of many Members across the House.  I want to put on the record that I was not approached and asked to sign such a motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H00500"><p>It was circulated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H00600"><p>The issue of funding for Rape Crisis Network Ireland arose last year.  It was due to the action of this side of the House that funding was restored.  It was due to the action of a number of people, particularly Senators Bacik and van Turnhout, who made much of Rape Crisis Network Ireland and the great work it does.  If Senator O'Brien wants to achieve something for Rape Crisis Network Ireland that is fair enough but if he simply wants to position Fianna F&aacute;il as champions on the issue then that is a different matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H00700"><p>Oh please.  It was circulated to your group's leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H00800"><p>Senator Hayden without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H00900"><p>I read my e-mails.  All I can say is that Rape Crisis Network Ireland is an issue that concerns Members on every side of this House.  I want to achieve something for Rape Crisis Network Ireland, which is why I will do my best in whatever way I can.  This does not mean parading the issue in the House when I know very well that there are-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01000"><p>Is the Senator saying I should not raise it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01100"><p>I am entitled to have my say as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01200"><p>Senator Hayden without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01300"><p>Ask her to mind her language.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01400"><p>For the record, this side of the House has not been found wanting in defending Rape Crisis Network Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01500"><p>I am afraid it would not agree with you on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01600"><p>Many of my colleagues have worked very hard on behalf of Rape Crisis Network Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01700"><p>Support the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01800"><p>I will not be supporting this motion because I question the reason Senator Darragh O'Brien is doing this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H01900"><p>That is outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02000"><p>Has Senator Hayden a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02100"><p>A motion was circulated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02200"><p>Senator Hayden without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02300"><p>If you do not want to support it, do not support it so, good luck.  Do your thing.  Do whatever you want.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02400"><p>I am not the only person who did not receive it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02500"><p>Has Senator Hayden a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02600"><p>I have two questions for the Leader.  The first relates to a report today from the Central Bank which found that seven banks have failed to protect customers in mortgage arrears in a number of areas.  It is very distressing to read the findings of the report.  This matter needs to be taken further on two levels.  I would like to hear the Minister for Finance give us his views on the report and what action the Central Bank intends to take.  The Office of the Financial Services Ombudsman has been especially lacking in terms of dealing with the worries of those in mortgage arrears and has taken a very limited view of its own remit.  I would like this to be brought forward for discussion.</p> <p>I also wish to mention patients left on trolleys in the accident and emergency department in Beaumont Hospital.  The country-specific recommendations for Ireland indicated that we are spending more and getting less for our money.  There is a real issue here in terms of patients in accident and emergency departments both in terms of their health and safety and the health and safety of nurses, doctors and other members of staff who work in the sector.  Such staff must work in situations where dangerous patients are left in situations where they damage themselves and those who work in the sector.  Could I ask for a debate with the Minister for Health on this issue?  I would very much like to hear his proposals for the health sector, particularly this issue.  </p> <p>I congratulate one of our former colleagues, Eugene Regan, who has been appointed to the European Court of Justice.  He is a former Member of this House and a notable barrister and this House should pass on our congratulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02700"><p>Questions need to answered about that appointment.  The Minister should come in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02800"><p>Is the Senator seriously suggesting that he is not a fit person for that role?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H02900"><p>Absolutely.  Questions need to be answered about that.  Talk about transparency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H03000"><p>I am happy to add my name to the motion.  I did not receive the e-mail.  I have double checked and I did not receive it.  I applaud the work of Ireland's top EU civil servant, Catherine Day, who has announced her retirement from the European Commission as of the end of August.  She is an unsung hero for us as Irish citizens but also for the EU, particularly when she championed the enlargement of the EU and its role.  I congratulate and welcome Alexander Italianer who will take up the position in August.  I suggest that we invite Catherine Day to address the House.  Perhaps that could be considered-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H03100"><p>The Senator can bring that issue to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H03200"><p>I will do so.</p><p>Could we have a debate at the earliest opportunity on the Government working group report on direct provision?  It has been widely reported on in the newspapers<i>.  </i>Senators and Deputies may be the last people to receive this 360-page report.  My understanding is that it is going to Cabinet next Tuesday.  Given the work we have done on a cross-party basis on direct provision - the working group was a culmination of the work we did - could we have a debate at the earliest opportunity on this report?  </p><p>I wish to raise the issue of the Gender Recognition Bill, which is going through the D&aacute;il at the moment.  I remain concerned about the exclusion of children from the Bill.  We had a good debate in the Seanad in February.  We were told that we were on our own on that issue.  However, when the Bill went to the D&aacute;il, many Deputies joined in the call regarding the importance of ensuring that children are recognised.  We were very quick in expressing our views on the marriage equality referendum, which I was glad to applaud but we cannot forget that the people of Ireland also voted for children's rights.  The Supreme Court cleared its way for passage into the Constitution after two and a half years of legal wrangling.</p><p>This is our first opportunity to show that we understand what is meant by children's rights.  This is one area of legislation in which we should ensure that we see children as rights holders.  They should not have to wait until they are 18 to have their rights recognised in this regard.  They are rights holders.  I considered there was a clear compromise in having a interim gender recognition certificate.  It is an issue I will continue to fight for.  The Bill will come back to this House given the amendments that have been made as it goes through the D&aacute;il.  I put on the record that I will continue to fight for the children of Ireland and their families who are looking for this gender recognition certificate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#H03300"><p>I second the amendment to the Order of Business by Senator Darragh O'Brien in respect of funding cuts to Rape Crisis Network Ireland.  I do not understand where this Government is coming from.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paschal Mooney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1990"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1990&amp;amp;pid=PaschalMooney&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Why does it constantly seem to undermine NGOs that are doing an extraordinary job across the whole field of human endeavour?  It is not just about the rape crisis centres, which we are discussing this morning; it will be another agency tomorrow.  I am getting requests, as I am sure other Members are, for funding from a variety of groups, the most recent being, Women's Aid, which has had its funding cut.  What is the Government about?  Does it care about the vulnerable people in our society?  All we keep hearing about is the spin about the economy recovering.  Tell that to the victims of rape, who are going to rape crisis centres for counselling, help and other support only to be told they cannot be seen today and it might be next week because the funding has been cut and they cannot provide the services required.  I will not go on and on about this.  Shame on the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J00200"><p>If the Senator had wanted our support he should have circulated the motion to us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J00300"><p>It was circulated and I ask Senator Hayden to support it.  It is on the floor of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J00400"><p>No crossfire this morning please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J00500"><p>I am just answering a question.  It is there for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J00600"><p>I share Senator Hayden's concerns about the Central Bank report on the seven banks that are breaking the rules on how they treat people in arrears.  It is disturbing to hear that banks are continuing with legal action to repossess homes even though they had agreed a revised deal with a struggling homeowner.  Other banks are taking away Central Bank protection from mortgage customers because they did not agree to a repayment schedule over the phone.</p> <p>What was disturbing about the interview I heard this morning with a representative of the Central Bank was that no stern action appears to be planned.  The banks were to be contacted and told to correct their misdemeanours, which is very limited action and the Central Bank needs to adopt a much tougher stance on those seven banks.  They were not named and I believe they should be named and shamed.</p> <p>I welcome the announcement that the Minister for Health, Deputy Varadkar, is preparing a new campaign to get workplaces to become more active by encouraging the public sector, which employs just short of 300,000 people, to develop healthy workplace policies.  Public sector companies and agencies, which employ 15% of the total workforce, will be encouraged to make their workplace a healthier place and get staff to be more active under the new plans to involve active travel.  It will also try to get employees involved in walking, running and other activities, and exercise groups as well as promoting healthy eating options in staff canteens.  This is very welcome.</p> <p>However, I also appeal to the private sector and in particular large employers to follow this line and to start to develop healthy workplaces promoting healthy food options in canteens as well as promoting exercise, walking and cycling groups within large enterprises.  We all know the problems we have with obesity and ill health.  The more we can promote healthy opportunities in all workplaces, the better for the Exchequer.  It should also help to ease considerably the strain on the health budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J00700"><p>I join Senator Mullins in raising the seven mortgage lenders who have been found to be in breach of the code of conduct on mortgage arrears following expressions by the Central Bank of Ireland.  As we know that framework was introduced in 2011 to ensure that the banks would play ball with the almost 120,000 residential mortgage holders who are in arrears.  Despite the concerns expressed by Senator Mullins, the problem with the Government's approach is that it is all tea and sympathy when it comes to people who are in mortgage arrears but it has done precious little about putting in place policies and supports for people who are in mortgage arrears.  It has continued to allow the banks to have an absolute veto on what is happening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J00800"><p>That day is gone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J00900"><p>Here we go again with Government Ministers and Senators passing the buck to the Central Bank and others.  Of course they have a role and they have expressed clear concerns about the breach of fair process, which was the very essence of the CCMA framework in the first place.  Today <i>The Irish Times</i>reported: &quot;Lenders also continued to seek additional ad-hoc payments from borrowers on top of agreed revised repayments without formally assessing their ability to make these additional payments.&quot;</p><p>A number of weeks ago I was outside the courthouse in Waterford when more than 30 families were before the courts over potential repossessions.  Again the banks were not playing ball with those families.  These are people who have tried their best.  They have gone through MABS and gone through the process.  They are paying what they can yet the banks are going for repossession.  There is no write down, no proper restructuring and none of the options the Government claims are available, such as split-mortgages and mortgage to rent.  Those options are not available to people because the banks are simply not using them.  Until the Government faces up to that reality and faces down the banks, into which we invested huge amounts of money, and properly represents those people who are in mortgage arrears, we will continue to have these problems.</p><p>My message to Government Senators and Ministers is for them to offer less tea and sympathy and show more action.  They should put in place the policies for which they are paid to ensure that those in mortgage arrears get at least a fair crack of the whip and are properly represented because the Government has failed them up to now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J01000"><p>I have received representations from parents who will be affected by this week's changes to the one-parent family payment.  I highlight mothers and fathers who are engaged in employment below the threshold of the 19 hours necessary to avail of family income supplement.</p> <p>I am aware of a specific case where a parent works for 15 hours spread over a five-day week in a local schools as a bus escort.  As a result they cannot avail of jobseeker's benefit for the days not in work as their employment is spread over the five days.  They cannot avail of FIS because they are at 15 hours and there is no prospect of increased hours due to the nature of their work despite the fact that they have offered to work the additional four hours on a voluntary basis.  This parent is just below the threshold to qualify for FIS which would significantly increase their weekly income by almost &euro;200 while continuing employment.  The individual wants to work, but in this situation they may be better off on jobseeker's benefit where they can avail of courses and training to reskill or upskill.</p> <p>I understand this is a particular case, but I know it is replicated across many counties, particularly with working parents employed on low-hours contracts in schools or other employment.  We need to use common sense in such cases where a parent wants to work.</p> <p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that No. 11 be taken before No. 1 today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J01100"><p>I support what Senator Darragh O'Brien said about the rape crisis centres.  I have no ulterior motive for it.  It is a scandal.  However, there is a bigger scandal.</p> <p>Yesterday, Senator Darragh O'Brien attempted to move an amendment to the Order of Business on No. 67, motion 17 which deals with the one-parent family payment.  Last night I watched Vincent Browne's show, during which he mentioned that out of 120 Government Deputies and Senators, not one was available to come on the programme to defend this scurrilous cut.  I call on the Leader to be brave and organise a debate in the House before this change comes in.  Let us discuss the exact implications for the lone parents.  We hear a lot of old bleeding-heart stuff here about our concern for children and for the poverty-stricken in this country.  I would love somebody on the Government side to have the courage to stand up here and explain how this will benefit the poverty-stricken of this country.</p> <p>Tomorrow I will move the same amendment to the Order of Business as Senator Darragh O'Brien did and I ask the Government to respond with courage this time.  If they are not able to face Vincent Browne, they should try facing the Opposition on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#J01200"><p>I wish to speak on the issue of the banks that Senator Mullins raised.  I reassure the Opposition because of the steps the Government has taken, the Governor of the Central Bank was able to come out and say what he said.  However, as Senator Mullins said, I noticed he was weak in his implementation of the powers he has been given by the Government.</p> <p>In 2011 the mortgage arrears resolution process was introduced.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator C&aacute;it Keane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2359"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2359&amp;amp;pid=CaitKeane&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In July 2013 it was strengthened by a detailed definition of what constitutes co-operation and non-co-operation.  With the powers that the Central Bank has been given by this Government the Governor is now able to wake up, whereas heretofore one could say the Central Bank was asleep when it should have been maintaining oversight.  I listened to what he said this morning and was most disappointed to hear that seven institutions are not co-operating as required by this Government.  He should name and shame these institutions and take them to task immediately.  The regulator now has the powers to do it and he should do it.  </p><p>An alternative motion was proposed on the cut to the funding of the Rape Crisis Network.  Only last week, when the funding was cut, I raised the issue myself in the Seanad.  I asked for a debate and I am still asking for a debate as that is the way to ensure that funding is reinstated.  It was not the Minister who made the cut.  When I was on the council we were always looking for devolution of powers and power was devolved to the Tusla board which made the decision.  I think it was the wrong decision and many in this House think it was the wrong decision.  I asked why the decision was made but have not been given an explanation.  I want a debate on it.  Rest assured that we on this side of the House are just as concerned about rape as Members on the other.  When I spoke on this subject I gave the statistics and pointed to the failings of every organisation in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1189" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K00200"><p>I ask the Leader for a debate on care of the elderly.  I sound like a long-playing record on this because I have made this request on many occasions down the years.  I do so today, however, in the context of the recently issued report by ALONE which clearly demonstrates that up to one third of people who are currently in nursing homes do not need to be there, should not be there and would be much happier and more fulfilled in their own communities with their own families, friends and neighbours.  It is a question of putting in place the resources, which may be significantly less than what is currently invested in fair deal and other such schemes.  If we were more generous and caring with the carer's allowance and made a change to the rules and regulations of that particular scheme, and if we looked at schemes such as the home help scheme, the public health scheme and public health nurses, we could ensure that up to one third of people currently in nursing homes are with their families and in their communities.  Everybody would win and it would be a win for society.  We are becoming fixated in Europe with the concept of long-term residential care but that it is a "shady pines" solution for the elderly.</p> <p>The majority of our elderly citizens can be looked after, provided for and supported in their homes and communities by a tweaking of the schemes which we have at the moment.  It would probably save the taxpayer money as well, as the cost of the nursing homes scheme to the State is &euro;1,200 per week while we simultaneously turn down carer's allowance claims of &euro;200 per week for flimsy reasons.  I ask the Leader to arrange this debate, either with the Minister for Social Protection, the Minister of State with responsibility for older people or a combination of the two.  We need to look at a much more holistic way of looking after the elderly and we should have an aspiration for our elderly above and beyond simply providing nursing home beds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K00300"><p>I second the amendment tabled by Senator Mary Moran.  However, there is an onus on speakers in the House to put accurate information on the public record.  Two speakers on the Opposition side said there were cuts to the rape crisis centre but there have been no cuts to any rape crisis centre.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K00400"><p>I said it was Rape Crisis Network Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K00500"><p>The Senator said that but two other speakers on the Opposition benches certainly said "rape crisis centre".  It is the network and we must distinguish what the network does from what the rape crisis centres do.  Rape Crisis Network Ireland does not offer frontline services but is a representative body of 14 rape crisis centres.  Tusla said on 11 June this year that it will maintain the &euro;4 million grant aid to the rape crisis centres and increase by &euro;500,000 the resources being put into them.  I want to make sure there is no misunderstanding because I have a sneaking suspicion that the information being put on the public record is not an error.  It is important we clarify the role of the Rape Crisis Network and that of the rape crisis centres.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K00600"><p>I support colleagues in the motion about the Rape Crisis Network.  The Senator will be able to watch a programme tonight about the work of the Rape Crisis Network in Kerry, the valuable work it does and how its funding is being cut.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K00700"><p>That is the rape crisis centre.  Can the Senator put accurate information on the record?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K00800"><p>As Senator Gilroy will know, the situation is dire and every time there is a trial reported in the newspapers or on television, as we will see tomorrow in relation to Father Brendan Smyth, Cardinal Brady and others, it means the victims relive their experience.  The Rape Crisis Network and those who support it have been damaged and have suffered from a grievous crime and for the Government to do this is an attack on the most vulnerable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K00900"><p>Facts do not seem to matter on the Opposition side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01000"><p>The Labour Party is used to breaking promises and Senator Gilroy is used to defending the indefensible but when he sees the Rape Crisis Network in Kerry he will hear about the loss of funding when all they have to do is look at the person to the left, to the right, to the front or to the back to see a victim.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01100"><p>One day Senator Daly will come in here and give factual information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01200"><p>That will be the day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01300"><p>Senator Gilroy is defending the indefensible, as usual, and talks out of both sides of his mouth.  Others had Commencement matters relating to this issue but we will see how they vote because how they vote on questions relating to the most vulnerable is the most important thing.  Actions speak louder than words.  When the motion comes up I hope Members opposite will reflect on it.  The most vulnerable people in society are being attacked by the Government and their funding is being cut, as we saw with lone parents and others, but the Labour Party continues to tout the line that social welfare has not been cut.  We know from lone parents and others that they are suffering a cut on Thursday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01400"><p>Accuracy and honesty do not matter in this House.  Nonsense repeated is still nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01500"><p>I am asking for a debate and I look forward to hearing from Government Members opposite, especially those in the Labour Party who talk on the radio on the one hand while, on the other, vote against the Rape Crisis Network and other organisations which provide so much valuable support to the most vulnerable people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01600"><p>The Senator is way over time.  He should resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01700"><p>These people have suffered and will continue to suffer if this Government goes ahead with its cuts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01800"><p>What did Fianna F&aacute;il do?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#K01900"><p>I share the concerns of other Senators over the Central Bank's report on mortgage lending and the lending institutions in question not behaving as they should.  I am also concerned at banks involving people in needless paper work and causing unnecessary delays where loans sanctioned for very necessary developments to get our economy moving again and provide more jobs are being thwarted by the banks.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Coghlan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We will have more about that on another day.</p><p>I join with Senator Hayden in congratulating and sending our good wishes to Eugene Regan who is a man of outstanding ability, as we know, and one of the great senior counsels of our time.  He is a former Member of this House who served with great distinction.  It behoves us to wish him well.  He will be an outstanding member of the European Court of Justice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L00200"><p>I wish to raise two matters.  Following on from Senator Bradford's contribution about nursing homes, the annual cost for the fair deal scheme is &euro;993 million or very close to &euro;1 billion.  I have highlighted this issue previously in the House.  We face major long-term challenges in this regard.  Every year more than 20,000 people will reach the age of 65 and the number of over-65s will continue to grow in the future.  We should have a debate about long-term planning in this area.  I wish to highlight the problems faced by nursing homes in hiring nursing staff.  People who want to work in this country are facing delays in being registered with An Bord Altranais, with delays in some cases of up to six months.  This is an urgent matter.</p> <p>I wish to raise an issue related to housing.  A person known to me has applied for housing assist under the HAP scheme, which is assistance from the local authority.  The person has been told that because one person in the household has an income and the other person is in receipt of social welfare their combined incomes do not qualify for assistance.  However, the same local authority will not grant them assistance to buy a house because social welfare income is not taken into account when applying for a mortgage.  They are caught in the middle.  They will not be granted assistance because their combined incomes are too high but on the other hand they will not be given assistance because their income is under-qualified.</p> <p>We need a resolution to this problem.  These people are trying to provide for themselves and their family and the system is not providing for them.  They either fit into one category or the other but in this case they are fitting into neither.  This is wrong and they are being sidelined by the system.  The irregularity needs to be resolved.  I ask the Leader to bring it to the attention of the Minister.  I intend following up on the matter but it would be helpful if the Leader would also bring it to the attention of the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L00300"><p>Last week I raised the issue of the rape crisis centres and the Rape Crisis Network Ireland.  The rape crisis centres are independent of Rape Crisis Network Ireland.  They are funded directly.  I have it in writing that the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Reilly, requested that Tusla give particular priority to protecting front-line services.  In that context funding for the 16 rape crisis centres nationwide which provide services directly to rape survivors has been protected for 2015.  Almost &euro;4 million in funding is dedicated to rape crisis centres in 2015.  No rape crisis centres are to be closed.</p> <p>However, I agree that we should have a debate on the network, which is independent.  It collates data.  Of the 16 rape crisis centres, only eleven use Rape Crisis Network Ireland while the remainder collate their own data.  They can explain that for themselves.  We must have a debate to allow the Minister to explain the reasoning behind the policy.  However, we should not accept an hour of statements but rather we should have a proper debate into which every one of us can have an input.  I reiterate my call of last week for a constructive debate with time for all Members to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L00400"><p>I will begin with the point raised by Senator Darragh O'Brien about Rape Crisis Network Ireland and to which Senators Gilroy and Moloney quite rightly referred.  The Government is committed to supporting the work of the rape crisis centres around the country because they provide invaluable support to people at an extremely traumatic and vulnerable time.  I understand that Tusla has confirmed that funding for the 16 rape crisis centres has been protected in 2015.  Some people on the other side of the House are mixing up rape crisis centres with Rape Crisis Network Ireland, but not Senator O'Brien-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L00500"><p>I led on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L00600"><p>Several other Senators mentioned rape crisis centres.  I think they should know what they are speaking about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L00700"><p>On a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L00800"><p>I will allow Senator Mooney on a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L00900"><p>Tusla has proposed new contracts for rape crisis centres which put at risk the autonomy of rape crisis centres.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L01000"><p>That was the context in which it was raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L01100"><p>Difficult funding decisions have had to be made by Tusla with regard to funding or service provision.  I understand that Rape Crisis Network Ireland, which is the representative body for rape crisis centres, as opposed to the service-provider, has had its funding ceased.  The priority of both the Minister and Tusla was to protect front-line services within the funding available.  The funding to Rape Crisis Network Ireland was in respect of the maintenance of a database incorporating data gathered and recorded by rape crisis workers who deal with the survivors of sexual abuse.  Tusla had concerns about the database, in particular the fact that the data collected by RCNI from rape crisis centres is not readily available to Tusla and not fully representative of all services dealing with sexual abuse.  As part of its statutory responsibilities for the provision of services to victims of domestic, sexual and gender-based violence, including information capability, a decision was taken to produce the data in-house in the future.</p> <p>Tusla is developing a national specialist service for all sexual, domestic and gender-based violence services, to enable better outcomes for children and adults who survive such violence.  It has appointed a national manager and eight additional staff to ensure a single line of accountability for all resources in this important area.  It is very important that people realise the difference between the network and what is being done by the network, especially in this specific instance and by the rape crisis centres.  Some speakers mixed up the situation and it is very important that it is clarified.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L01200"><p>We are so lucky to have Senator Gilroy here to show us the right path on every issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L01300"><p>Some people on the other side of the House have a habit of throwing out facts that are not correct-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L01400"><p>Nothing I said was-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L01500"><p>No interruptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#L01600"><p>-----and they do not understand the issue, unfortunately.  I think the comprehensive reply I have given clarifies the situation.  However, I will take on board what Senator Moloney asked for last week.  I have asked the Minister to come to the House for a debate on it.  He was not available this week.  I had provisionally arranged for him to come this evening but he cannot be here.  I hope we can arrange a debate at an early date.</p> <p>I will bring the issue of the Fampyra drug to the attention of the Minister.  I gave several comprehensive reports on that matter on previous occasions but we will follow it up.</p> <p>Senators Hayden, Mullins, Keane, Coghlan and Cullinane asked about the Central Bank report and the banks' treatment of people in mortgage arrears.  That treatment is not acceptable and there is a need for the Central Bank to use the powers available to it to take these banks to task.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I remind the other side of the House that the Government has removed the bank veto.  The Central Bank needs to take its responsibility very seriously and take action against the banks who are not playing ball on mortgage arrears.</p><p>Senator Hayden and Senator Paul Coghlan congratulated former Senator, Eugene Regan, on his appointment to the European Court of Justice.  Former Senator Regan was an excellent Member of this House for a number of years and I congratulate him on his appointment.  I am sure he will make an excellent judge in the European court.</p><p>Senator van Turnhout referred to the retirement of Catherine Day, a senior Irish civil servant in the EU.  I note the points she will bring to the attention of the CPP in terms of inviting Catherine Day to address the House.  It would be an excellent opportunity for the House to have her inform us on all the things that go on in the EU at senior civil service level.  The report on direct provision will be going to Cabinet on Tuesday next and I will try to arrange a debate with the Minister after that.  As Senator van Turnhout mentioned, we have debated the issue in this House on a number of occasions.</p><p>Senator Mullins referred to the Central Bank report, to which I have already alluded.  He also welcomed the new healthy workplace initiative introduced by the Minister for Health, Deputy Varadkar.</p><p>Senator Moran raised the plight of one-parent families.  She mentioned a specific case which could be dealt with by means of a Commencement matter.  I accept the amendment proposed to the Order of Business to the effect that No. 11 would be taken before No. 1.</p><p>Senator Keane also spoke about the Central Bank, an issue I have addressed.  Senator Bradford raised the care of the elderly and the recent report by Alone.  He called for a debate on the matter.  I will try to arrange it with the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch.</p><p>Senator Colm Burke raised the expenditure of &euro;1 billion on the fair deal scheme, which is a significant sum.  He also spoke about the need to address the delay in people trying to get on the nursing board register.  He referred also to housing funding and anomalies in the system.  If he tables the issue as a Commencement debate matter I am sure the Minister of State, Deputy Coffey, or the Minister, Deputy Kelly, will come to the House to address the matter.  I think I have addressed the majority, if not all, the issues Members raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#M00200"><p>Senator Darragh O&rsquo;Brien has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: &ldquo;That No. 67, non-Government motion No. 19, be taken without debate before No. 1.&rdquo;  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#M00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.109/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00100"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 14; Nl, 19.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paschal Mooney and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.109/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-06-24" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="14" noes="19" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" vote="aye">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="aye">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1200" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="aye">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.109/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00100"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00200"><p>Senator Mary Moran has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 11 be taken before No. 1."  The Leader has indicated that he wishes to accept the motion.  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.111" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.112" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00450">Education (Welfare) (Amendment) Bill 2015: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00500"><p>I move:<blockquote><br /><br />That leave be granted to introduced a Bill entitled an Act to increase the school leaving age to 17 and to provide for related matters.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" speakername="Tony Mulcahy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00700"><p>I second the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.115" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00800"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N00900"><p>Next Tuesday, 30 June 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#N01000"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.119" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.35 p.m. and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.120" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#O00100">Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) Bill 2015: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.121" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#O00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Dara Murphy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#O00300"><p>I welcome the opportunity to address the House on this important legislation which is a priority for the Government.  The purpose of the legislation is to protect consumers whose loans are sold by regulated financial service providers to unregulated firms.  It will address concerns surrounding the continued applicability of the Central Bank's codes and access for borrowers to the Financial Services Ombudsman after loan books are sold.  It provides that borrowers, whose loans have been sold, retain the protections they had when their loan was with a regulated lender.  For example, they will retain the protections provided by the Central Bank's codes such as the code of conduct on mortgage arrears, known as the CCMA, the consumer protection code and the code of conduct for business lending to small and medium enterprises.  Consumers need protection when taking out credit, during the course of holding credit and when they are repaying credit.  It is not equitable that some of these protections can be avoided owing to the regulatory position of the entity which owns the credit.  For this reason, consumers should maintain the protections they had before their loan was sold.  This is what the proposed legislation seeks to achieve.</p> <p>As Senators know, unregulated financial institutions are not bound by the Central Bank's codes.  In addition, while customers of unregulated financial institutions have access to the courts, they do not have access to the Financial Services Ombudsman.  Although, as the House will be aware, many purchasers of loan books have already agreed voluntarily to apply the Central Bank's codes when managing loan books, voluntary compliance is not enforceable.  As a result, the Government committed to ensuring these protections would be made available for all consumers whose loans had been sold.</p> <p>Senators might ask why loan books are sold.  It is generally accepted that there is a need for financial institutions to be able to deleverage and restructure their loan books so as to return to their main business of supporting the economy through the provision of financial services, including credit for SMEs and consumers.  We do not intend that this legislation will inhibit that process, but, more importantly, we do not want borrowers to lose protections because of a change in ownership.</p> <p>This has been complex legislation to prepare.  Department of Finance officials have carefully considered how best to protect consumers and, as is often the case when preparing legislation, their thinking has evolved during the course of the preparatory phase.  Last July and August the Department of Finance ran a public consultation process to seek views on the proposed legislation.  Some 19 submissions were received from a range of respondents, including the financial services industry, consumer groups, public representatives, individuals and other stakeholders.  These submissions are available on the Department's website.  Department of Finance officials subsequently met some stakeholders to clarify submissions and the technicalities of how the credit servicing industry operated.  The officials also discussed the issue with the authorities in the United Kingdom, as they had faced similar policy challenges in recent times.</p> <p>Officials in the Department of Finance have carefully considered the submissions and have been working intensively with the Central Bank and the Office of the Attorney General to progress the legislation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Dara Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2320"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2320&amp;amp;pid=DaraMurphy&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This experience has underlined the value of the public consultations process.  It means legislation is prepared in an open and transparent manner and also plays an important role in contributing to understanding the issues and avoiding unintended consequences.  When work began on this Bill, the initial thinking was that the ownership of credit should be regulated to ensure borrowers continue to receive the same protections they enjoyed prior to the loan book sale.  However, the public consultation process highlighted an issue with this approach, namely, that it was possible to envisage cases where owners would effectively function as passive special purpose vehicles, SPVs, and, where they outsourced servicing of loans to a firm, that would not be regulated.  It became clear from the consultation process that if we were to protect consumers effectively, it was better to regulate the process of credit servicing as that is the customer-facing activity.  However, if owners do not outsource credit servicing and instead undertake the activity themselves, they will be required to be regulated.  Furthermore, if a regulated financial service provider outsources its credit servicing, it will be obliged to ensure the firm credit servicing on its behalf is compliant with Central Bank regulations.  In other words, a regulated entity will be responsible for all credit agreements.<br/><br/>I will now turn to the details of the Bill, the Title of which was agreed following consultation with the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel and reflects the approach being adopted to protect consumers.  The legislation will amend the Central Bank Act 1942, Central Bank Act 1997, Central Bank (Supervision and Enforcement) Act 2013 and Consumer Credit Act 1995 and provide for related matters.  It is proposed to amend section 28 of the Central Bank Act 1997 by inserting definitions of the terms &quot;credit agreement&quot;, &quot;credit servicing&quot;, &quot;credit servicing firm&quot;, &quot;creditor&quot; and &quot;relevant borrower&quot;.  The term &quot;credit servicing&quot; is being tightly defined in order that a firm which communicates with relevant borrowers in regard to their credit agreement will require authorisation.  As mentioned earlier, the legislation will also require owners who do not outsource credit servicing to another party to be regulated.  The Bill ensures there is only a limited number of actions an owner can take without needing to be authorised as a credit servicing firm by the Central Bank.<br/><br/>The effect of all this is to regulate the activity of credit servicing, and the credit servicing firms engaged in such activity, in order that borrowers retain the protections they have before the loan book was sold.  All consumer and relevant small and medium enterprise, SME, loans that are sold will be covered by these amendments and will retain the protections they currently have.  First, the code of conduct on mortgage arrears, CCMA, sets out the framework lenders must use when dealing with borrowers in mortgage arrears or pre-arrears.  It requires lenders to engage positively with the objective of helping borrowers to meet their obligations.  Under the CCMA, borrowers must be dealt with in accordance with the mortgage arrears resolution process, MARP, which sets out the steps to be followed on communication, gathering financial information, assessing the circumstances of borrowers and proposing a resolution.  Procedures for complaints and appeals are also provided.<br/><br/>Second, the consumer protection code provides protections such as limits on communications, personal visits and other contacts, complaint resolution processes, error handling, compliance of outsourced activity with the code, and post-sale information provisions, including warnings on switching from a tracker mortgage to a variable rate mortgage.  Third, under the code of conduct for business lending to small and medium enterprises, SME customers of regulated financial institutions enjoy protections in respect of arrears handling, complaint resolution and so on.<br/><br/>Breaches of the Central Bank codes can lead to sanctions for the regulated entity.  As credit servicing firms will become regulated financial services providers under the new legislative regime, all appropriate supervisory powers of the Central Bank will be applicable to them as regulated financial service providers, including the administrative sanctions procedures regime.  Customers of regulated financial institutions also have access to the Financial Services Ombudsman whose role is to investigate, mediate and adjudicate complaints about the conduct of regulated financial service providers.  All personal customers, unincorporated bodies, charities, clubs, partnerships, trusts and limited companies with a turnover of &euro;3 million or less can complain to the ombudsman.  This is a very important protection for borrowers.<br/><br/>With regard to credit union credit, we must ensure that where credit union loan books are sold outside the credit union movement, the borrowers in question are afforded the same protections as other borrowers.  This requires an amendment to the Consumer Credit Act 1995.  Therefore, the relevant codes will apply to credit which is initially advanced by a credit union but is subsequently sold.  We are not aware of circumstances where this has arisen, but it is considered prudent from a consumer protection perspective to provide for it.<br/><br/>Section 1 amends section 28 of the Central Bank Act 1997 by inserting definitions of &quot;credit agreement&quot;, &quot;credit servicing&quot;, &quot;credit servicing firm&quot;, &quot;creditor&quot; and &quot;relevant borrower&quot;, as I have mentioned.  The activities of credit servicing have been defined to ensure the entity managing the relevant borrowers' credit agreements is regulated.  Owners who do not outsource credit servicing will be required to be regulated in order that a regulated entity will be responsible for all credit agreements.  The effect of the amendments to section 28 of the Central Bank Act 1997 is to regulate the activity of credit servicing and the credit servicing firms engaged in such activity in order that borrowers retain the protections they have before a loan book is sold.<br/><br/>The definition of SMEs, which comes within the definition of &quot;relevant borrower&quot;, ensures SMEs that borrowed from regulated firms maintain the protections they had, while SMEs that borrowed from legitimately unregulated firms are not captured.  Such unregulated firms are an important source of funding for SMEs and we do not wish to restrict the flow of funds to such businesses in any way.  The Bill will ensure the <i>status quo</i>is maintained.  As a result, where credit has been granted to an SME by a number of providers, both regulated and unregulated, it is only the credit that was originally provided by an authorised or regulated financial services provider that is covered by this Bill.  Essentially, SMEs will be restored to the protections they currently have, including under the code of conduct for business lending to small and medium enterprises, when they borrow from regulated lenders, but we are not extending the remit.<br/><br/>Section 2 amends the Central Bank Act 1997 in respect of the Central Bank's powers to grant and refuse applications for authorisation.  Section 3 amends Section 33A of the Central Bank Act 1997 to enable the Central Bank to impose conditions or requirements on authorised credit servicing firms.<br/><br/>Section 4 amends the Central Bank Act 1997 by inserting two new sections, 34E and 34F, with transitional provisions for retail credit firms and credit servicing firms, respectively.  Existing retail credit firms or credit servicing firms are taken to be authorised under this Act provided the person applies to the bank for authorisation no later than three months after the legislation is enacted.  However, these firms will &quot;stand authorised&quot; on an interim basis during that period and will be obliged to comply with relevant financial services legislation.  They will fall under the supervision of the Central Bank which can immediately step in if there is a problem with a firm's actions.  The Central Bank does not have to wait three months to have this power.  It will have it as soon as the Bill becomes law.  In addition, a regulated financial service provider authorised before or after the enactment of the legislation to provide credit in the State is taken to be authorised to carry on the business of a credit servicing firm by virtue of the amendment this Bill makes, in section 1, to section 28 of the Central Bank Act 1997.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Dara Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2320"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2320&amp;amp;pid=DaraMurphy&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Section 5 was introduced on Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il to strengthen protections for borrowers further.  It inserts a new section in the Central Bank Act 1997 that is a statutory obligation on both owners and credit servicing firms.  The statutory obligation will ensure that a credit servicing firm cannot do something, or fail to do something, that would be a prescribed contravention if performed, or not performed, by a retail credit firm.  It also prevents the owner of credit from instructing a regulated credit firm to perform such an action.  This obligation is considered necessary to return borrowers to the circumstances they were in prior to the sale of the loan book.  It strengthens the protections for borrowers and also effectively closes off possible behaviour by owners instructing firms to carry out inappropriate activities.  It also strengthens the position of an upstanding credit servicing firm as it legally obliges it not to carry out such instructions.  Furthermore, the obligation makes the issuance of such instructions by an owner an offence.</p><p>By this obligation, we are specifying an offence for the unregulated owner, but also ensuring that the breach cannot be implemented by the regulated servicer, over whom the Central Bank has oversight as a regulated entity.  This will mean a quicker response to possible breaches.  Furthermore, this oversight will allow the Central Bank to investigate in a case where an unregulated owner instructs a credit servicing firm to do something that would be a prescribed contravention if done by a retail credit firm.  Such a breach is actionable by the Central Bank against the credit servicing firm.  In addition, the owner could also be liable for credit servicing without authorisation.  The obligation on the regulated credit servicing firm not to perform the action also means that the borrower has access to the Financial Services Ombudsman.</p><p>Section 6 amends section 3 of the Central Bank (Supervision and Enforcement) Act 2013 to amend the definition of "customer".  We are adding paragraph (c) to include people whose loans are being serviced by a credit servicing firm.</p><p>Section 7 amends section 57BA the Central Bank Act 1942 to ensure that relevant borrowers whose credit agreements are being serviced by an authorised credit servicing firm are considered eligible consumers for the purposes of the Financial Services Ombudsman.  Customers of regulated financial institutions have access to the Financial Services Ombudsman, whose role is to investigate, mediate in, and adjudicate on complaints about the conduct of regulated financial service providers.</p><p>Section 8 amends section 3 of the Consumer Credit Act 1995, which concerns the application, to ensure that the relevant Central Bank codes will apply to credit union credit that is sold to an unregulated entity.  With regard to credit union credit, it is necessary to ensure that where credit union loan books are sold, those borrowers are also afforded the same protections as other borrowers.  This issue was raised by the Financial Services Ombudsman in the consultation process.  Credit union credit sold outside the credit union movement should be regulated so an amendment to the Consumer Credit Act 1995 is needed.  Therefore, the relevant codes will apply to credit that is initially advanced by a credit union but subsequently sold to an unregulated entity.</p><p>Section 9 contains the Short Title and collective citation.  The Bill will commence on its signature by the President.</p><p>This Bill is important because it addresses the concerns of borrowers whose loans are sold to unregulated entities.  It will give consumers a legally enforceable right to complain to the Financial Services Ombudsman and it will ensure that consumers whose loans have been sold will have the benefits of the Central Bank codes, and those dealing with those consumers will have to be authorised by the Central Bank.</p><p>The Minister, Deputy Michael Noonan, looks forward to a constructive debate on the Bill.  There is broad agreement in the House on the need to ensure borrowers will have the same protections as they had before their loan was sold.  We can all agree that this important legislation needs to be enacted as soon as possible so that borrowers are protected without delay.  While the Minister and his officials have been extremely careful and diligent in the drafting of this legislation to ensure it restores protections for borrowers, they believe that if issues emerge regarding the legislation, they may, if considered necessary, be dealt with at a later stage through amendments to the Act.  The priority must be to enact the legislation to ensure that protections for borrowers will be in place as quickly as possible.  I commend the Bill to the House and ask that Senators give it their full support and consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#Q00200"><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Dara Murphy is very welcome to the House.  I am puzzled as to why he is not in the Department of Finance himself.  He is responsible for European affairs and data protection.  I would have believed that the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, or his Minister of State, Deputy Simon Harris, who are responsible for this legislation, would have been here.  That they are not is no reflection on Minister of State Deputy Dara Murphy, who does a good job and is more than welcome here.  However, I would have believed that if the legislation is as important as stated and if, as stated, the Minister, Deputy Michael Noonan, looks forward to a good, constructive and forthright debate on the Bill, he or his deputy, Minister of State Deputy Simon Harris, would have come to the House to hear it.</p> <p>This is not great legislation.  It is important but it is drastically watered down by comparison to what we expected.  I would oppose it on Second Stage only that I have a series of amendments prepared for Committee Stage.  The Bill is deficient and watered down.  The watering down is akin to the watering down of the code of conduct on mortgage arrears that the Minister of State referred to in this statement, which is obviously prepared by the Department of Finance.  The Bill will not achieve what is required.</p> <p>When mortgage books are sold, it is a big issue for those concerned.  The mortgage holders will not be afforded the protection required based on the way this legislation is framed because the owner of the loan books, which could be a vulture fund that is not administering the mortgages, will not be covered by it.  If vulture fund ABC plc from the USA bought a loan book here but did not administer the mortgages, it would not be covered by the Central Bank or this legislation, as drafted.  It is mentioned in the statement prepared by the Department of Finance and read here this afternoon by the Minister of State that the Department of Finance consulted widely, there were concerns within the industry that what I suggest would be too complex, and that this is why the changes have been made.  I believe the changes have been made because the financial institutions and those who purchase loan books did not want the legislation to be as strong as it should be.  I could be wrong about this but it is more than likely the reason.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#Q00300"><p>The Senator is judging us by his own standards, I am afraid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#Q00400"><p>There is a real issue.  We have 11 or 12 amendments on the Bill that we will table.  I do not doubt the Government's desire to afford protection to mortgage holders but I believe the legislation needs to be strengthened sufficiently.</p> <p>The Minister of State referred to the question of why loan books are sold.  We understand why they are sold.  Mortgage holders wonder, in connection with the IBRC and Irish Nationwide book of residential mortgages that was sold, why the affected mortgage holders were not afforded the opportunity to purchase their own mortgages at a discount.  The Government saw fit to sell those mortgages as a block at a substantial discount, yet the mortgage holders, even if not in arrears, got no opportunity to make an offer on their mortgages.  My proposal might not seem realistic but I have dealt with people with Irish Nationwide and IBRC mortgages who were angry because their mortgages were sold by the Government to what is effectively a vulture fund and because they were not offered any discount.  Moreover, they were never told the discount at which the mortgages were sold.  People refer to a discount in the region of 50%, and this is more than likely the case.  This is a problem because the code of conduct on mortgage arrears is not as strong as it used to be.  I welcome the fact that the Government is seeking to remove the bank veto but its proposals do not do so.</p> <p>The problem concerns areas where house prices have risen.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Last year, more than 10,000 repossession orders were issued as a result of the Land and Conveyancing Law Reform Act, which the Minister of State's colleague, Deputy Shatter, brought in, which the House passed, and which set aside the Dunne judgment and made it easier for financial institutions to repossess people's homes.  At the time, many people warned that we should expect a raft of repossession orders, and this has happened.  If a vulture fund in New York has bought my &euro;100,000 mortgage for &euro;50,000 and thinks it can get full redemption of it, particularly if I am in arrears, it will go after me.  This is happening.  People who are paying their mortgages but who have an amount of residual mortgage arrears are being moved against, not just by vulture funds but also by Irish-owned banks.  The code of conduct on mortgage arrears is irrelevant.</p><p>Today's report by the Central Bank stated that there has been no financial penalty against any financial institution.  I have frequently had occasion to write to Bank of Ireland to ask why it has not offered a split mortgage to a client.  The answer is that the bank did not and will not, and that is the end of the matter.  The Minister of State should not wonder if I take the legislation and the Government's statement today not just with a pinch of salt but with a bucket.  The Government's track record on protecting people who have mortgages and are in mortgage arrears has been abysmal.  The legislation will let the people who own the mortgages off scot free.  Only the administrators of mortgages, not the owners, will be covered by this.  There are major deficiencies in this half-baked piece of legislation.  It is 100 million miles away from what the Minister, Deputy Noonan, said he would produce.</p><p>The Minister could be in Europe, and I understand there are important negotiations ongoing there which he must attend.  While I do not cast aspersions on the fact that the Minister of State, Deputy Dara Murphy, is here, and he is more than welcome, I am slightly bemused as to why the Minister State, Deputy Harris, is not here.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach might insist that the Leader ensure a Minister who has responsibility within the Department attends Committee Stage here and hears the amendments we plan to table.  We plan to table at least 12 amendments and I assume others will also table amendments.</p><p>Can anyone tell me why those who purchase distressed mortgages will not be covered by the legislation?  I do not understand why one would bother bringing the Bill forward without it.  There are issues with SME debt and certain anomalies within the Bill will cause difficulties for some major companies in Dublin in particular of which I am aware, and I will try to address them by way of amendment.  The Department and Minister are aware of unintended consequences which may befall some SMEs as a result of the legislation and I hope this will be tidied up on Committee Stage.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State for outlining the Bill.  I appreciate that he has taken the time to do it.  It is vitally important that the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, or the Minister of State, Deputy Harris, be here for Committee Stage.  Although I would be inclined to vote the Bill down on Second Stage, we will take the opportunity to strengthen the legislation on Committee Stage rather than oppose it now.  I hope the Minister will examine the amendments we will forward this evening.  I assume the Bill will come to Committee Stage next week.</p><p>I would give the legislation score of four out of ten, based on what was proposed at the start and what could have been done.  This is my humble opinion.  Senator Gilroy will disagree with all of this, which is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#R00200"><p>I will not disagree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#R00300"><p>We should try to explain to people why, when the Government sells their mortgages to a vulture fund, they have no opportunity to get a discount on their mortgages in the same way multi-billion dollar enterprises did when the Government sold the IBRC residential mortgage book at a substantial discount.  People in the portfolio will have their houses repossessed on the back of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#R00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Dara Murphy, to the House for this discussion on the Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) Bill 2015.  The Bill aims to ensure borrowers whose loans are sold by a regulated entity to a currently unregulated entity maintain the same regulatory protections as they had before the sale, including under various Central Bank codes and the code of conduct on mortgage arrears.  I share Senator Darragh O'Brien's concern and outrage at the Central Bank's report yesterday on how seven of the regulated entities are treating people in arrears and breaking the rules set by the regulators.  It is disturbing that some of these banks are continuing with legal action to repossess homes despite the fact that revised deals had been agreed with struggling home owners.  Other banks are withdrawing Central Bank protection for mortgage customers because they did not agree to a repayment schedule over the phone, despite the fact that banks are required to communicate a revised payment arrangement in writing, as the Central Bank has indicated.</p> <p>Seven banks are involved, none of which were named.  This morning I heard an interview with a representative of the Central Bank, and it is unfortunate the banks were not named and that stronger sanctions are not being imposed on them.  The Central Bank's report also showed that some banks were seeking irregular payments from stricken mortgage holders on top of agreed revised payments.  There were cases in which lenders continued to call borrowers directly rather than liaising with nominated third parties.  Some banks were not adhering to agreed timeframes for dealing with distressed borrowers.  These issues should be highlighted and put on the record of the House, as the Minister of State said.</p> <p>Customers need protection when they take out credit, during the course of holding credit and when they are repaying credit.  It is not equitable that some of these protections be avoided due to the regulatory provision of the entity that owns the credit.  The legislation rightly seeks to ensure customers retain the protections they had before the loans were sold.  Despite what Senator Darragh O'Brien said, the legislation is timely and urgent.  Of the 760,000 mortgages on primary dwellings in the State, approximately 102,000 are in arrears.  Thankfully, the figure has dropped significantly from 120,000 in February.  This is a positive development.  Deals are being done and people are returning to work and are, therefore, in a position to make the repayments.  The reduction in the unemployment rate from 15% to 9.8% is contributing significantly to the fact that more people are in a position to meet their revised mortgage commitments.  Of these 102,000, 5,000 to 10,000 do not enjoy the protection of the code of conduct on mortgage arrears.  This is a significant number.  The proposed legislation would bring peace of mind to many families.</p> <p>Protection became a major issue when the Ulster Bank loan book was sold by IBRC.  As public representatives, we have all heard harrowing stories from constituents about how they have been treated by lending agencies after the crash.  These agencies have taken no consideration of the parts they played in getting many people into severe financial difficulties.  I applaud the wonderful work being done by the Money Advice and Budgeting Service, MABS, and the credit unions and the support they have given many people who have been in great difficulty.</p> <p>The Bill will extend the regulatory remit of the Central Bank and ensure the applicability of various protections for consumers of financial services.  I have already referred to the code of conduct on mortgage arrears.  The consumer protection code and the code of conduct for business lending to SMEs and the Financial Services Ombudsman also apply.  In addition to primary dwellings, the legislation will apply to SMEs to facilitate access to credit for sustainable and productive business propositions.  The consumer code is essential in this regard.  While the primary purpose of the Bill is to provide protection for mortgages, many people have found themselves in great difficulty with loan sharks, properly known as regulated moneylenders, whose interest rates can be as high as 188%.  I very much welcome the announcement by the Government during recent days of the micro loans scheme and I applaud the work done by the Minister of State, Deputy Kevin Humphreys.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael Mullins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2368"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2368&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMullins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These loans will provide up to &euro;1,000 to 40,000 low to middle-income families at an interest rate of 12% as opposed to the 188% provided by moneylenders.  It will be administered through local credit unions and post offices.  I welcome the fact that it will be piloted by September.  Some people may have concerns that the loans will be given to people who may not be in a position to repay, but repayment is guaranteed because the payments can be taken through social welfare.  There will be involvement from the Money Advice and Budgeting Service and the Society of St. Vincent de Paul to ensure people do not seek loans they cannot afford.</p><p>I welcome the fact that this will be a hassle-free process whereby moneylenders will be taken out of the loop.  It should be a great boost to the credit union movement as well.  I come from a town that has a strong credit union which currently has plenty of money available to loan to business and borrowers.  As a Government, we need to strengthen the credit union movement to ensure it continues to play its rightful role in society and in our community, as it has always done.  While a few have run into difficulty, the majority of credit unions have run their businesses in an exemplary fashion.  I welcome the fact that the protections in this Bill will cover loan books sold on by the credit union movement.  As the Minister of State said, it is important to ensure borrowers will have the same protections they had before their loans were sold on.  I welcome the fact that the legislation is to be enacted without delay.  I commend the Minister for Finance on the work he has done in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#S00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, my constituency colleague, to the Chamber.  I also welcome Senator O'Brien's thoughtful and measured contribution, articulated in his normal coherent and clear style.  However, I am a little disappointed with regard to his comments, which may surprise some people.  He seemed to suggest that the legislation was constructed to satisfy the concerns of the financial industry.  Let us consider some of the publications which came before the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform during pre-legislative scrutiny.  They clearly outline in a transparent way most of the questions laid out by the very actors who we are seeking to regulate.  The suggestion that there has been a lack of transparency in the process is probably the complete opposite to what I sense in this legislation.  It has been outlined publicly in a public document and we can see the contributions and concerns of named companies, including Mars Capital, FLAC, Vivier Mortgages and the Irish Debt Securities Association.  These are the agents we seek to regulate.  They have all clearly laid out what they are seeking.  We can compare clearly what those agents seek and what is in the Bill.  If anyone can demonstrate to me that there has been a lack of transparency, they will have done a good job in the public interest.</p> <p>This legislation is a welcome development.  It has been the topic of much comment and concern in recent times.  We have heard this articulated in the media and through consumer organisations.  The sale of loans has a tendency to create uncertainty and concern among borrowers.  While it is commonplace in other countries, it is a relatively recent phenomenon in Ireland.  Up to now, borrowers in Ireland have had a reasonable expectation that they would continue to deal with the people who lent them money, that is to say, the financial institutions from which they borrowed the money.  Our domestic lenders are bound by the Central Bank of Ireland codes but up to now the so-called unregulated financial institutions have not been.  While borrowers from unregulated financial institutions have access to the courts, up to now they have not had access to the Financial Services Ombudsman, whose role is central in resolving disputes and complaints between customers and the lending institutions.  Many of the unregulated financial institutions have agreed to accept the voluntary code of the Central Bank of Ireland.  This voluntary code is a form of compliance, although it is not enforceable.</p> <p>I suggest that relying on the goodwill of international and mobile investors is not the most prudent course of action.  We have seen a stark example of this in the past week with the owners of Clerys.  They have strictly abided by the letter of company law but have shocked everyone with their ruthless application and disregard of the spirit of that law.  This is probably the first time we have seen international asset strippers arriving into the country to make a pure clear profit only to be gone as quickly as they came while using our laws to their advantage.  It is not the most prudent course of action to rely on the voluntary goodwill of financial institutions.  The Consumer Protection (Regulation of Credit Servicing Firms) Bill 2015 gives statutory protection to customers and will prevent this type of asset stripping.  It will go a long way towards reassuring customers that their loans and the conditions under which the loans were borrowed will retain the protection they have enjoyed up to that point.</p> <p>Before the economic implosion on a global scale we saw how the financial markets in the Americas, and the United States in particular, had securitised or bundled up various financial products, for example, life insurance policies, sub-prime mortgages and other financial instruments and derivatives, before selling them on in the secondary market.  In many ways this was the cause of the great crisis that has visited us in the past decade.  Does this Bill speak to any of those concerns in respect of financial institutions which might be tempted to securitise other products, including some of our non-performing mortgages in arrears?</p> <p>My second question for the Minister relates to credit union loan books being sold.  I was unaware of this practice or if I was, I had not given it much thought.  I do not imagine many people in the country are aware of this.  Will the Minister of State inform the House how prevalent is this practice in the country?  Is it something we are likely to see more of?</p> <p>Senator O'Brien made a reasonable point.  He asked why people in mortgage arrears are not allowed to buy their mortgages, while multinational companies are allowed.  Is this anything to do with the fact that people who find their mortgages being sold on are, by definition, in arrears and do not have access to capital to buy them?  Where can these people raise the capital if their primary asset is in trouble already?  Is that one of the reasons, or is it simply utilitarianism, that is to say, it is simply too difficult to administer?  If this were the case, it would be unacceptable.  Perhaps the Minister of State might comment on those points.</p> <p>We look forward to discussing the sections of the Bill in detail.  I presume the Minister, Deputy Noonan, will come to the House when the Bill is before us again.  I look forward to further engagement.  I also look forward to hearing details of the Opposition amendments to strengthen the provisions.  Senator O'Brien, in particular, has referred to this.  We look forward to discussing those at length at that Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#S00300"><p>The Minister of State is welcome.  I realise it did not sound as if he was being made welcome by Senator O'Brien earlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#S00400"><p>I did not mean anything by it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#S00500"><p>No, he did not.  He was careful about the way he worded it.  We have seen the Minister of State in the House on several occasions recently.  On this occasion he is wearing a particular hat.</p> <p>I welcome this Bill, which aims to give more protection to individuals and small and medium-sized enterprises.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Feargal Quinn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1972"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1972&amp;amp;pid=FergalQuinn&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is a loophole whereby certain loans that are bought by third parties may not be covered by current legislation.  The Minister of State explained that very clearly.  The original Bill was extensive as it was intended that it would apply to all credit agreements, including where an SME entered into a loan with an unregulated lender.  However, the amendments of 27 May have the effect that loans originally entered into between SMEs and unregulated lenders are not covered.  The provisions will only apply to regulated financial service providers.  I understand that the purpose of the Bill was to cover loans subsequently acquired by an unregulated entity but perhaps we can find a middle ground in order to offer some protection to SMEs and other customers.  I would appreciate it if the Minister of State could comment on that issue.  People may face an increased risk of losing their family homes if an unregulated firm holds their mortgage.  I am aware that there was discussion about the possibility that mortgages may still be a grey zone.  Perhaps the Minister of State can clear up any misunderstanding that may exist in this regard.  It would be useful to have clarity on how the so-called vulture funds will be regulated in respect of mortgages.<br/><br/>I recently drafted a Bill that would empower the Central Bank to force banks to reduce variable mortgage interest rates.  The Minister for Finance is aware of the bad behaviour and profiteering of banks in this respect.  While the Minister for Finance has done some work in this area, KBC Bank, Bank of Ireland and Ulster Bank ruled out the possibility that they would cut their variable mortgage rates.  A recent article in <i>The Irish Times</i>reported: &quot;The Minister reminded the banks that Senator Feargal Quinn&rsquo;s bill to give certain powers to the Central Bank to fix interest rates has been published in the Seanad, where the Government does not have a majority.&quot;  Where does the Minister of State stand on this issue and how does the Government intend to deal with financial institutions which do not pass on interest rate cuts to customers?<br/><br/>The ultimate purpose of this Bill is to give people access to credit and to protect borrowers.  One way that SMEs and individuals can get easy access to credit is by releasing some of the cash locked up in their pensions.  The Minister for Finance introduced a progressive measure which allowed people to access some of the cash locked up in their additional voluntary contributions for a three year period from 2013.  The scheme expires in less than a year, however.  The access to cash changed people's lives and it provided crucial cash flow for businesses.  By September of last year, more than 12,000 people had availed of the scheme, more than &euro;90 million had been released and &euro;36 million had been paid in taxes.  It was a win-win situation for Government and borrowers alike. However, I was disappointed to learn that the Minister has no plans to extend the scheme even though it has been a massive success with significant take-up.  We have to treat people as adults.  The banks are still reluctant to offer loans, while people are unable to access money locked up in their pension account to put their children through education or their businesses back on track.  Will the Government consider extending this very worthwhile scheme in the next budget?  If people knew they could access part of their pension funds for the rainy day, it would encourage them to invest in their pensions.  This has been done successfully in Britain and the ability to access pension funds may have been vital for more than 12,000 people in Ireland.  Anecdotal evidence indicates that the scheme has changed lives.<br/><br/>I hope the Minister of State will agree to the amendments that can improve this Bill.  I am confident that he has listened carefully to our arguments.  Senator Darragh O'Brien indicated that he intends to table a number of amendments.  I like to believe this House will be able to improve the Bill. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#T00200"><p>I thank Senators for their contributions.  As Senator Darragh O'Brien noted, the Minister for Finance is at a meeting in Brussels but he has indicated that he will engage with Senators at a later stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#T00300"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome.  I did not mean any offence to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#T00400"><p>I should have explained the reason for the Minister's absence at the outset of my contribution.  He is looking forward to engaging constructively on Senators' amendments.  The purpose of this Bill is to protect consumers whose loans are sold by regulated financial service providers to unregulated firms.  Senators offered broad support for the Bill's overall objectives.  While a number of purchasers of loan books have voluntarily agreed to apply Central Bank codes when managing loan books, the Government is introducing this Bill because voluntary compliance is not enforceable.  The Bill provides that borrowers retain their protections after their loans are sold, thereby addressing concerns about the continued applicability of the Central Bank's codes and access for borrowers to the Financial Services Ombudsman.  I have noted the points raised by Senators during the course of the debate and they will be considered carefully prior to Committee Stage, when they can be further explored.</p> <p>On the issues raised by Senator Darragh O'Brien, it was initially believed that the best approach was to regulate the new owners of loan books but the approach evolved on foot of the public consultation last July and August, which sought a broad range of views.  Further consideration on Committee Stage may be warranted.  The Bill also benefited from input from the Central Bank and the Office of the Attorney General.  The public consultation process highlighted an issue with the original approach which would facilitate the use of special purpose of vehicles and the outsourcing of loans to unregulated firms. </p> <p>Senator Gilroy referred to sales of credit union loan books.  This is not known to have happened and, while that is not to say it could not happen, it would be an unwelcome development.  We are taking a belt and braces approach in this respect.</p> <p>In order to further strengthen the protections for borrowers, a new section 5 has been added to provide for a statutory prohibition on a credit servicing fund doing something which is a proscribed contravention if performed by a retail credit firm.  This provision also prevents the owners of credit from instructing a regulated credit firm to perform such an action.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Dara Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2320"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2320&amp;amp;pid=DaraMurphy&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This copperfastens the protections for borrowers and ensures that owners' hands are very much tied in terms of what they can do in order to ensure that they do not act in a way that needs authorisation as a credit servicing firm and that they do not commit an offence by instructing a firm servicing their credit to do something or fail to do something which would be a proscribed contravention.  </p><p>I thank Senators for their constructive engagement on this very important Bill.  Most of those in opposition have engaged with it, although Sinn F&eacute;in Members were not particularly engaged with our deliberations today which is unfortunate because broad engagement by Members enables us to arrive at the best possible legislation.  I hope priority will be given to this Bill and I know that the Minister and his Department will engage fully on Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.143" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.144" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Acting Chairman" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#U00300"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#U00400"><p>Next Tuesday, 27 June.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.146" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Acting Chairman" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#U00500"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.147" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 27 June 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.148" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.45 p.m. and resumed at 3 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.149" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#CC00100">Petroleum (Exploration and Extraction) Safety Bill 2015: Order for Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.150" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Bill entitled an Act to give effect to directive 2013/30/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 12 June 2013 and for that purpose to amend the Petroleum and Other Minerals Development Act 1960, section 6 of the Continental Shelf Act 1968 and the Electricity Regulation Act 1999 and to provide for related matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" speakername="Tony Mulcahy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#CC00250"><p>I move: "That Second Stage be taken now."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.152" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.153" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#CC00400">Petroleum (Exploration and Extraction) Safety Bill 2015: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.154" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Question proposed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#CC00500"><p>  Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#CC00600"><p>Molaim an Bille seo don Teach.  Before I introduce this new Bill to the House, I would like to convey my apologies to Senators for the short notice in bringing this Bill before them today.  I know this was the subject of debate last week and I hope Senators got an opportunity to brief themselves on the information at their disposal since then.  As a former Senator myself, I am aware of the commitment and effort required by Senators to deliver robust legislation.  I wish to thank Senators for their forbearance and co-operation in endeavouring to meet the tight transposition deadline required in this instance.</p><p>I am pleased to introduce the Petroleum (Exploration and Extraction) Safety Bill 2015 for the consideration of this House.  The purpose of this Bill is to transpose directive 2013/30/EU, known as the offshore safety directive, which is focused on safety of offshore oil and gas operations.  Transposition of the directive will further strengthen the safety regulation of offshore oil and gas exploration and production in Ireland's offshore area.  The offshore safety directive, which was agreed under the Irish Presidency of the EU in June 2013, is the European Union response to minimise the risk of offshore accidents throughout the Union following its review of offshore oil and gas operations in Europe prompted by the <i>Deepwater Horizon</i>incident in the Gulf of Mexico in April 2010.  The offshore safety directive seeks to ensure a consistent implementation of best regulatory practices in all European jurisdictions with offshore oil and gas activities and to strengthen the Union&rsquo;s preparedness and response capacity to deal with an emergency that would potentially affect Union citizens or the environment.</p><p>It is an exciting time for the petroleum exploration sector in Ireland.  In the past three to four years we have witnessed strong momentum in exploration interest, with the number of exploration licences in place currently at its highest level ever.  This increased level of interest has resulted in a significant increase in the level of acquisition of new seismic data in the Irish offshore.  In 2013 and 2014, more new seismic data were acquired in the Irish offshore than in the previous ten years.  It is a positive indicator that acquisition of new seismic data is continuing at a high level again this year.  We now need to see the this effort translate into increased drilling levels, as it is only through exploration drilling that the true potential of Ireland&rsquo;s offshore area can be proven.</p><p>In September of this year, the 2015 Atlantic margin licensing round will close.  While the drop in oil prices is having a worldwide impact on investment decisions by exploration companies, feedback remains positive about industry interest in the licensing round.  A successful round would be important to maintaining the positive momentum that has been established in recent years.  It is also positive that the Corrib gas development is expected to come on stream later this year.  Corrib will provide over 40% of peak demand for the island of Ireland in its first year of production.</p><p>The Government&rsquo;s strategy for the exploitation of the State&rsquo;s natural hydrocarbon resources is premised on industry rather than the State bearing the risk for exploration investment.  In this context, it is important that the State provides the right environment to encourage the industry to take the risk associated with investing in exploration.  One of the key components to creating a robust and transparent regulatory regime in Ireland is the implementation of the Government&rsquo;s decision in June 2014 that Ireland&rsquo;s oil and gas fiscal terms should be revised along the lines recommended by Wood Mackenzie.  The key central conclusions of the Wood Mackenzie report were that there is scope for strengthening the current fiscal system in terms of providing for an increase in the overall State take, ensuring an earlier share of revenue for the State, and addressing what Wood Mackenzie consider to be inconsistencies in the current fiscal system.</p><p>Other initiatives in this sector include the conclusion of Ireland&rsquo;s first strategic environmental assessment of the entire Irish offshore exclusive economic zone.  This assessment will help to inform applications for both the current and future licensing rounds in Ireland&rsquo;s Atlantic margin basins.  This process will provide exploration companies working offshore Ireland with an environmental operational baseline against which they can conduct their work and ensure the protection of the marine environment.</p><p>In this context, I would also briefly like to mention the ObSERVE programme.  This programme, which is being undertaken by my Department in partnership with the National Parks and Wildlife Service, is unique to Ireland in its proactive approach to ensuring that the best possible information is available with respect to protected marine species.  This will mean that both regulatory authorities and the petroleum industry are well placed to make decisions in an environmentally robust and sustainable manner.  It is particularly satisfying that the two international consortia that successfully tendered for this work were led by Irish research institutions and that Ireland&rsquo;s national research vessel operated by the Marine Institute will play a key role.  The ObSERVE programme will see extensive aerial surveys being undertaken by a team of researchers led by University College Cork.  In parallel, a research team being led by Galway-Mayo Institute of Technology will deploy special underwater acoustic devices from the <i>RV Celtic Voyager</i>in Ireland&rsquo;s offshore canyon systems, to explore their importance for whales and dolphins.  I am pleased that this innovative Government initiative has been so positively received by industry.</p><p>Returning to regulatory robustness with regard to safety, the offshore safety directive specifically provides for the institutional separation of regulatory functions relating to offshore safety and the environment from those functions that are focused on the economic development of offshore resources, such as licensing and revenue management; a goal-setting approach in major accident prevention based on thorough risk assessment and reliable management systems; clarity on environmental liability in the event of a major accident; and emergency preparedness and response arrangements.  The deadline for the transposition of the directive is 19 July 2015.  This Bill is a relatively short one as the approach to transposition involves integrating the directive requirements with the safety regulatory system for oil and gas exploration, and production activities in Ireland introduced under the Petroleum (Exploration and Extraction) Safety Act 2010.</p><p>The 2010 Act conferred the Commission for Energy Regulation, the CER, with responsibility for the safety regulation of petroleum exploration and extraction activities in Ireland, including a requirement for the CER to establish and implement a petroleum safety framework.  The petroleum safety framework is the system that the CER uses to regulate the safety of petroleum activities carried out by petroleum undertakings licensed to carry out petroleum exploration and extraction activities.  The framework was designed In line with best international practice with petroleum undertakings required to reduce all safety risks to the internationally accepted level that is as low as is reasonably practicable, ALARP.  In conferring this new responsibility on the CER, the 2010 Act gave effect to a key recommendation of the report produced by Advantica following its safety review of the Corrib gas pipeline.  At that time, Advantica had recommended that a new risk assessment-based safety framework with respect to gas pipelines, in line with best international practice, should be developed and implemented in Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This approach is now the commonly accepted methodology for managing safety worldwide.  The Commission for Energy Regulation has successfully operated the petroleum safety framework since December 2013.</p><p>The key requirements of the directive are broadly analogous with the provisions of the 2010 Act.  These requirements are the institutional separation of safety regulation from the economic development of oil and gas resources and a goal-setting approach to major accident prevention.  A significant element of the transposition of the directive involves the introduction of consistent terminology and language.  The main regulatory implications of the directive that are required to be addressed in this Bill are the establishment of a national competent authority, provision for the assessment of potential major environmental hazards offshore within the scope of the safety case regime, clarity on industry liability in the event of a major accident, and specific obligations to be placed on both operators and owners of petroleum infrastructure.</p><p>Before turning to the detail of the Bill, I refer to hydraulic fracturing, an issue about which Deputies might be concerned in the context of these proposals  To clarify, the directive the Bill seeks to transpose relates only to oil and gas activities offshore.  As such, it is concerned solely with the safety regime applying to petroleum exploration and production activities in the offshore area and has no implications whatsoever for unconventional gas exploration and exploitation.</p><p>I shall now outline the detail of this quite technical Bill.  For the convenience of the House, a detailed explanatory memorandum has been published, which provides a synopsis of the Bill&rsquo;s provisions.  There are 24 sections in the Bill.  Part IIA of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999, as amended by the Petroleum (Exploration and Extraction) Safety Act 2010, relates exclusively to the regulation of petroleum activities by the commission.  Almost all of the sections of this Bill amend Part IIA of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999, save for section 23, which amends the Petroleum and Other Mineral Development Act 1960, and section 24, which amends the Continental Shelf Act 1968.  I will deal first with all the sections amending Part IIA of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999 before dealing with sections 23 and 24.</p><p>Section 1 is a standard provision concerning definitions.  Section 2 replaces section 13A of Part IIA of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999 with a new interpretation section that is consistent with the terminology and language of the directive.  Key new definitions include those for "operator" and "owner".  Currently, under Part IIA ,statutory safety responsibilities are placed on petroleum undertakings as licensee only.  The directive provides for three related regulated entities, namely, the licensee, operator and owner, each of which has different responsibilities.  The definitions of "operator" and "owner" in the Bill enable the obligations under the directive to be placed on the relevant entity and integrated with the existing safety regulatory framework for petroleum safety.  These obligations are reflected in various sections throughout the Bill.</p><p>Section 3 inserts a new section 13GA, which establishes the CER as the independent competent authority under the directive where it prescribes the functions of the competent authority.  The principal objective of the CER as competent authority is the effective safety regulatory oversight of operator and owner compliance in reducing the risk and potential consequences of major accidents offshore to a level that is as low as reasonably practicable.</p><p>Section 4 replaces the existing section 13H with a new section 13H which integrates the competent authority functions under section 5 and the directive requirements within the context of the CER's general petroleum safety functions.  The matters to be considered by the CER in carrying out its functions are also set out and include minimising the potential for overlap or duplication of effort.  Emergency preparedness and response constitute an important element of the directive.  In accordance with the Sea Pollution (Amendment) Act 1999, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport is responsible for preparing a national contingency plan which specifies the measures to be taken by the State resulting from discharges of oil from ships, offshore units and oil-handling facilities.  Offshore units operating in the State are required to have in place a plan for the prevention and minimisation of damage arising out of an oil pollution incident occurring on an offshore unit or oil-handling unit facility.  This plan is called the oil pollution emergency plan.  Responsibility for administration of the national contingency plan and assessment of oil pollution emergency plans is a matter for the Irish Coast Guard.</p><p>Section 5 further strengthens the existing emergency preparedness and response arrangements through inserting a new section 13HA, which provides the CER with the power to direct industry to conduct emergency exercises and tests and take adequate measures to ensure the continuing safety of designated petroleum activities.  Section 6 amends section 13I to align with the terminology and language of the directive.  Section 13I requires the CER to establish and implement a risk-based petroleum safety framework through which it will exercise its petroleum safety functions.  As set out earlier, the CER has successfully operated the petroleum safety framework established under the 2010 legislation since December 2013.</p><p>Section 7, which deals with obligations on petroleum undertakings, operators and owners, inserts three new sections, 13KA, 13KB and 13KC, to reflect the general and specific obligations of each of the three related regulated entities under the directive.  These are: the licensee, described in the 2010 Act as the "petroleum undertaking"; the operator, who is appointed by the licensee to carry out oil and gas operations; and the owner, who is the legal entity with operational control of the non-production installation.  Key obligations on petroleum undertakings include the appointment of an operator prior to the carrying out of any designated petroleum activity and financial liability for the prevention and remediation of environmental damage caused by offshore petroleum activities carried out pursuant to a petroleum authorisation.  Key obligations on operators include ensuring the risk of all major accident hazards in carrying out designated petroleum activities is reduced to a level that is as low as is reasonably practicable.  Key obligations on owners include ensuring the risk of all major accident hazards related to the non-production installation carrying out designated petroleum activities is reduced to a level that is as low as is reasonably practicable.</p><p>Section 8, concerning safety case guidelines, replaces section 13L with a new section that requires the contents of the safety case guidelines published by the CER to be consistent with the specific information requirements of the directive.</p><p>Sections 9 to 11, inclusive, replace the existing sections 13M, 13N and 13O with new sections 13M, 13N and 13O which impose an obligation to submit a safety case.  Section 12, which concerns notifications, sets out the regulatory process for the submission, assessment and acceptance or refusal of design notifications and combined-operation notifications by operators to the CER in accordance with the offshore safety directive.  Sections 13 and 14, on safety permits and the refusal or revocation of those permits, amend the existing sections 13P and 13Q to reflect the CER's assessment of safety cases submitted by operators and, where relevant, owners, and the capacity of the operator or owner, as appropriate, to carry out a designated petroleum activity.</p><p>Sections 15 to 18, inclusive, amend the existing sections 13S, 13T, 13U and 13V and relate to the notification of petroleum incidents to the CER by operators or owners, the further investigation and-or taking of enforcement action by the CER regarding the notified petroleum incident, and the issuance of a report by the CER to the Minister with respect to each petroleum incident that results in the loss of human life, serious personal injury, damage to third-party property or a major accident.  This section also makes it an offence for an operator or owner not to comply with its obligation to notify the CER of a petroleum incident.</p><p>Section 19, which deals with improvement plans and notice, amends the existing sections 13Y and 13Z to extend the existing power of the CER to issue a direction requiring the submission of an improvement plan or the serving of an improvement notice upon petroleum undertakings to apply to operators and owners.  Section 20, concerning access to safety case information, amends the existing section 13AC to put the obligation on the relevant operator to provide a mechanism by which a copy of the accepted safety case can be made available to any member of the public who requests it.</p><p>Section 21, which sets out miscellaneous amendments, makes a number of consequential amendments to the Act of 1999 to, among other things, extend the CER's existing enforcement powers to apply to operators and owners in addition to petroleum undertakings and enable the CER to charge operators and owners a safety case fee.  Section 22 amends the Petroleum and Other Minerals Development Act 1960 to require an assessment by the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources of the technical and financial capability of applicants for an offshore petroleum authorisation in line with the offshore safety directive.   This section also makes provision for ministerial approval of the appointment of an operator proposed by a petroleum undertaking.  </p><p>Section 23, an amendment to section 6 of the Continental Shelf Act 1968, modifies the definition of a "designated area" under that Act to align with Article 6(7) of the directive, which requires the establishment of a safety zone in the vicinity of an offshore installation.  Section 24 makes the usual provision for Short Title and citation.</p><p>This Bill is an important measure in the continued strengthening of the overarching regulatory framework governing offshore exploration for oil and gas and the production thereof in Ireland.  The Bill comprehensively transposes the relevant directive in a manner that will enhance the safety of the Irish offshore oil and gas sector, build upon the regulatory model successfully implemented in December 2013 under the 2010 Act and operate at least cost to the industry and the public service.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This legislation will contribute to the achievement of the policy objective of a safe offshore petroleum exploration and extraction industry in Ireland.</p><p>I hope this outline of the provisions of the Bill has been of assistance.  I look forward to listening carefully to the views of the Members of this House on this important legislation and to their assistance in progressing this Bill into law prior to the directive transposition deadline of 19 July 2015.  T&aacute;im ag s&uacute;il go m&oacute;r le ceisteanna agus le molta&iacute; na Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#EE00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and I welcome the delayed Bill to the Seanad.  As the Minister of State will be aware only 2% of the laws made in this country every year actually come before the D&aacute;il and Seanad.  Most of the laws that come into effect in Ireland are EU directives, EU regulations or statutory instruments, signed by Ministers directly into Irish law and they never receive the scrutiny they deserve.  This is one of the few occasions when a directive has to come to the Houses of the Oireachtas to be scrutinised before being passed.  However, as we see, we have less than four weeks to do it even though the directive started out in 2013.</p> <p>The Government and previous Governments have failed to put in place systems in this House, meaning that directives from Europe, many of which are excellent and much needed, are only dealt with at the last minute and do not receive the scrutiny they require.  In 2009 there were 47 Acts of the Oireachtas yet there were more than 1,200 EU regulations, 547 EU directives and nearly 600 statutory instruments.  The legislators only looked after 47 Acts and the rest were done by Ministers and civil servants.</p> <p>The Bill is to be welcomed.  In light of the disaster in the Gulf of Mexico where nearly 8,000 barrels a day, which is nearly 100,000 l, disappeared in the first 24 hours, increasing to 6 million l per day at the height of the disaster, obviously it is very important to have legislation of this nature.  With the estimated 10 billion barrels, 1 trillion l, in oil and gas reserves off the Irish coast, having a proper safety and regulatory system is important.</p> <p>The Minister of State outlined the Bill excellently.  When industry welcomes a Bill introducing safety regulation, we should be concerned.  While the Minister of State has said there is no cost to the Exchequer, was any regulatory impact assessment carried out?  The programme for Government promised that the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform would carry out regulatory impact assessments for Bills such as this.  Obviously, we do not want to put an undue burden on oil and gas industries or suppliers, but it is important to know what the regulatory impact assessment would be.</p> <p>I have concern over the decommissioning of oil and gas platforms.  It is great for the taxpayer that we would get the revenue from it.  However, if a company decides to fold its tent and close up its operations in Ireland, there is no entity to chase for the decommissioning of the platform.  In fact all the money we might have got from the taxation and the levies applied on the industry would then be spent on decommissioning oil and gas platforms.</p> <p>I believe the Minister of State will also be concerned that certain sections of the Bill refer to a maximum amount of money to be applied in fines.  The term "as low as is reasonably practicable" is very much open to interpretation.  I know they are talking about best practice, but I am sure other jurisdictions would have a definition of what is "as low as is reasonably practicable" regarding the prevention of major accidents offshore.</p> <p>We do not have much time.  I know this is a bit like Committee Stage.  We will ram through Committee Stage and I do not blame the Minister of State for that; it is just the way the Bill has come in.  Section 8 deals with safety case guidelines.  It refers to "the appropriate technical principles and specifications relating to... decommissioning of... infrastructure".  Should a bond not be put in place whereby as the Department gives out a licence it also asks the company to put a bond in place so that if it goes to the wall at least we would be able to get the money from the bondholder to decommission the infrastructure?  The concern is that that would be a massive cost on the taxpayer into the future.</p> <p>I am concerned about the lack of sanction over not carrying out requirements by the new authority and also about a limit on the fines.  One of the sections refers to "on conviction on indictment, to a fine not exceeding &euro;3,000,000&rdquo;.  I do not know why we would limit an oil company to a fine not exceeding &euro;3 million.  The cost of the clean-up for the Gulf of Mexico disaster has now reached &euro;14 billion and it has still not finished.  Every now and again BP issues an announcement that the clean-up is finished and then the US Coast Guard states it is not done and there is still more clean-up being done.</p> <p>Section 15 deals with a reportable petroleum incident.  This is why I highlighted the first 24 hours in the Deepwater Horizon disaster.  The Bill refers to the requirement for "information and particulars as may be prescribed by the Commission, without delay, and no later than 24 hours after taking those measures".  That relates to the reporting of an incident.  One of the issues with the Deepwater Horizon incident was that it was not reported early.  The fact that it went on for years was obviously a huge issue.  Section 15(2) states that they do have to report anything within 24 hours and make the State aware.  Failure to do this incurs a fine of &euro;1 million.  One would hope they would do it.  These companies deal in trillions and we are imposing an on-the-spot fine that is equivalent to a parking fine for some of them.</p> <p>The Minister of State spoke about the issues of transparency.  The Bill provides that: "The Commission may, with the consent of the Minister, publish a non-confidential version of the reports."  However, there are also confidential versions, which would lead to a lack of transparency.</p> <p>Obviously, I am concerned over the limited amount of time we have - we had two years to do this and we are doing it in four weeks.  This has happened before and I have spoken many times in this House about the lack of process when it comes to what is essentially a good directive.  I am not giving out about the concept of the directive, but we are missing opportunities, one of the most important of which is consequences for the operators not doing what they should do.</p> <p>We talk about the safety measures required, including fire tenders and other equipment, but do we actually have that in place?  How many fire brigades would be required?  Obviously, because it is mostly offshore, we will need boats that can deal with incidents at sea.  The fire services are provided by the local authorities and do not have these boats hanging around the place.  How many do we have?  How many are required?  If there is an incident and we do not have the equipment, whose fault is it?  To bring it in from the Gulf of Mexico or the North Sea would take days.  Those are the lessons that should have been learned from the Gulf of Mexico disaster - the equipment was not deployed in time.</p> <p>I wanted to make those points.  I know we are supposed to be discussing the generality of the Bill, but in reality we do not have much time to get this right.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Donegal and Kerry could be badly affected by oil rigs just sitting there, which has happened in California and other places because there is an issue around who is going to pay for them to disappear.  We should have a bond system in place on which the Government at least would be able to call in the event of a company no longer being in existence, as that would mean there would be money to pay for the decommissioning of such rigs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" speakername="Tony Mulcahy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#FF00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Joe McHugh.  First, I wish to point out that the Bill was published after the Government had signed off on it on the morning of 16 June.  We were originally due to speak about it last Thursday.  I was told the reason for the short notice was the delay in getting guidance from the European Commission on liability issues, yet we have to transpose the Bill into Irish Law by 19 July.  Surely the Commission with all of its resources could have given this advice earlier.  That is not a reflection on the Minister of State.</p> <p>This is a technical Bill which follows on from the EU offshore safety directive, Directive 2013/30 EU.  One could ask what caused the European Union to introduce the directive.  The answer simply is safety.  Two particular tragic events have brought home to us why we need such legislation.  The European Union reacted to the tragic deaths of 11 oil workers when there was an explosion on the Deepwater Horizon exploration rig in the Gulf of Mexico in April 2010.  This oil production platform had a crew of 126 at the time of the explosion and the disaster could have been worse and resulted in a greater loss of life.  It was also an environmental disaster.  We must transpose the Bill into law to prevent such tragedies from happening in European waters.  The Deepwater Horizon oil rig which had cost $560 million to build had only been in operation since 2001.  It had been designed to operate in deep waters.  Some of the oil and gas prospecting companies off the Irish coast also operate in very deep water.  In September 2009 the Deepwater Horizon rig had successfully drilled the deepest oil well in history when it drilled to a vertical depth of 35,000 ft., in water that was more than 4,000 ft. deep.  The rig was due to move to a new location when the explosion happened.  The fireball was seen more than 40 miles away and resulted in the largest ever oil spill in US coastal waters.  A US federal judge ruled in January this year that BP was responsible for the discharge of 3.2 million barrels of oil into the gulf.  The clean-up could potentially cost $13.7 billion.</p> <p>In April 2010 the Commission for Energy Regulation, CER, was made responsible for safety regulation after the Petroleum (Exploration and Extraction) Safety Act was passed.  It is ironic that the Act was passed when the Deepwater Horizon tragedy was unfolding.  Closer to home, on 6 July 1988 the explosion on the Piper Alpha oil rig in the North Sea cost the lives of 167 oil workers.  On the morning of 6 July a pressure safety valve was removed from a condensate pump for routine maintenance.  The original paperwork stated pump A was due for routine service.  It was one of two pumps on the rig used to pump oil 128 miles by pipeline to Scotland for refining.  The on-duty engineer filled in a permit which stated pump A was not to be used under any circumstance.  The day shift ended at 6 p.m., but, unfortunately, the engineer failed to inform the new shift of the off-line status of pump A.  The paperwork was located in another part of the platform.  At 9.45 p.m., a simple fault in the gas compression system resulted in a blockage in pump B and the pump could not be restarted.  At 9.52 p.m., the shift manager found the original paperwork which stated pump A was due to be serviced, but he did not have the paperwork which stated it was now out of service and not to be used.  He turned pump A back on, unaware of what was about to happen.  Three minutes later, at 9.55 p.m., gas that flowed through the unsafe pump A leaked out and there was an explosion which caused several fires and further explosions.  The flames from the fires could be seen 100 km away.  It took three weeks for the fires to be put out by a team led by the famous firefighter, Red Adair.  By 12.45 a.m.on the morning of 7 July the complete platform was destroyed, with the loss of 167 lives out of a total crew of 226.  A simple breakdown in communication and bad safety procedures caused massive loss of life.  That is why we need to have a vigorous safety enforcement regime in European waters to protect both workers and the environment.  </p> <p>The amendment to the 2010 legislation will further strengthen the current regulations governing offshore oil and gas operators.  Safety inspections must be regular and robust.  I urge the Minister of State to ensure that whatever resources are needed to ensure inspections take place are provided in order that we do not have more tragedies.</p> <p>I echo the point made on bonds by Senator Mark Daly who has left the Chamber.  Having a bond is a good idea to ensure we can deal with the problem of left-over rigs.  A fine of up to &euro;3 million is very small money when it comes to the cost of cleaning up following an oil spill.  I urge the Minister of State to consider these points when making his concluding remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#FF00300"><p>Cuirim c&eacute;ad f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  T&aacute; br&oacute;n orm go raibh m&eacute; beag&aacute;n mall ag teacht anseo.  T&aacute; m&eacute; s&aacute;sta go bhfuil an Rialtas tar &eacute;is admh&aacute;il go raibh s&eacute; m&iacute;-cheart agus go raibh s&eacute; ag teacht isteach lena oiread fuadair agus lena oiread deifre air leis an reachta&iacute;ocht seo.  T&aacute; an reachta&iacute;ocht seo thar a bheith t&aacute;bhachtach agus t&aacute; s&eacute; f&iacute;or-th&aacute;bhachtach go bhfaighimid deis ceart &eacute; a phl&eacute; trasna an T&iacute;.</p><p>Directive 2013/30 EU which the Bills seeks to transpose into Irish law was published more than two years ago on 12 June 2013.  We wondered why the Government had sought to rush the Bill through the House last week.  There are certain elements in Irish society which are concerned when they see something about oil and gas, in particular, coming through with such haste.  I am pleased that the Government has given us more time to ascertain the impact of the Bill on oil and gas operations in this country.  It is not appropriate to carry out business in this House in that manner and I am pleased this has been acknowledged and that the Leader has provided more time for us to reflect on the legislation.</p><p>This House has a history of rushing legislation through in a haphazard manner.  The bailout of the banks and the winding down of IBRC immediately spring to mind.  Neither does this House have a good record concerning offshore oil and gas safety operations.  An example of where engagement with the community seriously failed is the Corrib gas project and the effect it had on the community of Rossport.  The Rossport project is important because it involves a dispute about ownership and the use of natural resources.  It illustrates the threats posed to local communities by a powerful coalition of State and capital interests and as a consequence raises serious questions about the link between politics and power.  Locals opposed to the development frame their opposition in terms of safety and health.  They claim the pressure of unprocessed gas in the pipeline will be too high; that the pipeline will be too close to people&rsquo;s homes and that the environmental effects of gas transportation and processing will be devastating to the place, people and wildlife.  They want the gas to be processed offshore.  I note the sad death of Lars Wagner in a workplace incident in the Corrib gas tunnel in 2013.  I wonder whether the Bill under discussion would have addressed the situation that led to his death.  Has the Government received a full report on the incident and, if so, will it make it available to us?</p><p>Landowners also took issue with a high pressured pipeline running through their land and protested against what they believed to be an infringement of their rights.  As a result, in March 2005, Shell applied to the High Court for an order restraining landowners from interfering with the laying of the pipeline.  An injunction was given and five local people were imprisoned for interfering with the work of Shell.  These people became known as the Rossport Five.  Many maintain that the Government was complicit in the failure to engage with the local community.  Local people believe they were ignored by the Government and that private business was allowed a free hand in developing energy infrastructure as it wished.  This European directive appears to be well meaning.  We will examine it and introduce amendments on Committee Stage.</p><p>In May 2012 the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Communcations, Natural Resources and Agriculture published a fairly comprehensive report and made recommendations on the industry.  I have not seen much progress by the Government on the issues raised.  The 11 recommendations include the following: <blockquote>1. Having good basic law in which policy principles are enshrined can greatly assist a country in developing and benefitting from its petroleum resources.<br /><br />There should be a clear and transparent fiscal and licensing regime, which provides certainty for the State and industry alike. <br /><br />The Joint Committee recommends that a simple and transparent system be put in place which is underpinned by clear law.  To this end, the Petroleum and Other Minerals Act 1960<i></i>should be reviewed.<br /><br />Retrospective changes to fiscal and licensing terms can risk long-term reputational damage.  Existing agreements should be adhered to irrespective of changing circumstances.<br /><br />In contrast, future agreements can reflect policy changes necessitated by significant changes in the policy context and circumstances, for example a large increase in the number of commercially viable finds or the size of fields.<br /><br />3. Recognising that fields may be subject to corporation tax and profit resource rent tax (PRRT), the State should seek to maximise tax revenues from petroleum exploration and production without deterring petroleum investment.</blockquote>In addition, the report stated: &quot;4. The Joint Committee strongly believes that the State should keep fiscal and licencing terms under constant review.&quot;  It concluded: <blockquote>The obtaining of geological data from all licensees is of paramount importance ... This would entail mandatory unified operations for a field extending over different contractual zones by different operators and offers advantages including better resource management.</blockquote>Eleven recommendations were made in total.  Will the Minister of State, please, outline where we are in terms of their implementation?  There is a great rush to get the Bill through the House.  An Oireachtas joint committee's report has been sitting on the shelf since 2012 and it does not appear that any action has been taken.  There has been a complete lack of action.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2363"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2363&amp;amp;pid=TrevorOClochartaigh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is a fear that in that void the oil companies are being <i>laissez-faire</i>.  I note the Ballyroe oil find off the coast of Cork is 1.7 billion barrels.  Can the Minister of State outline what other oil finds there may be and the potential tax income for the State?  If the Government took on board the recommendations of the joint committee would there be a much greater income for the State?  There were very specific recommendations around the tax take in particular and we need to ensure that the natural resources of the State are used for the benefit of all the people and that the oil companies pay a greater share of the profits they make.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" speakername="John Whelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#GG00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and I commend him on bringing forward the legislation.  It seems to me that in some quarters one is damned if one does and one is damned if one does not.  The legislation is in the House but not before its time and there is a deadline on it.  It is important that it is passed in the interest of public safety, the people who work in the industry and, of course, the broader environmental issues that are at stake.  In his address he set out in great detail the provisions of the Bill.  On the face of it, the legislation that has emerged appears to be thorough and robust.  It is vitally important that is transposed into Irish law.</p> <p>Senator Tony Mulcahy has set out two examples of the kinds of incidents that can occur with devastating and disastrous consequences for the workers and the environment.  Therefore, any measures that can be put in place to prevent such incidents should be put in place.  We have only to get these things wrong once and then it is too late.  We are dealing with the area of prevention.  Once an incident occurs it is too late to address it.  Colleagues across the floor have made valid observations which should be taken into consideration.  A bond is a good idea.  Who is going to chase down the developers of the sector and the industry once a rig or a well has expired and run its course?  It is important that the infrastructure is not left to rust at sea or in close proximity to the shoreline and whatever other infrastructure is in place.  The onus is on anybody who has developed rigs and wells to put things back as they found them and to decommission the facilities properly.  There have been incidents around the country where that has not always been the case.  It has happened in the case of mining developments and in the chronic situation in Cork where the taxpayer continues to pick up the tab for restoring facilities in the former Irish Steel plant in Cork harbour.  Again, the taxpayer has had to clean up a really dangerous hazard and environmental mess left behind by the industry when it closed down.  It is important we do not have those kind of scenarios.</p> <p>We have a pitiful record in terms of enforcement of regulations from child safety to financial regulation to charities regulation.  I do not have any confidence whatsoever in the Environmental Protection Agency in terms of how it goes about its business.  I am glad it is not the assigned authority in this instance.  The CER has been selected as the competent authority.  In terms of resources, competence, skill sets and staffing how will it police the legislation?  How will it ensure compliance?  In recent decades basic building regulations were not adhered to or respected.  We can have all the rules and regulations we want but if they are not enforced and policed, they are virtually pointless.  We found out after the building boom was over that only a small percentage of building developments were inspected by planners to ensure that the conditions that had been applied had been adhered to.  </p> <p>This is important, robust and timely legislation but it will not be worth the paper it is written on unless the competent authority, in this case the CER, has the resources to ensure and insist on compliance and that, as colleagues have pointed out, the penalties for non-compliance are sufficiently imposing to ensure shortcuts will not be taken.  As we have noted in the House, the consequences for human life, wildlife, sea birds, fish stocks and the broader environment and ecosystems could be devastating in the extreme for generations to come should an accident occur.</p> <p>It is welcome that this legislation is before the House and it is important that we tease it out here, but my concern is that the regulations as set out should not be dealt with in a light touch, self-regulating or self-policing fashion.  The CER should have the teeth, the personnel, the skill sets and the resources to police this legislation and to ensure it is enforced and complied with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#GG00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it. The Minister has been a regular here for many years.  We get on very well together and he puts a lot of effort into his work and it is good to see him back again.</p> <p>I note that this particular directive is about minimising risks of offshore accidents throughout the European Union, a move in the right direction, but I want to make some comments on the area of safety.  I wonder if companies involved in risky operations could put up some sort of insurance in order that a quick clean-up operation could happen if an accident did occur.  I understand that such companies would have insurance but perhaps there could be a dedicated environmental fund in case an accident that affected the environment occurred.  Given that this is a directive, we have some flexibility on how the legislation is transposed into Irish legislation and perhaps we should include such a provision, particularly when we consider some of the disasters that have occurred in the Gulf of Mexico and off Alaska.  Those large companies were probably well able to cover it but that would not always happen.  If we were to approve some test for hydraulic fracturing in Ireland, we could get companies to pay into an environmental fund to give extra assurances, especially to the local population, that the environment around them would not be neglected.  I heard what the Minister said earlier about fracturing, and I will come to that shortly.</p> <p>The new legislation calls for all EU member states to prepare external emergency response plans covering all offshore drilling installations within their authority.  While I do not doubt that our national authorities can draw up such plans, I wonder if we have the necessary equipment to put them into practice.  For instance, I know that if we had a spill we could rely on the Air Corps to do some sort of aerial assessment but could it do such a job even more effectively if it had resources such as more unmanned aerial vehicles on which to rely?  I do not know.  Someone can fly over it and see where it is but if we cannot do something about it, without getting access using boats or whatever, having the knowledge but not having the equipment would be a disadvantage.  Being able to cope with possible offshore accidents may require more investment.  The Minister of State might comment on that area.</p> <p>I was disappointed to hear the Minister of State say earlier that shale fracturing has no implications onshore in Ireland.  I am disappointed that we are not even discussing it.  We should discuss it.  In terms of wider safety, this month, the Environmental Protection Agency said that its two year study into the safety issues linked with hydraulic fracturing for shale gas in Ireland is due to conclude in July 2016.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Feargal Quinn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1972"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1972&amp;amp;pid=FergalQuinn&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That means that even if fracking was deemed safe, no exploratory application would likely be received until close to 2018.  That seems to be a very lengthy period.  I do not wish to sound as though I am encouraging, proposing or believing in it but I believe we should be discussing the whole question of hydraulic fracturing and I do not think we are.  In the UK the Prime Minister is aiming to cut red tape for companies which want to conduct exploratory hydraulic fracturing.  I cannot say that fracking is either right or wrong but we are moving extremely slowly in this area.  When one considers the benefits the United States has had since the 1940s and 1950s with practically no disadvantages, it seems to me they have been able to solve the oil and energy crisis on that basis.  I believe we should be discussing it at least.  Perhaps the Minister of State will be able to tell me whether we are planning to discuss it.</p><p>Hydraulic fracturing has been around since the 1940s and it seems that Ireland will not go down that route, as things stand.  It is really a taboo subject in a lot of ways.  In spite of the fact that thousands of jobs could be created and we could drastically reduce our energy costs for both households and businesses, as well as reducing our reliance on energy imports, we have a culture of NIMBY, not in my back yard.  Professor Quentin Fisher is an expert in this area who says that drilling a well is noisy and disruptive but after a few weeks only a building the size of a garden shed remains.  He says that people may change their minds once they see how safe it is.  I ask for the Minister of State's comments on hydraulic fracturing and safety.  I am convinced that it is a topic we need to discuss and I am not sure that we are even taking the first steps towards a real discussion of it.  In Britain they have decided and it was announced yesterday that they will initiate the process in Lancashire.  Some people are not happy about it and there are some protests but on the other hand it is the sort of decision we have to be discussing and I ask for the Minister of State's views.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#HH00200"><p>I thank Senators for their contributions.  I agree it would be good to have a broad debate where people offer a critique.  While this legislation is very specific, it provides an opportunity to discuss a number of items.</p> <p>Senator Daly made a wider argument around the transposition of EU directives.  I share his frustration.  I refer to the 1992 habitats directive and the tensions which have arisen in his county and my county as a result of the directive being implemented and enforced.  However, there is a deadline on the directive which we are discussing now.  As Senator Whelan pointed out we have a deadline and our European partners share that deadline.  The Senator referred to culpability for what happened in the Gulf of Mexico and issues associated with BP.  He asked whether an assessment of the regulatory impact was undertaken.  The 2010 Act provides that the Commission for Energy Regulation has responsibility to ensure we follow through with the commitments we gave under that legislation.  The decommissioning of oil and gas platforms is an issue.  While it is not within the remit of this legislation, it is important to have that discussion.  It is an issue in the waters off the south coast of Cork.  There have been four successful gas finds in this country.  The momentum is good and positive with regard to the current Atlantic margin round which closes in mid-September and it is our success to date.</p> <p>The focus of the legislation is specific and narrow.  I refer to the framework regarding culpability, liability and responsibility.  Much of the work on the culpability conversation will happen after the Bill.  An EU report on culpability and liability is due in the autumn. I would not like to see bigger companies coming together to establish an exclusive insurance bond for themselves only.  We must ensure there is a level playing field for small companies.  An in-depth conversation is needed in this regard.</p> <p>There is no outer limit on environmental costs.  I will ask for further clarification on the figure of &euro;3 million.  Responsibility for a contingency plan lies with the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  The Coast Guard has responsibility for the implementation of the contingency plan.  Those of us of the same age were not part of the Internet generation and we were not brought up with broadband.  That is certainly the case with regard to County Kerry and County Donegal.  This is European legislation and an oil spill off the west coast of Ireland will need a collaborative approach from Europe.  We can share resources as members of the European Union.  That is outside the remit of this Bill but it is a conversation we could have.</p> <p>Senator Mulcahy mentioned fines and the &euro;3 million which I have dealt with.  I appreciate his points about more time but unfortunately we have a strict deadline as this is important legislation.  I note his points about the incident in the Gulf of Mexico and how to have a mitigating plan in place to avoid such situations.  He referred to the Petroleum (Exploration and Extraction) Safety Act 2010 and the recognition of the need for vigilance and a safety regime.  He spoke about clean-up costs which are dealt with under section 22(2).  The liability for environmental damage is not limited to &euro;3 million as I mentioned earlier in reply to Senator Daly.  The State will have to agree the liability for different operations.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh raised a number of issues.  He speaks as fast in English as he does in Irish-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#HH00300"><p>That is for sure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#HH00400"><p>-----which is no mean feat.  He covered many issues, including the general interaction with politics and power.  Even in the health sector there is a jargon phrase, "clinical networking", meaning consultants, the pharma industry or health departments working together on solutions.  From my short time in this Department I have noted the very strong collaborative spirit between industry and officials in efforts to work together to share resources and advice and ensuring environmental sustainability.  The officials in my Department are working on behalf of the political representatives on behalf of the people.  There is a high level of collaborative work on information about the sea bed.  Ireland is the fourth largest country in Europe when one considers the geographical size of our land mass under the sea after France, Portugal and Spain.  It is hoped that industry and officialdom can work together in assessing what is available and mitigate environmental damage.  Wearing my other hat, this is very important within the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht and the National Parks and Wildlife Service working hand in glove with the Department of Communications, Energy and Natural Resources on the protection of wildlife or other habitats that could be affected as a result of industry-led development.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=06&amp;amp;day=24"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Senator referred to the death in Corrib.  I will get the Senator information on that.  Those in the best position to talk about what happened in Corrib are the people who live there.  I had an opportunity to go to Bellanaboy and various parts of Bellmullet recently to hear a debate.  As with any debate, there is passion on both sides.  It was apparent to me that there were many economic benefits to the development.  Certainly, there were lessons in terms of regulation and enforcement as well.  Many lessons have been learned.  This has been a dragged-out project.  When the operation is commissioned initially it will provide up to 40% of all our gas needs in the short term.<br/><br/>There will be constraints on the fiscal potential or possibilities as a result of one thing and another in terms of a delay.  It is important to move forward.  Much work has gone on behind the scenes, including the Wood Mackenzie report.  The work includes looking at re-addressing the matter within the finance Bill this year, looking at the fiscal regime moving from 40% to 55% and looking at other ways of trying to get revenue once production starts.  That relates to future finds and does not affect existing finds.<br/><br/>We need to consider the context as well.  A drill can cost upwards of &euro;200 million.  Is the State prepared to put that type of investment into a risk that may find an empty field?  We need to keep in mind all these considerations.  We can learn from it, and we must put community to the heart of any new development.  I will digress a little.  Let us consider wind farms.  There are wind farms in my county.  The Donegal local authority gets over &euro;1.2 million in development charges or a rate base per annum.  At a local or micro level there are probably better, smarter and more clever ways of trying to ensure that communities get the dividend as well.  We can learn from that.<br/><br/>I do not agree with the comments on a <i>laissez-faire</i>attitude to companies.  Within the narrow confines of this legislation, companies must have a contingency plan and consider risk assessment.  They will have to show that they are prepared for a possible failure, if that happens.<br/><br/>Senator Whelan commented on how we need to learn from our history.  In our short history we have learned from the building boom.  We know that a serious lack of oversight and a <i>laissez-faire</i>attitude led to what happened today.  I met a developer in Letterkenny recently.  He has welcomed the new regulations on building control.  This will cost him more, delay his project and his profits will be reduced, but he has welcomed the new regulations.  The point is that we can learn from what has happened within the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government in respect of regulation.  That is what we are trying to do in this Bill as well.<br/><br/>Senator Whelan referred to decommissioning.  The matter is outside this legislation.  I appreciate his comments on trying to get this legislation through.  I note Senator Whelan's observations on the Environmental Protection Agency and his confidence in the Commission for Energy Regulation.  I do not agree with the former observation but I acknowledge the fact that there are areas where we can do better.  The CER has been doing this work since 2010.  The commission has been acting as an oversight body and it is important to note that.<br/><br/>A good point was made about resources and skill-sets.  Do we have the necessary resources?  How do we police the legislation?  How do we ensure an appropriate monitoring system?  How do we ensure compliance?  The CER is a competent authority and has the resources.  Our Department has been recruiting experts in the relevant fields.  The Department aspires towards looking at different skill-sets in different parts of Europe.  Let us consider the example of civil servants in Norway and the United Kingdom.  Perhaps we could be clever or smarter in looking at exchange programmes to bring that skill-set into this country.  For example, pre-2008 officials from Denver, Colorado engaged with counterparts in Germany and Denmark to try to build up a skill-set around renewable energy.  There may be clever ways of doing that.  Officials within the Department are looking at those areas and I wish to acknowledge that.<br/><br/>I thank Senator Quinn for welcoming me back to the House.  I am pleased to be here again.  The critique offered in this House is as good as ever and I acknowledge the Senator's contribution.  He referred to the offshore fund and whether the fund was a parent company.  Much of that will have to be worked out post this legislation.  This is an opportunity to offer suggestions on the matter.<br/><br/>Senator Quinn also referred to unconventional hydraulic extraction.  I did not use the word &quot;fracking&quot; but the Senator is right in that is exactly what it is.  As he is aware, a report has been commissioned.  A particular company or agency is involved but it is a multifaceted approach and involves universities and third level expertise, North and South.  I look forward to the outcome of the report.  I agree with the Senator that in the meantime the debate should continue.  Politicians are not precluded from debating the matter and perhaps there is an opportunity to do that.  Whatever the report shows up, it will be the outcome of two main pillars in terms of concern, that is to say, human impact and environmental concerns.  The report will also consider the geology and whether it is conducive or otherwise to carrying out this particular procedure.  We need to look at all of these factors and feed in to the process at a political level.  I agree that the debate should continue.<br/><br/>I made a reference to financial liability.  A report is due in the autumn in this regard.  I will ensure that my officials present the House with the findings from the European Union in the autumn.<br/><br/>I thank the Acting Chairman and I acknowledge the patience of Members in recent days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.170" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" speakername="Imelda Henry" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#JJ00300"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" speakername="Tony Mulcahy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015062400002#JJ00400"><p>Next Tuesday, 30 June 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.173" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 30 June 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-06-24a.174" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.10 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>