<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator Hildegarde Naughton that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for the Office of Public Works to outline the present readiness of the national flood defence programme in consideration of the record tides forecast for the west coast later this month.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Marc MacSharry of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to review the beef genomics scheme in consultation with suckler farmers to make it more workable for them and to ensure that its implementation maintains the quality of weanling production for smaller farmers in the north west of Ireland.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Bradford of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to reflect fully on all issues concerning the suggested merger of Cork city and county councils and if he will ensure that a full and inclusive debate takes place before any final decisions are made.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Terry Leyden of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide funding of an estimated &euro;13 million for the development of a new 50-bed single-occupancy facility with <i>en suite</i>toilet and shower facilities at the Sacred Heart Hospital, Roscommon.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator David Cullinane of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health, in respect of Waterford city and county, to provide a breakdown of waiting times for assessments, including diagnostic assessments for children with mild to profound physical and intellectual disabilities, and the number of speech, language and occupational therapy posts, in addition to child psychologist posts, and to outline how many child psychologist and therapy posts in the public system are vacant and the steps he will take to reduce assessment waiting times.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Naughton, MacSharry, Bradford and Leyden, and they will be taken now.  Senator Cullinane may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#B00200">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#B00300">Flood Prevention Measures</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#B00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Simon Harris, for coming to the Seanad this afternoon.  As he will know, the long-range weather forecast has estimated that severe flooding will occur in the west, particularly Galway city, in the coming days.  Water heights are estimated to rise to 20 ft., which is much higher than the quay wall at the Spanish Arch in Galway city.  Any such high tides will undoubtedly put at risk areas of the city in close proximity to the promenade in Salthill and the Claddagh, and businesses and locals are very concerned about the impact.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Hildegarde Naughton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2395"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2395&amp;amp;pid=HildegardeNaughton&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Any such high tides will undoubtedly put at risk areas of the city that are in close proximity to the promenade in Salthill and the Claddagh.  Businesses and locals are very concerned about the impact that this will have.  As the Minister of State will recall, on the last occasion high tides caused enormous water damage in Galway.  While it is good to see that Galway City Council has indicated that its new aquadam will be deployed at the Spanish Arch in order to alleviate matters, if bad weather accompanies the flooding, that might not be sufficient to prevent the repeat of previous flooding.  In light of that, I ask the Minister of State to outline where the national flood risk management programme now stands.  I understand that public meetings are taking place to develop a regional plan but there is a great need for these plans to be finalised and the necessary funding be put in place.  </p><p>I ask the Minister of State, on behalf of the Government, to commit to providing whatever funding would be required for remedial and repair work should the forecasted floods become a reality in Galway and the west.</p><p>Would it be possible to get a statement on the current state of affairs in regard to the River Clare in Claregalway?  There was severe flooding there, as the Minister of State is aware, almost six years ago, on 21 November.  Lawyers have been involved with regard to the progress of the works on the River Clare but there are people there who cannot sell their homes or who cannot get insurance because of the delays with this flood relief work.  I ask the Minister of State to update the House on the state of those works.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Naughton for giving me the opportunity to address the Seanad on these matters.  The Office of Public Works has arrangements in place with consultants to provide a tidal and storm surge forecasting service for the coast of Ireland to local authorities and to other relevant stakeholders during the autumn and winter period.  This service is now operating for the 2015 to 2016 autumn and winter period.  This service is provided twice daily and results are presented via a project website, which is password restricted, in the form of a surge, astronomical tide and total water level time series prediction approximately 65 hours in advance.  That provides advanced information to local authorities.  The service currently provides a low resolution storm surge forecast via website at 15 locations around the national coastline together with a high resolution forecast in Dundalk Bay, Galway Bay, Wexford Harbour, Cork Harbour and the Shannon Estuary.  High tide advisory notices are issued from time to time as deemed necessary by the OPW during periods of anticipated combined high tides and storm surge.  The OPW is monitoring closely the current surge forecasts for the upcoming high astronomical tides expected between Saturday, 26 September, and Friday, 2 October, and will issue a high tide advisory notice if deemed necessary in the event of anticipated coastal flood risk.</p> <p>Following the severe weather from 13 December 2013 to 6 January 2014, which caused widespread damage across the southern and western seaboards, the Government decided on 11 February 2014 to make available up to &euro;69.5 million based on estimates provided for repair works by local authorities for a programme of repair and remediation works to be carried out by those local authorities to roads, coastal protection and flood defences and other public infrastructure damaged in those storms.  Of the total amount available, up to &euro;19.6 million was made available through the Office of Public Works for the repair of damaged coastal protection and flood defence infrastructure.  A further &euro;48.7 million was made available through other Departments for restoration of damaged roads, local authority infrastructure, tourism, amenity and community infrastructure and piers and harbours, including those owned by the Department of Agriculture, Food and Marine, and for other transport infrastructure, including Irish Rail, Shannon Airport and the Irish Coast Guard.  A further &euro;1.2 million was made available for repair to OPW's own infrastructure.</p> <p>The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government wrote to all affected local authorities indicating that, based on the estimates submitted by them to the Department, the amounts being made available to the councils to undertake the necessary repairs works, including the amounts available via the OPW in respect of the cost of repairs to damaged coastal protection and flood defence infrastructure in the country.  Local authorities submitted programmes of works to the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government and other Departments and the OPW indicating how they proposed to spend the allocation made available to them.  The OPW has also written to the local authorities indicating that in order to assist them in a practical way and to avoid any potential cash flow issues, it would consider requests for advance funding of up to 80% where a contract for works had been made. </p> <p>Of the &euro;19.6 million made available via the OPW, approximately &euro;13.7 million was allocated to the local authorities in counties Clare, Galway and Mayo, reflecting the severe damage done in those counties.  To date, the local authorities have drawn down over &euro;8.6 million of the full allocation of &euro;19.6 million available to them from the OPW.  The allocation is expected to be fully drawn down by the end of 2015.  A large number of the projects included in the programme of works submitted to the local authorities are now completed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Irish coastal protection strategy study has surveyed and assessed the coastal erosion and flood risk along the entire national coastline, and this information is available to all local authorities to enable them to develop appropriate plans and strategies for the sustainable management of the coastline in their counties, including the identification, prioritisation and, subject to the availability of resources, implementation of coastal protection works, both of a structural and non-structural nature.  This office has provided funding to Clare, Galway, Louth, Sligo and Wexford for coastal risk management studies of main at-risk areas identified by these counties.  It must be emphasised that the management of problems of coastal protection in any particular area is first and foremost a matter for the relevant local authority.  With regard to the question of upgrading existing built defences or constructing new defences, this would depend primarily on the council's assessment of the measures that would be appropriate at a particular location.  Local authorities must assess the problem in the first instance and, if it is considered that specific measures and works are required, it is open to them to apply for funding to deal with coastal protection works under the Office of Public Works' minor flood mitigation works and coastal protection scheme.  <br/><br/>In addition to the storm damage repair funding, which is a one-off measure to reinstate built coastal defences to their pre-storm condition, the OPW operates a capital works programme for the provision of flood defences nationally.  In the six years from 2009 to 2014, the OPW has expended more than &euro;250 million of taxpayers' money under the programme on the development and implementation of major flood relief schemes, the catchment flood risk assessment and management programme and the minor flood mitigation and coastal works programmes.  In addition to the capital works programme, we also carry out a maintenance programme on all arterial drainage schemes.  Included in the major flood relief schemes being advanced are coastal schemes at Skibbereen and Clonakilty.<br/><br/>The OPW is currently undertaking, as the Senator says, the national catchment flood risk assessment and management programme, CFRAM, which is the principal vehicle for implementing the EU floods directive and forms the strategic focus of national flood policy.  Engineering consultants have been appointed to implement the programme through six regional studies.  Local authorities and other stakeholders are also involved in partnership with the OPW on steering groups and progress groups across the six study areas.  This programme, which is vast and is focusing on 300 areas for further assessment, including 90 coastal areas, involves the production of predictive flood risk and hazard mapping for each location, the development of preliminary flood risk management options and the production of flood risk management plans.  Under the programme, the draft maps have been produced and are already online for all to see and were the subject of a programme of local public consultation which concluded in April 2015.  The flood maps will be finalised following a national consultation scheduled for late 2015.  A programme of local public consultation on the preliminary flood risk management options is under way.  Further information is available on <i>cfram.ie</i>.<br/><br/>As part of CFRAM, a condition survey of flood defence assets is being undertaken for entry into a flood defence database.  I would also make the point that, in the context of capital, this will require significant investment of possibly up to &euro;1 billion over ten years.  As a country we currently spend about &euro;42 million a year on flood mitigation measures.  In fairness to the last Government and this one, that is a level that has been maintained through difficult years.  We now need to see that seriously increase so that we can deliver the CFRAM programme.  The programme is making significant progress and we expect by the spring of next year to be rolling out the solutions to those 300 areas, where there are possible solutions.  <br/><br/>In terms of the events that may happen in Galway in relation to astronomical tides, we will continue to closely monitor them and we will keep in touch with the Senator on that.  I will update the Senator on Claregalway in the next round.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply.  I look forward to the national flood risk management programme continuing its work but we also need to have the long-term plan put in place.  As the Minister of State states, this will take a multi-annual approach and continual investment so that we can protect our coastline against events such as those that have happened in the past.  Does the Minister of State have an update on the Clare River situation?  Many people living in the Claregalway area are at a loss as to when this is going to happen.  They are looking for a date with regard to when these works can proceed.  Many of them cannot get insurance on their houses or sell their houses at the moment.  I would appreciate an update in this House today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#D00300"><p>I agree with the Senator that we need a national plan.  When CFRAM is concluded, we will for the first time in the history of the State have a national flood mapping exercise.  However, more than just mapping the problem, we will also have structural solutions where they exist for each of the problems.  That will provide a roadmap for this and future Governments to deliver once and for all on the major infrastructural projects that need to be delivered in relation to flood mitigation.</p> <p>The Senator also touched on the issue of flood insurance.  There are a range of issues related to flooding that fall well outside the remit of the Office of Public Works.  Flood forecasting falls within the remit of the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government.  Flood insurance and insurance policies are the responsibility of the Department of Finance.  I have reconvened the interdepartmental group which brings together all the Departments with responsibility for various elements of what I call the whole of Government approach we need to take and that is due to report to Cabinet early next year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> In relation to Claregalway, I sense and share the frustration of residents in Senator Naughton's part of the country.  The OPW has committed to fully funding this scheme.  That funding is available and our expenditure profile is up to 2017.  As the Senator may be aware, under a different European directive, once we carry out an environmental income statement, and follow the other necessary statutory processes, it must be independently reviewed by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  That is where that is at.  I hope it does not take much longer.  I expect that works can start at the end of this year or early next year.  I am very much aware that residents want the work to start as quickly as possible but from an OPW perspective the funding is fully in place and it is in our profiles right up to 2017.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.16" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#E00200">Beef Data Programme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#E00300"><p>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for accepting the matter.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Simon Harris.  My matter relates specifically to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and while I accept it is not within the Minister of State's area of responsibility, I appreciate him coming to give a response.  The matter relates to the beef genomics scheme on which I have consulted with suckler farmers throughout most of the north west of the country.  The scheme is turning out to be totally unworkable and its implementation threatens the quality of weanling beef output in the north west.  I can only provide examples from counties that are close to mine.  In Donegal, Sligo and Leitrim some 12,800 farmers were eligible to apply for the scheme but fewer than 5,500 have applied.</p> <p>The cost of the scheme is &euro;52 million.  It was designed to assist farmers but, in effect, the science behind it will adversely impact on the type of weanling that is being produced by farmers throughout the north west.  Times are very difficult for farmers in the north west.  We have smaller holdings, longer winters and land that is of a lesser quality to other parts of the country but yet have been renowned for breeding the highest quality stock for export and processing for many years.</p> <p>The Minister of State might be aware, but the Minister will certainly be aware, that in recent weeks farmers are being informed about the grading of the cows.  They are finding that the cows that are producing the highest possible quality of weanling are being given a grading of two stars.  If the scheme works in the way the Irish Cattle Breeding Federation, ICBF, the IFA at a senior level and the Department seem to want it to work, we are going to end up with a much more maternal-focused herd rather than a paternal one.  We need a healthy mix.  In the first instance the scheme does not help the small farmers of the north west and the other parts of the country and does not serve to increase the quality of the type of output from the north west, which is already renowned as producing the finest store cattle and replacement cattle in Ireland.  Something must be done in that regard.</p> <p>A total of &euro;8 million of the &euro;52 million will go not to farmers but to the genomics testing.  One wonders what the ultimate contribution will be.  The Minister of State may know, but the Minister, Deputy Coveney, certainly knows, the money is derived from Pillar 2, in terms of funding under the Common Agricultural Policy, CAP.  There may have been a big uptake on the scheme generally as there are very large dairy and suckler farmers in the south of the country but it is not working in the north west.  It would be much better for the 12,800 eligible farmers in the north west where testing costs approximately &euro;1,000, if that money were made available through the payment to areas of natural constraint, what is traditionally known as the disadvantaged area scheme payment, which was substantially reduced.  It was originally introduced in the late 1970s and early 1980s to keep people on the land and to ensure the continuation of production.  Production has been of the highest quality in the north west in terms of weanling production.  Some 40% of the country&rsquo;s entire output of young calves comes from the area and that is now under threat.  The scheme is unworkable and is costing money.  It is not serving the purpose we need it to serve.  I appeal to the Minister of State to impress upon the Minister, Deputy Coveney, to undertake a full review of the scheme at least in the north west where it is not working.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marc MacSharry:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2010"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2010&amp;amp;pid=MarcMacSharry&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While I appreciate that it is not the Minister of State's line and while I appreciate him being here on behalf of the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, it would be remiss of me not to mention while he is here that the announced scheme for villages and towns is a very sad indictment of any Government, particularly this one.  It is less than &euro;190,000 per county, per year over six years.  Every Government over the past 30 years has been guilty of not adequately resourcing our regions and rural areas to enable them to reach their potential.  If any Government is committed to doing that, it needs to think in terms of billions over a six-year period to strategically target resources for the regions to empower them to reach their potential.  I hope the Minister of State will take that on board.  </p><p>First and foremost is the necessary review of the beef genomics scheme.  There is &euro;52 million there that I do not believe is going to serve an adequate purpose.  It should be diverted, as I have suggested, to the areas of natural constraint or what would have been known as the disadvantaged area payment.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#F00200"><p>I thank Senator MacSharry.  I am pleased to be here on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, who regrets that he cannot be here.</p> <p>The beef data and genomics programme, BDGP, was launched by the Minister on 5 May last.  It is part of Ireland's Rural Development Programme 2014-2020 and involves funding of some &euro;300 million over the next six years and builds on the State's investment in data recording and genomics in recent years.  It aims to address widely acknowledged weaknesses in the maternal genetics of the Irish suckler herd, reduce the greenhouse gas intensity of Ireland's beef production and make a positive contribution to the future viability of suckler farmers and the national suckler herd.</p> <p>Beef accounts for 35% of the gross output of the agriculture sector.  It is probably the most important product at farm level in Ireland.  Beef exports in 2014 amounted to 524,000 tonnes, worth &euro;2.27 billion.  The suckler herd is a critical component of this industry.  It is beef from the suckler herd that has principally enabled us to succeed on international retail markets.  It is important, therefore, that policy at EU and national level recognises the challenges and opportunities facing suckler beef farmers and provides the infrastructure to help it to respond and thrive.</p> <p>The BDGP is a response to these challenges and opportunities and particularly challenges associated with improved breeding performance, including for maternal traits such as cow fertility, and the very onerous requirements to reduce the percentage of Ireland's greenhouse gas emissions which comes from the agriculture sector.  Improving the genetics of the suckler herd can make a positive contribution in both of these areas while also improving the economic viability of suckler farming.  The BDGP provides targeted support to suckler farmers and builds on the success of the State's investment of over &euro;9 million in the beef data programme in both 2013 and 2014 and on the success of the pilot beef genomics scheme, which involved investment of around &euro;23 million last year.</p> <p>Participants in the BDGP will receive a payment of &euro;142.50 for the first 6.66 hectares and &euro;120 for each hectare thereafter, up to a maximum payable hectarage.  This is a strong commitment from this Government to the beef sector in Ireland over the next six years.  In return for this payment, participants will be required to undertake six actions, some of which will be well known to suckler farmers through their participation in previous schemes.  Participants will be required to complete surveys and submit information related to criteria such as milking ability, docility, size and animal vigour.  Farmers will be very familiar with these surveys which were previously part of the beef data programme operated in recent years.  Participants will be required to genotype animals on their farms which have been selected by the Irish Cattle Breeding Federation, ICBF.  The number of animals to be genotyped each year will be equal to 60% of the number of calved suckler cows that the applicant had on his or her holding in 2014.  These are known as the farmer's reference animals.  I should add that the cost of the genotyping tag has been significantly reduced from the 2014 beef genomics scheme and now stands at &euro;22 - a drop of over 26%.  </p> <p>The replacement strategy that farmers must undertake as part of the scheme requires them to ensure that a certain percentage of the animals on their herd at particular deadlines are of four or five-star rating on the Euro star ratings system.  It should be noted that most farmers are already well on the way to meeting the requirement for replacement animals on their herds with significant numbers of four and five-star animals already in scheme participants' herds.  </p> <p>In recent weeks, the ICBF has issued every scheme applicant with detailed reports on the current status of animals in their herds.  Participants will receive similar information related to the scheme and their individual herd on an ongoing basis.  This is in addition to a training programme which will be rolled out over the next 12 months.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Finally, farmers will be required to complete a carbon navigator on their farm with an approved adviser.  The carbon navigator will not cost anything for participants to complete and farmers will be paid &euro;166 to attend the training course for their time and expense in doing so.</p><p>The Minister does not agree that this scheme poses any threat to the quality of weanling that will be produced in the north west, quite the opposite is true.  The data from ICBF and all of the research to date clearly show that progeny, that is, the weanlings, from four and five-star cows perform significantly better than weanlings from one and two-star cows.  These cows have more milk, more calves and shorter calving intervals.  They produce heavier weanlings which are ultimately slaughtered earlier and with more weight.  These are the animals which can add value to farms in the west and we should encourage their use as replacements.</p><p>In the context of reviewing the scheme with suckler farmers - the issue Senator MacSharry raised - the Minister, Deputy Coveney, has committed to establishing a group to monitor the operation of the beef data and genomics programme, BDGP, with a view to feeding into a mid-term review.  Farm bodies and other stakeholders have already been invited to nominate representatives to this group and it is expected that a first meeting of the group will take place in the near future.  This is in addition to the range of clarifications made by the Minister upon the launch of the scheme.  It is clear from the large number of applications received for the BDGP that farmers recognise the benefits this scheme can deliver locally and nationally.  Just under 30,000 farmers applied to join the scheme and the small number that have since exited it, equivalent to approximately 2% of applicants, is in line with previous suckler-based schemes run by the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.</p><p>I reiterate, on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Coveney, that the BDGP involves an investment of &euro;300 million in addressing some of the key challenges facing the beef sector in Ireland.  The BDGP is the first measure of its kind anywhere in the EU and will place Ireland at the head of the international market place as a producer of high-quality, environmentally-sustainable beef.  It will also boost promotional initiatives such as Origin Green, which has been a central part of Bord Bia's marketing and promotion strategy in international markets.  This scheme is to be welcomed and I think the large number of applications received confirms this.  The Minister now believes that we need to move ahead with implementing it to ensure we gain the most possible for the large number of farm families concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#G00200"><p>A brief question from Senator MacSharry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#G00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  Sadly, however, I disagree with most of what has been given to him to provide in his reply.  I would like to bring some of the people from the Irish Cattle Breeding Federation, ICBF, to a few marts, and perhaps Senator Comiskey could come along with us, because what was said is not what is being borne out on the ground.</p> <p>The other thing that phases us in the north west is the risk of land abandonment.  We need to keep these producers at work, so supports are required.  The IFA is a great organisation and probably the best when it comes to lobbying.  There are many IFA members in our part of the country, but their leadership - including Kevin Kinsella, the director of livestock, and others - have sold out the north west when it comes to the implementation of this scheme.  He is admitting as much to people at the ploughing championships this week by saying, "Look, sure we can't change it now and that's it."</p> <p>I appeal to the Minister of State that, rather than wasting this money, he should talk to small farmers in the north west who sometimes find themselves all too under-represented by the big farming organisations.  He could thus see how best we can channel the necessary resources to them to increase their output at the appropriate quality.  This scheme is threatening that quality.  It is sadly proving to be extremely unworkable for farmers on the ground.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1106" speakername="Simon Harris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#G00400"><p>It is appropriate that in the week of the ploughing championships we should have an opportunity to discuss agricultural matters in this House.  I, therefore, thank Senator MacSharry for affording us that opportunity.  I will certainly convey his views to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  I reiterate that the RDP will be subject to a mid-term review.  All schemes are subject to monitoring and are reviewed on an ongoing basis.  This scheme will be no exception.  As I said, stakeholders, including the relevant agencies and farm bodies, have been asked to nominate representatives to a group to monitor the operation of the BDGP.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.24" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#G00450">Local Government Reform</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#G00600"><p>The third motion is in the name of Senator Paul Bradford.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Jimmy Deenihan.  Senator Bradford has four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#G00700"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for giving me the opportunity to raise the important issue of the proposed merger of Cork City Council with Cork County Council.  I also thank the Minister of State, Deputy Deenihan, for being in attendance.  I appreciate that the Minister, Deputy Alan Kelly, who is responsible for the implementation or otherwise of this report, cannot be present.  Presumably, however, the Minister of State will report back to him.  Along with other colleagues, I hope that we will be in a position to arrange a full Seanad debate on this matter in the very near future.</p> <p>I come here with no fixed agenda on this particular proposal of the review committee.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Bradford:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=73"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=73&amp;amp;pid=PaulBradford&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I served as a member of Cork County Council.  I respect fully its history and its traditions and recall with fondness the people who served as very effective managers, engineers and county council colleagues.  Overall, they did a very fine job in the management of County Cork.  I think back to various chairpersons of the council whom I served with and those stretching back long before my time.  They include significant dignitaries of State, such as former Deputy Martin Corry from the Fianna F&aacute;il Party and William Broderick from east Cork, who chaired Cork County Council for over 30 years.  We had people such as Philip Burton, Frank Crowley, Donal Creed and many others, who all ran a very effective local authority in conjunction with councillors and management.  The interaction between councillors and the community was very much at the core of that success story.  There was a feeling that local government was really local.</p><p>Likewise, Cork city, with its mayoral traditions stretching back generations, includes figures of significance in Nationalist history such as Tom&aacute;s Mac Curtain and Terence MacSwiney, who served with distinction in the city hall as lord mayors of the city.  In more recent years, Cork city was served with huge and effective distinction by a wide variety of figures, including the current Opposition leader, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, and I think in particular of the late Hugh Coveney, Jim Corr and many others whose leadership of their city council resulted in a huge dividend for the city.  Again, there was a city lord mayor and a city council working closely with the people.  I believe that concept of the people being close to local government - of local being local - made a very significant and positive difference.</p><p>One of the difficulties I have in understanding where the Minister is coming from is that, while this report is being considered and the Minister seems to have given it some degree of green light, at the same time, he has announced an operational review of the new local government arrangements under the Local Government Reform Act 2014.  I am firm believer in local government reform.   Having been a member of a local authority, I know much could be improved.  However, and I say this not in any way as part of a political point-scoring exercise, I believe the butchering of our local authorities and the decision in 2014 to rid our county of town councils will be shown to have been a grievous error.  While some of the town councils could have been more effective, the baby was thrown out with the bath water.  We now have local authority areas in our county that are 60 to 70 miles long.  That is no longer local government.  If this bare majority proposal by the review group goes ahead, we will not even have local government as planned in Cork; we will have an experiment in regional government.</p><p>I come to the debate as somebody who, when I looked at the concept of change in Cork initially, could see a purpose for a single authority.  However, I was looking at it as a very different single authority.  I was not looking at it as a chamber of 80 or 90 members, who would then be split into three parts and would probably be working against rather than for each other.  I wanted a new form of local government.  What has been proposed, sadly, may offer the worst of all worlds.  It is not a strong combined unit and it certainly is not local.  Before he makes any decision, I hope the Minister will sit down with all of the stakeholders - the councils and the communities - because this is a very major step.  I believe it is an experiment in regional government at the expense of local government.</p><p>If we were starting from scratch and there had been no 2014 changes in local government, we would be talking about strengthening local government, strengthening communities and ensuring that local government is real and is local.  The Minister of State has travelled as much of the world as I, probably more.  I believe one of the features of much of Europe and North America is the strength of local government.  Every community has its council, its mayor or its representation.  What is now being suggested here will blow all of that apart.</p><p>In conclusion, I concede I do not have the answers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Bradford:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=73"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=73&amp;amp;pid=PaulBradford&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I do not think any of us yet has the answers and the report does not provide sufficient answers.  We must note the very strong minority report of two of the five members who put forward a very important view which will require deep consideration.  I ask the Minister of State, Deputy Deenihan, to advise the Minister, Deputy Alan Kelly, to proceed with profound caution.  Some have suggested the Minister would like this to be one of his legacies.  However, it would be a dreadful legacy.  I hope his legacy will be one of caution and a careful, inclusive response.  I call on him to pause seriously and to think deeply before any further move is considered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#J00200"><p>I thank Senator Bradford for raising this issue because it gives me an opportunity to update the House on the matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government.</p><p>As members are aware, the Minister established the Cork local government committee on 15 January 2015 to carry out a review of local government arrangements in Cork city and county, including the boundary of Cork city, and to make recommendations with respect to whether the boundary of the city should be altered or whether Cork City Council and Cork County Council should be unified.  Since receiving the report on 2 September 2015, the Minister has had an opportunity to consider it and on 8 September 2015 he signalled his agreement with its main recommendation to establish a new unified Cork local authority.  The Minister is persuaded that a unified local authority for Cork has the potential to achieve important benefits, above all strengthening local government.  Other anticipated advantages include eliminating administrative duplication, securing greater efficiency through economies of scale, promoting economic and social development and, ultimately, improving service delivery.</p><p>The case for unification rests primarily in stronger, more effective local government speaking with one voice that can deliver a much better future for the people of Cork in terms of social and economic progress and quality of life.  However, it is important to stress that the model that is being proposed for Cork involves more than just a merger, as in the case of Limerick, Tipperary and Waterford.  For example, the report points out that there would be a strong case for major devolution of powers to what would be by far the largest unit of local government within the State.  Fragmentation and weak local government structures have inhibited devolution up to now; stronger more coherent local authorities can help to reverse this and reduce centralisation.  The report also sees scope for stronger leadership of a new authority and a continued role is envisaged for the Lord Mayor of Cork in providing civic leadership and underlining the status, customs and traditions of the city.</p><p>Since publication, much has been made in public commentary of the fact that this is a majority report.  However, this portrayal masks important aspects about which the committee was in full agreement, for example, the conclusion that retaining the <i>status quo</i>is not a realistic option and the need to acknowledge and develop Cork city as a driving force in economic and social development of the region.</p><p>The requirement for a new enlarged metropolitan area was also a matter of agreement but the committee differed on how best to achieve this.  A boundary extension, while maintaining two authorities, would really mean the city taking a substantial share of the county's population and resources, with implications for the future viability of the county.  Equally, the suggestion that Cork city would suffer economically or socially within a unified authority is not well founded.  It is essential that there be a clear overall vision for Cork and an approach that will achieve added value and strengthen local government.  Unification can achieve all of the benefits of addressing the boundary issue while avoiding the disadvantages and complexities which would arise for both authorities by extending the city boundary only.  A unified authority, with improved strategic capacity, can act as a leader and facilitator of change to support and develop Cork and the wider region in social, economic and environmental terms and can facilitate the delivery of efficient and effective customer services through innovative local government.</p><p>I remind the House that, in signalling his agreement with the main recommendation to establish a unified authority rather than simply extending the city boundary, the Minister indicated that he would give further consideration to all of the details in the report.  A considerable amount of work remains to be done to develop further the committee's high-level recommendation.  The detail of what a unified system of local government in Cork would involve - including governance arrangements, functions, and arrangements to maintain the status of the city - must be fully developed as, indeed, must the issue of addressing, as necessary, issues raised in the minority report.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jimmy Deenihan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=306"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=306&amp;amp;pid=JimmyDeenihan&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I understand that the Minister will be making a submission to the Government on the approach to be followed in light of this further consideration of the report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#K00200"><p>I appreciate that the Minister of State, Deputy Deenihan, is simply responding on behalf the Minister, Deputy Kelly, and has no discretion in respect of his response.  However, it is a matter of some concern and I ask the Minister of State if he would concur that the future governance of Ireland's largest county and second city appears to have been considered and decided upon within one week of the Minister receiving this report.  A one-week consideration by the Minister, Deputy Kelly, who presumably had much more on his plate, is simply not sufficient.  I ask the Minister of State to request that the Minister, Deputy Kelly, reflect further and deeper.  As I said in my initial contribution, he has committed to the House and the Government to look at all of what has happened as a result of the local government reforms of 2014 and the amalgamations which happened then.  I ask that this not be kicked into the distant future.  It is much too important to every citizen of Cork city and county for such a report to be considered and decided within one week.  I am sure I speak for many others in the House and beyond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1046" speakername="Jimmy Deenihan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#K00300"><p>The Senator must agree that publishing the report gave rise to a debate, which is part of what he is doing here today.  I was in the D&aacute;il last night when there was a similar debate by his colleagues in that House.</p> <p>There is an ongoing public discussion and the Minister also said he would give further consideration to all of the details in the report.  To repeat his statement, a considerable amount of work remains to be done to develop further the committee's high-level recommendation.  The detail of what a unified system of local government in Cork would involve needs to be fully developed, including governance arrangements, functions, arrangements to maintain the status of the city and, indeed, addressing as necessary issues raised in the minority report.</p> <p>The Minister has left it open for discussion, no doubt, and for further consideration.  I am sure that both the city and county councillors will be providing their responses to the high-level recommendation.  It will give rise to a major debate, obviously, and people will have to weigh up what is best for Cork overall.</p> <p>As Cork is really the engine of the south-west region, and has a huge impact in my own county, especially in the southern and eastern parts, it is very important that the right decision is made down there.  A strong entity would be a counterbalance to Dublin, which is currently experiencing one of the greatest booms in its history as we can see on the streets every day.  I could see this strong counterbalance as one of the advantages for the whole island.</p> <p>There are obviously pros and cons.  I will not be making the decision, but as Senator Bradford raised the question, I thought I would respond to some extent.  I will be passing on what he has said today and the various issues he has raised will be taken into consideration.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.33" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#K00400">Hospital Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#K00500"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Leo Varadkar, to the House.  I thank him for engaging in this Commencement debate on the future of the Sacred Heart Hospital in Roscommon.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I wish to share my time with Senator John Kelly.</p><p>The Minister is probably aware of the situation regarding the HIQA report into the future of the Sacred Heart Hospital in Roscommon.  In the report of 2 March when an inspection took place, HIQA highlighted many issues the director of nursing, Ms Silke, was well aware of but for which no funding had been forthcoming from the HSE.  I have a long association with the Sacred Heart Hospital, having been there at the opening of the new unit in the 1970s, as a former Minister of State in the Department of Health and as a Deputy and former chairman of the western health board.  I have always fully supported this fabulous institution in Roscommon.</p><p>I was also anxious to have the facility called the Sacred Heart Hospital, as opposed to Sacred Heart home, because it carries out the work of a step-down hospital and is a tremendous support to the work of the acute county hospital in Roscommon with which it works closely.  The Minister will be aware of the facilities there.  The hospital cares for 95 residents and has 35 full-time nursing staff, 48 health care assistants, 11 interns, cooks, kitchen staff, laundry staff, clerical staff, maintenance staff and two physiotherapists.  All of this is provided at the Sacred Heart Hospital.  The overall medical care is under Dr. Gerry O'Meara, consultant geriatrician and registrar, and staff.  All temporal and religious needs are cared for, with mass every day in the beautiful church on the site.</p><p>The immediate crisis is that from 7 September 2015, no new admissions are purported to be allowed.  However, I got an update on the situation this morning and have been informed by the management of the hospital that there is no block on admissions and it is still admitting patients.  The licence has not been renewed and they have been told it is in the process of being renewed.  The immediate challenge is the provision of approximately &euro;170,000 for remedial works - partitions, doors, toilets, etc. - which will ensure registration will continue, pending the allocation of a major capital injection from the Department. </p><p>I understand that in the past few days a proposal has been made to provide approximately &euro;400 million over the next five years for the upgrade of State institutions like the Sacred Heart Hospital, Roscommon.  Knowing the background situation in Roscommon, the Minister is aware that his predecessor, Deputy James Reilly, gave a commitment to maintaining the 24-hour accident and emergency facility, but that was closed despite the commitments given by the Taoiseach and Deputy Gilmore.  The people of Roscommon will not stand idly by and allow lightning strike twice.  If the new 50-bed single occupancy rooms with full ancillary services and facilities are not provided, at an estimated cost of up to &euro;13 million, the future of the Sacred Heart Hospital is in jeopardy.</p><p>The people of Roscommon have attended meetings in large numbers and have highlighted the issues on the Vincent Browne show.  I am confident the money will be forthcoming.  I have pressed my party's shadow spokepersons to ensure there is provision in the Fianna F&aacute;il manifesto for major capital investment.  This will be provided, but we must see this as an issue of putting people before politics.  I ask the Minister for an indication of the allocation and ask him to approve that allocation in the budget to secure the future of the Sacred Heart Hospital in Roscommon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#L00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I support Senator Leyden's matter.  Roscommon has the highest number of people over 65<i>per capita </i>in the country.  We have an excellent facility.  If funding is provided, the project is shovel ready and the HSE knows that.  It does not need to acquire land to build these extra units.  It is amazing that the project is under threat and that the hospital faces downsizing because of its four-bedded units.  There are four-bedded units in every hospital in the country, but will the same apply to them down the road?  If the investment is not put in place, there will be no more admissions, which will eventually bring about the closure of the Sacred Heart Hospital.</p><p>No complaints were made by patients about the facility.  On the contrary, patients were delighted to be in four-bedded units where they could talk to one another.  This is good for their mental health.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John Kelly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2348"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2348&amp;amp;pid=JohnKelly&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Now their proposals will isolate them, which will not be good for their mental health.  As Senator Terry Leyden said, health services in County Roscommon have suffered in the past four years, particularly following the closure of the accident and emergency department in Roscommon County Hospital and because of the underfunding of mental health services, which are in crisis.  We also have a problem with the ambulance service and cannot open the new ambulance centre in Loughglynn because we do not have the required staff.  It would be an endorsement of the Government if it gave something back to the people of County Roscommon.  Sadly, if it does not, it will be viewed as another means of privatising older people's services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/948" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#M00200"><p>I thank Senators Terry Leyden and John Kelly for raising this matter.  I am taking the debate this on behalf of the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, who is abroad on Government business.</p> <p>The policy of the Government is to support older people to live in dignity and independence in their own homes and communities for as long as possible.  If it becomes necessary for an older person to move to a nursing home, appropriate accommodation must be available that meets his or her care needs and matches his or her wishes and preferences.  </p> <p>The Health Service Executive, HSE, is responsible for the delivery of health and personal social services, including those at the Sacred Heart Hospital in County Roscommon.  </p> <p>The facility provides services for 80 residents in ongoing care.  Many of the residents have complex and challenging conditions and almost half have had a diagnosis of dementia, psychiatric conditions or other complex medical needs.  There are 15 beds used for rehabilitation, respite or palliative care.  The rehabilitation service is led by a consultant.  This service makes an important contribution to facilitating patients to move from acute hospitals to a more appropriate care centre when they no longer need acute care.  </p> <p>The Health Information and Quality Authority, HIQA, is the independent authority established under the Health Act 2007 to drive continuous improvement and monitor safety and quality in Ireland's health and personal social care services.  Since 2009 all nursing homes - public, private and voluntary - have been registered and inspected by HIQA.  The most recent HIQA report on the hospital was published last July.  Inspectors found that the centre was well managed.  Residents and family members told inspectors that they were very happy with the services provided.  While HIQA praised the care provided, inspectors expressed concern about environmental standards and staffing levels at night.  The issue of staffing levels has been addressed and is being progressed.  During August the HSE received a notice of proposal from HIQA to restrict admissions.  The HSE has responded to this notice and is in ongoing contact with HIQA regarding the registration.  This, of course, is a process that inevitably ends up in court.  It is not one in respect of which I can make any ministerial direction, nor do I have the power to do so.  </p> <p>As is in the case of the Sacred Heart Hospital, residents in public facilities and their families are generally very happy with the standard of care provided.  They frequently choose such facilities, even when other alternatives are available.  However, a number of buildings are very old and it can be difficult or very costly to fully adapt them in line with modern practice.  Demands on public capital funding generally exceed what can realistically be provided.  Only a finite amount of funding can be provided for public capital investment and there are many competing demands across government for the funds available.  However, the Minister of State and I have made the strongest possible case for investment in community nursing units.  My Department will work with the HSE to direct what does become available in the most effective way possible, with the safety and welfare of residents always being our top priority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#M00300"><p>I acknowledge that the Minister has acknowledged the excellent work of the staff at the Sacred Heart Hospital which is a very popular location for patients.  I am concerned, however, that he has not confirmed that there is a capital allocation of over &euro;400 million to be spread over the next five years.  Obviously, it has not been signed off on yet.  I note that the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform provided &euro;23 million for the accident and emergency department at Wexford General Hospital but closed the accident and emergency department in Roscommon.  I understand the Taoiseach provided &euro;10 million for a similar 50-bed unit in Castlebar.  There should be fair play.  I hope that, being very fair, the Minister will come to Roscommon to see the facility with Senator John Kelly, Deputy Frank Feighan and other colleagues and what is happening on the ground.  The people feel badly let down.  We provided two seats for Fine Gael in the last general election.  It will be lucky to win one the next time, but we will see what happens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/948" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#M00400"><p>I wish to mention, in particular, that many of my party colleagues are very concerned about and have been in touch with me about this issue.  Of course, Deputy Frank Feighan is the local Deputy.  Others involved include councillors Maura Hopkins and Michael Creaton.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Leo Varadkar:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2192"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2192&amp;amp;pid=LeoVaradkar&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->On foot of that, I spoke to the national director of social care in the HSE, Mr. Pat Healy, in the past couple of days.  He has informed me that remedial works worth &euro;170,000 would not be sufficient to satisfy the HIQA requirements and that what is required is either a total replacement of the facility or major refurbishment.  I cannot give any commitment at this stage on that, and I would not be honest if I did so.  The simple reason for that is that I do not know what is available for health in the capital budget yet.  That has not been signed off by the Government.  It is intended that it will be signed off next week, at which stage I will know what capital is available for the health sector for the period between 2016 and 2021.  I will have to sit down with Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, the HSE and everyone else to prioritise and decide what aspects might be addressed by direct Exchequer funding and what aspects could be addressed by public&ndash;private partnership.  However, I am not willing to make a commitment I cannot stand over.  I cannot make one at this stage.<br/><br/>Senator Kelly mentioned that there are people in four-bed rooms.  He asked whether this is happening throughout the country.  It is.  There are two facilities in my constituency in a similar position.  Neither has funding to be replaced at this stage.  Therefore, it is an issue that applies across the country.  It is deemed no longer appropriate to have people in long-term care in four, six or 12-bed wards.  People may have their own opinions on that but the general view is that it may be acceptable for somebody in hospital for a week or two but not for an individual for whom hospital has become home.  In the latter case, the view is that one should have a private <i>en suite</i>room or certainly a room with no more than two beds.  That is the current standard.  However, as Senators will appreciate, many of these facilities date back hundreds of years.  People have been in four-bed and six-bed units for-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#N00200"><p>There is confusion.  This is a new unit that was built in 1973.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#N00300"><p>We are way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/948" speakername="Leo Varadkar" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#N00400"><p>I said "many".  The standards now are very high and it will not be possible to replace 200 years' worth of health infrastructure in the course of five or six years.  However, we need a multi-annual programme that will allow us to make a good start on that.  In the meantime, while we are doing that, admission should continue to those facilities that are a few decades old or much older.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.45" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#O00100">Resignation of Member</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#O00200"><p>Before I call the Leader on the Order of Business I wish to announce that I have received notice in writing from Senator Jimmy Harte of his resignation as a Member of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  I wish to thank Senator Harte for his co-operation and assistance during his time as a Member of the House and I wish him well in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#O00300"><p>I would also like to pay tribute to Senator Jimmy Harte.  As we all know, he had a very bad fall and had serious head injuries as a result and was unable to attend the Seanad.  I am sorry to hear of his resignation.  Senator Harte was an excellent Member of this House.  He certainly represented the people of Donegal and indeed his family has given long service to the people of Donegal.  Senator Harte ran in several marathons to help charities.  We would all like to wish him good health and happiness in the future and hope that he will recover in the weeks and months ahead.  We also wish his wife, Mary, and his children well.  It is sad that he had to resign his seat under the circumstances but we certainly wish him well.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.48" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#O00400">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#O00500"><p>The Order of Business is No. 73, item 20, Private Members' business, to be taken at 5 p.m. and to conclude no later than 7 p.m.; and No. 2, Children First Bill 2014 - Committee Stage to be taken at 7 p.m. and to be adjourned no later than 9 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#P00100"><p>I wish to be associated with the Leader's remarks about our colleague, Senator Jimmy Harte, whom  I wish health and happiness in his retirement.  We all agree that he is an absolute gentleman.  He is an avid sports fan, particularly soccer.  He has had a rough couple of years and I hope his health will improve in retirement.  We will certainly miss him in the Seanad where he played a very important role.  I wish him all the best in his retirement.</p> <p>I welcome Members back after the recess.  On many occasions other Members and I have raised the issue of the availability of Fampyra, the multiple sclerosis, MS, drug that was withdrawn by the Government and the Health Service Executive, HSE, from 3,500 MS sufferers.  I am pleased to advise the House that just two weeks ago I received correspondence from the HSE and the Minister for Health stating they had approved it.  It will greatly assist the mobility of approximately 3,500 MS sufferers.  It will improve their independence and allow many of them to return to work, which is to be welcomed, although, unfortunately, it took 18 months to convince the Department that this was the right thing to do.  However, it has now been done and the House played a role in that regard.  I am very pleased that it has happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#P00200"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#P00300"><p>On health matters, I advise the House of a very serious issue in Dublin.  As of last Tuesday, 15 September, north County Dublin, an area with a population of 350,000, has been without the National Ambulance Service.  There has been no coverage whatsoever since 7 o'clock last Tuesday owing to the fact that a new ambulance base in Lissenhall north of Swords which cost &euro;500,000 has not been fitted out.  The HSE stated at a meeting today that it might be ready in December.  The issue is bad forward planning.  The Department has not even requested any of the fittings or equipment required to run an ambulance base.  As a result, HSE ambulances based at St. James's Hospital in Dublin city are expected to take calls from as far north as Balbriggan.  This is unacceptable and I am writing to the Minister about the matter.  I ask the Leader's office to also take it up with the Minister.  It is simply unacceptable that nearly 500,000 people in the Dublin region will be served by only one ambulance, provided by Dublin Fire Brigade.</p> <p>There have been a number of announcements on transport and transport policy within Dublin.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, to come to the House at the appropriate time when the final announcements are made for a proper debate on the Government's future transport plans, not just for Dublin but for also the country.</p> <p>Just before we returned after the recess we saw the publication of the interim report of the Fennelly commission on the retirement or sacking, depending on one's perspective, of the former Garda Commissioner, Mr. Callinan.  It is fair to point out that, judging from any of the polls taken, the general public does not believe the Taoiseach's version or his accounts of what happened at the time.  None of us does.  I doubt anybody could believe his surprise that the former Garda Commissioner had decided to retire.  Certainly, the former Secretary General, Mr. Purcell, was sent to give a message to the former Garda Commissioner that he had to step down.  However, one person with a unique insight into what happened and the decisions made by the Cabinet, particularly the advice that it and the former Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, was given, is the the Attorney General, Ms Marie Whelan.  She will have a unique and important perspective of what really happened around that time.  It is important, therefore, that she answer question about some of the contradictory evidence given and the fact that her evidence had to be changed four times during the course of the commission of investigation.  I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, that, under Standing Order 56, the Attorney General be invited to the House to answer questions about her role as the senior legal person in the State and senior adviser to the Government, the Cabinet, the former Minister for Justice and Equality and the Taoiseach.  Standing Order 56 clearly states a Minister of the State or the Attorney General may attend and be heard in the Seanad.  That Standing Order should be invoked, as it would provide an opportunity for the Attorney General to get her point of view across and answer questions from Members across the House who are very concerned, as is the general public, about the events that occurred around the time of the retirement or resignation of the former Garda Commissioner.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This needs to be addressed----- </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Q00200"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Q00300"><p>----- so I am formally proposing an amendment to the Order of Business that the Attorney General, under Standing Order 56, be invited to attend and be heard in Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Q00400"><p>Before speaking to the Order of Business, I join with colleagues in expressing tribute to Senator Jimmy Harte on the announcement of his resignation.  On behalf of my Labour Party colleagues, I echo the warm sentiments expressed about Jimmy by the Leader and Senator O'Brien.  Jimmy is well-known and well-loved by all of us.  He has had a long and distinguished political career.  He was first elected to the council in Letterkenny in 1994 and since then has been very much a leading light in his community in Letterkenny.  He is a keen sportsman and all of us are very well aware of that.  He ran many marathons.  He was chairman at one time of Finn Harps Football Club and has played a range of different sports.</p> <p>As a Seanad colleague, Jimmy was an exemplary colleague and a true gentleman.  I think all of us, on both sides of the House, were extremely shocked at his accident two years ago.  We have been following his progress since then with keen interest.  All of us wish him and his family, his wife, Mary, and their four children, the very best for his continued good health and full recovery and wish them the very best into the future.  I wish to note that on his resignation today.</p> <p>I welcome everyone back and ask the Leader if we might in early course have a debate on the dreadful humanitarian crisis arising from the migration of Syrian refugees towards the EU and into EU countries.  All of us have been shocked by the distressing images and reports of refugees on the borders of different EU countries.  I am glad of and welcome the Government's announcement that Ireland will play a strong part in welcoming Syrian refugees here under resettlement and relocation programmes, but I would like us to have a debate in the Seanad on this issue.  A number of us came together at a cross-party meeting on 10 September to discuss how Ireland can best respond.  There are different considerations around resettlement and relocation as well as practical and logistical issues which we should debate in this House while we see the process moving on with the Government's task force and the NGO consultations.  We should be as generous as possible towards people who are fleeing dreadful conflict in Syria.  </p> <p>I can inform colleagues that we considered the Fennelly commission report today at a meeting of the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality.  Mr. Justice Fennelly's interim report was produced on foot of a request by the committee for an interim report on a number of issues.  The committee will be writing to the Government seeking that the interim report and the full report, when it comes out, will be brought within its remit for discussion at the committee.  </p> <p>Finally, I welcome the signing into law of the Marriage Equality Bill and the fact that we will see in a very short time, I hope, the first gay marriages taking place in Ireland. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Q00500"><p>I also echo the sentiments and best wishes to Senator Jimmy Harte on his retirement.</p> <p>They are sleeping in tents in Tallaght.  These are people who often through no fault of their own are not only without a home but are also without shelter.  We have a shelterless crisis as well as a homelessness crisis.  Reports this week are that 50 families a day are without emergency accommodation in south Dublin.  We have a shelterless crisis in Tallaght and throughout the nation and the land, and in a culture where we have this extraordinary seanfhocal which says that we live in each other's shelter and shadow.  There still is a little bit of that going on in Tallaght.  I experienced it last week.  Under the shelter of the oak, beech and chestnut trees alongside the parking lot of the priory in Tallaght village, not far from the famous Friar's Walk, a group of volunteers who call themselves VISIT set up tables, brought food and started to serve people who were shelterless and homeless that day.  They have been doing this four times a week over the past year and the numbers they serve are growing.  Ask them what they do when it rains or downpours.  They say they walk over to the covered entrance to the priory itself.  Why do these civicly minded, generous volunteers have to do this in the rain?  Why do they have to do it at all?  The narrative of Ireland's recovery rings hollow close to the Friar's Walk.</p> <p>The Taoiseach said yesterday that the housing and homelessness crisis is not just a matter of money and I agree with him.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Katherine Zappone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2392"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2392&amp;amp;pid=KatherineZappone&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Not only have we not invested enough money - austerity politics was no excuse for that - we have not fixed the local, regional and national systems so that our investments can pay off with shelter for everyone.  The Minister, Deputy Alan Kelly, said yesterday at the publication of the first report on Threshold's brilliant Dublin tenancy protection service - hats off to the leadership of Senator Hayden and her CEO, Bob Jordan - that rent increases are a moral issue.  I agree with the Minister on that too.  It is a moral issue for all of us, not just the landlords.  Could the Leader ask the Minister, Deputy Kelly, when his solutions or proposals to the rent increase crisis will be tabled and implemented?  The people who are sleeping in tents in Tallaght want to know the answer to that too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R00200"><p>A Chathaoirligh, a chairde, welcome back everyone.  I wish to associate myself as well with the remarks regarding our colleague, Senator Jimmy Harte, who has become a very good colleague and good friend over the last several years.  I wish him all the very best for a full recovery.</p> <p>A Chathaoirligh, I would like to ask leave of the Leader that No. 15 be taken before No. 1 on the Order of Business today.  Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R00300"><p>Is Senator Crown moving an amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R00400"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, namely, that No. 15 be taken before No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R00500"><p>I also extend every good wish to Senator Jimmy Harte in his retirement.  He has been an amazing contributor to Irish public life, both on Donegal County Council and latterly in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, following in the footsteps of his illustrious father, Paddy Harte.  I am sure the Harte family will continue to be at the centre of Irish political life in the future.</p> <p>I welcome today's Private Members' motion on the current situation in Northern Ireland.  In that context I wish to condemn in the strongest possible terms the outrageous comments by a Donaghmede Sinn F&eacute;in councillor that those who run Irish rugby had an inferiority complex.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R00600"><p>I agree with Senator D'Arcy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R00700"><p>He went on to remark on the anti-national attitude of the west Brits who still run Irish rugby.  That is the equivalent of an American calling someone an Uncle Tom.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R00800"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R00900"><p>This goes to the heart of who we are.  In fact, the people who run Irish rugby could be termed national heroes as they have kept a united organisation throughout the Troubles in a deeply fractured space.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01100"><p>It is with great pride that I will cheer a 32-county Irish team as they play on the world stage with a fair chance of winning the tournament.</p> <p>Let us remember that Amhr&aacute;n na bhFiann is the national anthem of a 26-county Irish Republic and we are rightly proud of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01200"><p>Hold on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01300"><p>This rugby team-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01400"><p>Does Senator D&rsquo;Arcy have a question for the Leader on the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01500"><p>This rugby team is a much more ancient and deeply spiritual manifestation of an older Irish nation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01600"><p>I call Senator Leyden.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01700"><p>Senator D'Arcy should call for a debate on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01800"><p>Those who run the organisation should be applauded and not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R01900"><p>I call Senator Leyden.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R02000"><p>I wish to say one thing, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R02100"><p>Senator D&rsquo;Arcy is over time.  Many speakers are offering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" speakername="Jim D'Arcy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R02200"><p>He would not say that to our county men, the two Kearney brothers, Dave and Rob, if they were looking at him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R02300"><p>Senator D'Arcy will have a platform on a wider stage next week at the Council of Europe when he can explain all of those things to the 800 million people who are represented by the Council of Europe.  I look forward to hearing his contributions next week.  He is a very good contributor as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R02400"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#R02500"><p>I join with the Leader and our leader on this side of the House on what was said about Senator Jimmy Harte.  I wish him well.  He was very popular here and was so proud and delighted to be a Senator.  I know that from his contributions and meeting him.  It is sad that he has decided to resign for health reasons.  We wish him a speedy recovery.  I also extend best wishes to him, his wife Mary and family.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I served with his father, Paddy Harte, as a Deputy and I took over from Paddy in the Department of Posts and Telegraphs in 1982.</p><p>When I met Jimmy I was struck by how proud he was of his connection with the FAI and the staff there, whom he brought into the House.  We were all delighted to be in the House but he was particularly delighted as he had worked very hard to get here, having previously been a councillor.  His father and mother were also here and they were very proud of him.  It is disappointing but we wish him every success.</p><p>The decision by Paddy Cosgrave's company to move the web summit from Dublin to Lisbon is a major disappointment.  I pay tribute to him and his team of 120 workers in bringing the summit here, which grew from a small number, 400 or 500, in 2010 to 30,000 last year.  The Government should explain why it allowed this marvellous event to leave this country.  It was a great contributor to Dublin and to Ireland, because what comes into Dublin also spreads, from a tax point of view, to people around the country.  As the former political head of Bord Tr&aacute;cht&aacute;la, now Enterprise Ireland, I believe the State should have its own, Irish web summit next year.  I do not see why we are depending on any individual company to arrange for seminars and functions in this country, which is the leading light in the world.  Mr. Cosgrave has no monopoly on seminars or summits.  I am sure that Bord F&aacute;ilte, Enterprise Ireland and other enterprising people would be prepared to get the leaders of Google and such organisations together to bring our own international summit to Ireland and to hold it, not just in Dublin but in Galway, Cork, Limerick and other parts of the country.</p><p>Let us be more proactive in this regard.  This country is Ireland Inc. and we are stronger than any Paddy Cosgrave company.  We can do it if we want to do it, with the will and the right leadership, which I hope will be forthcoming from the last dying sting of this particular wasp of a Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#S00200"><p>I wish my good friend and colleague, Jimmy Harte, all the best on his retirement.  It is a sad day for Leinster House when we lose somebody of the calibre of Jimmy.  Jimmy is a gentleman and one of the most decent people I have met.  His contribution to Seanad &Eacute;ireann has been exemplary, as was his dedication to public service.  Jimmy seldom stood up without first thinking how his contribution would further the public good and that was obvious from all his contributions in the Seanad.  His insight, wit and general good form were a tonic to us all.</p> <p>Jimmy's contribution continues a long tradition in his family of political service.  His father, Paddy, was a man of his time and exhibited the same attributes as Jimmy, such as courage in the face of what were sometimes unpopular political positions.  I wish his wife, Mary, and his family, Amy, Lochlainn and Michael, and little Saidbh who is probably watching us on the television today, the very best and we hope that Jimmy's recovery continues and that he is back to the top of his health in no time at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#S00300"><p>I also wish Senator Jimmy Harte the very best.  He was an outstanding Senator who had one quality which some of us, myself included, lacked, namely fearlessness.  He was the one Senator who, when I first came here with him, was able to stand up to Sinn F&eacute;in and never let them away with a thing.  I admired him for that.  He never let them away with anything because he experienced it on the borders of Donegal all his life so I wish him the very best.  He will be sadly missed.</p> <p>I must also point out to Fianna F&aacute;il that Standing Order 56 states that the Minister of State and Attorney General may attend and be heard in the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#S00400"><p>To what is the Senator referring?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#S00500"><p>The clue is in the verb "may".  The inference from Standing Orders is that if the Attorney General decides that she or the Minister of State would like to come in and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#S00600"><p>Is Senator O'Donnell the Cathaoirleach?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#S00700"><p>-----not be hauled over the coals by a failing, degrading and good-God-give-me-an-issue Fianna F&aacute;il-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#S00800"><p>What are you talking about?  I read it into the record.  That is pathetic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.91" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#S01000"><p>Senator O'Donnell without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00100"><p>The Senator has tried to couch this motion in a benign way as the letter of the law but it is certainly not in the spirit of the law.  It is couched in malice aforethought with no-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00200"><p>I am glad that after four years the Senator has started to read Standing Orders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00300"><p>Might I point out to Fianna F&aacute;il-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00400"><p>The Senator does not seem to know how the House works.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00500"><p>Senator O'Donnell, without interruption please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00600"><p>Might I point out to Fianna F&aacute;il that the answer is in the "may" and the Senator understands the English language and the inference of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00700"><p>We are so lucky to have the Senator here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00800"><p>The Attorney General is not here to answer the Senator's partisan and political needs and make him feel relevant, nor is it to answer his need to seek attention now that he is on his way to an election.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T00900"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.102" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01100"><p>The Taoiseach may have been right-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01200"><p>Is the Senator going to keep referring to me or is she going to ask a question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01300"><p>Senator O'Donnell, without interruption.  Does Senator O'Donnell have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01400"><p>Thank you very much.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01500"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01600"><p>I am fearless in the face of Fianna Fail.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01700"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01800"><p>The Taoiseach may have been right in relation to the abolition of the Seanad if this kind of aforethought malice intent carries on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T01900"><p>What is the Senator talking about?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02000"><p>We are here to bring about a real democracy, real change, good reason-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02100"><p>The Seanad was kept despite the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02200"><p>It seems to me that it is "Look at me"-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02300"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02400"><p>Yes.  Fianna F&aacute;il's motion is basically "Look at me, I am dancing."  I suggest-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02500"><p>It is not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02600"><p>Senator O'Donnell, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02700"><p>It is an amendment to the Order of Business and not a motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02800"><p>Senator O'Donnell, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T02900"><p>That is exactly my reason.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03000"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03100"><p>It is not about-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03200"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03300"><p>It shows what happens when-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03400"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03500"><p>They just shout like little boys.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03600"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03700"><p>It is "Look at me, I am dancing."  I suggest the Senator finds his own mirror and dances in front of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03800"><p>I call Senator O'Neill.  Senator O'Donnell is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T03900"><p>The Senator should have done what Senator Zappone had said-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04000"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04100"><p>-----and spoke about homelessness-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04200"><p>I call Senator O'Neill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04300"><p>-----and about the banks-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04400"><p>I call Senator O'Neill.  The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04500"><p>-----which are down at the ploughing championship using words like "brave" when they are eating into people's lives, putting up interest points and actually giving a percentage of people's mortgages to spend as they will.  Fianna F&aacute;il should find its priorities and dance to its own tune.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04600"><p>I call Senator O'Neill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04700"><p>Senator O'Donnell should be in the Abbey Theatre as a great actress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04800"><p>The Senator can be at the aside but behind the curtain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T04900"><p>I would not be behind the Senator's curtain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05000"><p>It will be hard to follow that.  Senator O'Donnell has done well.  </p> <p>I would like to be associated with all the remarks made by my colleagues on Senator Jimmy Harte.  I did not know him that well until I was elected to this House and he became a very good friend and a very good colleague to work with and I wish him all the best in the future.  He is a big loss to this House.</p> <p>The big thing in the media during summer 2015 was rural crime.  I welcome the publication by the Minister for Justice and Equality later in 2015 of the Criminal Justice (Burglary of Dwellings) Bill 2015.  There should be a debate in this House not only on this Bill but on rural life in general.  I welcome the announcement today of &euro;30 million for village and town renewals.  This will spearhead a recovery in rural Ireland where much of rural Ireland has been left behind.  The Criminal Justice Bill we are discussing deals with bail laws and people who commit crimes while on bail.  I have raised this in the House before and the situation has to be looked at.  People who received concurrent sentences knew that they faced a concurrent sentence, no matter how many crimes they committed.  It is important that consecutive sentences are included in this Bill.  We are the people who make the laws of this country but we are not the people who implement them.  That is the garda&iacute;.  I welcome the reopening of Templemore where 250 guards passed out this year, with 500 more this year.  I think the Minister for Justice and Equality and the Commissioner will make sure that these are allocated to rural Ireland to ensure rural crime will stop.  There has been hypocrisy from Fianna F&aacute;il on the closing of rural Garda stations.  A garda in a rural Garda station will not stop rural crime in the middle of the night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05100"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05200"><p>I have asked the Leader a question on rural crime and I will continue with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05300"><p>The Senator should be careful or Senator O'Donnell will have a go at him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05400"><p>These people are highly organised and are coming in at night time, so it is important that sentencing is a deterrent, and that is the purpose of this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05500"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05600"><p>I want to finish.  We have all been victims of crime.  I have had diesel stolen three or four times and I have had tools stolen but I only reported it to the garda&iacute; once.  There is great community watch but people at home-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05700"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05800"><p>-----have got to take-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T05900"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T06000"><p>They have got to take the serial numbers.  I will finish on this point.  Take the serial numbers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T06100"><p>The Senator is way over time.  I call Senator Barrett.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#T06200"><p>These things are appearing at car boot sales.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pat O'Neill:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2364"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2364&amp;amp;pid=PatONeill&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Garda&iacute; should be inspecting these car boot sales.  I, therefore, ask the Leader for a debate on rural life, not just rural crime.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#U00200"><p>Disability groups lobbied overnight on two occasions last week outside the Taoiseach&rsquo;s office and Leinster House.  They were asking that payments be made to them directly rather than through corporate bodies.  We have discussed, at the instigation of Senator Colm Burke, the position of section 39 bodies.  I ask the Leader to organise a debate on the possibility of directing finances directly at disabled people in keeping with what they were seeking last week.</p> <p>I second Senator John Crown&rsquo;s motion that No. 15 be taken before No. 1.</p> <p>I call for a debate on housing costs which have moved out of line, from 2.5 times to as much as 12 times average income.  There are decisions to be made about the future of the National Asset Management Agency, NAMA, empty sites and ghost estates around the country.  We need to debate the problem the banking inquiry committee encountered that short-term finance was being used to fund the purchase of long-term assets such as housing.  Will the Leader arrange a debate this term on housing?</p> <p>In August, unfortunately, several workers died in public service.  On 13 August Mr. Padraig Noone was killed while fixing hedges near Castlebaldwin on behalf of Sligo County Council.  He was described as a gentle soul and a much loved father.  On 31 August, at Thomond Bridge, two public service workers were killed while repairing the bridge which has such historic connotations.  They were Mr. T. J. Herlihy from Castleisland and Mr. Bryan Whelan from O&rsquo;Brien&rsquo;s Bridge, both of whom were described as family men.  The people mentioned went to work on 13 and 31 August to serve our society and we owe their relatives our sympathy.  We owe them our appreciation as individuals who served this society so well every day. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#U00300"><p>I add my voice to those who have wished our colleague, Senator Jimmy Harte, a happy and successful retirement.  All of us in this Chamber had hoped to see him back among us before the House rose for the last time.  Like me, he is a graduate of University College Dublin, UCD.  We all know that he is a man with a very strong moral compass and with a very strong voice when it comes to supporting the national soccer team.  I wish him the absolute best.</p> <p>I thank Senator Katherine Zappone for her words about the first annual report of the Threshold Dublin tenancy protection service.  In the first year of its operation the service was responsible for preventing 2,808 people, including over 1,600 children, from entering homeless services.  I, therefore, support the call for a debate on housing generally because the issue of housing supply is critical but also on the ongoing problem of homelessness, the level of which continues to rise at an enormous rate.  The report contains many recommendations, one of which needs to be acted on immediately, that the service be extended beyond the Dublin region.  The problem of homelessness extends beyond the Dublin region.  The service is also open in Cork and we hope to be able to open it in Galway.  However, many areas surrounding large urban centres are also suffering significantly as a result of significant rent increases.  I ask the Leader to arrange a serious debate on homelessness in early course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#U00400"><p>I am very pleased that Sinn F&eacute;in was the subject of criticism from some Members of the House.  It shows again that we must be doing something right.  We will hear a lot of such nonsense from some Senators in the next few weeks and months.  I say to Senator Marie-Louise O&rsquo;Donnell that in a couple of weeks or months the people will have an opportunity to pass judgment on Sinn F&eacute;in and Fianna F&aacute;il and I am glad that they will have that opportunity.  Some believe their opinion carries more weight than that of others inside or outside this House.  We will have a general election when the people will make up their minds on all parties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#U00500"><p>I am shaking in my boots.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#U00600"><p>I have no difficulty with that whatsoever.</p> <p>I support Senator Aideen Hayden&rsquo;s comments.  I could be partisan, but I will not be.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Cullinane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2357"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2357&amp;amp;pid=DavidCullinane&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->She has done great work on housing and has raised many important issues in that regard in this House over recent years.  However, we are experiencing what has been described by many organisations as a national emergency.  All of us, both in government and opposition, have been raising the issue of housing for years.  The problem is that the State has completely abdicated responsibility.  There is no social housing being built at all.  There is no increase in the supply.  Many middle-income families who would ordinarily buy a home cannot get a mortgage and are renting property.  They are competing with people who are in need of social housing and who cannot find private rental accommodation.</p><p>Everyone who helps people or holds a clinic deals every single day with people in housing need who cannot find landlords and who will sign up to any of the options, be it the housing assistance payment, the rental accommodation scheme or the rent supplement scheme.  It is becoming a real crisis.  Homelessness, in terms of people sleeping on the streets, is a real problem and there is a crisis.  There is also a problem for people who are being forced to sleep in overcrowded and substandard accommodation because they cannot gain access to any of the options that exist.  The only option for them is the private rental sector.  The State is abdicating its responsibility.</p><p>I fully support the need to have a proper debate on this issue.  It is not just a question of a debate because people want solutions.  We have been talking about this repeatedly since Jonathan Corrie died only a couple of yards from Leinster House not so long ago.  There was a national outcry, yet precious little was done later.  We need to have a debate on this issue.  I ask the Leader sincerely to organise it in the coming weeks so we can make constructive proposals to the Ministers with responsibility.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#V00200"><p>I welcome everybody back after the summer recess.  I join my colleagues in wishing well our colleague, Jimmy Harte, on his retirement.  Jimmy has been a good friend to all of us in the Seanad.  He has had a very difficult couple of years but I know he is making a good recovery.  Like all my colleagues here, I wish him well.</p> <p>I welcome the announcement made in the past couple of days on rural areas, primarily in respect of the payments under the areas of natural constraint scheme.  This will mean substantial payments going into every county.  The scheme replaces the old disadvantaged areas scheme, which has been in place since the early 1970s and has paid much-needed money to farmers right across the old disadvantaged areas.</p> <p>I welcome the &euro;30 million allocated for towns and villages across rural areas.  This comes about because of the report produced on this matter by Pat Spillane and the Commission for the Economic Development of Rural Areas.  It is very welcome money and it will put life back into the towns and villages concerned.</p> <p>I call on the local authorities right across the country to examine how they value premises in respect of rates.  We have all been contacted from time to time by small businesses in towns that are finding it very difficult to pay rates.  I have raised this in the House previously.  I know a man with a small pub who pays approximately &euro;2,400 but who does not open his premises until 7 p.m. or 8 p.m. in the evening.  The entire valuation process should be examined to give businessmen a chance to do business in small towns.  We have seen far too many businesses closing down over recent years and we want to do everything possible to rejuvenate towns across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#V00300"><p>I second the motion to amend the Order of Business proposed by our leader, Senator Darragh O'Brien.  I join all sides of the House in saying how sad we are to hear of the resignation of Jimmy Harte.  I wish him a full and speedy recovery from his tragic fall a couple of years ago.  None of us realised at the time just how serious that event was and its unfortunate consequences, which we now see.  The high esteem in which he has been held on all sides of the House was reflected on this side in that our Whip facilitated the pairing of Senator Harte throughout his illness at all times and without exception, even when he might have been under severe pressure not to do so.  I compliment our Whip for coming to that accommodation with his opposite number, Senator Hayden of the Labour Party.</p> <p>I am particularly disturbed by yet more spin by the Government on rural regeneration.  The announcement seems to be welcomed here.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paschal Mooney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1990"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1990&amp;amp;pid=PaschalMooney&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A Chathaoirligh, we are talking about &euro;30 million over five years and that includes the Leader programme, the contribution to which this Government reduced by 40%.  This is a significant amount of money in rural Ireland.  I come from an area where the Leader programme was held up as a model, not only for the rest of Ireland but for the rest of Europe.  The Leader programme has worked and continues to work because it has an input from the ground up, from communities upwards.  In my county, and I think the same is true of other Leader areas, there is a consultation process under way which has received very positive feedback from the general public to ensure the money is filtered down to where it will be most effective.  If this Government was really serious about rural regeneration why does it not reintroduce the CL&Aacute;R programme that Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v had when he was Minister?  Why does it not reintroduce the RAPID programme which helped inner cities and which had a real positive effective impact on communities?</p><p>Would the Minister of State with responsibility for rural development come into the House and explain how this &euro;30 million - this drop in the ocean, this public relations stunt in the dying days of this Government - is going to be spent that will have any impact or any effect whatsoever?  Why is more money not given over to local authorities for secondary roads?  Why is there no reintroduction of the local improvement schemes?  Why are all these schemes, which were done away with by this Government and which were having a very real impact on rural Ireland, now being shunted to one side?  We get a PR statement coming out during the National Ploughing Championships which makes it look well.  I think it is unacceptable.</p><p>I also take up Senator Marie-Louise O&rsquo;Donnell on what she said.  I say to the Senator that we are very serious about our politics.  A newspaper headline some years ago said &ldquo;Payback time.&rdquo;  It is obvious from her remarks that the Senator is deciding in the dying days of this Government to ensure her own seat in this House because it is going to be payback time for her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#W00200"><p>My remarks were very clear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#W00300"><p>I join in tribute to my good friend, Jimmy Harte, and I wish him well in his retirement.  I had a particular relationship with Jimmy in that we met first on the Seanad campaign criss-crossing the country and we regularly met up and stayed in the Lucan Spa Hotel.  Sadly, Jimmy will not stand for re-election but I wish him well on his retirement and I wish him a speedy recovery.</p> <p>I wish to raise the matter of how business is conducted in government.  Every year during our budget we have the HSE calling for more and more money.  It is &euro;500 million short or &euro;400 million short.  The lack of interdepartmental joined-up thinking is one example of how we are wasting money.  I hope the Leader can bring this to the attention of both the Minister for Health and the Minister for the environment.  There is a lady in Castlerea in County Roscommon who has had a stroke.  She is in a unit in Galway and it is costing &euro;150,000 to keep her there with no end in sight.  She is also looking for a housing adaptation grant in order for her family to be able to take her home.  As she is over the limit she will not receive the grant she needs, which is only &euro;35,000.  If Departments talked to each other, one could say, "Give that woman the &euro;35,000 to make her house adaptable and let us save on the &euro;150,000."  However, it does not happen, it is ridiculous.  It is no wonder that families are frustrated looking at these scenarios.</p> <p>I now turn to the proposed wind turbine set-back distances, leaks about which featured in yesterday&rsquo;s media.  Going from 500 m to 600 m is nothing short of tokenism.  Greater set-back distances are required.  We have a peculiar scenario where two Ministers in one party, my party, cannot agree on this.  The Minister, Deputy Kelly, wants larger set-back distances but the Minister of State, Deputy White, is blocking it because he thinks we will not meet our 2020 targets.   We will reach our targets if other forms of renewable energy were explored instead of concentrating solely on onshore wind power.  The offshore wind power yield is ten times greater than onshore and it is not being done.  However it proves, and we have raised this many times with Senators Whelan and Landy in this House, that the conflicts of interest which exist have won this debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#X00100"><p>I also send my best wishes to Senator Jimmy Harte.  He impacted on all of us in this House when he spoke.  It is a reminder of how quickly his political life could stop.  We wish him well and hope he has a speedy recovery.</p> <p>The legislative programme published yesterday does not include Seanad reform, yet Senators Crown and Zappone and I have put down amendments, motions and Bills on this matter.  The Leader organised a debate on the report of the working group on Seanad reform in May with former Senators Maurice Manning and Joe O'Toole.  It gave great attention to the matter and we got significant promises but where has it turned up?  Seanad reform is not even included in the list for planned legislation in the coming session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#X00150"><p>It is shameful</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#X00175"><p>Senator Healy Eames is right it is shameful.  It is outrageous that it has not happened.  Is there any possibility that Seanad reform will be on the agenda?  I would quite happily introduce a Bill when my next Private Members&rsquo; time comes up in a month or so to debate this again.  Is it possible that we could manage to get it through?</p> <p>One of my frustrations in this House over the past 22 years is the time it takes for legislation to be introduced.  Six years ago, when I bought a German-made car which contained a reflective triangle, a first-aid kit, a torch and other emergency items, I called for the making of such emergency kits compulsory for all cars.  The Minister at the time supported my calls.  Nothing, however, happened.  Yesterday, the current Minister said he was delighted the Garda was calling for legislation to this effect.  My call was five years ago.</p> <p>Around the same time, I introduced a Bill concerning the provision of defibrillators.  The Minister at the time said the Health Information and Quality Authority, HIQA, would examine the possibility of such legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#X00187"><p>The Minister at the time was Deputy James Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#X00200"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#X00300"><p>Nothing happened, however, because it was claimed it was too costly.  What happened this week, however?  Ryanair announced it was going to put a defibrillator in each of its airplanes.  However, it will not be the case for Aer Lingus airplanes.  This shows the time it took for this to happen.  I believe we need to get the legislative process moving.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#X00400"><p>I too would like to be associated with the kind words of tribute to our dear colleague, Senator Jimmy Harte, on his retirement.  As everyone has testified, he is a sincere and thorough gentleman.  I wish him and his family well in his further recovery.  Please God, it will be complete in due course.</p> <p>I would like to be associated with the call by Senator Hayden for a debate on housing.  I congratulate Threshold on its great work and the many thousands of people it has saved from homelessness, despite the scale of the problem which still exists.</p> <p>I welcome the boost for rural towns and villages through the new &euro;30 million rural regeneration scheme.  Despite what the Opposition might say, it will support the revitalisation of towns and villages, provide better places to live and work and increase their potential to support growing economic activity.  The scheme&rsquo;s initiatives will be administered through local authorities with oversight provided by local community development committees.  We need to find a way to restrict the power of the large retail multiples to impose their big-box designs on edge and out-of-town sites.  This is one of the greatest challenges we face in halting the decline of towns.  There might be some measure that can be devised to provide a more level playing pitch.  As has been said by Senator Comiskey, many small shopkeepers, many of whom we know, are finding it difficult to face their rates bills.  I hope the Government will consider this.  Will the Leader take these matters on board, particularly the housing debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Y00100"><p>I welcome my colleagues back and offer my best wishes to Senator Jimmy Harte and wish him well for his recovery.  He is a man who loved soccer and tried to engage us in that sport.</p> <p>Over the summer, particularly in recent weeks, I have been reflecting on the relevance of this Seanad.  What is its relevance if it does not act in people's hour of need?  Just before the Seanad commenced its summer recess, I sought a debate on the 18 homeless pregnant girls, but that debate was refused.  I looked for a debate and a recall of the Seanad on the Syrian crisis, but it was refused.  I also raised the issue of the Aran Islands air service, not to mention the issue raised by Senator Quinn, namely no legislative plans for Seanad reform.  None of these issues have been resolved.  The people spoke out on Seanad reform, but all of these issues remain unresolved.</p> <p>We should not turn a blind eye to the fact that across Europe the refugee crisis is stoking passions.  We in this Chamber should be aware that we are likely to face a huge increase in anti-refugee sentiment when in our country we have more than 2,000 people in emergency accommodation, homeless people on the streets and half of those homeless being children.  This morning we heard a Capuchin monk say he is feeding 800 people daily.  What is the Government going to do for the Irish people who are forced to rely on Christian charity just to eat?</p> <p>I have heard the Taoiseach say he wants to see recovery behind every door.  So do I, but what I find behind many doors is unresolved debt and  missing people due to emigration and, sadly, suicide in some cases.  The fact our people have been left in this situation does not bode well for the refugees we should rightfully accept into our country.  The Government cannot continue to treat our homeless people, those in direct provision for up to ten years and the refugees who come here as numbers on a page.  Throwing hundreds of refugees into Monasterevin is not a way forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Y00200"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Y00300"><p>Will the Leader tell me what the Seanad will do this session in its dying months?  What will it do to address the serious issues of homelessness, shortage of accommodation and the refugee crisis.  What real debate will we have and what real action will we take?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Y00400"><p>I join my colleagues in extending good wishes to Senator Jimmy Harte.  I have known him for a long number of years and had the pleasure of serving with him on the HSE west forum for a number of years.  Both there and here I saw at first hand his commitment to public service and his concern for the people he represented.  I hope his recovery will continue and that he makes a full return to health.  We think of him and his family at this difficult time and hope the future will be much brighter for him.</p> <p>This year will be remembered for the appalling situation we have witnessed in Syria and other war-torn parts of the world, with hundreds of thousands of people seeking refuge in Europe.  I am pleased a decision was finally taken yesterday that 160,000 refugees would be accommodated, housed and cared for in the European Union and that we would take our share of those, at least 4,000.  Will the Seanad bring forward whatever legislation or authorisation is required from the Houses of the Oireachtas next week to facilitate the Government in accommodating those people?  I know a departmental task force, chaired by the Department of Justice and Equality, has been established in recent weeks.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael Mullins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2368"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2368&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMullins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It would be appropriate if, next week, we could get an update from it as to what progress is being made working with the NGOs, the religious orders and the Red Cross.  I certainly would not share the concern expressed by Senator Healy Eames relating to anti-refugee sentiment because I witnessed a huge outpouring of generosity last week in Ballinasloe when people were asked to contribute clothing for shipment to Calais to support people in emergency accommodation and I am sure that will be reflected throughout the country as we try to come to terms with this difficulty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Z00200"><p>I join others in expressing best wishes to our former colleague, Senator Harte, on his retirement from the Seanad and to wish him well in all respects, particularly in respect of his health.  He was most unfortunate to have had the accident he had and I suppose there but for the grace of God go any of us.</p> <p>I wish to raise the issue of housing about which we heard a lot over the summer months.  Unfortunately, the words have not been matched by action in this area, which is regrettable.  The fact that, in the lifetime of this Government, we have allowed construction of housing, particularly in the public sector, to fall to the levels it has fallen is a very significant contributory factor to the crisis and the levels of homelessness we now see.  In 2013, 8,300 houses were built.  The figure increased slightly to 11,000 in 2014.  It needs to be done on an annual basis.  Having just come out of a recession caused by a property bubble, we are on the cusp of another one, particularly in the capital city, and very little action is being taken to address it.  </p> <p>I am calling for a number of things to be done.  The cost of houses must be controlled and I am looking for the restoration of the certificate of reasonable value, which applied a number of decades ago and which could have an effect in controlling house prices.  I am asking that mortgage interest relief, which was abolished by this Government in 2012, be restored at the marginal rate in order to assist those trying to get on the property ladder.  I would like to see action taken in respect of the scandal of high variable mortgage rates, which has been allowed to continue and about which we have heard a lot of talk by the Minister for Finance and other politicians.  I would like to see it tackled seriously to force the banks to bring them down to competitive rates.  The banks have never borrowed at more competitive rates.  </p> <p>If we are to tackle this issue, it must be met with a significant improvement in capital investment, which this Government again slashed in 2012, in local authority house construction.  That is the only solution and it must be effected in the budget.  If politicians and the Government are serious about it, we should see that reflected in the Budget Statement of the Minister for Finance on 13 October 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Z00300"><p>We are way over time and there are eight Senators left so we will take them tomorrow.  They are Senators Brennan, Conway, Keane, Moran, Heffernan, O'Sullivan and White.  I call on the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" speakername="James Heffernan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Z00400"><p>It is not 5 p.m.  The next item of business is not until 5 p.m.  Surely we can get in before 5 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Z00500"><p>There is a set time of 55 minutes for the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" speakername="James Heffernan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Z00600"><p>I appeal to the Leader of the House to extend the Order of Business because what we have to say today is relevant today.  It is not relevant tomorrow.  Could I propose to the Leader that the Order of Business be extended?  It is the first day back.  In all fairness, give us a chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#Z00700"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien spoke about the drug Fampyra, which is now available.  This is to be welcomed.  He made points about the Government withdrawing it and we had long debates on that.  The Government did not withdraw the funding.  It was introduced as a pilot scheme with the drug companies and they withdrew.  Thankfully, it has been solved and that drug will be available to people suffering from MS.  Senator Darragh O'Brien also spoke about the ambulance service in Swords and Balbriggan.  Perhaps he could have a Commencement Debate on that matter to get an update.  He also called for a debate on a national transport plan.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Certainly, when it is published, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, will be quite willing to come to the House to debate the matter.</p><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien proposed an amendment to the Order of Business.  He is certainly entitled to his interpretation of the findings of the Fennelly report, but I do not propose to accept his amendment to the Order of Business.</p><p>Senator Ivana Bacik spoke about the situation in Syria and the migrant crisis, as did Senators Fidelma Healy Eames and Michael Mullins.  I think Senator Fidelma Healy Eames' comment about throwing refugees into Monasterevin is regrettable.  There will be no throwing refugees anywhere; they will be treated with the utmost respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#AA00200"><p>What about the system of direct provision?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#AA00300"><p>The report of the interdepartmental task force has been sought by Senator Michael Mullins-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#AA00400"><p>Spending seven to ten years in direct provision accommodation does not amount to respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#AA00500"><p>The Leader to continue, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#AA00600"><p>As I said, the report of the interdepartmental task force has been sought by Senator Michael Mullins.  I can assure the House that, as requested by quite a number of Members, we will have a debate next Thursday on a motion following the Minister's meeting in the European Union yesterday on the refugee crisis.</p> <p>Senator Katherine Zappone made proposals about rent controls and requested that the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Alan Kelly, be brought to the House as a matter of urgency.  The question of housing was also raised by Senators Aideen Hayden, David Cullinane, Paul Coghlan and Jim Walsh.  Many Members complimented Threshold on its report and Senator Jim Walsh came up with some very good points.  However, it has to be pointed out that the Government of which his party was part abandoned the building of social housing during the boom, when the country was awash with money and it was wondering how it could spend it.  That is one area in which it could have spent it, but it did not do so.</p> <p>I presume Senator John Crown was looking for permission to publish his Bill.  In that case, I will agree to the amendment proposed to the Order of Business, that No. 15 be taken before No. 1.</p> <p>Senator Jim D'Arcy referred to the regrettable choice of language used by a Sinn F&eacute;in councillor in describing as west Brits the people who ran Irish rugby.  It was a disgraceful comment.  As Senator Jim D'Arcy pointed out, the Irish rugby team is a 32-county team, an all-island team, and we wish it success in its ventures in the Rugby World Cup in the coming weeks.  Such comments are bigoted and we are adding credence to them in discussing them in the House.</p> <p>I note Senator Terry Leyden's comments about the Web Summit.  It is to be regretted that it is to be moved next year for the many reasons outlined.  They include the exorbitant prices charged by some hotels this year during the summit when they had a captive audience.  This is something we will obviously have to discuss at a later stage when we are debating tourism related matters.</p> <p>Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell is certainly vehemently opposed to the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by Fianna F&aacute;il.  She is correct in what she said about Senator Jimmy Harte.  He is a man who always despised violence by the IRA.  I remember vividly his description of his family house which was attacked by it during the Troubles.  He is a man who has always advocated the reunification of the country by peaceful means and with the consent of the majority in Northern Ireland, as his father advocated.  Many of the people who advocated it long before the Good Friday Agreement was signed were not taken seriously and frowned upon.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, it is a policy which Senator Jimmy Harte always advocated, as did his family before him.</p><p>Senator O'Neill spoke about rural crime and welcomed the publication of the new burglary and dwellings Bill and the announcement of &euro;30 million for village and town renewal.  He also made a very important point about the importance of people keeping the serial numbers of items in their house.  As he said, many of these items are put up for sale so it is important that people have the serial numbers to give to the Garda to prevent crimes and to catch the people who perpetrate these crimes.</p><p>Senator Barrett referred to people with disabilities and said the money should be paid to the people rather than the providers.  He is right in that regard.  It is something Senator Mulcahy has raised on several occasions in debates on disability.  I am sure the Minister has received the message at this stage but I will certainly bring the matter to his attention.  Senator Barrett also recalled the deaths of several public service workers when on duty over the summer.  We express our sympathies to the families of those workers.</p><p>Senator Comiskey raised the replacement of the disadvantaged areas scheme by a new scheme and welcomed that and the moneys being provided for it.  He also asked that the Minister of State, Deputy Ann Phelan, be invited to the House so the question of rates in rural towns could be examined.</p><p>Senator Mooney rightly recalled the fact, which I acknowledge, that Senator Wilson, the Opposition Whip, always gave a pairing to Senator Harte during his illness.  That must be acknowledged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#BB00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#BB00300"><p>It continues the tradition we have had over the last two Seanaid.  In the last Seanad, a Fianna F&aacute;il Senator was seriously ill and we provided a pairing.  It is the right and decent thing to do, and we thank Senator Wilson for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#BB00400"><p>That is very generous of the Leader.  I thank him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#BB00500"><p>Senator Kelly spoke on the need for the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government and the Department of Health to get together on the case he mentioned regarding the housing adaptation grant.  The Senator is right.  There is a need for more joined-up thinking in this regard.  I note his point on wind turbines.  I am sure we will have a further debate on that question in the near future.</p> <p>Senator Quinn raised the legislative programme.  There is a very ambitious legislative programme for this session, but I cannot throw any light on the question of Seanad reform.  My last information on the issue was that an implementation group was to be set up to progress the Manning report proposals, but I am not sure whether any progress has been made even on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#BB00600"><p>We will leave it until after the election.  It will be handier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#BB00700"><p>I will revert to the Senator on that when I have any news.  I also note his points about road safety measures, the German car makers and the delays in dealing with it.  With regard to defibrillators, I take note of his point.  The Second Stage of the legislation was accepted at that time and the Government indicated it might come back on the matter.  In the meantime there was a HIQA report suggesting that it would be far too expensive to implement the Bill that was put forward.  However, I would have thought that further proposals would have been brought to the House, so I will inquire about that.</p> <p>Senator Paul Coghlan complimented the work of Threshold.  He questioned the power of large multiples which were allowed to locate on the edge of towns throughout the length and breadth of the country.  Certainly the problems in town centres arose as a result of that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maurice Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2003"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2003&amp;amp;pid=MauriceCummins&amp;amp;year=2015&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I do not think we can turn the clock back.  It is regrettable that this was allowed, but we are where we are in that regard.  </p><p>I think I have addressed the points raised by Senators Healy Eames and Mullins on the refugee crisis.  I confirm that we will have a debate on Thursday next on that topic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#CC00200"><p>I asked the Leader if he would arrange a debate on the rural governance programme and that the Minister of State, Deputy Ann Phelan, might come before the House for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#CC00300"><p>We will certainly try to arrange that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#CC00400"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That, under Standing Order 56, the Attorney General be invited to attend the House and answer questions on the events that led to the resignation of the former Garda Commissioner, Mr. Martin Callinan."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#CC00500"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.203" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.204" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#CC00550"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(b), I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.206/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#CC00600"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 20; Nl, 27.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.206/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-09-23" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#CC00600">
            <divisioncount ayes="20" noes="27" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="aye">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" vote="aye">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1200" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="no">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1163" vote="no">Tom Shehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="no">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.206/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#CC00600"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2015092300002#FF00100"><p>Senator John Crown has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 15 be taken before No.1."  The Leader has indicated that he is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.208" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2015-09-23a.209" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>