<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200003#B00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Mark Daly that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Health to state whether any regulatory impact assessment has been carried out on the nursing home sector.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to clarify the reason a commercial vehicle may only obtain a six-month commercial vehicle roadworthiness certificate from the Road Safety Authority following a period during which the vehicle was off the road and the reason for the delay in issuing a commercial vehicle roadworthiness certificate following a successful commercial vehicle roadworthiness test.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to update the House on the takeover of Newbridge Credit Union by Permanent TSB and to inform the House of the measures, if any, the Government has put in place to deal with other credit unions which may be in financial difficulty.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to delay the commencement of the Local Government Bill 2013 until adequate consultation takes place with every town and borough council.</blockquote>  I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200003#B00300">Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200003#B00400"><p>I wish to inform the House that from now on, and for the assistance of Members, the Chair will announce to the House, where appropriate, the receipt of messages from committees reporting they have completed their consideration of matters referred to them by the Seanad.  Messages will be announced by the Chair at the first convenient opportunity.</p><p>A message has been received from the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality to the effect it has completed its consideration of the motions regarding a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council adapting to Article 290 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union a number of legal acts in the area of justice providing for the use of the regulatory procedure with scrutiny, and a proposal for a regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Regulation (EU) No. 1215/2012 on jurisdiction and the recognition and enforcement of judgments in civil and commercial matters.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200003#B00500">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200003#B00600"><p>The Order of Business is No.1, motion of the European Parliament and of the Council amending regulation on jurisdiction and the recognition and enforcement of judgments in civil and commercial matters, back from committee, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business without debate; No. 2, motion of the European Parliament and of the Council adapting to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union on the regulatory procedure with scrutiny, back from committee, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; and No. 3, statements on Science Week, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 2 and to conclude no later than 5.15 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be called upon to reply no later than 5.10 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200003#B00700"><p>Will the Leader arrange a debate with the Minister for Justice and Equality on the outcome of yesterday&rsquo;s Supreme Court decision which was one of quite a number of high profile legal cases recently involving the State?</p><p>Lissadell House, a great national amenity and an important iconic attribute in the tourism infrastructure, has been closed in recent years because of the dispute between Sligo County Council and the Cassidy family.  While one celebrates that finally this debacle has come to an end, it raises the general question as to how State agencies consider their responses to legal issues.  Should there be a centralised unit, perhaps the Office of the Chief State Solicitor, the Office of the Attorney General or some other fora, which local authorities or other State agencies could consult for advice on how best to proceed in difficult circumstances in legal cases?  It would seem ridiculous if all State agencies were to take the view that every possible legal case was to be rigorously defended and pursued.</p> <p>It would beg the question why any barrister would advise any State entity that it had anything other than a solid case, for the sake of his or her own business?  Yesterday we heard the trial may have cost up to &euro;12 million, without prejudice to either side.  One hopes the Cassidy family will return to Lissadell House, open it to the public and get a worthy return for their valued restoration and investment over the years.  This is something we must examine.</p><p> I have just come from a meeting of the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission, which is rigorously defending a number of cases that have been taken against it for a variety of reasons.  Do we approach this with a cost-benefit analysis and assess it in the same way as if the Leader and I were personally to assess whether we might go to court on an issue?  I am not convinced that is the case.  There is a need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to examine this issue and, perhaps, have a national resource to which all State entities can refer when considering their response to a legal case.</p><p> Equally important is the ongoing fallout from the Newbridge Credit Union and I ask the Leader to have the Minister for Finance come to this House specifically on this issue.  He must ask how a reputable and eminent firm such as Ernst &amp;amp; Young can be <i>in situ</i>for two years yet late in the evening a court must be assembled and a credit union pushed into a failed bank.  How is that in the best interests of a co-operative movement?  While I appreciate the Central Bank does not act lightly, I do not believe it examined every possible outcome.  There were suggestions about Naas Credit Union taking over, but were sufficient investigations done to find a solution within the Irish League of Credit Unions?  It is far too easy for the Central Bank to amalgamate some of the banks.  It regulates a couple of Irish banks and if it had its way it would probably regulate the credit union movement, which would undermine the community nature of this vitally important social financing outlet.  It would be worthwhile to have the Minister here to debate this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200004#C00200"><p>There was some discussion last week about motions coming back without debate from the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality.  Those of us who were at the justice committee meeting last week participated in a very full debate.  I personally questioned the Minister about the nature of some of the proposals in the motions and we were satisfied that there was nothing in them of sufficient concern to delay the approval of exercise by the State.  The motions received a full debate and the transcript of the debate is on the Oireachtas website.  If anybody else wants a full debate they may ask for it but it may be useful for colleagues to know we had a full debate on those motions before the justice committee last week.</p><p>I ask the Leader for a debate on overseas aid in light of the dreadful catastrophe in the Philippines.  More than 10,000 people are presumed dead as a result of the typhoon which has wreaked terrible devastation for the people there.  There is a significant Filipino community in Ireland who are very distressed by what has happened.  I very much welcome the &euro;1 million contribution Ireland has already made.  I ask that we invite the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Costello, perhaps in a number of months, to talk to us generally about our overseas aid budget and Ireland's response to this sort of international catastrophe.</p><p>I ask the Leader to set a date for the debate on the youth guarantee which the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton, promised us last week in the context of the Social Welfare and Pensions Bill.  There have been some worrying reports of concerns that sufficient funding is not in place to ensure there will be adequate places for all the people under the age of 26 to be guaranteed a placement in training or education or an internship if they have no employment opportunity.  We had a very good debate in this House during the Social Welfare and Pensions Bill debates, particularly about the implementation of the youth guarantee and the Minister, Deputy Burton gave us a personal assurance that she would come here before the end of this session to debate with us the detailed plan for the implementation of the EU youth guarantee.</p> <p>I ask the Leader if we could set a date for that.  I believe early December would be best as she has promised the plan would be with the EU by the end of December, as I understand it, and it would be very useful if we could have a debate before it is submitted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200005#D00200"><p>I also noted there are, once again, two measures to go through without debate.  I am not criticising the procedure and we have had an explanation from Senator Bacik, but it does seem to point out how we need to think very carefully before we take sole responsibility for taking all of this material on board.  If we fail in this, it will be held against us, so I believe it is dangerous.  Every day that goes by highlights this, as far as I am concerned.</p><p>  I am also a little concerned at the lack of coverage this House is continuing to receive.  Basically, only one newspaper covered it last week and, as far as I could see during a scan of the newspaper, the only thing that was covered was a ministerial speech which was redacted.  There was no contribution from any Member of the Seanad, so we might as well not have been here.  The Minister might have just issued the speech directly to the newspaper and had it redacted.  I do not believe that is proper coverage.</p><p>  I want to also raise the issue of the Battle of Clontarf, the 1,000th anniversary of which is coming up next year.  I have been contacted by the head of the O'Brien clan, The O'Brien, Conor O'Brien, Baron Inchiquin, and a number of other people who are concerned that this very historic matter should not go unremarked.  We will be extensively marking the commencement of the tragedy of the First World War but the Battle of Clontarf was one of the most significant dates in Irish history and we still have living descendants of the people who fought there.  It would be immensely important for tourism and if we could extend the idea of The Gathering and bring people back here for some kind of celebration, including The O'Brien himself and perhaps representatives of the Scandinavian monarchies given the Vikings were heavily involved as well, this would also be very useful.  I ask that the Leader would be kind enough to contact the Minister, Deputy Deenihan, who has already been contacted in this regard.  While there is general enthusiasm, the people involved in organising these events have found difficulty in getting access to F&aacute;ilte Ireland websites and so on.</p><p>  Finally, I note we had an important debate on the Social Welfare Bill last week.  I am not sure there was any great coverage of it but one of the things a number of us pointed out to the Minister was that there is a very sizeable gap between the number of jobs or placements available for jobseekers and the number of people who are going to be unemployed.  This was in the context of a serious cutback to &euro;100 a week for those aged under 25.  Today, <i>The Irish Times</i> has uncovered a document from within the Department of Social Protection which appears to confirm everything we said, namely, there are less than half the number of places for young people.  Instead of fudging these issues in Parliament, we should face them directly and honestly and try to address them. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200005#D00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200005#D00400"><p>This is very disillusioning for young people.  If we get real honesty from the other side, I am sure it would be met by understanding on this side of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200005#D00500"><p>I find Senator MacSharry's suggestion worthy of merit and no doubt the Leader will comment on it.  In light of the two financial scandals that have been highlighted in recent days involving Royal &amp;amp; Sun Alliance insurance and the credit unions, I believe it would be appropriate that we would review how the Central Bank handled both in order to see what lessons, if any, were learned from previous financial calamities affecting the sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200005#D00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200005#D00700"><p>Taxpayers are exposed to the tune of &euro;54 million because of what has happened in Newbridge.  The people's trust has undoubtedly been betrayed.</p> <p>It would appear to me that it was reckless lending that forced the State bailout.  It is not good enough.  We have to hear more from the Central Bank on the issue, which is something that we should pursue later. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" speakername="Kathryn Reilly" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200006#E00200"><p>As mentioned by other Senators this afternoon, European leaders are meeting in Paris to finalise the youth guarantee.  We all know that the Government announced &euro;14 million in funding for this.  Last year the ILO, in a document based on studies of job creation policies across Europe, estimated that the youth guarantee would cost &euro;21 billion in the eurozone.  The EU announced that it would provide &euro;6 billion, which was increased to &euro;8 billion, for the youth guarantee.  The ILO said that it would cost Ireland &euro;347 million, without administration costs, to implement the guarantee, but Ireland has allocated only 4% of the ILO's recommendation.  I acknowledge that the EU has only allocated 38% of the ILO's recommendation, but Ireland should at least match that figure by giving &euro;131 million.  It is important to remember in any discussion on the youth guarantee that Ireland can recoup up to 66% of its investment.  The ILO has said that the figures are modest when one considers how much youth unemployment and emigration will cost the economy and society.  Therefore, I support Senator Bacik's call to arrange a discussion on the youth guarantee, with the Minister for Social Protection in attendance, as soon as possible.  It is important for us to debate the substance of the youth guarantee's implementation plan.</p><p>Last week, in a response to a parliamentary question tabled by my colleague Deputy Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in, the Department stated that the OECD, which is working with the Government on the implementation plan, will submit a report to Government at the end of the month.  The Government will then examine the report and will submit its plan to the Commission by the end of December.  I want us to hold a discussion on the OECD document after it reaches the Government but before the Government submits its plan in December.  It is important for us to discuss the substantive implementation issues, given that the OECD has met stakeholders and carried out a wide range of research on the matter and is examining international best practice on how to implement the youth guarantee.</p><p>The reply to the parliamentary question further stated that the Government had not decided whether to publish its plan, which is worrying.  I call on the Department and the Minister to make sure the plan is finalised, published and made available to the Houses of the Oireachtas to allow us to openly discuss it.  </p><p>With regard to discussions at the summit today, I remind Members that Angela Merkel urged member states to boost employment among the young on 3 July.  Recently, the Minister with responsibility for this area, Deputy Richard Bruton, launched a submission on the Action Plan for Jobs 2014 that comprised seven key themes, but youth employment was omitted.  I urge him to make youth employment one of the plan's key priorities, given that it is so important.  The USI, the ICTU and the ISSU called for a youth jobs strategy in their document Locked Out, while our own Joint Committee on European Union Affairs called for a section of the next jobs plan to be dedicated to youth employment.</p><p>I have a brief question.  Can the Leader let us know when the Protected Disclosures Bill, also known as the whistleblower legislation, will return to the House for Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200006#E00300"><p>I support Senator Bacik's call for a debate on Irish Aid.  I extend our solidarity in the House to the unfortunate people in the Philippines who are experiencing severe hardship, with over 10,000 people dead and millions of people displaced and left destitute.  I welcome the fact that the Government has provided &euro;1 million to the country, but much more is required.  I urge the Government to be part of a major international response that will provide help to the people concerned, because what happens in the next week or ten days will be critical in saving the large number of people who are in dire straits.</p><p>The generosity of the Irish people is much recognised and I urge citizens to support the Irish organisations working to help the people in the Philippines.  Members can also provide practical help.  Today I received an e-mail from a staff member who has arranged a coffee morning for next Thursday in order to raise funds for the people in the Philippines.</p><p>I support the call to arrange a discussion on Newbridge Credit Union with the relevant Minister.</p> <p>We also need to discuss how far removed Newbridge Credit Union has been from the aims and objectives of the founding fathers of the credit union movement.  It was certainly acting more like a major bank in having leant &euro;3.2 million to one customer, it had a huge office block and was dispensing major loans.  There is a major debate and discussion to be had in the House around how Newbridge Credit Union operated and how other credit unions who may be in difficulty have run their business in the past decade.</p><p>On a happy note, it is appropriate that we recognise a major sporting achievement by an Irishman, AP McCoy who rode his 4,000th winner last week and has been a champion jockey in England for the past 18 years.  He has been a major role model for young people and those interested in sport.  We are particularly pleased that he has Galway connections in that his wife, Chanelle, comes from Loughrea, County Galway, and is a member of the Burke family, significant business people and major employers in Loughrea.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00150"><p>Tuam Town Council.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00200"><p>No credit for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00300"><p>We send him our sincere congratulations and continued success and hope he gets to that magic figure of 5,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00400"><p>I ask the Leader to arrange for a debate on the European Union and its policies.  A report by Joseph Stiglitz, a Nobel prize winner for economics, stated that Ireland is facing a lost decade because of the policies being imposed upon it by the EU, the troika and the IMF.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00500"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00600"><p>The Senator means Fianna F&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00700"><p>I do not want to see fatalism being replaced by pessimism and in light of EU policies 1,000 people per week emigrating.  I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for announcing that we will get reports on EU legislation that have been decided at committee level.  However, what we are not getting - I ask the Leader to clarify this - is what was actually decided upon.  Did the committee make any changes to the proposals put before it and, if so, may we see what it has done?  We realise it is not easy for our staff to keep an eye on all the material that comes from committees, of which there is much, including many reports.  Perhaps a short note could be prepared along with the report from the committee stating that no amendments were made to the proposals or, if amendments had been made, what those were.  The Leader is not at fault in this area but there is a range of legislation not only by the Opposition but by Government in respect of proposals that would improve the economy.  </p><p>I note today that there is no legislation on the Order Paper.  As the Leader is aware we on this side of the House fully support his efforts for the running of the House but it shows there is not a real and genuine attempt by the Government to reform the way politics is done in this country.  If the Government was genuine about improving the position, it would have legislation in the House to cut red tape to create jobs and improve society.  I know the Leader will do all he can to rectify the situation but it cannot be allowed to continue.  We have no legislation today and a couple of Bills tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00800"><p>The Senator has made his point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F00900"><p>I remind Senator Mark Daly when his party left office that 7,000 jobs per month were being lost; at the moment 3,000 jobs per month are being created.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F01000"><p>Some 3,000 people per month are emigrating.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200007#F01100"><p>I join my colleagues in commenting on the issue of Newbridge credit union.  While there is a need for a debate there is also a need to reassure the general public that credit unions are a good place in which to have investments.  They have served local communities well down through the years and will continue to serve them.  I do not want a situation to arise where there is scaremongering about all credit unions.  One of today's newspapers reported that a watchful eye is being kept on 100 credit unions.  In fairness they have been quite conservative about giving out loans and managing their affairs and will continue to be so.  However, it is important to have a debate on the issue.</p> <p>Senator Mullins said that over &euro;3 million was given to one company or individual.  That is a concern.  If there are other credit unions where this has occurred, we need to deal with the issue and ensure this does not happen in the future.  We also need to discuss the structure and governance of credit unions to ensure proper procedures are being followed and that expertise is available when needed.  It would be useful to have a debate to deal with those issues.  Therefore, I support Senator MacSharry's call for the Minister to come to the Seanad for a discussion on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200008#G00200"><p>I agree with Senators MacSharry and Burke on the need for a debate in the Seanad with the Minister for Finance on financial regulation in Ireland.  It is not just that one credit union has cost us &euro;54 million.  An insurance company from the UK has had to be bailed out and two foreign banks, Danske and Rabo, have substantially reduced their operations in Ireland.  This has all happened within a matter of days.</p><p>Five years after the collapse of the banking system, we need to debate financial regulation here.  We need the Department of Finance and the Central Bank to take a positive role in this and to explain what they are doing.  We also need to examine the role of auditors and accountants and the need for rules that will enforce loan-to-value and debt-to-income ratios.  Mention has been made of a &euro;3 million loan from a credit union.  This debate is a matter of some urgency as we are not making much progress in this area.</p><p>I compliment the Taoiseach on completing 38 years in the Oireachtas today.  I look forward to 38 years' more co-operation between the Seanad and whoever is Taoiseach of the day.  I also compliment the Lord Mayor of Belfast, M&aacute;irt&iacute;n &Oacute; Muilleoir, for attending the Remembrance Day ceremonies in Belfast yesterday.  This was another step forward in the peace process.  I met the Lord Mayor in Toronto at the weekend where he was energetically promoting Belfast tourism and the peace process.  I bring greetings from the Speaker of the Senate of Canada, Mr. Noel Kinsella, who has strong connections with this city and who lived in Leeson Street as a student.  He was delighted with the popular vote to retain the Seanad in this country because tomorrow a court case begins in the Canadian Supreme Court, with five provinces taking a case against the abolition of the Canadian Senate.  We have a lot in common with Canada and people there are delighted with the verdict given by the people in our referendum.  One of the positive aspects of bicameralism - I am aware the Leader has been developing these points - is that it is a bulwark against monopoly.  An interesting Canadian project in co-operation with Saudi Arabia is to promote a bicameral system in Saudi Arabia.  The Saudi Arabian draft proposes a strong female representation.  This is a positive development and one hopes these female representatives will be allowed to drive to the meetings on the bicameralism system that Canada seeks to export to Saudi Arabia.</p><p>Bicameralism is an important part of extending democracy worldwide.  I know how much the Leader has developed this House internally.  Perhaps there could be a joint initiative to extend that to countries that need the democracy bicameralism brings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200008#G00300"><p>I noted a recent article on the Swedish penal system and the fact that the number of people committed to prison in Sweden has dropped by 1% a year since 2004.  In 2001 and 2012, the rate decreased by between 6% and 12%.  The decrease is to such a degree that four prisons and a remand centre there have been closed down.  This has come about because of determined penal reform, education programmes and programmes to assist prisoners when they leave prison to ensure they do not re-offend.  There have also been programmes of restorative justice.  I call on the Leader for a debate on penal reform in this country.  Keeping people in prison here is expensive.  If we could reduce the number of people in prison, we would improve life for those in prison.  This would make economic sense because, despite the fact that we will come out of the bailout on 15 December, the country is still struggling.</p> <p> I was invited to speak at a conference organised by F&eacute;ach, an organisation which provides support for the parents of young and visually impaired children who face challenges from birth up to the age of ten or 15 years as a result of the fact that they have difficulty seeing.  One of the issues raised with me at the conference was related to school books made available electronically.  Some publishers make entire books available in this way but others just make the text version available.  A science manual might refer the reader to a diagram, but this will not be available in a text-only version.  I would like the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, and the Minister of State at his Department, Deputy Sean Sherlock, to immediately enter negotiations with publishers in order to ensure all schoolbooks, in their entirety, will be made available at the same cost to all students.  What is happening in this regard is farcical.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200009#H00200"><p>I again call for a debate on unemployment, specifically in the context of the Action Plan for Jobs.  The Leader will agree that we continue to face many challenges and that we still have a great deal of work to do in order to create the jobs that are needed in the State.  Job retention which is as important as job creation is an issue on which we must also focus.  The Leader will be aware of the Essentra company which may be transferring its operations to Dublin from Waterford, with the potential loss of 50 jobs.  I raise this issue because Essentra produces packaging, etc., for pharmaceutical companies.  There is a strong cluster of pharmaceutical and life sciences companies in the south east, many of which do not use the services provided by other local companies and instead seek such services either outside the region or even the country.  Multinationals which come to the State to set up operations can avail of very attractive taxation rates, which I support.  However, there is a responsibility on them to support other businesses and, by extension, employment in the regions in which they are located.  If such support was on offer from the multinational pharmaceutical companies operating in the south east, Essentra would not be faced with the possibility of being obliged to make 50 people in Waterford redundant.  In the context of job retention, perhaps the Leader might liaise with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation on what is happening in Waterford in order to discover if anything might be done to retain the jobs in Waterford.  As he is aware, there is a very high and unacceptable level of unemployment in Waterford city.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200009#H00300"><p>I welcome yesterday's announcement by the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, to the effect that applications are being invited from the 35 or so women who were excluded from the original redress scheme relating to Our Lady of Lourdes Hospital.  Since becoming a Member of the Seanad I have met many of these ladies and campaigned to have the redress scheme extended to them.  Many of them were excluded from the original scheme simply because they were over the age of 40 years.  The individuals in question suffered unnecessary hysterectomies or were obliged to undergo the unwanted removal of one or both ovaries.  They then suffered further when they were excluded from the original redress scheme on age grounds.  The programme for Government contains a commitment to the effect that this matter will be addressed and I am delighted that it began to be addressed yesterday.</p><p>Will the Leader ensure the Minister for Health will announce in the next couple of weeks or, even better, days the appointment of a judge in order that the Walsh report on the survivors of symphysiotomy might be dealt with?  I understand the report will not be published until that appointment is announced.</p><p>I thank the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, and commend him for announcing yesterday that he was going to invite education partners to engage with officials of his Department on decisions relating to school uniforms.  As a mother, a former teacher, a member of the Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection and my party's spokesperson on education in the Seanad, I deal with the matter of the cost of school uniforms on a daily basis.  Parents sometimes find the cost of uniforms to be way beyond their reach.</p> <p>It is an issue I have campaigned on for the past few years because parents have reported to me that schools demand that uniforms be bought in certain shops and must have certain labels.  That can be distressing, particularly when virtually the same uniform can be bought in another shop at half the price, so the idea that this will be put out to parents is extremely important because parents should have a greater say in the uniforms for their children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200010#J00200"><p>I want to put on the record my sympathy and I am sure that of Members on all sides of the House to the family of the late Eddie McGrady, the SDLP MP who passed away in the past 48 hours.  I had the great pleasure of meeting Mr. McGrady on a number of occasions and he was an extraordinarily compassionate and committed public representative.  I extend my deepest sympathy to his family.</p><p>To follow up on Senator MacSharry's comments about Lissadell House, as a former chairman of F&aacute;ilte Ireland North West I was involved in the early stages of the attempts made at that time to ensure that Lissadell House would remain open for tourism purposes.  I attended a launch of what was then called the Yeats Trail in the company of the late great Seamus Heaney in Sligo in 2008 and the portents at the time were very positive in that Lissadell House would be a centrepiece of the entire Yeats Trail but the court case intervened and the matter has remained in stasis for the past five years.  I now call on Constance Cassidy and Eddie Walsh, following their victory in the Supreme Court yesterday, to give serious consideration to reopening Lissadell House for tourist purposes.  It is the jewel in the crown of tourism in the north west.  I understand their position, the fact that the question of costs is unresolved and the amount of money they expended but it is sad to read in the newspapers that the walled garden, which they restored, has returned to weeds and that the restaurant has closed down.  I remember it being reopened as part of a shop in the old stable area.  The amount of restoration carried out by Constance Cassidy and Eddie Walsh was extraordinary, not only in terms of the initial financial commitment they made but also the amount of money subsequently spent.  It would be a tragedy if Lissadell House was to be lost to the many hundreds of thousands of tourists not only in this country but also overseas who come to visit the north west because of the focus on Yeats.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200010#J00400"><p>I noted with concern in recent weeks that five female Fine Gael councillors have announced that they do not intend to run in the next local elections.  At a time when we are actively pursuing policies to encourage women to get involved in politics it seems there is a parallel problem of keeping women in politics, particularly women of my generation.  Three of the five mentioned are about my age and four of them are coming to the end of their first term.  There are various reasons people decide not to run, and it may be a coincidence, but there appears to be a need for an examination of the factors causing women already active in politics to opt out after one term.  While we ponder how we will encourage more females into politics we should also examine how we can encourage them to remain in politics.  That is a facet of the debate that might be worth discussing in the House.</p><p>I join Senators Mooney and MacSharry in their comments about Lissadell House.  I would encourage the two owners of Lissadell House to open it to the public.  They did huge work, as Senator Mooney said, in restoring the House and with great enthusiasm.  I know them both personally and have had many discussions about the work they did and the efforts they made to get original pieces of art and furniture that belonged to the house back to it, and all the other issues Senator Mooney mentioned.  It is not my area but now that the case is behind everyone I hope something can be done in that regard because it is a significant building in the north west.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200011#K00100"><p>Credit unions have been receiving a significant number of calls from concerned customers.  I myself took several calls on my way to the House.  Customers are not concerned about their savings because they know they have a guarantee but they want to know how safe their local credit union will be.  Credit unions enjoy a high level of trust compared with banks.  I agree that the Minister for Finance needs to address this issue urgently.  There is urgency about financial regulation, foresight and oversight.</p><p>This morning I spoke to a manager of a local credit union, who told me that it had more than enough money in provisions to cover the small percentage of its loans that were in arrears.  However, he was aware of credit unions in which more than 70% of loans were in arrears of more than three months.  He had great difficulty with the statement issued this morning by the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Brian Hayes, because he did not accept it was an isolated incident.  We need to be vigilant in avoiding a repeat of the situation that arose with our banks.  The credit union manager asked me to call on the Central Bank and the Irish League of Credit Unions to issue a firm statement by tomorrow at the latest on the state of individual credit unions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200011#K00200"><p>Is the Senator calling for a debate on it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200011#K00300"><p>Yes, it is critical because the public are worried.  The last thing we need is a flight of capital from our credit unions.  That is the money they lend.  They do a good job of meeting their criteria.  I have enjoyed the services of credit unions through the years, as have many other people in this country.  It is our job as politicians and public servants to ensure they are safe for their customers both immediately and in the long run.   The Minister, Deputy Noonan, needs to act quickly by asking the Central Bank and the league to step up to the plate and issue a statement so that the public can feel confident in their local credit unions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200011#K00400"><p>I join my colleagues in calling for a debate on the youth guarantee.  When the Minister for Social Protection was in the House last week she gave a firm undertaking that she would return for a debate on the issue.  I ask the Leader to facilitate such a debate at the earliest opportunity rather than leave it linger any longer.</p><p>More than 70,000 Irish people have had their credit card details accessed through the breach in the SuperValu getaway breaks data.  At a time when public confidence in financial institutions is so low, it is another blow for them to find out that even their credit card details can be accessed.  I understand the Data Commissioner has moved to find out from the company concerned why the credit card details were retained.  They should not have been retained by any company.  We need to restore confidence in our financial institutions and financial matters by assuring the public that no other company retains details of their credit cards.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the issue of data protection.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200011#K00500"><p>A number of speakers have expressed solidarity with the people of Newbridge on the loss of their credit union but the events of recent days are disappointing not only to the people of Newbridge but also to this House and the High Court.  This House has once again been treated with contempt by the Government in the way the matter has been addressed.  This day last week I asked the Minister the plans for the future of Newbridge Credit Union but I was told they could not be discussed due to the fact that the High Court had issued an order.  Yet again, however, we find the Government telling the media its plans before it informs this House or even the High Court.</p> <p> The events of recent days have sent shockwaves throughout the credit union movement.  The speed with which the Government acted using these special powers - powers which were intended for its dealings with banks - was incredible.  Now the people of Newbridge are left without a credit union.  The Minister and the Department are sending mixed messages to the 2.8 million people in this country who are credit unions savers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200012#L00200"><p>I have accepted the Senator's Adjournment motion which will allow him an opportunity to discuss this issue tonight.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200012#L00300"><p>Thank you, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.  I am raising very specific questions on the Adjournment.  My request to the Leader that the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, come into the House is relevant to the Order of Business.  We need to hear from the Minister and a statement on what the Government intends to do.  Will there be better consultation with ordinary people, the people who have put together the credit union movement brick by brick, or will there be mergers and takeovers of credit unions by stealth, including their being merged into banks?  That would not be in the public interest.  The last thing the people of Newbridge or anywhere else need is another bank.  The Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, is saying Newbridge is the only place where this type of merger will occur, but the Minister is saying one quarter of credit unions might be in trouble.  It seems, in this case, that the credit union was treated like another failed bank, which clearly it is not.  There should have been more consultation, including with the communities served by the credit union.  The members who are ordinary people are the owners of the credit unions.  I ask the Minister to come to the House in early course to discuss the issue.  I hope there will be an end to the situation where information on such matters is communicated to the media before it is conveyed to the D&aacute;il and the Seanad.  I do not believe the bogus claims that people are bound by confidentiality in a context where selective leaks are being made to the media, as I believe happened in this case.  Above all, however, there must be consultation with the Irish League of Credit Unions and ordinary people who wish to retain a credit union facility in their community.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200012#L00400"><p>Colleagues have already covered the main issues in regard to the credit unions.  It is important to reiterate, however, that savings up to &euro;100,000 are guaranteed.  I received a telephone call from a person who was concerned about the security of savings.  It is important that people are aware of the threshold.</p><p>Will the Leader facilitate a debate on public rights of way?  The outcome of the court case concerning Lissadell House suggests the goalposts have moved in this regard.</p><p>I support Senator Catherine Noone's call for action on the issue of participation by women in politics, a matter that has been debated several times in this House.  There are courses one can take on women in politics, women in business, women in this, that and the other, but it all comes down to who is minding the baby.  We must facilitate men to take a greater role in child care responsibilities through the provision of paid paternity leave and other means.  I take the opportunity to compliment Senator Mary White on her efforts in this regard.  Until such time as we have equality in terms of the participative input of males in child rearing, nearly all women in politics will have a choice to make.  That choice is already being made.  We must have a comprehensive debate on child care and the range of child allowances and benefits available.  It is only when we have a more level playing field that we will see fewer women leaving politics.  Three young female members of my own party have left in recent times, although I cannot say the reason in each case was child care responsibilities.  My youngest child was nine years old when I began my career in politics and I was only able to do it because my husband was a teacher.  Many people have to wait until their children start school before they can become involved.  We cannot have a debate about women in politics without discussing child care issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="15:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200012#L00500"><p>I understand the accounting problems being experienced by RSA are not as a consequence of fraud or anything like it but stem from a misjudgment of the number of injury claims.  It is only ten years or so since the legislation establishing the injuries board was passed in this House; it was meant to solve the problem of the large increase in the number of injury claims.  In this case, however, the RSA has had to put in &euro;100 million to cover the cost of the growing number of claims.</p> <p>I do not know how this has come about but we should have a discussion on insurance claims.  There was a 13% increase in motor insurance.  While RSA says it has no intention of increasing its rates, if it has one third of business in Ireland it is highly unlikely we will be able to avoid an increase in insurance premiums.  We should have an open debate about this on the grounds that it represents a huge cost to the nation.  It will affect our economy and jobs.  Some ten years have passed since the legislation was passed and perhaps it needs another look.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200013#M00200"><p>Some ten days ago I attended the opening of the first phase of a greenway in north County Louth.  I have heard a lot about the greenway from Westport to Mulranny and onto Achill.  This is a truly magnificent route along the shores of Carlingford Lough, with magnificent views of the Mourne Mountains and Cooley Mountains.  I acknowledge the funding of &euro;687,000 received from the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  It will be a major tourist attraction for Omeath, Carlingford and the Cooley Peninsula.  I look forward to the second phase of the route, which will be from Greer's Quay in Omeath to my home town of Carlingford, amounting to a total distance of 7 km or 8 km.  The route runs from Omeath to Dundalk and we hope to cross the Border to Portadown.  I do not think I will be around to welcome that stage when it happens.  I acknowledge the co-operation with the proposal from landowners along the route, without which it could not have happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200013#M00300"><p>Senators MacSharry, Mooney and Noone raised the issue of the Supreme Court judgment on Lissadell House.  They called for more joined-up thinking and for cost-benefit analysis before cases are taken.  I note the points and empathise with the point made by Senator MacSharry.  I do not know how that position can be arrived at but I will bring his point to the attention of the Minister for Justice and Equality.  It is an important issue where councils or State bodies take cases.  There is a need for examination before cases are brought to court.</p><p>A number of members have raised the question of Newbridge Credit Union today.  I praise the role of credit unions since their foundation.  They have done a tremendous job in local communities throughout the length and breadth of the country.  I am proud of my membership of the credit union.  It never ceases to amaze me that credit unions can give out loans of &euro;3.2 million and 26 loans over &euro;550,000.  This was not what the credit union movement was set up for and the founders mentioned today would be turning in their graves if they heard that such loans were being given out by any credit union in the country.</p> <p>The Government recognises the important role of credit unions as a voluntary co-operative movement and the distinction between them and other types of financial institution.  The Government's priority in assessing the Central Bank's proposal on Newbridge was to protect the savings of depositors and members of Newbridge Credit Union.  The action by the Central Bank of Ireland protects and secures the savings of all depositors and members of Newbridge Credit Union.  Members of the credit union will continue to have full and uninterrupted access to their savings.  The Government's second priority was to prevent the liquidation of Newbridge Credit Union because of the negative impact this would have on members and their locality and also because of the wider implications for the credit union movement overall.</p><p> I agree with Senator Barrett on this issue that we must look at the role of auditors and accountants, not alone with regard to credit unions but throughout the financial system as a whole.  The House has debated financial regulation but there is a need for a further debate and I will ask the Minister for Finance to come to the House to discuss financial regulation and the role of auditors and accountants.  There are many unanswered questions for auditors and accountants with regard to the collapse of the banks many years ago.</p><p> Senator Bacik raised the matter of overseas aid in light of the dreadful happenings in the Philippines.  Senator Mullins made the same point.  It is a dreadful situation and we should ask the Minister of State, Deputy Costello, to come to the House to give us an update on overseas aid.  Senators Bacik, Norris, Reilly and Moloney asked about the youth guarantee.  The figure of 42,000 mentioned in this morning's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i>- referring to those potentially coming under the umbrella of a youth guarantee - was a 2012 figure which is based on estimates that about 66,000 young people became unemployed and signed on for welfare payments in 2012 and that 42,000 of these claims lasted for four months or more.  However, there has been a reduction in the number of new claims in 2013 to date.  This suggests that the number of new claims from young people for the year as a whole will be down to about 56,000 and the number staying longer than four months will be down from the 2012 figure of 42,000, to 35,000.  The Minister intimated that she was willing to come to the House before Christmas to discuss the youth guarantee.  I will ask the Minister to honour that commitment she gave when dealing with the Social Welfare Bill.  The Taoiseach travelled to Paris today at the invitation of President Hollande for the second conference on youth employment in Europe.  This is an effort to maintain the political momentum for addressing the challenge of youth employment.  The Taoiseach regards the issue of youth employment as being of great importance.</p><p> I note Senator Norris's points about the thousandth anniversary of the battle of Clontarf.  I will bring the matter to the attention of the Minister for the Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy Deenihan.  His point about the lack of media coverage of the proceedings of this House is a long-playing record at this stage.  There is very little we can do to entice the media to come to the House.</p> <p>Senator Paul Coghlan spoke about the credit union and the &euro;56 million that the taxpayer, through the Government, has had to pump into the credit union in Newbridge.  We can discuss those matters when we have a debate on the subject.</p><p>I have addressed Senator Reilly's points about youth unemployment and the Protected Disclosures Bill, will come to us the week after next.  Senator Mullins mentioned the need for a major international response to the disaster in the Philippines.  Our hearts go out to the people there and we are probably only seeing a small portion of the effects of the unfortunate disaster.  Senator Mullins also complimented Irish jockey A. P. McCoy on riding more than 4,000 winners, which is an extraordinary feat that will probably never be emulated by another jockey.  Senator Daly spoke about EU reports from committees.  These are available for access by any Member.  I assure the Senator that any legislation that becomes available will be in the House as soon as possible.  We can only act on the legislation we receive from Departments and we are doing as well as we possibly can in that regard.</p><p>I note Senator Barrett's points on financial regulation and I welcome the Lord Mayor of Belfast's attendance at the Armistice day services, which is to be welcomed.  I also note his points with regard to Canada, and we welcome the Senator back from his trip there.  He has indicated that the Canadians are discussing a unicameral system but they will probably reserve judgment after seeing the results here.</p><p>Senator Conway asked for a debate on penal reform and restorative justice.  We have a report from the justice committee on the issue and we will try to invite the Minister to the House to debate that important matter.  I also note the Senator's points about pupils who are visually impaired and their need to access school books.  I will raise the matter with the Minister for Education and Skills.</p><p>Senator Cullinane mentioned a printing company in which 48 jobs could be lost.  I would not give up on those jobs as these people are doing excellent work in difficult conditions.  Their company has bought another firm in Dublin and these people have found their services dispensed with.  It is a despicable action and the union should act strongly.  I hope these people will retain their jobs and I agree with Senator Cullinane's comment that there is a need for local companies to support each other in the regions.  It is of paramount importance that people should look out for each other, with companies in the region supporting others in the locality.  That would apply in this instance and in many others.</p><p>Senator Moran commented on the extension of the redress scheme for former patients of Dr. Neary, which is to be welcomed.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Reilly, should be complimented on the issue.  I note the Senator's points on symphysiotomy and the Walsh report, and I will inquire about the appointment of the judge as requested.  Senator Moran also discussed the cost of school uniforms in lauding the greater role for parents announced yesterday by the Minister for Education and Skills.</p><p>Senator Mooney extended his sympathy to the family of Mr. Eddie McGrady.</p> <p>We would all like to join him in sending our sympathy to the family of the late Eddie McGrady who was an excellent representative for his people.</p><p>Senators Catherine Noone and C&aacute;it Keane spoke about the role of women in politics and how they could be kept involved in it.  That applies not only to women but also to many young people who have become involved in politics in terms of retaining their interest.  The matter is worthy of further debate in the House.  I will invite the Minister to come to the House to discuss it.</p><p>I have addressed the points raised by Senator Fidelma Healy Eames on the safety of local credit unions.  The message should go out from this House that people&rsquo;s money in credit unions is safe.  They have the same guarantees as in the case of banks in that savings up to &euro;100,000 are guaranteed.  The Irish League of Credit Unions and the Central Bank are singing from the same hymn sheet in that regard.</p><p>Senator Marie Moloney referred to the youth guarantee, an issue I have addressed.  I note her points on data protection in connection with accessing the credit card details of 70,000 people, which is not proper.  I agree that we should possibly have a further debate on data protection, an issue we debated in the House previously.</p><p>Senator C&aacute;it Keane called for a debate on public rights of way following the Supreme Court's decision yesterday.  We should wait for the dust to settle before we have such a debate in the House.  I agree that the decision gives rise to a number of questions, but we need time to consider them before having a debate in the House.</p><p>Senator Feargal Quinn spoke about problems with RSA Insurance.  He said much of the problem related to insurance claims, but I do not think the major shortfall in the accounts in question was due fully to injury claims.  They account for part but not all of the problem.  The Personal Injuries Assessment Board has done an excellent job in recent years since it was set up.  Perhaps we might receive an update and discuss the matter in the House.</p><p>Senator Terry Brennan commented on the opening of a greenway in Carlingford and the Cooley Mountains.  Greenways such as it and the one in Westport and Castlebar are of great benefit to the tourism industry and for the general health of those who use them.  I hope to see a similar greenway open in Waterford along the old railway line between Waterford and Dungarvan.  That will need similar co-operation from landowners as has been shown in other areas.  I hope it will be forthcoming because there are major benefits for tourism in areas where they are located.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.61" nospeaker="true" time="15:40:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.62" nospeaker="true" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200016#P00300">Jurisdiction and Recognition and Enforcement of Judgments in Civil and Commercial Matters: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200016#P00400"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Regulation (EU) No 1215/2012 on jurisdiction and the recognition and enforcement of judgments in civil and commercial matters, a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 23rd August 2013.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.64" nospeaker="true" time="15:40:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.65" nospeaker="true" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200016#P00600">Article 290 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200016#P00700"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure: Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council adapting to Article 290 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union a number of legal acts in the area of Justice providing for the use of the regulatory procedure with scrutiny, a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 12th July 2013.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.67" nospeaker="true" time="15:40:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.68" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200017#Q00100">Science Week: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200017#Q00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Education and Skills, Deputy Sean Sherlock.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/979" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200017#Q00300"><p>I thank the House for giving me the opportunity to speak about Science Week.  This week, from 10 to 17 November, Ireland will reverberate with the sights and sounds of science when Science Week 2013 takes place.  There is a lot of alliteration in that sentence.  Now in its seventh year, Science Week is a national initiative co-ordinated by Science Foundation Ireland's Discover programme that allows everybody to embrace science by way of an enormous range of events taking place the length and breadth of the country.  The aim of Science Week is to promote the relevance of science, engineering and technology in our everyday lives and demonstrate the importance of these disciplines to the future development of Irish society and the national economy.</p><p>  The theme of Science Week 2013, Exploring the Extraordinary, provides people with the opportunity to explore what is happening behind the scenes of everyday life and to look at the extraordinary processes that make up the ordinary parts of our lives.  Last year more than 200,000 people participated in hundreds of events run by schools, colleges, libraries, teachers, researchers and students throughout the country.  There are more than 770 events registered on the Science Week website for this year and even more events will take place during the week.  Despite the pressure on limited resources that everyone faces, Science Week keeps going from strength to strength and every year event organisers have seen a rise in attendance, year on year.  </p><p>  The Discover Science and Engineering, DSE, programme has been a considerable supporter of Science Week during the years.  Administration of the DSE programme was taken over by Science Foundation Ireland last year and as the Discover programme, it continues to successfully develop and implement effective ways of engaging students, teachers and the public in the STEM subjects, namely, science, technology, engineering and mathematics.  The overall objectives are to increase the numbers of students studying the physical sciences, promote a positive attitude to careers in STEM and foster a greater understanding of science and its value to Irish society.  Achieving this requires close interaction with third level institutions and intermediate audiences such as industry and the media.  The programme aims to make a co-ordinated effort to increase interest in STEM and encourage young people to consider STEM areas as viable career options.  Apart from a comprehensive events and activities programme, the programme's web portal features links to relevant programmes and areas.</p><p>  Some examples of Discover-DSE initiatives are the Discover Primary Science and Maths website, aimed at primary school teachers and pupils; Greenwave, a mass science experiment involving primary schools on the arrival of spring in Ireland; Nanoquest, a project that uses video gaming to encourage 13 to 15 year old school students to develop an interest in nanotechnology and science generally; ESERO, under which Discover partnered with the European Space Agency to establish the European Space Education Resource Office, ESERO, a programme to inspire and engage young people in STEM subjects; ProjectBlogger, a site that allows teachers and second level students in Ireland to create blogs based on their science experiences and interests; My Science Career, a website that brings together resources for finding out more about a career in STEM and includes information on careers in a number of STEM areas, including ICT; <i>science.ie</i>, which provides a wide range of information on science, technology, engineering and mathematics to stimulate young people's interest in these areas; and Smart Futures, a national campaign for second level students in Ireland, highlighting career opportunities in information and communications technology, ICT, in association with the annual e-Skills Week.  These are all initiatives capable of exciting, stimulating and inspiring young people, which is exactly what we need to achieve.</p> <p>This is extremely important as the Government remains committed to the vision of using research and innovation to generate jobs and economic growth so that scientific innovation and new technologies will shape the future for the next generation of our students.  The jobs agenda is writ large all over this Administration's programme for Government, as we seek to deliver qualified and high-quality personnel to take up jobs in both foreign direct investment enterprise and indigenous enterprise.  We are also pursuing the provision of highly skilled employment by repositioning Irish enterprise higher up the value chain.  The Government is working towards this vision through many complementary initiatives, one such being research prioritisation.  The research prioritisation exercise identified priority areas that will build on Ireland's existing research strengths.  They will also have the potential to deliver sustainable economic return through enterprise development, employment growth, job retention and tangible improvements to quality of life.  The report of the research prioritisation steering group recommended 14 areas of opportunity, as well as underpinning technologies and infrastructure to support these priority areas.  The areas were identified on the basis of existing strengths of the public research system, existing strengths of the enterprise base, opportunities that exist in the global marketplace and those which are most likely to deliver economic and societal impact, as well as jobs.</p><p>The report also made 13 systemic recommendations which were required to improve the efficiency and effectiveness of the science, technology and innovation, STI, system to support the implementation of prioritisation.  The 14 priority areas cover a diverse spectrum of activities including data analytics management, security and privacy, connected health and independent living, food for health, marine renewable energy, and smart grids and smart cities.</p><p>The Government agreed to the adoption of the research prioritisation steering group's recommendations as a whole-of-government policy goal and with regard to the future alignment of the majority of public STI investment with these 14 areas of opportunity.  Following publication of the steering group's report on 1 March 2012, the prioritisation action group, PAG, was established under my chairmanship and political leadership to drive implementation of research prioritisation under the broader authority of the Cabinet committee on economic recovery and jobs.  The group meets in plenary and has set an ambitious pace for implementation.  It is supported by a range of working groups established to progress implementation between plenary sessions.  Action plans designed to identify the actions required across research funding organisations to realign the majority of competitive public research funding around the priority areas have been developed for each priority area.  Engagement with relevant stakeholders on the draft action plans took place at the end of 2012.  The action plans were approved by the Government in June 2013 and published in July 2013.</p><p>To oversee their implementation in a holistic manner, each action plan has been assigned a champion who, in almost all cases, chaired the relevant working group which developed the plan.  This is providing the forum to pave the way for an efficient process for the implementation of the plans.  At the first meeting of champions, it was agreed the plans should remain live and evolve over time to ensure they can respond to real-time market developments and opportunities.  The PAG will oversee implementation of the plans.</p><p>Moreover, a detailed framework of metrics and targets has been drawn up as part of research prioritisation to measure the outputs and impact of funding provided, which will comprehend all of the 14 action plans for the respective priority areas.  This too was approved by the Government in June 2013.</p><p>There will also be ongoing monitoring and reporting of developments of the systemic recommendations contained in the report of the research prioritisation steering group.  For the second pillar, 13 systemic changes are necessary to support prioritisation by improving the efficiency and effectiveness of the STI system.  The PAG is also making significant progress.</p> <p>In June 2012 an intellectual property protocol was published outlining new structures to encourage more businesses to commercialise research and development by ensuring they could access the results of State-funded, effectively taxpayer funded, research and development with greater clarity and certainty.  The PAG is also considering how application procedures for research funding can be adjusted to assess relevance to, and impact on, priority areas, as well as assessing excellence, with Science Foundation Ireland already leading the way in this regard.</p><p> In response to recommendations to align supply and demand of trained researchers, the Irish Research Council has rolled out an employment-based PhD and masters programme where awardees will be employees with the majority of time spent in-company.  In response to the recommendation that research centres be more industry-focused, on 25 February the largest ever State-industry co-funded research investment was announced.  This investment of &euro;300 million is made up of &euro;200 million of Exchequer funding and a &euro;100 million co-investment by over 150 industry partners.  This level of industry commitment is sure evidence of the value and potential of the research that will be carried out in each of the seven new world class SFI research centres established.  These are research centres of excellence and scale.  Under the awards programme, they will be funded over six years, support key growth areas and undertake research into major social challenges, including health, communications and energy.  A capability to add &quot;research spokes&quot; around the original &quot;hub&quot; will make them more adaptable to account for changing circumstances and emerging research challenges.</p><p> To return to Science Week, I cannot over-emphasise how important it is as an annual national awareness raising event.  It is an exciting collaboration of events run by colleges, schools, libraries, teachers, researchers and students throughout Ireland.  Science Week has become an important event in many people's calendars and it is truly inspirational to see the numbers who turn out and support all of the events each year.  Event organisers across the country become actively involved with Science Week each year and it is their dedication and hard work that make the week the success that it is.  This year there are new key elements.  A new festival in the midlands is bringing top-class exhibitions, workshops and talks, including Trinity College Dublin's Luke O'Neill and Canadian neuroscientist Deborah Saucier, to venues in counties Offaly, Westmeath and Laois.</p><p> A major new hub is being created in Temple Bar in Dublin this weekend where there will be a free experiential event at the Gallery of Photography, a free family event at Filmbase, a kids' science show at City Hall, as well as physics buskers on the streets.  It is also encouraging that, yet again, festivals in Cork, Galway, Mayo, Sligo, Waterford and Limerick are all running an extensive programme of events this year.</p><p> Evidence from research carried out in 2012 by DSE, now the Discover programme, suggested the 18-24 year age cohort still did not consider science and technology industries interesting.  Last year Science Week set out to change that perception and follow on, like for like research showed that among that age group interest had increased by 7% in science and 8% in engineering.  Most of our children's career opportunities will be built around harnessing new and evolving technologies that are only now establishing themselves.  It is critically important that we give students a window into these industries and the experiences of people working in them.  It is also vital that we ensure students are engaging in science and scientific thinking at an early age.  We must continue to encourage young school students to engage with scientific learning and thinking which, in turn, will encourage them to consider studying STEM subjects at second and third level.</p><p> Science Week serves as a magnet that continues to attract inquiring young students to the world of science and it stimulates their awareness of the many possibilities and pathways that study in this area will offer them.  Therefore, I urge all Senators to check out <i>scienceweek.ie</i>and attend or promote as many events as possible.  Not only will they be pleasantly surprised by the huge voluntary effort that has gone into the organisation of the week, but I also guarantee that they will, as I have done, learn and be entertained at the same time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200020#T00100"><p>I congratulate Deputy Sherlock on his activities to date as Minister of State with responsibility for science and innovation and on the passion he has put into his work.  I know his father, looking down, will be very proud of him.</p><p>Science Week promises to be a very beneficial initiative to bring science closer to the people.  Science Week also awards us the unique opportunity to examine the role science can play in addressing major societal challenges such as poverty and hunger.  While science plays a central role in the lives of everyone, it is important that we use this initiative to bring science closer to our younger people in particular.</p><p>I am hopeful that national Science Week 2013 encourages participating students to become more engaged with science subjects because I believe science is a core part of employment creation and retention.  We must rethink science education in our schools in order to ensure scientific subjects become a more attractive option for our young students.  As the Minister of State also has responsibility in the Department of Education and Skills, I urge him to address the very important aspect of curriculum development and reform of STEM subjects.  Concentrating efforts to make science, technology, engineering and mathematics more vibrant and interesting subjects to students in our primary and secondary level schools and colleges must be a key objective for the Government.</p><p>In the Irish societal context, rethinking our education system must be a high priority to ensure our young people are prepared for the very different world and jobs market they will be facing in the future.  I suggest that we make STEM subjects more practical.  I watched a programme on Discovery Channel the other night which explained the way the earth, moon and sun interact to teenagers.  One child acted as the sun, another as the moon and so on, and the programme explained the concept in a simple way that made it very comprehensible, rather than just having those involved read theoretically from a book on how the solar system works.  It was fascinating and I wish I had learned it like that at school.  Giving students something they can reach out and touch, and get excited about while in the classroom, will keep them engaged with the subject matter.</p><p>Last week in this House, I spoke about the brilliant German system of dual education.  The German dual education system requires that students spend up to 70% of their time in third level in the workplace of offices, shop floors and foundries in an apprenticeship capacity and the remaining 30% in the classroom.  I raise this with the Minster of State in his dual capacity in regard to research and innovation and also in regard to education and skills because I believe it is urgent that we establish a similar system in Ireland.  We are behind the times in our narrow-minded focus on preparation for the jobs that are available in the market.  It is clear that education which adopts an enhanced practical approach is working.  Angela Merkel and David Cameron have expressed the belief that the German system of dual education, which champions a practical approach, is the best way to tackle youth unemployment.</p><p>Science Week 2013 is an important part of Discover Science and Engineering, DSE, which is Ireland's national science awareness programme.  The programme aims to contribute to Ireland's growth and development as a knowledge economy, keeping us among the world's most competitive economies so that we can attract foreign direct investment.  If this ideal is to become a reality, the Government must do the groundwork to ensure that enough of our young people choose careers in the relevant sectors.</p> <p> It is vitally important that initiatives such as Science Week assist young people at all levels of education to recognise the very promising career opportunities that are available in the enterprise economy and realistically attainable through the study of science.  Over the past decade, Ireland has built a quality research capability.  The time is now right to more aggressively develop the translational part of the discovery-to-delivery continuum.  Ireland is excelling in a range of key scientific disciplines such as immunology, nano technology, materials science, genetics and genomics.  Initiatives such as Science Week give us an opportunity to promote the progress that we have made and highlight the future possibilities a career in science can offer our young people.  Research and innovation are of critical importance when one considers their potential role in contributing to economic recovery and growth.  This is why we must prioritise intensifying the relationship between science and our primary, second, third and fourth level students in order to nurture and encourage a new generation of researchers and innovators who will create enterprise, jobs and growth within our economy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200021#U00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for being in attendance to discuss the important topic of Science Week.  Therefore, it was important to set aside time for it today and this week.  The debate affords us the opportunity to air our views and even promote the initiative.</p><p>As we all know, science is extremely important to the economy and for community and societal development.  Science Week has been in existence since 1996.  The Discover Science &amp;amp; Engineering programme has been very successful.  It has worked extremely well and encourages primary and secondary school students to take up science and pursue it as a career by studying the STEM subjects of science, technology, engineering and maths.  The objective of Science Week is to increase awareness among parents, teachers and the general community of the value of science.  The initiative has a successful track record and will continue its work.  </p><p>Earlier this month Forf&aacute;s published a report by its Expert Group on Future Skills Needs that addressed future demand for ICT skills and information and communications technology.  The report indicated a continued demand for high level ICT skills across the economy.  It also reckons that 44,500 jobs will have to be filled by graduates and skilled professionals and demand will continue right up to 2018.  Of course the report recommended various initiatives that could and should be taken.  It also recommended a continuance of the current initiatives such as focusing on mainstream education, training such as the conversion and reskilling programmes, and continual professional development for teachers and graduates who work in disciplines that no longer provide employment.  We must also attract experienced international talent, including ex-pats, in order to develop an awareness and contribute to further employment creation in the economy.</p><p>The report by the Expert Group on Future Skills Needs is one of a series of reports.  They are very important because they highlight the area, focus on vacancies and play a strong role in promoting the sector which can be proven because the number of computer graduates has increased by 25% over the past two years.  A target was set to double the number of computer graduates by 2018 but it looks like we will reach that target by 2015.  That is positive news. </p><p>The words &quot;ICT sector&quot; turns many people off.  As the Minister of State said himself, the ICT sector does not engage 18 to 24 year olds and they are uninterested.  However, ICT is not just about technology, computing or coding.  It covers a wide range of jobs such as web development, special effects for film and the arts, selling to customers, customer services and more.  We need to get that point across.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200022#V00100"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200022#V00200"><p>It is not just for a narrow focus.  Nine of the ten top software companies are established here, including Intel, Dell, Microsoft, IBM, Apple, HP, Facebook and Google.  As it accounts for one third of our exports it is hugely important for the economy.  Eight of the ten top pharmaceutical companies are located here.  This is a very important sector for the economy and guarantees job security.  For every one job created in the IBMs, the Dells or the Microsofts, there is another one to 1.4 jobs in the community, an issue that needs to be highlighted.</p><p>I really like the theme of Science Week.  It appeals across the community and to parents and teachers to encourage careers in this area.  This is the time of year we hear about parent-teacher meetings.  I know from attending them there was always a queue for the language teachers.  In the previous eight or nine years the focus was on business.  The science, physics and applied maths teachers always had the shorter queues.  I do not think that has changed much, despite the fact that those subjects are extremely important.  Those students are no different from any other students and they have the potential to study those subjects to honours level, as required.</p><p>There are many openings in the area which can be satisfying because technology crosses all sectors of our lives.  The companies whose operations are located here serve global markets, therefore languages are important.  The fact is that technology contributes to a very meaningful industry and is available on the doorstep to many young people and those who are not so young who may have participated in the ICT action plan.</p><p>In summary, does the Minister of State plan to have a review of the ICT action plan and particularly the graduate conversion programmes which were introduced very quickly and were successful in many cases?  Many individuals who had a profession that was no longer relevant could avail of those conversion programmes.  The quality of the programmes is important.  That message needs to be developed to ensure positive results.  As the ICT action plan will be in place for two years in January 2014, a review of the conversion programmes, in particular, is extremely important.</p><p>As the Minister of State is responsible for research, an area that has come to my attention, on which he might wish to comment, is PhD students and the payment they receive.  I was contacted by a female who is doing research and is being paid a stipend, not a salary.  She is a mother of two young children who has lost the one-parent family payment.  When I made inquiries of the Minister for Social Protection I found it was because the money that is paid to PhD students is not insurable income.  Therefore, such students are not entitled to sick pay, maternity pay and other means-tested benefits.</p><p>My understanding is that in other European Union countries, not in the UK, the payment to postgraduates is considered insurable income.  Many of these students are in their mid to late 20s and may have transferred straight from undergraduate level but are still treated as students while their peers may be earning, investing in mortgages and having children.  They are still treated as students by the legal, tax and social welfare systems here.  A move towards a recognised status with the normal payments made towards social welfare and pension systems would certainly strengthen the general professionalism and recognition of a doctoral student's studies.  As it is a subject the Minister of State may have covered already or may have encountered it previously, I  would be interested to hear his comments.</p> <p> I commend the Minister of State on his important support for science and research.  The figures for the uptake of computing and core science subjects show that our efforts are bearing fruit.  The 25 bonus points initiative for maths was a positive move.  It may not be the be-all-and-end-all for everybody, but it made a strong statement on the part of the State that maths is important and that we want to give bonus points to people of that calibre who take on maths at higher level.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200023#W00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and I am delighted that science is part of his portfolio.  I was very fortunate to attend Newbridge College, back in the 1950s, where we had a marvellous science teacher, Fr. Michael Casey.  Everybody did science.  We had a great laboratory and a great teacher.  Later on, Fr. Casey became a professor of science in Maynooth.  We studied physics, chemistry, physiology and botany.  It is important that we get our young people interested in and enthused about all of these areas of science.  The concept of Science Week is important in encouraging children to become interested in science.</p><p>There are other things we could do to promote an interest in science.  Do we need more of a push to promote science as a career rather than just as a subject?  A group of legislators in the United States came up with a Bill recently to promote the creation of a science laureate who would be tasked with exciting children about careers in science.  The Bill was defeated politically, but the question of how to promote science among students remains relevant, particularly in this country.  Senator Clune's comments reminded us of this.</p><p>Should we consider getting more impetus at a political level?  While science is taught in schools and while Science Week raises significant interest, it is interesting to see what is going on in the United States.  There is a youth organisation in the US called the 4-H Club.  This club has been around for a long time and was to do with agriculture originally.  The 4-H stands for heart, head, hands and health.  The club is administered by the US Department of Agriculture and it aims to spread science ideas among young people.  Some 2 million children attend the group's clubs and camps, while millions more follow the 4-H programmes in schools.  The group reaches approximately one out of every three children in farming in states such as Nebraska and it has a great focus on agriculture and the science behind it.  I mention this club because I believe we should have a debate here on genetically modified foods.  I believe there is a danger that we will lose out unless we consider the situation in this regard.  If we who are in the agrifood business ignore the trends and changes, we are in serious danger of falling behind.  Children in the 4-H clubs do a variety of projects such as looking after egg incubators in schools, dissecting a pig's eye, analysing farm animal diseases or starting their own organic farm projects.  We should do something similar here.  This is an American idea in that it twins the great outdoors with personal development and how to make money from it - what we call entrepreneurship.</p><p>Ireland remains an agricultural country and the fact the sector is making a comeback in recent times may be reason to consider the example of the 4-H Club.  I know we have Macra na Feirme, but the 4-H Club's combining of hard science and agriculture and how to make money from them is very interesting.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn, wants to introduce significant reform.  Agricultural science would appear to be a logical step in that regard and would be more relevant than some of the current subjects taught.  Some amazing things are happening in the area of personalised learning.  Rocketship is a chain of seven charter schools in California that blend traditional teaching with at least one hour a day of individualised online instruction in mathematics, literature and comprehension.  Its low-income students outperform those students living in the wealthiest districts of the same state.</p> <p> Another school in North Carolina introduced personalised learning on laptops for all students aged ten and over in the year 2000.  Between then and 2012, the proportion of the pupils considered proficient in maths, science and reading rose from 73% to 88%.  Bill Gates of Microsoft fame, who follows developments in education technology and whose foundation funds some such developments, refers to this as a special time in education.  We have a great deal to learn in respect of this matter.</p><p>Some years ago, I was very fortunate to get to know James Watson who, along with his colleague, Francis Crick, discovered the structure of DNA - the double helix - in 1953.  Both were awarded the Nobel Prize in 1962.  James Watson comes to Ireland every year, visits Trinity College and usually comes to our home.  We have got to know him well and we have also visited him at his home.  He is 85 years of age but it remains a joy to meet and speak to him.  When he came to Ireland this year, a group of us arranged for him to unveil a lovely piece of sculpture - the double helix sculpture - in the Botanic Gardens.  Anyone who has not already visited the latter should make a point of doing so.  The Botanic Gardens are huge but they are also very educational.  I am sure people will visit in much larger numbers in the future.</p><p>As stated on previous occasions, I would love to see greater focus on teaching entrepreneurship in schools, perhaps even at primary level.  Entrepreneurship is taught in schools in Norway with support from, among others, that country's Ministry of Trade and Industry and local businesses.  The Norwegian strategy is aimed at developing knowledge and comprehension relating to entrepreneurial activities in students in order to strengthen their belief in their own capabilities and creative force.  I am of the view that science can help a great deal in this regard.</p><p>Science Week provides us with the opportunity to pursue that to which I refer with vigour, enthusiasm and a huge commitment that will benefit the entire country.  I am delighted that this debate is taking place.  I am strongly of the view that the efforts to promote Science Week will bear fruit not just immediately but also in the years to come.  I congratulate the Minister of State on those efforts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200024#X00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  It only seems like five minutes ago but a full 12 months have passed since we last discussed Science week.  It has been a busy year.  It is good to hear about all the many projects that were progressed and the advances that were made during those short 12 months.  Dublin City University, DCU, has referred to a significant swing in the direction of STEM-based courses, which are now attracting more than 4,000 first preference applications.  When we are seeking hard evidence with regard to progress being made, we can point to the fact that those in DCU are happy.  There has been an increase in the number of first year students entering Sligo Institute of Technology this year.  Part of the &euro;35 million development programme at the institute involves the construction of an extension to the science block, which will house several lecture theatres, specialist laboratories and a 600-seat student restaurant.  Of course I hope students will not spend all of their time in the latter.  If the Minister of State visits Sligo IT this week, he will have the opportunity to try out the bed of nails which has been put in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/979" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200024#X00300"><p>I am already on a bed of nails.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200024#X00400"><p>Indeed.  As previous speakers indicated, the purpose of Science Week is to try to make science exciting.  The question which then arises relates to how to export that excitement back to the classroom.  Senators White and Clune referred to the very real challenge which exists in this regard.  We can have a week of terrific excitement, as should be the case, and we can celebrate that the fact that science is all about the world around us and that everything we do has some scientific basis.  What has been the feedback with regard to how we might recreate the excitement to which I refer in the classroom?</p><p>I am aware, from speaking to a number of them, that secondary school students can become a bit bogged down in science in the early stages.  This occurs at the very moment when a teacher wants them to stay with it.  When, at the age of 13 or 14, they are still young enough to be excited and are not entirely cynical about the world, how do we keep them in that state of excitement where anything is possible?  This is the best thing that Science Week brings out in students in the various locations throughout the country to which the Minister of State referred.</p> <p>All my colleagues here are aware of places close to them where Science Week is working well.  We can continue to celebrate Science Week and put on terrific events but how do we take that forward?  Is there a bridging committee or piece of research to ensure that schools could take hold of even one or two of the best of those ideas in a simple way?  I know from talking to science teachers in schools that they are always looking for ways to excite their students.  Some of them are dedicated scientists in their own right who want to give to children what they got when they were studying, and they are trying to do that in a modern environment where they are fighting all the other distractions that steal children's time and attention.  Is that something we could do?</p><p> It is worth patting ourselves on the back briefly in terms of those students who have done Ireland proud.  For three years in a row we have won the European Union young scientist competition, which is no mean feat given the size of Ireland and the size of the competition.  Ciara Judge, Emer Hickey and Sophie Healy-Throw from Kinsale Community School won this year.  Their investigation into the effects of a particular form of bacteria on the germination of seeds is the kind of project that has been praised for its commercial potential in the agri-industry, something in which I know the Minister is particularly interested.  He praised Professor Fergus Shanahan from UCC, my <i>alma mater</i>, on his award for researcher of the year and the work it is doing with Moorepark food research centre, all of which ties back to the agri-food industry.</p><p> In that regard I disagree with my colleague Senator Quinn because I would like to believe that Ireland's agriculture and food industries would be built on a GM-free environment.  We must have that debate because we have moments where we disagree but I am sure we could have a rewarding conversation about that, which is something that would have an implication for the Minister's Department as well as for his colleagues in the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  Given the level of scientific knowledge and our own experience in places like Moorepark, the whole of Teagasc, UCC, UCD and across the country - we have a wealth of knowledge - how would we approach the GM debate?  We should not shirk it any longer.</p><p> The students in Sligo IT won the Microsoft Imagine Cup, which is probably the biggest cup for students.  They won it twice in Ireland and in 2011 they won the worldwide Imagine Cup.  This is a small academy compared to the huge organisations with which they are competing.  We have a wealth of talent but we must continue to encourage those students who come forward.  </p><p> I am reminded of the Collison brothers of whom I am sure the Minister is well aware.  Patrick Collison was 19 when they sold their first Internet company and made &euro;1 million.  Patrick was a winner in the young scientist award and obviously was a man with huge natural talent yet the brothers are now working in the United States.  One of the Forf&aacute;s recommendations is that we would encourage not just international expertise to Ireland but ex-pats to come back to Ireland.  It is to people like Patrick and his brother John that we would be looking with a view to forming relationships.  I am aware they have a business here but I understand they are based in the US.  Originally they looked a little young and they went to the US without being able to get investment here.  We do not want to see those opportunities fall through the cracks on another occasion.  In regard to an issue I brought to his attention the Minister has helped to try to avoid that, and it is something we must try to avoid.</p><p> In terms of opportunities for the future, is there a way the top companies in Ireland listed by Senator Clune can open their doors to students and young people in this Science Week?  Would they be able to offer time and space once a year for children and young people to see what it is like to work in one of those companies?</p> <p> I note that President Higgins presented the gold Gaisce awards today.  Could Science Week and all the great work being done by Science Foundation Ireland and the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation be developed in collaboration with Gaisce?  </p><p> In regard to work experience, is there a way in which companies could agree to offer 1,000 work placements every year to transition year students on a formal as opposed to an <i>ad hoc</i>basis?  AbbVie in Sligo has been particularly good at supporting young people in our community and while I am sure other companies do the same, perhaps a formalised approach would strengthen the link between young people and the working environment and help in the transition from the excitement of Science Week to the reality of finding a job.</p><p> Senator Feargal Quinn touched on the subject of sponsoring after school clubs.  Perhaps companies involved in information technology, science and research might consider this suggestion in some shape or form.  I am aware that the Minister of State is working very hard on Horizon 2020 and I urge him to keep up the good work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200026#Z00200"><p>I welcome the opportunity to take part in this discussion.  It is not a debate because most people are of one mind on the importance of science and the welcome role Science Week plays in connecting young people to the area of science.  A wide range of events are taking place, with nearly 1,000 events listed on the website.  Schools and libraries in County Meath are hosting a considerable number of events.</p><p>Last week a 16 year old transition year student was in my office to gain work experience.  She raised an issue that I thought had gone away some time ago, namely, the attitude towards the teaching of physics and chemistry in girls' schools.  They are seen as boys' subjects, whereas biology is seen as a girl's subject.  I had believed those days were gone.  My recollection of chemistry and physics is that they were difficult subjects.  I often recommended people not to pursue them if they were simply looking for leaving certificate points because there were easier options.  However, they are also important subjects.  I would like to see an examination carried out of where physics and chemistry are taught and whether statistical evidence is available to suggest they are less likely to be taught in girls' schools.  The person with whom I spoke thought it was disgraceful that physics, in particular, was not always made available in schools.  In some schools a choice is offered in the junior cycle between arts and music, on the one hand, and science subjects, on the other.  If one takes that option at an early stage, one's educational options are being closed to further development.  Students' intellects and interests develop rapidly during their years in secondary school.  This is an issue the Department of Education and Skills could easily investigate.  If a significant number of girls are not being offered physics and chemistry because of an outdated culture in their schools, it would be a shame and a disgrace.  Many of these girls are equally as good as, if not better than, their male counterparts.  The aforementioned person was involved in CoderDojo outside her school and is fascinated by computing and physics.  She wants to work in that area, but it may not be possible for her to do so in the context of the subjects she can take in school.  We have a challenge to ensure these sexists attitudes do not prevail because they will only hold the country back.  I would be concerned if my daughter was restricted to a choice between artistic and science subjects from an early age.</p><p>I wish those involved in national Science Week well and hope those who will participate in events will benefit from them.</p> <p>The are many positive aspects to participation, with great enjoyment and learning to be had in making discoveries, doing experiments and making some mistakes.  Participation could also be of benefit to students in securing employment in the future, which is a practical consideration as things stand in this country.  Above all, however, science is about discovery, about finding out how things work at all levels of human existence and experience.  I support and encourage the Minister of State in his efforts in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200027#AA00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Sherlock, to the House.  I attended a conference this morning in the Rotunda Hospital at which he delivered a very good and detailed contribution.  The area of medical research is very relevant to our discussion today.  This country can have an important part to play in progressing developments in this area and devising new solutions to medical problems.</p><p>Senator Clune referred to funding for people involved in research.  There was discussion at the conference this morning about the lack of a career path for researchers and the pay scales involved.  Perhaps it is time to consider offering tax reliefs, comparable with the reliefs offered to artists, to people who are directly involved in and whose only source of income comes from research and development, particularly medical research.  There might be an upper income limit below which people would be exempt from paying tax.  The same type of scheme has worked very well in the case of artists, particularly people involved in the music industry.  The advantage of such reliefs is that as well as offering a benefit to the recipient, there is a benefit for society at large whether in terms of artistic output or medical breakthroughs.  The introduction of a tax relief scheme in the area of research and development also offers the potential to generate a large number of jobs.</p><p>I do not want to take from the importance and benefits of Science Week, but it is important to highlight another issue that was raised at the conference this morning, namely, that funding for research and development is provided by different organisations without any overall strategic co-ordination.  It is an issue we must address.  People and organisations, including pharmaceutical companies, hospitals and universities, should be working together to achieve the maximum impact in this area and an overall benefit for the country.</p><p>Another issue raised at the conference related to the Health Research Board, the shift away from biomedical research and the fact that Science Foundation Ireland is not picking up all the slack.  In other words, research is falling between two stools.  The question was raised this morning as to whether we have the necessary infrastructure in place in certain areas to ensure we get the maximum benefit out of Horizon 2020.  The target is to get in more than &euro;1 billion over a period of time and it is important that we prioritise that.  I take the opportunity to thank the Minister of State for the work he has done to date in this area.  He has been very proactive in putting the co-ordination process in place, but a great deal of work remains to be done.  We are very fortunate in Cork to have nine of the ten top pharmaceutical companies based within a 50 mile radius of the city.  We need to start taking better advantage of that by enhancing co-ordination between, for example, universities and hospitals.</p> <p>The lack of co-ordination of clinical research was also raised.  We must do more in that area.  I was at the conference because of an interest in rare diseases.  Science has moved on and medical research has moved on and we are now identifying rare conditions.  The country is so small that the number of directly people affected is quite small, with only four or six families being affected by a given disease.  In United States, a rare condition might affect 200 or 300 people.  It is not possible for us to provide the backup support to a person with the condition.  We need to co-ordinate between member states in the European Union to share information.  That also ties into the directive with regard to cross-border health care and the sharing of information between member states and medical organisations across the 28 member states.  The directive was passed in February 2011 but the target is now to have it in place by February or March 2014.  This will be welcome in terms of co-ordinating the health services to provide solutions to particular problems.  We need to do more work on getting assistance from the UK, where the population is 55 million or 60 million and where more people are affected by rare conditions than the number affected here.  There is much to be learned with regard to research and development and we need to do it in a far more co-ordinated way than was the case in the past.  The Minister of State has done much work in the area and hopefully he can get the necessary support to continue to develop and grow the area.  I thank him for his contribution to date.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200028#BB00200"><p>I am delighted we have the opportunity to discuss science policy.  It is not widely appreciated that the brief of the Minister of State is the most important in the Government.  It is unlikely that the future of our species will be determined by real estate prices or paying bondholders but there is no doubt that this century we could cease to exist if we do not get the right answers to a number of critical science questions about food, water and energy.  It is a measure of the importance that the broader scientific laity are attracting to science that there is increasing recognition of science as critically important.  Why is it important?  We need more people to do science in school and for longer.  Is it because we need more people to be full-time scientists?  No, although we do need more people to be full-time scientists, it is not the principal reason.  We need everyone to know more about science because it is the process by which we interrogate the laws of nature, learn from them and increase the body of knowledge we have so that we can adapt the laws to our benefit.</p><p>To an extent, we are all scientists.  Every child that has poked a finger at a hot object and recoiled has made a scientific observation.  That wisdom continues throughout life and we continue to learn.  We tend to compartmentalised &quot;science&quot; as a thing done by people who look like Christopher Lloyd in &quot;Back to the Future&quot;, with frizzy hair and long white coats, and that it is not relevant to what the rest of us do.  Clearly, that is misconception.  Much of that has influenced the way we educate people to do science in school.  With no disrespect to religion, it is extraordinary that religion is seen as a mandatory subject all the way to leaving certificate level in so many schools, whereas science becomes wholly optional.  Whatever one may say about the reality or otherwise of the theories on which various religions are based, the reality of science is there and if we do not know about it is greatly to our detriment.</p><p>During Science Week, the Minister of State and his colleagues in education must be thinking about a core policy of making some form of science education an integral, non-optional part of the curriculum until the day students leave school.</p> <p>There are two tricks involved, one of which is to make it interesting because our history is replete with examples of subjects we decided by virtue of social engineering to make compulsory which resulted in large numbers of people hating them.  In truth, compulsory Irish was one of these subjects.  Many people never liked learning Irish in school because of the element of compulsion involved.  In a previous generation there was a necessity to have Irish when applying for public service jobs, there was the incredible focus on the teaching of grammar as opposed to trying to learn about the beauty of the language and its cultural context.  This policy has not worked.  The de Valera vision that in this century we would be an Irish-speaking nation and doing our normal business through Irish has not come to pass.  We cannot allow the same to happen to science.  It is critically important that we educate a generation of people who understand the laws of science because they are going to be asked to vote on things in respect of which science is relevant.  Society will have to make decisions about things like genetically modified food, energy policy, nuclear energy policy, tobacco and alcohol regulation and other aspects to do with vaccination policy.  Into the vacuum of ignorance of science step all kinds of bizarre theories which can have very negative social consequences beyond the narrow scientific confines in which they are found.  Most people do not study religion until they are 18 years old because they plan to become priests, nuns or imams, but they study religion nonetheless, nor should people only be expected to study religion until they are 18 years if they intend to follow careers in science.  Lawyers need to know about science, as do real estate brokers, architects, artists and poets.  The study of science should be an integral part of everyone's education.  To that end, I urge the Minister of State and the Minister for Education and Skills to come together to develop what I believe should be a core module of broad science for those who are not particularly interested in pursuing a career in science but who would like or would be encouraged to the point of compulsion to have an ongoing education in science, including the study of health science, health care, food science, nutrition and environmental studies.  These are critically important aspects about which people need to know.</p><p>On a practical level, I was delighted to hear Senator Colm Burke say something I had been advocating for a while.  We should consider the idea of introducing 0% corporation tax for science-based research and development enterprises, but it would have to be policed and bona fide.  It could not be some kind of accounting exercise to enable people to hide manufacturing or investment expenses or pension funds in some kind of spurious research and development.  It would need to be tangible, subject to the same kind of peer review as science grants and would need to generate jobs for research scientists.  The spin-off benefits would be significant.</p><p>Senator Colm Burke mentioned the need for co-operative clinical research.  I would like to think I was one of the people who had some role in developing such research in this country.  In the sphere of cancer research I founded two cancer research organisations, one of which has true national clout, which has brought research-based treatments to patients throughout the country and brought in tens of millions of free drugs into the country.  It has created hundreds of jobs in the industrial sector in support of the fact that companies that previously would have only had a drug representative visiting doctors' offices to encourage them to prescribe medication suddenly have research places because the Irish co-operative oncology research group is conducting such high quality research and the companies are now locating trials in Ireland.  In recent years we have done something similar on the more pure lab and bench side of the cancer research model with Molecular Therapeutics for Cancer Ireland which we have recently rebranded as NCRCI, the National Cancer Research Centre of Ireland.  These models can have not only scientific and social benefits but also economic and employment benefits.  </p><p>I have two specific suggestions for the Minister of State.  He  should give serious consideration to making a major effort at curriculum development in order to develop a branch of scientific education which is interesting.</p> <p>It may or may not be points-focused.  It should occur not to help people to matriculate but to educate them in order that they could deal with the scientific decisions they would have to face in real life.  We should examine critically corporate incentives for siting research and development in Ireland.</p><p>As a parting shot, we should be among the world leaders - perhaps we are in some areas - in the areas of food science, agri-science and marine science.  We should be at the top of the tree in these matters, generating employment on a scale that without parallel.  We have already demonstrated that on a small slab of relatively fertile land we can feed numbers far beyond those achieved by larger agricultural societies and we must leverage that ability to increase knowledge in relevant sciences.  I ask the Minister of State to, please, keep up the good work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" speakername="Mary Moran" time="16:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200030#DD00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Sean Sherlock, for this debate.  Science was never my strong subject at school.  When I met my old science teacher lately, we reminisced about my participation in science, but my talents, limited as they are, lay elsewhere.  They were geared more towards music when I was at school.</p><p>This morning, as I was gathering my thoughts for my contribution to the debate on a subject which was not my fort&eacute;, I wondered what I could say about science.  As I drove down the motorway from Dundalk to Dublin, I appreciated the simplistic motion of turning the key in the ignition and driving off.  As I reached the halfway point between Dundalk and Drogheda I thought about a local man from County Louth who had been forgotten by many but who was still very much a part of our lives and the enjoyment we experienced every day.  He was the Reverend Professor Nicholas Callan from Darver, County Louth.  My initial research indicated that he had invented the induction coil in 1836.  As I stated, I was never a very good science student, but we know the induction coil is still in use today, powering, for example, car ignition systems.  When a car breaks down, we all learn what an induction coil does.  It is also used in televisions and other electronic devices.  What Reverend Professor Nicholas Callan achieved so many years ago was dangerous and many people thought it was impossible.  By 1837, one year after inventing the induction coil, he was generating an estimated 60,000 volts of electricity in his laboratory in St. Patrick's College in Maynooth.  I spoke to somebody earlier who told me a hall was dedicated to him - Callan Hall - because of his work.  His invention revolutionised the way in which we travelled.  Before 1926 all cars used a hand-crank to start and required physical labour, but after that date every Ford Model T came equipped with starting batteries.  Reverend Professor Nicholas Callan's induction coil made it possible to start a car with the power of a small battery.  This improvement to the Ford Model T gave it further mass appeal.  Like most geniuses, Reverend Professor Nicholas Callan was not appreciated for or credited with his invention until almost 70 years after his death.  I was amazed that I had not known about this man before I carried out research for this debate.  We may all take for granted the simplicity of turning a key in the ignition to start a car.  We have so many famous Irish people that can be credited with wonderful inventions such as this.</p><p>I commend initiatives such as Science Week, as they are so important in generating curiosity among students.  For example, when I taught I took students to W5 in Belfast.  There have been conferences held as part of Science Week which have proved really beneficial in introducing young people to the simple pleasures and learning experiences involved in science.</p> <p>I know of many great events taking place in my own county, which include moonlit archaeological and geological walks and photo competitions.  I am aware of an especially interesting event that will take place this Thursday, hosted by the Mourne Cooley Gullion Geotourism project, on Carlingford and its castle in the middle ages.  I am delighted that a past pupil alerted me to it and I hope to attend the event.</p><p>Events and weeks such as this bring science to the fore and hopefully spark an interest or get young people to think of science in a different way.  It is like the week when we have the Young Scientist exhibition.  It is something for which I never managed to qualify but attended on many occasions.  In recent years it has become one of the high points in the school calendar.  Students attend the exhibition and appreciate the work of their peers.  Some of the projects in recent years have been overwhelming in terms of the thought processes behind them.  Ireland has a strong reputation for science, as evidenced by Nicholas Callan, but also by the fact that it has won the top prize at the European Union contest for young scientists 16 times, most recently with the win by the three young ladies from the Minister of State&rsquo;s county of Cork.</p><p>Day in and day out we discuss the impact of the downturn in the economy on the jobs market and the people who visit our offices every day.  Science can play a key role in helping to fix the jobs crisis.  The unemployment rate among science professionals comes in at less than 3% compared with a higher national average.  The sector is crying out for young scientists from this country.  Studying science at third level does not only have to be about laboratory research, it could mean a career in computer gaming, energy, sports, agriculture or any number of other professions.  Science is versatile and can bring one to any number of places.  Let us take the example of Nicholas Callan from Louth &ndash; this is the last time I will mention him &ndash; the fifth child born into a family of seven in 1799 who entered Maynooth college at the age of 17, studied in Rome, became the chair of the physics department in Maynooth and lived to the age of 65 and whose memory, through the invention of the induction coil, is still remembered today.  It just proves that much is possible through science.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200031#EE00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Sherlock, who is present for the debate on this intriguing topic.  The word &ldquo;science&rdquo; comes from the Latin, <i>scientia</i>, which means knowledge.  Nobody could speak in the House against knowledge but sometimes the gap between the hyperbole in terms of what we set out to do and the reality does let us down.</p><p>  On an Adjournment motion, Senator Clune pointed out mistakes in the leaving certificate and junior certificate maths papers in spite of the fact that maths is a national priority.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn, found more because he is an architect.  By the end of the session we had found three times as many mistakes in the paper than the number that had been subject to official apology by the State Examinations Commission, which then issued some daft statement to the effect that it was understaffed and that was the reason for the mistakes.  Sometimes, we have to take issues seriously.  There were faults which this House found.  It is evident from the record that the Minister was happy to acknowledge that the Senators found the faults in the leaving certificate examination papers this year.  I hope the situation will be remedied.</p><p>  It seems to me that bonus points for maths rewards people who have a maths teacher in the school but the problem, as the Royal Irish Academy has pointed out, is that many maths teachers in Irish schools have no qualification in maths.  The Minister for Education and Skills came to the House to speak about changing teacher training, which became a power struggle between institutions as to who had what teacher training.  He was as embarrassed by the situation as anyone else.  We did not opt for the model which I believe would have been preferable, namely, that science teachers would be trained in science departments with perhaps a top-up from the higher diploma in education course.  It is wrong to just give people the higher diploma in education, which is a widely decried qualification, and say that young people have to face the task of trying to learn science from somebody who is about one page ahead of them in the book.</p> <p> The abolition of rural science and nature study as a subject in primary schools was a serious mistake.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/979" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200032#FF00200"><p>May I clarify something?  I did not quite understand what the Senator was referring to when he spoke about some people being one page ahead of others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200032#FF00300"><p>My point was that people who did not have a qualification in a subject should not be teaching it.  Teachers with only a leaving certificate qualification in a science subject are really only one step ahead of the pupils they are teaching.  I am arguing for a more coherent connection between education departments and teacher training colleges, on the one hand, and science departments, on the other.  The model of teacher training I am espousing is one where science teachers would be trained alongside other science students rather than separately in teacher training institutions.  Unfortunately, in keeping with ancient tradition in this country, there has been a turf war about which students go where and so on.</p><p>Removing rural science and nature study from the primary school curriculum was done to make room for Irish and was a mistake.  The same is true of continental languages.  As Senator John Crown observed, the excessive concentration on grammar rather than spoken Irish has taken up a great deal of time from the rest of the curriculum.  The success of Science Week is important in that regard and there is scope for expansion.  I hope we do not see any more mistakes in the leaving certificate maths paper such as we saw this year.  Aspiring to something at national level while failing to realise it where 18 year olds doing the leaving certificate examination and younger people doing the junior certificate examination are concerned lets the side down.</p><p>We need other dedicated weeks in addition to Science Week.  Policy is frequently implemented without being scientifically thought out, not in the Minister of State's Department but in Departments in general.  There is a culture of amateurism in public administration and a dreaded culture of amateurism in banking, finance, accounting, auditing and the construction industry.  How did we end up with pyrite in so many houses while fancying this as a &quot;smart economy&quot;?  Knowledge is key and we will support the Minister of State in that regard.</p><p>It was interesting to hear Senator Feargal Quinn talk about Professor E. T. S. Watson who went from Tipperary to Cambridge and returned home each year.  It was relevant to Senator Thomas Byrne's reference to the take-up of physics.  I have met female graduates from Cambridge and what they remember most about Professor Walton is not the Nobel prize he won but the fact that in junior freshman lectures he sought out women who had been to schools where physics was not taught.  It remains the case in many schools today that physics is not offered.</p><p>Science needs to learn to communicate to the next generation, the 16 and 18 year olds.  There are more important measures of output than academic journals which many people might not read.  If we succeed in getting through to good students, they will communicate their enthusiasm for the subject.  That is key.  The emphasis, however, seems to be on the peculiar system of reviewing scientific research where it is a case of the more authors the better.  To the economist, that signifies lower productivity rather than higher productivity, but it is apparently necessary to add 17 or 18 authors, all of whom will be promoted as a result.</p><p>There are clear gaps in our knowledge and we must not be overcome by the type of hyperbole that suggests otherwise.  We were tempting fate when we claimed that Ireland had a smart economy.  In fact, it was one of the dopiest economies ever in 2008.  We must be careful not to get carried away with self-praise.  The reform of education and learning is vital, yet it seemed like the goal of facilitating research and development had become an artificial goal when the Finance Act last year included a provision to reduce the amount of time engaged in that activity, from 75% to 50%, in order to qualify for a tax break.  In effect, one is paying twice as much for the research one receives.  That relief ought to be more firmly targeted to ensure it is going to those who are conducting research and development all the time, rather than giving a full subsidy to people who are engaged in that work only half of the time.  We will be discussing that issue when the Finance Bill is brought before the House.</p><p>Some of the people who make representations to the Minister of State are seeking subsidies for themselves.  Distinguishing rent-seeking, subsidy-seeking and grant-hunting from genuinely productive education activities is a difficult task, but we will assist him in it.  Science Week and the extension of scientific knowledge in general are very good ideas.  I assure the Minister of State of our support in his endeavours.  He is always welcome in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200032#FF00400"><p>The debate on this very important subject has been most enlightening. I agree with Senator Sean D. Barrett that for a smart country and smart people, we were quite dumb in 2008.  There are, undoubtedly, individuals within the economy and our society who are extremely smart.  Unfortunately, many of these extremely smart people are going abroad to find their feet.  There must be an effort to move science to centre stage.  There should be no sense in which it is presented as elitist, particularly in the language used.</p><p>Like Senator Mary Moran, I was a poor science student.  My teachers' main concern was that I might mix the wrong chemicals and blow up the science laboratory.  Science must become part of the dialogue in this country - in fact, it must be at the centre of that dialogue.  It is by fostering creativity that we will create indigenous and sustainable jobs and become a world leader.  Science gives us the opportunity to do that and we do not require access to billions of euro.  We do not even need millions of euro.  All we need are people with brains who are prepared to dedicate their expertise in the area of science.</p><p>The Young Scientist competition, sponsored by BT, has seen the emergence of several immensely talented young people.  Some of them have gone on to win the international competition, which is a testament to what is being done in this country at second level.  Investment in science is an investment in the future.  One might not see a benefit instantaneously, but there is a clear benefit in the long term, not least in so far as it fosters confidence among investors internationally.  Investors seeking bases in which to invest or set up business will see us as a nation investing in science and establishing a creativity culture within science.  We have demonstrated that we are capable of following international best practice and creating world class products.  We need only look at the dairy and farming sector to see the evidence of this.  I regularly speak to agricultural students in UCD and other colleges whose ideas and vision for the country are mind-blowing.  That is the type of confidence in which we need to invest.  Above all, we need to hold onto these young people.</p><p>This has been one of the better debates in this House and certainly proves the usefulness of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  We are fortunate to have Members like Senator Sean D. Barrett who is one of Europe's best transport economists and can also speak with confidence about science.  I hope this debate will be part of an ongoing discourse with the Minister of State that will allow us to address the challenges that present in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/979" speakername="Se&aacute;n Sherlock" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200033#GG00100"><p>I will endeavour to respond in the best way I can to the points raised.  I genuinely acknowledge the contributions of my fellow Members of the Oireachtas.  Hopefully I will be able to respond, and if I am not, Members should not hesitate to follow up with me.</p><p>  Senator Mary White referred to a dual education system, and I wholeheartedly agree with the point she made.  The example of the University of Limerick is the best national example of industry engagement by undergraduates where accreditation is given to the student for participation in industry, enterprise or on a community basis.  That model should be replicated.  Other universities or institutes of technology should take it as an example.  It is for universities to do so, but I am in favour of the model.</p><p>  I will contact Senator Deirdre Clune about a review of the ICT action plan after two years.  I want to give an accurate picture of it.  The same applies to the PhD candidate to whom Senator Clune referred.  A PhD candidate is a student, technically speaking, and I am happy to liaise with the Senator on that issue.</p><p>  I agree with Senator Feargal Quinn on the potential of the agricultural and food sector.  It is one of the 14 sectors outlined earlier.  We are looking at food, food innovation and, particularly, food for health.  Teagasc and SFI have signed a memorandum of understanding to try to leverage new opportunities within the sector, something the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Coveney, and I signed off on some time ago.  It presents an opportunity in terms of mapping areas opportunity onto the food sector and the agricultural sector.  This is particularly true in respect of ICT and dairy expansion, where the employment of new ICT technology will be necessary for success.  That is where we see a natural synergy between SFI and Teagasc.</p><p>  With regard to GMOs, research on genetically modified organisms is already being carried out by Teagasc.  A potato trial is under way within Teagasc.  At this juncture, if we look at the trends in terms of global population growth, we must be pragmatic about the approach we take.  I am expressing a personal opinion.  Sometimes the issue of GMO gets tangled up with the biotechnology companies and the control of seed and intellectual property.  We must have a rational and reasonable debate on the issue in a proper forum, devoid of some of the emotion that exists around the topic.  I would welcome a rational, coherent and objective debate.  There is potential for mapping ICT onto agriculture and developing higher-end food products, particularly in the area of probiotics and functional foods.  The taxpayer, through SFI, has funded an alimentary pharma-biotic centre in Cork through Professor Fergus Shanahan, who was referred to by Senator O'Keeffe.  Last week, Professor Shanahan was nominated as researcher of the year.  That is the kind of excellence in research that we are carrying out in the area of food, and it will map onto dairy expansion and the potential of the agricultural economy.  We recognise its importance.</p><p>  The feedback on Science Week will be about capturing what the broadcaster and researcher Aoibhinn N&iacute; Sh&uacute;illeabh&aacute;in calls the <i>zeitgeist</i>.  She called this a <i>zeitgeist </i>space where learning takes place, through events such as Science Week, for parents and teachers as well as for the children and students involved.  It is about implanting new ideas in teachers to apply some of the learning from individual events in the classroom.  In terms of feedback, the expectation is that teachers will take something from the events and implant that learning in the teaching experience within the classroom.  There is no reason, in the current system, they cannot do so.</p><p>  The topic of religion in schools concerns management and patronage structures.  It is arguably for a board of management to determine the particular ethos of the school.  That is why, in certain instances, religion becomes an important topic, depending on the ethos in a school.  I agree that we need more primary school teachers engaging with science, technology, engineering and mathematics subjects at primary school.  We must help teachers.  All too often, it is easy to be critical of teachers and say that they spend too much time teaching English or art and not enough time on science, technology, engineering and mathematics subjects.  We must create a supportive framework for teachers and give them the tools to do so.</p><p>  Senator Thomas Byrne referred to physical sciences and hard sciences.  Looking at the results in physics and chemistry, one can see there is no difference between the genders at national level.  With regard to the school in question, I do not know the facts of the situation, but I imagine it may be a geographical issue or a localised issue.  There are opportunities for people to be taught physics or chemistry no matter where they are in the country.  If there are exceptions, I would like to hear about it.  It may be a local variation.  If we examine the breakdown of physics and chemistry in the leaving certificate, we find that, broadly speaking, there is no gender imbalance.  I am happy to talk to the Senator about that point.  </p><p>  I was delighted to meet Senator Colm Burke at the medical research charities group conference this morning.  We are a small country and we are still borrowing more than &euro;1 billion per month.  It is not possible for a small country in these economically constrained times to try to be all things to all people in terms of our research funding.  It is appropriate to smartly specialise in an area in which we can get a societal and economic return.  People may have a rational critique of the research prioritisation exercise, but I do not believe they cannot be funded through other sources if they feel they are left outside of the process.  There are sources of funding other than research prioritisation.</p><p>  In the health area, in drug synthesis and drug formulation, Ireland is investing heavily through the solid state pharmaceutical centre, SSPC, cluster at the University of Limerick, which brings in the pharmaceutical companies so vital to our industrial landscape.  We are partnering with them through SFI to examine the concept of manufacturing from molecules to medicine, as the saying goes.  We must be smart about how we specialise.  Drug discovery is an area of importance.</p> <p>We recognise that.  If we are talking about an emphasis on these, we will be moving towards a manufacturing and processing synthesis crystallisation space.  We are absolutely right to prioritise in that area.</p><p>There were comments about 0% corporation tax.  Considering the foreign direct investment wins we have had in 2012, approximately 45% were predicated on research and development.  I have an open mind on the corporate tax rate and, as a Minister of State, that type of designation is probably beyond my pay grade.  We should debate the matter and I acknowledge the points made by Senator Barrett on how the research and development tax credit is utilised.  The last budget set down clear markers on the research and development tax credit designation and there is no ambiguity about that.</p><p>Senator Crown mentioned religion and I spoke about governance in response to that.  Science is a core subject, which I agree with, and the metrics would probably indicate that science is taught at post-primary level in approximately 85% to 90% of schools.  I could stand to be corrected on the exact percentage, and although it is an option, science is still taken by the vast majority of students right up to leaving certificate level.  I agree with the Senator that this is about people having a basic conceptual understanding of science because of its translational impact across a number of sectors, including solicitors and the other professions mentioned.  I agree with the Senator's comments about a core module.</p><p>I do not see how the junior cycle could not provide for that kind of model, especially in short courses, and junior cycle students on short courses should be engaged in that kind of scientific inquiry.  The idea might be grown from the conceptual perspective of &quot;putting the finger on the hot plate&quot;, as people should have such a conceptual understanding of scientific endeavour.  There would be an important outcome for people downstream in terms of how they grow, effectively, as people.</p><p>With regard to the food space, the Alimentary Pharmobiotic Centre in Cork is working with Teagasc, and it is one of the foremost probiotic research entities in the world.  It carries out research on functional foods, gut health and mapping the gut &quot;genome&quot;.  Ireland is at the forefront of that scientific endeavour, and downstream permutations will include medicinal potential for food as a delivery mechanism.  That is long-term thinking, with people like Professor Fergus Shanahan leading that kind of research.  I will never forget the name Nicholas Callan as long as I live.  The next time I step on the locomotive to Mallow or into the car, I will be thinking of Reverend Professor Nicholas Callan.  I take that as a learning point and acknowledge the comments of Senator Moran in that respect.</p><p>Senator Barrett always provokes challenging thoughts and I like coming to the Seanad because it facilitates such debate.  Senator Barrett drew on the &quot;one page ahead&quot; analogy with regard to Project Maths and the State is expending considerable resources on bringing teachers of mathematics - out of field maths teachers - through a professional diploma which is being delivered by the National Centre for Excellence in Mathematics and Science Teaching and Learning, in collaboration with other entities like the National University of Ireland, Galway.  We have invested heavily in bringing in those teachers and the taxpayer is funding this professional diploma in order to upskill the teachers and enable them to teach mathematics at post-primary level.  I would be very surprised if the vast majority of teachers graduating from that course would not leap-frog some of the existing pure mathematics teachers in the system.  That may sound controversial but it is what the evidence indicates, although we have not yet had a full analysis of how the course panned out.</p><p>In fairness to teachers in the post-primary sector, they have had to embrace serious challenges in dealing with Project Maths and some of the teachers have been resistant to it.  I am confident that given the right levels of continuing professional development and supports for those teachers, as well as introducing the out of field mathematics teachers into the equation, some of the issues with the State Examinations Commission will be solved.  Everybody acknowledges the turmoil created but we must still acknowledge that Project Maths is still in its early days, so there is work to be done.</p><p>There are still pockets of resistance by some teachers involved with Project Maths and we are trying to work with them as best we can in order to get through the existing issues, recognising the challenges they face.  A teacher has to go from &quot;chalk and talk&quot; based on a model of past papers to a process of collaborative problem solving with students, and some teachers may have been teaching for 20 or 25 years.  We must acknowledge that such a change can be difficult for teachers.  I am hopeful that we can get through those challenges and I acknowledge the points.</p><p>I do not agree with the Senator's comments about a culture of amateurism.  He was speaking specifically about pyrite issues and so forth.  I will stand up for the officials with whom I interface in the public service on a daily basis.  One can consider the negotiations around Horizon 2020, and although they have political leadership, the teams on the working groups are all public officials.  These are civil servants who did an excellent job in negotiating these programmes on behalf of Ireland.  I know the Senator is not painting with a broad brush with regard to public administration but sometimes we must acknowledge that there are excellent people within our public administration who have a very strong sense of policy outcomes and delivering based on Government objectives, etc.  I do not know if I missed an issue when the Senator mentioned the culture of amateurism, and I stand to be corrected if I have missed a point.</p><p>Some 45% of our foreign direct investment wins last year were predicated on research and development.  The challenge for us is to start examining the primary school system now to ensure we can have a throughput.  There are intermediate measures at post-primary level, and I argue there is a certain responsibility on higher education institutions to start remodelling how they offer particular courses.  Perhaps there is an onus on the institutions to consider the possibilities of more industrial engagement by undergraduates.  If that is done there will be a positive consequence on the numbers of people staying here rather than emigrating, and particularly with people under 24 who are freshly graduated.  At this stage, if those people had some sort of industrial experience or could interface with industry in some way at an undergraduate level, receiving accreditation for their efforts, many might take up opportunities at an earlier career stage.</p> <p>I remain open to challenge on that point also at some stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200035#JJ00200"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" speakername="Deirdre Clune" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200035#JJ00300"><p>Tomorrow at 10.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.105" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200035#JJ00400">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.106" nospeaker="true" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200035#JJ00550">Regulatory Impact Assessment Usage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200035#JJ00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Kathleen Lynch, for coming to the House to deal with this matter.  It is great to see her.  </p><p>The issue I wish to raise relates to regulatory impact assessments.  We were promised that the Government would cut red tape.  &quot;Reform&quot; became part of a ministerial portfolio, the purpose of which was to cut red tape.  When I asked how many regulatory impact assessments had been carried out in the Department of Social Protection, I was informed that only one had been carried out.  Much bureaucracy and paperwork have been created.  In many respects, it is more to do with covering the officials and bureaucrats than improving the system.  A red tape report was carried out on Valentia Island.  We found that if we could reduce the amount of red tape, 70 jobs would be created.  I refer to foreshore licences, planning and other areas.</p><p>I wish to focus on nursing homes which are being crippled by red tape.  What often happens is that when something goes wrong, as has been the case when patients receive bad care or in certain cases are the victims of cruelty and treated more like prisoners in the 1800s than patients in the 21st century, the follow-on action by the Government involves significant levels of reporting which generates enormous amounts of work for people who are trying to carry on a business.  BDO has carried out a cost-pressure survey report on the nursing home sector.  Independent commentators have revealed that in the long term the demands placed on nursing homes in terms of pricing are not sustainable.  I know the Minister is working hard on that issue.  I have been told by people who run nursing homes that paperwork that used to take a couple of hours now takes staff two days to complete and submit.  One wonders how many people are required to read the reports.</p><p>On a practical level, I accept that the Minister wishes to ensure the necessary care is available, but the over-reaction and bureaucracy created to counteract cases of poor care have stifled the provision of care in some cases and made it unviable for people to continue in the sector at a time when we need more nursing homes, not fewer.  People are being squeezed out of the sector, not only because of pricing by the HSE but also because of the level of bureaucracy being created as part of a reporting mechanism.  Will the Minister of State outline whether the Government carried out a regulatory impact assessment on the impact of regulations and the practical implications of compliance in terms of staff time required to fill in forms and reporting on an ongoing basis?  Was a regulatory impact assessment carried out as to whether we could do it better?  </p><p>I look forward with interest to the reply of the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200035#JJ00700"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  Before I give the official response, I wish to outline that the balance is delicate because we are dealing with vulnerable people.  Because of the approach taken to long-term residential care for older people we must strike the balance well.  We do not want regulation and bureaucracy to interfere with the care people receive, but, on the other hand, we must be extremely careful that the type of light-touch regulation we have seen in the past is not applied to a sector which must be regulated and in which we must ensure people receive the best of care.</p><p>  As the Senator is well aware, Government policy is to support older people to live in dignity and independence in their own homes and communities for as long as possible and to ensure only the most highly dependent people are in long-term nursing home care.  We are dealing with a vulnerable cohort of people and must be careful about how the care is delivered.  There is and will always be a cohort of older people who require the long-term residential care option.  Residential care for older people is provided in a range of public, private and voluntary facilities throughout the country.  In recent years there have been two significant developments in the nursing home sector, both of which were the subject of regulatory impact analyses, RIAs.  The introduction of the nursing homes support scheme in 2009 put in place a system of financial support that ensured nursing home care was affordable to all.  It is a very generous scheme of assistance under which the State bears the larger part of nursing home costs.  Contributions from individuals who choose their own nursing home from an approved list are related to their ability to pay.  More than &euro;970 million is allocated to the scheme this year to support more than 22,700 people.  Under the Health Act 2007, statutory responsibility for registering and inspecting nursing home settings against national quality standards was given to the Health Information and Quality Authority.  Access to appropriate quality long-term residential care is now underpinned by both a strong regulatory regime and an excellent system of financial support.</p><p>  A regulatory impact analysis was completed in advance of the introduction of both the nursing homes support scheme and the nursing homes standards drawn up by HIQA.  The Department of Health prepared information leaflets, A Guide to the Fair Deal and a frequently asked questions document.  In addition to dealing with queries and representations from interest groups, public representatives and members of the public, the Department also met interested parties.  The factors arising from the RIA were taken into account in implementing the scheme.  For the RIA on the national quality for residential care settings for older people in Ireland the<i></i>Department commissioned an independent consultancy to carry out an assessment of costs on the impact of the standards.  In addition, a consultation session was hosted in Dublin Castle.  The Department has also recently carried out a regulatory impact analysis arising from two changes to the nursing homes support scheme announced in budget 2013.  One of the changes was related to the contribution.  All three RIAs are published on the Department's website.  The Senator will be aware that a review of the nursing homes support scheme is under way and will include a broad analysis of how future overall provision for older people can be made sustainable and best meet people's needs.  The review is being carried out by the Department, in collaboration with the HSE.  Work will continue on the review in the coming months with a view to completion in early 2014.</p><p>  I accept the Senator&rsquo;s point on bureaucracy and form filling, but one must bear in mind that the sector deals with vulnerable people and that it is only the most vulnerable who receive such long-term residential care.</p> <p> We must be extraordinarily careful that one does not impact on the other and at the end of the day, the care is really what is important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200036#KK00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House and I agree with what she has just said.  However, instead of having officials in the Department reading the reports and determining whether all of the reports from the various nursing homes were received, we should be deploying more inspectors for surprise visits.  We need boots on the ground.  As the Minister of State knows, one can read a paper report on a nursing home that does not reflect the reality.  When one sees the home in reality, one can understand the situation better.  Surprise visits are very effective, especially if those running the homes know they will be inspected once or twice a year.  That is a better approach than simply reading reports.  I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House and for her efforts in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/982" speakername="Kathleen Lynch" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200036#KK00300"><p>Senator Daly should be aware that we have just recently employed an additional 48 HIQA inspectors.  At a time when we are being asked to dramatically reduce the numbers of staff employed by the State, that is significant.  We are prioritising areas where we need additional staff on the ground.  Where there is a concern about a care institution, HIQA returns to that institution repeatedly.  It is not as if the announced visit is a once-off event and nothing else happens.  If there are concerns then those concerns are addressed by continuous, regular visits.  It is very difficult to hide something that is wrong if an inspector is constantly at the door.  That is what we need.  I make no apologies for that happening.  The majority of people who deliver care in this country to our older people do an extraordinary job.  We hear that from families and the older people themselves.  However, that does not mean that we should not be vigilant.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.112" nospeaker="true" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200036#KK00400">Roadworthiness Testing</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200036#KK00500"><p>I have been contacted by a number of road hauliers who are struggling at the moment.  Part of the problem is the fact that their vehicles are off the road because business is so poor.  They are concerned that a road worthiness certificate will only be issued for six months.  There are also delays in the issuing of commercial roadworthiness certificates.  I raise this issue in an effort to bring clarity to the matter and determine if the Minister of State and his officials and aware of this anomaly.  There are significant additional costs involved in having roadworthiness tests carried out every six months.  I am not sure that the Department is aware of the fact that there is a delay in issuing a certificate when a vehicle has succeeded in meeting the criteria.  I look forward to the Minister of State's response.  I hope common sense will prevail and the issue can be resolved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1088" speakername="Alan Kelly" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200036#KK00600"><p>I thank Senator Conway for raising this very important matter.  I am sure the Senator is aware that commercial vehicle owners have always been obliged to test their vehicles annually.  This is a legal obligation throughout the European Union.  The minimum testing frequency of commercial vehicles is specified in Directive 2009/40/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council on roadworthiness tests for motor vehicles and their trailers.  There have never been exemptions from the requirement to have commercial vehicles tested annually and this is not determined by the period during which the vehicle is or has been in use, nor its mileage.  The law stipulates that it is an offence to use a commercial vehicle, including a trailer, in a public place unless, at the time, there is in force in respect of the vehicle, a certificate of roadworthiness.  Roadworthiness testing standards are aimed at detecting any wear and tear, deterioration or modifications that could adversely affect the roadworthiness or safety of the vehicle and its compliance with road traffic construction and use regulations, where these items can be assessed by inspection.  In cases of vehicles which were off the road, their condition can degrade and deteriorate so it is just as important that they are tested also before they re-enter service.</p><p>The new certificate of roadworthiness, CRW, issuing system is aligned to the long-standing obligation to have commercial vehicles tested annually.  The period of validity of the CRW is calculated by reference to the last test due date and any delay in completing the test has the effect of reducing the validity period of the CRW.  The longer the delay in completing the test, the shorter the validity period of a CRW.  In cases where a vehicle is overdue its test by more than one year and is presented for testing, commercial vehicle roadworthiness testing regulations provide that the validity for the CRW shall be either for the six month period after the testing date or a period determined by reference to the anniversary of the test due date, whichever is earlier.  This modification to the previous scheme has been introduced in order to ensure that an operator who does not test the vehicle by the due date does not gain any economic advantage over an operator who tested his or her vehicle in accordance with the legal requirements.  This point answers the question posed by Senator Conway.  </p><p>Regarding the printing, posting and issuing of a CRW to the vehicle's registered owner, I can confirm that when a vehicle passes a commercial vehicle roadworthiness test, this results in a request for the issue of a CRW being sent to the driver and vehicle licensing computer services division of the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  In order to facilitate cases where vehicles may be undergoing a change of ownership, there is an in-built time lag of one hour after the completion of the test before the vehicle details on the National Vehicle Driver File, NVDF, are updated.  Accordingly, one hour after the test has been completed, the person can renew his or her motor tax online or in the motor tax office.  The driver and vehicle licensing computer services division arranges the printing, posting and issuing of the certificate to the vehicle's registered owner as a matter of course at the end of each working day.  I am advised that certificates are usually received by their vehicle owners within one to three days of the commercial vehicle test having been passed.  Thus, with the CRW details being available online within one hour after the test and the CRW being posted out immediately, operators who are having their vehicles tested on time need have no concerns about not having a CRW for a day or two.</p><p>Furthermore, RSA vehicle inspectors have access to the online record and will know that the vehicle possesses a valid roadworthiness certificate.  Where a vehicle is travelling abroad, the operator can avail of the new facility to have the vehicle tested up to one month early and receive a certificate for up to 13 months, thus enabling operators to ensure that the vehicle has a valid CRW for any international operations.  Under the new system, operators may also choose to change the date of the test for a time during the year that better suits their business needs.</p><p>The new centralised CRW issuing system has been in operation since 1 October 2013.  I am advised that there were a few occasions in the initial week or two where there were some technical difficulties in communicating between the commercial vehicle information system, CoVIS, and the driver and vehicle licensing computer services division which may have resulted in delays in the issuing of CRWs.  I am advised that in such instances, the CRWs were subsequently successfully issued to the vehicle owners and all issues were resolved..</p><p>Separately, the RSA is also aware of exceptional cases of delay in the issuing of CRWs in respect of imported vehicles where these vehicles had been registered by the Revenue Commissioners on the same day and the NVDF had not been updated.  There are also exceptional cases relating to older trailers whose records are not on the NVDF.  In these cases, the Department and the RSA have facilitated the vehicle owners by enabling the trailer record to be updated without the owner of the trailer having to go back to the motor tax office.  These are transitional issues arising in individual cases and once the record has been updated on the NVDF there will be no complications with the vehicle record subsequently.</p><p>Under the new system, the vehicle test details are recorded centrally.  This supports effective enforcement of the obligation to have the vehicle test annually and ensures that compliant operators can go about their daily business with minimum disruption at the roadside while non-compliance can be quickly and easily identified and addressed.</p><p>These changes are part of wider reforms which the RSA is implementing to improve the roadworthiness standard of commercial vehicles on our roads.</p> <p>The Road Safety Authority's reform focuses on three key areas: making the roadworthiness test more effective; introducing premises checks for operators of commercial vehicles to review their maintenance system, records and procedures; and increasing the effectiveness of roadside inspections of vehicles by the Road Safety Authority and An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I am confident commercial vehicle roadworthiness reform will make our roads a safer place for everyone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200037#LL00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his comprehensive reply.  I will bring it to the attention of the Irish Road Hauliers Association which I am sure will come back with a response in due course.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.117" nospeaker="true" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200037#LL00250">Credit Unions</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200037#LL00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it, ach caithfidh m&eacute; a r&aacute; nach &eacute; a bh&iacute; uaim ar an &oacute;c&aacute;id seo.  N&iacute;lim ag caitheamh anuas ar an Aire St&aacute;it at&aacute;im in aon chor nuair a deirim go raibh m&eacute; ag s&uacute;il le bualadh leis an Aire Noonan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1000" speakername="Dinny McGinley" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200037#LL00400"><p>T&aacute; s&uacute;il agam nach bhfuil an Seanad&oacute;ir ag r&aacute; gur sop in &aacute;it na scuaibe at&aacute; ionam.  Ar chuala s&eacute; &eacute; sin riamh?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200037#LL00500"><p>Chuala m&eacute;.  T&aacute; sin an-mhaith.<br /><b></b>I welcome the Minister of State but it is the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, who should be here instead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1000" speakername="Dinny McGinley" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200037#LL00600"><p>He is in the other House as we speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200037#LL00700"><p>I would have liked if there had been a representation from the Department of Finance at the very least, given the issue of tremendous urgency that has arisen with Newbridge Credit Union.  The events of recent days are not only a disappointment to the people of Newbridge but also to this House and the High Court.  This House, even more so now with the absence of any representative from the Department, has yet again been treated with contempt by this Government.  Only last week I asked the Minister what the plans were for the future of Newbridge Credit Union.  I was told they could not be discussed due to the fact there was a High Court order.  Later in the week, the Government told the media its plans before telling this House or the High Court.</p><p>Whatever the agreed and uncontested evidence of irregularities in lending practices at the credit union, the events over recent days and the actions taken by the Central Bank have sent shockwaves through the credit union movement.  The speed and pace with which the Government acted under these special powers which were originally meant for banks was unbelievable.  Now, the people in the area are without a credit union.  The Ministers from the Department of Finance are giving mixed messages to the 2.8 million credit union savers nationwide.  The Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, says Newbridge is the only case while the Minister, Deputy Noonan, claims a quarter of all credit unions are potentially in trouble.</p><p>This credit union was treated like another failed bank.  However, credit unions are not banks.  They are owned and built by communities, brick by brick.  There should have been more consultation.  For the past 23 months there has been a special manager appointed to the credit union yet there was this lightning surprise development over the weekend, reminiscent of the late-night decisions regarding the banks.</p><p>The late night application by the Central Bank to the High Court was reminiscent of the worst night of the last Government, the night of the bank guarantee.  People deserved more consultation locally.  There needs to be more transparency.  I do not buy the arguments that everything has to be done in absolute confidentiality.  The lightning strike actions at the weekend do not reassure people in the slightest.  There are specific questions that people want answered.  People want to know which credit unions have been placed on a watch list by regulators.  Media reports suggest one in four is in trouble.  Which credit unions are these?  What percentage of credit union loans are non-performing?  What stress tests are in place to gauge the support the sector needs in the future?  Most importantly, will the Minister for Finance commit to more consultation with members of the sector and no more late-night takeovers of the kind we have seen?</p><p>I regard it as contempt for this House what has gone on in circumstances where specific questions were asked last week but there was no transparency or accountability from the Department.  Tonight, again, there is no representative from the Department of Finance, which is regrettable, not regarding the personal regard I have for the Minister of State, Deputy McGinley.  If the Government wants to change the way business is done and mark its difference from the last Government, there must be honesty, respect for depositors and savers, as well as respect for transparency, accountability and being upfront in its actions as well as those of the Central Bank.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1000" speakername="Dinny McGinley" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200037#LL00800"><p>I am deputising for the Minister for Finance who is engaged in the other House.</p><p>On Sunday, 10 November, the Central Bank applied to the High Court under the Central Bank and Credit Institutions (Resolution) Act 2011 and received approval for the transfer of the assets and liabilities of Newbridge Credit Union, excluding the premises, to Permanent TSB.  This action was necessary to safeguard members' savings as the only alternative option available to the Central Bank was liquidation which would have seen unprotected savings of &euro;1.1 million lost.  These would have included the savings of charities, schools and individuals.  The Central Bank has published extensive information on its website setting out the details of the transfer, including the relevant background material and financial details.</p><p>On foot of a request from the Governor of the Central Bank, the Minister for Finance agreed to the payment to Permanent TSB of a financial incentive of up to &euro;53.9 million to support the transfer.  This consists of &euro;23 million in cash up front, &euro;4.25 million for restructuring and integration costs, &euro;2 million for other transferring liabilities and a maximum additional &euro;24.7 million to cover additional costs resulting from all loans being written off with nothing recovered.  A 50:50 risk-sharing agreement is in place where the resolution fund will absorb 50% of losses where loans perform below their transfer value and 50% of gains where loans perform above their transfer value.  The financial incentive provided in the Newbridge case is fully recoupable from the financial services sector over time in the form of a levy.</p><p>In line with the resolution options available, the Central Bank undertook a process which involved the examination of possible credit union combinations.  This resulted in an approach being made to several credit unions.  Ultimately, however, no credit union considered it was in its best interests to complete such a combination, even in the context of extensive taxpayer support.  This partly reflected the relative scale of Newbridge Credit Union in the sector and the exceptional nature of its financial difficulties.  The Central Bank also considered proposed solutions put forward by various interested parties but none proved feasible.</p><p>It was in the context of a possible liquidation that the Department of Finance, with the support of the Central Bank, requested Permanent TSB to undertake this transaction.  The participation of Permanent TSB, for which I express my thanks, has brought stability and certainty to the situation and specifically to the members and staff of Newbridge Credit Union, providing an alternative to liquidation.  This transfer means that Newbridge Credit Union members can be assured they can continue to operate their loan and deposit accounts as normal.</p><p>The bad practice in Newbridge over many years can be illustrated in the following key lending statistics.  There was an individual loan of &euro;3.2 million which was in excess of the Credit Union Act restriction of a maximum of 1.5% of the total assets.  Up to 52% of the loans exceed the five-year duration as opposed to the maximum set out in the Credit Union Act of 20%.  The average loan in Newbridge Credit Union was &euro;17,281 as compared to the average credit union loan which is &euro;7,764.  There were 26 loans of an average value of &euro;550,000, which were seriously distressed.</p><p>These statistics illustrate that Newbridge was very different from a normal credit union.  The structure of many of these loans was more akin to development loans with bullet repayments as opposed to regular repayments.</p> <p> The Central Bank has informed me that, based on data submitted by credit unions as at 30 September 2013, some 20 credit unions have reported regulatory reserves below the minimum requirement of 10% of assets.  This gives rise to a capital shortfall in the region of &euro;11 million in total.  The Central Bank continues to work through a portfolio of approximately 100 credit unions on a case by case basis.  The programme of work to engage with such credit unions is informed by levels of arrears; inadequate bad debt provisions; high fixed asset to total asset ratio; and other supervisory concerns including weak lending practices.  The outcomes of these engagements can include governance changes; risk mitigation programmes; lending and other business restrictions; and requirements for credit unions to seek capital support.</p><p>The Government has made available &euro;500 million to support the stability of the credit union movement.  This amount is divided between two funds of &euro;250 million each, one for resolution, which is being used in the Newbridge case, another for voluntary restructuring under the Credit Union Restructuring Board.  The funding required for Newbridge is fully recoupable from the financial sector via a levy over time.</p><p>The Government recognises the important role of credit unions as a volunteer co-operative movement and the distinction between them and other types of financial institutions.  The Government's priorities remain the protection of members' savings, the financial stability of credit unions and the sector overall.  The Government is absolutely determined to support a strengthened and growing credit union movement and would encourage the movement to work with its stronger credit unions so they can provide a viable option for assisting weaker credit unions.  In particular, the Government supports the future return of a credit union to Newbridge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200038#MM00200"><p>I thank the Minister for doing as much as he could but it is not good enough to focus on Newbridge.  We did not get the information we sought last week.  This response ignores the questions I asked.  I repeat that savers and members are being treated with contempt with a lack of information and, in some cases, mixed messages from the Department of Finance.  I wonder who will next wake up to find their credit union is secretly a bank.  The Minister mentioned 20 credit unions having reported regulatory reserves but out of how many that have reported is that?  Is that 20 in total or is it only the figure the Central Bank is prepared to tell us?  Overall, I am unhappy with the level of information from Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1000" speakername="Dinny McGinley" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200038#MM00300"><p>The Central Bank has informed the Minister that based on data submitted by credit unions as at 30 September 2013, some 20 credit unions have reported regulatory reserves below the minimum requirement of 10% of assets.  This gives rise to a capital shortfall in the region of &euro;11 million.  The Central Bank continues to work through a portfolio of approximately 100 credit unions on a case-by-case basis.  That is the information the Central Bank has provided to the Minister for this evening's discussion.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.127" nospeaker="true" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200038#MM00350">Local Government Reform</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200038#MM00400"><p>Tr&aacute;thn&oacute;na, is mian liom an r&uacute;n i dtaca leis an mBille rialtas &aacute;iti&uacute;il at&aacute; ag dul tr&iacute; Tithe an Oireachtais faoi l&aacute;thair a phl&eacute;, mar go bhfuil an Bille seo ag teacht in am ina bhuil go leor ceisteanna &aacute; ard&uacute;, chan amh&aacute;in sa t&iacute;r seo ach ag leibh&eacute;al na hEorpa.  Mar shampla, since 2007 the Council of Europe has consistently warned of a general shift towards greater centralisation in Europe and Ireland.  The Local Government Bill 2013 is nothing to do with reform but is a drastic attempt simply and naively to reduce overall Government expenditure.  By definition "reform" should mean improvement or changing with the modern era but the abolition of town councils and democracy in the Bill is nothing to do with reform.  On 31 October 2013 the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe recommended that the Irish authorities revise the Local Government Bill to ensure the subsidiarity principle is better enshrined and protected.  It stated that the importance of this (subsidiarity) principle is not adequately reflected in the local government reform legislation.  It further encouraged the Government to revise the legislation to ensure the subsidiarity principle is better enshrined and protected in law and to promote this crucial principle and practice in Irish public administration.</p><p>The principle of subsidiarity is fundamental to the functioning of the EU, specifically to European decision making, in particular the principle determines when the EU is competent to legislate and contribute to decisions being taken as closely as possible to the citizen, particularly at town council level.  The principle of subsidiarity is established across the EU, including in Ireland, under Article 5 of the treaty on the European Union.  It appears alongside two other principles that are also considered essential to European decision making, namely conferral and proportionality.</p><p>The Irish people overwhelmingly passed a referendum in 1999 which gave recognition for the first time in Irish law to local government structures being recognised in the Constitution, under Article 28A.  That created a legitimate expectation that local government structured as it was at the time would continue to be voted on every five years in town and county council elections.  The doctrine of legitimate expectation regarding town councils is being eradicated under the proposed legislation coming forward under the Local Government Bill without any consultation whatsoever by the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government and the Minister, Deputy Hogan.</p><p>I am not saying this.  Fine Gael town councillors up and down the country are saying it.  Last week a prominent Fine Gael county councillor in Mayo spoke on this issue locally and nationally.  The members of Westport Town Council, controlled by Fine Gael, have written a very comprehensive document on this issue and I salute them for the work they have done in consultation with Fianna F&aacute;il councillors.  I mention Fine Gael councillors in particular because a Fine Gael-led Government is introducing this abolition Bill.  The Minister of State, Deputy McGinley, is not responsible for this area but I call on the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Hogan and the Government to park or suspend this legislation, listen to councillors up and down the country, particularly town councillors who represent the citizen at the closest possible level.  A number of town councillors have spoken publicly on this.</p><p>I also call on the Government to listen to the recommendation from the Congress of Local and Regional Authorities of the Council of Europe and its rapporteurs who are concerned that consultation with local authorities and their associates has not occurred in this country.  They also call for the legislation to be suspended or parked until adequate consultation happen with each town council.</p><p>I call for the Bill to parked or suspended, that 2014 be used as local government consultation year, not local government abolition year.  Let us use it to talk to the people around the country about local government.  When one examines it across Europe it is very interesting.  We will put ourselves at the top of the pile regarding the average population per local authority.  In France there is a local authority for every 1,500 people.  In Germany there is one for every 6,500.  We will move to the top of the pile and be less democratic than all the other OECD countries and will have one local authority for every 139,800 people.</p> <p>We are going to make this the least democratic country in the OECD.  What we are actually doing is following the UK example.  The State broke with the Britain and we established our own local government structures under Michael Collins.  We are now disenfranchising and going back to the same principle of local government that has evolved in the North of Ireland and throughout the rest of the United Kingdom.  This is wrong because there has been no consultation.  I am not the one who is saying this; I am only conveying the message on behalf of town councillors throughout the country.  I ask the Minister of State whether he agrees that there needs to be more consultation and that the Bill should be parked.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1000" speakername="Dinny McGinley" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200039#NN00200"><p>Ba mhaith liom bu&iacute;ochas a ghabh&aacute;il leis an Seanad&oacute;ir as an &aacute;bhar seo a ard&uacute;.  T&aacute; m&eacute; ag seasamh isteach don Aire, an Teachta Hogan, nach f&eacute;idir leis a bheith anseo.</p><p>  I inform the Senator and the House that the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government did have a very successful trip to County Donegal at the weekend, where I understand he addressed a public meeting in Ballyshannon at which many of these issues were addressed.  I believe his contribution was very impressive and that people's fears and concerns were allayed to a great extent.  While I was not present at the meeting, I have read the media reports on what happened.</p><p>  I am glad to have the opportunity to provide a policy context and some detail in the context of the Local Government Bill 2013, with particular reference to changes at sub-county level, a matter which has been raised on the Adjournment of the House a number of times recently.  As Members are aware, the Government's action programme for effective local government, published in October 2012, sets out Government policy decisions on a range of measures to reform and strengthen local government structures, functions, funding, governance and operational arrangements.  Chapter 6 of the action programme sets out arrangements to replace town councils with a new comprehensive model of municipal governance based on principal towns and designed to strengthen local government within counties and address weaknesses and anomalies in the current system.</p><p>  Local government reform has been the subject of deliberation and discussion for many years.  The process of consultation, prior to the current reform programme, effectively began with the public consultations in the context of the 2008 Green Paper on local government and has continued in the context of the 2012 action programme, the current Bill and specific aspects of the reform agenda such as the alignment of community and local development with local government and implementation of the local government efficiency review.  These previous deliberations and consultations helped to inform the development of reform proposals in the action programme.</p><p>  Since coming to office, the Minister, Deputy Phil Hogan, has considered submissions from and held discussions with the local government representative associations, individual local authorities and other interested groups and individuals.  He also invited each individual councillor in the country to submit views to him on a number of issues relating to local government reform to help in finalising the production of last year's action programme.  Following the publication last year of the reform action programme, a specific structured process was put in place for engagement with the local authority members' associations in the local government reform implementation process.  This took the form of a working group for engagement with, and input by, the associations in regard to the development of the legislative provisions, including those relating to sub-county reorganisation, thereby providing a direct conduit for input and involvement by councillors in the reform implementation process.  I record appreciation for the positive engagement on the part of the members' associations which has helped to inform the provisions included in the Bill.</p><p>  The content of local government reform legislation was, of course, a matter for Government decision in the first instance and is now the subject of Oireachtas scrutiny and debate in the normal way.  The Minister will be giving careful consideration to relevant issues, views and suggestions raised in that context within the parameters of the policy decisions taken by the Government.</p><p>  Without question, the sub-county reform in the action programme is a radical departure and the decision to change fundamentally our approach to local government arrangements within counties was not taken lightly.  It was taken, for example, in the full knowledge that town councils had enjoyed advantages such as proximity to citizens and the ability to respond to local needs.  There is also a considerable element of history, heritage and civic status associated with town authorities.  However, these strengths cannot hide the fact that the existing system of town local government contains glaring weaknesses, including limited functions, outdated boundaries, duplication of administration and insufficient scale to maximise efficiency or support expertise or resources to carry out a range of complex functions.  This duplication is illustrated, for example, by the fact that in Tipperary, a county with a population of just under 160,000, there are nine local authorities involving nine sets of elections, nine annual budgets, nine annual reports, nine corporate plans, nine development plans and many other examples of political and administrative duplication.  Similarly, a situation where town councillors nationally account for 46% of all local authority representatives but represent only 14% of the population is not sustainable in a modern, democratic society.</p><p>  The new model of municipal governance will address these and other limitations.  Equally, there is no reason whatsoever the strengths and qualities associated with many town councils cannot be extended beyond the &quot;town walls&quot;, as it were, to embrace the wider hinterlands of the towns which are linked with them for a range of social, commercial, educational, employment and other purposes.  Municipal districts will cover the entire territory of each county, reflecting European norms, removing outdated boundaries and ending the anomaly of small towns having municipal status and dual representation, while some larger centres and rural areas lack any sub-county governance.  The performance of appropriate functions by members at county and district levels, respectively, will result in greater effectiveness than the current parallel town and county system.  The allocation of functions between county and district levels will be determined on the basis of what is most relevant to each level.  Local matters will be dealt with at municipal district level, while those of wider strategic application will be decided at county level.</p><p>  The new sub-county governance arrangements will deliver the administrative and operational efficiency of a single county-wide organisation, while bringing county council decision making closer to local communities by virtue of assigning a range of reserved functions to elected members at district level, improving accountability and responsiveness.  The increased measure of subsidiarity which the new sub-county arrangements will bring has been recognised in the recent report on local democracy in Ireland, published on 30 October by the Congress of the Council of Europe.  While drawing attention to certain weaknesses in Ireland's system of local government which have developed over the decades and which the current reform programme is designed to address , the report specifically welcomed the action programme for effective local government which it referred to as &quot;ambitious&quot; and endorsed particular measures in it, including the structural changes at sub-county level.</p><p>  Some people have disingenuously tried to suggest the Council of Europe has criticised the Bill because the congress report recommended changes in &quot;legislation&quot;.  In fact, what the report was referring to was the current legislation, since the report was drafted well before the Local Government Bill was published.  On the specific issue of the replacement of town councils by municipal districts, the Council of Europe's report had the following to say:<blockquote>In the rapporteurs' opinion, the structural changes are a positive element of the proposed reform, as it provides a solution to an unfair situation whereby those living in towns had two votes as compared to the rural areas which had one.  It also simplifies the structure.  These changes are also expected to be followed by other important steps, including greater subsidiarity, avoidance of duplication, a review of boundaries, better representational balance between urban and rural areas and a cohesive administrative/executive reorganisation.</blockquote>There could hardly be a clearer endorsement of the reforms.  This is entirely consistent with the fact that two amendments critical of Ireland's reform programme were voted down in the Council of Europe chamber by a large majority of the representatives of local authorities from across Europe.</p><p>  I will refer back briefly to the overall local government reform programme by reminding Members that the core purpose of the programme is to put local government in a position to deliver better services, amenities and governance to communities by strengthening the structures, finances and operations generally of the system.  In the context of future governance arrangements within counties, the principle of strength through unity will be a key factor in ensuring these objectives are delivered on to the benefit of all communities, urban and rural.  The Local Government Bill 2013 reflects the benefits of consultation to date, the extensive studies undertaken of local government during the years and the input provided from a range of sources, not least the elected members of local authorities.</p> <p>Different views are an inherent feature of democratic debate but the <i>status quo</i>in local government is not a realistic option.  Change inevitably involves difficult decisions.  It is a responsibility of the Government to take decisions that will make a real difference and the decisions that the Government have made will bring significant net benefits to local government and the communities it serves.  They will deliver on the vision set out in the action programme on making local government the primary vehicle of governance and public service at local level.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200040#OO00200"><p>The Minister of State's response did not address my question.  He selectively quoted the Council of Europe but the chair of the monitoring committee of the Council specifically asked the Government not to pass the legislation until adequate consultation has taken place with local authorities.  In regard to the principle of subsidiarity, the report recommended that the recommendation be revised in order to ensure that principle is better enshrined in and protected by law, to promote best practice in Irish public administration as set out in article 5 of the founding treaty.</p><p>On the issue of consultation, 14% of the Irish population live in areas governed by town councils.  There is one town councillor for every 865 of these people.  That ratio will now decrease to one councillor per 4,830 people.  That is a major democratic shift.  If the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government wants consultation, why has he failed to meet the elected members of Letterkenny Town Council despite umpteen requests?  He was in Letterkenny last week but he failed to meet the members of the council.  I attended a public meeting in the town on the issue and I am aware that similar views are being expressed in town councils all over the country.  It is time for consultation not abolition.  The people spoke on the Government's recent attempt to abolish the Seanad and I believe if the people in these towns were given an opportunity to speak, they would not agree with the Minister in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1000" speakername="Dinny McGinley" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013111200040#OO00300"><p>I do not agree with the Senator.  I have outlined comprehensively the widespread consultation that took place with organisations representing members of local government bodies.  They were invited to make submissions and, given that the legislation is currently going through the Oireachtas, it is difficult to imagine that the Minister would have a bilateral meeting with a town council here or there.  The consultations have taken place and the Minister was available at another function in Donegal.  I do not want to be parochial but I happened to be at the function and I am aware that he addressed the matter extensively.  The fears expressed by those in attendance were allayed by his comments.  Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill can cite the Council of Europe but I have quoted an expansive and positive response from it to the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-12a.134" nospeaker="true" time="18:25:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.25 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 13 November 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>