<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#A00100">Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#B00200"><p>The Joint Committee on Agriculture and the Marine has completed its consideration of the following motion:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following regulations in draft: <br /><br />Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund Regulations 2020, a copy of which was laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 13 November 2020. </blockquote></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#B00300">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#B00400"><p>I have received notice from Senator Eugene Murphy that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Justice to make a statement on the treatment and care of prisoners with a mental illness in Irish prisons. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Regina Doherty of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the future of transgender healthcare in Ireland. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the continuing Covid-19 restrictions on religious worship in Ireland and the constitutionality of these restrictions. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice form Senator Catherine Ardagh of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to provide an update on plans for Scoil Colm, Crumlin, Dublin 12.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:  </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to provide an update on his Department&rsquo;s plans to improve the water and wastewater infrastructure in the villages of Doolin, Broadford, Cooraclare and Carrigaholt in County Clare. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aidan Davitt of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the implication of the national planning framework strategy of removing one-off local needs rural planning and rezoning-dezoning population caps. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the growing crisis in the Irish horticulture sector in relation to the provision of peat.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to allocate urban regeneration and development funding for Clonmel, County Tipperary. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to provide an update on a request for funding for additional classroom space in St. Mel&rsquo;s College, Longford.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter: </p><p>The need for the Minister for Transport to provide an update on waiting lists for driving tests.</p><p>I have also received notice from Senator Alice-Mary Higgins of the following matter:  </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Justice to make a statement on the recent and ongoing issuing of deportation notices to asylum seekers from Ireland during the global Covid-19 pandemic. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to outline the transitional arrangements in place to deal with applications outstanding on the closure of Caranua at the end of this year.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer of the following matter:  </p><p>The need for the Minister for Finance to clarify whether travel agents qualify for the Covid restrictions support scheme.</p><p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the nursing homes support scheme. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Pat Casey of the following matter:  </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to outline when he proposes to make waiver of rates regulations under section 15 of the Local Government Rates and other Matters Act 2019. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield of the following matter: </p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to ensure that all social housing tenants have access to all facilities in housing developments. </blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and I have selected Senators Murphy, Doherty, Mullen and Ardagh and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.9" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#B00500">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.10" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#B00600">Prison Mental Health Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#B00700"><p>I welcome former Senator and now Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, to address the House and Senator Murphy on the issue he has tabled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#B00800"><p>I appreciate this matter being taken this morning.  The reason I tabled it is that I have had a long involvement in supporting people with mental health issues in my constituency and on a broader basis for a number of years.  I also served on the prison committee of Cloverhill Prison for almost two years.  Anybody who has been a member of a prison visiting committee will know the one job one has to sign on the dotted line is to represent the welfare of prisoners.  It was a difficult experience but it teaches one a great deal about life when one meets a person in a cell who is behind bars because justice has been put in place.  In this particular situation we would all accept that something needs to be done rather quickly.</p><p>I acknowledge the phonecall I received from the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, last night.  She would dearly like to be here today but I understand she is tied up with other issues at the moment.  She has taken a keen interest in mental health issues during her period in the Oireachtas.  However, it is great to have my own county man here, the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, who also has a very good understanding of this situation.</p><p>We are discussing this issue today because of an article by Conor Gallagher in <i>The Irish Times </i>yesterday in which he reported the inhumane treatment of a mental health patient put into Cloverhill Prison, which was highlighted by the Council of Europe's Committee for the Prevention of Torture and Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment, which found serious failings in the treatment of mentally ill prisoners, and that prisoner in particular.  We all know the details of the case.  They were horrifying and shocking.  I read them again this morning.  I also acknowledge the Irish Prison Service wants to deal with this matter very urgently.  It should not be happening.  </p><p>I know the Minister will agree with me that we have to stop the practice of putting mentally ill patients into prison cells and, worst than that, isolating them in a terrible way.  We must consider putting in place a system within our prisons that will specifically deal with mentally ill patients where there would be a special quarter for them in which psychologists and psychiatrists can deal with them.  Isolating these patients in a cell for up to two weeks, apart from handing them in a bit of food, is obscene in this day and age.  If we are to treat human beings with any bit of dignity and respect we must move away from this type of carry on.  This is not the only case.  As was highlighted in the article in <i>The Irish Times </i>yesterday, there are other such cases happening. </p><p>In our constituency offices from time to time, we are contacted by families who on many occasions are struggling to cope with a mentally ill family member and find their family members are brought to court and put into prison because there is nowhere else for them to go.  The man in this instance was waiting to get into the Central Mental Hospital in Dundrum, for which there is a waiting list.  Again, that begs the question of why we cannot provide more places in Dundrum.</p><p>I will not labour the point any further.  This issue has been well flagged in recent days.  I raise it in the context of being a former member of the board of Cloverhill Prison and on the basis of my involvement in many cases, some involving families who had a person put in prison because of mental illness.  I hope the Minister of State's response will give us some good news.  It would be the wish of everybody in this Seanad to move forward with this issue and make the changes necessary as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#B00900"><p>I thank my colleague for raising this issue.  The Minister for Justice yesterday welcomed the publication of the report of the committee for the prevention of torture and fully acknowledges the importance of external oversight and evaluation in helping develop and improve our penal systems.  While the report offers encouragement in a number of areas and recognises progress made, it clearly identifies issues that need to be addressed urgently.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frankie Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Among the issues to be welcomed is the introduction by the IPS of a new prisoner complaints system before the end of the year which, when bedded down, will include an oversight role for the Ombudsman.  In addition, a review of the prison rules is under way, taking account of the most recently published European model rules.  A specifically designed detention facility in Dublin Airport will provide a dedicated short-term facility for persons refused permission to land and will reduce the need to transfer such persons to another facility.  The operation, management and governance of special observation cells is being reviewed and a clear distinction between the operation of close supervision cells and safety observation cells will be made.  The practice of slopping out has been significantly reduced over recent years, with over &euro;130 million invested in capital projects to improve and modernise the prison estate.</p><p>One of the most pressing issues raised by the committee relates to how we provide for the complex needs of people with mental health difficulties who come into contact with the criminal justice system.  This is a priority for the Minister for Justice and I am pleased to say that in September, she met my colleague, the Minister for Health, to discuss this.  They agreed to establish a high-level, cross-departmental and cross-agency task force to consider the mental health and addiction challenges of those imprisoned, as well as their primary care support on release.  This work is under way with a view to planning for and implementing a revised model of care in order to deliver appropriate inpatient and step-down resources in the Central Mental Hospital, CMH, complemented by adequate prison in-reach and community forensic mental health services and supports.  The Government acknowledges that every person with mental health difficulties coming into contact with the system should have access to a comprehensive mental health support system and the high-level task force will look at how we deliver this as a matter of urgency.  Both the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, and the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, recognise the urgent need to design and put in place proper systems to care for the most vulnerable people who come into contact with the criminal justice system.  It is only fair to acknowledge the very positive comments made by the CPT in its 2019 preliminary report regarding the overall high level of care provided by prison staff to prisoners, which demonstrated a genuine concern among staff for those in custody.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I accept that the setting up of that task force was very important to the three parties in government as part of the programme for Government.  I am delighted to hear him say that the Ministers for Justice and Health have met.  I do not want to be blaming the people in the Prison Service because they are not trained for this type of work.  The task force is great.  The Minister of State may not know the answer to this but when is it due to report back?  If he does not have that answer today he might come back to me with it.  In the meantime, we must ensure that there are psychiatrists, psychologists and people to deal with this issue within the Prison Service to deal with any mental health patient who ends up in prison.  The divide needs to be addressed quite clearly in order that a person in this situation can go directly to a psychiatric hospital and not to a prison.  It is not the place for those people and we see what happens, which shows that those people are in a vulnerable position if they end up in prison.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#C00300"><p>The Government is committed to delivering safe, secure and humane custody for those sent to prison in this State.  This includes the provision of appropriate mental health services to persons in custody. We accept the CPT's findings that there is much to be done in this regard but welcome its recognition that progress has been made in a number of areas.  We are considering how best to deliver appropriate CMH inpatient and step-down resources, complemented by adequate prison in-reach and community forensic mental health services and supports.  This is a priority for the Ministers for Health and Justice and for the Government collectively.  In addition, a review of the use of special observation cells is under way and appropriate and robust standard operating procedures and training on their use will be implemented.  A new prisoner complaints system will be implemented before the end of the year and prison rules are under review to ensure they are aligned with international best practice.</p> <p>Greater use is being made of alternatives to imprisonment and the IPS has developed a prison population management plan to maximise capacity within the estate, increasing the use of open centres and backdoor strategies, including structured temporary releases.  The Irish Prison Service's capital strategy outlines plans for the complete replacement of outdated accommodation in Limerick and Portlaoise prisons, as well as improvements across a number of other prisons.  A capital allocation of &euro;36 million has been set aside for this under budget 2021.  The Government and the IPS are committed to implementing the longer-term changes required to make our penal system safe, effective and able to respond to the needs of all prisoners, especially vulnerable ones.  While there is unlikely to be a quick-fix solution to some of the issues highlighted by the CPT, we will work intensively together to ensure all people get the care and support they need from the system.</p> <p>The Senator asked about when the task force will report back.  I will try to get an answer for him on that as soon as possible. </p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.17" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#C00400">Health Services Reform</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#C00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his attendance in the Seanad this morning to discuss this issue.  It is hugely important to the transgender community in Ireland, as well as their families, friends and supporters.  Last year, the then Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, became increasingly aware of the difficulties faced by the transgender community in accessing essential healthcare in Ireland.  He listened to that community and in taking on board their concerns, he set up and established the national transgender healthcare steering committee in May 2019.  The committee was made up of members of the advocacy group Transgender Equality Network Ireland, TENI, clinicians, psychiatrists, endocrinologists and representatives from both the HSE and the Department of Health.</p> <p>The overarching objective of the committee was to present a report to the Minister on how to develop a seamless and integrated service for those who present with gender identity issues, with clear pathways of care in order that the needs of the patients and their families are placed at the centre of the delivery of those services.  This report was completed earlier this year and was received by the Department of Health on 28 February, which was unfortunately just one day before the first case of Covid was discovered in this country.  While focus on tackling the pandemic understandably delayed the examination and publication of the report's recommendations in the first few months, the fact that no movement whatsoever has happened in the interim months is hugely disheartening.</p> <p>The HSE and the Department of Health have done fantastic work to make sure normal healthcare services have for the most part resumed, yet the report remains shelved.  According to some of the members of the steering committee, it is worse than shelved; it appears to be lost.  It is an extremely important and valuable document which was developed at the request of the Minister for Health and was then submitted to the Department.  That it seems to have just disappeared is baffling.  The HSE maintains that it was submitted to the Department but the Department and the Minister of State - not Deputy Feighan - believe the HSE is still working on it.  This passing of the buck is not good enough.  It is a very serious report with very serious recommendations and it needs and deserves immediate attention and action.</p> <p>What is even more worrying is the lack of engagement between the Minister for Health's office and his own ministerial appointee to the committee since the formation of the Government in June.  That appointee has made six attempts to communicate with the Minister, all of which have been ignored.  That is the main reason I am standing in this Chamber today.  It is a real pity.</p> <p>Members of the transgender community need to know their voices are being heard.  As the previous Minister gave them a platform to speak, I hope their voices will not fall on deaf ears.  The report must be examined and published without delay and a plan to introduce the recommendations in the report must be put forward immediately.  Obviously, no one here has seen the report but given the wealth of expertise, personally and professionally, of the people on the committee, I have absolutely no doubt that the recommendations would improve the services for our transgender community and that this Seanad and the D&aacute;il will support them.</p> <p>Over the last few years I have had the privilege of working in a personal capacity with the transgender community, with TENI, and with members of the trans community seeking employment, where they face huge discrimination.  We are making progress but it is slow.  Often, some of the issues we highlight and some of the recommendations we make get ignored and are marginalised by governments around the world.  This Government needs to make huge strides to represent this community, as did the previous one.  This is a small community but it is large in its heart and even larger in the impositions its members face every single day.  The future of transgender healthcare in this country is unclear.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The current haphazard provision of services to our young people who are struggling with their identity is unreliable and potentially unsustainable in its current format.  Two years ago, the people made a decision not to export our citizens for healthcare to other countries and yet this year alone, we have sent more than 80 patients under 18 years of age to the UK for health.  In the space of four months from November 2019 to February 2020, the waiting time went from 12 months to 24 months.  This issue is critical and needs an immediate response.</p><p>Has the Minister received the report?  Has it been read?  Has it been actioned?  If not, when will it be actioned?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Doherty for raising the issue.  The National LGBTI+ Inclusion Strategy 2019-2021 sets out Government policy for promoting inclusion, targeting discrimination, and improving the quality of life and well-being for the LGBTI+ community in Ireland.  It is supported by the LGBTI+ National Youth Strategy 2018-2020.</p> <p>The strategy commits to ensuring that people can fully and equally avail of mainstream health services.  In addition, the strategy recognises that targeted services are needed to support transgender people, including through the process of transition.</p> <p>In line with international trends, the demand for transgender services in Ireland has increased exponentially over recent years.  Prevalence studies suggest an increase in those experiencing gender dysphoria.  In 1997 the World Health Organization reported a prevalence of 1:60,000 and in 2013, the fifth edition of the Diagnostic and Statistics Manual of Mental Disorders reported a prevalence of 1:20,000.</p> <p>Services for transgender care have evolved organically over recent years, with adult services based in St. Columcille's Hospital, which is part of Ireland East Hospital Group, and children's services located in Our Lady's Children's Hospital, which is part of Children's Health Ireland.  Endocrinology and psychological support services are delivered on both sites.</p> <p>A model of care was developed to support the development of HSE gender identity services.  The model of care was supported by the allocation of additional resources to enhance services.  Recognising the need to develop gender identity services and to best use the additional funding, in May 2019 the HSE established a steering committee chaired by the national clinical lead in mental health, Dr. Siobh&aacute;n N&iacute; Bhriain, as the Senator outlined.  The committee had the specific purpose to develop a seamless and integrated service for those people who present to the health service with gender identity issues.  The committee brought together the various HSE transgender services, along with service users, as represented by Transgender Equality Network Ireland and ThisIsMe.</p> <p>The committee concluded its work in January 2020 and issued its final report in February 2020.  I recently had the opportunity to read the report.  The report details the two outcomes achieved by the steering group, namely, the development of a job description for a consultant psychiatrist in child and adolescent psychiatry post to develop the transgender identity services for those aged under 18; and support for a governance committee across the Ireland East Hospital Group and Children's Health Ireland to ensure ongoing review of the national gender service as it develops.</p> <p>The report notes the development of a strong sense of collegiality among the committee members and the commitment of all to develop a well-governed service for the transgender patient group.  The report makes seven recommendations to enhance the model of care for the transgender community, all of which fall under the remit of the HSE.  One of the recommendations is to develop a service users' forum within the national gender service.  Most of the report's recommendations are in progress or ongoing.</p> <p>I note the Senator's concerns about trying to get a meeting with the Minister and the Department.  I will also bring those concerns back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#D00300"><p>I genuinely thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to give us that information because the members of the committee have not been able to get it in any other format.  I appreciate not only that the Minister of State said he had actually received the report but also that the seven recommendations have been read and some actions taken.  I say on behalf of the transgender community that is greatly welcome.</p> <p>I have two requests.  I ask for the Department of Health, if not to re-engage with the entire committee, to absolutely return one of the six calls made by the Minister's advocate on that committee.  He is a young gentleman who has worked his socks off to try to improve conditions in this country for himself and his friends.  Having asked him to do that body of work, the very least we can do is to engage with him.</p> <p>I ask the Minister of State to publish the report and outline the status of the seven recommendations.  That will instil trust and restore faith in the transgender community and among the people who put this body of work together that they have been listened to and their recommendations have not fallen on deaf ears.  I know the Minister of State might not be able to commit to those requests himself, but I ask him to bring them back to the Minister, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, and ask for a response to be issued immediately.  I thank the Minister of State; I really appreciate his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#D00400"><p>I am committed to supporting the HSE in ensuring that people wishing to transition their gender have timely access to treatment that accords with the best practice.  I note the Senator's welcome for the report.  I want to see the HSE develop a well-governed and patient-centred healthcare service for adults and children in the transgender community in line with the programme for Government.</p> <p>The report of the steering committee on the development of HSE transgender identity services is an important step in achieving this objective.  Already the committee has achieved two tangible outcomes and its seven recommendations are in train.  I am seeking a further update on the implementation of the committee's recommendation over the recent months from the new national clinical lead in mental health, Dr. Amir Niazi.  I commend the work of the steering committee and I would welcome the early publication of its report by the HSE.</p> <p>The six calls from the advocate for the group should be responded to.  I know many people in the Department are working on Covid, as I have seen with people working in the sections dealing with alcohol and tobacco.  However, they should be able to reply to a phone call.  I will also bring that back.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.23" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#D00500">Covid-19 Pandemic</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#D00600"><p>It would be good if we had a debate in this Chamber on that last important and sensitive topic.</p><p>Article 44.2.1&deg; of the Constitution states, &quot;Freedom of conscience and the free profession and practice of religion are, subject to public order and morality, guaranteed to every citizen.&quot;  Article 9 of the European Convention on Human Rights binds Ireland to ensure that &quot;Everyone has the right ... either alone or in community with others and in public or private, to manifest his [one might say his or her] religion or belief, in worship, teaching, practice and observance.&quot;</p><p>Some 1.2 million people, representing 36% of all adults, exercise these rights on at least a weekly basis by attending a religious service.  However, under the current Covid regulations, SI 448 of 2020, in force since 21 October, the organiser of any event is liable for a fine of up to &euro;2,500 or up to six months in prison.  No exception was made for religious gatherings of any kind or of any denomination.</p><p>It is not an exaggeration to say that this is the first time that religious leaders have been threatened with prosecution for holding religious services since the last of the Penal Laws was abolished in the late 1700s.  This blanket ban on worship is a flagrant breach of the constitutional guarantee in Article 44.2.1&deg;.  In 1972, in the case of Quinn's Supermarket <i>v</i>. Attorney General, the Supreme Court ruled that laws of general applicability which have the effect of preventing the right to practise religion are unconstitutional unless they include a carve-out protection for religious practice and any restrictions of that right must also be proportionate.</p><p>The European Court of Human Rights has repeatedly ruled that governments must conduct a detailed scientific analysis showing that a ban is absolutely necessary on public health grounds.  However, the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, has already suggested in the D&aacute;il that no such analysis exists.  On 22 October he told Deputy McNamara that he would &quot;challenge NPHET to provide the evidence&quot;.  On 3 November Deputy Nolan asked a parliamentary question seeking the evidentiary basis for the restrictions on public worship.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In a quite remarkable 800-word written reply, the Minister, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, provided no evidence and completely dodged the question he was asked.  This suggests that the restrictions were applied arbitrarily, with no study of the available evidence.  That is a breach of the Constitution and the convention.</p><p>I would be grateful if the Minister of State would state clearly whether the Minister for Health sought advice from the Attorney General on the constitutionality of these regulations, given the failure to make an appropriate exclusion for matters concerning religious worship, and what that advice was.  The first part of the question can be given a "Yes" or "No" answer.  Was advice sought from the Attorney General?  Second, has an evidentiary analysis been compiled by the Department of Health on the need for such a blanket ban, given that such an evidentiary analysis would be required by the European Convention on Human Rights?  Third, why was no detail given to the D&aacute;il or the Seanad up to this point?</p><p>I would appreciate an answer to those questions.  We all understand the need for restrictions for the sake of public health, and why the Government might urge such restrictions on people as a moral matter, as it were, and, if necessary, as a legal matter.  However, where the Constitution is so clear on freedom of religious worship issues, it appears to be inadequate and unacceptable that legislation providing for penalties in the context of the breach of such restrictions would not nod, at least, to the constitutional reality and say that the State is not constitutionally permitted to impose penalties in this area.  Good lawmaking would require that.  That would not stop the Government from urging religious leaders, who have been very anxious to be compliant in all this, and religious communities not to have public gatherings in certain circumstances.  However, to legislate for restrictions and penalties, knowing there is a constitutional problem with such penalties, seems at least sloppy and, more seriously, disrespectful to the State, the Constitution and the law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#E00200"><p>I thank Senator Mullen for raising this matter.  I would love to see the churches open again.  Indeed, I, my wife and my family are looking forward to returning to mass, and I am proud to say that as a politician.</p> <p>The Government's strategy, in line with the public health advice, is disease suppression.  Covid-19 spreads when individuals and groups come into close contact with each other, enabling the virus to move from one person to another.  The framework for restrictive measures is framed to account for periods when there is low incidence of the disease, with isolated clusters and low community transmission, through to situations where there is high or rapidly increasing incidence and widespread community transmission.  It recognises the need for society and business to be allowed to continue as normally as possible.  The framework takes account of the societal and economic impacts of the response to Covid-19.  Nuanced and sectoral responses are in place to ensure the number of people impacted will be kept to the minimum necessary to control the disease, given the psychosocial impacts of the disease on the population.</p> <p>With the recent epidemiological situation of high incidence of disease, widespread community transmission and increasing hospitalisations and deaths, it was necessary to put in place significant restrictions at level 5 to arrest the current trajectory of the disease and break transmission chains.  This means asking people to stay at home and eliminating as much activity and contacts as possible to ensure that opportunities for the virus to transmit are minimised.  Unfortunately, this includes moving religious services online, with places of worship remaining open for private prayer only and exceptions continuing for funerals and weddings, where 25 may attend.  It is important to note that at all framework levels, ministers of religion are permitted to travel to perform a service online, to minister to the sick, and to conduct a funeral or wedding ceremony.</p> <p>These restrictions have posed major challenges for the religious community and they are to be commended on how they have responded.  By adopting new ways of connecting through social media and various communication channels, the church has continued to bring comfort and assistance to those in need, in particular those who are grieving.  It is acknowledged that these restrictions impact on the spiritual well-being of faith communities, but the measures in place to suppress the disease transmission are intended to minimise the risks to public health while striking the right balance in prioritising and protecting some activities over others.</p> <p>Regular ongoing contact is maintained with the faith groups and non-confessional organisations by the protocol and civic policy division of the Department of the Taoiseach, especially with regard to specific queries on interpretation of the Covid-19 guidelines and regulations.  In this regard, the Taoiseach had a number of Covid-19 related meetings with faith groups.  On 8 April 2020, the Taoiseach held a meeting with leaders of the main faiths and non-confessional organisations to discuss the effects Covid-19 is having on their communities.  On 14 May 2020, the Taoiseach met with representatives of the Catholic Church, Archbishops E. Martin, D. Martin and K. O'Reilly, to share thoughts on the reopening of places of worship over the course of the summer.  The church shared information on the work that is being done at all levels to develop a national church plan for safe reopening and emphasised it would play its part in applying public health measures to ensure the health and safety of its congregation.</p> <p>A further meeting with the Catholic archbishops was held last month.  Discussion at that meeting focused mainly on the effect which the current Covid-19 restrictions are having on the health and well-being of the faith community and the great desire to return to worship as soon as possible.  The archbishops emphasised that they are fully supportive of the public health messages, but highlighted that coming together in prayer and worship, especially for mass and the sacraments, is fundamental to Christian tradition and a source of nourishment for the life and well-being of communities.  The importance of gathering for worship as a source of consolation and hope at Christmas time was stressed.  The need for a shared understanding of the effects of the pandemic as it evolves and to align our response accordingly was recognised.  All agreed on the importance of solidarity in facing and overcoming the challenges of Covid-19 together.  Pastoral work continues as we enter the traditional time of remembrance in this month of November.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  His personal expression of the importance of public worship for him and many other people will be appreciated by people of faith.  However, he is in the unfortunate position of not being the Minister with Cabinet responsibility and having to come to this House to give a reply that does not address the core point I raised.  There appears to be no constitutional justification for creating restrictions with penalties and not excluding public worship.  In the D&aacute;il, in response to Deputy Nolan, the Minister said that it could be noted that holding a religious gathering is not a penal offence.  How does this make sense if there are provisions for a fine and potential prison for holding gatherings but no exclusion made for religious gatherings?</p> <p>This is extremely problematic.  As I and Members of the D&aacute;il have pointed out, faith communities have been extremely compliant and have led by example.  There appears to be no evidence that there has been a spread of the virus associated with religious gatherings.  In that context, if we return to level 3, it would be intolerable if the Government were to continue to pretend, implicitly or explicitly, that it is somehow against the law to hold religious gatherings.  Let it propose what it wishes, but it should not suggest that this is against the law.  In light of what we know, it would also be intolerable if there would not be the possibility of public worship, as technically would be the case if we only return to level 3.  It is clear that we need a modified level 3.  That message must be conveyed, loudly and clearly.  The Government has not done its work properly here by proposing to legislate to penalise those who organise religious gatherings when, in fact, it has no legal or constitutional basis for being able to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#E00400"><p>I thank Senator Mullen for being so diplomatic in his response to my reply.  The Government recognises the immense sacrifices that are being made by the country in this difficult time.  As I mentioned, there has been significant engagement and solidarity from the Catholic Church and other faith communities at all stages through the pandemic to ensure the protection of individuals and communities from Covid-19.  I agree with the Senator.  As a politician and Minister of State and as a citizen, I believe the churches have done extremely well.  They have gone out of their way to put all the necessary protections in place.  I have highlighted to the Government that this should be taken on board.  I hope that when we go down to level 3, it will be a modified level 3, as the Senator said.  I look forward to a time when people who are responsible, and the churches and faith leaders are responsible with their congregations, will get the answer we all want.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#F00150">Special Educational Needs</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#F00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Education who is here to update us on plans for Scoil Colm, Crumlin, Dublin 12.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#F00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming in to address this issue.  I have worked with the Dublin 12 campaign for ASD inclusion and the Involve Autism groups since their inception.  These are groups of courageous and dynamic parents who campaign for autism units in their local schools.  More specifically, the Dublin 12 for ASD inclusion has campaigned since 2018 for an autism-specific school in Dublin 12.</p> <p>Over the years we have had huge difficulty in obtaining the exact figure for those diagnosed with autism in Dublin 12.  There also remains an unanswered parliamentary question on how many children in Dublin 12 have been diagnosed with autism.  Despite this we know that there is much anecdotal evidence that there is a massive need in the area for an autism-specific school.  The Department of Education has identified that there are 25 children in the Dublin 12 area who receive home tuition.  However, there are other children who live in the area but attend less suitable schools and autism units located outside of their area, so there is a huge need for an autism-specific school in Dublin 12.  These groups of brave parents have identified a site at Scoil Colm.  It is an empty building on Armagh Road that has the potential to be of huge benefit to the community.  We have met the Minister for Education and asked her to open Scoil Colm as an autism-specific school.</p> <p>As many Senators will know, Scoil Colm is set in the middle of an educational hub and surrounded by schools.  Scoil &Uacute;na Naofa is a mainstream school that does not have a mainstream ASD class.  Scoil Eoin is a special school that caters for all disabilities with students ranging in age from nine to 18 years.  The Rosary College is a secondary school that does not have an autism class.  There is also a Youthreach and primary care centre that provides the community with access to GPs and public health nurses.</p> <p>Scoil Colm has been closed since its amalgamation in 2016.  Everyone involved in the project is aware that the premises need a massive amount of work but it can host up to 132 children.  Scoil Colm also has a big campus on beautiful grounds so could provide a sensory garden.  The vision is for Scoil Colm to open and become a centre of excellence for those with autism.  I visited the site several weeks ago and met the Minister for Education.  This project has the cross-party support of all the politicians in the area who know first hand the huge need felt by children with autism in the area.</p> <p>I congratulate the Minister of State on the recent announcement whereby she asked, or perhaps ordered, 25 schools in south Dublin to open special autism units.  That is a hugely welcome development but there will always be children who do not thrive in a school with an autism-specific unit so need the services provided at a autism-specific school.  It is in that light that I ask for an update on Scoil Colm.  What is the future envisaged for Scoil Colm?  When will a decision be made?  The site is vacant and the local community want the premises to be opened as an autism-specific school because the children in the community lack such a service.  Does the Minister of State know how many people in the Dublin 12 area have been diagnosed with autism?  How many children are on waiting lists for either an autism-specific school or unit?</p> <p>It is important for the public to know how difficult it is for parents who have a child with autism.  When they seek to register their child in a school, parents must apply to all autism classes in the area regardless of suitability for their child and they must apply to all autism classes outside of the area to improve their chances of getting any placement for their child, regardless of suitability for their child.  Schools contact parents to advise if their child has been offered a placement.  This offering can be made well into June thus increasing uncertainty for parents.  If a placement is offered a parent must accept it regardless of the suitability of the class for the child.  It is difficult enough for a child to get a place in a local school without having autism needs.  However, when one's child is diagnosed with autism, one is faced with treble red tape when trying to get him or her a place in a school, which is hugely unfair.</p> <p>Last week, the Minister for Education announced a no homework day.  The children in Dublin 12 who are being home schooled and have been diagnosed with autism would like to experience a no homework day.  We must, as we all know, treat all of our children equally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#F00400"><p>I can hear the Senator's frustration on behalf of the parents of children with special needs and their journey, and I share her concern.  As the very first dedicated Minister for special education, I am going to do precisely what she asked and make the entire process of locating a placement whether it is a special class or special school as easy as possible because at the moment it is unsatisfactory.  I will outline this matter in my contribution.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter.  I want to acknowledge the tremendous work done by Involve Autism and the Dublin 12 campaign, both of whom I have met.  Many of the parents have become activists as a result of their children's issues and challenges that they have had to face when dealing with the Department and the system.  </p> <p>Next year, as the Senator will know, we will have a record breaking &euro;2 billion investment in education or 20% of the overall budget.  As a result, the number of special education teachers, and special classes and school places will be at an unprecedented level, which is a step forward in the right direction.</p> <p>Since my appointment I have met not just Involve Autism and the Dublin 12 campaign groups but a number of different associations and advocates for the special education sector.  They have raised a number of issues with me that I hope to tackle through action priorities.  I have published a list of my action priorities.  I intend to itemise them and state deadlines and timelines for achieving those goals.  Through both better planning at local and national levels, it is my objective to have special education places to meet the stream of emerging demand.  The Senator talked about the number of autistic children.  The data is something that we are looking at in terms of collecting and harvesting the information.  </p> <p>A forecasting model is being developed by the National Council for Special Education so that in the future this perennial issue, where there is a dearth of special class places, is tackled from a demographic perspective.  It is important to note that the growth of autism has grown exponentially not just in Ireland but throughout the world and constantly evolves, which we have noted is particularly true for girls.</p> <p>I am very conscious that there are some parts of the country, including south Dublin, in which there has been an increase in population that has led to valid concerns about the shortage of school places.  I assure the Senator that the NCSE is continuing its engagement with schools, patron bodies, parents and others across south Dublin to bring the required additional special education placements onstream.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Josepha Madigan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2424"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2424&amp;amp;pid=JosephaMadigan&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Senator will be aware that Scoil Colm has been identified as a potential location in terms of the provision of additional special school places for the area and my Department has had engagement with the building owner in this regard.  Discussions are ongoing regarding the next steps in utilising this accommodation for special school places.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#G00200"><p>That concludes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#G00300"><p>Can I not come in again?  Everyone else had the opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#G00400"><p>It is now 11.30 a.m.  The Senator can have one minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#G00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State, but I asked for a specific update on Scoil Colm.  I would like to know where we are in regard to the discussions.  What the Minister of State has said is very unclear.  We need to know what is the future for Scoil Colm.  What is going on is very cloak and dagger but the Department should give parents a proper update on the position of the school.  They want to know what state the negotiations are at and what stage we are at in the ongoing process.  It is hugely unfair to lead people up the garden path.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#G00600"><p>I assure Senator Ardagh that nobody is leading anybody up the garden path.  Suffice to say, there have been site visits and discussions with the patrons, trustees and the principal of Scoil Colm where some 150 children are already provided for.  My understanding is that the school will provide some but not all of the classes.  There are ongoing discussions and we need to be hopeful in that regard.  I hope something might arise out of the discussions and that I will be able to inform the House of it in due course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.39" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.32 a.m. and resumed at 11.41 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.40" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#H00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#H00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the Technological Universities Act 2018 (Section 36) (Appointed Day) Order 2020 - back from committee, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, the Planning and Development Bill 2020 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 1 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 1, whichever is the later, and to conclude within two hours, with the time allocated to group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and a Minister to be given no less than seven minutes to reply to the debate; No. 3, motion regarding the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund Regulations 2020 - back from committee, to be taken at 3.15 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 2, whichever is later, and to conclude after 75 minutes, with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed six minutes, of all other Senators not to exceed four minutes and a Minister to be given no less than five minutes to reply to the debate; No. 4, Criminal Justice (Theft and Fraud Offences) (Amendment) Bill 2020 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 3, whichever is the later; and No. 27, motion 7, to be taken at 6 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 4, whichever is the later, with the time allocated to this debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#H00300"><p>I would like to address a number of issues to the Leader and to the House, the first of which relates to Tusla.  There is a very disturbing report in this morning's newspapers in regard to Tusla and the problems within that agency.  The specific issues mentioned are a lack of consistency in how Tusla operates and the retention of staff, which is a particular concern.  There are many fine people working in Tusla and doing an excellent job but it is difficult for them within what is described as "an over-centralised out-of-date structure".  As we know, children are being moved from social worker to social worker.  This is very traumatic for children because it means they have to relive their negative experiences again and again.  There are many challenges facing Tusla, including securing foster parents.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on Tusla, how it operates and what it needs to do to improve.</p> <p>The other area is remote working and poor broadband and telephone services, particularly in regard to Eir.  I welcome that the chief executive of Eir is to appear before an Oireachtas committee this week.  Many people are having horrific experiences in their dealings with customer services at Eir.  A staff member in my office has not been able to make or receive calls on a mobile for the past four months and cannot access customer services in Eir.  As the largest telecoms operator in this State Eir needs to do better.  We need to engage with ComReg on this matter and, possibly, a debate in the House on communications would be worthwhile.</p> <p>The final area is public transport, which is always important.  It is important it is accessible, affordable and flexible, particularly for those in the commuter areas outside of Dublin, including Kildare, Laois, Meath and Wicklow.  In Kildare, north Kildare is part of a short-hop zone and the remainder of Kildare going forward part of a long-hop zone.  There is need for a medium-hop zone, particularly now when many people are working from home and may not need to avail of a full-year annual tax saver ticket.  There should be more flexibility for people who need to travel to Dublin once or twice a week.  The extension of the Leap card would provide this for people in commuter belt areas.  I ask the Leader to ask the Minister for Transport to come the House for a debate on accessible and affordable public transport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#H00400"><p>I would like to propose an amendment to the Order of Business.  I propose that No. 1 not be taken without debate and that a 45 minute debate be allowed, with the associated changes being made to the Order of Business.  I am a member of the education committee, all members of which had something to say on this important issue.  The future of our technological universities and their establishment is an important issue and merits Senators having an opportunity to comment on the matter.</p> <p>I had intended to raise the issue of the welfare of pre-born children.  I am glad the Minister for Health has finally established an inquiry into the use and licensing of the drug valproate, otherwise known as Epilim, which has for decades been licensed and used in the treatment of epilepsy and manage seizures but it has been known for some time that it can cause birth defects and developmental difficulties in a child if taken by the mother during pregnancy.  No warnings were given to women about this until recent years and so there is a very low awareness of how much of a problem it is.  I was going to ask that the Minister address the issue in this House in due course, so I welcome that development.</p> <p>The second issue is a specific and tragic issue which requires that the Minister for Health come to the House for a debate.  Two years ago almost to the day we debated abortion legislation in this House and several Senators raised the possibility that Irish babies would be born alive as a result of failed abortions, particularly in late-term abortions.  This happens regularly in the UK and elsewhere.  The former Minister described this as scaremongering.  A report published recently by three medical professionals in UCC studied the work of ten doctors who have performed late-term abortions under the 2018 Act.  I urge Senators to read it.  It is deeply disturbing and chilling to read.  It highlights three main issues.  First, it is clear from the study that babies have been born alive, having survived the abortion procedure, and have been left to die, with doctors interviewed saying they were "begging people to help deal with the situation", referring to calls for help made to colleagues.  The doctors surveyed described what they do as brutal, awful and emotionally difficult.  Second, it is clear from reading the study that administering pain relief to unborn babies before late-term abortions is not something that features in the considerations of those carrying out the abortions.  This, too, must stir our consciences.  Third, there is the heart-breaking accounts of the feelings among doctors, with one doctor describing "stab the baby in the heart in order to induce a fatal heart attack before inducing delivery" and saying "I remember getting sick out in the corridors afterwards because I thought it was such an awful procedure and so dreadful".  The doctors reported widespread opposition to abortion from other doctors.  This was compiled by academics who broadly support relaxing the restrictions, even currently, in place.</p> <p>In 2018, I and other Senators proposed amendments to the Act which would allow precautionary pain relief for surgical abortions and after care for babies who survive the procedure as a gesture towards the compassion we should feel in these cases.  These proposals were rejected.  I call for a rethink.  Regardless of how people voted in the past, I sincerely hope we can all recognise that there is something dreadfully wrong here.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I sincerely hope this is an area we can revisit urgently and that we can unite in finding a way to show mercy and compassion to unborn babies who end up in these appalling, horrific and heartbreaking situations.  Let us disregard how people voted in the past and let us not be bound by that.  This is a call to our consciences.  I ask that the Minister would come to the House on this issue and this issue only.  It cannot just be dealt with on the fly as if it was some normal everyday issue.  I plead with the House on this, that at least we can unite about some aspects of this debate.  We should all be extremely disturbed by what this report has brought to our attention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J00200"><p>I want to raise a number of issues on our Defence Forces with the Leader.  The first issue is to support calls made in this House by colleagues for getting an update on the commencement of public pay talks.  There may have been some preliminary contact with the representative bodies of our Defence Forces, which is always welcome, but I am sure that those representative bodies, like the rest of us in the House, would welcome clarification of the reports in the media of preliminary talks, and referred to in the media as exploratory talks, before the invites were sent out to representative bodies yesterday.  From dealing with those representative bodies in the past months I know that they are very keen to be at the table to represent their members but they want to ensure that they are all starting from the same starting blocks with the Department.</p> <p>I want to use this opportunity to reaffirm the Labour Party's support for the Permanent Defence Force Other Ranks Representative Association, PDFORRA's desire, and now the growing need, to affiliate to ICTU.  It is events like those over the past days that should finally convince the Minister, Deputy Coveney, that this affiliation should happen.</p> <p>In replies received by my Labour Party colleagues over recent days we learned that up to 500 Defence Forces personnel will leave our Permanent Defence Force by the end of the year.  If we do not address pay and conditions urgently then we are simply not being serious about the future of our Defence Forces and no forthcoming commission will solve this.</p> <p>With regard to the forthcoming commission I too believe it is very important that the House gets the chance to discuss the terms of reference for the commission.  I am sure that like many Members who made a submission to the Department of Defence, we would all like to know how the commission is progressing, what terms of reference are being considered, and indeed the timelines involved.</p> <p>I have been contacted by a number of members of the public who are very complimentary of our Defence Forces and the work they are carrying out during Covid-19, especially over the past days, and they wanted that acknowledged in the House.</p> <p>I welcome the meeting this week between the Minister and representatives of the Reserve Defence Force.  It was reported that the Department has also agreed that members of the RDF will be able to serve overseas in the future.  This is a welcome development, but it needs the support of employment legislation, which I hope will be forthcoming.  Our Reserve Defence Force has an important part to play in the future of our Defence Forces, and this meeting was an important step in that development.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister for Defence, Deputy Coveney, to the House to urgently address these issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J00300"><p>I wish to raise reports in the media yesterday in relation to some prisoners in Coverhill Prison who are mentally unwell.  In its latest report on Ireland, the Council of Europe's European Committee for the Prevention of Torture and Inhumane or Degrading Treatment or Punishment revealed some shocking conditions relating to some male prisoners in Cloverhill Prison, one of whom was left in an observation cell for two weeks, naked and in his own faeces.  The prisoner had not received so much as a shower, and the only time the door was opened was when his food was being put into his cell.  This is happening in Ireland's prison system.  I cannot even say that we can blame the prison system.  Clearly, people who are mentally unwell are being sentenced to prison and are being sent into a prison system that is not fit for purpose for someone who is so unwell and who should definitely not be in the prison system at all.</p><p>Will the Leader ask the Minister for Justice to come to the House in the near future for a debate on prison reform and prison conditions?  I remember reading a quote in some research I did with Fiona O'Reilly, CEO of Safetynet services, when she said that the streets became our asylums.  When we moved from mental health facilities and putting people into institutions, we did not necessarily get it right when we said that we would reintegrate people and that we would treat them within the community.  In fact, those very people who would have been in institutions have ended up in our prison system and on our streets.  We really need to address this issue and do so quickly.  When a person who is so unwell is sentenced there needs to be some level of understanding and awareness within the Judiciary of the resources and supports the prison system has in being able to deal with that person, including security staff within the prison itself.  They are not mental health nurses, and I am sure they are at a loss in what they can do.  We need to be able to fix this.</p><p>On Senator Mullen's contribution, we need to be very careful when we say &quot;late-term abortions&quot;.It is not a late-term abortion, it is actually for fatal foetal abnormality.  We need to be very careful of what language we use.  There is no late-term abortion in Ireland unless it is for fatal foetal abnormality.  If one looks for the report, the only place one can find it on Google is in the likes of <i>gript</i>.<i>ie</i>.  I could not find the original report.  I would like to be able to access the original report-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J00400"><p>But-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J00500"><p>Through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J00600"><p>We need to be very careful about our language.  They are not late-term abortions.  I am sure people will read the report very differently and with a different lens.  I just wanted to refer to the language used of "late-term abortions".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J00700"><p>I agree with some of the statements made by Senator Ruane on Senator Mullen's language today.  It was completely inappropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J00800"><p>But it does occur in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J00900"><p>Members know that under Standing Order 39, if they want to interrupt, they must ask the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J01000"><p>Today is international day for the elimination of violence against women.  This is against the backdrop of reports where we have learned that one in eight women suffers violence during pregnancy and that one in five women who are in an intimate relationship suffers violence.  Domestic violence did not go away during the lockdown, where one might have thought it may have.  This shows that a huge amount of violence is happening within people's homes.  Today the director of the Dublin Rape Crisis Centre, Noeline Blackwell, stated that an "epidemic" of sexual violence has been going on in Ireland for the past two decades.  Obviously, we need proper resources, including proper resourcing of women's refuge centres, for which there is a huge demand during lockdown.  Nearly half a dozen women have been on to me who could not get a place in a refuge.</p> <p>If they do get a place the women have a struggle to continue on.  Leaving a relationship is hugely difficult.  Not only do the women need places in refuges they also need the resources to continue on, including counselling support and housing so they can leave abusive relationships.</p> <p>This is also against the backdrop of anecdotal stories yesterday of the school in Carlow telling young girls how to dress.  This has been denied but it feels as though we are slipping backwards when it comes to women's rights and women's welfare.  We really need to put our money where our mouths are.  We possibly need to have a dedicated Minister, not necessarily just for women's rights, but this area needs to be funded properly because domestic violence has not gone away.  It remains very prevalent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#J01100"><p>Over the past years we have seen huge investment and resourcing in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to increase the strength of the force.  It is now nearly at 15,000 with the highest budget ever of &euro;3 billion in 2021.  New and upgraded equipment, fleets of vehicles and new stations have been delivered in places such as Wexford and Kevin Street, not too far away from where we are now.  In Waterford there has been an increase of 29% in Garda numbers between 2011 and September of this year.  This is hugely welcome.  Their presence has certainly been felt in Waterford.  The work they have done throughout the pandemic has been exemplary, which I would like on the record of the House.  The increase in numbers presents it own challenges, however, with regard to space constraints and the facilities available to garda&iacute; and civilian staff.  I am sure this is reflected in many parts of the State.  In Waterford, which I know best, space is certainly at a premium in Ballybricken Garda station.  Now is the time to focus on the next phase of investment and development of the force.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John Cummins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=JohnCummins&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Waterford city is home to the divisional headquarters for Waterford, Carlow and Kilkenny.  While the station was state-of-the-art when it was opened over 20 years ago, further investment is needed to expand on the existing site, perhaps over the former labour exchange, an old building that the Garda occupies but which is in need of significant upgrade and expansion works.  Otherwise, perhaps the solution is the construction of a new substation on the outskirts of the city to house some of the divisional units and equipment that are currently on the constrained site.  The latter would probably be a more appropriate use, given the projected population growth in the national planning framework.  Given the fact that the current plan runs from 2016 to 2021, early in the new year would be an opportune time to have a debate on the new capital plan for investment in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I know that responsibility for Garda stations straddles both the OPW and the Department of Justice.  I ask the Leader to organise a debate on this early in the new year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#K00200"><p>Yesterday evening on the six o'clock news we heard a report from a secondary school in Carlow.  The people behind the story need to be given an opportunity to explain themselves.  I was absolutely horrified as a former teacher to think anybody would go into a room of young women and talk to them about their dress and sexualise them on the basis of their dress.  The principal of the school involved has issued a statement, and the Department of Education needs to provide a full report on exactly what was said.  I cannot imagine how a young girl in that school is feeling today, questioning herself on her dress.  This goes back to the likes of young women being told they were raped because they were wearing a particular type of clothing.  It is just wrong.  It should not have happened, if it did, so we need a full report on it.</p> <p>I support Senator Wall in his comments this morning on the Defence Forces and Defence Forces pay.  As a former president of an ICTU-affiliated union, we need to hear ICTU come out and support the special status of the Defence Forces.  I recall from my time in trade unionism that pay differentials were a huge issue.  While the Defence Forces are currently prevented from being members of ICTU, ICTU needs to come out and formally support them, and I am making that call today.  It is vitally important that the lowest paid workers in the public service are given an opportunity.  We should not have heard at the weekend that pay talks were ongoing.  The Leader has tried to contact me on this already and we can talk about it later today.</p> <p>I second Senator Mullen's amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#K00300"><p>Today, 25 November, is the UN's International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women.  The UN says violence against women and girls is one of the most widespread, persistent and devastating human rights violations in our world today.  It remains largely unreported due to the impunity, silence, stigma and shame that surrounds it.  In general terms, violence against women and girls manifests itself in physical, sexual and psychological abuse.  This includes everything from rape to intimidation, harassment, human trafficking and female genital mutilation.  One in three women experiences physical or sexual violence in her lifetime, quite frequently from an intimate partner.</p> <p>In the Covid-19 pandemic domestic violence has increased dramatically.  In my constituency of Dublin Central, the Garda has reported a 100% increase in the number of reports of domestic violence, and that is just the domestic violence that is being reported.  In our Ireland of today, violence against girls, young women and women of all ages includes domestic abuse and the image-based sexual abuse that took place on a mass scale last week with the release of more than 6,000 images.  Then today we are talking about the events in a school down the country.  However, it is wrong of us to demonise or call out one school.  We miss the point if we do that.  Whatever exactly happened in that instance masks what is happening generally in our society.  We have schools all over the country telling girls that they must wear skirts and not trousers, that they must wear their jumpers over their shirts because their bras might be noticed or that they cannot wear Lycra exercise clothing because it would reveal the shape of their bodies.  That is all wrong.  It forces all the responsibility on young girls at a very impressionable age for adult men's thoughts.  That is wrong.  It is a failure of our society.  When we fail girls and young women, we fail our society.  We must all, therefore, on this day and every day call for and promote gender equality and call for the criminalisation of any form of gender violence or abuse.  We must all stand up for young girls and young women and gender equality for all our citizens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#K00400"><p>I welcome the news this week of the announcement that an application has been put forward by Limerick Institute of Technology, LIT, and Athlone Institute of Technology, AIT, to become a technological university.  It is really welcome news for the region - the mid-west and the midlands - and for Tipperary.  We have two sections of LIT, one in Thurles and one in Clonmel.  It is really important for a region such as Tipperary that we have a university in a town such as Clonmel.  It brings so many advantages.  I really hope that in a number of months the same will happen in Waterford and Carlow as well, and that an application will go forward for the two institutes of technology there to become a technological university.  I encourage the Leader to ask the Minister with responsibility for higher education to come to the Seanad to speak on this issue.  In Clonmel the university is coming to Kickham Barracks, which has been closed for six years.  The barracks is in the centre of town, and the new university will see extra students come in.  There are 14,000 students in the two institutes of technology combined, but the new university will accommodate up to 1,000 students in Clonmel.  That will have huge implications for a town the size of Clonmel.  I ask the Leader to ask the Minister to come before the House to make a statement on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#K00500"><p>I wish to reflect on third level education.  There is a lot of talk about what will happen when students go back to college, if they go back after Christmas.  Third level educators and the staff and teachers have been left in a grey area as to how they are to teach.  They have been left in the grey a few times already this year, and that cannot happen again.  I agree with what IFUT has said, that there needs to be a clear, agreed process as to how to conduct teaching and lectures for the new year.</p> <p>While the student experience is valuable, safety must be paramount, and it would be possibly more helpful for the Minister to give teachers clarity on whether or not they will be online or offline so they do not find in January that they have wasted December preparing for in-room teaching while they will have to adapt to online teaching again.  I am also acutely aware of the number of students who are perhaps sitting at home alone in their bedrooms trying to study and the deep impact that is having on them.  I know it is very hard to give clarity in these very difficult times, but we have workers who are trying to adapt to what will come, so I ask the Minister to offer clarity in that area.</p> <p>I wish to refer very quickly to the Debenhams workers.  Last night there was an attempt at an overnight grab for stock in the former Limerick and Tralee stores.  The workers and their supporters successfully held back the liquidators' attempts to access the stock.  I know this has been raised a few times here, but the Debenhams workers have been holding the picket line for seven months trying to get a redundancy agreement.  They met with the Taoiseach last week and were hoping for some resolution to this issue.  I would posit that if the buying of clothes is not deemed essential during lockdown, this grab attempt on clothes is also not essential.  I wish to put on record that these workers are still waiting for a response from the Taoiseach, and the attempt last night would perhaps suggest that it is not as forthcoming as it was implied to them that it would be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#L00100"><p>I wish to start by agreeing with Senators Wall and Craughwell on addressing the terms and conditions affecting those in the Defence Forces, who are the worst paid members of the public service.  A role has to be found for PDFORRA as part of the discussion, because this issue has being going on for far too long and it is important that it is addressed.</p> <p>I agree with Senator Mullen around the need for debate on the future of the technological university sector.  I do not know whether it is appropriate to have it right now but certainly in following on from Senator Ahearn's comments, it is essential.  The motion regarding the creation of the Munster technological university, which is scheduled to be taken without debate, is extremely welcome.  l look forward to the south east having a technological university in the near future but it would be important to have a major debate on the future of our higher education sector in this House, including the role of lifelong learning.</p> <p>Members will be aware that the Environmental Protection Agency, EPA, published a quite comprehensive and worrying report this morning on the state of the Irish environment.  There are many aspects that we could debate and discuss in this House but I particularly want to focus on questions around air quality.  It is clear that there continue to be problems in respect of good air quality in Ireland.  At Government level, there is a commitment to introducing clean air legislation and that needs to be fast-tracked.  Given that there is supposed to be a ban in place on the burning of smoky coals, I looked at the statistics for last weekend.  The WHO has stated that safe levels are those of 15 particles per 1 million or fewer.  In Enniscorthy last weekend, the levels were 94.76 particles per 1 million, and in Wexford, where there has been a ban supposedly in place for many years, the levels were 122.34 particles per 1 million.  This is replicated all over the country.  The reality is that we do not have clean air in this country and it is having a serious impact upon those with respiratory illnesses and diseases.  The clean air legislation needs to be introduced as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#L00200"><p>I welcome the great funding that was announced yesterday as part of the just transition fund, which amounts to over &euro;27.8 million.  It is wonderful to see a project in my own home town of Ballinasloe getting funding of nearly half a million euro for remote working hubs.  The just transition process follows on from job losses, climate change and us changing the types of industry that we have in Ireland.  More than 200 jobs were lost locally in Shannonbridge, more jobs were lost in Lanesborough, and there were also jobs losses in Aptar, so it is great to see this investment, which will bring jobs and people to work the middle of Ballinasloe town and increase footfall in that area.</p> <p>I also welcome the wonderful funding that has been announced for Roscommon, with greenways being funded, the bog rail train routes being taken off in Cloontuskert and around by Shannonbridge, and action plans being put in place for Shannonbridge.  All of this is to support people who are seeking to re-skill and retrain and also to have opportunities for work that they did not have previously.</p> <p>I would also like to follow on separately to Senator Ahearn in welcoming the announcements of the plans for the Athlone and Letterkenny institutes of technology.  That new technological university in Athlone will really be transformative for our region.  As Athlone is only 20 minutes away from Ballinasloe, it will have a huge impact in east Galway, as it will in Tipperary.  It will have a wide catchment area, and we look forward to having excellent research available and ready to imbed in industry and attract investment into the region of east Galway and into Roscommon.  It will be fantastic to have a technological university on our doorstep.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#L00300"><p>I wish to speak on a few issues this morning.  First, I request the Leader of the House to ask the Minister for Foreign Affairs for an update on the Brexit negotiations.  Every single day we get a drip feed of new crises from Tony Connolly from RT&Eacute;.  As the news reporting seems to be the best source of news we can get as Members at present, it would be really good if we could get a Minister into the Houses to talk us through what is actually happening, and what will happen on 1 January 2021.  As someone from the Border region, I have more than a vested interest in the negotiations.</p> <p>I also wish to reiterate what my colleagues said about what basically amounts to gender shaming.  We had a great discussion yesterday in the Seanad on gender-based and domestic violence, and I am sick of women's bodies being used against them as a tool or a reason to put them down or to abuse them.  Women are being abused and harassed because they can be, and there are no laws in place to prevent this.  Thankfully yesterday the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, reiterated her desire to have online harassment legislation passed through the House before the end of the year.  It is therefore very important that we grow up in this country and cop on.  Women's bodies have been there for quite a long time and we need to grow with them.</p> <p>My final point is to invite the relevant Minister to come to the House to discuss car insurance and the cost of it, particularly for young people.  For young people in rural Ireland there is no public transport and they can no longer even car-share to get to college or wherever they need to be.  The cost of car insurance is very prohibitive for young people, and therefore I would welcome a debate on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#L00400"><p>This morning we heard the unfortunate news from the Environmental Protection Agency that there are significant risks to the environment throughout the country.  We have been made aware now that there are particular identifiable aspects that are causing damage to the environment and to water quality in particular.  One of the references made by the chief executive, Laura Burke, on RT&Eacute;'s "Morning Ireland" programme this morning was to the discharge of untreated sewage into rivers and waterways throughout the country.  This is an issue that really has to be addressed and which is particularly close to my heart, because in D&uacute;n Laoghaire, there is a pumping station on the west pier of the harbour, which removes the waste from the broader south Dublin area and pumps it into the treatment plant at Poolbeg.  In the ordinary course of events, it works very efficiently and removes it but if there is a high rainfall event, that pumping system becomes overwhelmed.  Because of a Victorian sewer system, the run-offs from the streets and gardens etc. go into the same courses as the sewage.  This means the attenuation tanks at the west pier cannot cope with it, with the result that if there is a very heavy rainfall event, there is an overflow of untreated sewage into Dublin Bay.  Dublin Bay is a UNESCO biosphere, a special area of conservation and a tremendously important recreational amenity for all people in Dublin, including those in D&uacute;n Laoghaire.  In recent times we have seen an increase in the incidences of bathing water bans and overflows into Dublin Bay at Seapoint and the west pier, which are unacceptable.  We need to provide funding to rehabilitate the sewage system in the D&uacute;n Laoghaire and Rathdown areas to ensure that when there is rainfall, the associated run-off water is separated and put directly and safely into the sea, rather than putting it into a sewage system unnecessarily, resulting in damage to the water quality in Dublin Bay and the environment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#L00500"><p>Everyone in the country is eagerly looking forward to the easing of level 5 restrictions next week, the reopening of retail and the return of many aspects of normal life as we know it.  The Irish people deserve great credit for the huge effort and sacrifice that they have put in, and thankfully we are seeing the results of this, with the figures falling day by day.  However, I have been intrigued recently with the debate around the wearing of face masks as opposed to face shields or visors.  Many people out there are confused as to which is the best option.  The wearing of visors is particularly commonplace in the hospitality sector, and indeed across many other sectors including offices etc.  Some people have contacted me to seek guidance on which is the best face covering to wear.  There has perhaps been a lack of guidance from NPHET and the HSE on this issue.  It is timely, as we prepare for the reopening of as many aspects of our society as possible next week, that NPHET and the HSE provide clear guidance on the wearing of visors as opposed to face masks.  Irish people, by and large, like to do the best thing all the time and it is important that there is no confusion out there.  If visors are not as effective in ensuring the safety of those wearing them and those around them, then clear advice should be given in that regard.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I would be grateful if the Leader would ask the HSE and NPHET to give that clear guidance in view of the reopening of the country or, hopefully, as many parts of it as possible next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#M00200"><p>We have serial advisers in the present company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#M00300"><p>I wish to raise in the House something that has come to my attention in the last few months.  The fact is that we need to do more for our old people.  They are probably suffering the most.  I am receiving telephone calls from many old people who have major concerns.  Some of them live in cold houses.  They have been in contact with me since August about it, but nothing has been done.  Some of them want home help, but they are not physically disabled.  To get home help on mental grounds one has to be completely dishevelled, falling apart and not dressing or feeding oneself.  The standard has to be very low and there does not appear to be any formula for getting home help to prevent somebody getting into that state.</p> <p>The main cause of their problems is loneliness.  We must start to recognise loneliness as a justified reason to provide home help if there are no family members and people receive no visitors.  I believe some of the people are reaching out to me because they are lonely and not for any other reason.  I do not know if my colleagues concur with me, but I believe a massive cohort of old people have been left on their own and are lonely.  The concept of home help must be re-examined because mental health is as important as physical health.  It can cost the State up to &euro;3,000 per month to have an old person in a home.  If one paid a home help worker &euro;30 per hour, that would give the person 100 hours per month and 25 hours per week of home help.  Many old people do not want to be in old folks' homes.  They want to be at home and independent, but they need some home help.  They might need it just for company or to do shopping and the like.</p> <p>I would like the Minister of State with responsibility for old people to come to the Chamber so we can have a debate focused on our elders.  Traditionally, old people were treated as the most revered and wisest people, but we are not doing that as a society.  I feel very strongly about this.  The run-up to Christmas has been a very difficult time for old people as well because they have been confined to their houses and are not allowed to move around.  When the State provides a house for an elderly person because the person is on a State pension, the owner of the house gets a long-term lease and is paid for 20 years.  That money is guaranteed for that property owner, regardless of what he or she does to the house.  It is not good enough that old people in their 80s are ringing me to tell me their houses are freezing and nobody is doing anything about it.  The local authorities say it is not their fault, but the owner's fault.  We must refocus and talk about old people more frequently in the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#M00400"><p>We saw the photographs yesterday from Kent when queues of trucks built up after the French started a trial of post-Brexit checks.  Lorries seeking to cross the English Channel were forced to stop in long lines as they tried to approach the Eurotunnel entrance.  There have been warnings of queues of up to 7,000 lorries post Brexit.  The French were rehearsing post-Brexit immigration procedures.  The UK is used as a land bridge and it is now clear that, deal or no deal, there will be queues and delays in places such as the Eurotunnel approach.</p> <p>As we look at the use of alternative routes and ports, we must ensure there is adequate supply chain capacity post Brexit.  My area of Galway is a centre for medical devices and IT.  We need to know if the supply chains of raw materials inwards and finished goods outwards are in place.  We must ensure there is sufficient capacity in our transport network.  I ask for a debate with the Minister for Transport, the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment or the Minister for Foreign Affairs on our ports, airports and the land bridge in the UK post Brexit.  This is a crucial issue as we approach the final deadline.  As I said, deal or no deal, I believe this will continue to be an issue.  Some of those 7,000 lorries will be Irish, carrying Irish goods or importing raw materials for use in manufacturing in this country.  Irish jobs are at stake.  I realise the Government, the Departments and the various Ministers have done a great deal of work on this area, but I ask for a debate on this important subject in the coming weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#M00500"><p>First, I join Senator Dolan in saying what a great day yesterday was for our region and the towns in the midlands.  It is a significant amount of money.  I spoke to many people yesterday and, like Senator Dolan, I was delighted to be involved in seeking those projects from Ballinasloe to Ballyforan to Lanesborough and throughout parts of Roscommon and east Galway and the adjoining counties.  It is a sign of a Government delivering what it promised it would do, which is important for people.  We need it there.</p> <p>I support Senator McGreehan's call for a debate on the cost of insurance.  Will the Leader also invite the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sports and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, to the House to discuss the arts and entertainment businesses?  I constantly make the case that they will be the last in line to return to business because of the nature of their businesses.  Whatever happens with vaccines, and we hope that will work out and we can get back to some form of normality as quickly as possible, the arts and entertainment sectors will be at the end of the line in terms of getting back to business.  They have worries.  Obviously, the &euro;350 payment is very important, and they would like that to continue.  These sectors also have great expense with regard to transport.  If one is an engineer or in a band, or one is preparing a stand for a performance, one cannot have a vehicle that has a 03 D or 03 RN registration.  It must be from 2018, 2019 or 2020.  The cost of vehicles to these sectors is enormous.  We must take another look at these sectors.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister to the House for a debate on how we could, perhaps, further improve any payments we make to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#M00600"><p>I again raise the issue of the Public Health (Alcohol) Act 2018.  This was debated at great length in the House a number of years ago.  This month, a number of provisions of the Act were commenced in law.  There was great division among Members and great debates when the Bill was going through the House.  Ultimately, the Bill was passed.  One matter every Member agreed on was minimum unit pricing, but that is the one aspect of the Act that has not been commenced.  This week, Tesco is selling cans of alcohol for 70 cent per can, which is &euro;14 for a slab.  I cannot understand why the provision dealing with minimum unit pricing in the Public Health (Alcohol) Act 2018 cannot be implemented at this stage, particularly when we have a lockdown and people cannot travel further than 5 km.  For a long time, one could not travel from county to county.  We were waiting for Northern Ireland and the South to agree on a date to introduce minimum unit pricing together.  It has been a great success in Scotland, so for the life of me I cannot understand it.  This was a contentious issue and one that, in every Member's view, would bring realism to the price of alcohol.</p> <p>Why has it not been introduced at this stage?  The Government should treat it as a priority, but obviously it is not a priority.  It is also not a priority for Dr. Holohan, even though he said it was at the time.  I ask that minimum unit pricing be introduced.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#M00700"><p>My request is that the Seanad receive an update on the status of the provision of universal period products.  It is over a year since a cross-party motion was passed in the D&aacute;il calling for the provision of free period products in all public buildings, including schools, universities, direct provision centres, hospitals and prisons.  Yesterday, Scotland became the first country to provide universal access, and I hope Ireland will follow as soon as possible.  Some measures have been taken at local authority level, in Dublin City Council and by my colleague, Deputy Ward, in South Dublin County Council when he was mayor.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Period poverty is very real.  Yes, part of addressing period poverty is addressing the wider issue of poverty and deprivation in this country.  Period poverty is also the outworking of our attitudes towards women and girls.  Nobody bats an eye when they go into a bathroom and there is a toilet roll provided.  In fact, people are very quick to point out if it is absent.  However, despite the fact that periods are a normal bodily function, we have a situation whereby it is seen as shameful and something that should be hidden away.  We see tampons slipped up the sleeve, discreet packaging and adverts that show blue ink to avoid embarrassment.  The provision of period products in public buildings would help to break down the stigma, and it must go hand in hand with an education module in schools that is inclusive of all students.  We have seen what happens when one separates students, as in the Carlow situation.</p><p>A study conducted by Plan International found that six out of ten young women reported feeling embarrassed about having their period and 50% find it difficult to afford the products.  That situation has been exacerbated during the pandemic.  I give credit to Homeless Period Ireland and its amazing volunteers who ensured that period products were still delivered to the direct provision centres, food banks and homeless shelters despite their drop-off points being closed during the restrictions.  I request that we get an update on where the motion is going and when we will have universal period products for all of our women and girls.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#N00200"><p>I concur with the comments made by Senators Dolan and Murphy about the significant funding that was received yesterday, in the midlands in particular, through the just transition fund.  As much as &euro;5 million was given to specific projects in my own county of Longford and multiple millions of euro was given to others that cross over the area.</p> <p>I concur with the comments that Senator Burke made about minimum unit pricing of alcohol and the abundance of cheap alcohol that is available at a time when all of the pubs are closed.  There is talk of reopening different parts of society.  According to media reports in recent days, public houses, which are regulated areas, will not reopen while we allow off-licence sales and, as the Senator Burke said, the sale and consumption of cheap alcohol in an unregulated area, which is causing problems.  There is a huge difference between wet pubs in Dublin city centre and those in rural Longford where I am from.  If we are not going to allow the pubs to open, which I believe we should, because they are regulated, they are licence holders, and it is up to them to enforce the restrictions that are put in place, none should open.  We have seen what happened previously, and we drove alcohol consumption underground.  We need to learn from that.  I ask that that would be taken on board in the discussions over the next few days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#N00300"><p>I know that colleagues will join with me in expressing sympathies to the Senator on the sad loss of his mother.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#N00400"><p>I will first address the proposed amendment to the Order of Business and ask for the guidance of the Senator concerned.  I can offer two choices.  I cannot accept his amendment today only because I do not have a Minister available for a 45-minute debate.  I can propose that No. 1 on the agenda be withdrawn and rescheduled for next Wednesday or I can ask the Senator to allow No. 1 to go ahead without debate and we schedule a wider debate on technological universities for next Wednesday, as has been requested by other Members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#N00500"><p>I thank the Leader for the options and I am happy to withdraw my amendment on that basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#N00600"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#N00700"><p>I thank Senator Mullen.  If the schedule that I will issue this afternoon does not have it listed, then I will make sure to add it on.</p><p>I thank colleagues for the number of issues that have been raised today.  The Tusla report that was raised gives rise to concerns, particularly when the concerns themselves are being expressed and shared by Tusla.  It would be very apt to invite in the Minister for a debate on Tusla, its operation, its planned progress and what issues that it might have, so I will request that today.</p><p>Based on what Senator Mullen raised, I will ask for a debate.  From the number of responses that he has received, he can see that there are still very strong emotions on this debate.  I do not think ignoring the facts does justice and service to people's views, so I will again ask the Minister for Health to schedule that debate in the coming weeks.</p><p>In response to Senators Ward and Craughwell, I rang their offices and apologise that I did not get them yesterday evening.  Progress was only made at Cabinet yesterday morning to advance those talks.  I know that information was leaked before the Cabinet made its decision yesterday morning, but all interested parties received an invitation yesterday evening to sit around the table.  I am not sure whether people are starting from a different place than other interested agencies, but I do know that every representative body will be sitting around the table and I very much anticipate that they will express their views and the concerns of their members to the negotiators at the table.  I genuinely wish them a successful outcome for all of our public services.  I know people are coming and starting from different points from a wage, pay and terms of conditions perspective.  I hope that they reach a good leap pad, as it were, for the end of it so that there is a good positive outcome for all of them.</p><p>In response to Senator Ruane, a number of colleagues raised the issue and the report in <i>The Irish Times</i>yesterday morning detailing the awful incidences.  I wrote yesterday to the Minister and there was a Commencement matter this morning where a Minister gave a response to the effect that the Minister is quite happy to have a debate.  I expect to get a date sooner rather than later for a debate on prisoners' conditions, and as soon as I do I will let the Senator know.</p><p>Many colleagues - interestingly, mostly women - mentioned that today is the international day for ending discrimination and gender-based violence towards women.  I am sometimes dismayed that we have to fight tooth and nail for every little step forward just to be equal in a world where there more of us than the people who seem to deprive us of the equality of opportunity.  I will go straight to the end to Senator Boylan's request.  I read with interest that Scotland yesterday was the first country, and indeed I hope it is not the last, to end period poverty.  The fact is that we have to ask for paraphernalia to be put in a loo for something that happens naturally to a women, and Senator Boylan is absolutely right that if anybody went into a loo and there was no toilet roll, there would be blue murder, so it is beyond me why we must fight for something that is so fundamental to our monthly lives.  Enough nonsense and interjections that we are busy doing something else; this is a basic human right for a woman.  It is not something that a woman can put off or can say it will not happen, although, thankfully, it stops at some point in a woman's life.  However, for the vast majority of a woman's adult life, from about 12 or 13 years of age until she is in her 50s, it is something we have to deal with, so get over it and just put them in every public place, in every toilet, in every university and in every workplace.  It should not have to be begged for.</p><p>I will ask the lads for their help.  We stand up in this House as women and talk about the fact that we constantly have to fight arguments over body shaming, discrimination, gender-based equality, and access to healthcare, education and equality in the boardroom.  The only way it is ever going to change is if we all want it to change and we have to stop begging for it.  It is a basic human right to have equality of opportunity to access every level of service from the State, and it should be something that all men should want for their womenfolk and family members as much as women want for themselves.  Help us out, please.  That is definitely a debate.  We started it yesterday and it is rescheduled with the other Minister the week after next.  I invite the people who did not get access to speaking time yesterday to access that opportunity on the next occasion.</p><p>I will ask the Minister for Justice to come in after Christmas for a debate on the upgrade of the capital plan for the Garda.  I will also schedule the debate for the technological universities next week.</p><p>Senator Hoey raised the issue of the safe return of third level education.  That is something we can bring up when the Minister is in the House next week to debate higher education.  What we need is consistency, and it is not just that sector that seeks consistency but all of us.  We all just want to know what the plans are.  I know we have to change plans in terms of how the virus reacts, but we would like to know where we will be in six weeks and six months.  I think that will arise from our debate on Thursday, but also, obviously, from the announcement that Government will make arising from the NPHET meeting today.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The just transition funding yesterday was very welcome.  I wish some of it was coming to my own area, it has given such cheer.  It is a real sign that Ireland is changing and we recognise that we need more than a passive engagement to result in the changes required.  It was very important to receive that amount of money yesterday.  </p><p>Others raised the EPA and its chairperson's interview earlier on "Morning Ireland".  There is no doubt that this country has serious environmental challenges such as air and water pollution and the surges into our sea from leaks.  It is nearly like Groundhog Day.  The EPA gives the same report every year and we never seem to make any progress.  It definitely needs a debate and I will look for one from the Minister today.  </p><p>The House will debate reopening Ireland on Thursday.  I do not know when either Professor Nolan or Dr. Holohan said that wearing visors was not safe.  I will get the text of that.  It might be worth reading it into the record here on Thursday, to note precisely when they did say that.  It is timely given that we are all hopeful that hospitality and restaurants and pubs will reopen in some shape or form in what hopefully will be a jolly season between now and Christmas.  </p><p>In response to Senator Garvey, I have mentioned the "L" word a few times in recent weeks over Covid.  I do not think loneliness is just an issue that pertains to older people.  It might be more prevalent to older people but loneliness and people's well-being is something we need a debate on.  I will write to the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, who has responsibility for well-being and ask him to come to the House for a debate sooner rather than later.  It is far more obvious under Covid but there are people who, even under normal circumstances, do not see one person from one Sunday to the next and only do so when they go to mass, perhaps with the exception of someone delivering meals on wheels.  Some of our older people do not see anybody from one end of the week to the other and it is not fair.  There are also many who are in the midst of lots of people who still experience loneliness.  I will ask the Minister for a debate on well-being.</p><p>Several Members raised Brexit and its ill effects, including transport links.  Next Tuesday lunchtime, the House will start a debate on Brexit.  There is no time limit.  Everyone can speak for as long as they like.  Next Thursday, there is seven hours to deal with Committee and Report Stages of the Brexit Bill.  We will definitely have an update before then but everyone will have an opportunity to talk about the ill effects that are coming.  We all hope there is a deal but even then we cannot get excited about that because that will have no positive outcome.  No deal is less positive but there is no upside to Brexit.  That debate will be significant.</p><p>On the public health alcohol Bill, I do not know why Northern Ireland and the Republic have not done what they said they would, that is, to work together to provide all-island pricing in unison.  We seem to be experiencing a number of difficulties working on an all-Ireland basis in recent months which is an awful pity.  I will write to the Minister and send the Senator a written response when I hear back. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#O00200"><p>May I ask the Leader about the arts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#O00300"><p>I will ask them to come in and speak on the new pilot scheme for the universal payment to people in the arts industry.  It would give the Minister a good opportunity to share her plans with us.  I will write today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#O00400"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#O00500"><p>Senator Mullen has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 1 be taken with a 45 minute debate."  He has indicated that he wishes to withdraw the amendment and the Leader has indicated that she will organise a debate next week on the issue No. 1 will be taken today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.84" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.85" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#O00700">Technological Universities Act 2018 (Section 36)(Appointed Day) Order 2020: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#O00800"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft:   	Technological Universities Act 2018(Section 36) (Appointed Day) Order 2020, copies of which have been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 28 October 2020. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.87" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.88" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.45 p.m. and resumed at 1 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.89" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Q00100">Planning and Development Bill 2020: Order for Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.90" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p></p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Q00300"><p>I move: "That Second Stage be taken today."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.92" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.93" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Q00500">Planning and Development Bill 2020: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.94" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Q00700"><p>I thank Senators for facilitating the introduction of the Planning and Development Bill 2020 and the urgent passage of this important legislation through the Houses of the Oireachtas.  For this reason, I will be requesting, in due course, that this House considers a motion to enable the President to sign the Bill earlier than would be routine.</p> <p>I am bringing forward the Planning and Development Bill 2020 as a matter of urgency in light of the present Covid-19 pandemic and to ensure that the necessary protections are in place to safeguard the operation of the planning and building control systems.  The purpose of the Planning and Development Bill 2020 is twofold.  Its first purpose is to amend section 11(3)(b) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 in respect of the mandatory requirement to hold public meetings with regard to proposed development plans.  Its second purpose is to allow the Government to make orders, during the period of the Covid-19 pandemic, which would extend certain statutory periods applying under the Planning and Development Acts and the Building Control Acts.</p> <p>Before I address the rationale behind the Bill and specific details of it, I would like to address the matter of my request to an Ceann Comhairle, as Chair of the D&aacute;il Business Committee, to waive the requirement for pre-legislative scrutiny of the general scheme of the proposed Planning and Development Bill 2020.  I had sought this waiver due to the urgent nature of the proposed Bill, which I am bringing forward in response to the present Covid-19 pandemic.  However, last Tuesday I was advised that I could secure an early time slot to commence the Bill's Second Stage today, Wednesday, 25 November, if I introduced the Bill through the Seanad.  I was happy to do this, not only to progress the Bill as soon as possible, but also to allow me to fulfil a promise I made to Members of the Seanad just a few short weeks ago to initiate Bills in this Chamber. </p> <p>The acceptance of an early time slot for this urgent Bill necessitated the publication of the Bill for the Seanad last Wednesday, which unfortunately rendered the potential for pre-legislative scrutiny by the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage unfeasible in these exceptional, time-sensitive circumstances.  In acknowledgment of this, and in accordance with Seanad Standing Order 149(2)(i), I confirm that the reason that pre-legislative consideration did not take place under Seanad Standing Order 143 is the time-sensitive nature of this emergency Bill resulting from the pandemic's potential to negatively impact on the operation and integrity of the planning and building control systems, which required this exceptional accelerated approach.</p> <p>Having regard to the above, I assure the House that the decision to commence the Bill in the Seanad was not intended in any way, shape or form to circumvent consultation with the joint committee, but rather was motivated by the desire to have this emergency Covid-19-related legislation enacted as soon as possible.  However, I apologise to the Chair and to the members of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage for any confusion caused by the urgency of this approach and for the resulting effects on pre-legislative scrutiny procedures.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Today, I am asking Senators to pass the Planning and Development Bill 2020.<br/><br/>The Bill is being brought forward as a matter of urgency due to the Covid-19 pandemic to ensure that the necessary protections are in place to safeguard the operation of the planning and building control systems.  In particular, this Bill will ensure that the integrity of the public participation elements and decision-making processes of these systems are protected.  Local authorities play a critical role in facilitating construction activity, including housing construction, through a range of responsibilities, including granting permission under the Planning and Developments Acts and granting fire safety certificates and disability access certificates under the Building Control Acts.  It is therefore essential for our economy and our collective aim of housing delivery that these services remain functioning and open.  In this context, every effort is being made to ensure that the planning and building control systems can continue to remain open, with appropriate accommodations and taking into account public health advice.<br/><br/>Notwithstanding the present Covid-19 level 5 national restrictions on travel, it is important to note that the planning and building control systems remain open for business.  In particular, the public participation elements of the planning system have been recognised as an essential service in SI 448 of 2020, introduced by the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, which implements these level 5 restrictions.  Attending the offices of a planning authority or An Bord Plean&aacute;la to engage in a statutory planning process, including inspecting the file, making an observation or submission to a development plan process or inspecting a site notice, is deemed to be a reasonable excuse for travelling or moving during these level-5 travel restrictions.  <br/><br/>My Department continues to work with the planning and building control authorities to ensure that these systems, which are vital to the delivery of housing and infrastructure, remain open.  Local authority public offices and the offices of An Bord Plean&aacute;la are open to the greatest extent possible, subject to adherence to HSE guidelines on physical distancing and any local arrangements on managed access.  Furthermore, systems including the building control management system, can be accessed remotely over the local authority network; while in the case of the planning system, established systems are in place that enable people to view planning applications and submissions online.  <br/><br/>As a direct response to the potential for Covid-19-related restrictions to have an impact on public participation in the planning application processes, the planning and development regulations were amended in May with the introduction of SI 180, the Planning and Development Act 2000 (Section 38) Regulations 2020, to require all planning authorities to upload all planning application documentation online for public viewing within five days of receiving the material, save for exceptional circumstances.  My Department and I will continue to keep matters related to planning and building control regimes under review, in consultation with planning authorities.<br/><br/>It is hoped that the safeguarding provisions in section 3 of this Bill are never used.  However, if there is a critical deterioration in staffing levels due to infections in one or more planning or building control authorities or in the event that the public at large or particular groups of the public may not generally be capable of engagement with the planning system due to the introduction of more restrictive measures that may prevent the public, for example, from seeing site notices or attending planning offices or meetings, it may be necessary to use the proposed measures in section 3 to ensure the integrity of the planning and building control system is maintained throughout the pandemic.<br/><br/>I will now outline the main provisions of the Bill.  As stated earlier, the purpose of the Planning and Development Bill 2020 is twofold.  First, the Bill proposes to amend section 11(3)(b) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 in respect of the mandatory requirement to hold public meetings concerning a proposed development plan.  Second, it will allow the Government to make orders, during the period of the Covid-19 pandemic, which would extend certain statutory periods applying under the Planning and Development Acts and the Building Control Acts.  <br/><br/>The Long Title of the Bill outlines the aims and policy context in which the proposed measures to safeguard the operation of the planning and building control systems are being introduced in light of the present Covid-19 pandemic and the associated restrictions required to contain the disease.<br/><br/>There are four sections in the Bill.  Section 1 provides a definition for &quot;principal Act&quot;, which means the Planning and Development Act 2000.  Section 2 amends section 11(3)(b) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 to replace the mandatory requirement to hold public meetings regarding a proposed development plan with a more flexible requirement for planning authorities to consult with members of the public in such a manner as it considers appropriate and to invite written submissions from members of the public regarding a proposed development plan.  This may include the holding of a public meeting, newspaper notices, written submissions or online communication or both.<br/><br/>The proposed amendment will allow the planning authority to take whatever steps it deems necessary to ensure the public are consulted in compliance with the principles of the Aarhus Convention, which include public participation in environmental decision making.  This measure is required immediately to allow planning authorities to adapt public consultation procedures given the present restrictions on the holding of public gatherings during the pandemic.  If this amendment is not made, such restrictions will delay the progression of development plans during the pandemic.  The amendment is also in line with the modernisation agenda for the planning system to increase online activity and ensure continued flexibility in communicating details of draft development plans to the public and it will therefore be a permanent amendment.<br/><br/>Regarding the proposal in section 2 of the Bill, and following a submission from my colleague in government, the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, and as raised by Deputy Matthews, Chairman of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage, I wish to inform the House that I will be seeking to introduce a Government amendment to section 2 of the Bill on Committee Stage here in the Seanad on Monday to confirm that section 11(3)(<i>b</i>) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 will require the planning authority to hold either a public meeting or an online public meeting in respect of a proposed development plan.  The Bill, as proposed, had required the planning authority to &quot;consult with members of the public in such manner&quot; as the planning authority considered appropriate, &quot;which may include the holding of a public meeting&quot;.  The Government amendment will ensure, for the avoidance of any doubt, that there will always be some format of public meeting under section 11(3)(b) in respect of a proposed development plan, either by way of a public meeting attended by the public in person or an online public meeting.  That amendment will be introduced on Committee Stage on Monday.  <br/><br/>Section 3, regarding emergency periods, would allow the Government to make orders, during the Covid-19 pandemic, which would extend certain statutory periods applying under the Planning and Development Acts and the Building Control Acts.  This contingency measure is also urgently required to provide an essential legislative safeguard, which can be invoked as necessary to ensure that public participation elements of the planning regime, as well as certain decision-making and enforcement systems of the building control regime, are not compromised if further waves of Covid-19 may necessitate a further period of stay-at-home travel restrictions or may critically impact on the operation of individual authorities.<br/><br/>A core principle of the planning and development system is that of public participation and the assurance that planning is conducted in a manner which affords a high level of confidence in the openness, fairness, professionalism and efficiency of the process.  This requires people to have the opportunity to participate in decisions being made at the strategic plan-making and individual planning application levels.  Public participation is also central to certain decision-making and enforcement systems of the building control regime.<br/><br/>In the absence of section 3 of this proposed Bill, if circumstances arose during the pandemic which impacted on the public participation elements and decision-making processes of the planning system, these circumstances could cause significant difficulties, including preventing compliance by authorities with requirements set out in law and raising the prospect of knock-on effects.  The possible consequences which might arise from these difficulties include the inability to operate statutory consultation periods, the inability to progress the making of development plans and deemed decisions, where decisions have not been made by the. appropriate authority.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They could also raise the prospect of financial penalties being applied against authorities for not making decisions within statutory time limits; judicial reviews of decisions where individuals contend that the process did not adhere to statute; where public offices close, the inability to view information and make submissions; where enforcement proceedings are about to be commenced or are ongoing, the time limits are a key issue; and undue benefit accruing to some people by automatic default or through the elapsing of observation, submission or enforcement timelines before an observer, respondent or indeed the authority has time to act.<br/><br/>The main provision in section 3 is modelled on the recently expended section 251A of the Planning and Development Act 2000.  Section 251A, in turn, was modelled on the existing section 251 provision within the Planning and Development Act, which applies each year for the Christmas period, when public offices are closed, whereby, when calculating an appropriate period or other time limit referred to in the Planning Act or regulations, the period between 24 December and 1 January, both days inclusive, shall be disregarded.  The recently expended section 251A of the Planning and Development Act 2000 introduced a similar disregard provision for statutory periods during the first lockdown earlier this year, in which case the Government order made under section 251A lasted for eight weeks, from the end of March up to 23 May 2020.<br/><br/>However, the proposed provision in the current Bill includes new flexibilities, which were not previously included.  More than one extension period order may be made within the confined operative period for this Bill, which is linked to the operation of Part 3 of the Health (Preservation and Protection and other Emergency Measures in the Public Interest) Act 2020, which now ends on 9 June 2021 following a resolution of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  Extension period orders, if required, can be applied to specific administrative areas of the country, as opposed to applying to the entire country.  The Government, at my request, may choose which statutory periods it requires to extend, rather than applying the extension to all periods under the planning Acts and the specified provisions of the Building Control Acts.<br/><br/>The proposed provisions in section 3 also introduce additional oversight of the Oireachtas, whereby any such order shall be laid before each House of the Oireachtas as soon as may be after it is made and, if a resolution annulling the order is passed by either House within the next 21 days on which that House sits after the order is laid before it, the order shall be annulled accordingly.<br/><br/>Similar to the provisions of the recently expended section 251A of the Planning and Development Act 2000, section 3 of the Bill requires that I, as Minister, shall consult the Minister for Health and request the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform prior to making a request to the Government to make an order specifying the period for which the order shall apply.<br/><br/>In making an order under section 3, the Government is required to have regard to the following principles and policies: the nature and potential impact of Covid-19 on individuals, society and the State; the need to eliminate or reduce the threat to public health of Covid-19; the policies and objectives of the Government relating to the protection of the public from Covid-19; the need to mitigate the adverse economic effects resulting from the spread of Covid-19 or the measures adopted to prevent its spread; and the need to eliminate or reduce the impact of Covid-19 and the measures adopted to prevent its spread on the effective operation of relevant enactments and the effective performance of functions under those enactments.<br/><br/>In the case of sections 4(4), 6 and 17(6) of the Building Control Act 1990, or any instrument thereunder, which concern the operation of the building control regulations, the Government shall not make an order unless it is also satisfied that the making of such order is in the public interest having regard to the need to ensure the effective operation of that Act and protect the health, safety and welfare of occupants of buildings.  In the case of the other enactments, which comprise the various Planning and Development Acts listed in section 3, the Government shall not make an order unless it is also satisfied that the making of such order is in the public interest having regard to the need to ensure the effective operation of such enactment<b></b>and proper planning and sustainable development.  These principles and policies, which the Government is required to consider before making an order, broadly mirror the principles and policies of the expended section 251A.  Section 4 provides the Short Title and collective citations to the Bill.<br/><br/>In addition to my detailed comments on the Planning and Development Bill, which is currently before the House, I also wish to inform the House that I will need to introduce further Government amendments as the Bill makes its way through the legislative process in the D&aacute;il.  Yesterday, the Government approved at Cabinet the priority drafting of modifications to the operation of the Residential Tenancies and Valuation Act 2020, which are being worked on by my officials and the Office of the Attorney General.  The aim is to continue but modify the operation of the temporary protections to tenants under the Act that we passed here in late July until 12 April 2021 while recognising and balancing the constitutionally protected rights of property owners.  An amendment will also be tabled to extend from 10 January 2021 to 12 April 2021 the provision under the Act of 2020 that proceedings before a Residential Tenancies Board, RTB, tribunal need not be held in public during the Covid-19 emergency period, with the aim of continuing the protection of the health and safety of participants in the proceedings and of RTB staff.<br/><br/>It is recognised by me, and I have stated it in this House previously, that a cohort of tenants are experiencing Covid-related economic difficulties for a second time this year as a result of the current lockdown.  A further cohort may face a negative financial impact for the first time on foot of Covid-19.  Low-income tenants are disproportionately employed in sectors that are severely affected by Covid-19, for example, in the hospitality and retail sectors, and are likely to face continued and particular strain.<br/><br/>The State continues to provide immediate support to families and individuals in private rented accommodation under the Department of Social Protection's rent supplement scheme.  The scheme provides short-term income support to eligible people living in private rented accommodation whose means are insufficient to meet their accommodation costs and who do not have accommodation available to them from any other source.  The scheme ensures that renters experiencing a temporary loss of employment during the Covid-19 emergency can continue to meet their rental commitments.  The Act of 2020 complements the provision of rent supplement and other State supports, such as the supplementary welfare allowance, the pandemic unemployment payment and the employment wage subsidy, by providing time and security for tenants while engaging with State services in a bid to resolve their financial difficulty and to meet their obligation to pay rent. <br/><br/>The temporary tenancy protections under Part 2 of the Act of 2020 for tenants in rent arrears due to Covid-19 and at risk of losing their tenancy are due to expire on 10 January 2021, hence the amendment that will be brought forward in the D&aacute;il.  The economic impacts on tenants in the residential rental sector of Covid-19 and successive restrictions on the movement of people continue to be felt and the early part of 2021 is likely to be financially challenging for tenants.  I have said that if I consider it necessary to bring in further protections for tenants, in particular in these difficult times during the Covid pandemic, I would do so.  It was a Bill most Members of this House supported in July.  It came into effect from 1 August.  That Act has worked.  This is effectively an extension of the provisions of that Act, coupled with the additional protections around the protection of tenants during the 5 km travel restriction, which we brought in a few weeks ago and which was passed unanimously in this House.  This is a further protection that will be brought in and we will extend that out to April 2021.  The amendment I mentioned is not quite ready and it will be introduced in the D&aacute;il and added to this Bill<b>.</b><br/><br/>Through these proposed amendments, the Government aims, as do I, to balance in a carefully calibrated manner the legitimate interests of both tenants and landlords.  The proposed time-limited extension and modification of the provisions of the 2020 Act will apply only to those tenants who can demonstrate that, despite the significant State supports available, they have been negatively impacted by Covid-19.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In concluding the introduction of this Bill to the House, I confirm to Senators that it is urgently needed to provide essential safeguards to ensure the continued operation of the planning and building control systems during this pandemic.  The provisions in section 2 of the Bill to amend section 11(3)(<i>b</i>) of the Planning and Development Act are immediately required to allow planning authorities to adapt public consultation procedures in light of current restrictions on the holding of public gatherings during the pandemic.  If this amendment is not made, such restrictions will delay the progression of statutory development plans during the pandemic.  These amendment provisions are also in line with the modernisation agenda for the planning system to increase online activity and ensure continued flexibility in communicating details of draft development plans to the public and will, therefore, be a permanent amendment to the Planning and Development Act.<br/><br/>With respect to the safeguarding provisions in section 3 of the Bill, it is hoped that once enacted, they will never need to be used.  However, these essential provisions are urgently needed to give the planning and building control systems the legislative flexibility and agility to react to more restrictive travel constraints, if issued by the Minister for Health, during the remainder of the pandemic, or in the event that significant infections among local authority staff critically impacts on the resourcing and operation of individual planning or building control authorities.  This is all in order to ensure that the integrity of the planning and building control systems is maintained throughout the pandemic.<br/><br/>I look forward to our debate on the Bill's provisions and will seek to respond to any specific questions.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#T00125"><p>I wish to share time with Senator Byrne with six minutes for me and two minutes for the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#T00162"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#T00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him for bringing this legislation to the Senate first.  I am a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage and I appreciate that some members were confused as to the Minister's intentions.  I accept the Minister's apology and accept that his intention in bringing forward this legislation is both to support the proper functioning of our local authorities and our planning, development and building control processes and to protect public participation in those processes.  I welcome this debate and Fianna F&aacute;il Senators will be supporting the Bill today.</p> <p>The Bill as I read it is an updating of the Planning and Development Act 2000 to allow for public consultation processes which are used for consulting with the public on city and county development plans to be updated and for the continued operation of the planning and building control systems during emergency situations like Covid-19.  I welcome the fact that the Minister is replacing the mandatory requirement on local authorities to hold public meetings with a requirement that they consult with the public.  The amendment he mentioned, which will be brought forward on Monday, provides that local authorities will hold either physical or virtual public meetings.  This is very welcome and we will be happy to support it.  Allowing the Government to make orders during emergency periods like the pandemic to extend the statutory periods applying under the Planning and Development Act and the building controls is also to be welcomed and I hope the whole House will support that.  </p> <p>This legislation reflects a Government that is trying to modernise how we do our business.  It is also reflective of a Government that is responding to the very real-life circumstances in which the country finds itself in terms of the pandemic.  It aims to improve accessibility and inclusiveness in our statutory processes while at the same time upholding the very important values asserted in the Aarhus Convention regarding public participation in decision making when it comes to environmental matters.  I am coming at this from the perspective of a former city councillor in Dublin.  The Dublin city development plan is a really important document that sets out the statutory guidelines and objectives for the development of our city.  The current development plan was drawn up in 2016 and will expire in 2022.  In June of this year, city council officials and councillors commenced work on the new development plan.  The plan has multiple stages, beginning with a pre-draft consultation, on which submissions are invited.  Then there is a consideration of those submissions, following which a draft plan is put out for public consultation.  More submissions will be received on that draft plan and then that will come back for consideration.  Following this, a plan is actually made.  The process takes 99 weeks or almost two years of work.  It is a really important piece of work that requires significant resources, not just from officials but also from the elected representatives.  In that context, I am not going to let the Minister leave the House without reminding him of the Government's commitment to local authority members to deliver on the Moorhead report.  It is an outstanding action and one that I ask the Minister to provide an update to the House on, as all Members would appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#T00300"><p>According to the rules of the House, Members are not supposed to raise issues that are not related to the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#T00400"><p>I apologise to the House.  I did not realise that was the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#T00450"><p>We appreciate the Senator's lobbying effort.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#T00500"><p>I am speaking as a former city councillor and I genuinely understand the enormous time and effort that councillors put into the making of development plans.  It is two years' work and requires significant effort on their part.  They engage with their constituents, lobby groups and so on.  I am not going to repeat my request to the Government; everyone here knows what I want to say, including the Minister.</p> <p>This legislation is important and the Fianna F&aacute;il group will support it.  We will also support the amendment as outlined.  I would encourage the Department to continue to work in this way and to continue to engage with this House.  We have a number of requests which I will not repeat now because I will be accused of lobbying.  We have a number of requests of the Department and this House really wants to engage on them.  I would encourage the Minister to come back to do that and we look forward to working with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#T00600"><p>I endorse Senator Fitzpatrick's views entirely, including on those issues about which we should not be speaking.  I support this legislation but I do not want to see emergency periods being used, effectively, as an excuse for things not to be done.  I have a specific question, for example, regarding why extended periods might be allowed under derelict sites legislation.  I have no problem with allowing for extensions to consultation periods, planning permission for developments and so on but where we are dealing with somebody who has been subject to a derelict sites levy or has been ordered to carry out the cleaning of an area, I seek an assurance that nothing in this legislation will prevent such work from happening.  Somebody who has allowed an area of land to be derelict for a long period should not be able to use this legislation or any loophole within it to prevent necessary work from being done, particularly given that the construction industry can continue to operate under all levels of Covid-19 restrictions.  It is important for the Minister to confirm that this will Bill not prevent work from taking place in the case of derelict sites or dangerous structures.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My specific concern is in regard to the inclusion of the Derelict Sites 1990 Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#U00200"><p>For the information of Senators, a copy of the Minister's speech is available outside the Chamber.  I was not aware of that until it was brought to my attention by a colleague.  Copies of speeches are normally distributed in the Chamber.  There are amendments being referenced that we may wish to address.  It is beneficial to have the speech so all Members need to know that it is available outside.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#U00300"><p>In normal circumstances, copies of speeches are sometimes distributed in regard to Commencement matters, but because of Covid-19 it is not advisable to have people walking around the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#U00400"><p>I appreciate that but we were not aware of it.  We made the assumption we were not being given a copy of the speech but it is available outside.  I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#U00500"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  This is the first time we have been in this House together so I take this opportunity to congratulate him on his appointment.  We soldiered together on the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government.  The Minister has been on all sides of this debate, brief and portfolio.  I wish him well and every success in it.</p><p>On the Minister's apology and clarification in regard to the pre-legislative scrutiny, I fully accept his bona fides.  On the Planning and Development Bill 2020, I have one major concern.  In regard to Covid, I understand the significance and importance of people being safe, be they staff, members of the public or anybody else.  That is really important.  I see the necessity for emergency legislation.  However, I have a difficulty with section 2 of the Bill.  The Bill will be amended, as the Minister will know, but the briefing also says the amendment is in line with the modernisation agenda and that this change will be permanent.  I have with me a letter I received from An Bord Plean&aacute;la which I will circulate to the Minister.  The Minister will be aware of the ongoing engagement with An Bord Plean&aacute;la in regard to Rebuilding Ireland, modernisation and IP planning.  The board has been telling us for four years that it is working on a pilot scheme.  I made some inquiries today.  It still has not got that up and running.  The modernisation of IT and IP project is a wonderful one, but it does not exist.  </p><p>I am aware of a local authority that cannot scan applications, drawings and montages in colour in regard to protected structures.  That is the reality for most councils.  Another local authority does not have a proper archive of protected structures.  I have had to visit the Irish Architectural Archive in Merrion Square to look at drawings because they were not retained by local authorities.  I intend to bring a proposal to this House and to the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage in the next few weeks in regard to a national archive of protected structures because these applications are lodged but not centrally retained.  There is a gap there that needs to be closed.  </p><p>My issue is in regard to inclusivity and respect for the elected members - city and county councillors - who do an enormous job.  I was a member of D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council which had thousands of people engaging in county development plans.  That is the reality.  There is great interest in planning.  It is about the future planning and sustainable development of people's areas.  Citizens have those rights.  We talk about the Aarhus Convention.  If we attempt to curtail public consultation in statutory format it will end up in the courts.  There are a number of environmental groups and prescribed bodies under the Planning and Development Act, of which the Minister will be aware, which are engaged in this area.  I salute them.  They are watchdogs for planning.  I also thank the public, who are our greatest watchdogs in regard to proper planning and sustainable development, as are elected members.</p><p>The Bill seeks to amend section 11(3)(<i>b</i>) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 to replace the mandatory requirement to hold public meetings in regard to the proposed development plan, with an obligation for planning authorities to consult members.  Who are the planning authorities?  There is always a conflict between the executive, which holds the executive function, and the elected members who hold the reserve function.  That is a constant battle.  As a former councillor, the Minister will know that.  Is this decision to be made by the executive?  Will such decisions be made by resolution of the council?  Who will decide how this happens?  </p><p>The briefing also states that the amendment is in line with the modernisation agenda for the planning system to improve accessibility and inclusiveness through increased online activity and assured continued flexibility in communicating details of draft development plans and will, therefore, be a permanent amendment.  The Minister referred to this modernisation in his speech.  This change is to be a permanent arrangement.  I will not be supporting it.  I had hoped that the Minister would reconsider that amendment.  I can understand it in the Covid context but not outside of it.  I see the need for a sunset clause in regard to this aspect.  I do not believe it is right and appropriate to make this a permanent change.  This is a matter of concern for me and I ask the Minister to provide for a review of it in a few months' time.  </p><p>In some local authority offices elected members do not have access to the Internet.  Under this proposal we may be excluding a generation of people over 55 or 60 who have a difficulty in terms of accessing IT?  That is the reality.  In many local authority offices in rural Ireland, members have not been able to engage in Teams meetings of authorities because there is no connectivity.  There are many city and county councillors across the country.  I have spoken to a number of them in the last few days.  I have also engaged with all of the other stakeholders.  They, too, have a concern.  I do not see in any of the correspondence I have on this matter any reference to engagement with the Local Authority Members Association or the Association of Irish Local Government.  I do see reference to Fianna F&aacute;il Senators having raised this issue with them in correspondence.  I have communicated it to them myself and invited feedback.  That is their concern.  As I said, I have serious concerns in regard to this change.</p><p>Did the Minister give consideration to extending the lifetime of county development plans by 12 months?  It is an option.  This could be done through legislation.  I mentioned the principles of the Aarhus Convention and the right of citizens to engage.  Many people that are outside of the technology and skills area like to, and benefit from, visiting a public town hall to see the plans and montages and to meet planners.  I know this is not possible in the context of Covid.  I have no difficulty supporting any other aspect of this Bill.  My concern is the permanent little arrangement which the Minister references in the context of reform and modernisation of the planning process.  The Minister also has a responsibility in terms of An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  It cannot manage its own IT systems.  It has failed to deliver on commitments, albeit it has been set back by Covid for the last nine months like everybody else in terms of access to information.  That is important.</p><p>The Aarhus Convention references citizens' rights in regard to environmental and planning issues.  Most Senators here are former councillors of city and county councils.  We often talk about the right to subsidiarity, to decision-making on the ground and engagement with people.  The Green Party has a strong record on this issue and organises meetings and rallies in its constituencies and communities to highlight issues about planning.  I know all parties do that but to an extent the Green Party has been at the edge of this in terms of its engagement with communities and electorate and the principles of the Aarhus Convention.  I took some time to look at the Green Party website today.  It has a very strong record on that.</p><p>I propose to bring an amendment to the House.  I will lobby in advance of doing so.  I will ask local authority councillors to engage on it with all Senators in this House.  Will the Minister give consideration to a sunset clause to end this permanent arrangement?  We do not need a permanent arrangement, we need an arrangement in place for Covid but not to extend beyond that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#U00600"><p>I thank the Minister for being here today and for initiating this legislation in the Seanad.  I am also a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage and I want to acknowledge the Minister's wholesome and fulsome letter to the committee and his apology for any sleight that may have been experienced by some members who would doubt for a moment his bona fides in bringing this forward and understanding the emergency of the situation.  I put that on the record of the meeting this week in defence of the Minister and the urgency of this legislation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I fully support the legislation.  I am getting to grips with the amendments proposed by the Minister and I will address them in a moment.  To be honest they look sensible and embracing of the needs that are emerging in the context of Covid-19.  I support this measure and we must recognise, in the context of Covid-19, that we cannot hold public meetings and it is ridiculous to run against public health advice.  The planning process and the development plan process really need to proceed, despite current restrictions.</p><p>I am interested in the suggestion of extending the development plan period as it stands.  However, I know in my area and South Dublin County Council, where I was a councillor, there is a need to press on with the amendments and changes so as not to lose a year.  In that regard, although it is an eminently sensible suggestion, I would not be in favour of it.  That is just in case the Minister is thinking about it.</p><p>I am glad that in his speech the Minister references "flexible" measures in looking at extension orders.  I have a concern with how public consultation is handled in a pandemic.  It is reasonable not to hold public meetings but the absence of public meetings must be dealt with through a stepped up and amplified level of advertising of the fact that public consultations are ongoing.  Everybody needs to be in the know.  We do not have the normal recourse of being able to go to residents' associations and talk about these matters.</p><p>We need to provide finance for advertising that these processes are ongoing and not just on social media.  We are still in a transition period between pre-digital and digital contact and connectivity, and we must respect that by looking at different ways of advertising.  A planning notice or something small is not enough.  This must be a big half-page advertisement in all the local newspapers indicating that a public consultation period is ongoing.</p><p>We also need longer public consultation periods.  If we limit something to six weeks, local representatives are now obliged to contact residents' organisations and try to organise Zoom meetings while getting out leaflets or initiating contact to ensure everybody is adequately informed and support them in making submissions in that time.  We need to extend the consultation period to allow for the fact that the process is not as easy as it was.  We have WhatsApp groups and other tools but with the residents' association of which I am a member, many people are older and do not use WhatsApp.  They must be called individually and this takes a greater amount of time.  We need to consider this and the Minister should take it on board.</p><p>The Oireachtas Library and Research Service document we were given to inform us on the legislation quotes the Maastricht recommendations on promoting effective public participation in decision making.  It states that online consultations can complement face-to-face public meetings and hearings but should not replace them.  It also goes through criteria that should be considered, including scale of activity, potential impact, size of the affected population and the controversial or high profile nature of an activity.  It gives a list of considerations.  I urge that we have a statutory instrument that sets up criteria for deciding on the length of time and how the public consultation period is to be addressed or advised to the public.  We should take that into account.</p><p>On a related matter, the process of the development plan was very eloquently described by my colleague.  In it we really need to respect much work over much time by the public and their representatives.  That goes into arriving at a development plan with which we can all live.  The decisions made for the period taken in by the development plan are guided by this work.  In that context, and again in alignment with public consultation, it was very disturbing to me the extent to which An Bord Plean&aacute;la admitted to the Oireachtas joint committee that it does not really take on board the development plan.  We are going to the trouble of changing how consultation is going in legislation and ensuring that the development plan process can go on, yet there are areas like Dublin 8 where the development plan has not been considered and there has been a proliferation of co-living and student accommodation.</p><p>I very much welcome the Minister's initiative on co-living this week.  I have never been a great proponent of it, although it has a place in a very small niche.  In such circumstances we must ensure the development plan really is absolutely adhered to, as we are going to all this trouble, and more than due regard should be given to it.  It must be the guiding light in this.  I ask the Minister to elevate this element and look at an amendment to the legislation to ensure the development plan must be adhered to and given respect.  We should respect all the work done by the public and public representatives.</p><p>I welcome the amendments and I will comment more fully on them next time around.  I broadly support the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#V00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House to propose the legislation.  Before addressing the Bill, I welcome the decision he made this week on co-living.  The decision should have been made sooner but when I read the report I realised the Minister had not taken on officials' advice to tinker but rather made a clear decision on banning co-living.  I would have liked for this to apply retrospectively and particularly to current proposals going through the planning system.  I hope An Bord Plean&aacute;la takes on board the Minister's indications on co-living and turns down such permission applications.</p> <p>I read the circular the other day and the Minister also gives guidance on the changing of purpose-built student accommodation for short-term lets, as that has happened in five cases.  Some of the other student accommodation providers are thinking about doing that in the long term.</p> <p>I have no problem with the majority of the Bill but the section making a permanent change in the modernisation agenda is a sneaky change.  Having a public meeting is really important and I will bring forward an amendment putting a sunset clause on that section.  An older person who is not engaged online would see value in having a planner in front of him or her when speaking about complicated matters like site density, ratios and heights.  It is important for planners to be able to explain these concepts.  If local authorities get away with not having planners at public meetings, I see the process moving online.  This is about a modernisation agenda in general but the change is being introduced for the long term so I would like to see a sunset clause attached.</p> <p>It is quite ridiculous in 2020 that if I submit something to An Bord Plean&aacute;la, I must physically go to the building as it does not take payment online.  A person would have to go to a post office and pay an additional charge in order to get a postal order otherwise.  That is while we are talking about an online modernisation agenda.  The first thing we can do is sort out the planning system so it is facilitating and flexible for people before we change it.  We are submitting an amendment that will introduce a sunset clause.</p> <p>The importance of development planning is acknowledged in this Bill but the Minister has other powers relating to heights and standards.  There has certainly been a feeling that heights and standards have been undermined with the Minister's powers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rebecca Moynihan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RebeccaMoynihan&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I would ask that the Minister would take similar action to that which he took on co-living and have a clear look at where his regulations are over-riding well-considered development plans.  Senator Fitzpatrick and I were both members of Dublin City Council and we spent nights and days until 12 a.m. or 2 a.m. debating and considering the heights and densities within our city and we reached comprises on it.  It was never a NIMBY development plan and agenda.  We fought with the planners and with each other and we had it out, but it was a really well-considered plan for our city.  I imagine that other local authorities around the country do that as well.</p><p>There is a real feeling that there is an undermining of local democracy, not just in participation but also in decision-making, when it comes to the heights and standards in the ministerial guidelines.  We do not want to go back to the mid 2000s, when we had developer-led planning.  We have issues such as construction defects that we have to deal with now as a result of that.  We want to make sure that local people are involved in the decision-making and planning process.  The Minister should reconsider some of the heights and standards changes he has made.  I am not a believer that height equals density.  I will argue hard with residents for density and say that this is the best way to have a good planning system, but it is difficult to do that if, within a couple of years, we have an undermining of that and if we have heights that are completely out of place.</p><p>I welcome the Minister's comments on the eviction ban and I welcome what he did last night.  I ask that the Minister consider, and we have tabled amendments to this effect, that where there are restrictions in a county, the eviction ban will remain in place.  Evictions are still happening for other reasons, and in the course of a pandemic we should not be balancing the rights of people.  Public health has to take priority and anybody losing his or her home for reasons such as family members moving in or for substantial renovations should not be left in that position over the course of a public health emergency.  I ask and plead that the Minister consider extending that to situations where there are county limits or restrictions on travel beyond 5 km.</p><p>I thank the Minister for coming into the House and I ask that he accept the amendments we have submitted when it comes to Committee Stage on Monday because it is important that we continue to have public meetings and that members of the public have access to professional advice and planners in the course of the development plan.  I understand that we cannot have them in the course of a pandemic but there should be a sunset clause for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#W00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the Chamber.  As one of my Government colleagues said, I am never out the Chamber these days but it is good to be here to welcome the amendment that the Minister is putting forward on behalf of the Green Party and through the Government.  That shows how the Government is working together on these issues and I am delighted to see that the Minister is amenable to that.</p> <p>For clarity and for those who are not aware of the background to this, the 2000 Act had a provision that the planning authority shall hold public meetings and it was thanks to Deputy Matthews, as the Minister said, who is the Chairman of the Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage.  He had a concern when looking at the draft Bill because it says: "shall consult with members of the public in such manner (which may include the holding of a public meeting)".  It is the wording of "may include the holding of a public meeting" that caused concern.  I have not seen the wording the Government is proposing and I look forward to seeing that and engaging on it on Monday, but as I understand it, the wording will be to the effect that the planning authority shall hold a public meeting, whether that is online or a physical public meeting.  That provision is hugely important to all of us and I am sure it was inadvertent and accidental in the draft Bill.</p> <p>Many of us, as has been stated, have come from the background of local government and our engagement with people on the ground is a form of public participation.  If we lose that from planning, it basically means there is a top-down heavy Government approach to how planning is operated.  That sense of public participation, grassroots ownership and involvement within our local communities is hugely important to us in the Green Party, and I know our councillors would have found this particular provision difficult, as the councillors within Fianna F&aacute;il would, because I know they are dedicated to that public service as well.</p> <p>An interesting and important point was raised by Senator Seery Kearney.  When we are looking at public participation and the types of engagement involved, the most helpful kind of public participation is to look at local development plans, city and county development plans, and local area plans, interrogate those plans, either as councillors, other elected representatives or interested members of a political party, and see where planning does not align with a city or county development plan or with a local area plan.  There is a valid concern around a lack of local area plans, and I would have such concerns in my constituency.  We need to ensure we are addressing that as a Government and I ask the Minister to look at that.  We have few local area plans and we need to interrogate how we are carrying out public participation and how local councillors are able to engage with the kind of planning that is going on.  They are the people who are best placed to know, not people up in Dublin.  It is the people on the ground who are best placed to know what will work within their constituency.</p> <p>I welcome that the Minister is bringing forward other amendments.  I would like more clarity around those and around the Residential Tenancies Board, RTB.  If it is not being held in public, what kind of transparency is being proposed?  I understand there is a sunset clause for that.  If it is only until April, it is essential that we make sure tenants can bring forward issues to the RTB.  I welcome this move overall.  I do not fundamentally agree with the Labour Party's perspective on a sunset clause for these online or in-person meetings because it is important that we have some kind of continuity and we do not know when we will potentially be coming into and going out of the kinds of lockdowns that will not facilitate a large public meeting.  Therefore, we have to plan for that and we cannot stop building and planning or stop the interrogation of the environmental aspects of planning.  It is crucial from that perspective.</p> <p>Overall, I welcome the Bill and most Members are welcoming the Bill and most of the provisions the Minister is addressing.  I thank the Minister for that and I look forward to seeing the amendments when they come before us and when they go to the D&aacute;il and come back to us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#W00300"><p>I look forward to seeing those amendments and I welcome the Minister to the House.  First, I would like to reference the Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage, which has been mentioned a number of times in this debate.  The committee met on Tuesday last, 17 November and at that meeting, I understand that the Minister asked that pre-legislative scrutiny be waived for this Bill.  A vote was taken and that proposal was defeated.  However, using Seanad Standing Orders, the Minister was able to initiate this legislation in this House and, therefore, bypass the pre-legislative scrutiny altogether.  Rather than a respect for this House that was outlined by the Minister, it was akin to a loophole.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#W00400"><p>On a point of order, I do not want to be argumentative in any way but I have outlined what happened clearly, in good faith and in a truthful manner.  The Senator is trying to twist that.  That did not happen so let us be honest about what happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#X00100"><p>I appreciate that these changes to the form and manner of public consultation are necessary to provide alternatives to face-to-face meetings during the pandemic.  However, I would like to hear more detail on the Minister's plans to use a wide array of technologies to ensure the greatest possible outreach.  Not everyone will have the experience, expertise or technical support to make a written submission.  To achieve the highest possible level of participation, I therefore ask the Minister to examine a wide range of options, including holding meetings on platforms which are accessible to the public, such as Microsoft Teams.</p> <p>I also ask the Department to examine how best to provide all the usual support and assistance to those with impairments or disabilities to enable them to participate fully in whatever form the consultation may take.  While a public meeting may need only one or two individuals to provide an Irish Sign Language service, a bit more planning may be needed to ensure these essential aspects of accessibility can be delivered in whatever new format is adopted.  The process of proper planning and development must be seen to be open and accountable at all times and not the exclusive preserve of those who already have access to and knowledge of the system.</p> <p>The Department has said that these measures will also form part of the modernisation of the consultation process.  Does this mean that if the format envisaged in the legislation proves to be a success, it may be kept on as a means of involving even more people?  How will the Minister judge whether a particular format meets or exceeds the participation threshold of traditional face-to-face meetings?  It is important that any benefit from new forms of outreach and participation in the planning and development process are consolidated.  There must be a clear process for evaluating this.</p> <p>The Minister has said he is committed to answering some questions.  I have some specific queries.  When does he intend to impose the emergency periods outlined in the legislation?  Will these periods be time-specific or in line with public health advice, such as measures restricting travel to 5 km or within individual counties during localised lockdowns?  Will the emergency periods apply throughout the State or only to specific local authorities at specific times?  It appears that the Bill only refers to deadlines to do with planning and control.  The Minister's Department deals with many other diverse areas, from quarry licensing to environmental protection.  Are there plans to extend deadlines to other areas under the auspices of the Department?</p> <p>We will absolutely support the legislation.  Depending on clarification of the points I have raised, we may introduce amendments on a later Stage.  I stress our willingness to co-operate with the Minister.  The Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, has articulated the Minister's willingness to engage with us on Seanad reform, which I welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#X00200"><p>I welcome the Minister back to the House.  Yet again we are discussing emergency legislation.  The Minister has indicated that he intends to come before us to allow for more substantial debate.  It would be very useful to know when that will be.  As we have seen again and again, so many of the issues of concern in housing policy have been flagged but have not been engaged with at the most opportune moments, for example, in relation to co-living.  It is welcome to see that there will be a move towards ending it, but a large number of planning permissions have already been issued in that area.  It was an issue that was well flagged in advance.  It is similar with strategic housing development where we now see that a very large number of planning permissions which were granted under that legislation when it was very much fast-tracked as an issue through the previous Oireachtas.  At that time we warned of the danger of land hoarding and called for a use-it-or-lose-it clause, and now we are seeing that that may eventually come in years later after the exact consequences which were flagged have occurred.</p> <p>There are several issues relating to planning and development, some of them I, with others, will be introducing on Committee Stage, while others will not be appropriate and I will not be able to bring them forward.  They are, however, very important, especially when the Minister indicates that the Bill to amend the Residential Tenancies and Valuation Act 2020 is to be introduced in the D&aacute;il.  When can we expect both pieces of legislation to be opened for full and proper review and scrutiny?  That is very important.</p> <p>It should be borne in mind that an unfortunate scenario arose the last time emergency legislation came through the House, where due to the limited time available and the Minister's enthusiasm for giving substantial answers to every question put-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#X00300"><p>I was trying to be helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#X00400"><p>Yes, indeed.  It meant a very large number of very important amendments relating substantially to the issue were not discussed at all.  I am sure the Minister will want to assure us that there will be no guillotine on the Committee Stage debate on this legislation and that all amendments will be dealt with.  That will be very important.  While this may be emergency legislation or may relate to a particular crisis, it is important that it has full and proper scrutiny.</p> <p>On the substantial issues, I have some caution and concern.  I welcome the fact that there was a suspension of planning decisions during the first lockdown.  That was a positive decision.  I would have liked to have seen a similar action taken during the current level 5 lockdown, and I understand that section 3 of the legislation could facilitate such a measure if an emergency period is declared.  That is positive.  The Minister said he hopes to use it very rarely.  I think he should use it if it is the situation that circumstances are getting in the way of people being able to participate fully in the planning process.</p> <p>I have a concern that it seems to be that a very large volume of planning applications have been made during the Covid crisis.  Perhaps between now and Committee Stage the Minister might provide us with this information because I think it would be useful.  I can only go on partial figures that I might have and we do not have the option of asking parliamentary questions in the Seanad.  I have spoken to people who encountered real difficulties in engaging with the process at that time.  It would be useful to know how many applications have been made.</p> <p>I know that many local authorities encourage those making or intending to make planning applications to engage with others who might do so, resulting in many cases in sets of planning applications being made.  This is sometimes a co-ordinated activity at a time when individuals or individual households who may be impacted by planning and development decisions have not had the same freedom to engage with each other, not just simply giving their input into the process but engaging in a co-ordinated way around input into the process.</p> <p>In that sense, I have a strong concern about the proposal to make some of the changes in this Bill permanent.  While it is fine to modernise systems, if we do so in a way that leaves people out, if we change our consultation process to upgrade it but effectively leave out those who need to be consulted, that is not adequate.  I am concerned by the changes to section 11 of the principal Act and the idea that could potentially lead to a scenario where all consultation takes place online.  It is perhaps worth reminding ourselves that 55% of people in Ireland are not considered to have strong digital skills.  We might be confused by seeing the high-rise buildings of the many digital platforms headquartered in Ireland, many of which are very familiar with navigating the planning process, but Ireland is 17th out of 24 countries in terms of digital literacy.  Some 55% of the adult population between the ages of 18 to 65 are qualified as having low digital skills.  It is not enough that there is consultation if it is not consultation that everyone can access.</p> <p>Given that the Minister is amending the Bill anyway when it comes to Committee Stage, I urge him not to make that a permanent change in section 11.  If he is bringing the Planning and Development Bill 2020 back to the Houses again, let us examine a roadmap towards making such permanent changes, if they be needed.  If, however, the Minister is asking for a particular measure in response to Covid-19 while inserting a permanent change in policy, that requires a different level of scrutiny.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I suggest that the Minister does one or the other.  If these are measures around Covid-19 and responses to similar emergencies, so be it.  If these changes relate to the Aarhus Convention, public consultation, and the right of every person, be they or be they not skilled in navigating digital platforms, to be heard, to exercise their rights and to have a say in the environment in which they live, then that is a separate discussion.  I urge the Minister to separate these issues and to remove the sections of this Bill that make those changes permanent.  I will be challenging that on Committee Stage, although I would prefer if we were able to have a proper and more robust discussion.  I recognise that the amendment the Minister intends to bring to the D&aacute;il is a small step but it is not adequate.  That amendment would require a public meeting but it could still be online.  I look forward to further debate on these issues. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00200"><p>I thank the Minister for bringing this important legislation before the House.  He has been criticised in some quarters for expediting the Bill through the Seanad without pre-legislative scrutiny by the committee.  As a member of that committee and as someone who was at the meeting referred to by Senator Warfield, it is disingenuous to try to twist the reality of how this Bill came before us.  I accept fully the Minister's bona fides and the comprehensive letter he supplied to the committee explaining the urgency of bringing this Bill to the Seanad and why pre-legislative scrutiny could not happen.  It is important that that is clarified, given what Senator Warfield said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00300"><p>On a point of order, I understand that a vote was taken and the proposal was defeated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00400"><p>Please address the Chair.  We are not engaging in a to-and-fro here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00500"><p>I accept that the measures in this Bill are immediately required to enable the planning authorities to proceed with their development plans.  In many cases, especially in local authorities like my own in Waterford, as well as those in Limerick and Tipperary, which are amalgamated, their development plans should have lapsed in 2016, 2017, 2018 or 2019.  They have been extended beyond their life as a result of the amalgamation and because the authorities are awaiting the national planning framework and the regional planning guidelines.  It is important that, while we ensure consultation takes place, these development plans are not delayed any further.  They are so important for the future development of our cities, towns and villages across this country.</p> <p>I am sure the Minister will clarify what has been referred to as the permanent amendment and I certainly do not believe it is his intention to permanently replace in person public meetings.  Rather, the amendment would be used as an option in circumstances such as those we face with at the moment in the Covid-19 pandemic.  It will allow further enhanced consultation to take place in the future.  While we have to look at our older generation and their ability to engage in the planning process, we equally have to accept that in order for our younger generation to engage with the planning process we must modernise it and engage them in ways that are not onerous and do not require travelling to a public meeting.  I ask the Minister to clarify that in his response.</p> <p>I also ask that his Department gives further clarity to local authorities regarding their process of engaging with their own members on the development plan process.  Some of my former colleagues on Waterford City and County Council have criticised the fact that some of these meetings have been held online.  While that is necessary at the moment, as we go further through the stages of the development plan process they should be held in person insofar as possible.  We all know from our experience over the past number of months that although technology is fantastic, engaging in person is far more effective.  I thank the Minister for bringing this Bill before the House and I look forward to his response. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00550"><p>I call Senator Keogan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00600"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman.  It is great to see a Meath man in the Chair today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00700"><p>It has been a tough week for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00800"><p>Do not mind him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Y00900"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House.  Public meetings are the cornerstone of local government and are central to the participation of all citizens and members of the public in local democracy.  This has been the way since the birth of western democracy.  Some 2,500 years ago people would gather in the agora in ancient Athens for political, judicial, commercial, social and religious activity.</p><p>Section 11(3)(<i>b</i>) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 reads, &quot;a planning  authority shall hold public meetings and seek written submissions regarding all or any aspect of the proposed development plan and may invite oral submissions to be made to the planning authority regarding the plan.&quot;  This section refers to that fundamental and foundational aspect of democracy, the public meeting.  The public meeting is an important vehicle where people can quite literally voice their opinions, ideas and concerns to those who govern and can listen to their response.  The development plan of a local authority can have a significant and lasting impact on the physical surroundings, amenities and environment of a community and those who live in it.  Therefore, it is of the utmost importance that the ability to meet physically in person is not limited in any way.  The new section 11(3)(<i>b</i>), as proposed in section 2 of the Planning and Development Bill 2020, would read:</p> <blockquote> 	a planning authority&mdash;  	(i) shall consult with members of the public in such manner ... as it considers appropriate, and invite submissions in writing from members of the public, in relation to a proposed development plan, and<br /><br />(ii) may invite oral submissions from members of the public in relation to a proposed development plan.  </blockquote> <p>This section would make the holding of a public meeting subject to the discretion of the planning authority.  I am glad the Minister will be amending it.  According to the current amendment, it would no longer be a legal obligation to hold a public meeting when a planning authority is reviewing a development plan.  Rather, the authority would merely have to consult with members of the public as it considers appropriate.  The manner in which the proposed consultation would take place would be determined completely by the planning authority.  This amendment weakens the democratic process and weakens participatory democracy.  Making a public meeting optional undermines a key cornerstone of local government, one that has existed since the dawn of democracy.</p><p>I have grave reservations about this amendment, based on my own experience of having previously served my community as a county councillor.  Other forms of consultation are not optimal and if a meeting were to be held online via Zoom or some other app, it could be prejudiced against people who are not IT literate and those in rural areas who do not have reliable broadband.  Certain demographics would be prejudiced and excluded from the democratic process in 21st-century Ireland.  There are 500,000 people in this country who cannot even read.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Too many people are already being alienated and left behind.  We should always seek to empower people and enhance the role of citizens in government and democracy, thereby respecting the subsidiarity principle of European Union law.  While I acknowledge that the advice of the Attorney General has been sought in drafting the Bill and that the preservation of public participation was a consideration, I have doubts that this amendment achieves that or that it is in the true spirit of the principle of subsidiarity.<br/><br/>Notwithstanding the opinion I have expressed, if this amendment is to be passed, it should be accompanied by a sunset clause to ensure that the amended section 11(3)(<i>b</i>) would expire on 9 June 2021 along with all the other Covid-19 restrictions unless it is extended by means of a resolution passed by both Houses of the Oireachtas prior to this date.<br/><br/>Will this legislation affect the amendment stage of the development plan and, if so, how?  Councillors in Meath will be in work every day until 15 December going through the development plan.  It is a major task, particularly for new councillors who have not had the proper training on development plans and are obviously at a loss as a result.  Someone mentioned that the development plans are really important.  In 2014, across the country 17,000 ha were zoned to deliver 414,000 houses.  Therefore, there is no hurry with development plans.  I just wanted to put that out there.<br/><br/>I will always pat the Minister on the back when he does a great job.  However, in the past 24 hours two homeless men in their 40s have died, one very close to this building.  I ask the Minister to please tackle the homelessness issue in the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Z00200"><p>I believe this is my first opportunity to welcome my good friend and colleague, the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, to the House.  He was the Leader of the Opposition in Seanad &Eacute;ireann from 2011 to 2016 during which period he was constructive in the way he dealt with the role.  His constructive approach will percolate right into his Ministry.  We want to see problems resolved.  Politicians are there to solve problems.  If there were no problems, we would not be here.  To get someone of his calibre to take responsibility for solving the problems in housing is a very good fit.  He has a deep understanding of the challenges of housing, having been in politics for most of his adult life in this city.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Z00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Z00400"><p>I very much look forward to what he will achieve.  I know of his dogged determination and he will deliver.</p> <p>I echo what Senator Cummins said about this legislation.  It is essential to continue the important work of local government and the process of passing county development plans.  The pandemic has changed how we do business in the country.  The Bill enables local authorities who are going through the development plan process to continue holding their public engagements, which they are statutorily obliged to do while using modern technology.  When the legislation that preceded this was introduced, everyone was able to hold public meetings; it was not an issue.  Nobody envisaged a situation where we would not be able to hold public meetings, public consultation processes and so on for development plans.</p> <p>Along with others, I really encourage the public to engage more with their county development plans.  In my county, Clare, submissions for the latest county development plan closed on Monday.  It is a plan that will follow through on a number of steps.  I encourage people who are watching today's debate to read the development plan and make their views known to the local authority and to their councillors.  We need people to engage more in the process and share their views, experience and knowledge bearing in mind that many people living in County Clare, as in other counties, have travelled the world and seen good ideas abroad.  We want to draw on those good ideas and suggestions to feed into what is the bible in planning and development for the coming years in our county, as it is in every other county.</p> <p>On the principle of encouraging people to participate more in county development plans, the Minister should consider embracing modern technology.  Sadly, in my view, social media is probably viewed more than local newspapers, and observed and listened to more than local radio stations.  I do not know whether it is good for democracy, but it is not going to change, and we are where we are.  As with other aspects of life, county development plans need to embrace that modern technology to try to reach a bigger audience and elicit the views of many more people.  This legislation is important because it broadens the toolkit of local authorities to do that.  It allows us to live with Covid - that awful phrase.  It allows local authorities to continue with their development plans.  It gives the Minister the flexibility to be flexible during this crisis.</p> <p>I wish the Minister the very best of luck.  I know he will initiate many Bills in this House because he knows the value of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#Z00500"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I am very happy to see this Bill introduced.  It is important that we are providing ways for local authorities to come together.  I know how difficult it is.  Many Senators were recently local authority members.  Galway County Council is trying to hold its plenary meetings by bringing 40 to 45 councillors together in large GAA halls at the moment.</p> <p>The county development plan is very important, and this legislation is really about the county development plan.  In my area in Ballinasloe we are looking at developing areas for residential use and for industrial use.  We are crying out for office space.  The local authorities have encouraged and received written submissions.  If we are doing this in an online way, we need to ensure there is communication allowing people to join in.  With so many online meetings, it is very hard to galvanise people to get involved in the process of submissions and consultations.</p> <p>Before I became a councillor, I probably did not understand the impact a county development plan has on my local areas for five years.  It has enormous repercussions.  This is a crucial period for all the towns and villages in Ireland to plan for the coming five years.  It needs to be cross-departmental.  As Senator Fitzpatrick said, it is an enormous process taking place over nearly two years.  As I only became a councillor in 2019, I have not been through it previously, but I am seeing it now and looking at it from a little further away in this House.  We need to find a way to incentivise people to participate in the consultative process.  When we have these online consultation measures, local authorities should have targets for the minimum number taking part in these meetings or in representative groups.</p> <p>Is it possible for me to share time?  I forgot to mention it at the beginning.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aisling Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AislingDolan&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I wish to share time with Senator Ahearn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA00200"><p>Senator Ahearn will have five minutes on his own.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA00300"><p>My final comment is on timelines for planning developments.  Again, I am very familiar with a local one.  I refer to a permit, nothing to do with planning as such, for the operation of a waste transfer station and I am involved in the campaign about the inappropriate location.  The challenge we have is that there is no extension to the 25 working days for people to respond and make submissions.  Especially with Covid, and we have just gone through a lockdown level 5, there is no way to galvanise or engage with the community.  I have a huge concern that community groups are literally fighting.  We have already gone to the High Court where we fought, under the habitats directive, to protect a piece of ground and challenged Galway County Council.  I ask for consideration to be given to extending timelines for planning and permit applications if we engage in more level 5 lockdowns during the year ahead because the county council has not allowed an extension with the current level 5 lockdown.  I thank the Minister for his time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA00400"><p>I probably will not need five minutes and I can accommodate Senator Burke if he is happy to share time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA00500"><p>We can accommodate whatever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA00600"><p>I will only take two or three minutes so either way.  If Senator Burke is next on the list, it is fine.</p> <p>I welcome the Minister to the House and it is a pleasure to have him here.  I congratulate him on his appointment and wish him well.  He has hit the ground running.  He will certainly have my support and that of Senators on this side for the work being done.  </p> <p>This legislation that has been brought forward today is very welcome and I support it.  Obviously the function of the legislation is to support the local authorities going forward.  In a time of Covid they are having an awful lot of difficulties.   The legislation seeks to facilitate public consultation whether that is in person, which we cannot do at the moment but we will see where we are in the new year.  If it is not possible to do that through public consultation or public meetings then it should be done online or using Zoom or Webex.</p> <p>It is important that we promote public participation and I encourage people to participate as much as possible in county development plans.  We have started the Tipperary county development plan 2022 to 2028.  It is so important for the public to give their views on plans so I encourage people who want to see their town or county progress to use county development plans as an opportunity to get involved.  I do not mind whether that is done through traditional public meetings or through another facilitation using Zoom so long as people give their views on how they want to see their constituency and county develop over the next number of years.</p> <p>We need to focus on one planning issue.  In my own county of Tipperary many people have applied for planning.  As they want to live in rural areas they might seek to live just outside of a local town.  I know that we encourage people to build and live in communities and not in what we would class in Tipperary as the middle of nowhere but we need to focus on areas that are very close to town centres.  Whether classified as agricultural areas, there is a restriction so people who are not from a farming background or do not own 30 acres of land will be unable to live in the area.  Albeit these people work in a town or give back an awful lot to the region in which they live, they still cannot build in the area.  I am lucky that I live on my own farm that is quite a distance from town but not everyone has an opportunity to live in the area.  People are trying to live much closer to towns than in the past but they are not getting planning permission because of provisions that were brought through six, seven or ten years ago.  That situation needs to be looked at certainly from the perspective of Tipperary.</p> <p>In terms of the legislation today, I fully support it.  However, we need to promote and advertise it as much as possible so that people can engage and give their views.  I again welcome the Minister and thank him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA00700"><p>I welcome the Minister back to the House.  I wish to share my time with Senator Currie unless she gets time herself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA00800"><p>At this point only one person has offered to speak after the Senator.  If Senator Currie is here then I can add her name to the list.  There are eight minutes remaining to be shared between both Senators.  There is also time for the Minister to come back in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA00900"><p>The Minister has said that the Bill will not be a cost to the Exchequer.  However, section 3 of the Bill states that he must do this in consultation with the Minister for Health and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  Why, if the Bill will not be a cost to the Exchequer, must he consult the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform?  Is it just a case of the Department of Finance shoving its weight around the place?  I would say that is probably the case.</p> <p>I welcome the Bill and wish the Minister well with it.  The legislation will put a lot of extra pressure on councillors because they will have further consultation with the public and, therefore, have an increased workload.  I know that the Minister has the Moorhead report and should make a decision in relation to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA01000"><p>I urge the Senator to not stray into such territory.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA01100"><p>I am not.  This Bill will place an extra workload on local authority members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA01200"><p>I know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA01300"><p>The Minister knows what he must and should do.  The Government has very ambitious renewable energy plans for up to 2030, particularly for the east coast from Wexford to County Louth where it is planned to generate 3.5 GW of electricity.  As of now, we have only 25 MW generated by a very small offshore farm on the Arklow Bank.  The Marine Planning and Development Management Bill will come before the House shortly but there is a crossover concerning An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  Has An Bord Plean&aacute;la the expertise and resources to deal with the ambitious plans the Government has for renewable energy, which is massive compared with what we have?  I like to think that the resources available to An Bord Plean&aacute;la will be taken into consideration and that whatever it requires will be dealt with, maybe not in this Bill, but somewhere because there is a crossover with the other Bill that will come forward.</p> <p>As a result of today's Bill there will be a change in work practices because as more people work from home, less office space is required but garden offices will be required.  In the last year or two an office space, back garden shed or whatever in Dublin was refused planning permission.  Throughout the country there will be a sea change in work practices with people working from home.  Will the Minister offer advice to local authorities and their members on changed work practices when they compile development plans going forward?  With that, I wish the Minister well with his Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#AA01400"><p>That completes all of the listed speakers with three minutes remaining.  As Senators Currie and Davitt have not spoken, I ask them to take a minute and a half each before I bring in the Minister to reply.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB00200"><p>I will be fast.  When I was a councillor, the Minister's brother was mayor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB00300"><p>Was he okay?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB00400"><p>Of course he was okay.  I have one or two points to make.  It would be a good idea to establish guidance on best practice for running public meetings online and for online consultations.  I appreciate the speed at which things have changed but how things have been handled has varied dramatically between different local authorities and the National Transport Authority, NTA.  We have had some experience with Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann in this regard.  It is important that a review of what has worked and what has not be carried out urgently so that we can establish what is best practice from the start.  People were trying to cope and, in some cases, it did not work out very well.  In the case of Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann's consultation, it was left to communities to figure out some very technical information for themselves in the middle of level 3 restrictions.  That caused a great amount of stress.  If public meetings are held on matters that really affect a community, there will be hundreds of people on the call.  A consultative interactive process in which people feel like they are getting answers to their questions is required.  This is really important.  With regard to the Minister's modernisation agenda, a hybrid model is preferable if we are to ensure universal access.</p> <p>I welcomed the Minister's announcement last week with regard to co-living.  A suburban cul-de-sac in Castleknock was never the place for co-living.  That application is with An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  I hope the board listens to its inspector and the Fingal County Council planners in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB00500"><p>There are actually an extra couple of minutes available if the Senator would like two minutes more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB00600"><p>No, I have finished.  I thank the Acting Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB00700"><p>The Senator was working with the good O'Brien.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB00800"><p>Before the Minister winds up, I will compliment him on all the good work he has done in this Department.  He has shown great initiative.  He has been bounced around by bad luck, as has everyone else, as a result of the pandemic.  It certainly has not helped the Minister to fulfil some of his expectations but I know he is working hard to maximise output in the housing industry.  This legislation is forward-thinking, as are the bits and pieces that Senator Currie just mentioned on which the Minister has given promises.</p> <p>I will raise one issue of which the Minister might take cognisance in the future.  I refer to the national planning framework and Project Ireland 2040.  We have a crisis in housing, which the Minister is certainly doing his best to work on.  In Westmeath and Meath, the process of drawing up county development plans is ongoing but constraints on numbers in certain hubs and areas are causing serious complications in counties such as Westmeath, Meath and Longford.  When a lot of this was put together, we were in a different place.  There was a downturn in housing and an economic crisis.  Much of this forward planning was carried out at that stage.  As the Minister knows, it really only came to fruition in 2019 but a lot of work had gone into it over the previous five or six years.  The Minister is new to his Department.  This planning was done before he came into his position.  I sincerely feel that Project Ireland 2040 should be reviewed and that a lot of it should be put on ice for now.  </p> <p>I see this all over the country in my interactions with different councillors who tell me about the complications in their own areas.  In Westmeath, there are logical places to zone for development in towns like Castlepollard, Kinnegad and Rochfortbridge.  I refer to infill sites, for example.  I have been made aware of one particular example in Castlepollard, although I will not mention any names, in which a builder had built a certain number of houses and had given the 20% allocation to the council.  We were delighted to get some housing on the back of the development.  He had another 4 acres which had been dezoned under the previous development plan which he sought to have rezoned.  It had all the services.  He wished to build more houses which would have allowed for more social housing and housing for the general public.  This application was refused as a result of the constraints under which Westmeath County Council finds itself as a result of new development plan guidelines.</p> <p>This is blatantly wrong.  It does not make any sense.  There are crunches because of the numbers involved.  The main thrust of the development plan was aimed at bigger hubs such as Athlone or Mullingar.  Towns like Kinnegad, Castlepollard, Rochfortbridge and so on will suffer on the back of this.  If we are serious about the divide between rural areas and the cities, we must support well-established towns in rural areas.  If we do not, we will face serious problems.  That is a fundamental result of the Project Ireland 2040 plan and no one will tell me otherwise because it is there to be seen.  It is laid bare in all of the county development plans being drawn up across the country at present.  </p> <p>I know this is not totally within the terms of the debate for which the Minister is here today and I sincerely appreciate all the good work he is doing.  He has been thinking outside of the box, which I hope bears fruit for him.  I sincerely ask, however, that he look again at the Project Ireland 2040 plan because it is causing an untold number of problems throughout the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB00900"><p>I thank the Senators.  This debate has shown their depth of knowledge regarding the issues pertaining to this particular Bill.  Many Members have worked on county development plans in their previous lives.  Today's debate has shown their appreciation of the nuances involved and their consciousness of the realities of the process and the importance of public engagement.  As there are no other Senators offering, I will now call on the Minister to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#BB01000"><p>I thank Members for their contributions and for the points they have raised, all of which I have taken note of and some of which I will do my best to respond to today.  We can come back to some of the others on Monday, but all of the points have been taken on board.</p><p>At the outset, I will mention an issue which was raised by a Senator today.  I refer to a very tragic death in the vicinity of this House.  I am loath to comment on specific cases, as the Senator may understand, because each case is a tragedy for the family of the person involved and for his or her case worker if he or she had been engaging with emergency services.  I feel it acutely when people die in such tragic circumstances.  We discussed aspects of this matter in this House last night as well.  It is important that people know that this specific tragedy is unrelated to emergency services and emergency bed facilities.  There is emergency bed capacity in every city in this country.  There was spare capacity last night.  We have made sure that our winter plan is in place.  My priority, above planning processes, development plans, Covid and all else, is to eradicate homelessness and to keep our most vulnerable people safe during the pandemic.  I commend all of those workers who are on the front line every single day of the week in our local authorities.  I meet many of them in the Dublin authorities regularly.  I have a homelessness task force including all homelessness partners which convenes weekly.  I want to put that on the record of this House but I will say no more about it to respect the privacy of that individual and his family.</p><p>With regard to the points that have been raised, there has been a lot of discussion around our plans <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>public consultation, whether in person or online.  Perhaps I was not as clear as I might have been, although I thought I was, but meetings under section 11(3)(<i>b</i>) relate to issues at the consultation stage of development plans.  This is the preliminary, pre-draft stage which involves very little consultation, if any.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2020&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=25"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In my view, this would improve that further.  Obviously, Members will have the course of the week to look at that, but it will be open to authorities to hold online or in-person meetings, or both, into the future, and that is why I think it is a good thing.  I have seen that consultation work very well.<br/><br/>The Senator rightly discussed, as did Senator Cummins, bringing in newer generations and people who do not necessarily tend to engage with these types of process, and I see Senator Dolan and others agreeing.  We want to get more people involved, increase access and have more transparent meetings.  Many council meetings are streamed live, for example, my own local authority in Fingal and that of Senator Currie has been streaming both area and full committee meetings for years, and that is a good thing.  It does not exclude anyone, and I would not be so presumptuous or ageist to say that just because people are older, they will not be able to access meetings or will not have the ability to do so.  I think that is incorrect.  Some have alluded to the idea of where there is an older population, they may not be able to access online meetings, but I disagree.  My own father is 85 years of age and is more than capable of accessing many different things, including meetings.  The point is that this concerns the pre-draft stage, and it relates to development plans only, but what it might do is help in other consultations, and I have seen it in practice.<br/><br/>Senator Currie has made a very fair point about other consultations and how they are managed and following good procedure within them.  It is not just a case of putting all the information online and leaving it to people.  It requires us to do more, and that is why I signed an order, and went further and issued draft standing orders from my Department to every single local authority to permit them to hold their meetings remotely, in person or using a combination of both, if they wish.  It is up to each local authority to adopt these orders, to bring in their own standing orders, and they can even decide vote remotely.  There were some criticisms initially, with people claiming that this was a diminution of local government, and I cannot understand why anyone would say that.  If anything, it makes it safer for people, potentially, but it leaves it up to the local authorities themselves to decide how they want to do it.<br/><br/>Many points have been raised and I will speak on a few items.  On the issue of construction and all its ancillary services, I was slightly concerned when a few Senators spoke of their desire to pause the planning process.  We fought very hard to have construction and ancillary services remain open during level 5 restrictions, and there is a reason for that.  The initial shutdown earlier this year has actually meant that our housing delivery will be substantially behind what we need, with somewhere in the region of 16,000 to 18,000 housing completions being delivered in total by the end of the year when we need to be building and delivering about 33,000 per annum, based on the ESRI research that my own Department commissioned.  We are living with this pandemic at the moment and there is light at the end of the tunnel, thankfully, and there is good news in respect of vaccines, but we are going to be living in this type of scenario right into next year.  I think it was Senator Higgins who raised the point of pausing planning right now, but I think that would be an absolutely retrograde step.  There is nothing to be feared from what is being brought in today.  If anything, it creates a more transparent system and, as has been mentioned by Senator Dolan, a hybrid type system, which is what I would encourage people to do to allow more people to be involved.<br/><br/>Senator Boyhan raised a number of points in respect of a sunset clause, as did a number of other Senators, including Senator Moynihan.  I do not believe we need a sunset clause.  It relates to section 11(3)(<i>b</i>), which is the pre-draft stage, so maybe they want to consider that, but I have taken the points raised by the Senators.  From our perspective, we do need these measures brought in quite urgently, and I explained at the outset the issue with pre-legislative scrutiny.  I cannot have a situation whereby, if there was an outbreak of Covid, and we hope that does not happen, in a particular planning authority or in An Bord Plean&aacute;la and staff are affected, the planning or building control system and the operation of it would be put at risk.  That is why we need these measures to be put in place.<br/><br/>The Residential Tenancies Board, RTB, data amendment contained in the Bill simply allows those hearings to be carried out online to allow them continue.  It is obviously not the optimum as we move through the pandemic, but it is to allow it.<br/><br/>In advance of Monday, just so Members are clear on the amendment that will be tabled, a draft of which I have with me, although I am not moving it now, obviously, as we are on Second Stage, it clearly states that a local authority shall consult with members of the public in such a manner which shall include the holding of a public meeting or an online public meeting, so it is one or the other, as it considers appropriate.  Obviously members of local authorities will have an input into that.  It also states that a local authority can invite submissions in writing from members of the public in relation to a proposed development plan, so it is at the pre-development stage, not when the draft is published, although I would expect and think it would be appropriate at that stage as well.  The vast bulk, if not all, of our local authority meetings at the draft stage, when members are actually engaging with the development plan, are open to the public to see what is happening, or they are open to submissions.  We want to see that.<br/><br/>Senator Burke raised the issue of resources for An Bord Plean&aacute;la and other pieces.  The marine planning and development Bill is well advanced, but that issue is outside the remit of this debate, but I will talk to him separately about it.<br/><br/>I thank the Senators for their time because they have been most accommodating and constructive in respect of two important pieces of legislation that have been passed recently.  I do intend to continue to initiate legislation here because the debate here really informs what we can do in the D&aacute;il and how we may move and tweak pieces of legislation.  With the co-operation of the Senators, I will certainly be doing that again.  A Senator mentioned the potential use of the guillotine procedure on Monday.  The Order of Business of this House is a matter for this House itself, and it has nothing to do with me.  I get a sense that the vast bulk of Members here today support the thrust of this legislation and understand the urgent need for it to be passed.  I therefore thank them for their co-operation today.  I have noted all the points that have been raised, even though I have not been able to cover all of them, but I will respond to other points on Monday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.162" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#CC00300"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#CC00400"><p>Next Monday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#CC00450"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.166" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Monday, 30 November 2020.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.167" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.07 p.m. and resumed at 3.22 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.168" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#EE00050">Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund Regulations 2020: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#EE00200"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:  	Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund Regulations 2020, copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 13th November 2020. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1546" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2020112500002#EE00300"><p>I am glad to be here today to discuss this issue.  An important pillar of Government policy is to ensure the horse and greyhound racing industries have achieved their maximum potential and, in doing so, contribute to economic and social development across a wide geographic swathe of the country.  Those industries make a valuable contribution to our economy.  It is estimated the thoroughbred industry has an annual economic impact of &euro;1.9 billion, with direct and indirect employment of 9,000 people, and the greyhound sector provides an estimated 12,000 people with economic benefit.  The thoroughbred industry, in particular, brings a high level of international investment into Ireland.</p> <p>Government funding, in addition to supporting these key industries, presents an excellent opportunity to yield a high return for its investment leading to a flow of income right through the economy, thereby providing widespread benefits to our society.</p> <p>The Irish equine breeding and racing industry is extremely competitive, as the Members will know, at a global level.  We are the third biggest producers of thoroughbred foals in the world and estimates place Ireland only behind the United States in being the biggest seller of bloodstock by public auction globally.  Time and again, successive Governments have acknowledged the importance of these industries and have supported them through legislation and policy initiatives.  The support provided by public funds through investment in these industries has enabled Ireland to develop a world-class reputation for excellence in horse racing and greyhound racing and in breeding.  </p> <p>The current Covid-19 pandemic poses particular challenges for Horse Racing Ireland, HRI, R&aacute;sa&iacute;ocht Con &Eacute;ireann, RC&Eacute;, and the industries as a whole.  The Government's plan, Resilience and Recovery 2020-2021: Plan for Living with Covid-19, does not provide at any of the levels for a return to full commercial operations.  This will impact significantly on the finances of HRI and RC&Eacute; both this year and up to the end of the timespan of the plan in June 2021.  It is essential in these circumstances therefore that additional Covid-related supports are made available to HRI and RC&Eacute;, reflecting costs incurred and changes to the trading environment.</p> <p>These industries receive financial support from the State through the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund, under section 12 of the Horse and Greyhound Racing Act 2001.  My Department makes payments from the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund to HRI and RC&Eacute;.  In the period 2001 to date, a total of &euro;1.36 billion has been paid from the fund to the horse and greyhound racing industries in accordance with the provisions of the Act.  The cumulative upper limit on payments from the fund, provided for under the relevant regulations has therefore been reached.  </p> <p>Exchequer funding provided from the fund is crucial to the survival and continued development of the horse and greyhound racing industries.  In order to give effect to the provisions of budget 2021, this cumulative upper limit must be increased by regulation.  The Estimates for my Department, passed by both Houses as part of budget 2021, include an allocation of &euro;96 million for the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund.  This will be distributed in accordance with section 12(6) of the Horse and Greyhound Racing Act 2001, with 80% or just over &euro;76 million going to the HRI and 20% or &euro;19.2 million going to RC&Eacute;.</p> <p>In order to allow my Department to provide the moneys allocated in budget 2021, it is necessary to comply with the technical requirement under section 12(13) of the Horse and Greyhound Racing Act to increase the cumulative limit on the amount payable from the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund by &euro;96 million to some &euro;1.46 billion.  This is achieved by way of the regulations submitted to this House today.  The aggregate limit on the Horse and Greyhound Racing Fund has been increased in this manner in 2004 and in 2009 to 2020, inclusive.</p> <p>Regarding the horse racing industry, the 2017 Deloitte report into the economic impact of Irish breeding and racing, commissioned by HRI, indicates that the total direct and stimulated expenditure of the Irish breeding and racing industry was estimated at &euro;1.84 billion in 2016.  In addition, it is estimated that there are 15,200 jobs at the core of the racing and breeding industry or in directly related industries.</p> <p>Horse racing generates a very significant return to the rural economy in Ireland and a positive international profile for our country.  Behind all the facts and figures are the thousands of men and women who, directly and indirectly, make the Irish racing and breeding industry what it is today.</p> <p>The HRI 2019 annual report indicated another successful year for the Irish racing and breeding industries.  The focus on ownership leads to a further increase in the number of horses in training and to more horses competing.  There was also an increase of more than 3% in attendance figures for 2019 and an increased demand for Irish horses at the sales, which was welcome, particularly given the uncertainty as a result of Brexit.</p> <p>As proven in 2020, albeit mostly behind closed doors due to Covid-19, Irish owners, trainers, jockeys and horses are setting high standards globally and their stellar achievements and enduring influence underscore Ireland's international prominence.  The Irish equine breeding and racing industry is extremely competitive at a global level, despite other major racing nations having much larger populations and economies.</p> <p>It is worth noting that Government funding, in addition to supporting this key industry, also presents an excellent opportunity to yield a high return for its investment leading to a flow of income right throughout the economy.  Support for certain strategic industries is important for future economic growth and can provide widespread benefits for society, as well as for the wider economy.</p> <p>HRI has engaged extensively with my Department and other key stakeholders on the significant risks to the industry as a result of Covid-19.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2020-11-25a.171" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow</p></speech>
</publicwhip>