<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from the following Senators that they propose to raise the following matters:</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#A00400">State Bodies</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#A00500"><p>I welcome and thank the Minister of State, Deputy Malcolm Noonan, for coming to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#A00600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting this Commencement matter and the Minister of State for coming to the House to deal with it.  The matter relates to the Government's plans for making new temporary appointments to the board of An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  I hope the Minister of State will outline what those plans are and make a statement on them.</p> <p>None of us needs a lesson on An Bord Plean&aacute;la and the lack of confidence in the board among many members of the public.  I acknowledge, as I have done all along, that there is a place for An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  It needs to be restructured and reconstituted, and needs greater focus and clarity.  Above all, it needs to communicate its decisions in a timely manner and to explain in greater detail decisions to overturn its inspectors' decisions or recommendations.  This is presenting difficulties for members of the public who do not quite understand the dynamic between the inspectors and the board itself.  It creates a feeling that there is a tension there and they cannot understand it.  There has to be such a tension and I accept that the board has to take decisions.</p> <p>I do not subscribe to the idea of scrapping An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  I support its work and acknowledge there are great people in it doing their best.  There are, however, challenges and difficulties.  I hope An Bord Plean&aacute;la can bounce back and build a strong, confident relationship with the people it represents and rebuild the professionalism it has shown in the past in the area of planning and determining planning appeals.</p> <p>I understand from media reports that the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage will appoint temporary members to fill a number of vacancies on the board.  I also understand the board needs its full complement of board members because while there are ongoing investigations, the board still has to do its work.  The chairman needs to have a full board and its members need to work together constructively.  I understand there are only six board members still in place in the crisis-hit planning authority.  As I said, An Bord Plean&aacute;la is the subject of ongoing investigation and it would not be appropriate for the Minister of State or me to comment on the series of investigations.  Clearly, there will be structural reform.  We need a full complement of board members and we need to rebuild confidence in it.</p> <p>I am conscious that there needs to be greater clarity about the Minister's intentions.  Will all the new board members be ministerial appointees?  Will the Minister seek public servants to fill the temporary positions?  What is temporary?  I presume it is for a period of up to 12 months because that is the time it will take to put in place the new structures.  Is the Minister of State in a position to indicate whether these or future appointments will be filled by the Public Appointments Service?  That is an open and transparent way to do this and it is particularly important.  I accept that there is chronic understaffing and there are rushed decisions and that the board is not always in a position to determine decisions within the specified timeframe, which is an issue.  In essence, I am asking what the Minister's short-term plans are for filling the current vacancies on the board and what his long-term plans are for bringing in people to serve on the board.</p> <p>I will finish on this point.  There is a case for allowing the representative bodies, the Local Authority Members Association, LAMA, and the Association of Irish Local Government, AILG, not necessarily to nominate members to the board but to nominate persons who could be considered by an independent appointments commission.  There is a way to move away from having ministerial appointments to the board.  While the Minister could make recommendations and put forward names, ultimately there has to be an independent system for making appointments to the new board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#A00700"><p>I thank Senator Boyhan for his comments on the necessity of An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  He and I interact regularly on the issue of public participation in our planning system.  He feels it is vitally important that we have a robust planning system in which members of the public can have confidence and in which they have a right to participate on the basis of parity.  I commend the Senator on that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Malcolm Noonan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmNoonan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> On 4 October, following Government approval, the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, published an action plan for An Bord Plean&aacute;la which was informed by phase 1 of the review by the Office of the Planning Regulator of certain systems and procedures used by An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  The action plan outlines several measures relating to the board appointment process, structure, capacity and operations within An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  Its intention is to underpin public confidence in the efficacy and ability of An Bord Plean&aacute;la to decide cases in a timely manner while supporting the values of independence, impartiality and integrity.  A number of the proposed actions contained in the action plan require legislative underpinning.  Some of these will be pursued as part of the review of the planning legislation currently being led by the Attorney General but other measures including a new regime of recruitment for appointments to An Bord Plean&aacute;la require more immediate legislative underpinning and will be addressed in the planning, development and foreshore (amendment) Bill 2022, the general scheme of which will be published shortly.</p><p>The Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended, currently provides for the board of An Bord Plean&aacute;la to consist of a chairperson appointed by the Government and nine ordinary members appointed by the Minister.  Action 10 of the action plan specifically relates to the new regime of recruitment for board appointments to An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  The aforementioned legislation which received Government approval for priority drafting on 4 October 2022 will remove the nominating bodies system for board appointments to An Bord Plean&aacute;la and replace it with an open competition process to recruit suitably qualified candidates with the necessary range of skill sets to serve on the board.  As an interim measure, the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, is also advancing the recruitment of a board member with environmental expertise, particularly in relation to marine matters under section 106(1)(e) of the Planning and Development Act 2000, as amended, in a manner similar to the proposed new arrangements outlined in the action plan.  In addition, a number of temporary appointments will be made in line with the provisions of the current Act.  Under the new board, members are recruited under the new arrangements.  </p><p>As detailed in action 13 of the action plan, it is the intention that board membership should be increased as part of the new, more immediate legislation to allow for new functions and sufficient rotation of members across different classes of files.</p><p>The Senator put forward a proposal about LAMA and the AILG.  As the Minister outlines it is an open process and it is important to have that environmental, ecological and water expertise in An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  Given the broad range of legislation and the broad range of environmental climate considerations that now have to be taken into account, it is a vitally important part of it, but the Minister is committed to ensuring An Bord Plean&aacute;la is fit for purpose and is able to serve the planning interests of the country well and serve the broader community and the ambitions of the State in respect of proper spatial planning.  That is something we all want to achieve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#B00200"><p>The Minister of State is absolutely correct as regards maritime issues.  We have seen maritime legislation and the Maritime Area Regulatory Authority, MARA, and all of the bits of legislation around that.  That is an important complement to any new board.  The heavy emphasis on environmental issues is important because many of those subsequently become challenges and are referred for judicial review.  Planning should not be determined by judicial review.  I understand why it goes down that road, but we need a better, more robust system.  I fully acknowledge the importance of maritime and environmental expertise on the board but it is important that local government can contribute in some way.  It does not necessarily have to have the final say but that it can contribute.  I would like to think this new legislation will not exclude former city or county councillors.  They bring a certain amount of expertise.  That is something we can tease out in the legislation.  I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#B00300"><p>I thank the Senator for his positive contribution and that is certainly something I can take to the Minister.  We have to hugely value the role of any expertise many former elected members have brought to local government over many years.  They have expertise in formulating development plans and setting the agenda at local level for how our communities are planned.  While An Bord Plean&aacute;la has been through an incredibly challenging time, we see the positive outcomes of this report and the intent of the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, to address this issue and deal with it.  He has acted swiftly and decisively.  We need a board that is fit for purpose, able to meet the broader environmental climate challenges but can also plan this country in a sustainable way that is future-proofed for future generations.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#B00400">Planning Issues</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#B00500"><p>The next Commencement matter is from Senator Paul Daly &ndash; the need for  the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to consider amending section 42 of the Planning and Development Act 2000 to allow for changes to conditions for the extension of planning permissions for one-off rural housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#B00600"><p>I welcome and thank the Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, for coming in to take this Commencement matter.</p><p>I will read the Commencement matter again to highlight some issues in it.  It is to request that the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage would relax the conditions for the extension of planning permission for one-off housing under section 42(1)(b) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 in light of delays caused by Covid and now the inflation in construction costs, which could result in many planning permissions granted in 2018 expiring in 2023 with parties being unable to commence construction in the time period.</p><p>I specifically included one-off housing because if my request were to be successful, the last thing I or anyone would want is a <i>carte blanche</i>extension.  We are all aware that people are reputedly hoarding development sites and this might give them a window to extend that period of hoarding.  I am specifically asking that consideration be given for people who had planning permission for one-off housing.  </p><p>The reason for the request is that a number of people have contacted me with quite genuine reasons they are unlikely to be able to commence construction before their planning permission expires.  For example, people whose banks reneged on their mortgage when they went on the employment wage subsidy scheme and they ended back at square 1.  Some people could not get builders because of the lockdown.  Two years were basically lost in every sphere of life and some people are still in the situation of having Covid-related health issues, be it long-Covid or whatever.  It has put a stall to their gallop, to coin a phrase.  They may get started but at the moment the conditions state they must have a reasonable amount of work done and in most cases councils will insist that is up to wall plate level.  This is unlikely to happen before their planning expires in 2023.</p><p>Provisions were made during Covid for planning permissions that were granted during that period of time and that expires at the end of 2023.  It is well worth considering or looking at this again.  As I have said, I am not requesting it be done in a <i>carte blanche</i>fashion.  If it were to happen, I would include conditions that people have to apply and give plausible reasons as to why they could not proceed for the council to examine on a case-by-case basis.  It is unfair where people have genuine Covid related reasons and indeed when we got out of Covid we entered the construction inflation period which again is a hindrance to many people.  People have genuine reasons for not being able to proceed, for maybe not being able to commence on time, but they still genuinely intend to go ahead.  If they were allowed to make a case, without being required to have commenced and to have reached a specific level with their house, it would be of benefit to the one-off housing market in rural Ireland.  I stress again, as I did at the outset, I specifically made this request about one-off housing.  The last thing I want to start is a process from which people who are hoarding larger development sites benefit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#B00700"><p>The duration of a planning permission is generally set at five years, but the planning authority may grant shorter or longer durations with a maximum duration of ten years available for residential development, for example.  Section 42 of the Planning and Development Act enables a planning authority to extend the initial duration of a planning permission, providing certain conditions are met.</p> <p>A package of measures was introduced in September 2021 to amend section 42 and related provisions in the Planning and Development Act regulations.  This included, among other things, a new temporary provision in section 42(1B) which was introduced in response to construction delays as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic, to provide for a further extension of duration for planning permission by an additional period of up to two years or until 31 December 2023, whichever first occurs, subject to certain requirements being met.  Section 28(1) of the Planning and Development (Housing) and Residential Tenancies Act 2016 was commenced.  This provision deleted section 42(1)(a)(ii) of the Planning and Development Act.  This removes the possibility of an extension of duration for uncommenced development or development where substantial work has not been carried out.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Malcolm Noonan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmNoonan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Section 42(8) of the Planning and Development Act 2000 was introduced to provide that a planning authority shall not extend the appropriate period of a planning permission if an environmental impact assessment or appropriate assessment is required in relation to the proposed extension.  As such, a planning authority can only grant an extension of duration where it is satisfied that the development has commenced; substantial works have been completed; the development will be completed in a reasonable time; and the environmental impact assessment and appropriate assessment are not required for the proposed extension.<br/><br/>Cognisant of the recent impacts of Covid-19 on the construction industry, section 42(1B) provides, on a temporary basis, for further extensions in respect of planning permissions which have already availed of an extension in duration by up to an additional two years or until 31 December 2023, whichever occurs first.  This will facilitate the completion of developments already commenced and with substantial works carried out, which were delayed or interrupted due to the impacts of Covid-19 on construction activity.  This further extension period takes into account the restrictions on construction and disruptions in logistics, supply chains, etc., as a result of the Covid-19 pandemic.<br/><br/>While there may be legitimate reasons that a holder of a planning permission may not have commenced or carried out substantial works under that planning permission, to allow for an extension or further extension of duration beyond their initial duration of five years, or possibly more, in such circumstances would conflict with the Department's objective to expedite the activation of planning permissions and the completion of developments that have substantial work already carried out, particularly with respect to delivery of housing.<br/><br/>Any interventions in this area must have a positive effect on development and must incentivise holders of a planning permission to activate and complete planning permissions to the greatest extent possible, as soon as possible, particularly with respect to housing developments.  Accordingly, it is not considered appropriate to provide for extensions of duration of planning permissions for developments that have not been commenced or have not been substantially completed within the initial duration of their planning permission.<br/><br/>The Department is mindful that construction costs have risen considerably over recent years, as the Senator has pointed out.  Extensive mitigation measures have been implemented in collaboration with other Departments and agencies to address the increasing cost by, <i>inter alia</i>, increasing efficiency and innovation, including the advancement of modern methods of construction, MMC; a national demonstration park; a construction technology centre; the Built to Innovate campaign; and the progression of a residential construction cost study.  I hope this response is of some use in answering the question the Senator put to me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#C00200"><p>The response was informative but not very positive in respect of my query.  I ask the Minister of State again if this matter could be addressed.  I am not looking for extensions to planning permissions across the board.  We are all aware of the two years we just had.  People are trying to get back to normality.  While a five-year window may sound like a long time, it becomes a very narrow window when the two years of the pandemic are subtracted, especially in cases where people's circumstances have changed.  There is a case for giving consideration to special circumstances, on a case-by-case basis, through an application process with criteria for genuine people.  I appreciate the urgency involved and the reasons the legislation seeks to expedite the activation of planning.  However, letting planning go because people cannot commence construction, for genuine reasons, will possibly result in the loss of a house or houses.  I would appreciate if this matter could be considered from a human perspective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#C00300"><p>I welcome a group of young boys and girls to the Chamber.  I am not sure what school they are from.  It is great to see them engaging with politics at such a young age.  Some of them might be sitting here in a few decades' time.  I extend a warm welcome to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#C00400"><p>They are from Stepaside.  It is great to have them here.</p> <p>I thank the Senator.  My response probably did not give him much comfort in relation to the individuals he represents.  I urge them to engage, on a case-by-case basis, with their local authority planners.  That is the point of contact.  The Department does not have plans to introduce further legislation to extend planning permission.  It is open to individuals who cannot avail of an extension of duration to reapply for planning permission.  I have tremendous sympathy for anyone who has been caught in that cycle or whose banks have rescinded mortgages because of circumstances or due to Covid-19.  It is critically important that they engage and I hope they will be able to advance plans for their homes.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.23" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#C00450">General Practitioner Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#C00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Anne Rabbitte, to the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#C00700"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking the time to be here.  She and I attended a meeting on Monday evening in the Shearwater Hotel at which GPs from the Ballinasloe and south-east Galway area came together.  They came from group practices, including the Marina House and Dunlo medical centres, which are well known in Ballinasloe town.  These cover a huge area, not only of County Galway but also of south County Roscommon because we are right on the county boundary.  It includes places like Taghmaconnell, Moore, Aughrim and Clontuskert.  We also had GPs representing single practices, including Dr. Mary Murphy from Laurencetown health centre, Dr. Ranga from the Eyrecourt medical centre and Dr. Ferguson from Kiltormer health centre.  Kilconnell, where there is a locum and no GP, was also represented.</p> <p>As the Minister of State will be aware, I and other public representative have raised this matter for the past number of years.  The network of GPs in the area provides an excellent service 24 hours per day, 365 days a year.  They do night-time and weekend cover.  These GPs are suffering, as are patients and families in the region.  We have a crisis because people cannot access Westdoc supports.  Westdoc, which is co-funded by the HSE, can provide cover and support GP networks all around the county.  There are challenging areas, including east and south-east Galway.  Portumna, which is in the Minister of State's area, is a big challenge, as is Moycullen.  These are areas of the west that face a huge challenge in recruitment and retention.  How on earth can we attract quality GPs to start a life, live in our region and perform an invaluable service to our community?  The GP is the first point of call for people getting health checks, X-rays or blood tests or dealing with a family crisis.  How is the State supporting the GP network in east and south-east Galway?  How are we going to recruit?  The HSE had to bring a locum into Kilconnell and there are other locums because there are about ten vacancies in the west.  These locums are costing approximately &euro;180,000 each.</p> <p>All of the local public representatives attended the meeting on Monday, as did HSE representatives from Community Healthcare West.  I am grateful they were able to attend.  They highlighted that the cost of a locum in Kiltormer was &euro;180,000 and that the overall cost of cover with Westdoc was roughly &euro;528,000.  The HSE group in the area submitted requests last year and the year before that but no funding is arriving and none has been allocated.  GPs in the area are at crisis point.  We have heard stories, as has the Minister of State, of GPs working for 40 hours straight.  They then have to get into a car and travel.  This is putting doctors and patients at risk.  There is no EU working time directive for GPs.  We need to protect our GPs and ensure they have a good work-life balance.  I know the Minister of State has been supportive on this issue.  She spoke with the GPs who attended, including Dr. Genevieve Flynn and Dr. Jennings, women who are working in our region.  What about bringing in young GPs, including young women GPs with families?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aisling Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AislingDolan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->How on earth are young GPs, GPs with families, going to support doing a one-in-eight rota and trying to work 13 days in a row?  These are doctors who have not taken a break since January and are afraid to bring locums in because, if they do, the locums will not provide the same level of service as they do and how are they going to be responsible for their community?  There is a commitment and a diligence to patients in our local area.</p><p>I have written a letter to the Minister for Health, Deputy Donnelly.  I know the Minister of State has mentioned we might potentially be able to hold a meeting.  This is something I have raised over recent years, as have GPs, but we need a solution.  Is this going to come out of the winter service plan or from the budget that has been allocated for GP visit cards, where it has been stated there is extra budget for GPs and the GP network?  We have expanded the GP cards now to people under the median income from April of next year.  Where are the funds with which we can support our GPs right now?  I do not want to lose any more GPs in my region and I am responsible for that Ballinasloe to south-east Galway area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#D00200"><p>I am also responsible for the people of south-east Galway, and the Senator is quite right.  We attended that meeting the other night and it is important to share here that a selection of GPs from right across the Ballinasloe, Kilconnell, Kiltormer, Eyrecourt, Lawrencetown area were in attendance.  There was one outlier, a Dr. Fahey, who came with me came from Portumna to attend.  The whole purpose of the meeting was to ensure the creation of a cell in what I would deem technically the Ballinasloe area and to highlight the need for this.  As the Senator can see from the response from the Department, no additional funding has been approved to this request.  The &euro;528,000 that was sought from the HSE for the creation of this cell has not been approved under the budgetary allocation.  I could come to the House and give a very fluffy answer, skirt around the edges and not give it exactly as it is.  As it is, no funding in budget 2023 has been allocated for the creation of a new cell in the proposal that has been forwarded by the HSE.</p> <p>What has been awarded is &euro;2.5 million to the HSE in the west to ensure the continuation of the HSE Westdoc practices currently in operation.  That is &euro;2.5 million that is to go all the way across an area that covers CHO 2, which we discussed at length the other night.  We saw how much investment was made in 2021 and 2022, but now we have a real figure as to what that comes to.  It comes to &euro;2.5 million for Westdoc in our area, but it completely excludes everything from the bridge in Portumna to the bridge in Banagher, all the way to south Roscommon to the areas and the GPs the Senator talks about, including the Ballinasloe area.</p> <p>What concerns me greatly, and I raised this with the Minister, Deputy Donnelly, is that the GPs in the Ballinasloe area have served notice to withdraw their weekend cover from 1 December.  There were very clear about that.  If that were to happen, it would be the first time in 50 years that our GPs would have withdrawn from providing a service but also the first time in 50 years they have would terminated themselves out of a contract.  They are contracted, of course, but not supported.  In fairness to the Minister, Deputy Donnelly, when I met him, he suggested, just as the Senator has, discussing the winter plan to see if there was capacity there to support GPs.  To be fair to the Minister as well, I only sprang this on him yesterday.  The Senator was very rapid in tabling the Commencement matter, so I have not had the space to have that conversation with the Minister and with my elected representatives from the area who were present the other night.  They heard about the very concerning effects this is having on the protection of females within the practices and the out-of-hours services, and the pressure it is putting them under.  There is also the health and safety piece but we also have to ensure we can maintain people within the practices and attract people into the practices in the area.</p> <p>I am confident we will meet the Minister, Deputy Donnelly.  We are still trying to figure out his availability.  There may even be tonight after the voting block.  I am not saying this is definite but we are looking for that space.  The Minister has talked to me about the winter plan.  There are two parts in this conversation.  There is the Ballinasloe set and there is the Portumna piece.  The latter is on three borders and the country boundaries of Clare, Tipperary and Galway.  To be fair to those in Ballinasloe, they were never part of that arrangement and I do not think they wish to be part of it either, because that would mean Westdoc would be covering from Roscommon town all the way up to Portumna and to Lawrencetown.  That is not feasible either if we are to ensure a proper delivery of a Westdoc service.  We have a Portumna piece but we also have the creation of a new GP cell in Ballinasloe.  When we get to meet the Minister, it is to be hoped we will be able to articulate, as the Senator has put eloquently, the need for representation for our GPs but also the need for the delivery of support in the area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#D00300"><p>I know this is not an easy situation but we need that meeting with the Minister, as the Minister of State has mentioned.  That has to happen.  It is incredible to say we cannot support a network of GPs who are, as the Minister of State said, entering into retirement age and who have no support in place.  We cannot talk about legacy issues here because right now we are talking about families and people living in Galway and south Roscommon who will not have access to GP support. They will not have access and yet we are saying we will expand the GP visit card and will have spent the largest ever HSE budget last year and will spend the largest ever this year.  Despite this, we will not be doing anything about GPs, Sl&aacute;intecare or supporting families on the ground, even though GPs are the first point of contact when it comes to medical issues, mental health issues and trying to make sure our families are supported.  I am frustrated and I know GPs will be very frustrated with the fact there is nothing in the budget this year to support Westdoc and an expansion of its services.  It needs to happen.  It is not enough that the HSE has been asking for this and has been putting in submissions year after year for the past five years asking for support and it has not happened.  That is not good enough.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#D00400"><p>Let us be very clear.  The Department funds the HSE.  We give the HSE the money and it is up to it to operationalise it.  How the HSE decides to do this is out of my control as much as it is out of the control of the Senator.  In any case, the HSE get the funds to operationalise it wherever it deems it necessary.  The HSE obviously does not deem south-east Galway a priority within its allocation of funding.  To get &euro;4 million and not see Ballinasloe as a priority to me is wilful neglect.  That is what it is.  I call on the HSE to go back to the drawing board and reallocate its funding to see equality for our GPs right across the county, not in particular areas where operational cells are easy to work.  Operational cells that are difficult, like those in Ballinasloe, need to be addressed head on.  The HSE needs to reprioritise its &euro;4 million because it is not good enough that the likes of a GP in Portumna gets a half day off every weekend.  That is not sustainable, it is not good work-life balance and it is not good for their mental health.  I will work with the Senator on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#D00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her time.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.31" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#D00550">Ukraine War</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#D00600"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, to the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#D00700"><p>I welcome the announcement that the Government has reversed the decision in Killarney.  It was a very welcome development that, once it was drawn to the attention of Government, it operated in a very humane and quick way.  It is regrettable it got to that stage.  However, I very much appreciate and welcome that this morning.</p> <p>When we began welcoming and supporting the families fleeing Ukraine due to this horrific and illegal war, we anticipated a six-month timeframe and we talked in these terms when families were asked to open their homes and support Ukrainians coming to Ireland.  I appreciate that the situation escalated and continues to go on.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In the last few days there have been further atrocities with bombings and missile strikes on Kyiv, and on Lviv only yesterday.  The war in Ukraine will go on for much longer than we anticipated or hoped and I appreciate that the war has put staff and certainly the officials in the Department under huge pressure.  I wish to pay tribute to departmental staff, particularly those in Citywest whom I know work extraordinary hours and well beyond what normally is demanded as part of their job descriptions because of their sheer passion for supporting Ukrainian families.</p><p>I tabled this matter long before what happened in Killarney.  In the last few weeks a number of families have approached me to tell me that the Ukrainians who are staying with them are worried that as their six months stay is coming to an end they will have to return to Ukraine or wonder what is the best course of action.  I know of one instance that occurred in a conversation I had last night where I learned that one mother had informed the school attended by her children that the family would be leaving because their accommodation was going to finish this month and that situation had consequences for SNA hours for a child.</p><p>There is uncertainty with regard to Ukrainians staying with families.  Perhaps there are Irish families who initially opened up their homes and now need to be assured that support will continue, and to have certainty that the Government is engaged with the ongoing plight of the Ukrainians and will provide families with supports.</p><p>My main question is about communication.  I appreciate that this is a fluid situation and that everyone does their best but clarity is absent.  Can the Department ask people to extend their accommodation for a further six months?  The State has committed to at least a further six months but I contend that ideally the period should be a year because Ukrainians would have no homes to return to even if the war ends.  I believe that there is a necessity for us to visit the fact that those initial commitment periods are now ending and, therefore, a solution must be provided.  Will people be housed elsewhere?  I would prefer if people could stay where they are because they have already come from trauma and are only a short period in Ireland.  I would prefer if people were allowed to stay where they are as they have now built up networks, taken jobs and are part of a community.  We certainly have a desire and a need to communicate stability and clarity in order to give Ukrainians some level of certainty and comfort.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter in terms of the operation of the pledge process.</p> <p>Since the outbreak of the war in Ukraine on 24 February, and the activation of the temporary protection directive shortly afterwards, my Department has worked intensively as part of the cross-governmental response to the Ukraine crisis.  My Department is focused on the immediate, short-term accommodation needs of those who fled here.  To date, 52,000 people have arrived in Ireland from Ukraine of which more than 41,000 people are being accommodated by my Department and we are also accommodating people in the international protection process.  All of that creates real challenges in terms of the delivery of accommodation and I think that we are all aware of that.</p> <p>The Government is committed to delivering a humanitarian response to the needs of people from Ukraine and providing shelter and safety for these individuals.  The response by the public has been huge.  We have seen that in communities all around the country but we have particularly seen it in the context of the pledge process.  Early on we put in place a pledge process with the Irish Red Cross and a very significant number of pledges were made.  We have worked closely with a number of implementation partners such as the International Organization for Migration, the Peter McVerry Trust and all 31 local authorities.</p> <p>I note that there were some initial delays with the pledge process but by and large it has worked well.  At this point over 4,500 Ukrainians have been accommodated around the country.  More than 10% of the Ukrainians that the State is accommodating are accommodated in accommodation that was pledged.</p> <p>As Senators will know, earlier this year my Department introduced the &euro;400 recognition payment.  The payment is just recognition and gives some support to the families who have either pledged vacant accommodation or rooms within their own home.  The payment has been availed of by 3,500 applicants who are hosting over 7,500 Ukrainians.  Again, we made the payment open not just to those who had gone through the official pledge process but those who brought Ukrainians into their homes through other channels.</p> <p>Obviously we would hope that at the end of a six-month pledge period a family would look to extend the period and we would look to support that.  However, that may not always be possible.  Where an arrangement comes to an end the implementation partners, whom I referenced earlier, will work with the Ukrainian beneficiaries and the local authorities to seek alternative pledged accommodation.  Where this is not possible then the beneficiaries will have to return to our transit hub in Citywest for the allocation of suitable alternative State-sourced accommodation.  We will try to do what the Senator said is the preferred option, which is to locate people somewhere local but we can make no commitments to do that.</p> <p>I have to be very upfront in terms of the difficulties being experienced and pressures on my Department.  What happened yesterday in Killarney is another example of that very real and immediate pressure that the Department is under to provide accommodation.  We cannot give guarantees but we will always do our best.  This morning, we were able to find a solution for the Killarney situation but there is no guarantee that a solution can be found for every situation.  That reflects the unprecedented scale of this crisis and the uncertainty because in the last month the number of Ukrainians arriving has doubled from 700 a week at the start of September to 1,500 a week, which puts real pressure on international protection.  We are operating to try and move people into alternative pledged accommodation where their pledged accommodation has come to an end or to extend the pledges.  We will do our best but we cannot give guarantees.</p> <p>I take the point the Senator made about communication and communication is important.  We can do better in terms of communication on the Department side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#E00300"><p>I acknowledge the exceptional welcome and generous actions by Irish people.</p> <p>An issue arose in Killarney because the accommodation was continuing but with replacement people which created a curious and unnecessary situation.  If there is a family who have completed their six-month pledge of accommodation and genuinely do not want to renew then that is fine but people will need to be relocated to wherever there is accommodation.  I am sure we all appreciate that the spirit is to accommodate as much as possible.</p> <p>I urge that families are communicated with and asked whether their pledge of accommodation is open-ended or whether they can commit for another six months.  I make that suggestion because at least if people sign up their accommodation for another six months then the Ukrainian people staying with them will have certainty, particularly as these Ukrainian people are already in a precarious position.  This is not a leasehold arrangement, and neither should it be, but extending the pledge will give people clarity and certainty.  In addition, language difficulties will lead to a further anomaly.</p> <p>I appreciate that the Minister has committed to ensuring there is communication. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1477" speakername="Roderic O'Gorman" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#E00400"><p>An extension of a further six months provides very real certainty to Ukrainians and provides certainty to my Department.  We are seeing situations where pledges have ended and people have had to go to Citywest thus requiring us to find new accommodation for them.  We will find new accommodation for people but such movement adds to the  pressures on the Department.  I will certainly look for my pledge team to place some of its focus on the renewal of pledges while at the same time look to develop further pledges.</p> <p>In terms of Killarney, the key point is that we seek two types of accommodation at all times - accommodation for Ukrainians and accommodation for international protection.  It is incredibly difficult to source accommodation for international protection.  We had to avail of the opportunity at the hotel in Killarney because we all saw what happened when we did not secure enough accommodation and international protection applicants ended up sleeping rough on our streets.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Roderic O'Gorman:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RodericOGorman&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a situation I wish to avoid repeating but I cannot give that guarantee because the housing situation is so incredibly tight right now.  This is the vista I am looking at.  It is for this reason and this reason alone that the Department proposed to move the Ukrainians from Killarney to Westport.  In this situation we have been able to find alternative accommodation in Killarney for them and they will be moved there shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.39" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 11.20 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 11.33 a.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 11.20 a.m. and resumed at 11.33 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.40" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#G00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#G00200"><p>I welcome the Spanish ambassador to Ireland, H.E. Ildefonso Castro.  He is most welcome to the Seanad on the National Day of Spain.  It is a day of recognition of the genuine democratic nature of modern Spain.  This year also commemorates another significant event.  It marks 530 years since the expedition of Christopher Columbus reached America.  This year also marks the 500th anniversary of Juan Sebasti&aacute;n de Elcano's first circumnavigation of the globe.  We share a long and distinguished history and friendship dating to the 16th century with the Treaty of Dingle, in my county, which was signed in 1529.  Throughout our shared history, there has been constant communication and travel.  Our pilgrims have travelled the Camino de Santiago, going to the city where the ambassador went to university.  He is familiar with our weather, having described the weather in his part of Spain as "Galway weather".  It is weather he is very much used to.  It was that part of the world the earls went to during the Flight of the Earls, and the Irish colleges founded there helped to preserve the distinct cultural identify and facilitated Ireland's engagement with the wider world.</p> <p>There are more than 40,000 Irish citizens living in Spain and nearly 12,000 Spanish citizens living in Ireland, and they are most welcome.  We hold the second largest share of the EU market in the teaching of English with 35,000 Spanish students coming here to learn the English language annually.  Their presence adds to our society and economy, but their interaction with our students is also deeply appreciated and we build on that connection.  The Spanish Prime Minister, Pedro S&aacute;nchez, spent some of his adolescence in Ireland.  He was one of those students who came here and probably spent some time on Grafton Street.  He is, as are thousands of Spanish students, familiar with Ireland.</p> <p>On Spain's national day, I thank the ambassador for coming to Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  We greatly appreciate his presence and thank him for coming.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.42" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#G00300">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#G00400"><p>I thank Ambassador Ildefonso Castro for coming to the Seanad and for his service to Ireland; I wish him continued success.</p> <p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on the report of the Commission of Investigation (IBRC) on the transaction in relation to Siteserv, to be taken at 2 p.m., to conclude at 2.30 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, all Senators not to exceed seven minutes, on which time may be shared, and the Minister is to be given no less than five minutes to reply to the debate; No. 114 (4), Private Members' business, motion on breast-feeding, to be taken at 4 p.m. with the time allocated to the debate not to exceed two hours; and No. 2, Air Navigation and Transport Bill 2020 &ndash; Committee Stage (Resumed), to be taken at 6 p.m. or on conclusion of No. 114 (4), whichever is the later, and to adjourn at 8 p.m. if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#G00500"><p>I join the Cathaoirleach and the Leader in extending a c&eacute;ad m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte to the ambassador.  He has now left the Chamber but we were delighted to have him in the Seanad.</p> <p>When we returned to the Chamber yesterday after the weekend, we spoke about the sadness of all that happened in Creeslough.  All of a sudden last night, a lady named Amber Barrett lit a light.  Anyone who knows Donegal and the region from Kerrykeel, Portsalon and Milford to Creeslough will know that what happened on Friday affected not only all Donegal people but also Amber Barrett.  It was remarkable and wonderful to see her go down on her two knees, grab her armband and kiss it, and dedicate that wonderful goal, which means the Irish ladies football team will go to the World Cup, to those ten people.  At an extraordinary time of depressing and sad news this week, I do not know about the Cathaoirleach or the rest of the Senators but I find it very hard to be joyous.  It was such a terrible occurrence that it is hard to go about one's business in the usual way, yet last night, Amber Barrett lit that light.  It was like a night-light appearing out of the dark.  In some way, it must be great news for Donegal, despite all the trauma and tragedy.  We heard her refer to her grandparents who come from Creeslough and live in the area.  She is an extraordinary young woman.  Along with everybody, I extend my sincere congratulations to the Irish football team and Vera Pauw, an extraordinary woman.  I am sure the Government will put adequate funding in place to help them with their World Cup trip.  It will be great to see the Tricolour there.  There is something special about the team, the management and the players.  They all seem so united and happy as a group and it is a wonderful thing to watch.  I would not miss any of their matches on TV and I hope to go in person to some of them shortly.  It was a fantastic night.</p> <p>I raise a new programme by Agri Aware that we should promote.  The initiative, Farming Through the Seasons, enables Irish schoolchildren to learn all about what happens on Irish farms from farmers themselves.  Agri Aware launched this plan to provide virtual farm visits for all schools.  I understand there is a large take-up at present and I urge all schools to get involved.  I know the Leader agreed with me on my next point some months ago.  We should all realise how important agriculture still is to the economy.  It is worth &euro;14.5 billion in exports and employs several hundred thousand people on farms and in agribusiness.  It is a major contributor to our economy.  Sometimes we do not realise the great product we have that is recognised throughout the world - Irish food.  Even in terms of where crops come from, as some people do not know, this initiative will be a wonderful experience.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eugene Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2444"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2444&amp;amp;pid=EugeneMurphy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I urge all schools to become involved in it.  It is a wonderful thing to do.  We will help to promote it in any way we can.  I am certainly doing my bit for it today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H00200"><p>I also welcome the Spanish ambassador to the Chamber.  I join the Senators who yesterday paid tribute to the families, friends and neighbours of the people of Creeslough following the tragic loss of ten human lives.  I extend the sympathies and condolences of the House to them on their tragic loss.  What happened was unbelievable.</p> <p>I raise an issue in regard to some organisations that are anti-drink.  They express reservations about Drinkaware, arguing that the organisation should have no influence on the promotion of education for people in regard to anti-drinking because it is funded by the drinks companies.  Some of the organisations in question are funded by the taxpayer and taxes are collected from drink and cigarettes.  This is a case of double standards.  Any organisation that can help to prevent excessive drinking and the abuse of drink and drugs is to be welcomed.  I welcome anything that Drinkaware does in promoting an anti-drinking and anti-drugs message.  It is a bit rich of organisations to complain about those who are doing great work because they are funded by drinks companies when the organisations in question are themselves funded by the taxpayer and money collected from taxes paid through drink and cigarettes. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H00300"><p>I have a question.  I want to move a motion and I wonder if I need a seconder.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H00400"><p>Yes.  The motion can be seconded later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H00500"><p>I propose to move No. 114, motion 3.  This is a motion related to the matter of the current pay claim sought under the scheme for Senators&rsquo; secretarial assistance to make a recommendation to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform that Seanad secretarial assistants be permanently regraded to the role and remuneration of parliamentary assistants.  I hope I will have a seconder later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H00600"><p>The Senator has moved an amendment, that No. 114, motion 3, be taken without debate on the conclusion of the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H00700"><p>I second that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H00800"><p>Senator Clonan will have to be here for the conclusion of the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H00900"><p>I would like to know what is going on with the Intreo office for Dublin 7.  I have raised this issue a number of times.  I have written to the Minister and requested a meeting with him.  Indeed, I asked the Leader to request that the Minister meet members of the local community.  More than 1,500 people have signed a petition calling for the Intreo office for Dublin 7 to be reopened.  The office serves the communities of the Navan Road, Cabra, Phibsborough and Stoneybatter.  I am sure Senators are familiar with the area, which has a population of more than 10,000.  When the office was initially closed in April, we were told it was being closed temporarily and that there would be no interruption or change to services and that some maintenance and upgrading works were to be undertaken on the building.  In July, I was told the building situation was being reviewed and there had been an increase in costs due to construction inflation but, again, there was no significant change proposed to the services.  I have now heard that the office is closed permanently and that a division of the Garda will be relocated to it on a temporary basis.  This means that 40 front-line staff who would present a human face, on behalf of the State, to people in need when they apply for a service have been unilaterally and without consultation withdrawn from the community of Dublin 7.</p> <p>Let us stop and think for a moment.  In the middle of a cost-of-living crisis, which type of people would be affected by this?  The reply I have received has suggested that people go online, make a phone call or download a form.  That is the type of approach that a commercial entity, a bank or other entity that does not have a social conscience or social responsibility, might take.  To give an example, people who are looking for the additional needs payment cannot apply for it online because there is not a portal to do so.  They now need to get a form, fill it out and submit it.  God knows, when they will receive a reply or any other form of human interaction.  The same goes for the supplementary welfare allowance.  There were no fewer than ten welfare officers serving the Dublin 7 community in that office.</p> <p>This decision is hugely disappointing.  It is devastating for the local community.  I ask the Leader to use her offices on behalf of the people of Dublin 7 to address this issue with the Minister.  I will also be addressing it through my Fianna F&aacute;il Parliamentary Party channels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H01000"><p>Yesterday, I read in the <i>Irish Examiner</i>an article from 1985 about Cork County Council being under exceptional financial pressure with its budget and needing &pound;2.3 million to stay afloat.  I read the <i>Irish Examiner</i>today, 37 years later, and it features a similar headline.  The council now needs &euro;24 million to stay afloat.  It is amazing that this issue occurs on a continuous basis.  How do we fund our local authorities and ensure they are providing appropriate services for the people?  I was opposed to the new arrangement in Cork when the city boundaries were extended, taking the rate base away from the county.  We are seeing the knock-on effect of that decision now.  According to the <i>Irish Examiner</i>, we have a local authority in a county the size of Cork writing to three senior Ministers asking them to intervene in order that it can have sustainable funding going forward.</p><p>It is appropriate at this time to have a wide debate about local authority funding and how and where it is provided.  We also need to debate the role of the Office of the Comptroller and Auditor General in regard to local authorities and if it should have a say on whether they are spending money appropriately.  Over the past 40 years, we have put a plaster over a gushing wound.  We need a root-and-branch review of what happens and how it happens to make sure we do not have another headline of the same nature in 37 years' time. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#H01100"><p>I ask the Leader to organise a debate on the changes proposed under the 2023 Common Agricultural Policy, CAP, programme.  For some years now, the Burren region of County Clare has been a specially designated zone under the Burren programme, which was developed by Dr. Brendan Dunford.  It is about the appropriate management of the grassland that makes up the Burren, done in a sympathetic way with nature, working with the farmers in the region to ensure the environment is not just protected but enhanced and allowed to develop in an appropriate way.</p> <p>I understand the plans for the new agri-climate rural environment scheme, ACRES, as opposed to the green low-carbon agri-environment scheme, GLAS, and rural environment protection schemes, REPS, that went before, will have a significant impact on farmers on the designated zone of the Burren.  The plan is to widen the designation to include many other areas, including in south Galway, the islands and a wider part of County Clare.  While this is to be welcomed, unfortunately the devil is in the detail.  It now seems that those who have done an immense amount of work in a sympathetic way to protect and preserve the fauna and flora of the region are going to be at a disadvantage.  It now looks like the average payments made in the past will become the maximum payments.  That is perhaps good for those in the wider region who will see an increased benefit.  However, those in the core area of the Burren will take a significant hit or cut in payments.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Timmy Dooley:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2015"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2015&amp;amp;pid=TimDooley&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is not fair or appropriate.  People developed a coherent programme from the very start that was science-based and science-led and has worked tremendously well.  It was a pilot project that is now recognised across Europe.  A number of years ago, along with the then Commissioner for Agriculture and other experts across Europe, I went to see how farmers could play an important role in protecting and preserving the unique characteristics of areas such as the Burren.  I would like a debate on the ACRES programme so that we can tease out in detail how we might be able to re-engineer things so they meet the needs and expectations of farmers.  If farmers are not properly remunerated under this programme, the incentives to protect and preserve the unique characteristics of the Burren will be lost.  I appeal to the Leader for a debate with the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine at the earliest opportunity.  It will give him an opportunity to discuss the matter.  I am sure others have local interests.  If the Leader could organise such a debate, it would be great.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#J00200"><p>Yesterday on the Joe Duffy show, a woman rang in to say she was seven months pregnant and went to a well-known department store to use a toilet.  She was initially told that she could, and then a supervisor came along and said she had to have a medical letter to justify having access to the toilets in the department store.  She had to leave the facilities, at seven months pregnant.  She felt it was self-evident why she might need to go to the toilet as a matter of urgency.  She went to a small coffee shop some distance away.</p> <p>In the UK there is a bylaw right to go to the toilet if one is pregnant, including in a policeman's helmet.  That is how old the law is.  I presume it is not exercised nowadays.  We seem to be in a culture of incrementalism.  We have yet as a species to recognise that women, in particular, and other people get pregnant and may need to go to the toilet.  We do not put services in place or require services to be provided in public spaces.  If planning permission is being granted for a department store, at the very least it should have public toilets which are accessible without a jobsworth denying people access to them.</p> <p>I question the idea that women have to acquire rights slowly in the workplace.  It is a matter of gender discrimination on the grounds of pregnancy.  It would be the most litigated case of discrimination against women and pregnant people in the Workplace Relations Commission.  We still seem to have a mindset that does not recognise that we need the propagation of the species to happen.  We need the next generation.  We should put supports in place.  I am not quite sure where to go with this issue, except to express outrage that there is no accommodation for women and that someone who is obviously pregnant should be asked to produce a letter.</p> <p>I understand there are occupiers' liability issues, companies may not want to have facilities, there may be issues around drugs and so on.  However, it is a basic human necessity.  It is not something we can put off until tomorrow.  When you gotta go, you gotta go.  Perhaps we need to have a discussion on gender or on occupiers' liability legislation.  I know that legislation is being reviewed by the Minister for Justice.  We need to have a discussion on how basic and fundamental human rights and necessities are being vindicated as we go about our normal daily lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#J00300"><p>Like so many others, I was overjoyed to see the women's team make a remarkable breakthrough in qualifying for the World Cup next year.  I want to extend my heartfelt congratulations to Vera Pauw, Katie McCabe and all on the team.  As has been said so many times, they are an inspiration to all girls in sport across this country.  I refer in particular to the words Amber Barrett spoke last night with regard to her relationship to Creeslough and the dark times in Donegal at the moment.</p> <p>It is important to say that just five years ago a number of those players, along with Stuart Gilhooly in the PFAI and Ethel Buckley in SIPTU, had to call a press conference to talk about how they were treated like fifth-class citizens.  It is great that the FAI has responded.  However, I would like the House to have a discussion with the Minister of State, Deputy Jack Chambers, to ensure proper resources are put in place for women's football in this country.  We know just one of the players plays here in Ireland.  The rest have to go abroad, which is brilliant if they want to do so.  In terms of the support for players and allowing them to play professionally here, it is not an option right now and I would like to have a discussion on that in the House.</p> <p>I also want to call for a debate with the T&aacute;naiste on the range of business supports available at the moment.  Over the past 24 hours there was a report by Fergal McCann and Niall McGeever from the Central Bank on the level of distressed businesses at the moment.  Some of the figures in the excellent report are stark and frightening, in particular the role that loan forbearance is playing in keeping some of these companies open.  This is not just about companies, but also the jobs that are at stake.  I would like to have a debate in the House on what will be put in place.  We have the temporary energy support scheme, the details of which we need to see.  There are other measures that need to be taken to ensure jobs are not lost on a massive scale this winter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#J00400"><p>I have raised before in the Seanad the vision for high-speed rail on the island of Ireland, in particular between Belfast and Dublin.  I am raising it again today following a meeting that Deputy Carroll MacNeill and I held last week with people who want to support the concept.  This would be one of the largest infrastructure projects on the island of Ireland.  It is something that will take 20 years at a minimum.  If we started on day one with all of government behind high-speed rail, we would not have it on the island of Ireland until 2024.</p> <p>One of the key reasons it should be between Belfast and Dublin to start with is because that is the economic engine of the island of Ireland.  The vast majority of the population, about 2.3 million people, live in that area.  When high-speed rail is introduced, it will cut the journey time of approximately 2.5 hours to just one hour.  That is the economic reason for the project.</p> <p>There has been a great deal of talk in recent weeks and months about a united Ireland.  One of the key things we need to do between the Republic of Ireland and Northern Ireland is to try to increase co-operation through infrastructural projects.  I firmly believe that if we can show that we can make this island economically viable through infrastructure like high-speed rail, that will do a lot to bring both communities together.</p> <p>There has been some talk about strategic rail reviews and feeding into that.  What is needed is a Minister, similar to S&eacute;amus Brennan in the 1990s who deregulated the airline market to allow Ryanair in, who will come along and say we are absolutely doing this.  It will take time and will be unpopular.  People will question the need to do it when it is 20 years away, but it could be one of the largest infrastructural projects on the island of Ireland and would have a huge benefit North and South.  It is something we need to consider strongly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#J00500"><p>I ask the Leader to facilitate a debate with the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, on the HSE winter plan.  The &euro;169 million plan was announced yesterday, yet today we were told by Liam Woods from the HSE, who spoke on the national broadcaster, that the recruitment process to hire a consultant from beginning to end takes up to 40 weeks.  We all agree that 40 weeks from today means it will almost be next summer before the relevant consultants are approved and appointed in our hospitals.</p> <p>As part of the debate, I ask that the Minister for Health answer questions pertaining to the new elective hospital for Cork.  I want to commend my colleague, Deputy Colm Burke, on his work on this.  It is a bit disappointing that as we come towards the end of the tenure of the Taoiseach we do not have the location, foundation or scaffolding in place to start the new hospital.  I hope the Minister comes to the House to announce good news before the Taoiseach leaves office in December.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is an issue with bed capacity in our public hospitals, whether we like it or not.</p><p>The second point I would make as part of the debate is that we are, we are told, looking at a twindemic of Covid and flu again this year.  I encourage and ask all Members of the House to support the HSE's campaigns on the booster for Covid and the flu vaccine.  It is important we support the HSE on both those issues because the flu vaccine will help most particularly the vulnerable groups of our society and the booster vaccine those of us of a certain age and beyond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#K00200"><p>Like other Members, I congratulate the Irish ladies' team on its fantastic success last night.  I was, however, very disappointed by videos that surfaced late last night and this morning of the chants of "Ooh, ah, up the 'RA".  Senator McGahon has talked about projects to build co-operation in our country, and we have our shared island unit.  What happened was not appropriate on what was a fantastic night for Irish sport.  A very strong statement on it needs to come out from the FAI.  It really took the gloss off the victory for me.</p> <p>I wish to speak about palliative care beds, an issue I have raised in the House before, and the fact we have just one palliative care bed in St. Joseph's Care Centre, Longford.  I have given figures before of numerous families' loved ones passing away in an acute hospital or in a bed in a home in another county.  That is not acceptable.  We have been fighting with the HSE over recent years for just one additional bed.  I want the Minister for Health to come into the House and give us a positive answer to that query.  Only in the past week I had a case in which an elderly man in his 80s was not able to come back to his own county and his elderly wife was not able to travel to visit him.  It is not acceptable.  We have put investments into Tullamore and now a regional 16-bed unit, but the major population areas in my constituency, which are Mullingar, Athlone and Longford, need sufficient numbers of beds also.  It is only right we give that right to the families of people coming to the ends of their lives.</p> <p>I thank the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, for her announcement in the past half hour on the community centres fund.  She is a very proactive Minister, especially for us in rural Ireland.  The fund is a fantastic initiative.  A significant number of projects have been funded, with more funding to come.  I just hope that, before the year is out, additional funding will be put in to look after the larger infrastructure projects that are needed and that for centuries have been at the heart of all our communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#K00300"><p>The issue of policing is one that all of us grapple with regularly.  The announcement in the budget that 1,000 additional garda&iacute; will be allocated and provided for is very welcome.  However, the issue of allocation and where those garda&iacute; eventually find themselves in our local towns and villages is one I think we all have concerns about.  When we raise that in here, if we have a debate in this Chamber and the Minister for Justice addresses us, she will, of course, defer to the line that policing matters and where garda&iacute; are placed are matters for the Garda Commissioner.  Then we raise it at our joint policing committee meetings, which is our forum to do so, and we speak about the fact we need garda&iacute; in Navan, Ratoath or wherever else and, of course, we are then told it is a matter for the chief superintendent.  That is all well and good, but there is a political problem here, and it is historical, with where garda&iacute; were placed over a number of years and with the fact that, when people retire, other garda&iacute; are brought in but that Garda strength has not kept pace with the urbanisation of the east coast in places like Meath, Kildare and Wicklow and where greater resources are needed.  Actually, a disproportionate advantage is given to those growing counties.  What prompted me to raise this is that my town of Navan, with a population of some 36,000 people, does not have a second patrol car.  Having spoken to local garda&iacute;, I am told that to man that requires an additional 12 garda&iacute; to make sure the shifts are covered so that that is in place.  It is not a simple case of just two garda&iacute; but a case of 12.</p> <p>Tonight we have a public joint policing committee meeting in Ratoath for County Meath.  One concerned resident from Navan wrote to me ahead of tonight.  He says that what finally prompted him to correspond with the committee was that he saw the welcome from many quarters to news that 58 CCTV cameras are being installed in Navan.  His first reaction, however, was to ask what sort of a town must have 58 CCTV cameras watching it.  He asks if that is where we are as a community and a society.  I hope we are not going to replace badly needed visible human interaction with CCTV cameras.  We need to make sure we are putting the human resources into our communities, not just to keep them safe but also to give the people that sense of human interaction.  I am calling for that debate because it is not simply a matter for the Garda Commissioner.  The resources start in the Department of Justice and with making sure we allocate those resources, and that debate needs to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#K00400"><p>I join my colleagues in congratulating the Irish women's soccer team.  It is phenomenal.  It was great to hear the players speak about how inspirational it is and will be for future generations of young girls watching the team now.  They will consider taking on football and, it is to be hoped, will play again.  A local player, Heather Payne from Galway, came through Ballinasloe Town AFC and is playing with them as well.</p> <p>I acknowledge the incredible funding that has come through the Department of Rural and Community Development, through the Minister, Deputy Humphreys.  We see in excess of &euro;700,000 coming into County Roscommon for more than 30 centres and community halls across the county.  In Galway we see about &euro;860,000 coming in for nearly 40 community halls and centres.  There are so many aspects to this, including retrofitting, renovating, painting, green initiatives and solar panels.  All of this means there will be a real sense of pride and activity for the volunteers in those local areas doing that work.  There will be a real sense of seeing that progress happen in the next few months.  It will also be a real boost for local tradespeople because that work will happen in the coming months and that fund is to benefit people living in towns and villages.</p> <p>I acknowledge the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, who came to the House this morning to speak to us about the expansion of Westdoc services for the Ballinasloe area.  There was a public meeting held on Monday evening with public representatives.  I acknowledge also the support of Senator Murphy in a serious, urgent crisis and for a case that has been made and that needs to be taken into account now for the expansion of Westdoc services for those GPs in the Ballinasloe and east Galway area who are at crisis point right now.  There are GPs retiring and they are not being replaced.  Nobody wants to go into a role in which they will work a one-in-eight rota.  They are in a rota.  They have attempted to join Westdoc and the HSE and the community healthcare organisation, CHO, in our area have put in the request.  However, it is not happening.  I would very much appreciate any support on this.  We hope to meet with the Minister, Deputy Donnelly.  Any support regarding these services would be very important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1652" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#K00500"><p>I wish to bring up the issue of the burdens facing businesses in Ireland.  There was a recent review that found that approximately 10,000 businesses are under financial strain and pressure at present.  A lot of that is due to the warehousing of taxes from the Covid era.  That has been filtering to an end.  That is causing serious problems at a time when businesses are looking to a slowdown in our general economy, rising costs of power, staffing and spiralling inflation.  The Leader might consult the powers that be in the Minister and the Department and have a serious conversation with the Collector General's division, which, in fairness, going by my work with it since I have been a Member of the Oireachtas, has always been quite empathetic to businesses that have a plan.  That will certainly be needed to work with businesses, to work through this hiatus at present and to see them out the far side.  The last thing we want is for these 10,000 businesses, which I think is approximately 4% of our listed businesses, to run into bigger trouble or hit the wall.  I would appreciate if the Leader could do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#K00600"><p>I welcome the announcement about the community centres.  For too long, community centres have struggled.  They play a vital role in our community as hubs for people to gather, social areas for people to hang out in and places for young people to play sport.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They have struggled, particularly during the pandemic, to keep their centres heated and maintained.  The announcement by the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, of a small grant will go a long way towards helping community centres.</p><p>We should acknowledge the work done by the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, in ensuring that all households benefit from the credit scheme.</p><p>I am concerned, as some people in health settings who are entitled to get the &euro;1,000 pandemic bonus payment still have not received it.  The payment was committed to in early January.  We need to draw a line in the sand and the payments need to be made before the end of the year.  It is farcical that the State cannot pay in a timely manner the &euro;1,000 to everyone who is entitled to it.  That is regrettable and I would like to see it addressed.</p><p>Seanad &Eacute;ireann, under the Cathaoirleach's leadership, is doing a wonderful job commemorating Seanad 100.  The events and the recognition of minority voices within the Seanad are welcome.  Seanad 100 should spur an interest and a debate in the House on the future of the teaching of history.  A number of years ago, history was threatened as a core subject on the junior certificate curriculum.  Thankfully, that idea was reversed and the threat was removed.  We need a long-term strategy for the teaching of history and its place within the structure of education.  How can we move forward with positivity unless our young people understand their past?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#L00200"><p>Last night, I felt so much pride as an Irish woman and as a mother of two girls to see Ireland's women's football team reach their first ever world cup.  It was touching that a Donegal woman scored the goal.  It came against the backdrop of one of the most traumatic weeks that we have experienced in a long time.  We saw the PSNI and Garda working side by side in Donegal, we saw emergency services from the North and South working side by side and we saw politicians standing shoulder to shoulder.  It is devastating that, 25 years after the Good Friday Agreement, the girls would want to chant what they chanted.  For such a moment of pride and joy for the entire nation to cause hurt and division is a pity and a disappointment to us all.  After 12 July, I stated in the House that there should be zero tolerance of sectarianism.  I am saying the same thing now.  The Seanad is considering the constitutional future of the island and we are speaking about a shared island, potentially with shared sports teams, so to hear chants like that sets us back.  I feel I need to say that, after such a momentous occasion, what happened has left us with a heavy moment and it needs to be reflected on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#L00300"><p>I join with others in supporting the proposal on Seanad secretarial assistants' pay.  The Leader is committed to it, as are all other Senators, so we do not need to discuss it at any great length today.  We know the shortcomings and we have promised to address this issue many times, but we have not got it over the line.  That is a disappointment, given that there is support for it across the Houses.  I hope that we can work collaboratively in support of our amazing secretarial assistants, who support us every day of the year in doing our jobs in the Seanad.</p> <p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for his leadership and work on the select committee on the constitutional arrangements of the island of Ireland.  Our committee meetings on Fridays have been excellent and well attended.  Young people of this island spoke over the past two weeks about wanting to be part of the solution, about integrated education and about their prospects.  The solidarity and purpose they showed were great.  It was an eye opener.  I have attended many such gatherings, but never anything with the same focus, intent and positivity.  I thank the Cathaoirleach for that and for bringing the initiative to the House.  I thank him for pioneering and for continuing to push for Seanad reform, which has been the hallmark of his tenure.  His time is not done yet and we will have other days to thank him, but his work and that of his office are paying dividends.</p> <p>If Senators can make it to the Chamber this Friday when Northern voices will be one of the themes, it would be positive.  As well as engaging, we must listen.  I would like to see more people on this side of the House next Friday to balance the other side, where every seat will be full.  When I left last week, someone asked me how many Senators had been in the House, but I had to say that it was a select committee, not the House.  That does not stop people from coming and engaging, though.  To be fair to the Cathaoirleach, any Senator who was present and wanted to engage and ask questions was fully facilitated by him.  I thank him for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#L00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#L00500"><p>Senators Boyhan and Clonan are proposing an amendment to the Order of Business, which I will be happy to accept and support.  I thank them for that.</p> <p>Among other colleagues, Senators Murphy and Currie spoke about the momentous occasion that happened last night with the Irish women's team.  Today and yesterday, Labour Party representatives asked for a debate on ongoing and professional funding for our female soccer players, particularly given that the national team will now head off to Australia and New Zealand to represent us.  Senator Murphy spoke with great clarity about how Amber Barrett's integrity and heartfelt display of emotion last night captured everything about the team, including the support she got from her team members around her emotional speech on how Creeslough had affected her and put her in such a sombre mood in the days leading up to that momentous match.  Everyone was overwhelmed with emotion last night because of their win and the poignancy of what they said afterwards.</p> <p>I agree with colleagues, though.  I was naive this morning when I saw the clip because I thought they were shouting, "Ooh, aah, up Vera" in support of their wonderful manager.  While it sounded like what we have all come to despise as a chant, I am genuinely dismayed that it turned out that I was naive.  It puts a sad tinge on the occasion, but we need to get back to focusing on the team's future and our support for them.  I thank colleagues for raising the team's momentous win last night and for saying that we all support them.</p> <p>Senators Conway, Dolan and Carrigy spoke about the welcome announcement by the Minister for Rural and Community Development of community centre funding.  For a long time, we in this House have spoken about how community centres are forgotten about, do not have money to fix roofs or install windows and must fund-raise themselves.  I commend the Minister on her announcement.</p> <p>Senators Davitt and Sherlock sought a debate with the Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment on supports - this matter also touches on the remit of the Minister for Finance - for the 10,000 businesses that may be in a precarious situation because of warehoused debt.  Since Covid in particular, we have always as a State striven to support businesses that are vulnerable but viable.  The 10,000 businesses fall into that category.  Additional careful consideration is required and I will organise a debate as soon as I can.</p> <p>As she did on a Commencement matter today, Senator Dolan raised the expansion of Westdoc's services and the intolerable situation of us having given the HSE the money for those services but the HSE not having provided for them.  That is not good enough.</p> <p>Senator Cassells asked for a debate on the policing allocation.  He is right, in that it is bizarre that the State provides the money but we let someone else deploy the resources autonomously in a way that does not reflect the needs of communities, particularly those communities that, according to the figures of the Central Statistics Office, CSO, in recent months, are growing.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Carrigy raised the need for more palliative care beds in his area.  Also related to health services, Senator Buttimer asked for a debate on the winter plan and the looming event of the twin pandemic of Covid and flu which the HSE tells us we may face over the winter.</p><p>Senator McGahon spoke about high-speed rail and the bravery it would take for the Government to look at a project that would not deliver for 20 years.  It is certainly something we can see has had a massive benefit in very advanced communities and countries throughout the world.</p><p>Senator Seery Kearney raised the story of a seven-months pregnant lady who was refused the use of a toilet.  I do not know why we would need laws to ensure somebody was treated as a human being.  If people see a seven-months pregnant lady in front of them, bloody hell, they should let her use the toilet.  There is probably a need for a debate on where the gaps fall in our laws with regard to the provision of services.</p><p>Senator Dooley asked for a debate on the agri-climate rural environment scheme, ACRES, which has followed GLAS and REPS.  He pointed out it needs some tweaking because some people will be less well-off despite the years of investment in our land.</p><p>Senator Lombard asked for a debate on local authority funding and spoke about the ongoing intergenerational precarious nature of funding for Cork County Council.  We will organise that debate.</p><p>For the second week in a row Senator Fitzpatrick raised the issue of the Intreo office.  At her request last week I made contact with the Minister about what was then a temporary closure but has now been announced as a permanent closure.  There certainly has not been a satisfactory explanation from the Department of Social Protection on why this is a permanent closure and what is expected, other than the services to go into the cloud.  It is not good enough.</p><p>Senator Clonan proposed an amendment to the Order of Business.  Senator Burke spoke about the support of the drink aware programme in helping young and old people to be conscious of the effect drink has on them and to drink moderately.</p><p>Senator Murphy spoke about Agri Aware's farming through the seasons programme which is being rolled out to all of our schools.  To my mind the only way we could probably enhance it is by having real tours instead of virtual tours to farms.  There is nothing like getting muck on our boots and hands to realise the value of rural Ireland and for people to really see what is involved in the production of our top-quality food.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#M00200"><p>Senator Clonan has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 114, motion 3 be taken without debate on the conclusion of the Order of Business."  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.74" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.75" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#M00400">Scheme for Secretarial Assistance: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#M00500"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann calls on the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission in the matter of the current pay claim sought under the Scheme for Senators&rsquo; Secretarial Assistance to make a recommendation to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform that Seanad Secretarial Assistants be permanently regraded to the role and remuneration of Parliamentary Assistants. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#M00600"><p>I second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.78" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.79" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 12.23 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 2 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 12.23 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.80" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#W00100">Report of Commission of Investigation (IBRC) into Siteserv Transaction: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#W00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1475" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#W00300"><p>As Senators are aware, the Taoiseach is the specified person and the Department of the Taoiseach is responsible for certain administrative functions regarding the IBRC commission.  Unfortunately, the Taoiseach cannot participate in today's debate due to prior commitments.  He has asked me to attend in his place and extend his apologies to the House.</p><p>The commission was established in June 2015 following the making of a Government order, which was approved in draft by this House and the D&aacute;il.  The commission's terms of reference, which were also approved by both Houses, were the subject of extensive discussions between all parties in the Oireachtas both at the outset and during the lifetime of the commission.</p><p>In summary, the commission was required to investigate all transactions, activities and management decisions at the IBRC other than those relating solely to the acquisition of assets by the National Asset Management Agency, which occurred between 21 January 2009 and 7 February 2013.  They either resulted in a capital loss to IBRC of at least &euro;10 million, or are specifically identified by the commission as giving rise, or likely to give rise, to potential public concern in respect of the ultimate returns to the taxpayer.</p><p>In November 2015, the commission submitted an interim report that indicated 38 transactions came within its terms of reference.  The interim report also raised significant issues regarding legal professional privilege, banking confidentiality and its terms of reference.  As a result, following consultations with all Oireachtas parties, bespoke legislation was enacted in 2017 to provide a new legal basis for the commission.  The commission's terms of reference were also amended following consultations with Oireachtas parties.</p><p>Under the commission's amended terms of reference it was charged with, in its first module, investigating the Siteserv transaction, which had been identified by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann as a matter of significant public concern.  The commission was also charged with, in its first module of work, reviewing and reporting on the principles and policies within IBRC in respect of the setting of interest rates generally during the relevant period.</p><p>The commission's terms of reference also provide for investigating matters relating to: (a) the processes, procedures and controls which were operated by IBRC; (b) whether there is <i>prima facie</i>evidence of material deficiencies in the performance of their functions by those acting on behalf of IBRC, including the IBRC board, directors, management, the staff of the wealth management unit and agents; (c) whether it can be concluded that the transactions were not commercially sound; (d) whether any unusual share trading occurred; and (e) whether the Minister for Finance or his Department was kept informed, where appropriate, in respect of the transactions concerned, and whether he, or officials on his behalf, took appropriate steps in respect of the information provided to them.</p><p>The commission sent its report on the Siteserv transaction to the Taoiseach on 29 July 2022.  Following consultation with the Attorney General, the Taoiseach arranged for the report to be published and laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas on 7 September 2022.  The commission's report runs to more than 1,500 pages.  Unsurprisingly, in a report of its length, it goes through all aspects of the Siteserv transaction in detail.  The commission has made extensive findings of fact which are of great concern to the Government.  It is clear from the recent debate on the report in the D&aacute;il, and media commentary, that these concerns are shared across the political spectrum.</p><p>I think it would be useful to briefly highlight some of the commission's main findings.  For example, the commission determined that it can be concluded that the bank made its decision to approve the sale of the Siteserv group in good faith but based on misleading and incomplete information provided to it by the company.  The commission found that there were two parallel processes during the sale process.  One of these was below the surface and meant that decisions were made in the course of the Siteserv sale process which were clearly and manifestly improper, and which undermined the integrity of the process.  The commission also determined that it can be concluded that the Siteserv transaction was, from the perspective of the bank, so tainted by impropriety and wrongdoing, that the transaction was not commercially sound.  It found that the bank might, subject to certain assumptions, have recovered up to &euro;8.7 million more than the &euro;44.3 million it agreed to accept in the sale.</p><p>It is worth putting on the record that many of the allegations made in the Oireachtas and elsewhere were not upheld by the commission.  For example, the commission found that many aspects of the transaction, and the behaviour of a number of parties, including in IBRC itself, were appropriate.  It also found that the procedures and controls that were operated by IBRC at the relevant time regarding the Siteserv transaction were fit for purpose and that there is no evidence that any unusual trading in Siteserv shares occurred.  The commission also established the approach taken by the IBRC regarding the setting of interest rates for individual loans, and how these decisions were reached, and made no adverse findings.</p><p>The report did make a number of negative findings regarding some individuals who were closely involved in the sale of the company.  I think that everyone in this House will agree that people be held responsible for their actions but, of course, it is also important that we do not prejudge anything and we must wait for the outcome of the follow-up investigations, which are to be completed as a result of the commission's findings.  In this regard, the commission recommended that the report be brought to the attention of the relevant authorities concerning a number of taxation, company law and bankruptcy issues.  Accordingly, as per the commission's recommendations and on foot of advice from the Attorney General, the Taoiseach arranged for the report to be brought to the attention of the Revenue Commissioners, the special liquidators of the IBRC, the Corporate Enforcement Authority, the Central Bank and the official assignee in a bankruptcy case.  These bodies are now responsible for conducting any appropriate investigations on foot of the report.</p><p>I thank Mr. Justice Brian Cregan, who was the sole member of the commission, for his work in compiling the report.  Clearly, it was a very onerous task.  He deserves great credit for his thorough analysis of a very complex and detailed commercial transaction.  However, I believe that the length of time that the commission took to complete its report on the Siteserv transaction raises broader questions about the effectiveness of the commission of investigation model.  To illustrate this point, it should be noted that it took the commission over seven years to produce its report on the Siteserv transaction.  During that time the commission has cost over &euro;12 million approximately, excluding third-party legal costs incurred by witnesses who appeared before the commission, which have not yet been paid.  The commission signalled in its interim report dated 25 July 2022 that after it had finished the report on Siteserv it would begin to work on the third-party legal costs.  I understand that this process is now under way.  The final cost of the commission will only be known when the commission makes its determination on these third-party costs.  It is clear that the total cost is going to be extremely high in any case.</p><p>The commission signalled in its interim report dated 25 July 2022 that it would provide its report on the other 37 transactions covered by its terms of reference before the end of this month.  I understand from the Taoiseach that he has now received this report and that he is currently considering it.  Before the contents of the report are made public the Taoiseach is consulting with the Attorney General and further details will be provided when that process has concluded.  It should be noted that the commission previously indicated that there will be significant, if not insuperable, difficulties in progressing the investigation into the other 37 transactions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jack Chambers:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2429"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2429&amp;amp;pid=JackChambers&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is because, for example, many of the companies involved are located outside the jurisdiction of the State or no longer exist if they have been dissolved or gone into receivership.  I will use the limited time available to me at the end of the debate to comment on the most significant issues that are raised and to provide clarification to colleagues on the issues they raise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#X00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  Those of us who were then Members of the D&aacute;il and Seanad will recall that the commission was established by the Government in June 2015 following approval of a draft order of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  Senators may also recall that the commission submitted an interim report in November 2015 which raised significant issues regarding legal professional privilege, banking confidentiality and its terms of reference.  As a result, following consultation with all Oireachtas parties, bespoke legislation was enacted in 2017 to provide a new legal basis for the commission.</p> <p>As the Minister of State pointed out, we are now seven years on and only last month the Taoiseach published the 1,500 page report of the commission of investigation on the IBRC transaction relating to Siteserv and the principles and policies in IBRC on interest rates.  The Government accepts the findings of the commission.  It believes the report shines a light on unacceptable practices by certain parties during the course of the transaction.  It focuses on the soundness of one of the transactions.  In this regard the commission has determined it can be concluded that the bank made its decision to approve the sale of the Siteserv group in good faith but this was based on misleading and incomplete information provided to it by the company.</p> <p>As the Minister of State said, the commission found there were two parallel processes during the sale.  There was the above surface process organised by Siteserv and its advisers in which the company chose bidders, evaluated the bids, decided to grant exclusivity to one bid and then signed and completed the sale.  As the Minister of State pointed out, the below the surface process was where certain events occurred in the course of the Siteserv sale process without the knowledge of the bank.  This below the surface process meant steps were taken and decisions were made in the course of the Siteserv process in a manner that was manifestly improper and which undermined the integrity of the Siteserv sale process.</p> <p>The commission makes a number of highly critical findings about certain individuals working for or involved with Siteserv plc.  It does not make any critical finding of Mr. O'Brien.  The commission has also determined that it can be concluded that the transactions were not conducted in a manner that was reasonable from the perspective of bank and that decisions were made and actions taken in the course of the transaction that were not reasonable from the perspective of the bank.  The outcome of the transactions was also not reasonable from the perspective of the bank.  The commission has also determined that it can be concluded that the Siteserv transaction was, from the perspective of the bank, so tainted by impropriety and wrongdoing that the transaction was not commercially sound.</p> <p>The report states the bank could have recovered up to &euro;8.7 million more than the &euro;44.3 million it agreed to accept in the sale.  The headline price of the alternative bidder for Siteserv was &euro;4 million more than the headline bid of Mr. O'Brien.  That could have been pursued.  The company agreed with Mr. O'Brien a reduction in the sale of the proceeds of &euro;1.8 million through working capital adjustments.  There is no evidence that a rival bidder would not have been given the same adjustments.  Siteserv directors awarded themselves and other directors bonuses that cost the company more than &euro;800,000.  These bonuses should never have been paid.  The company did not need to pay the sum of &euro;5 million to its shareholders and could have obtained their consent to the transaction with a payment of &euro;2.1 million less.</p> <p>The report goes into other areas, with regard to the procedures and controls in IBRC share trading, interest rates and interactions between the IBRC and the Department of Finance.  As the Minister of State said, and as all of us have said, the Government accepts the findings of the commission.  It believes the report shines a light on unacceptable practices by certain parties during the course of the transaction.  I welcome the news that the Taoiseach is arranging to bring relevant recommendations made by the commission in its report to the attention of the relevant Departments and sections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1669" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#X00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  The report of the Cregan commission of investigation into the sale of Siteserv Limited to a company beneficially owned in the majority by Mr. Denis O'Brien is a matter of public interest.  Siteserv was indebted to the State-owned IBRC to the amount of &euro;156 million arising from its debts to Anglo Irish Bank.  Accordingly, the terms on which it was sold concerned the people of Ireland as taxpayers and as guarantors of the failed Anglo Irish Bank.  Indebtedness of the order of &euro;110 million was written off by IBRC.  In these circumstances, there was a grave obligation to conduct the sale of Siteserv in an ethical and lawful manner designed to maximise the return to IBRC and the citizens of Ireland.  The commission&rsquo;s report is very lengthy and detailed but, happily, its conclusions are summarised at chapter 27.  These conclusions have been laid before us as Members of the Oireachtas for our brief consideration today.  I propose to comment on these conclusions.</p> <p>The commission found that the sales process was conducted in good faith by IBRC but that it was tainted with impropriety and illegality as a result of the improper actions of three persons in particular, namely, Niall McFadden, Brian Harvey and Robert Dix, whose evidence the commission disbelieved and rejected in relation to crucial aspects of the transaction.  Niall McFadden and Brian Harvey concluded a secret deal with Denis O'Brien and persons acting for him under which they would receive 15% of the shares in the acquiring company owned by Mr. O'Brien as a "management incentive".  They collectively took steps to ensure that this side deal would be concealed from most members of the Siteserv board and from those in IBRC who were supervising the sale of Siteserv.</p> <p>McFadden and Harvey abused their positions to ensure that highly confidential information relating to the competitive bidding process was revealed to those conducting the O'Brien bid.  Their aim was to give the O'Brien bid the inside track and an unfair and improper advantage as a bidder for Siteserv.  The commission found that the compromised sale process could have yielded &euro;8.7 million more for the taxpayer.  The presence of McFadden and Dix at a ski resort "boot camp" holiday with Mr. O'Brien at the precise time that crucial decisions were pending or being made in relation to the Siteserv deal does not appear to me to be entirely innocent or mere coincidence.  The commission found that Dix improperly and inexplicably concealed this event from his fellow directors.</p> <p>O&rsquo;Brien had, on the evidence, made strenuous but unsuccessful interventions with IBRC to reduce or write off the major personal indebtedness of his friend McFadden to the bank.  The 15% shareholding deal was deliberately structured offshore to disguise the existence of these shares from creditors of McFadden and Harvey, including IBRC.  False backdating of employment documentation, to which Mr. O'Brien&rsquo;s company was also party, appears to have been done to conceal and evade tax liabilities.</p> <p>All of these are findings of the commission and they are all to be found in chapter 27.  These facts raise the obvious question as to why Mr. O&rsquo;Brien took no steps to prevent the improper actions of those who tainted the Siteserv transaction.  None of these improprieties could have occurred had he lifted a finger to stop them.  While the commission forbore to deal with that question, we to whom the facts have now been conveyed must ask this question and seek an explanation, if there is one.  The people of Ireland cannot continue to ignore as a mere string of coincidences the findings of the Moriarty tribunal and the Cregan commission and the circumstances giving rise to the data scandal and other serious issues at Independent News &amp;amp; Media, INM, which are under investigation.  There is an undeniable common link to all of these events.  It is the tainted pursuit of greed by any means, fair or foul.</p> <p>What I have said is based entirely on the findings the Government has said it has accepted in chapter 27 of the commission's report.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Those findings of facts give rise to questions which must be answered.  Why did these events take place?  Mr. O'Brien knew what was happening and must have known he was receiving confidential information improperly, even though the commission found he did not seek it in the first place.  Why did he not say to Mr. McFadden and Mr. Harvey that he was having nothing to do with them, that he wanted the deal to go through fair and square, and that he would deal with it on the same basis as anybody else?  </p><p>The time has come for the Irish people to demand of those who have received great assistance from them in accumulating their wealth that they demonstrate standards of ethics and propriety in their dealings with State institutions.  This is not just a hard deal done between two sets of businessman, both of whom are to be imputed with the capacity to look after their own interests.  Rather, this was Irish taxpayers' money in IBRC.  This was a deal which was or was not going to try to recover as much as possible for the Irish taxpayer arising from the debts of Siteserv to the IBRC of over &euro;150 million.  The Irish people are entitled to high standards.  I fully accept what has been said, namely that the IBRC acted honourably and in good faith.  </p><p>Let us not forget that the commission has found that it was deceived and that facts were kept from it.  The result was not merely that the transaction was tainted and unlawful, but also that it probably resulted in the sale of this asset at an undervalue to a company owned by Mr. O'Brien, in which Mr. McFadden and Mr. Harvey were to have a secret offshore shareholder interest, in circumstances which give rise to the reasonable inference that the whole thing was structured to conceal from the Irish Revenue the reality of where the money was going and what money would be available by way of taxation to defray the liabilities of those involved.</p><p>I welcome the report, but we should not cover up what has happened.  We should not simply say that it is for another day, or for the Revenue Commissioners, the Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement or somebody else to draw conclusions.  These facts speak for themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#Y00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House to discuss the important issue of the IBRC commission of investigation.  The report was published on 7 September 2022.  I would like to pay tribute to Mr. Justice Brian Cregan.  He had a major task in terms of the work involved.  The commission was established in June 2015 to investigate certain transactions, activities and management decisions in the IBRC.  The commission's terms of reference provided that the first module of its work would investigate the Siteserv transaction, which has been identified as a matter of significant public concern in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  That has been referred to by other speakers.</p> <p>The report considers the matters coming from within the commission's terms of reference regarding the Siteserv transaction in a comprehensive manner.  It goes through all aspects of the transaction in an extraordinary level of detail and makes extensive findings of fact.  One person was vested with carrying out the transaction, but to start in 2015 and end up in 2022 is far too long to wait for a report.  I understand and compliment the judge who had to carry out complete works.</p> <p>The report is 1,500 pages long and quite detailed, and has taken a considerable length of time to be finalised.  Among the findings, the commission determined that the IBRC made its decision to approve the sale of the Siteserv group in good faith, something to which many speakers have referred, based on misleading and incomplete information provided by the company.  The commission has also determined that it can be concluded that the Siteserv transaction was, from the perspective of the bank, so tainted by impropriety and wrongdoing that the transaction was not commercially sound.  </p> <p>I am glad to hear that the Government has accepted the findings of the commission and believes the report has highlighted unacceptable practices by certain parties during the course of the transaction.  I was going to ask whether the Government intends to hand the findings to another organisation, but the Minister of State covered that in his opening remarks when he said it will be given to the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment, the Revenue Commissioners, the special liquidators of the IBRC, the Corporate Enforcement Authority, the Central Bank and the official assignees in bankruptcy cases.  This is certainly the right route to take.</p> <p>The commission found that there were two parallel processes during the sale process: first, the above-the-surface sale process organised by Siteserv and its advisers, in which the company chose bidders, evaluated the bids, decided to grant exclusivity to one bid and signed and completed the sale; and second, the below-the-surface process, in which certain events occurred in the course of the Siteserv sales process without the knowledge of the bank.  The below-the-surface process meant steps were taken and decisions made in the course of the Siteserv sale process in a manner that was manifestly improper and undermined the integrity of the Siteserv sale process.  </p> <p>The commission made a number of highly critical findings.  It determined that it can be concluded that the transaction was not conducted in a manner that was reasonable from the perspective of the bank.  The decisions made and actions taken in the course of the transaction were not reasonable from the perspective of the bank.  The outcome of the transaction was not reasonable from the perspective of the bank.  The commission concluded that the Siteserv transaction was not commercially sound.  It stated that the bank could have recovered up to &euro;8.7 million more than the &euro;44.3 million it agreed to accept in the sale.  The figure of &euro;8.7 million includes the headline price bid by an alternative bidder for Siteserv, which was &euro;4 million more than the headline bid and could have been pursued.  The company agreed a reduction in the sale proceeds of &euro;1.8 million through a working capital adjustment.  There is no evidence that the rival bidder would have given the same adjustment.  The company did not need to pay &euro;5 million to shareholders and could have obtained their consent to the transaction.  The payment could have been between &euro;700,000 and &euro;2.1 million less.</p> <p>The commission also found that the procedures and controls operated by the IBRC at the relevant time regarding the Siteserv transaction were fit for purpose, although the bank's failure to address a payment to Siteserv shareholders contributed to the bank recovering between &euro;700,000 and &euro;2.1 million less than it might otherwise have received from the proceeds of the sale.  The commission found no evidence that any unusual trading on Siteserv shares occurred, which would give rise to an inference that inside information was not improperly provided to or used by any persons.  The commission also established the approach taken by the IBRC regarding the setting of interest rates for individual loans and how these decisions were reached, and made no adverse findings.</p> <p>I welcome the debate today.  Taxpayers are the losers.  The investigation has happened.  In conclusion, I do not believe there is any guarantee that we will not have a commission of investigation down the road.  While I welcome that the investigation has taken place and the Government is acting appropriately, it is worrying that there are no guarantees and the loss of money to the public is of concern.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#Y00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  I am covering these statements on behalf of my colleague Senator Gavan, who is at the Council of Europe in Strasbourg.  In approaching this debate I remember the advice given to me in the last Oireachtas that when it comes to situations like this, I should follow the numbers or, in this case, the money.  I did precisely that regarding the formal investigation into the 2012 sale of Siteserv, a business services company.  Following the money regarding Siteserv revealed a disturbing level of abuse of power among the wealthy and the elite in sections of a financial hierarchy who thought, and indeed behaved, as though they were an unaccountable power unto themselves.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The first thing that struck me about this financially sordid affair is that the bank involved, IBRC, formerly Anglo Irish Bank, which was then State-owned and had received a &euro;34 billion bailout from the taxpayer in 2009, decided to write off &euro;118 million of &euro;162 million owed to it by Siteserv.  It settled on a sum of &euro;44.3 million for the sale of Siteserv.  An already overburdened taxpayer had to carry the loss of &euro;118 million.  Next Siteserv shareholders would be paid &euro;5 million to ease their financial situation.  There was, however, no financial gift to ease the financial burden on the hard-pressed taxpayer.</p><p>In June 2015 the commission of investigation was established.  Mr. Justice Brian Cregan was appointed to lead it.  In the course of his investigation many issues pertaining to the handling of the overall situation by IBRC and by individuals were unearthed.  One issue was a failure by IBRC to secure &euro;2.1 million from the proceeds of the Siteserv sale, which, of course, directly affected the taxpayer's burden.  The other issue was that preferential treatment was granted to Cathkin Investments Limited, or Millington, to buy Siteserv when at least one other company was interested in buying it at a higher price - another loss to the taxpayer.  The commission found that this "buddy deal" with Millington was "so tainted by impropriety and wrongdoing" that, from the perspective of the bank, the transaction was not commercially sound.  In this regard the commission also found that the manner in which the transaction was conducted, the decisions and actions taken by individuals in the course of the transaction, and its outcome were all unreasonable from the perspective of the bank and, therefore, the taxpayer.  As for the sale of Siteserv to Millington, the commission said this decision was made "without even considering whether to contact" other interested bidders and described this behaviour as "totally improper".</p><p>The commission also found that throughout the Siteserv sale process there were two parallel processes at play, as other colleagues have said.  One was above the surface, seemingly conducted by the company in plain view, but the other was below the surface, carried out without the knowledge of IBRC.  In the words of the report, this "below the surface process" "undermined the integrity of the Siteserv sale process".</p><p>The commission also criticised the credit committee of IBRC for its failure to disclose the paperwork in respect of the &euro;5 million payment that was made to the shareholders as part of the Siteserv transaction.  The commission stated that that failure contributed to IBRC recovering up to &euro;2.1 million less from the proceeds of the Siteserv sale, to the detriment of the taxpayer.</p><p>The comments of the commission on individuals, namely, Mr. Dix, Mr. Harvey and Mr. McFadden make for pretty damning reading.  They are shocking and reveal disregard which some in high places have for the requirements by which ordinary citizens abide every day.  The report lifts the veil on a reckless and elitist culture that infected certain echelons of big business and high finance during a dark chapter in this State's history.</p><p>We must remember we are dealing here with a bank that the taxpayer had bailed out at huge economic and social cost.  The findings of the report also reveal a sad fact that has bedevilled this State and its citizens for far too long, that is, that there is a revolving door between the corporate world and the State and that it opens at times when in fact it should be very firmly closed.  It is quite clear that we still do not have robust enough safeguards in place to ensure that individuals do not move freely and with ease between the corridors of corporate Ireland and the corridors of power.</p><p>This inquiry has cost the taxpayer &euro;30 million in seven years.  We need to take stock of this process and evaluate whether it is fit for purpose, whether it delivers value for money and whether it acts as an incentive or a disincentive for further corporate malpractice.  It cannot be the model we pursue in eradicating wrongdoing.  It is important that, following this report by the commission of investigation, the Government charts a clear and robust pathway forward.  I agree with other colleagues in looking forward to the Minister of State outlining what steps the Government plans to take next on this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#Z00200"><p>That concludes the statements from Senators.  I thank Senators Casey, McDowell, Maria Byrne and &Oacute; Donnghaile.  The Minister of State has now more than ten minutes to reply if he wishes.  It is up to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1475" speakername="Jack Chambers" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#Z00300"><p>I will take less than ten minutes.  I thank all the Senators who contributed to the debate.  A number of issues were raised on which I think we can all agree, on both the Government and the Opposition sides.  I acknowledge Senators Casey, McDowell, Maria Byrne and &Oacute; Donnghaile for their contributions.</p> <p>There has been criticism across the Oireachtas about the length of time the commission took to compile its report and the costs the commission has incurred in these times of constraints on the public purse.  It must be remembered that when the Commissions of Investigation Act was enacted in 2004 it was hoped that it would enable quick and cost-effective investigation of matters of significant public concern.  Back then we had experience of a number of tribunals which had run for a long time and at great cost, and there was a public mood that we needed a better alternative.  In light of the experience since then, with the IBRC commission and other commissions, the Oireachtas collectively might wish to consider whether we can do anything further to improve the current regulatory framework for statutory investigations.  It must be recognised, however, that commissions have to be independent in their investigations and adhere to fair procedures.  Any changes to the way in which matters of public concern are investigated need to be fully thought out and considered.  It may be that using the current model for investigations into complex corporate transactions is not as suitable as using it for matters concerning public administration issues where it is possible to confirm facts more easily.  The ultimate objective for everyone in the Oireachtas is to ensure that, as far as possible, Ireland has a regulatory framework which promotes and ensures a culture of compliance and good ethical standards in matters of both public and corporate affairs.</p> <p>The need for proper efficacy in the corporate world and for a statutory framework which effectively facilitates detection and prosecution of wrongdoing has also been referred to.  The Government has made progress with a range of initiatives designed to combat corruption and white-collar crime.  For example, earlier this year the Government established the Corporate Enforcement Authority, which will have the autonomy and resources to thoroughly investigate suspected wrongdoing.  Staffing levels are increasing by nearly 50%, including a doubling in the number of garda&iacute;, and the authority's budget has also been increased by almost 30%.  It is also worth mentioning that an all-of-government implementation plan to progress the recommendations in the Hamilton review into economic crime was published in April 2021.  This sets out 22 actions to enhance enforcement and prevention capacity in the criminal justice sphere.  Five actions have already been completed in full, and a number of others have been significantly advanced.  For example: the Criminal Procedure Act has been enacted; the Judicial Council has been engaged with in respect of the development of judicial training on complex economic crime and corruption cases; a forum of senior representatives from the relevant operational bodies was established in June 2021; and the Competition (Amendment) Act was signed into law on 29 June.  There has also been significant progress in implementing other recommendations, including greater powers for investigating agencies to tackle economic crime and corruption, reform of the ethics Acts, and additional resourcing for enforcement agencies.</p> <p>Questions have also been raised as to whether the commission will, or should, investigate the other 37 transactions that come within its remit.  As I mentioned in my earlier address, the commission recently submitted its report to the Taoiseach on this matter, and when his consultations with the Attorney General are completed, the position will be made known at that stage, which I understand will be quite soon.  The cost of the commission to date, the length of time it has taken to report, and the commission's views on the matter are significant factors that should be considered in deciding the best approach to take.</p> <p>It would be great if there were no need to establish commissions of investigation or other types of statutory investigation in the future but, unfortunately, experience tells us that there will be instances that require these types of inquiries again.  That is a theme many people referred to.  As Senator McDowell mentioned, when we look at matters of fact, we need to ensure that we have structures that fully investigate people and hold them to account where matters of fact are found in these types of inquiries.  We need to examine the model, and that is something the collective Oireachtas will have to consider.  It is to be hoped that the lessons learned from the IBRC commission's experience and findings will be of value in ensuring such processes are efficient, effective and beneficial for all our citizens and our society as a whole in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.92" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 2.39 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 4.02 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 2.39 p.m. and resumed at 4.02 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.93" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#JJ00100">Breastfeeding: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#JJ00200"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann:   	recognises that: <blockquote> 	- according to the Irish Maternity Indicator Report 2021, Ireland&rsquo;s breastfeeding rates are among the lowest in the world. Only 62.3% of babies are breastfed at birth compared to 90% in Australia, 81% in the UK and 79% in the USA, with only 37% of babies discharged from hospital being breastfed exclusively. By the time babies are three months old that number has dropped to 31.2%, one of the lowest in Europe;<br /><br />- the 5 year National Action Plan for breastfeeding in Ireland ran from 2016 to 2021 and included a target to increase breastfeeding rates by 2% annually. Data on breastfeeding rates only commenced in Irish maternity hospitals in 2019, and in that time breastfeeding rates have declined from 63.8% at birth in 2019 to 62.3% in 2020; <br /><br />- the Lancet Series on breastfeeding in 2016 provides an in-depth analysis of the health and economic benefits of breastfeeding. The Series concluded that breastmilk makes the world healthier, smarter, and more equal; states that the deaths of 823,000 children and 20,000 mothers each year could be averted through universal breastfeeding, along with economic savings of US$300 billion; confirms the benefits of breastfeeding in fewer infections, increased intelligence, probable protection against overweight and diabetes, and cancer prevention for mothers; and represents the most in-depth analysis done so far into the health and economic benefits that breastfeeding can produce;<br /><br />- there is only one human milk bank on the island of Ireland, located in Co. Fermanagh;<br /><br />- the International Code of Marketing of Breastmilk Substitutes (the Code) is an international health policy framework to regulate the marketing of breastmilk substitutes in order to protect breastfeeding. It was published by the World Health Organisation in 1981 and is an internationally agreed voluntary code of practice, that Ireland has still not fully implemented;<br /><br />- according to the World Health Organisation&rsquo;s Marketing of breast-milk substitutes: National implementation of the International Code, Status Report 2022, 32 countries worldwide are currently &lsquo;substantially aligned&rsquo; with the Code. Ireland is not one of these countries. The 2022 report concludes: <i>&lsquo;UNICEF and WHO maintain that the $55 billion formula milk industry uses systematic and unethical marketing strategies to influence parents&rsquo; infant feeding decisions and exploitative practices that compromise child nutrition and violate international commitments.'</i>; </blockquote>acknowledges: <blockquote> 	- the Programme for Government&rsquo;s commitment to <i>&lsquo;promote an increase in the number of new mothers breastfeeding, by increasing support in our maternity hospitals and primary care centres, through access to lactation specialists and public health nurses</i>&rsquo;; <br /><br />- according to a HSE press release of October 2022, 20 new infant feeding and lactation posts have been recruited in the last two years and 44 positions are available nationwide to support parents;<br /><br />- 110 breastfeeding support groups are operational nationwide supported by the HSE;<br /><br />- live chat and e-mail breastfeeding supports are available online with experts at mychild.ie Instagram and Facebook;<br /><br />- the National Action Plan for Breastfeeding 2016 &ndash; 2021, has been extended by an additional 2 years to 2023;<br /><br />- regulations to control the marketing, advertisement and promotion of infant formula and follow-on milk are proposed in the Online Media and Safety Regulations Bill 2021, currently at Second Stage in the D&aacute;il. This Bill includes important provisions to establish Comisi&uacute;n na Me&aacute;n (referred to as The Commission). The Bill establishes a requirement for the Commission to introduce media service codes and online service codes having particular regard to the general public health interests of children: <blockquote> 	<i>- S 46N(5) Media Service Codes</i><br /><br /><i>Provision made for the purpose referred to in subsection (2)(d)(ii) may prohibit or restrict, in accordance with law, the inclusion in programmes of commercial communications relating to foods or beverages considered by the Commission to be the subject of public concern in respect of the general public health interests of children, in particular infant formula, follow-on formula or those foods or beverages which contain fat, trans-fatty acids, salts or sugars;</i><br /><br /><i>- S 139K Online Safety Codes</i><br /><br /><i>Without prejudice to subsection (2) or (4), an online safety code may prohibit or restrict, in accordance with law, the inclusion in programmes or user-generated content of commercial communications relating to foods or beverages considered by the Commission to be the subject of public concern in respect of the general public health interests of children, in particular infant formula, follow-on formula or foods or beverages which contain fat, trans-fatty acids, salts or sugars;</i> </blockquote>- although the promotion of infant formula, designed as a breast milk substitute, for newborn babies is prohibited under EU law, infant formula is cross promoted in the market through the marketing and promotion of follow-on formula, a product designed to substitute breast milk for babies over the age of 6 months; <br /><br />- infant formula is essential for some babies and is a medical necessity that is life-saving in instances where breast milk is not available to babies. It is also a choice, of which all parents are aware. However, this product that is designed to meet the needs of a small number of people is marketed at all parents of new babies; <br /><br />- bans are currently in place on all marketing of breast milk substitutes including follow on formula in Brazil, India, Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Ghana, Armenia, Fiji, Myanmar, United Arab Emirates, Nigeria, Thailand, Bahrain and Mongolia;  </blockquote>and calls on the Government to: <blockquote> 	- support the Milk Bank Scheme in Co. Fermanagh, the only one of its kind on the island of Ireland, including: <blockquote> 	- providing funding for resources in the data and technology tracing and in transporting milk supplies to recipients;<br /><br />- providing funding to increase public awareness of the milk bank to encourage volunteers to contribute;<br /><br />- carrying out a scoping exercise to explore the possibility of replicating the Milk Bank service in the Republic of Ireland with a view to working in collaboration and supporting the work of the existing Milk Bank in Co. Fermanagh;  </blockquote>- work with the HSE to expand the criteria for prescriptions for babies accessing milk from the Milk Bank, noting at present that only premature babies can access milk from the Milk Bank;<br /><br />- develop a governance structure for breastfeeding in primary care and acute hospital divisions;<br /><br />- provide breastfeeding training at undergraduate and postgraduate level across relevant disciplines; <br /><br />- provide education on breastfeeding in all secondary schools as part of the current Social Physical and Health Education course;<br /><br />- develop a clear referral pathway for mothers requiring additional breastfeeding support, before and after birth, to lactation consultants (IBCLCs) from GP&rsquo;s, midwives, public health nurses and consultants;<br /><br />- ring-fence funding for a public awareness campaign on the benefits of breastfeeding, both health and environmental;<br /><br />- improve provision of information on accessing breastfeeding supports, including the promotion of voluntary groups such as La Leche League, Cuidi&uacute; and Friends of Breastfeeding and increase funding to these organisations, in recognition of the essential support services to people breastfeeding in Ireland provided through these voluntary groups; <br /><br />- work with the HSE to ensure that where meeting spaces are available in public health facilities, breastfeeding support groups can have access to the space to host meetings; <br /><br />- provide access to suitable breast pumps, free of charge, to all mothers of preterm and hospitalised infants, and breastfeeding mothers hospitalised after maternity /paediatric discharge with support and information from lactation specialists for all mothers who need to use breast pumps; <br /><br />- implement evidence informed programmes and initiatives to provide support and address barriers for women, with a particular focus on young mothers under the age of 18 and women in the Traveller community;<br /><br />- ensure clinical midwife/nurse specialist lactation consultants (IBCLC) are appointed within all Irish maternity hospitals and paediatric hospitals, according to a determined births-to support staff ratio, with dedicated CMS/CNS lactation in NICUs;<br /><br />- ensure dedicated full-time lactation consultants (IBCLC) posts in each of the 9 Community Health Organisations (CHOs) are appointed, according to population need;<br /><br />- extend the &lsquo;Baby Bundles&rsquo; scheme nationwide, and ensure consultation with the Association of lactation consultants in Ireland and voluntary breastfeeding groups on the educational materials and equipment provided in the bundles in relation to feeding babies;<br /><br />- ensure the Online Safety Codes and Media Services Codes as related to the public health interest of children, which are to be established upon passing of the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill, are enacted as soon as practicable; <br /><br />- ensure the Code is fully implemented in Ireland, and ensure no state funding for any marketing of breast milk substitutes is provided to any private sector companies, in particular companies that are marketing breast milk substitutes in international markets aimed at parents and health care workers, or funding initiatives that promote formula feeding including promotional material, free samples in hospitals, sponsorship of helplines and other fundraising activities. </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#JJ00300"><p>I second the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#JJ00400"><p>I thank all of our guests in the Visitors Gallery.  I will list the organisations because it is important to show the breadth of the voluntary organisations that do such amazing work when it comes to supporting women and breastfeeding.  We have Friends of Breastfeeding Ireland, Baby Feeding Law Group Ireland, Bainne Beatha, Cuidi&uacute;, the Association of Lactation Consultants in Ireland, Pavee Point and La Leche League, which also does huge work in the area of voluntary support.</p> <p>That brings me to my first point.  We are heavily reliant on the voluntary sector when it comes to supporting women.  Breastfeeding is often quite an emotive topic.  Over the past couple of days, as I have been walking around Leinster House, many politicians, both men and women, have shared their personal stories with me.  Everybody has a personal story when it comes to how they feed their children and the kind of supports they feel they did not get.  Journalists who I have spoken to over the past couple of days also shared their stories.  This is an important day and I believe this is the first motion on breastfeeding to come to the floor of the Seanad.</p> <p>It is important to point out that this is fundamentally about choice.  How people feed their infants and children is a matter for themselves.  However, what is important is that the State supports that.  Some 62% of women start breastfeeding.  Within a couple of days of women leaving hospital, however, that figure drops to 37%.  It almost halves and then falls to 31% by month three.  That is shocking and it is one of the lowest percentages in the world.  We have to ask ourselves why that is.  There are a number of factors involved but one is that some time ago we lost the tradition of breastfeeding.  We lost that culture and it is important to bring it back.  That starts at the very earliest age.  We have a young man in the Gallery who supports breastfeeding mothers when they come to his house for the meetings of Friends of Breastfeeding.</p> <p>This starts in the education system.  Many people do not have the experience of having been breastfed themselves or having mothers or significant others in their lives who have that breastfeeding experience.  So much of what happens in our lives as mothers is about a network.  That is what the voluntary organisations provides and that network is missing from many people&rsquo;s lives.</p> <p>The low breastfeeding rates do not even touch the surface when it comes to some sections of Irish society.  Looking at the Traveller community in particular, Pavee Point, which has done huge work on this, has found that only 2% of women in the Traveller community breastfeed.  We have to be honest with ourselves.  What has happened to date has not worked.  There has not been enough work and some of it is a little bit cynical.</p> <p>I have spoken about the formula industry in the House many times.  Ireland is a large exporter of powdered milk.  It exports formula milk all over the world.  That has a devastating impact, apart from anything else, on some of the poorer nations across the globe, which is why the motion refers to the importance of ethical considerations.  It also means that we have a lobby group and an industry that is putting vast amounts of money into advertising formula and free formula in hospitals.  I was delighted that the Minister, Deputy Catherine Martin, was very much on board when we asked her to include a measure in the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill to restrict advertising of formula.</p> <p>It is important to note again at this point that this is not to say that those who formula-feed are doing anything wrong.  However, there is something wrong when an industry goes out of its way to heavily market towards a vulnerable group.  In the middle of the night, someone struggling to breastfeed who looks up supports for breastfeeding will see an advertisement for formula, which is not what she is looking for.  This is about supporting a person&rsquo;s journey in breastfeeding.</p> <p>I have spoken to many people over the past year when working on this and doing other work on breastfeeding.  One message that has come back very strongly is that we need to have a proper joined-up approach.  We need more lactation consultants and I hope the Minister of State will give us information as to where the lactation consultants are that have been promised.  We also need to make sure that every touch point a woman has in her journey also has that expertise on breastfeeding.  Some public health nurses are doing great work but we have other public health nurses who do not feel they are qualified or are being supported by midwives and GPs with the information they are giving.  There is a referral system in place but when somebody goes to their GP looking for support with mastitis, as I have in the past, or something else related to breastfeeding, the first answer that comes back is &ldquo;Well, sure, use a bottle&rdquo;.  That might be the only contact somebody has because it can be cost prohibitive to visit a lactation consultant.</p> <p>We have a lack of equality in our system where when it comes to issues related to women&rsquo;s health, in particular, we are supposed to pay for it whereas other types of healthcare are delivered through the public healthcare system.  At the moment, there is a postcode lottery and there is also a lottery based on how much money one has.  That is just not good enough and it has to change.</p> <p>The motion refers to the milk bank.  There is only one milk bank on the island of Ireland, in Fermanagh, and it struggles for funding all of the time.  Our hospitals rely heavily on it.  Having spoken to people, I understand there are a few issues with it, one of which is that the level of donations it receives means that prescriptions for donated breast milk are only available to women who have a premature baby.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pauline O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=PaulineOreilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to look at expanding that so people who have children in critical care, for instance, and others would have access to those donations.  It is also important to look at opportunities to have such a bank in the Republic of Ireland. </p><p>I thank the Government for the steps that have been taken to date but it is important to say that it is not enough.  We have not seen all of the required lactation consultants come on stream.  I will go back to where I started with the voluntary organisations.  Having been involved in two such organisations and having supported and run breastfeeding support groups in my own house and elsewhere, I know that one thing that bothers people is the cost of finding space to run breastfeeding support groups.  For that reason, the motion proposes that we use all of our healthcare clinics to provide space for these groups, which are doing hugely important work.  It makes sense to do that because many of them are being funded by the HSE, so why would they not be able to use the spaces available?  Furthermore, they are not being funded to the level that they need to be funded, as the motion points out.  </p><p>I will be returning to this topic again and again because, as the Minister of State knows, it is something I feel very passionately about.  It is really important that we, as public representatives, keep banging on the door to get all of the changes that we need implemented.  It is also important that we work on a cross-party basis.  This Chamber has demonstrated an ability to work on a cross-party basis to achieve our goals for women in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#KK00200"><p>I welcome Senator Pauline O&rsquo;Reilly&rsquo;s motion.  This is an historic occasion.  This is the first time that a motion on breastfeeding has been brought to the Seanad and that is worthy of note.</p> <p>Ultimately, as Senator Pauline O'Reilly said at the start, this is about choice and giving women choice.  All of the data stack up in terms of the benefits of breastfeeding.  I was fortunate to be able to breastfeed four of my children.  They will be mortified if they hear me saying this now but I was very lucky.  I had difficulty breastfeeding my first baby but there was a wonderful lactation nurse in the hospital and I went back to her several times in those first very fragile couple of days and weeks.  I also attended some La Leche League meetings but it took six or seven weeks for me and my baby to really get the hang of it.  Had I not had any support then, I fear I probably would not have done it.  That would not have been the end of the world but it was something that I was very determined to do.  Those first babies are so important because I knew for my second, third and fourth babies that I could do it.  I knew that it could be done.  It had done it and I could do it again.  There is a certain confidence that women need and that is where the support and the advice come into play - the security blanket of speaking with others who understand the issues and can help and explain them away.  </p> <p>The benefit of breast milk to infants is absolutely unchallenged but the benefit of breastfeeding to women is not given as much consideration.  It is really important in the postpartum period and is one of the best things women can do to get back into shape.  It can potentially delay the return of menstruation and is a method of contraception, if nothing else.  There are lots of benefits to breastfeeding for the longer term health and well-being of both mother and child.</p> <p>I am not going to speak for the Minister of State but am grateful to him for spending some time with our guests in the Public Gallery before the debate began.  The Government hears the voices and the pleas of our guests.  I am sure the Minister of State will address their concerns and the points made in Senator Pauline O'Reilly's motion.  I thank our guests in the Public Gallery for being here today.  As Senator Pauline O'Reilly said, women like me have relied on the voluntary support they have provided for years.  Now it is time for the Government to step up to the mark and provide the support that is needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101200002#KK00300"><p>I thank Senator Pauline O&rsquo;Reilly for this motion which I wholeheartedly support.  The figures really illustrate how startlingly different Ireland is when it comes to breastfeeding rates.  At birth, the rate here is 62% but in the UK it is 81%, in the US it is 79% and in Australia it is 90%.  By the time women leave hospital, the rate has fallen to 37% but the fact that at three months old the rate is 31% shows that the most vital period is in the hospital.  It is so important to make sure people are getting support in those early days.</p> <p>That was my experience as well.  I could not breastfeed exclusively but I really put so much effort into trying.  I was given the impression when I was pregnant that the baby would nearly latch on itself when it came out.  I was surrounded by contraptions to make it happen, including an industrial-sized pump that I can still hear to this day.  My baby was very small when she was born and I remember that formula was just provided because the breastfeeding was not working.  When I spoke to the nurse the next day and asked if someone could come and help me with the breastfeeding, the answer was that it was too late.  I was vulnerable because I had a Caesarean section, was tired and so on but I really had to push to get that support, just to be able to do what I could do.  That was nearly ten years ago.  There was a lactation consultant in the hospital but by the time the consultant was free to speak to me, I was well gone.</p> <p>I really do not want any woman to feel guilty about not being able to breastfeed.  One does what one can.  I do not want them to feel guilt or to feel less than.  I am not going to try to put pressure on any woman.  The pressure should be put on the system that is just not working for women.  So many women put pressure on themselves to be perfect and it is hard for them when they have the impression that breastfeeding is natural and easy but they find it is not.  For some people it is easy but for others it is incredibly difficult.  In my case, no matter what I did it was never going to work in the way I wanted it to work.  We need to provide multi-level supports.  This is a public health issue and ambition and it must be reflected in our public health system at every touch point.  This is about having lactation consultants in the hospitals and providing support for people when they leave hospital.  The public health nurse that I had was brilliant.  I could have hugged her whenever I saw her and I am sure so many women feel the same way when they have a new baby.  The public health nurse for those first two weeks, which feel like two years, becomes part of one's inner circle.  The public health nurse really helped us through that period.</p> <p>This is about all of the touch points and having the expertise in place but it is also about education.  I worked in advertising for over 15 years and one of the accounts I worked on back in the day was that of the health promotion unit of the HSE.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-12a.100" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>