<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Marc MacSharry that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />The need for the Minister for Health to confirm the existence of a special group chaired by a person (details supplied) to address the anomaly of the lack of a cardiac catheterisation laboratory, with a view to confirming Sligo Regional Hospital as the logical site to locate a laboratory and enhanced cardiology facilities.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Jillian van Turnhout of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask the Minister for Justice and Equality the reason there is no legislative basis for direct provision accommodation as operated by the Reception and Integration Agency under the aegis of his Department.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Ivana Bacik of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask the Minister for Justice and Equality if consideration has been given to the circumstances in which a change may be effected to the upper age limit of 35 years for recruitment to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Denis O'Donovan of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask the Minister for Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht if he will make a statement on the future of the Dursey Island cable car; if he will provide funding to carry out the necessary repairs to same; and if he will ensure the islanders can transport livestock on the cable car to and from the island.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Averil Power of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask the Minister for Health if he will approve the proposal for a south-east Fingal drugs and alcohol awareness project to replace the former Howth based project to ensure this area is not left with a service.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to ensure funding is provided for all children with hearing difficulties in need of cochlear implants.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Marc MacSharry, Jillian van Turnhout, Ivana Bacik and Denis O'Donovan and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.  Senators Averil Power and Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800002#A00300">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800002#A00400"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Public Health (Tobacco) (Amendment) Bill 2013 - Second Stage, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business, with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be called to reply to the debate not later than 1.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800002#A00500"><p>What is the position on item No. 13 on the Order Paper, Civil Registration (Marriage Equality) Bill 2013, which was published in great haste during the Meath East by-election?  Will the Deputy Leader inform the House when she will introduce the Bill in her name?</p><p>I request a full debate next week on policing and Garda recruitment.  Yesterday the Minister for Justice and Equality who is not happy that he is the most unpopular justice Minister who has ever served the country and has lost the confidence of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na - when we tabled a motion of no confidence in him more than one month ago, he did not bother to turn up to take it - stated to the Association of Garda Superintendents and Inspectors that he would delay the arrival of new recruits in Templemore effectively because the Croke Park ll agreement had been voted down.  As we all know, there are no garda&iacute; in training in Templemore.  From the time new recruits enter the Garda Training College there is a two year training cycle before they pass out and become full members of the force.  The Minister is, in effect, continuing to bully An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, the members of which are not just concerned about pay and conditions but also that they are not being given the resources they need to carry out their jobs.  I have given specific instances of the lack of Garda resources, vehicles and new recruits.  What does our esteemed Minister do?  In a fit of pique following the failure of members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to vote in the manner he wanted them to do, he states he will not recruit.  We need him to come to the House to answer questions on how he will rescue the situation, as members of the force have voted no confidence in him.  Not only are the members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na suffering, so too is the general public.  Does the Government have plans to restart recruitment of new members to the force?</p> <p>Was it a Government decision, supported by the Labour Party, that new garda&iacute; will not be recruited?  Is this a Cabinet decision or is it the Minister, Deputy Shatter, on another solo run?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B00200"><p>On a point of clarification, did Senator O'Brien move an amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B00300"><p>No.  We have another one on the way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B00400"><p>I wish to warmly compliment and commend the Chief Justice on her speech yesterday at Griffith College.  She has obviously proven to be a steady hand on the tiller, so to speak.  As I said yesterday, all this needed was a little period of calm and reflection and I think this has been achieved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B00500"><p>She is a Trinity graduate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B00600"><p>Of course.  I look forward to the Deputy Leader responding on these matters as it is up her alley, so to speak.  She is another eminent legal person and a professor.</p><p>The working group has been agreed and was outlined by the Chief Justice.  It will be wonderful and it will deal with an agenda of items.  While the traditional route through the Attorney General's office was always available and will continue to be, it will be aided and abetted by the working group or forum.  I compliment everyone involved in so far as there were two sides and everyone is very pleased with the outcome.  I wish to compliment the Chief Justice, Susan Denham, once again for what she has achieved.  Maybe &quot;achieved&quot; is the wrong word because she was always very involved.  The Taoiseach met with her and with the Attorney General in the recent past.  The Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, has regular meetings with members of the Judiciary on a wide range of matters.  The proposed court of civil appeal will help to remove the backlog of cases before the Supreme Court.  I look forward to the Deputy Leader's appropriate comments on that matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B00700"><p>Arising from the two very fine debates in the House yesterday on research I am pleased to note today that the Leiden University research impact index ranks TCD at ninth in Europe and 48th in the world.  We also had a very useful discussion on banking.  I note that in putting the squeeze on small business, AIB is increasing the charge of 17 cent per &euro;1,000 lodged to 45 cent, from 1 June 2013.  That belies all the bank's statements about helping small and medium enterprises.  As discussed last night, the bank is not helping people with mortgages and it is putting the squeeze on small business as well.  I ask the Deputy Leader to cast her eye over that increase in charges for small and medium enterprises.</p><p>I refer to No. 14 on the Order of Business, Financial Stability and Reform Bill 2013.  I move and amendment to the Order of Business, that item No. 14 be taken before item No. 1.  My seconder is Senator Mullen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B00800"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B00900"><p>I thank the Opposition for a very constructive debate yesterday on the issue of mortgage arrears.  I welcome the publication today of the personal insolvency guidelines.  It is important to acknowledge that they are a minimum and they go some way to answering the incredible uncertainty among people who are in debt. Now anyone approaching a lending institution and enduring the humiliating experience of their bills being examined knows that at least these guidelines will give some measure of what they can expect at the very least from a lending institution.  We were all agreed yesterday that banks need to be held to account.  There was genuine agreement on all sides of the House that we are not happy with the way in which banks are treating borrowers in difficulty.  I am personally very concerned about this issue of a case-by-case resolution of problems.  It reminds me of the "Life of Brian"; we are all individuals, except we have no idea how we are to be treated.  We have no idea whether what is being offered is a good deal.  I reiterate my call to the Leader to ask the Minister for Finance to come to the House to have a discussion on the role of banks in Irish society, particularly in the context of how they are dealing with borrowers in difficulty.  It is clear that there is not a level playing field.  Allowing &euro;250 for people to get expert advice when they have been offered a deal by a lending institution to which they cannot probably, in all truth, say, "No", is way too little and way too late.  Expert, independent advice must be available for anyone who is dealing with a borrowing crisis.  Nothing less is sufficient.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B01000"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B01100"><p>I reiterate my call for an urgent debate on the farming crisis.  While I acknowledge that the Deputy Leader is a very capable lady and a Trinity graduate, I must not allow her to forget her roots in Baile na Gallda, Crookstown, in west Cork, where she comes from farming stock.  As I said yesterday, many farmers are disillusioned and there is much despair and depression.  I am not here today to point the finger of blame at the Minister, Deputy Coveney, or the troika or the banks because the Minister is not to blame for the weather.  However, because the situation is so serious it demands an urgent response.  A precedent was set by the previous Government in 2009 when money was provided on a short-term basis for those in difficulties during the fodder crisis.  Farmers are currently being billed for the property tax.  They look out their windows and in some instances the cattle and sheep are staggering around the fields with starvation.  The supply of credit from the banks is very tight and many farmers are unable to get extra allowances from the providers of foodstuffs such as bags of nuts and other animal feed.  It is a very serious issue.  I am pleading from my heart rather than making a political point.</p><p>I will propose an amendment to the Order of Business that this matter be debated.  The Leader said yesterday that the Minister, Deputy Coveney, may come to the House in two or three weeks' time.  However, in two or three weeks' time, it will be too late for many farmers.  The situation is very serious.  Their livestock are in a desperate state because they are starving in many instances.  I pity the farmers.  It has been a terrible winter and March has been the worst on record.  Last year was so inclement and many farmers did not have the necessary fodder provisions to tide over the winter.</p><p>I appeal for an urgent debate with a heavy heart.  I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that we have a debate this evening and that the Minister or some other Minister with a knowledge of farming come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B01200"><p>I rise to support Senator O'Donovan.  I am very familiar with the hardship being suffered by farmers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B01300"><p>Is Deputy Healy Eames seconding the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B01400"><p>I am not seconding the amendment but I am supporting his concern-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B01500"><p>The Senator is half-supporting it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800003#B01600"><p>I would appreciate if I could speak.  There is a desperate fodder crisis at the moment.  We are looking for a few weeks' support until the grass grows.  It has been a very dry and bitterly cold period.  Farmers have been unable to get their cattle out and nothing is growing.  To be fair, the Minister, Deputy Coveney, addressed us on this matter last evening.  He spoke to all of the banks and the co-operatives yesterday.  Farmers have been relying on the co-operatives to provide them with lines of credit.  The banks have assured the Minister that credit is currently available to the farmers.  It is encouraging to know that Ulster Bank stated it has set money aside.  The bank is surprised that more farmers are not availing of this funding.  However, I am not surprised, given the overall concern about the banks.  Farmers must be supported at this crucial time.  We are relying on this industry to pull us out of this mess of the recession.  Farmers generate money in their local economy and they must be supported.</p> <p>This House is unanimous in calling for help for farmers and for the banks to be sympathetic to them, given that they have made that commitment to the Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800004#C00200"><p>I support previous speakers.  I have experienced the frustration and anxiety of farmers as they look at a shrinking fodder supply and cattle still inside when they should be out in the fields.</p><p>I mention an issue which is particularly acute in Galway and Roscommon.  The local authority in Galway has announced a &euro;750,000 cut in housing aid for the elderly and disabled persons.  These days as we reflect on the business of personal insolvency arrangements, in particular people's inability to pay for their houses, there is nothing as acute and frightening for a family as insecurity when it comes to the family home.  Approximately 4,800 families are seeking family homes in Galway, while approximately 500 households are waiting to be housed in Roscommon.  Given the cuts in housing aid generally, it is unlikely that there will be much progress in reducing these lists.  The call made by Cl&uacute;id, the national non-profit housing association, for innovative solutions is very welcome and timely.  Mr. Simon Brooke, its head of policy, has called on local authorities to look at long-term leasing schemes, using the large number of unoccupied houses remaining from the previously buoyant property market.  This is not a new idea, but it is one we must continue to discuss.  Will the Minister of State responsible for housing and planning, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, come to the House to clarify how the Government plans to address this problem?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" speakername="John Kelly" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800004#C00300"><p>A number of weeks ago Senator John Whelan and I called for a moratorium on wind farm developments until the review of the current guidelines was completed.  Needless to say, that call fell on deaf ears, but there have been a number of developments in the past couple of weeks as a result of a European Court of Justice ruling which found that Ireland was not compliant with an EU EIA directive.  Where property is devalued, the State will be held liable.  From a rough tot of the possible liability, we are talking about anything up to &euro;1 billion for persons affected in living too close to wind farm developments.  In the past few days we have been talking about how we can save &euro;300 million.  However, when the floodgates open on this issue, we will be talking about a sum of at least &euro;1 billion, or perhaps more.  Will the Deputy Leader bring this to the attention of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government?  It would be in everybody's interests if he could come to the House next week to debate this issue because we simply would not be able to afford this bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800004#C00400"><p>Last week Diageo announced that it would close its manufacturing plant in Waterford city.  As many know, there has been a long tradition of brewing in Waterford.  The plant mentioned which produces the concentrate, or the essence of Guinness, which is exported all over the world, has been in operation for hundreds of years.  Some 35 jobs are to go, while I understand production will be centralised in the St. James's Gate facility in Dublin.  Obviously, that is an issue for the company and I do not place responsibility for what has happened on the Minister, the Department or the Government.  Multinational companies make these decisions, but that is cold comfort for the 35 people in Waterford who might lose their jobs.  Will the Deputy Leader ask the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation what interventions have been made by him and the Department?  This is a very strange decision because in 2004 the company invested &euro;40 million in the facility in Waterford which is state-of-the-art.  Public moneys were used to invest in that facility, yet a short number of years later the company has decided to close down the manufacturing plant, despite the fact that it is state-of-the-art.  Obviously, the trade union involved is trying to put pressure on the company to reverse its decision, but if that is not possible and jobs are lost, there will be a responsibility on the Government and Enterprise Ireland to look at the future of the site and ensure some micro-brewing company is put in place in order that an iconic building in Waterford city will not be left vacant.  Obviously, our primary goal is to try to convince the company to maintain the jobs in Waterford.  What actions can be taken and what interventions can be made by the Minister and the Department to save the jobs in question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800004#C00500"><p>I again call for an independent inquiry into the death of Savita Halappanavar.  We have all seen the great pain experienced at the inquest into her death, the aim of which is to find out the cause of her death.  The reason I again call for an independent inquiry is to find out exactly what happened in the hospital and how the death occurred in a modern hospital of a woman miscarrying at 17 weeks.  This is something we need to do urgently because the case raises many questions about the health care of pregnant women.</p><p>With the indulgence of the Cathaoirleach, I draw attention to the young Senators event which will occur in the House next Tuesday.  The idea behind the event is to reach out to transition year students and allow them an opportunity to be Senators for half a day.  It is also to allow the Seanad to showcase how it operates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800004#C00600"><p>They will not be here for a full day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800004#C00800"><p>The event will start at 12.30 p.m. and there will be 45 students representing a number of counties, including Dublin, Galway, Wicklow, Roscommon, Kilkenny, Westmeath and Sligo.  We are very lucky that the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, will be here at 1.30 p.m. to hear the students' views on the leaving certificate examination and what they think should be done with it.  They will have an opportunity to read their contributions to him and he will answer questions.  The Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, will listen to their contributions on what they think about Ireland and their future here.  It will be the first time this will ever have been done in the Houses of the Oireachtas and it would be great if Senators were able to support these young people on the day and show that we were interested in their future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800004#C00900"><p>I support the impassioned plea made by my colleague, Senator Denis O'Donovan, on the fodder crisis and the amendment proposed to the Order of Business.  I inform the House that this very serious issue was raised at a meeting of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine this morning.  It was traumatic to hear the distressing tales from the south of the country, in particular, where the weather has been so horrendous in recent months.  Families are in distress such that they cannot afford to buy silage and hay.  The reason I am supporting Senator Denis O'Donovan is to call for solidarity in the farming community because one of the issues which arose at this morning's meeting was that there seemed to be exploitation of farmers in distress by unscrupulous marketeers, which is the only way I can describe them because I do not know from where they come, but they are reportedly selling bales of silage for upwards of &euro;50 or &euro;60, which is exploitation at its worst.  I hope somebody will report not only on this call for a debate but also on the call for solidarity in the farming community and that at this time of crisis those with surplus fodder will release it at reasonable prices to those farming families in serious distress which is being added to by the fact that the banks are not lending money.  The figures about which we are talking are significant.  It has been estimated that in the case of an average holding, a farmer may have to find upwards of &euro;10,000 to maintain proper feeding standards.</p> <p>Senator O'Donovan is right that animals are dropping dead from starvation.  Imagine that happening in this day and age in a civilised country.  People are exploiting the distress suffered by farmers.  I call for some solidarity and hope that the IFA will engage immediately, as a matter of urgency.  I hope that it will ensure that fodder will be provided to farmers who need it and are in distress.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D00200"><p>I support the call by Senator Mooney for solidarity among the farming community.  Yesterday I supported the call by Senator O'Donovan for a debate on the crisis in the farming community.  I welcome the statement made by the Minister yesterday when he said that he had made personal contact with the banks and the merchants asking that the farming community be treated fairly and with consideration and compassion.  I hope the period of distress will be short-term.  Over the next couple of weeks the farming community should be in a better position when the grass begins to grow and the weather improves.  It is appalling that unscrupulous people make money on the back of struggling farmers at this time.  I strongly urge the IFA to become actively involved and ensure solidarity in its community so that better-off farmers assist those in dire need.  It is appalling that animals are dying of hunger in this day and age.  I hope that merchants will play their part in helping farmers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D00300"><p>I ask the Leader to investigate a troubling matter and report to the Seanad.  I understand that a group calling itself the Iona Institute deliberately misled the convention by knowingly using inappropriate information.  It is serious that a body established by both Houses of the Oireachtas should be so misled.</p><p>  I refer to page 1 of the institute's submission which quoted a 2002 Child Trends Research Brief entitled Marriage from a Child's Perspective: How Does Family Structure Affect Children, and What Can We Do About It?  The institute cited the report as supporting its case against marriage equality.  The authors of the report placed a disclaimer on its front page stating:<blockquote>Note: This Child Trends brief summarizes research conducted in 2002, when neither same-sex parents nor adoptive parents were identified in large national surveys.  Therefore, no conclusions can be drawn from this research about wellbeing of children raised by same-sex parents or adoptive parents.  </blockquote>The authors contacted the convention to make its disclaimer plain.  This situation is a repeat of what happened some years ago when somebody associated with the group wrote an opinion piece citing scientific surveys and so on.  The article was immediately met with a disclaimer in the letters column by the very authors cited who said that it was a completely inappropriate use of their research material.  Attempts were also made to impugn individual members with tables-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D00400"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D00500"><p>I do and indicated that right at the beginning.  My question is very serious and I ask for the Cathaoirleach's indulgence, please.</p><p>Complaints were made, investigated and found to be untrue.  Will the Deputy Leader contact the convention and ask it to confirm these matters that I believe to be true?  Having satisfied herself that this is the case, will she establish for us who are these people?  How were they established?  What is their membership?  What is their constitution?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D00600"><p>The matter is more appropriate for the Adjournment debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D00700"><p>No, it is a matter for the Deputy Leader because this is a very, very serious matter.  If people are deliberately misleading a body established by the Oireachtas with the plain knowledge that the authors of research have said that their research must not be used in this situation.  The matter should trouble all of us who believe in truth, integrity and the decency of public standards.  This body must be held accountable.  I have one more question.  How is it funded?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D00800"><p>Go raibh maith agat, a Chathaoirligh.  I, too, join with my colleagues on both sides of the House in their call for support to be given to the farming community.  The problem seems worse in the south.  Having listened to the stories debated at my party's meeting at 9.30 a.m. a letter will be sent to the Minister.  Yesterday evening at a meeting of my parliamentary party, as my colleague, Senator Healy Eames, has said, we were briefed that the Minister had been in touch with the banks and co-ops.  I know that a large co-op in the south is importing hay from England and selling it to farmers at cost price.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D00900"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" speakername="Michael Comiskey" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01000"><p>I reiterate what my colleague, Senator Mooney, has said.  It is important to have solidarity between farmers now.  I will telephone my colleagues in the IFA this morning to make sure that farmers with fodder will transport it to the areas that are stricken and in difficulty.  My party has been involved in this procedure during difficult years.  We worked with farmers who had fodder, covered the cost of transport and moved fodder to areas experiencing difficulties.  I hope that something will alleviate the problem in the next few days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01100"><p>I suggest that Senator Kelly table Committee Stage of his Wind Turbines Bill 2012.  It would resolve some of the issues that he raised regarding the location of turbines next to families and their homes, particularly in Rahara, County Roscommon where a family have been badly affected.</p><p>There is a two-tier system in the Labour Party.  The upper echelon comprises Senator Ivana Bacik and a few more who get their Bills through the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01200"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01300"><p>The lower echelon comprises the newcomers, the Senators who rose with the "Gilmore gale" and  came from all parties and none.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01400"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Deputy Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" speakername="Averil Power" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01500"><p>They defer to the Labour Party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01600"><p>From all parties and none they were all gathered up by the gale and were blown in here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01700"><p>The Senator is very ill-informed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01800"><p>They were blown in and they will be blown out as fast.  A gale works both ways.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D01900"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Deputy Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D02000"><p>I do not want to give my view of the gale.  I ask Senators to bear in mind that gales can go in reverse.  I ask the Deputy Leader to convince the Government to take Committee Stage of Senator Kelly's Bill as she is so persuasive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D02100"><p>It is hot air rather than a gale.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D02200"><p>Senator Bacik is special within the Labour Party.</p><p>I support the good proposal made by Senator O'Donovan to deal with the fodder crisis, which was supported by other Senators.  The crisis is evident and there is not one bale of hay left where I live in the parish of Athleague-Fuerty.  In my area people sell them at a normal price but the cost of buying fodder from mills and so on is a terrible hardship for farmers.</p><p>Fianna F&aacute;il always responded to such situations but the Government and the Minister seem to be above doing so.  He is too busy in Europe and is obviously not interested in the situation.  There is a crisis here and it is about time that Fine Gael Senators asked their Minister to do something and take stern action.  I am not talking about ringing bank managers or co-operatives.  I implore it to do like what my party did when it faced such crises in the past.  I suggest the Government provide a distress fund, import fodder at a price or even involve the Army to transport or import fodder.  Fianna F&aacute;il always took action in such situations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D02500"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il acted all right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D02600"><p>Excuse me, madam.  The former Minister, Mr. Joe Walsh, prevented foot and mouth disease from entering the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D02700"><p>He never got much thanks for doing so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800005#D02800"><p>It is hard to get a word in.  Something very serious has occurred.  The Irish Lung Fibrosis Association is concerned at a decision taken by the National Centre for Pharmacoeconomics, NCPE, not to make Pirfenidone available to patients.  I have been a patron of the association for some time.  Lung fibrosis is a very serious disease with no cure but Pirfenidone enables people to stay alive.  The issue is not dissimilar to what happened with cystic fibrosis sufferers earlier this year when a decision was made not to spend money on a drug.  A campaign led to the Minister reversing his decision and made an exception for cystic fibrosis sufferers even though the drug is costly.  The Irish Lung Fibrosis Association faces the same dilemma and is concerned.  Not many sufferers are involved but the drug will keep them alive.  Its benefits were only discovered in recent times.</p> <p>It has been approved by the European Medicines Agency and the National Institute for Health and Clinical Accidents in Britain but we have not allowed it to be distributed to patients.  It is worthy of the same attention given to the drug for cystic fibrosis earlier in the year.  I will write to the Leader on the issue and also to the Minister for Health.  Attention needs to be drawn to the issue and it should be given the necessary priority to save lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E00200"><p>T&aacute; go leor caint faoi dhaoine sa ch&oacute;ras ag baint m&iacute;-leas as daoine bochta leochailleacha.  There is much talk about people in the system exploiting vulnerable people.  I agree with those statements in regard to the farming community and certainly their help is needed.  Another example of that, which we have raised on a number of occasions, is the direct provision system.  There are still approximately 6,000 people in 43 hostels across the country.  One third of those in direct provision are children and many of the families are in the system for more than five years.  It is important to note that in the past ten years 53 people died in direct provision, a quarter of whom were under five years of age.  It is a privatised system.  People who are running for-profit centres are profiting on the backs of other people's difficulties.  On a positive note I remind Members that we have called for a debate on the issue and ask the Deputy Leader when it may take place.</p><p>An unusual presentation is taking place today, next door to the Kildare Street Hotel, in Comhdh&aacute;il N&aacute;isi&uacute;nta na Gaeilge, where a full scale model of a direct provision room, made by Doras Luimn&iacute;, shows where people are asked to stay in a direct provision centre.  A presentation is also being made by the Irish Refugee Council, AkiDwA and Doras Luimn&iacute;.  I call on all Senators to go there between now and 4 p.m. and get the information.  I ask the Deputy Leader to outline when the debate promised to Senator Jillian van Turnhout and me will take place.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E00300"><p>In the context of the debate on mortgage arrears yesterday and other comments on the issue, there is a need for a publicly-funded financial adviser to provide advice to borrowers in distress at an early stage.  Currently borrowers in such circumstances are entitled to have &euro;250 towards an accountant who can have a look at the deal that has been struck with the bank which is too late as far as I am concerned.  To a large extent the public is not aware of the &euro;250 fee which is available to accountants.  It is better than nothing but we need a publicly-funded adviser who can assist at an early stage.  The Money Advice and Budgeting Service is doing a great job in assisting and organising people with debt.  Not only does it not have the specific expertise to interact with banks and advise on deals at an early stage but it is inundated with work and unable to deal with this ever-increasing issue.  I ask the Deputy Leader to arrange for a debate on this issue in the near future when the Minister for Finance would come to the House, although we debated mortgage arrears yesterday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E00400"><p>I ask the Deputy Leader to arrange for the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform to come to the House for an early debate in light of the vote on Croke Park II.  It is imperative that the choices being made by Government are fair.  Previously I raised the issue of housing grants for the elderly, the disabled and mobility grants, all of which have been cut.  My own County Wexford has had a cut of 55% in its allocation for this year.  This means that those who had been waiting three and four years for these grants are saving the Exchequer a considerable sum of money.  Without these grant aids they would be in State care much earlier which is very expensive.  There is a compelling reason for reinstating the level of allocation.  Wexford and other countries were very dependent on the construction industry for employment and due to the collapse of the industry there is considerable unemployment.  These small schemes were the ideal projects which many Members on all sides spoke of for getting people back to work.  There are people who are unemployed who could be usefully engaged doing good work to assist people to remain in their own homes.  This is a false economy.  I ask the Deputy Leader to arrange for the Minister to come to the House for a debate on the difficult fiscal position, which nobody denies.  Hard choices have to be made but, unfortunately, the choices being made are wrong.  We need an informed debate and given the decision taken this week it is imperative that debate takes place sooner rather than later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E00500"><p>I second Senator Barrett's amendment to the Order of Business.</p><p>I join the leader of my party in calling on the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, to come to the House.  I ask the Deputy Leader to set aside quite a few hours for a debate as there are many issues to be discussed.  Those issues include: the low morale in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na; the depletion in the numbers of the force, with no recruitment on the cards; the inability of members to do their job due to a lack of equipment, in many cases they use their own cars and mobile telephones to do a job which should be facilitated by the State; the closure of Garda stations, courthouses and Army barracks; the debacle with the Judiciary; and, in particular, why D&uacute;n U&iacute; Neill barracks in Cavan, was closed in March without any logical reason being given for doing so.  It was the most modern barracks in Europe and the only purpose-built barracks in the history of the State, located seven miles from the Fermanagh Border, where there has been three incidents involving dissident terrorists in the past month.  I pointed out on many occasions, as other colleagues did, that the terrorist threat to the State is not gone.  This has been proven seven miles from Cavan town, the location of D&uacute;n U&iacute; Neill barracks, where three incidents have taken place in the past month.  </p><p>That the G8 summit is to be held in Enniskillen in June 2013 is welcome.  What will the Government do to protect the Border?  From where will the troops come?  They will come from Athlone, where they were moved from Cavan, for a month and will have to be facilitated in private accommodation.  I predict that a barracks will again have to be built in Cavan town to protect the State from the threat that exists.  I ask that the Minister for Justice and Equality come to the House and to be open and honest, not shrouded in a straitjacket of pomposity, and to tell Members exactly what is going on in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Defence Forces, of which he has made a total shambles to date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E00600"><p>I agree wholeheartedly with my Ulster colleague, Senator Wilson, in his call to invite the Minister for Justice and Equality, the most arrogant Minister in Europe, to the House as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E00700"><p>The Senator would know all about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E00800"><p>I put a message on Facebook yesterday.  One of the comments read: "I am sure Minister Shatter had no friends at school."  He is certainly losing friends very quickly given the arrogant and blunt manner in which he is taking decisions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E00900"><p>Those are very personal remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E01000"><p>It is totally unacceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E01100"><p>I think the Senator should withdraw those comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800006#E01200"><p>On a point of order, they are not my words, I read them on the Internet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F00200"><p>They are very personal remarks.  They have been put on the record of the House and should be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F00300"><p>I have only quoted the words.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F00400"><p>The Senator should not have quoted them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.75" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F00600"><p>I can confirm that he does indeed have friends - not a great many but some.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F00700"><p>The Senator should withdraw the remarks.  Senator Norris should resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F00800"><p>Senator Norris has clarified the position very well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F00900"><p>It does not matter if the comments were on the Internet or not.  They should be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01000"><p>They were not meant personally but are available for all our colleagues to read on the Internet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01100"><p>Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill chose to put them on the record of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01200"><p>On a point of order, it is appropriate for Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill to criticise the Minister politically, but the personalised attack must be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01300"><p>I ask the Senator to withdraw the remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01400"><p>I will amend the remarks.  They are quotes on the Internet to which I will not refer further.  However, the point I am trying to make is a valid one.  Anyone with a political understanding of what is happening in the country will realise that the Garda is being treated with contempt.  The people who defend the State, our elderly and young and prevent crime are being treated with contempt.  Garda cars in my constituency have done more than 300,000 km and are being taken off the road.  Garda&iacute; do not have transportation to investigate crime.  The Minister is treating the country with contempt.  Not only is he being arrogant in his defence and justice portfolios, he is treating the safety of the nation with contempt.  I agree wholeheartedly with Senator Wilson that the Minister should come to the House to explain the rationale behind some of his decisions.</p><p>I support the raising of the fodder crisis.  It is a major issue which received all-party support at the meeting of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine this morning.  The problem is one for farmers west of a line between Donegal to Waterford.  Many animals are dying as a result.  People are charging up to &euro;78 for a bale of silage and the crisis is escalating.  The Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine must address the crisis immediately and support farmers.  It is now an animal welfare issue, which is a subject on which the Minister recently came to the House to process legislation.  He must live up to the legislation he brought before the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01500"><p>We are constantly harangued on the Opposition side by Members on the Government side about the bad decisions Fianna F&aacute;il made.  I joined Fianna F&aacute;il because the people in it, from Lemass on, were pragmatic doers.  In 2001, the then Minister for Agriculture and Food, Joe Walsh, single-handedly prevented foot and mouth disease from spreading in Ireland.  Every  morning he held crisis meetings and put plans in place which were implemented on a daily basis.  The current Minister is a bit wet behind the ears on how to achieve anything other than PR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01600"><p>That is another personal attack.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.87" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01800"><p>That is unparliamentary language.  It is not a fair remark to make about a Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F01900"><p>I have heard Senators call for meetings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F02000"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F02100"><p>We need the Minister to lead from the front and deal with the crisis in agriculture.  On Sunday, I had the pleasure of going to Moneygall, outside which the sign I achieved in getting erected said it was the ancestral home of President Obama.  It was put up last week.  All the animals in the field beside the sign ran towards us because they thought they were going to be fed.  They were hungry.  We need the Minister to lead from the front like a military general to solve the problem.  We must think of the pain of the lambs, sheep and cows that are hungry.  It is terrible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F02200"><p>Unfortunately, generals tend to lead from the back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800007#F02300"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien raised a number of matters, including the Civil Registration (Marriage Equality) Bill which is on the Order Paper in my name.  I hope to bring it forward as soon as I can.  I am conscious that colleagues might have other matters they wish to raise during the Labour Party's Private Members' time.  It will take its turn.</p><p>  I can ask when the Minister for Justice and Equality will be available for a debate on policing.  To be fair to the Minister, he is in the House on a very regular basis and is one of the Ministers who most frequently initiate Bills in the Seanad.  It is an important thing to note.  It is very good for the House and the quality of debate on Bills generally when they commence here.  The Minister will be here regularly in the coming weeks on other legislation.</p><p>  Senator Coghlan raised developments in the context of the speech of the Chief Justice at Griffith College's law society.  I join the Senator in commending the Chief Justice, Mrs. Justice Susan Denham, for her measured approach and her steady hand.  I should declare my own interest as a barrister and member of the Law Library.  Many of us with an interest in the area anticipated that the Chief Justice would have sensible comments to make on the matter.  As she has said, the Attorney General is the appropriate channel for communication between the Judiciary and the Executive.  That has remained the case in recent weeks when the matter has been in the media.  The Chief Justice has established a working group for renewal which will support the channels of communication which have remained in place and which continue to remain in place between the Judiciary and the Executive through the offices of the Attorney General.  It is very clear that the working group will work very well in supporting the communication channels.  We are all very conscious of the need to protect the separation of powers but also to ensure as a matter of practicality that there are working channels of communication.  I am very glad the issue has been dealt with clearly by the Chief Justice.</p><p>  Senator Barrett raised the welcome news of the university rankings in which Trinity College Dublin is ranked 48th in the world.  I join the Senator in commending the ranking.  I join the Senator in expressing concern on reports of an increase in charges by AIB.  Other Senators have sought a debate on banking, in which context the issue might be raised.  He also raised the matter of an amendment to item 14 on the Order of Business to debate his Financial Stability and Reform Bill.  I am happy to accept the amendment in the normal way.</p><p>  Senator Hayden raised the publication of the personal insolvency guidelines which will be launched by the Minister for Finance this afternoon.  There has been a great deal of debate in the context of the guidelines, which we all look forward to seeing.  I am glad to see reports today which suggest there will be a degree of flexibility built into them.  Senator Hayden is right to say the guidelines will, at least, give borrowers in distress objective criteria by which they may deal with banks.  It is very important that banks be held to account.  The current case-by-case way in which borrowers are being dealt with raises issues about inconsistency and arbitrary decisions.  It will be very helpful to have a clear set of guidelines in place.  We hope they will be sensible and provide the required degree of flexibility.  Senator Hayden also sought a debate with the Minister for Finance on the role of the banks.  She has sought that before and I will renew my request to the Minister.</p><p>  Senator O'Donovan was the first to raise the fodder crisis.  He very kindly referred to my Crookstown roots, which I am always delighted to recall.  I grew up to the west of Cork city in the Crookstown-Macroom area where there is a strong farming community.  I am aware of the serious fodder issue and the great distress of farm families who see livestock starving.  It is an issue many colleagues raised.  Senators Healy Eames, Mullen, Mooney, Mullins, Comiskey, Leyden, &Oacute; Clochartaigh, &Oacute; Domhnaill and White also raised the issue.  Senator O'Donovan called for an amendment to the Order of Business.  While I have sympathy for the proposal, I cannot accept it.  I have put in a call and cannot get the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to attend the House today.  As there has been such concern, I will read a statement from the Minister as to what has been going on.  The matter was also raised at the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine which is writing to the Minister for an urgent response and will follow the matter up strenuously in the coming days.  The statement reads:<blockquote>Over the past number of days the Minister Coveney and Department officials have spoken to members of the pillar banks and representatives of a number of co-ops, including Glanbia, Dairygold and Lakeland.  The Minister spoke individually to representatives from the main banks operating in the sector - Ulster Bank, AIB and Bank of Ireland.  <br />Ulster Bank:<br />Last autumn made available a &#8364;15 million &quot;weather fund&quot; to farmers to be drawn down as short term loans in recognition of the bad weather last summer.  Their preference is that farmers would take down lower interest short-term loans in preference to more expensive overdraft facilities.  More recently they have released &#8364;10 million in response to the crisis in Northern Ireland, this fund however is also available for farmers in the Republic of Ireland. <br />AIB:<br />They have put a significant number of personnel in place to deal with the issues facing farmers on the ground and the increased demand for overdraft and short-term facilities.  AIB are encouraging farmers to come forward to talk to them about their individual circumstances.  They are insistent that farmers will get a positive response as they see this [as many colleagues described it] as a short term financing issue in a year when prices for milk and meat in particular will remain strong.<br />Bank of Ireland:<br />Like the other banks they are encouraging farmers to come and talk to them and they are anxious to make credit facilities available to the farming community. Some of the figures worth noting from the bank include:<br />Only 65% of existing overdraft facilities are being currently used across their portfolio of farming customers.<br />While there has been a 15% increase in requests for increased overdraft facilities by farmers this is much less than the increases requested by other small business sectors.<br />While there has been an increase in demand for short term loans it has not been dramatic.<br />All three banks were insistent that they view farming and farmers as customers to be facilitated in the current fodder crisis with regard to access to credit facilities in form of overdrafts and short term loans.  [The Minister] will be meeting the banks in person next week and will continue the conversation with them.<br />Co-Ops:<br />With regard to the Co-Ops that were spoken to a number of significant initiatives are apparent [and many colleagues recognise that this is not just an issue that concerns banks but also a matter for farming solidarity, for the IFA to intervene and for co-ops and merchants to intervene].<br />Over &#8364;25 million in additional credit facilities have been made available to farmers. <br />In the specific case of Dairygold who are responding to these exceptional circumstances they are making interest free credit available for purchases of ruminant feed that are taking place in March and April.  They are also importing a large volume of hay from the UK and making it available at cost to farmers in need.<br /><br />  The Minister and Department have been reassured by the conversations with the Co-Ops that they are aware of and are continuing to support their members in recognition of the significant pressure that farmers are under.  The Minister and Department will continue to monitor the situation closely on a daily basis and will respond appropriately as the situation develops.</blockquote>I hope the information provides some assistance and some comfort to colleagues but I am aware it is a distressing situation for many farm families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G00200"><p>It is not much good in the west of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G00300"><p>It is something the Minister is very much aware of and is responding to on a daily basis.  I am also conscious the Minister will be in the House to deal with the Animal Health and Welfare Bill.  Colleagues can raise these concerns at that point.</p><p>Senator Healy Eames also referred to the fodder crisis and I have set out a detailed response to her concerns.  Senator Mullen also raised the housing crisis and asked for the Minister of State with responsibility for housing to come to the House.  The Minister of State, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, will attend the House on 15 May to discuss wind energy.  Perhaps we can expand the debate.</p><p>Senator Kelly referred to a wind farm moratorium.  The Minister of State will be in the House on 15 May to discuss the matter.</p><p>Senator Cullinane referred to the potential closure of a Diageo manufacturing plant in Watford.  It is a sensitive issue and we all join him in hoping the efforts to ensure jobs are not lost will be successful.  It is perhaps early to seek a debate in the House on the matter given the current nature of talks.  We all hope the jobs will be kept.  Enterprise Ireland will work on it.</p><p>Senator O'Keeffe raised the matter of an independent inquiry into the death of Savita Halappanavar.  Those listening to reports of the inquest are very concerned to hear the evidence emerging, particularly the evidence yesterday of Dr. Peter Boylan, the former master of the National Maternity Hospital.  He gave expert evidence that suggests the real problem is with the law and the lack of legal clarity.  It shows us that X case legislation may not go far enough and that the problem lies with the wording of the eighth amendment and the serious difficulty-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G00400"><p>With respect to all sides, we are not having a debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G00500"><p>The Deputy Leader without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G00600"><p>On a point of order, it is not appropriate to have a debate when the Deputy Leader is introducing her view on something and when no one else can respond.  There are ways of having a proper debate in a respectful way-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G00700"><p>I am responding to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G00800"><p>The Deputy Leader is responding to the questions raised by the House.  Please allow the Deputy Leader to proceed without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G00900"><p>I think the Deputy Leader is abusing her position to some degree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01000"><p>Senator Darragh O'Brien, I am responding to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01100"><p>Senator Bacik is referring to a pro-abortion doctor.  He sent his sister-in-law in here during the health committee hearings.  The man's opinion on the issue is on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01200"><p>The Deputy Leader is responding to questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01300"><p>She is very selective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01400"><p>It is a sensitive issue and it is not appropriate for the Deputy Leader to use the response to a request for a debate to expand upon her own point of view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01500"><p>Deputy Darragh O'Brien should resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01600"><p>She is entitled to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01700"><p>The Deputy Leader without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01800"><p>As Deputy Leader of the House, I ask for respect.  I am responding to an issue raised by a colleague.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G01900"><p>Senator Bacik is giving her own opinion, which is pro-abortion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02000"><p>Can we have the Deputy Leader without interruption?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02100"><p>I ask Senator Walsh to withdraw that deeply offensive remark.  It is a disgrace and Senator Walsh is a disgrace.  I ask for it to be withdrawn.  Will the Cathaoirleach ask him to withdraw it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02200"><p>I did not hear the remark.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02300"><p>I did, and he said the Deputy Leader of the House was pro-abortion.  It was very clear, he said it and I ask him to withdraw it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02400"><p>I call the Deputy Leader, allow her to proceed without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02500"><p>Will the Cathaoirleach ask him to withdraw it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02600"><p>I did not hear what the Senator said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02700"><p>If I said it, I would not withdraw it because it would be true.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02800"><p>Did the Cathaoirleach hear that?  Was it clear enough?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G02900"><p>We are allowed to speak the truth in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03100"><p>I ask that the Cathaoirleach assert some respect for the role of the Deputy Leader of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03200"><p>On a point of order, as the inquest is under way, Senator Bacik should not prejudice the outcome of the inquest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03400"><p>That is not a point of order.  The Deputy Leader is responding to questions raised in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03500"><p>I am sorry, this is a serious matter.  She is prejudicing the outcome of an inquest in Galway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03600"><p>The record of the House will show the points raised this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03700"><p>The record will show very serious statements.  It should be brought to the attention of the coroner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03800"><p>Senator Leyden raised issues this morning and the Deputy Leader is trying to respond to the questions raised by Members.  We should have some respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G03900"><p>I did not refer to an inquest under way in Galway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04000"><p>Can House have respect for the Deputy Leader, who is responding to the questions raised?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04100"><p>The coroner should be informed of her statements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04200"><p>The record of the House will show that the longest response I have given and will give is the response on the agriculture issue, the fodder crisis in farming, which was raised by the majority of people who spoke.  I gave a full response directly from the Minister.  That is the way in which I am seeking to respond to every colleague in the House in a courteous and fulsome way, to deal fully with the issues raised and to respond in an appropriate way.  As a lawyer, I take strong objection to the suggestion that I am in some way overstepping the line.  I take that very seriously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04300"><p>Senator Bacik is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04400"><p>Senator Bacik is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04500"><p>I will be raising the issue with the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  I will also be raising issues about personal attacks because there have been many from the other side of the House----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04600"><p>Were they on Senator Bacik?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04700"><p>Not just on me.  Political attacks are one thing but to make attacks on people is another issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04800"><p>We can say whatever we like about people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G04900"><p>Senator Bacik selected one piece of evidence-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G05000"><p>Senator Leyden, we will now hear from the Deputy Leader as she finishes up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800008#G05100"><p>I have quite a bit more, as many other colleagues raised issues that deserve a response.  I will deal with the issues unless colleagues want me not to respond.  The role of the Deputy Leader is to respond to queries raised.  Senator O'Keeffe raised the issue of the need for an independent inquiry into the death of Savita Halappanavar and there are issues raised on the evidence presented at the inquest.</p><p>Senator O'Keeffe also raised the issue of the young Senators event next Tuesday, 23 April, from 12.30 p.m.  to 2.30 p.m.  We should commend Senator O'Keeffe on the immense work done on initiating the proposal for a great event.  Some 45 students from different counties will come into the Chamber to experience what it is like to be a legislator.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Quinn, and the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Fitzgerald, will attend and I know colleagues will be very supportive of the endeavour.  All colleagues are invited to attend and I commend Senator O'Keeffe on taking the initiative.</p><p>Senators Mooney and Mullins also referred to the fodder crisis, which I have dealt with.  Senator Norris referred to the Iona Institute submission to the Constitutional Convention, which he said mis-cited a report entitled Child Trends from 2002.  The authors of the report placed a disclaimer on the front saying it was not to be cited in debates on marriage equality.  </p> <p>Senator Norris said that that organisation has communicated its concern to the convention that it was misreported or mis-cited in its submission to it.  I share the Senator's concerns and I will be happy to pass them on to the convention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H00200"><p>The Deputy Leader might also contact the Iona Institute.  It would be interesting to hear what it has to say on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H00300"><p>The Deputy Leader, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H00400"><p>The institute might take a different view of what Senator Norris said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H00500"><p>That would not suit Senator Bacik's agenda.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H00600"><p>It is a matter then for the convention to make a response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.149" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H00800"><p>Please allow the Deputy Leader to continue without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H00900"><p>Senator Norris asked me to contact the convention and I will do as he has asked.</p><p>Senator Comiskey raised the issue of the fodder crisis.  The Labour Party is always happy to hear Senator Leyden's pearls of wisdom on the internal affairs of the Labour Party.  It was a lot of hot air.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01000"><p>The Gilmore gale.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01100"><p>That will blow out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01200"><p>Senator Quinn raised the issue of lung fibrosis.  While it is not an issue of which I am aware I would be grateful if he could pass on the details to me which I, in turn, will pass on to the Minister for Health as it would appear to be a serious matter.   While as the Senator stated only a small number of people in the country will be affected, it is nonetheless an important issue.  As in the case of the issue raised by Senator Norris, I will pass on the information on the issue raised by Senator Quinn to the Minister for Health.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh raised concerns about the direct provision system, on which he and other Senators have previously called for a debate.  I will again request the Minister to come to the House for a debate on that issue.  I am aware of the briefing today by the Irish Refugee Council, Doras Luimni and AkiDwa on direct provision, which I will attend.  I am sure other Senators will also attend it.  </p><p>Senator Noone raised the issue of financial advisers and borrowers in distress, which matter might well be dealt with as part of the general debate on banking sought by other Senators.  Senator Walsh asked that the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin, come to the House for a debate on the second Croke Park agreement.  The comments made yesterday by the Taoiseach, T&aacute;naiste and Minister, Deputy Howlin, illustrate the need for a period of reflection, on both sides, to consider what should be the response on this issue.  There is a consciousness among parties, particularly on the Government side, and on the part of those unions which urged a &quot;Yes&quot; vote that the core of the agreement is worth saving, in particular the need to protect core pay of public servants earning less than &euro;65,000, as per the agreement.  It is important to point out that some unions had negotiated separate sectoral arrangements, which were agreed by members.  It is too soon to ask the Minister, Deputy Howlin, to come to this House for a debate on that matter.  I hope we will see a further phase of negotiation.  I believe that is quite likely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01300"><p>What about the debate on housing aids for the elderly and grants for disabled people?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01400"><p>The Deputy Leader without interruption please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01500"><p>We can invite the Minister, Deputy Howlin, to the House when that period has ended.  Senator Walsh can ask that the Minister, Deputy Howlin, come to the House for a debate on the issues he raised.</p><p>Senator Wilson seconded Senator Barrett's amendment, which I have already accepted.  He also called for a debate with the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Shatter, on the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and policing.  The specific issue of the barracks in Cavan might well be a matter more suitably raised on the Adjournment.  Senator Wilson also raised the issue of security for the G8 meeting in Fermanagh, which he has raised previously and to which he received a response.  There has been a great deal of communication between the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and Police Service of Northern Ireland on this issue.  I am sure adequate security arrangements will be put in place for that important meeting being held in Fermanagh, which we welcome.  It is a huge boost not alone for Fermanagh but the entire region.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill also raised the issue of policing.  I believe he withdrew his personalised attack on the Minister, Deputy Shatter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01700"><p>It was not a personalised attack, it was a matter of fact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01800"><p>Please allow the Deputy Leader to continue without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H01900"><p>They are attacking our party.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02000"><p>I suggest the Deputy Leader have a cup of green tea and calm down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02100"><p>The Deputy Leader without interruption please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02200"><p>Suffice to say that all of us in this House have immense respect for the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  To suggest that anyone in this House or the D&aacute;il has contempt for the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na is utter nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02300"><p>Ask the garda&iacute; and the unions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02400"><p>The Deputy Leader without interruption please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02500"><p>I have worked on the front line in criminal law for many years.  I have enormous respect and admiration for the dangerous work done by garda&iacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02600"><p>We all have great respect for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02700"><p>It is outrageous to suggest that anyone in this House, in particular those with knowledge of the law, would have contempt for the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  It is utterly outrageous to suggest that.</p><p>Senator White raised the issue of the fodder crisis, to which I have already responded adequately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02800"><p>Senator Barrett has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 14 be taken before No. 1."  The Deputy Leader has accepted the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>Senator O'Donovan has also moved an amendment to the Order of Business: &quot;That a debate on the current crisis in farming be taken today.&quot;  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800009#H02900"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.171" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>Amendment put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.172" nospeaker="true" time="11:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800010#J00100"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(b) I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.174/1" nospeaker="true" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800010#J00200"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 19; Nl, 26.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.174/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-04-18" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800010#J00200">
            <divisioncount ayes="19" noes="26" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" vote="aye">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="aye">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="no">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="no">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="no">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="no">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.174/3" nospeaker="true" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800010#J00200"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.175/1" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800011#K00100"><p>Question put: "That the Order of Business, as amended, be agreed to."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 27; Nl, 19.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden; Nl, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.175/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-04-18" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800011#K00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="27" noes="19" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="aye">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="aye">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="aye">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="aye">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="aye">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="aye">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="aye">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="aye">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="aye">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="aye">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="aye">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="aye">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="aye">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="aye">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="aye">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="aye">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="aye">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="aye">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="aye">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="aye">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="aye">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="no">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="no">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="no">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" vote="no">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="no">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="no">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="no">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="no">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="no">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="no">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="no">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="no">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="no">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="no">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="no">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="no">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.175/3" nospeaker="true" time="11:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800011#K00100"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.176" nospeaker="true" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800012#L00100">Financial Stability and Reform Bill 2013: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800012#L00200"><p>I move:<blockquote><br />That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to to promote the financial stability of Ireland by improving accountability and transparency in the financial system; reduce systemic risk; end &#8216;&#8216;too big to fail&#8217;&#8217;; improve capital adequacy and to protect the State from non-transparent safety net subsidies and open-ended bailouts of monetary and financial institutions.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.178" nospeaker="true" time="11:50:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800012#L00400"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800012#L00500"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800012#L00600"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.182" nospeaker="true" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800012#L00700">Public Health (Tobacco) (Amendment) Bill 2013: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.183" nospeaker="true" time="11:50:00" ><p>Question proposed: &quot;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800012#L00900"><p>I welcome the opportunity to speak on the Public Health (Tobacco) (Amendment) Bill 2013 and to outline the background to the amendments being introduced.  As a public health measure, Ireland has for many years set a mandatory level below which the price of cigarettes could not be lowered.  For over 30 years an arrangement was in place between the Department of Health and Irish tobacco companies whereby a weighted average price was calculated for cigarettes based on sales volumes data and retail prices to year end each year.  However, in 2010 the European Court of Justice ruled that by imposing minimum retail prices for cigarettes, Ireland had failed to fulfil its obligations under article 9(1) of Council Directive 95/59/EC.  As a consequence of the court judgment, Ireland can no longer set a mandatory level below which cigarette prices cannot be lowered, as this would be restricting the freedom of industry to make effective use of competitive advantage.  The Commission indicated that infringement proceedings would be initiated unless Ireland took steps to comply with the court's judgment.</p><p>As a result of this ruling, my Department informed the tobacco industry that the practice of setting floor prices for cigarettes each year would cease.  In addition Ireland advised the Commission that new regulations would be introduced to remedy the infringement.  Draft regulations were developed to remove the price setting provisions currently in our tobacco regulations.  During this process, and after a considerable period of time, the Commission indicated that in addition to the new regulations the primary enabling tobacco legislation would also have to be amended to meet with the requirements of the court judgment.  The purpose of amending the primary legislation would be to remove the legal basis for the fixing of a minimum price.  In order to comply with the court judgment, therefore, new regulations were to be devised and the primary tobacco legislation was to be amended.</p><p>It is important to state that I have completed the first step in complying with the court's ruling.</p> <p>Last December I signed regulations, the Tobacco Products (Control of Advertising, Sponsorship and Sales Promotion)(Amendment) Regulations 2012, which had the effect of removing the regulatory basis for the fixing of a minimum price.  On examination of the tobacco legislation, it appeared that both the Public Health (Tobacco) Act 2002 and the Tobacco Products (Control of Advertising, Sponsorship and Sales Promotion) Act 1978 required amendment to satisfy the court judgment.  This Bill achieves this in that it removes the legal basis for the fixing of a minimum price.  However, in amending the relevant sections of the Act it is important that I and future Ministers retain powers to introduce regulations relating to tobacco sales promotion activities.  A provision in the Bill allows for the development of regulations in this regard.  More specifically, it sets out some of the types of promotions to be included in these regulations such as prohibiting buy-three-for-two, happy hour promotions or buy-one-get-one-free offers.  The issue of sales promotion activities falls outside of the European Court of Justice ruling because it does not relate to minimum or maximum pricing of tobacco and was not, therefore, a direct requirement of the European Commission.</p><p> Section 1 amends section 38 of the Public Health (Tobacco) Act 2002 by removing any perceived price fixing provision.  However, it retains the power to make regulations in respect of activities which are intended or are likely to promote the sale of tobacco products.  Specifically, the new section 38(10) gives the Minister for Health the power to make these regulations.</p><p> The new section 38(10A) sets out some of the provisions which may be included in these regulations, namely, the prohibition of the promotion and sale of tobacco products at a reduced price or free of charge on the purchase of another tobacco product or other products or services.  This covers the types of promotions mentioned - buy-three-for-two, happy hour promotions or buy-one-get-one-free offers.  It also covers the prohibition of the promotion and sale of tobacco products at a reduced price or free of charge for a limited period of time on any day.  This prohibits happy hour type promotions.</p><p> The new section 38(11) makes it an offence for someone to contravene the regulations made under section 38(10).  In this context, it is important to state my Department, in consultation with the Health Service Executive, is continuously monitoring the ever evolving marketing tactics of the tobacco industry.  As these evolve, so too must our legislative and policy framework.</p><p> I am sorry the young men and ladies from France have left the Visitors Gallery.  It is important to remind ourselves that 700,000 Europeans, including 5,200 Irish citizens, die every year from tobacco related illnesses.  It must be remembered that the tobacco companies must replace these customers with new ones.  Whom do they go after?  They go after our children.  Why can I say this with such conviction?  Irish surveys have shown that 78% of smokers started when they were under 18 years of age.  The figure is the same in the rest of Europe.  How do they attract young people to smoking?  Most young people will say they started smoking because it looked cool.  For the tobacco companies, their nirvana is getting people addicted after smoking 20 fags.  A person under the age of 18 years is a minor and the State has a duty to protect him or her.  If one is addicted before reaching 18 years, what choice does one have after passing that age?  This is one of the most addictive substances known and would not be legalised if it were discovered today.  I intend to introduce a Bill to introduce plain cigarette packaging, as was done in Australia.  That will tackle that form of advertising.  Smoking causes cancers and pain, damaging the lungs, heart and throat.</p><p> I have been asked by the industry not to refer to it as evil.  How else can one describe an industry that produces and promotes an addictive product to children which will kill one in two of them?  I intend to wage war on this industry because it is killing more people in Europe every year than anything else.  If one looks at the cumulative number of lives lost in Europe, one is looking at a greater number of people dying from smoking than were killed in the Second World War.  No one can talk about a nanny state.  Adults can do as they wish, but I, as Minister, and the Legislature have a responsibility to protect children and that we will do.</p><p> Section 2 repeals provisions contained in section 2 of the Tobacco Products (Control of Advertising, Sponsorship and Sales Promotion) Act 1978.  It also revokes regulation No. 17 in the Tobacco Products (Control of Advertising, Sponsorship and Sales Promotion) Regulations 1991.  These provisions contain price fixing elements which are seen to be in contravention of the relevant European Council directive.  In this regard, they were deemed to be restricting the freedom of industry to make effective use of competitive advantage and must be removed.  I have asked the Department to investigate how we can address issues of public health importance being dominated by a competition directive.  It should never be a case of jobs over lives.  The countries that grow tobacco should be offered incentives to become involved in other industries.</p><p> Specifically, section 2(1) repeals sections 2(1 )(<i>c</i>), 2(2)(<i>h</i>) and (2)(2)(<i>i</i>) of the 1978 Act.  Section 8 of the Public Health (Tobacco) Act 2002, as amended by section 4 of the Public Health (Tobacco)(Amendment) Act 2004, sets out the provision for the repeal of the 1978 Act.  However, it is important to note that this provision has not yet commenced and the 1978 Act has not yet been repealed.</p><p> Section 2(2) is a standard saver provision.  Section 2(3) revokes regulation No. 17 in the Tobacco Products (Control of Advertising, Sponsorship and Sales Promotion) Regulations 1991.  This regulation had already been amended, while regulation No. 16 was deleted by the regulations I signed in December 2012 to remove any price fixing provisions from them.  The revocation outlined is to allow my Department to introduce new regulations, mentioned previously, relating to sales promotion activities.  This will ensure there will be no overlap of provisions.  </p><p> Section 3 is a standard provision.  It provides for the Short Title, collective citation, construction and commencement.</p><p> As a doctor with decades of experience, I have seen at first hand the damage caused to the health of those who become addicted to tobacco.  Tobacco use is the leading cause of preventable deaths in Ireland.  Each year more than 5,200 Irish people die prematurely from diseases caused by tobacco use, while over 700,000 Europeans die annually from tobacco-related diseases.  Smoking is the largest avoidable health risk in Europe; it causes more problems than alcohol, drug abuse and obesity.  A study commissioned by the European Union estimates that in Ireland health expenditure on treating smoking related illnesses is approximately &#8364;500 million, while approximately &#8364;170 million is lost because of absenteeism and long-term incapacity due to smoking.</p> <p>From my perspective as Minister for Health, Government tobacco control initiatives are about saving lives.  However, it is obvious that from an economic perspective there is an additional incentive for us to reduce the number of smokers in our country.  When we discussed this in Europe, it became apparent that the tobacco industry is worth approximately &euro;20 billion to the Union as a whole, but we spend &euro;25 billion every year in Europe treating the damage it causes in terms of health.  It costs another &euro;8 billion a year through lost productivity through absenteeism and ill-health.  Morally, ethically and financially, this is not an industry that should be supported.</p><p>I am keen during my period as Minister for Health to make a significant impact on the area of tobacco.  The regulation of the tobacco industry and its sales promotion activities, as set out in this Bill, is just one of the ways I hope to achieve this.  A comprehensive range of tobacco control legislation is already in place in Ireland, which places us in the top rank of countries internationally.  These include the workplace smoking ban in 2004, the ban of the sale of packs of cigarettes of fewer than 20 and the ban on in-store display and advertising.  I was very pleased to introduce regulations placing an obligation on tobacco manufacturers to include photographs on cigarette and tobacco packs.  These images depict the negative health impacts associated with smoking.  Research and experience in other countries has shown that health warnings with coloured photographs can be an effective means of discouraging smoking and informing people about the health risks.  These packs have been on sale since February.  The picture warnings, together with the retail point of sale display and advertising ban, will have a positive impact on reducing the numbers of young people starting to smoke.  It is heartening to see that in a recent survey the number of children smoking fell from 18% to 12% from 2002 to 2010.</p><p>However, more needs to be done.  No single measure will significantly reduce the numbers who smoke.  A range of initiatives is required, including those I have already set out.  I hope to publish a strategy in the near future which will set out a plan for Ireland to deal with the problem of smoking.  This strategy will set out various actions, including improving cessation services, educational initiatives, tobacco price increases, extensions of the smoking ban and research.  Protecting children and the denormalisation of tobacco in our society are the key principles underpinning these actions.</p><p>I have heard stories, as I am sure other Members have, of children running home to their parents in tears concerned about their parents because the teacher has told them people who smoke are going to die.  The parents have to reassure them that will not happen.  This demonstrates our adult behaviour is hugely influential on our children.  The less they see adults smoking, the less likely they are to become smokers.  I assure Senators that while this strategy is being finalised, we are already moving ahead in achieving our goal of a tobacco-free society.  Significant work is being undertaken at present in many areas.  This includes the valuable work of Senators Crown, van Turnhout and Daly in developing a Private Member's Bill to prohibit smoking in cars where children are present.  A lot of work has been done on that and I am aware another meeting is to take place shortly.  The Office of the Attorney General is making good progress on the various issues raised by the Bill.  I fully support this Bill and my officials are working with the Senators to ensure that an effective and robust piece of legislation is developed.  It must be robust because the industry will challenge it at every opportunity.  I would like to reiterate that this legislation is not about restricting the rights of adults, but is about protecting the rights of children.</p><p>I plan, in the near future, to seek approval from my Cabinet colleagues to proceed with the drafting of legislation to introduce plain or generic tobacco packaging in Ireland.  With the introduction of tobacco advertising and display bans, tobacco packaging has become the key promotional vehicle for the tobacco industry.  My aim is to ensure that all forms of branding - trademarks, logos, colours and graphics - will be removed from packages, apart from the brand name.  All packs will be in a plain neutral colour, except for the mandatory health warnings.  The objective will be to make all tobacco packs look less attractive to consumers and to make health warnings more prominent.  Ultimately, this will make tobacco products appear to be the harmful products they really are.  Australia was the first country in the world to introduce plain packaging and has successfully defended a legal challenge in its high court.  While there is not complete evidence that these warnings reduce smoking, there is evidence, from Canada in particular, that since the introduction of the pictorial warnings, there has been a fourfold increase in smokers wanting to give up their habit.  As I said, no particular move will improve the situation, but a range of measures.</p><p>Knowing what we know, if there was a drug available tomorrow that could save 700,000 lives a year in Europe, we would all be screaming for it.  There is a drug available in Europe that is killing 700,000 people a year and we should be doing everything in our power to stop people using it.  I am not a Minister who is anti-smoker.  I want to support smokers to get them off cigarettes.  However, I am 100% anti-smoking.  I ask Senators to support this Bill today and any future tobacco legislation brought through the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="12:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800014#N00200"><p>Ba mhaith liom f&aacute;ilte a chur roimh an tAire go dt&iacute; an Teach inniu chun pl&eacute; a dh&eacute;anamh ar an Bhille t&aacute;bhachtach seo a bhaineann le tobac agus caitheamh tobac.</p><p>Fianna F&aacute;il supports the Bill before the House and any measure the Minister will take to curb the prevalence of smoking or its consequences in society.  Smoking is a curse on society.  The Minister rightly pointed out that, unfortunately, the major companies manufacturing and promoting cigarettes are now targeting young people, and women in particular.  The reason for this is that they have lost so many of their other customers.  Cancer is a major scourge for our population.  Professor Crown is our expert in the House in that regard.  We all visit people when they are ill and have attended funerals when people have died.  Unfortunately, the majority of these people die as a result of encountering cancer and having to battle with it at the end of their life.  They get palliative care support, but smoking exacts its cost.  We all remember the smoke-filled rooms of years ago when we attended political and community meetings.  Whether people were smokers or not, they were smoking passively and we are now aware this has had a devastating effect on human health.</p><p>The smoking ban has been hugely successful since its introduction.  While publicans were against it at the time, if they were asked about it today, they would be in favour of it.  Talking to a colleague earlier, we recalled how if one was in a pub years ago, when one came out one's hair and clothes reeked of smoke.  Thank God those days are in the past.  </p><p>The Minister touched on the issue of brand monopoly.  According to Bloomberg, the Marlboro brand company is worth &euro;21 billion per year.  It is the tenth biggest brand on the planet and has huge financial weight.  However, we must deal with these companies and take them on.  I fully support the Minister's aspiration to introduce universal plain packaging and hope he brings that to Cabinet in the near future, along with the hard-hitting message of the detrimental health impact of smoking on the package.  Australia has done this very successfully.  Researchers in the tobacco field show the companies are totally opposed to this and are targeting new smokers in countries where there is no universal packaging, including here in Ireland, where young people are being targeted through clever advertising.</p> <p>The Minister drew our attention to the clever new packaging that is being used.  The first time I saw such packaging at the supermarket counter - I am not a smoker - I thought the branding made it look like some form of lipstick tube, health food or supplement.  These people, who have huge amounts of money, did not some up with such a clever approach on the spur of the moment.  Governments need to be responsible.  Along with my Fianna F&aacute;il colleagues, I will support the Bill in question when it comes before the Oireachtas.  The sooner it does, the better because we need to take on the vested interests in this sector properly.</p><p>The issues of the cost of tobacco and the money being made by tobacco companies arise in the context of the legislation we are discussing.  The cost of cigarettes is approximately twice the EU average.  People often bring cigarettes home with them when they go on holidays in Spain, Portugal and places like that.  They can buy 200 cigarettes there for the price of 40 cigarettes in Ireland.  Smokers might disagree with me when I say it is not a bad thing that cigarettes are so expensive here.  Every time the level of tax on cigarettes in Ireland has been increased - I appreciate that the State generates a great deal of revenue through such measures - the companies have dovetailed with that to increase their profits.   According to the Irish Heart Foundation and the Irish Cancer Society, the tobacco sector's revenue on every packet of 20 cigarettes increased from &euro;1 to &euro;1.84 in the decade up to 2010.  The companies are piggy-backing on what the State is doing.  I encourage the Minister to examine this aspect of the matter.  Some form of regulation or legislation is needed to prevent companies from piggy-backing on increases in the level of tax imposed on tobacco products.</p><p>If the Minister decides to introduce generic packaging that is light green, dark green or some other colour, I encourage him to include cigars and all other forms of tobacco in that regime.  We should not confine our attention to cigarettes - we have to focus on every form of tobacco.</p><p>I think an educational campaign is needed, particularly in our primary schools.  I know this is happening in some secondary schools.  If teachers do not have the dedicated expertise to show young people the deadly effects of tobacco smoking, they should be supported in doing so.  Believe it or not, tobacco companies are using their clever advertising to target children of primary school age.  The Minister should work with his ministerial colleague in the Department of Education and Skills to target such practices through the school network and the education system as a whole.  If that were done in an effective way, it would educate the next generation about the deadly effects of smoking tobacco products.</p><p>I could say much more on this issue.  The Minister has articulated most of what needs to be said about the health effects of smoking.  As a medical practitioner, he is familiar with those effects.  I am sure he has seen many cases of people suffering from cancer, particularly lung cancer, as a result of smoking over a long number of years.  As politicians, we have an obligation to protect the nation and to protect people against smoking.  I agree with the Minister that we are anti-smoking rather than anti-smokers.  I would subscribe to that.  I have never smoked, but I have friends and family members who smoke.  My younger brother who smokes was diagnosed with cancer a number of years ago.  He would love to give up cigarettes if he could do so.  When people get addicted to cigarettes, unfortunately they get a grip on them and form part of their daily lives.  It is very difficult to give them up.  We need to give serious consideration to ways of educating young people, showing them alternatives, assuring them that smoking is not a cool thing to do and reminding them that they should not follow their friends who might smoke.  That would be very useful.</p><p>We are fully supportive of this short Bill.  We look forward to the publication by the Minister of legislation on cigarette packaging.  I encourage him to keep an eye on major companies that might seek to piggy-back on any decision to increase our tax revenues from cigarettes.  That is exactly what they are doing.  A cap needs to be placed on the profit they can make from every packet of cigarettes that is sold in our supermarkets.</p><p>The issue of contraband cigarettes, which are readily available, has not been mentioned during this debate.  They come into this country through the North and other channels.  They are sold on many streets in this country at heavily reduced prices.  I am not sure how we can target this phenomenon.  The State is losing substantial and serious revenue.  The Criminal Assets Bureau, the Revenue Commissioners and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na are working to try to close the various loopholes that exist in this regard.  I am not sure whether more can be done to that end.  As the cigarettes that are coming into this country in this way contain all sorts of fillers, they are even worse than the cigarettes that are being sold in our shops.  I am not sure how we can deal with this problem.  Former members of certain parliamentary groups in the North are involved in this activity.  This problem need to be targeted.  The population needs to be educated about the consequences of products that are being sold under the counter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="12:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800015#O00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I welcome the Public Health (Tobacco) (Amendment) Bill 2013, which has arisen on foot of the European Court of Justice ruling on minimum pricing.  The Minister went through the figures.  It is amazing that there has not been a substantial decrease, in real terms, in the number of people who smoke.  We still seem to have a problem with people in the younger age group.  They are continuing to support the trade of the tobacco companies despite the statistics mentioned by the Minister.  Some 5,000 deaths a year are directly related to people smoking.  Approximately 50% of all long-term smokers will die prematurely.  That is a huge number in real terms when one considers the overall percentage of people in the country who are smokers.</p><p>When I did some reading on this issue, I was interested to find that in 2008, the most recent year for which statistics are available, approximately 36,000 hospital admissions were directly related to people's smoking habits.  I presume that annual figure has not really changed.  Smoking is a huge drain on our medical services from general practitioner level right through to the hospital system.  We have to do a great deal of work to try to reduce the number of smokers in this country.  The Minister referred specifically to younger people in this context.  I was interested to her somebody suggest that the slogan &quot;kiss a smoker - taste the difference&quot; should be used to discourage younger people from smoking.  I am not sure whether it would work, but it might be a new and useful way of getting our message to young people.</p><p>I am awaiting the outcome of a study I commissioned to measure the responses of young people to the graphic images that are now being displayed on cigarette packets.  International studies show that these images should have an effect.  I decided to undertake a study of how young people in Ireland will react to them.  I will be interested to see what the results of the survey will be.  It is important for us to continue to support research aimed at reducing the number of people who smoke.  As I said earlier during a debate on organ donation at the Joint Committee on Health and Children, there is a huge need for a public awareness campaign in relation to these matters.  Over a ten-year period, a very proactive road safety campaign brought about some very good results.  We probably need to review how we are managing our campaign aimed at discouraging people from smoking.  We need to continue to research how we can ensure there is a reduction in the number of people starting to smoke.  Equally, we need to help those who smoke to move away from their problems.  As Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill said, it is not easy for anyone who smokes to move away from cigarettes.  It is a huge task and a huge obstacle for them.</p> <p>We should be doing everything possible to provide those people with the varied medical assistance they need.</p><p> With regard to the court decision, it was interesting to read:<blockquote>...the Court adds that the prohibition on fixing minimum prices does not prevent Member States from prohibiting the sale of manufactured tobacco at a loss, so long as the freedom of manufacturers or importers to determine the maximum retail selling prices for their products is not undermined.  Those economic actors will not be able, in that case, to absorb the impact of the taxes on those prices by selling their products at a price below the sum of the cost price and all taxes.</blockquote>While the European Court of Justice states we cannot impose minimum prices, we can make sure we prohibit the sale of manufactured tobacco at a loss, which is important.</p><p> The figures on the amount of tobacco coming in from abroad are interesting, with some 6% of the market accounted for by legal cross-border purchases and 14% by illegal sales.  It is an area we really need to tackle and every assistance should be given to the Garda and the Revenue authorities to ensure the amount of cigarettes on the market illegally is reduced considerably.</p><p> I recently spoke to a medical practitioner who was holding a high-risk pregnancy clinic and was astonished to find the high level of smoking among people who were pregnant.  In fact, one patient acknowledged she had reduced smoking from 300 cigarettes a week to 200.  The issue here is the danger caused to the foetus in the long term.  We need a campaign in this area given that there are still a high number of women who continue to smoke while pregnant, despite all the warnings.  It is interesting how those patients end up having to be dealt with in the high-risk clinics.</p><p> I welcome the Bill and I know the Minister has a number of other Bills in this area coming down the road.  They will certainly receive the support of this House because anything we can do to help reduce the number of people who are smoking in this country is welcome, and it also helps to reduce the overall cost of the health budget in the coming years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P00200"><p>Ba mhaith liom tr&iacute; noimead a thabhairt don Seanad&oacute;ir Norris.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P00300"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P00400"><p>I thank the Minister for his continued professional and political attention to the scourge and evils of smoking.  I believe he is a committed campaigner toward the goal of making Ireland a tobacco-free society.  Like those of us who have been privileged to be members of our profession and other caring health professions, we do tend to get a different perspective on the reality of the evil that is this industry.  It is an evil industry and we need to call it what it is.  At no level within our body politic, be it local government, national Government, Legislature, Civil Service or the EU, should we in any sense be engaging with the tobacco industry.  We should see it as an industry that needs to be stamped out completely, 100%.  We should put it on notice that it is our intention to make the activity which it does completely and comprehensively illegal within a meaningful timeframe.  This is why a number of us are in the early stages of a campaign called SOS 2030, the goal of which is to persuade the European powers that they need to adopt this as a fundamental principle within the appropriate timeframe.  This is not crazy, bomb-throwing radicalism.  We are saying they have 15 or 16 years to teach the farmers to grow something else, get the pension funds to invest in something else, get the factories to retool and tell the shopkeepers they had better sell something else because, after 2030, if someone wants to sell tobacco, they will be doing it on the same legal basis as the Cali cartel sell their products - it will be illegal.</p><p>Some will say there are precedents for prohibition having not worked.  We are not advocating the prohibition of the practice or the growth of tobacco.  What we are advocating is the prohibition of commerce in tobacco.  People may have a civil right to smoke or to grow a tobacco plant in their back garden and roll their own cigarettes, but no one has an innate civil right to profit from cancer-causing addictive drugs.  When I talk of the tobacco industry, I include everything from the mom and pop shop on the corner in the suburbs of Dublin, Cork or Abbeyfeale to the people in the boardrooms of RJR or British American Tobacco and the people who own the vast plantations in Virginia or Turkey.  Let us face it, the business plan of the entire tobacco industry can be summed up in four words: addict children to carcinogens.  If they do not do it, the business ceases to exist.  If anyone tells me there is any civil, human or legal right to that, they are clearly incorrect.  This is why I am delighted to have the Minister as our leader in many of our smoking initiatives.  On behalf of Senators Daly and van Turnhout, I am grateful for his confirmed and explicit commitment today to ensuring the passage of our own little practical step along this way by banning smoking in cars with children.</p><p>While I can be very supportive of what the Minister is doing, I hear a noise in the Chamber today.  It is a grinding noise and I think it is the noise of gritted teeth.  I can only presume the Minister is not happy he has been handed the chalice of passing this particular legislation by the European Commission.  I am less bound by the conventions of party loyalty and diplomacy than he is, so I will say what I think.  This stinks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P00500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P00600"><p>I cannot believe that anybody at a European level would come out with this ruling.  I know our Fianna F&aacute;il colleagues have said they will support it.  I believe we should make a symbolic rejection of this Bill, not for the positive public health matters, which are encouraging - and we will attempt to amend it to within an inch of its life if it gets to Committee Stage - but to send a message to the EU that something stinks about this.  How could anybody in their right mind actually try to make it easier for people to engage in a cheap price war on behalf of tobacco products?  How could they do this?  Unless I am really, as George Bush would say, misunderestimating what is in this thing, it seems to me we are basically being forced to be complicit in the making of a bad decision to the benefit of the tobacco industry, which should be our unambiguous sworn enemy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P00700"><p>The Senator's time is almost up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P00800"><p>In that case, I will conclude.  Is the Minister personally satisfied with the integrity of the decision making process in the EU on this issue?  I can tell him something stinks to the high heavens about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P00900"><p>I am very honoured to speak after Senator Crown.  We are delighted he took the trouble to come direct from the airport, despite probably being jet-lagged, to speak here so passionately.  He said what I had decided myself to say.  I think this is appalling legislation.  The Minister has done a little bit of tweaking to make it appear acceptable through cosmetic measures and I am not going to go back over the statistics as the Minister has passionately laid them out.  This is something that kills.  It is bad for us, I know, because I am a sometime smoker.  Luckily, although I have an addictive personality, I do not seem to be addicted to nicotine.  I can smoke for a couple of days and then give it up for a month or three months.  I am now not going to ever-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P01000"><p>On a point of order, I believe the Senator is addicted to nicotine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P01100"><p>Maybe I am.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P01200"><p>It is an addiction.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800016#P01300"><p>Fine.  I would like to say that it is disgraceful, corrupt and criminal that these people deliberately target young people - the vulnerable - but it is not just young people.  They go out Africa and to South America - they go to people who have no defences.  These are people with their headquarters in the United States and in Europe and they must be confronted.</p><p>I am appalled by the court's ruling, which I believe is disgraceful, wrong and, in some measure - possibly even morally, if not in any other sense - corrupt.</p> <p>Our Constitution puts as the primary plank the public good.  This is probably unconstitutional.  How in the name of God can it be for the public good that we allow this competitive selling of cigarettes?  Is there a mechanism whereby one can shove up the tax if they dare to lower the price?  We should shove the tax up immediately by regulation.  Perhaps the Minister could talk to the Minister for Finance to see if that can be done.  Politically, it may be less than popular.  The Minister said he had completed the first step in complying with the court ruling.  To hell with them.  They have not been our friends either in bankrupting this country or, now, in forcing ill-health upon our citizens.  Removing the legal basis for the fixing of a minimum price is a yielding of sovereignty.</p><p>I believe much of this stuff is just cosmetic.  For example, the Minister talks about the prohibition of the promotion and sale of tobacco products at a reduced price, free of charge with the purchase of another tobacco product or under three-for-two arrangements.  Can the Minister show me one shop in the entire country that has ever done this?  I asked my colleague, Senator Quinn, whether he had ever come across this and the answer was &quot;No&quot;.  This is just a bit of cosmetic stuff to say that we are barricading this, that or the other.  It is rubbish.  This is a nonsense.  It means nothing.  The Minister referred to &quot;happy hour&quot;-type promotions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800017#Q00200"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800017#Q00300"><p>That is a complete nonsense.  I will certainly oppose the Bill and will be back here to vote against it, although not out of any sense of antagonism.  I understand the Minister feels his hands are tied, but it is a disgraceful decision.  What are these people in the court doing?  It is not in the interests of people.  It was the same with this ridiculous equality-based rubbish about gender weighting in the car insurance industry.  God knows, my reputation on gender equality could not very well be impugned.  The court is behaving in an insane fashion that is detrimental to the public good and must be challenged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" speakername="John Gilroy" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800017#Q00400"><p>I welcome the Minister to the Chamber.  I note his obvious determination to deal with this public health matter, which is also a private health challenge, and restrict, reduce or prevent smoking.  To use the Minister's own words, to wage war on this product is commendable.  This level of determination is welcome but will, unfortunately, be necessary.  He painted a very powerful image in his speech when he said that the customers of the tobacco industry die younger and in greater numbers than the population at large and that in order for the industry to sustain its level of profit, it must find replacement customers.  This is a terrible, stark image.  The replacement of customers comes from the deliberate and specific targeting of our children.  The Minister held up some packages a while ago.  I was not even aware of this practice.  It is remarkably deceptive, sophisticated, subtle and insidious.  This is what we are dealing with.  If we attack it head-on in the manner that many people are prescribing we will not really deal with the issue, because we must attack it on several fronts.  As well as highlighting the danger associated with the product, we must also move to some sort of cultural change whereby the use of tobacco products is not seen as cool any more.</p><p>The Minister will come across some people, in this battle, who will be opposed to the steps he is taking.  They will put up arguments about freedom of choice and how we are all adults.  The tobacco industry will look on those advocates in the same way as Stalin looked upon the crazier Communist states.  He called them &quot;useful idiots&quot;.  The tobacco industry will look on advocates who make those arguments in a similar fashion.  </p><p>Sometimes the directives we receive from Europe throw up some very strange situations, bedfellows or positions.  Policy objectives in one area sometimes appear to contradict those in another area.  This certainly seems to be one such conflict coming from the European Court of Justice - public health versus competition law.  I see Senator Norris's argument, although I do not fully understand it.  It is similar to several other arguments in law where one can see that the legislation under which the challenge has been brought very often determines the result or priority attaching to the ruling in one area as opposed to another.  I have seen it in this country.  If one was to bring in legislation dealing with gender equality versus health and safety, very often, a court could come down on one side and those on the opposite side of the argument would feel there was something wrong with the judgement, and perhaps there would be.  That is the nature of the judicial process.  I do not think there is a conspiracy.  Maybe there is but I cannot see it here.  I think it is the way the judicial process grinds on in its inordinate fashion.  </p><p>I commend the Minister on moving to ensure this Bill will bring a sense of policy consistency into the area.  It is about time we had it.  It is a very short Bill, consisting of three sections.  The Minister outlined what those three sections contain in his speech so I do not intend to repeat it.  I used to smoke up to about two years ago.  Since then, I have taken up jogging.  One might not think that to look at me, but I have.  When I am scaring the dogs on the back roads of Cork with my puffing and panting, it is not the cigarettes that are causing it.  It might be the few extra pounds of weight I am carrying but I would not have thought of going jogging two years ago when I was smoking.  These are benefits that I have gained and I am sure many people in my position, at my age and with my physique would also benefit from them.  I will say no more about it.  We will talk about it again on Committee Stage.  It would be remarkable if we could find any amendments to put forward at that stage but we will wait and see.  I again commend the Minister.  Anything he wishes to do to prevent new customers - our children, in other words - from taking up cigarettes will have my support and the support of the Labour Party.  I urge the House to fully accept and embrace what the Minister intends to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800017#Q00500"><p>Senator White is next on the roster, but she is unavailable, so I will take Senator Barrett, who has five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="12:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800017#Q00600"><p>I welcome the Minister.  We always have great debates when he comes to this House.  There may be some useful points on minimum pricing.  I accept what Senators Norris and Crown have said.  Minimum pricing enriches the people doing the minimum pricing.  I understand the Minister for Finance, the Minister of State with responsibility for public service reform and the OPW and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform would be delighted to have more tax revenue.  I agree with the Senators who said it is a very strange imposition of competition policy to have competition in products that, as the Minister so eloquently put it, damage people.  It might be important, because there are also voices saying that the Minister should think of minimum pricing for alcohol, and some of them are in the alcohol industry.  Some producers like minimum pricing.  That we can drive down prices and give them less, even in this heinous industry, is the grain of consolation I see in the court decision.  In response to Senator Crown, action on smoking in cars should have been much quicker.  Senator Crown proposed that measure to protect children in cars going on holidays with their parents last summer and I do not know the reason for the delay.</p><p>The Minister should examine duty-free return of tobacco.  As our very helpful research services show, we quite rightly have an extremely high price for cigarette products and people bring them back by the cartload through Dublin Airport and other airports.  This is damaging, and must undo much of the work the Minister is trying so valiantly to do.  I do not know whether it contradicts our European obligations, but this should be considered in terms of dealing with it as a health issue, and we should aim to bring the price of tobacco products people bring back into this country up to the Irish retail price.  As other speakers have said, we sometimes get fairly strange decisions from Europe.  One speaker mentioned the gender equality ruling that will result in women, who are safer drivers, being charged more for car insurance on the grounds that it makes them equal with dangerous male drivers.  That is a very strange definition of equality.  The design faults in the euro itself have cost this country billions, so we must examine what comes from Europe rather than always touching the forelock.</p> <p>We need research on the reasons people take up smoking.  We have run the smoking information campaigns but we need to get into the psychology of young people who take up smoking as a way of appearing to be mature.  Will the Minister consider interviewing people whose smoking has brought therm to the point of exit from this world?  Let the real story be told.  Let us interview people who will no longer be alive in a few months time because of smoking.  I recall being in Howth with a dear friend, who was a heavy smoker.  He could walk down the hill of Howth but it took ages to walk back up it.  Let us put the truth about this dreadful product before young people.</p><p>The measures against smuggling are absolutely essential.  I see, and I am sure the Minister does see, these products on sale widely.  I wonder if some of the victims would take court cases against the tobacco companies, as they do in the United States, as this would take some of the load off the Minister's shoulders.  Very successful cases have been taken in the American jurisdiction against the industry for selling narcotics branded to persuade people they will become a better cowboy or a more beautiful film star.  Let us go for the reality.  There are cases pending against the health service in cases in which people believe there has been malpractice, however, as the Minister said, this must be one of the greatest malpractices.</p><p>I note the Minister has raised the issue of plain packaging.  Are we carrying community rating on health insurance excessively when we do not allow a discount for not smoking.  I am aware the Minister is looking at the health insurance sector.  I recall a very eminent colleague who actually told people that he could not go ahead with the expensive operation because the patient was smoking in the room and all the medical expense and all the expertise would be undone by a person continuing to smoke.  I do not know whether he ever carried out that threat or promise.  Taking such action would bring across from medicine how appalling people find smoking.  I asked Professor Shane Allwright in TCD who has done a lot of work on this issue and she welcomes the Minister's anti-promotions section.  Sometimes I think the European Court should think about what it is legitimising.  Minimum pricing may have made the sellers' role more profitable.  Let us get at them by reducing their profitability.  I am sure the Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, would be delighted to hear of proposal to increase taxation as he needs the revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" speakername="Jimmy Harte" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800018#R00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I know he is passionate about this subject as any medical practitioner would be.  What would we think about manufacturing a product and following the instructions which guarantee that it will kill people early or destroy their quality of life?  The costs resulting from tobacco are phenomenal.  I suppose in a couple of hundred years, the next civilisation will look back and question how it was legal to sell items that would kill people.  There is no other benefit from cigarettes.  It damages people's lungs and arteries and results in collateral damage to the family and increases the cost of the health service.  People will question why people smoked.  No matter how one looks at this issue, the evidence is against cigarettes.</p><p>I know the research in Australia shows that if people do not smoke by the age of 26 years there is a 99% chance that they will never smoke, which ties in with Senator O'Donnell's point on education.  Education is so important.  I do not smoke.  I have never smoked but my wife smoked for a while.  However, my daughter, who is seven, thinks that smoking is bad.  When people reach the age of 14 or 15 years, their attitude to smoking changes.  Perhaps it is a result of watching old films.  Smoking was a normal part of life in the 1960s and early 1970s, as shown in &quot;Mad Men&quot;, but there must be an input to combat this idea in primary and secondary level education rather than after leaving education.  There is a great deal of emphasis on packaging.  By the time the packaging comes out the people are hooked or they have had subliminal advertising from Hollywood films.  I grew up at a time when it was normal to smoke and most people smoked - starting at the age of ten or 12 years.  The damage is immense.</p><p>I congratulate the previous Government, and the then Minister, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, for introducing the smoking ban.  I have said it before, we were lucky that Fianna F&aacute;il was in power at the time of the introduction of this ban because if other parties in government introduced it, the people leading the publicans down the main streets of every town would be the Fianna F&aacute;il Party members, because the publicans are a strong lobby.  I am sure that Members were lobbied by publicans who stated that a ban on smoking would be the end of their business.  In fairness, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin did stand up to that lobby and that legislation has been a major factor in reducing the incidence of cancer.  The causes of cancer and the cost of treating it are really appreciable.  </p><p>I worked in insurance, and when people looking for life insurance stated they were smokers, the rate increased dramatically.  There is no argument against an actuary who states that people are more likely to die earlier because they smoke.  We are probably ahead of the European countries and we are definitely ahead of the Third World and Asian countries which still promote cigarettes as a source of revenue.  Many Asian countries would be copying the American way.  Recently I was in Taiwan and one of the problems in that country is that the cost of cigarettes is cheaper than in Europe but they are reluctant to increase the cost because of the revenue generated for the country from the sale of cigarettes.  We are leading the charge on tobacco products.</p><p>The Minister referred to the advertising introduced in Australia on 1 January and they have been proactive, even though the problem there is not major.  I hope the measures being introduced by this Bill will be supported by all Members.  In the coming centuries people will appreciate the legislation.  I hope we will have a healthier nation and I hope that cigarettes will be eradicated from society in the next century.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="12:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800018#R00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I intended to rise to support the Bill, but having listened to Senators Crown, Norris and Barrett they have challenged my analysis of the proposed legislation.  I will listen to the Minister's response before I make up my mind.  The Bill has two primary functions, the first is that it provides the Minister with additional powers to combat the promotion of tobacco products.  Any measures taken to ensure the advertising and sale of tobacco and tobacco products are restricted are supported fully by my party and me.</p><p>I have very deep reservations about the element of the Bill that relates to European law, about which Senator Crown spoke.  l will develop that point later.  </p><p>The aim of the additional powers that have been given to the Minister is to ensure that tobacco products will not be available at a reduced price or for free when people purchase another tobacco product or any other product or service.  This allows the Minister to control and regulate the promotion of tobacco products through special offers whereby they are offered free or at reduced prices together with other products.  This follows on from the legislation put in place in July 2009, to prohibit all point of sale advertising in retail outlets.  This required the storage of tobacco products out of sight of the customer.  </p> <p>Ensuring that tobacco is not available cheaply is very important to deter smoking.  Sinn F&eacute;in supports this policy.  Senators Norris and Crown referred to these provisions as being somewhat cosmetic, covering up the fact that the real substance of the Bill is to deal with the areas which relate to European law.  I am not sure if this is the case but I will listen with interest to the Minister's response.  I share the concerns of the Senators about those provisions relating to EU law.  My colleague in the D&aacute;il, Deputy Caoimhgh&iacute;n &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in, highlighted his disquiet about these aspects.  While he signalled that the party would not be opposing the Bill on that basis, it underlines the many difficulties this State faces due to the increasing encroachment of the EU and EU law on all areas of our sovereignty. </p><p>This Bill amends existing legislation to comply with the European Court of Justice ruling that the setting of minimum prices for tobacco in this State is in breach of EU law.  Our legislation required that the retail price of cigarettes be at least 97% of a weighted average, based on sales of each brand the previous year and the recommended retail price.  This was covered under provisions of the Tobacco Products (Control of Advertising, Sponsorship and Sales Promotion) Act 1978 and the Public Health (Tobacco) Act 2002.  However, I understand that under EU competition law, this is not allowed and manufacturers and importers must be free to set their own prices for their products.  Our policy in this area is sensible and prudent.  It cleaves to the aim of seeking to deter tobacco smoking, particularly among the young.  Therefore, it is regrettable that this has been struck down as being contrary to European law.</p><p>We will take the opportunity to record our unhappiness at the way in which this directive has been applied.  The EU Directorate General for Competition is massively influential and powerful within EU structures.  The ideology associated with competition being a wholly positive influence has permeated the EU at all levels.  Many are unwilling to consider its ill effects, many of which are economic ill effects.  However, in this case, it is one of infringement in the area of public health considerations.</p><p>Many will make the point that we can continue to tax as we please, and this is true.  However, it will not always be correct as there is a strong lobby within Europe, particularly among federalists, for tax harmonisation.  In those circumstances, there will be an impact on our tobacco pricing policies.  We are opposed to the implementation of this directive but we accept that it is something over which these Houses do not have control.  </p><p>I support the Bill but I will listen to the Minister's response before I make up my mind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800019#S00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I welcome the content of the Bill.  I appreciate that the European framework and legislation make it difficult for the Minister and will raise challenges in the future as to how the Department and the Government continue the battle against smoking.  The Minister has always been passionate on this topic and this comes from personal experience.  We are spending &euro;2 billion a year in combating the effects of smoking, and that is a lot of money.  I would prefer to see this money being spent on education, prevention and smoking cessation measures.  The Minister hopes to develop a policy on those matters in the near future.</p><p>The public consultation committee of this House sat recently.  One of the topics raised was the need for further and more effective smoking cessation programmes.  I attended the launch of the Healthy Ireland framework, which deals with smoking.  One in every two smokers dies from smoking-related illnesses.  The Minister has no choice but to do everything in his power to fight this battle - and it is a battle - because the very powerful tobacco companies have massive funds and they have longevity on their side.  They have been promoting cigarette smoking for a long time.  Cigarettes are part of the way we live, on sale in shops and in places where we do business every day.  It is very difficult to change overnight something that is woven into the fabric of our world.</p><p>This Bill is one small step against special offers such as three for two.  It is a welcome initiative, as was the change in packaging.  The Minister is correct to say that his Department will need to be vigilant about how manufacturers and retailers will try to continue to sell tobacco.  It is good to see that the number of child smokers is decreasing, but it is still very high at 12%.  As a GP, the Minister will agree that it is terrible that young children are smoking.  Their later health will be compromised due to the emergence of diabetes and heart conditions which we know are preventable.  The challenges for public health are obesity and smoking.  This Bill is a tiny but welcome piece of the jigsaw.</p><p>I would love to see some of the expenditure that is needed to look after those who are suffering the ill effects of smoking being spent instead on education so that we are not relying solely on photographs on cigarette packs.  Children need to be educated to understand the dangers of smoking.  The Cabinet committee on social policy is the committee responsible for ensuring that the Healthy Ireland framework is implemented.  There is much work to be done.  We should declare war on the tobacco lobby.  We should say that we will defy any actions to promote and pursue the sale of tobacco in this country.  It is a difficult task, because smoking cigarettes is endemic, but we have to stand up to these activities.  The tobacco companies have lots of money and deep pockets.  The Minister knows the figures.  I welcome the Bill as a small piece of a jigsaw.  I ask if the Minister has any influence over online selling of tobacco products, which is not included in this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800019#S00300"><p>I wish to share my time with Senator Darragh O'Brien.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800019#S00400"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" speakername="Mary White" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800019#S00500"><p>The Minister stated that tobacco use is the leading cause of preventable death in Ireland.  Each year, more than 5,200 Irish people die prematurely from diseases caused by tobacco use.  A total of 700,000 Europeans die annually from tobacco-related illnesses.</p><p>The Minister reminded us that tobacco is one of the most addictive drugs.  I gave up smoking cigarettes 30 years ago.  Like 99% of smokers, I found it very difficult to give up because nicotine is a very serious addiction.  The tobacco companies that produce these products will need to be regarded as pariahs by society.  The Minister must target children in school and explain to them how addictive nicotine is.  We have not spoken about that aspect.  I eventually underwent cold turkey in order to stop smoking.  All the talk about giving up smoking does not address how difficult it is to give it up.  I listened to Senator Crown and Senator Norris.  Senator Crown spoke about his work in treating cancer.</p>                              &Oacute; Murch&uacute;, Labhr&aacute;s. <p>Senator David Norris spoke about civil rights and the intervention of the European Union.  I am a supporter of the Minister, but having listened to the expert, we cannot support the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800020#T00200"><p>What is important in any democracy is that one listens to debate.  I listened with interest to the argument of Senators David Norris and John Crown in this regard which can be teased out further on Committee and Report Stages.  For the reasons outlined by Senators David Norris, John Crown and Mary White, we will oppose the Bill on Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800020#T00300"><p>I left the House during the Minister's opening contribution to meet approximately 40 students from a school in the area in which I live.  I was delighted to have the opportunity to quote the Minister and Senator Mary White has just spoken about there being 5,000 deaths.  We were always told tobacco was addictive and knew this from a very early age.  People say they did not realise it was addictive, but I certainly knew it was.  I wanted to get on the rugby team and knew when I was 13 or 14 years of age that if I smoked, I was unlikely to get on it.  The vast majority of youngsters who smoke claim they do not know how bad it is and we must do something to overcome this.  However, I have a problem with automatically increasing the price because each time we do so, we encourage smuggling.  Given that there is so much smuggling of illegal cigarettes, we need to find a better way.  </p><p>If we are really serious about dissuading people from smoking, should we ban smoking in schools and educational establishments, as has been done in Denmark?  That would include teachers and students.  The idea is not to smoke in front of students.  It would be worthwhile considering this suggestion.  Denmark also significantly increased fines for breaking the smoking law and selling tobacco to youths under 18 years of age.  I am not sure what the situation here is and whether there are serious fines in that regard.  In Denmark, in the case of a first offence, the fine is approximately &euro;700; in the case of a second offence, it is &euro;1,400 and in the case of a third offence, it is &euro;2,100.  Perhaps we should also significantly increase fines imposed for this offence.  </p><p>Last year Senator John Crown proposed banning smoking in cars carrying children, but should we not ban smoking in cars entirely?  In certain countries it has been found that smoking can be a contributory factor in car accidents.  To this extent, smoking in cars is now banned in Italy, as it has been found that if a smoker drops a cigarette or throws a cigarette out a window and it blows back in and he or she starts to look for it in the car, it can cause an accident and even result in death.  There are fines and penalty points for someone found smoking in his or her car.  As we have banned the use of mobile phones in cars as they are a distraction, should we not consider banning smoking cigarettes also?  That is a very important issue to be considered, especially when considered with the harmful effects on children.  The issue should be considered as we are discussing how to reduce the harmfulness of smoking.  </p><p>I refer to politics and tobacco lobbyists.  On a philosophical level, should we look at the relationship between alcohol and tobacco and politics?  We know about the link with sports, which is not often mentioned.  In Australia the New South Wales state parliament recently passed legislation banning donations to political parties from the alcohol, gaming and tobacco industries.  I am not sure if any money is given to political parties here by alcohol or tobacco companies, but we need to make things clear.  Could we, as politicians, send a strong message by formally breaking the link between the tobacco industry and the lobbyists and the political system?  </p><p>There are things we could do.  I know what the Minister is attempting to do, but I support Senator John Crown whom I regard as an expert in this area.  I am aware of his frustration that we are doing away with minimum pricing because we are being forced to do so by the European Court of Justice's ruling, but there must be steps we could take.  I have never seen three-for-two, happy hour or buy-one-get-one free tobacco promotions, as there would not be the margin to do it.  However, there must be other things we could do.  We have a strong message to send.  The Minister's heart is in the right place and we will support him in any way we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800020#T00400"><p>I thank Senators for their support in the battle against tobacco.  I understand the sentiments expressed about the European Court of Justice's ruling.  In my opening contribution I alluded to the fact that I had asked my Department to investigate how we could amending the directive - in other words, change the legislation - in order that it did not apply to matters of public health, which clearly would be in the common good.</p><p>  There is no need for me to rehash what we have said about the damage this product causes to people and the fact that the industry focuses on children, which is particularly disgraceful.  I acknowledge the dissatisfaction expressed about the ending of the minimum pricing of cigarettes.  I know Senators understand Ireland has an obligation to comply with this decision.  We are bound by the European Court of Justice's ruling; there is not an <i>&aacute; la carte</i> menu available.  As Ireland is bound by the legislation in Europe, the way to tackle this issue is to go through the legislative process to try to get support in Europe for this approach.  </p><p>  The tobacco directive is going through the European Union.  It is one of the main planks of our Presidency and I want to see it progressed.  We are gathering support for it, but some countries have very strong tobacco lobbyists and industries and we will meet resistance.  For instance, it was made very clear to me that if I went for plain packaging in the directive, it would not get through, but I want to bring that in here and have given an undertaking to that effect.  I hope to bring a memorandum to the Government in the next few weeks to seek support for this. </p><p>  The directive is very important because it refers to the percentage of a pack that can be given over to the health warning and pictures.  It also refers to flavourings.  Commissioner Tonio Borg has made the point that tobacco should look like tobacco and also taste like it.  Adding menthol and other flavourings to disguise the bad taste does a disservice.  Sometimes the human body has an innate ability to avoid danger and taste is one method by which it does so.  Pure tobacco tastes bad because, as we know, it is.  Why should we allow the industry to disguise the nature of its product in the way it advertises, packages or flavours it?  </p><p>  I have no objection to the sentiments expressed by Senators in terms of sending a message to the European Union that we find this ruling extremely difficult to understand, that it runs counter to the common good, that it allows commercial enterprise to supersede the well-being of people and that it pushes forward a theory that there is a choice to be made between jobs and lives when it does not have to be this way.  As I have pointed out and Senator John Crown re-emphasised, we should encourage people into other industries which do not carry such catastrophic consequences for the children whom they are trying to get to use their product and the citizen of Europe.</p><p>  Many Senators repeated the well established link between price and cigarette consumption.  As I said, there are 5,200 deaths per year in this country which are attributable to smoking.  That works out at a figure of 100 citizens each week, including friends and family members.  I lost a brother who was a doctor - an epidemiologist - who had studied the tobacco industry, had much information on what it was at and how it was striving to reach nirvana where following the consumption of one 20-pack, one would be addicted.  So strong was his addiction that he kept smoking even until the day he died.</p> <p>We must protect our children and I know that everybody in the House agrees.  I must apply the law and that is why I must introduce the Bill.  I have said in the other Chamber, and I shall say it again here, I intend to make this a pyrrhic victory for the tobacco industry.  It might have a slight smile on its face but it will be nothing when compared with the moans and groans it will endure under this Government and for as long as I am Minister for Health.  </p><p>More than 5,200 people die prematurely each year which is 19% of all deaths here.  We know that one in two smokers will die from their smoking habit.  Smoking is lethal and the Government must and will act.  I shall repeat a point that I have made on several occasions.  I have never met a smoker who wanted his or her child to smoke.  Not even the representative of the smoking industry at the European hearings by the Committee on the Environment, Public Health and Food Safety, ENVI, was prepared to do so.  He said that he did but he certainly did not say that he wanted his children to smoke.</p><p>Forest is an organisation that represents smokers but its use of the term is cynical.  Forests are the lungs of the world but the organisation promotes a habit that wrecks lungs, lives and the environment.</p><p>It is heartening that research shows that the number of children smoking has reduced but I accept that we must do a lot more.  The younger people are when they start smoking the longer and more heavily they are likely to smoke.  We know that the majority of smokers became addicted in childhood and I mentioned a survey revealed that it was 78%, a fact worth repeating. </p><p>The introduction of warning pictures on packets and the ban on displaying products in shops will, in my view, have a significant impact on young people in the long term.  The plain packaging of tobacco packets is another initiative that will assist in making smoking less attractive to children.  Offering a cigarette from a plain packet, even if one is a child, means that any child with two eyes in their head will wonder about cigarettes.  They will decide that they do not want to look cool and end up with a disease.</p><p>All of the little things that we do to tackle the problem will give us what we all want, a tobacco-free society.  De-normalising smoking will play a great part in achieving same.  The strategy that is being finalised in my Department will strive to achieve such a society.</p><p>We have already discussed the introduction of the smoking ban in cars when children are present.  We know the initiative is about protecting the health of children, not infringing the rights of people.  Other initiatives include banning smoking in playgrounds, sports stadia and other places where children and young people congregate.  I congratulate and acknowledge those who have already taken steps in this regard.  Many local authorities, including Fingal in my constituency, have made the decision to ban smoking in public playgrounds.  The Aviva Stadium is part of the European healthy stadia network and operates a no smoking policy.  The HSE is rolling out its tobacco-free campus policy with a view to having it operating on all sites by 2015.  </p><p>Let us think of the unintended consequences of actions.  A ban on smoking in hospitals has resulted in people standing at the front door of the premises acting like an advertisement hoarding when sick people enter.  An alternative smoking area should be provided off campus where smoking is allowed.</p><p>I understand how difficult it is to stop smoking as I used to smoke.  Luckily, like Senator Norris, I was not as heavily addicted to smoking as two members of my family.  They smoked two cigarettes each before having breakfast. </p><p>The illicit trading of cigarettes was mentioned.  From a public health perspective, it is my job to prevent people from smoking cigarettes whether they are legal or illegal.  The bottom line is, tackling the illicit trade of tobacco directly rests with the Revenue Commissioners.  It is an enforcement issue.  The Revenue Commissioners attaches a high priority to combatting smuggling and the illegal sale of tobacco products.  It is implementing its comprehensive strategy to tackle the problem.  In 2012 nearly 96 million cigarettes and 5,000 kg of tobacco were seized and there were 132 convictions for the smuggling of illegal cigarettes or the illegal sale of tobacco.  Therefore, we should not allow the illicit trade of tobacco to become an obstacle or an argument against the introduction of public health tobacco policies and legislation.  Successful public health policies and strategies for tackling illicit trade can operate effectively side by side and one is never an excuse for the other.  </p><p>I have said on record before that I would love to see cigarettes cost &euro;1 each so people would think long and hard before inhaling.  It has been shown elsewhere that people are price sensitive.  A lot of prices are introduced incrementally but a sudden shock increase would make many people stop and think about smoking.  </p><p>So many of the legislative measures that we have undertaken have put us to the fore internationally.  I acknowledge one of my predecessors, Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin, who introduced the smoking ban.  Many of the measures were facilitated by developments at European level.  It is important that our tobacco policy and legislative framework continues to develop within the context of a European Commission. </p><p>I shall return to a key point made by Senators.  I want to change the law rather than break it and that shall be the focus of the  tobacco unit in my Department.  I welcome the Tobacco Product Directive.  I know that it shall not be as easy to progress as Senators may think because many forces are at play.  As I spoke,  I was reminded of an episode of the &quot;Yes, Prime Minister&quot; television series that was devoted to banning smoking.  I am confident that the outcome of the revision of the directive, together with the publication of the tobacco strategy, will go a significant way in moving us towards a tobacco free society.</p><p>Senator Barrett and other Senators spoke about driving down profit.  I agree with them that we should do everything that we can to drive down profit while driving up the price.</p><p>A couple of other issues were raised.  The HSE is still running two successful campaigns and the number of calls to its helpline has greatly increased in the past number of months.  </p><p>Senators Norris, Crown, Quinn and other Senators alluded to the fact that they have never seen three-for-one promotions.  They have not because such promotion has never been necessary.  As opportunities to sell tobacco products diminish further the Senators can be damn sure that the industry will explore every avenue to promote their products.  I do not want to see a large multiple advertising a promotion offering customers 20 free cigarettes with every &euro;100 worth of groceries.  The legislation will prevent such promotions.</p><p>Very often we are reactive rather than proactive.  The Bill is proactive and will send a message to the industry.  I am aware that the Office of Tobacco Control was broken into in Europe.  The perpetrators scaled down the building from the roof, cut holes in the glass, entered the premises and stole hard drives from computers but from that office only.  Ceist beag de gach &eacute;inne anseo, who has the money, the sophistication and the motivation to carry out such an operation?  </p><p>In conclusion, I am not pleased that we must reduce minimum pricing for tobacco products.  I am concerned that it makes our issues surrounding the minimum pricing of alcohol very difficult.  I shall seek support in Europe to amend the legislation that underpins this decision so that it does not apply to areas of public health and the common good.  I ask Senators to support the Bill because we must act within the law.  I understand the sentiment behind the Senators who called for us to send a message.  I commend the Bill to the House.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800021#U00200"><p>I thank the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.223/1" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800021#U00400"><p>Question put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 27; Nl, 18.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden; Nl, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.223/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-04-18" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800021#U00400">
            <divisioncount ayes="27" noes="18" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="aye">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1114" vote="aye">Deirdre Clune</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="aye">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="aye">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="aye">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="aye">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="aye">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1144" vote="aye">Jimmy Harte</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="aye">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" vote="aye">Fidelma Healy Eames</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="aye">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="aye">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="aye">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="aye">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="aye">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="aye">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="aye">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="aye">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="aye">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="no">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="no">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="no">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1119" vote="no">James Heffernan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="no">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="no">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="no">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="no">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1139" vote="no">Darragh O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="no">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="no">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="no">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="no">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="no">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="no">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.223/3" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800021#U00400"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800022#W00100"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800022#W00200"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.226" nospeaker="true" time="13:25:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 24 April 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800022#W00300"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800022#W00400"><p>At 4 p.m. on Tuesday, 24 April.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.229" nospeaker="true" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800022#W00600">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.230" nospeaker="true" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800022#W00700">Cardiac Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800022#W00800"><p>I thank the Minister for taking the time to come to the House to discuss this issue.  Among the successes in the health service are the national cancer control programme and the new approach to cardiac care where outcomes are improving.  The Minister is very familiar with the fact that the north-west region, north of the Dublin-Galway line and south of Mullingar, is not adequately catered for.  We will leave the cancer debate for another day.  However, I have probably clocked up a good few hours during the years talking about the issue here.  I understand a group is being put in place and that there has been an acknowledgement by the Minister and his officials that, from a cardiac care perspective, there should be an opportunity to insert a stent within 90 minutes of an episode occurring.  A total of 80% of the population enjoy proximity to a cardiac centre where that should be possible.  However, the north-west region is not adequately catered for in that respect.  While there are cardiologists available there, there are no cardio-catheterisation laboratory facilities.</p><p>I understand a group has been put together and is chaired by the geriatrician Dr. Colm Henry.  I think he is senior in the representative body of clinical directors in the various hospitals.  With other cardiologists, he is looking at how best to deal with the anomaly in the north west where, frankly, people who have a heart attack do not have the same potential for survival as those within the catchment area of one of the specialist cardiac centres.  I have seen this happen before when the centres of excellence were being chosen.  From a clinical perspective, a particular clinic in Sligo was at an advanced stage.  However, the Government of the day wound it down and revved up one in Letterkenny in terms of the provision of breast cancer care services.  </p><p>I gather two cardiologists from Galway will be or are in this group with Dr. Henry.  It would suit them to have a cardio-catheterisation laboratory as far away as possible because they do not want to have anything eating into their catchment area, which I know sounds laughable when we are talking about saving people's lives, but there are medical politics.  I want to ensure that, if money is made available for the construction and staffing of a cardio-catheterisation to be run at least on a 9 to 5 basis, like the one in Waterford, it will be appropriately located within the region.  The appropriate location, notwithstanding the fact that I am from Sligo, is Sligo Regional Hospital which is equidistant from Galway and Altnagelvin in Derry where there is a cardio-catheterisation laboratory and eight cardiologists.  The logical location for the laboratory is Sligo.  </p><p>I hope the Minister will confirm that the group is in existence and chaired by Dr. Henry and outline what it is considering.  I want to use this opportunity to impress on the Minister the need to ensure Sligo will be the location of the facility where it would be best placed to serve the entire region.  The northern end of the catchment area can be served by Altnagelvin hospital, with the hospital in Galway serving the southern end.  I am interested in hearing the Minister's views and hope he will be able to give me some good news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800022#W00900"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue which I know is of some interest to Senator Michael Comiskey and Deputy John Perry, the Minister of State with responsibility for small business, as well as Deputy Tony McLoughlin.  I was in Sligo a couple of weeks ago and was sorry to have missed the Senator.</p><p>The acute coronary syndrome, ACS, clinical care programme was initiated to standardise treatment nationally for patients suffering from a heart attack.  It is one of a range of national clinical care programmes established by the HSE with the aim of improving quality access and cost effectiveness.  Primary precutaneous coronary intervention, PPCI, is the preferred treatment for ST elevated myocardial infarction, STEMI, in terms of morbidity and mortality outcomes.  Where PPCI cannot be delivered within an acceptable timeframe - the Senator mentioned a figure of 90 minutes - administering a clot-dissolving or thrombolysis drug is recommended, with early transfer to a PPCI centre for angiography.</p><p>International best practice indicates that Ireland should have four to eight PPCI centres to accommodate the demands of the population.</p> <p>Based on the European Society of Cardiology guidelines, patients should be transferred directly to a PPCI centre if this can be achieved within 90 minutes of the first medical contact.  No PPCI centre exists in the north west and a report for the regional director of operations of HSE west in 2012 highlighted that 91.4% of the population lived at a distance greater than 90 minutes road time from the nearest PPCI centre in Dublin or Galway.  This situation is not unique to the north west, however, because other areas of the country are also outside the 90-minute range.  The report presented a series of options that would lead to the provision of PPCI to a greater proportion of the population.  These options include cross-Border collaborative initiatives that could deliver a sustainable model for a greater proportion of the population of the north west.  The solution would also probably involve air ambulance services in order to meet the 90-minute target.</p><p>Data from the heartbeat system shows an increase in STEMI patients receiving PPCI from 45% in the period from October 2010 to September 2011 to 67% in the period from October 2011 to September 2012.  We have made great progress, although I recognise that is scant consolation to the people of the north west who want to have the same access as everybody else to this service.  It is our intention to ensure that happens.  We will have to think outside the box to achieve our targets but the group is working to that end and will make recommendations shortly.  </p><p>Galway and Limerick are currently operating well as PPCI centres.  A project is under way to enhance the provision of cardiac services to the population of the north west in view of the considerable distance factors involved.  A project team comprising senior clinicians from the west and north-west area, chaired by Dr. Colm Henry, programme lead for the HSE clinical director programme, was established in March 2013.  This team is to provide a report making specific recommendations on the following issues: delivery of cardiology services in the north west, noting findings of the situation report on services for acute coronary syndrome in the north west produced by Dr. Peter Wright in 2012; delivery of PPCI in the north west in line with the ACS programme, to include consideration of cross-Border provision; identification of a fixed elective cardiac catheterisation laboratory for the region to replace the current arrangement whereby services are delivered from a mobile laboratory on both acute hospital sites; and configuration and integration of cardiac services in the north west in anticipation of hospital groupings.  Dr. Henry has convened a group including cardiologists from Galway, Sligo and Letterkenny hospitals, the national lead for the ACS programme and representative of the ambulance service.  The group has sought and will consider detailed information from both hospitals and will be visiting both hospitals as well as Altnagelvin Hospital in Derry to meet hospital personnel.  The group is scheduled to deliver its final report to the regional director of operations by June 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800023#X00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his reply and for confirming that the group exists.  Although I am sure that he intends to take heed of the advice of the clinicians involved, I caution him that heavy pressure will be brought to locate the cardiology laboratory in the northern end of the catchment at Letterkenny General Hospital.  While I do not wish to disenfranchise the people of County Donegal, the reality is that it is 20 miles from Derry.  I would hate to see us making the same mistake that we made on cancer care.  I ask the Minister to use his good offices to impress that on the group.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.235" nospeaker="true" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800023#X00300">Asylum Support Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800023#X00400"><p>Although I am disappointed that none of the Adjournment matters I have raised in regard to direct provision has been taken by the Minister for Justice and Equality, who has direct responsibility for the matter, I welcome the presence of the Minister for Health.</p><p>  The system of direct provision has been in operation since April 2000.  However, concerns have been expressed about the lack of a legislative basis for the operation of direct provision.  In light of the Ombudsman's concern about the operation of the former mobility allowance scheme, it is essential that the rule of law operates in all aspects of our social welfare code.  When direct provision was initially introduced 13 years ago, it was viewed as a limited system that would operate for a maximum of six months.  However, the legal basis for the system is now unclear.  When it was initially introduced it was argued that the direct provision for asylum seekers was permitted by providing supplementary welfare allowance in kind rather than in cash.  Asylum seekers were offered bed and board by the Reception and Integration Agency and were provided with a weekly allowance of &#8364;19.10 per adult and &#8364;9.06 per child, amounts that have not changed since 2000.</p><p>  Since the introduction of the Social Welfare and Pensions (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009, asylum seekers cannot be considered as habitually resident in the State.  Given that access to most welfare payments, including supplementary welfare allowance, is restricted to those who are habitually residents, what is the legislative basis for the continued accommodation of and payments to asylum seekers?</p><p>  Dr. Liam Thornton, a researcher on the law and policy of direct provision in UCD's school of law, recently published an article on the dubious legality of the direct provision system.  The article notes that in 2006 the then Secretary General of what is now the Department of Social Protection, Mr. John Hynes, raised his concern with the then Secretary General of what is now the Department of Justice and Equality, Mr. Se&aacute;n Aylward, that the regular direct provision payments to asylum seekers were outside the powers, or <i>ultra vires</i>, of the Department of Social Protection.  According to documents received by Dr. Thornton after a freedom of information request, an attempt was made in 2006 or 2007 to place the direct provision payment on a legislative footing.  However, the attempt was subsequently abandoned.  I can provide the Minister with a copy of Dr. Thornton's article, the correspondence between the Secretaries General and the draft legislation if he so desires.  </p><p>  It is necessary for the Minister for Justice and Equality to provide an assurance that the direct provision system has a clear legislative basis in Irish law.  It is of serious concern that the system leaves individuals and, in particular, families to languish for several years without any definitive decision on their entitlement to remain in the State.  I welcomed the Immigration, Residence and Protection Bill 2010 but it has been on Committee Stage in the D&aacute;il since 2010.  We have now been waiting for that Bill for eight years and counting.  What is the legislative basis for the continued operation of the direct provision system?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800023#X00600"><p>Before I call the Minister to reply, I ask Members to join me in welcoming the Right Honourable Ivan Rombouts, the honorary consul in Antwerp.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800023#X01000"><p>He is very welcome.  I recognise the tie.  I am responding on this topic on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Justice and Equality.  The question asked by the Senator presupposes that there must be a specific legislative underpinning for the provision of State services to persons who otherwise would not be entitled to such services.  Legislating for legislation's sake is unwise.  If a case is being made for a change in how asylum seekers are accommodated, which is a view that the Senator has expressed on a number of occasions, that is an issue for policy in the first instance rather than legislation.</p><p>  The direct provision system ensures the delivery of services alongside legislative provisions which would otherwise specifically prohibit asylum seekers from being provided with the basic necessities of life.  For example, asylum seekers cannot work under section 9(4)(<i>b</i>) of the Refugee Act 1996, cannot access rent allowance under section 13 of the Social Welfare (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act, 2003 and are not entitled to a range of benefits, including child benefit, as they are deemed to be not habitually resident under section 246(7) of the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005.</p><p>  As an administrative system, direct provision is unique in this State but as a result of it no asylum seeker has ever been left homeless.  Clearly the system is not without its faults but in the 13 years of its existence over 51,000 asylum seekers have been accommodated under it.  Asylum seekers receive nourishment on a par with, and in some cases superior to, that available to the general population.  They receive a health service on the same basis as Irish citizens and in many cases the service is far superior to what is available in their countries of origin.  Children of asylum seekers are provided with primary and secondary education in the local community on the same basis as the children of Irish citizens.  The system of direct provision is not unique to Ireland.  Many other countries operate similar systems for meeting the reception needs of asylum seekers and all face challenges which are broadly similar to the issues arising here.</p><p>  There are no cheaper alternatives to the direct provision system.  If we were operating a system which facilitated asylum seekers in living independent lives in individual housing with social welfare support and payments, the cost to the Exchequer would be double what is currently paid under the direct provision system, even discounting the additional pull factor this would entail.</p> <p>This was a key finding in the value for money report in 2010.</p><p>Allowing asylum seekers access to the full array of welfare and housing benefits would run a real risk of resulting in a large upsurge in economic migrants masquerading as asylum seekers coming here in the expectation of accessing these services.  Furthermore, in respect of any major change of policy, we have to take account of the common travel area between Ireland and the United Kingdom which facilitates free movement between the jurisdictions.</p><p>It must be borne in mind that the persons residing in direct provision accommodation are here for a specific reason, namely, to claim international protection from the State.  This entitlement is protected by international obligations which the State has entered into and by a comprehensive national and EU legal framework and accompanying administrative processes which govern the processing of protection applications.</p><p>The Minister acknowledges that there is an issue with the length of time applicants spend in direct provision accommodation.  While not suggesting applicants are not entitled to the protection of the courts and due process, a consequence of frequent recourse to the courts to challenge decisions in these legislative processes is an extension of the length of time spent in direct provision accommodation.  This underlying problem does not arise from a lack of legislation - quite the opposite.  There are many reasons applicants spend lengthy periods in direct provision accommodation.  I have referred to legal challenges as one reason.  Undoubtedly, another significant issue is the cumbersome and multi-layered legal protection process in the State.  There is a clear imperative to change and radically reform that process and the Minister is committed to introducing it.</p><p>As the Minister has stated, he intends to republish a revised immigration, residence and protection Bill which will substantially simplify and streamline the existing arrangements for asylum, subsidiary protection and leave to remain applications.  It will do this by making provision for the establishment of a single application procedure in order that applicants can be provided with a final decision on all aspects of their protection applications in a more straightforward and timely fashion, thus reducing the length of time they spend in the direct provision system.</p><p>Pending the enactment and commencement of the new legislation and with a view to improving processing, the Minister proposes to introduce new arrangements for the processing of subsidiary protection applications in the light of recent judgments in the superior courts.  His Department, in consultation with the Attorney General's office, is developing a new legislative and administrative framework for the processing of current and future subsidiary protection applications.  This work is being given high priority and applicants will be advised of the new arrangements as soon as possible.  In the meantime, the system is overseen by the Reception and Integration Agency of the Department of Justice and Equality.  The RIA is subject to the same Civil Service obligations of fairness in the implementation of policy as any other area of government in implementing a scheme, statutory or non-statutory.  It is worth noting that since the Minister took office, the number of persons being accommodated in direct provision accommodation has fallen significantly, by approximately 1,000 or 25% in the period in question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800024#Y00200"><p>Perhaps my question was not clear enough.  I will take it up again with the Minister for Social Protection.  The correspondence between the then Secretary General of the Department of Social Protection and the Department of Justice and Equality in 2006 states payments made to asylum seekers were <i>ultra vires</i> the Department of Social Protection.  The Social Welfare and Pensions Act 2009 clearly states asylum seekers cannot ever be considered habitually resident in the State.  My question is: how is the State making these payments?  I advise the Cathaoirleach that I propose to submit a request to raise this matter on the Adjournment with the Minister for Social Protection.  While I appreciate the response given by the Minister for Health, Deputy James Reilly, it does not answer my question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800024#Y00300"><p>The Minister would like to be here, but that is not possible.  On his behalf, I acknowledge the points made by the Senator.  However, this is essentially about policy rather than legislation, as emphasised by the Senator in her follow-up remarks.  The reasons behind that policy remain unchanged.  The direct provision system was not put in place by accident; it was a necessary response to the increasing number of asylum seekers arriving in the State.  Before 1999, asylum seekers were treated as homeless persons under the structures in place.  These structures were unsuited to the situation facing Ireland; the homeless persons service of the then Eastern Health Board could not cope and there was a serious prospect of widespread homelessness among asylum seekers.  The direct provision system is only one element of the State's response to its international obligations on the asylum issue.  As well as educational, health and welfare costs, there are asylum determination system and downstream judicial and policing costs.  Meeting our international obligations in this respect consumes considerable public moneys.  However, Ireland is not unique in this respect.  All countries which take this issue seriously are faced with similar calls on their financial resources.  The role of the Reception and Integration Agency is to adapt to circumstances in ways which specific legislative provisions might not anticipate.  In recent years it has introduced child protection measures, including Garda vetting, and will in the coming months begin to publish on its website completed inspection reports on each of the centres under contract to it.  It has also to adapt to the decline in the number of persons seeking accommodation.  In the four year period 2009 to 2012, inclusive, it closed 25 centres and accommodated 2,161 fewer persons.  This flexibility and adaptability of the direct provision system would not be assisted but, possibly, hindered by specific legislation underpinning it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800024#Y00400"><p>My question is about the legal status of the payments being made.  It is not about the legal status of the policy in place.  I appreciate the Minister's response, but it does not address my question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/952" speakername="James Reilly" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800024#Y00500"><p>I will make the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, aware of the position.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.244" nospeaker="true" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800024#Y00600">Garda Recruitment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800024#Y00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, and thank him for taking this matter.  Like Senator Jillian van Turnhout's, my question is also directed to the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, and I am disappointed he cannot be present.</p><p>I would like to know if consideration has been given to the circumstances where a change may be effected to the upper age limit of 35 years for recruitment to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I had not anticipated that the issue of recruitment to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na would be in the news today for other reasons.  My specific purpose in asking this question is to focus on the upper age limit for recruitment.  I have received a communication from a constituent who has been prevented from applying to join the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na because of the upper age limit of 35 years.  My constituent is 37 years old and the recruitment requirement was introduced when she was 32 and unable to apply.  She is conscious that age is not an issue in other jurisdictions, including for the Swedish police, Strathclyde Police which is now part of Police Scotland and the Police Service of Northern Ireland, PSNI.  I am told that the Scottish recruitment team was surprised to hear that there was an age bar in Ireland.  </p><p>This matter has been the subject of questions in the D&aacute;il; the most recent I can find is from Deputy Thomas P. Broughan on 12 July 2011.  When he asked the Minister about the upper age limit, the Minister responded that he was giving consideration to the issue of the circumstances which might effect a change to the upper age limit for entry to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The Minister went on to outline the position and said recruitment was governed by statutory regulations, namely, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Admission and Appointments Regulations 1988 and 2005.  He also said the recruitment age had been considered as recently as 2004 when, on the recommendation of the Garda Commissioner, the maximum recruitment age was increased from 26 to 35 years, which, I acknowledge, was a substantial increase.</p><p>Given that a substantial and significant increase could be provided for in 2004, I wonder why the upper age limit of 35 years cannot be increased.  The Minister's response to Deputy Thomas P. Broughan in 2011 was that consideration was being given to the issue.  The Minister also gave as a reason for setting the upper age limit at 35 years the need to have regard to equality legislation.  I cannot see where that is relevant, as I am sure equality legislation would pre-empt any arbitrary age limit being set.  The current age limit appears to be somewhat arbitrary.  While 35 years is perhaps a little more justifiable than 26 years, it is an age limit that might not be so objectively justifiable under equality legislation.  The Minister gave three reasons for this in July 2011: the cost of training which I am not sure is valid; the need for recruits to serve for a sufficient period of time as full members of the service to recoup this cost, which is a more substantial reason; and the operational requirements of the service in terms of having an age profile appropriate to the physical demands placed on members in the course of their duty.</p> <p>He then said:<blockquote><br />Consideration is being given to changing the upper age limit, in limited circumstances, in a way which would be beneficial to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na .... Regulations 2006 already allow the Public Appointments Service to give due recognition to any satisfactory service by a person as a reserve member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na. </blockquote>I think I am correct in saying that there is no age limit for joining the Garda Reserve.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800025#Z00200"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800025#Z00300"><p>I am right.  There is no age bar for the Garda Reserve.  It sometimes carries out front-line Garda work but it does not have full Garda powers.  I simply ask, in light of a direct request from a constituent, whether there have been updates since July 2011.  Has the Minister given consideration to changing the upper age limit for entry?  If the age limit was raised in 2004 by a significant amount then it should be possible to raise it again.  The three arguments given by him do not seem to me to be sufficiently weighty to justify 37 years as being too old.  The third issue of operational reasons is a matter of physical fitness which could be the subject of a very different test and perhaps does not require a blanket or rigid age limit.  I am interested to hear the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800025#Z00400"><p>I thank the Senator for raising the matter.  I apologise on behalf of the Minister for Justice and Equality who is unable to attend.</p><p>As the Senator rightly stated, the age limit is set out in statutory regulations.  She has already put those regulations, for the information of Senators, on the agenda of the House.  She also acknowledged that there had been a substantial increase in the age limit from 26 years to 35 years. </p><p>I understand from the Minister that the upper age limit of 35 years was set following a comprehensive examination of the issues surrounding recruitment to the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  In particular, the assessment took account of developments in equality legislation and the Senator asked a question about it but I cannot sufficiently answer her at this point.  She also outlined the criteria: the cost of training; the need for recruits to serve for a sufficient period as full-time members of the service to recoup the cost; and the operational requirements of the service.  Having considered all the relevant matters, the Garda Commissioner recommended that the recruitment age be extended from its then limit of 26 years to a revised limit of 35 years.  The Minister agreed with his recommendation which led to the introduction of revised regulations.</p><p>The Minister does not have any proposals to increase the recruitment age for entry to the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na at this time.  He believes that when recruitment begins again, as it inevitably must, there will be a sufficient pool of suitably-qualified and eligible candidates who will be provided with excellent training at the Garda College in Templemore and on the job in Garda stations throughout the country.</p><p>The training programme was recently revised as a result of the recommendations contained in the report of the review group on training and development in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Following the publication of the report, a working group was set up to examine the current entry requirements and amend, if necessary, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na (Admissions and Appointments) Regulations to accommodate the recommended changes to the student-probationer training programme.  The aim is to improve and realign recruitment training in line with best practice in order to meet the new challenges of a changing society.  It is anticipated that the amended regulations will be finalised in the near future.</p><p>The Minister has asked me to point out that there is an ongoing civilianisation programme in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  While the moratorium on recruitment in the public service still exists, the recruitment age for civilian staff is well in excess of 35 years of age.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800025#Z00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response but some of it reflects what was said in the D&aacute;il in 2011.  The updated part of his response refers to the report of the review on training and development in the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I am not sure when the report was published.  I am glad to hear that a working group was established, following publication, to examine the entry requirements and amend, if necessary, the regulations.  Given that the regulations also set the minimum age limit I hope that, at the very least, some consideration will be given in the working out of changes to the regulations to increase the minimum age.  I ask the Minister to State to convey my following comment to the Minister.  One might anticipate that the working group would examine the minimum age in the course of generally examining the recommended changes to the regulations.  It would be a good opportunity to do so and would be in keeping with the Minister's previous response that consideration was being given to the circumstances where an increase in the age limit could be affected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800025#Z00600"><p>The Senator made a helpful suggestion.  There is a process under way to examine the amended regulations and I understand that the working group is due to submit its report in the near future.  It is important and opportune that the Senator raised the matter.  I hope that the question of limitation of age would be part and parcel of the work of the working group.</p><p>As the Senator mentioned, there are special circumstances, from time to time, where an individual might apply to be a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  There should be some flexibility in that regard, particularly if people can bring expertise and specialist knowledge to the force.  That would be a logical outcome of what we are trying to encourage in terms of members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  I shall convey the Senator's view to the Minister for Justice and Equality and ask him to consider the matter in the context of the working group.      </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800025#Z00700"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.253" nospeaker="true" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800025#Z00800">Island Communities</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800025#Z00900"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending.  As he will know, Dursey Island is served by a cable car which was the first cable car to connect an island to this country.  A number of difficulties have arisen in the past 12 to 18 months.  The islanders have successfully accessed the island by cable car for some decades.  They also transported animals but due to health and safety concerns and other issues the practice has virtually stopped.  There are two points of severe concern at present.  First, it has been announced that the cable car needs its structures and cables upgraded and improved.  It has been proposed to cease the service for a full calendar month to carry out the work.  How will people gain access to the island?</p><p>I shall outline the second concern.  I tabled this Adjournment matter about four weeks ago but I have not got around to dealing with it for a number of logistical reasons.  Since I tabled the matter I have learned that there is a proposal by the office of the Minister of State, Deputy McGinley, to provide a ferry service to transport animals to and from the island at certain times of the year.  Perhaps it will assist people who also want to repair houses.  At present two properties are being upgraded so blocks, plaster, timber and bits and pieces must be transported to the island.  People who either live on the island or originally came from it and still view it as their home need access on a daily or weekly basis.  Today I was told by an island representative not from Dursey Island that the next proposed ferry to transport bulk loads to or from the island, or transport cattle to the island for summer grazing or transport cattle, sheep or other animals off it, will be in August.  A cable car that has successfully transported animals for over 30 years is being stopped.</p><p>Local councillors and the council gave a commitment to provide a ferry which must be funded by the Department.  However, it has been suggested that people must wait until August for a ferry service.  That is not on.  As I said here before, the people who live on Dursey Island and farm the land, some of whom live on the mainland, have the same rights as people who live in Dublin 4, Cork city or wherever.  It is ridiculous to leave the islanders totally cut-off and isolated without access to the island.  It is not good enough to simply provide a ferry to the island in lieu of the animals and other materials not being taken on the cable car twice a year.  There should be a monthly service weather permitting.  Many people say that one could use boats but Dursey Sound is known traditionally as one of the most inhospitable stretches of water due to severe currents. </p> <p>In this weather, it is normally inaccessible by any boat.  Only a lunatic or a madman would envisage trying to land on the island in these appalling conditions.  I hope the Minister of State has some good news for the island about the cable car and the ferry.  I have spoken about the rights, worries and concerns of the island people and those near Dursey who access the island regularly.  Many access the island on a daily basis.  Their rights are being encroached upon and they deserve better treatment.</p><p> This is a case of passing the buck from Cork County Council to the Department, and there is also the matter of health and safety and regulations.  There should be joined-up thinking to deal with the problem people on Dursey Island have.  I refer to people who live on the island or own land on the island and regularly farm it.  One of my hobbies is affected by this, because the area is part of the Beara walkway.  The two or three hours of walking are a wonderful experience.  From a tourism point of view, it is a terrible drawback that there is no access to the island.  The islanders deserve all the facilities we can give them.</p><p> I am coming to the conclusion that we might as well say goodbye to Dursey Island because of the problems with the cable car and the loss of a ferry to transport animals and materials.  It will be like <i>An tOile&aacute;nach</i>or &quot;Farewell to the Blaskets&quot;.  I would hate to see another island off west Cork becoming depopulated.  The Minister of State at the Department of Arts, Heritage and the Gaeltacht, Deputy McGinley, and the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Brian Hayes, will understand the plight of the islanders, and I hope the latter will give me a good news story.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800026#AA00200"><p>I apologise on behalf of Deputy McGinley, who is taking a Bill in the Dail.  He wanted to be here because of his interest in the islands and because of his commitment, on behalf of the Government, to do what we can for the long-term sustainable development of all inhabited islands.</p><p>The cable car to Dursey Island is the responsibility of Cork County Council and the Department has no role in its operation.  I am aware that Cork County Council engaged consulting engineers in 2010 to undertake a complete structural assessment of the cable car, in accordance with national and European legislation and with the Eurocodes.  As a result of the structural assessment, the consultants recommended that the transport of animals on the cable car be discontinued.  Based on this recommendation, Cork County Council prohibited the transport of animals on the cable car with effect from January 2012.</p><p>In order to alleviate the difficulty of transporting cumbersome items to the island, the Department agreed to allocate a grant for the provision of a cargo ferry service to allow for sailings on three separate days during the period 1 July 2012 to 31 August 2013.  This allowed for the transport of essential cargo to the island and facilitated the occasional transport of animals on the return journey, although the subsidy was not provided for this specific purpose.</p><p>Cork County Council commissioned a further study in 2012, entitled Dursey Island Cable Car Strategic Review, the purpose of which was to consider access to the island that would sustain growth, allow farming practices to be facilitated, attract people to the island and ensure compliance with relevant legislation.  The review considers different scenarios with regard to the future of the cable car and access to the island.  I understand that the review will be published shortly, and it will form the basis of future decisions on the cable car and the island.  The Department will consider any proposal it receives from Cork County Council on island infrastructure or access, while bearing in mind the very limited funding available for infrastructural development. </p><p>The Minister of State, Deputy McGinley, is acutely aware of the issue and is committed to doing what he can to help the island and its long-term sustainable growth.  In any circumstance the issue of funding arises, but in the first instance we will wait to see the published report from Cork County Council, which has responsibility in the area, before seeing what further action can be taken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800026#AA00300"><p>I thank the Minister and I acknowledge that he is taking the matter on behalf of the other Minister of State, Deputy McGinley.  The Minister of State suggested Cork County Council should commission a report on facts that are patently obvious.  All it needs to do is to listen to people who live on the island and who access it.  The demands are very basic and simple.  They need access and they need the cable car not to be out of action for a calendar month.  It sounds crazy.  I hope the Minister of State can convey to the Minister that there should be a monthly cargo ferry service, subject to weather conditions.  It could be funded by the council or co-funded by the Department.  It may not be used every month, but if there was an emergency, such as an outbreak of TB on the island, the current cargo ferry service could not meet the needs of the islanders.  With or without the report, the Minister of State could listen to the islanders and their demands, which are very reasonable.  The Minister of State should convey my deep concern to Deputy McGinley, who has a love of all islands and rural areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013041800026#AA00400"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter and making the argument on behalf of the community in a sensible and reasonable way.  I will convey the remarks of Senator O'Donovan to the Minister of State, Deputy McGinley, so that he is aware of the position.  We all await the report commissioned by Cork County Council, which will be published shortly, before seeing what further action can be taken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-04-18a.259" nospeaker="true" time="14:05:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.50 p.m. until 4 p.m. on Tuesday, 23 April 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>