<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.2" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 12:00:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.4" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.5" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Mark Wall that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to review the housing adaptation and housing aid grants available through each local authority. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Rural and Community Development to make a statement on whether the streetscape enhancement scheme will be extended to next year. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on the provision of a natural gas pipeline from Ballymahon to Longford town. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment to make a statement on changes to the visa and work permit schemes to facilitate non-EU nationals working in Ireland. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to provide an update on the timelines associated with the design and planning for the proposed new build for the Summercove National School, Kinsale, County Cork. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator John Cummins of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Social Protection to remove receipt of disability benefit as a qualifying criteria for eligibility for the winter fuel allowance for those persons who meet the income means test.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Rural and Community Development to make a statement on the national outdoor recreational strategy including the extension of the walks scheme to the farming community. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Seery Kearney of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Social Protection to make a statement on the status of the Indecon report which was commissioned to examine the cost of having a disability in Ireland. </blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Marie Sherlock of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth to make a statement on the measures in place to address waiting lists for counselling services for victims of rape and sexual assault. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Lynn Boylan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on blockages in the planning system associated with solar panel installation and microgeneration. </blockquote><p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and I have selected Senators Wall, O&rsquo;Loughlin, Carrigy and Byrne and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.<br/><br/>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Malcolm Noonan, for coming to the House this morning.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.8" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#B00150">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.9" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#B00175">Housing Schemes</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#B00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House to address what I feel is an important matter for many people in this country, especially those in my county, Kildare.  I am sure that, like me, the Minister of State has assisted many people and families with what has always been a worthwhile grant.  The grant has made such a difference to the day-to-day lives of so many older people and families with medical issues who needed assistance with the quality of life of their loved ones.  Over the past year, many families have found themselves unable to afford the work which is recommended in the context of these grants and which can make people's lives so much better.  Rising building costs have practically stopped many people from being able to access these grants.  An urgent review of the grants must be carried out.  In recent months, my office has received an increasing number of calls from people.  Many are at their wits' end and are asking for help for their loved ones who, in some cases are still in hospital waiting for the promised work that can bring them back home, where they and their families want to be.</p> <p>As I said recently in the House, in one case, the cheapest quote that the person dealing with my office received was more than 200% above the maximum grant payable, which is &euro;30,000.  The quote that person sought was for the works recommended by the local authority's occupational therapist.  The person had engaged with five different contractors to try to get a cheaper quote but could not achieve that.  There are many similar cases.  Another issue is that more and more builders are demanding that the cost of the grant be paid up front because they cannot afford to wait on the council payment system.  With so few builders now completing council work, families have no option but to borrow from where they can in order to secure these building services and get the work done.  This puts added stress on families who need our help rather than finding themselves under more pressure.</p> <p>Another issue relates to the means test for older people, where the private pensions that they worked hard for all their lives are reducing the amounts they are offered via the grant.  They are turning to family members or credit unions to try to fund the difference.  The type of works involved will allow members of our older population to remain in their homes where they want to be.  Too many of our older population find themselves unable to access a grant which, at their time of life, is essential to their well-being and which, as I have said on countless occasions, is needed for all their work and contributions to the State over many years.</p> <p>These issues are having a knock-on effect.  In some cases that I am dealing with, the applicants have to remain in hospital because the family cannot afford the cost of the works to bring them home.  In an ever-increasing number of cases, people can no longer continue to live in their own homes and this is causing an additional cost to the State through the nursing homes scheme.  In many cases, I turn to another arm of the State and try to engage the community welfare officer service to see if it can come up with the difference to secure these payments and ensure that grants are paid.  These issues are causing much stress, as the Minister of State can imagine.</p> <p>I know that staff dealing with these grants are inundated with queries from worried applicants, fearing that they will not get work done on their homes.  We need to provide additional resources to local authorities to cover the administration of these grants.  The ever-increasing waiting times for some of these grants are a worry, both at the beginning of the process and when payment is due.  I have raised the need to create permanent posts in our local authorities rather than the contracted positions that seem to be on offer at present.  We need to offer staff security in these positions, which will have a knock-on benefit in the context of these grants.</p> <p>Time is not the friend of many of these families.  There is an urgent need for a revised grant.  I know from previous discussions and replies to parliamentary questions from my Labour Party colleagues that a review will be carried out by the end of the year.  I ask the Minister of State to speed up this review to change these life-changing grants now and allow those who need these grants the most the benefit of works that will change their lives for the better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#C00100"><p>I thank Senator Wall for raising this issue and providing me with an opportunity to give an update on the matter on behalf of the Department.  The Department provides funding to local authorities under the suite of housing adaptation grants for older people and people with a disability to assist people in private houses to make their accommodation more suitable for their needs and also to facilitate an early return from hospital stays.  The grants include the housing adaptation grant for people with disability, the mobility aids grant and housing aid for older people, which are 80% funded by the Department with a 20% contribution from the resources of the local authority.  The detailed administration of these schemes, including assessment, approval, prioritisation and appointment between the three schemes, is the responsibility of the local authorities.</p> <p>Funding of &euro;75 million is available nationally in 2021 from the housing adaptation grants for older people and people with a disability scheme.  This funding has increased year on year since 2014.  As part of the budgetary process, consideration will be given to increasing this funding in future years in line with the programme for Government commitments and the policy statement on housing options for our ageing population.  The housing options for our ageing population policies statement emphasised the Department's commitment to streamlining the application process and ensuring the grounds were more accessible to applicants.  In this regard, the Department met all 31 local authorities in 2019 to review the detailed administration of the grants in a series of workshops countrywide.  The Department also met key stakeholders, including the National Disability Authority, Alone and Age Friendly Ireland, which helped to bring clarity and guidance to the issues raised at the workshop.</p> <p>A revised single application form to cover the three grants, which was tested for plain English, was issued to all local authorities in December 2019 together with revised guidelines for implementation by the end of January 2020.  The Department is working to ensure full implementation of the new process, which will make the grant application process more user-friendly and accessible as well as standardising the individual local authority approach to administering the scheme.</p> <p>The receipt and processing of housing grant applications has continued throughout the pandemic.  Carrying out of such works was specifically exempted from the construction restrictions under the public health regulations which were in place.  It is accepted, however, that the pace has been affected by the effects of wider restrictions and revised work methodologies necessary in response to the pandemic.  Inevitably, this has led to a backlog of applications in some local authorities.  Officials in the Department are engaging with local authorities and emphasising the importance of urgently reducing any existing backlog through the provision of additional resources and ensuring that all applications are dealt with in accordance with departmental guidelines.</p> <p>As detailed in Housing for All, housing policy objectives Nos. 6 and 7 give a commitment to undertaking a review of the range of housing grants, which I understand is what the Senator is seeking, and specifically meeting housing needs for the ageing population and people with a disability.  On the specific issues raised by the Senator, I also dealt with many of these schemes in my time as a local authority member.  They are fantastic schemes but the issue of cost is now proving prohibitive to many people.  The other issues the Senator raised, such as builders demanding that they be paid up-front and the additional resource burden on local authorities, suggest to me that we need to carry out a review of the current set of challenges with this scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply, the final few sentences of which addressed precisely the problems people have raised with me.  It goes without saying that other Senators are dealing with similar matters.  Building costs have risen exponentially over the past 24 months and the grant has not kept pace.  I have had people cry on the other end of the telephone line as they told me that a loved one was in hospital and could not come home to them.  Increasing the grant by a relatively small amount could make the difference and allow a loved one to be brought home.  Unfortunately, local authorities are restricted to providing the prescribed amounts.  An urgent review is needed because people cannot continue to have loved ones in hospital settings.</p> <p>I raised previously the issue of permanent contracts.  More and more contracts in local authorities are temporary.  This does not allow them to recruit the staff they need to carry out works and inspections.  That is having a knock-on effect on the grants.</p> <p>I ask the Minister of State to examine those two issues and convey my views to the Minister.  A review is urgently needed.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1512" speakername="Malcolm Noonan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#D00100"><p>Following the stock response that we have given the Senator, as well as the specific issues the Senator has raised here, the Department needs to come back with a specific set of answers.  The workshop that was held with local authorities was useful in teasing out these issues.  A new set of challenges has come about as we emerge from the pandemic.  Building costs are surging.  There is another issue around contractors and their availability.  Many of them are probably taking work that is easier to come by.  Hence those issues that the Senator has raised.  It is therefore important that our Department comes back with a specific response on that set of challenges, as well as on the permanent posts in local authorities.  It is a worthwhile suggestion.  We will get back to the Senator with a response from the Department.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.14" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#D00250">Departmental Schemes</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#D00300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for affording me the opportunity to speak on the streetscape enhancement scheme in the Chamber.  I thank the Minister of State for his attendance. I was pleased to see in September that Kildare County Council had been successful in securing funding from the Department of Rural and Community Development through the 2021 streetscape enhancement measure.  I was especially pleased to see that four lovely villages in my own local area were accepted by the scheme, namely, Castledermot, Ballitore, Monasterevin and my own home village of Rathangan.</p> <p>This is a good scheme.  It offers many small rural villages, not just those in Kildare but all around the country, an opportunity to access Government funding and use it in a way that is community focused and will benefit the entire area.  A scheme such as this is needed in rural areas. The Minister of State will have heard me saying before that the Government must support rural Ireland both to develop its own way and, of course, to attract new residents and businesses.  A scheme such as this, when it is fit for purpose, will result in a more attractive environment that residents, visitors, shoppers and businesses alike can enjoy.  However, the deadlines and the practicalities in accessing such schemes must be logical, user-friendly and accessible.</p> <p>When we devise schemes that are intended to be accessed by the general public, the deadlines and requirements need to be achievable.  The turnaround time that was required to apply for this scheme deterred many people in Castledermot, Ballitore, Monasterevin and Rathangan from availing of this funding.  As a Member of the Oireachtas, I was first notified of the scheme on 25 August.  The closing date for receipt of fully completed applications was 5 p.m. on Tuesday, 7 September 2021.  The following is what was required for a complete application: photographs of existing buildings; photographs of an example of what the new building facade would look like; maps identifying the location; records of protected structures' numbers, where relevant; exact details of work proposed, including a copy of relevant, plans, designs and specifications; indications of material type and colour; two written quotations for proposed works from builder contractor; one written quote for materials if the grant applied for was under &euro;5,000; and three written rotations required for contracts above &euro;5,000.  All of the above was to be completed in just two weeks.  </p> <p>I appreciate that the closing date for applications was pushed out to 17 September, but that extension was not announced until 3 September.  This meant that anyone who had not applied due to time pressures had lost another week.  In addition to this, in order for an applicant to draw down the funding, works needed to be completed by Sunday, 31 October 2021, just three weeks after the cut-off for applications.  It is practically impossible to get anybody to do any work for the smallest thing within a home.  This is just ridiculous.  I put it to the Minister of State that we are discouraging applications to good schemes by putting incredible pressure on business and property owners to provide a plethora of information and to complete works in a short time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is simply not achievable.  Only seven applications were received from the four towns I mentioned, and those applicants were not certain that it would be possible to get the works required completed in time.  Is the Department planning another streetscape enhancement scheme?  If so, will the Department learn from the haphazard approach adopted this year and support applicants in a way that will enable them to avail of the scheme?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  I am here on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Heather Humphreys.  I am glad the Senator supports the revitalisation of towns and villages and helping people to work from home.  It is Government policy to do that.  We agreed it last summer.  The Senator is raising the practicalities of the short time permitted for the submission of applications, the great amount of detail required, including quotations, and the need to complete the works quickly.  Those aspects provided practical problems.  I can see that and I will relay the Senator's observations to the Minister.</p> <p>The streetscape enhancement measure fulfils a commitment in Our Rural Future to provide funding to support the upgrading and enhancement of shopfronts and street facades in rural towns and villages.  Many actions and commitments across all of Government are contained in Our Rural Future: Rural Development Policy 2021-2025 and those aim to make rural Ireland a more attractive place to live and work.  The streetscape enhancement measure was introduced this year by the Minister.  It is designed to make around 120 rural towns and villages more vibrant and welcoming places for locals and visitors alike.  Property owners across the country are being part funded to undertake a range of eligible projects.  The types of projects eligible include the commissioning of murals; the painting of buildings and shopfronts in vibrant colours; the upgrading or restoration of historic shopfronts; the provision of street planting, shrubbery, trees, flower boxes and the installation of street canopies and street furniture; and the decluttering of streetscapes through the removal of unnecessary signs or wires.  The wide range of possible projects that could be funded was designed to ensure that the available funding would have the widest possible impact across our rural towns and villages.  Measures are being delivered by the local authorities on behalf of the Department of Rural and Community Development, with considerable discretion being provided to each local authority to design the scheme to meet the needs of their area.</p> <p>Given the concerns raised by some property owners regarding the timelines for delivering these projects, the Minister recently announced an extension of the original deadline for the completion of works until the end of the year.  I understand that the local authorities were consulted regarding this extension and that they were informed of this change at the end of last week.  I am confident that this extension will alleviate much of the pressure on property owners and facilitate the full delivery of the works planned under the measure.  In addition to this extended deadline, I understand that local authorities were also provided with further flexibility regarding how they manage the scheme locally and in respect of subsequent reports on the outcomes to the Department of Rural and Community Development next year.</p> <p>We have all seen the huge success of those towns around the country that have invested in recent years in improving their streetscapes by painting buildings in vibrant colours, upgrading and restoring traditional shopfronts and removing unnecessary clutter from the main streets.  The funding available under this measure will help to replicate this kind of success in rural towns and villages across Ireland.  It provides a real opportunity for local authorities, businesses and property owners to work together in adding colour and vibrancy to our rural towns and villages.  There has been a very positive response to this new initiative and I have no doubt that this funding will impact greatly on the appearance of our towns and villages.  I understand also that a decision regarding a further round of funding in this regard will be considered alongside other town and village investment priorities next year and will also draw on the experience derived from this year's scheme.  </p> <p>I look forward to seeing the impact of this year's initiative on our towns and villages in the coming months and I am confident that this will be a highly visible example of how Our Rural Future is delivering real benefits for rural Ireland.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#E00300"><p>I welcome the extension.  I noticed a press release an hour before I came in here announcing its granting.  It is welcome, but the constant changing of the goalposts is not acceptable.  My concern is that there were seven applicants from four vibrant areas.  There should have been many more, and several people to whom I spoke did not submit an application because they knew that they would not have been able to get the works completed by the original date.  To a certain extent, therefore, those people are being discriminated against now.  If they had realised that there was going to be an extension, then they would certainly have applied.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We must address that.</p><p>I appreciate what the Minister of State said about vibrancy, etc.  I invite him to visit south County Kildare to see the results of these four applications.  However, we should not be in the position of looking for and welcoming an extension.  When these plans are put in place they must be realistic.  They must have smart goals.  Local authorities should have more flexibility.  I appreciate the Minister of State's comment that they will have that.  That is good news as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#F00200"><p>I take the Senator's point about changing timelines and how they may have dissuaded applicants and I will take those back to the Minister.  I thank her for her invitation to visit south Kildare.  I recently bought a renovated electric car from a company called Range Therapy in Narraghmore, outside Kilcullen.  It took a very old electric car and upgraded it by adding extra batteries.  It is a business that is involved in the circular economy and I compliment those involved on that.  I would be very happy to visit south Kildare.  I am responsible for the national broadband scheme, for example, and am keen to go to areas that Oireachtas Members may wish me to visit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#F00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I would say the invitations are in the post at this stage.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.22" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#F00350">Energy Infrastructure</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#F00400"><p>I tabled this Commencement matter in response to recent reports of a potential energy shortage in the next 24 months.  This is very worrying for many house owners and businesses.  We also had discussions on whether we should grant permissions to develop data centres which, in general, do not provide jobs, although many of the companies developing those centres employ thousands of people here.  The large amount of energy these centres use has been discussed.  We have also seen significant increases in energy costs.  Only in the last two weeks, we have had another one from Electric Ireland.</p> <p>A large number of employers in County Longford are reviewing their energy use.  They include Panelto Foods, which recently doubled the size of its operation and opened a research and development centre in what was our enterprise office in Longford, and Birds Eye, which is owned by Nomad Foods and supplies pizzas to virtually the entire UK market.  A number of businesses in the county are expanding, including Abbott which employs almost 1,000 people.  In response to the need to address climate action, Longford County Council, in conjunction with Gas Networks Ireland, having consulted local businesses, submitted an expression of interest some years ago under the climate action fund seeking an extension of the gas network from Ballymahon to Edgeworthstown and Longford.  I have a copy of the submission with me.  In this regard, I recognise the work of the former Minister, Eoghan Murphy, the former Minister of State, Senator Kyne, and the former Minister, Deputy Naughten, in supporting the proposal to have the pipeline brought from Athlone to the Center Parcs site in Ballymahon, rather than from Mullingar.  The reason it came from Athlone was to allow the potential expansion of existing capacity to do this.</p> <p>The application made provision for the development of anaerobic digestion and associated biogas to be deployed into the gas network via an injection facility as part of the proposal.  It did not seek only the extension of the pipeline.  It proposes an extension from Ballymahon to Longford and Edgeworthstown of almost 60 km to facilitate connections to high energy users, allowing them to reduce their energy emissions, utilise energy efficiencies and apply renewable technologies while exploring expansion potential.  The injection of renewable gas to this network would be carried out in tandem with the development of anaerobic digestion facilities at the Lanesborough-Mount Dillon area as part of the just transition process, following the closure of Lough Ree power station and the Bord na M&oacute;na works.  The core aim is to deliver renewable energy back to the grid, driven and supported by the local communities most affected by the process of climate action.  The holistic package will provide employment opportunities and economic development and enhance biodiversity and environmental quality by promoting community-based initiatives to decarbonise the difficult areas of agriculture and transport.</p> <p>Since this application was made, Lough Ree power station has closed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MichealCarrigy&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Bord na M&oacute;na works have also ceased.  The just transition fund was initiated and Longford County Council is progressing a study, funded by the just transition, on anaerobic digestion, AD, in this area and engaging with the national stakeholders and the local communities.  This study will support the original expression of interest, which I have here, lodged under the climate action fund to develop and extend that pipeline into Longford.  I have asked that this project be supported and our county town get infrastructure of which it was deprived in the early 2000s, while all other towns in the midlands received natural gas.  It is the most efficient energy for running businesses.  We have found it difficult to attract some businesses due to the fact we do not have that infrastructure.  I ask that this application be looked at in a positive light.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#G00200"><p>I thank Senator Carrigy for referencing the climate action plan which, as he probably knows, is being updated.  The newly revised climate action plan will be issued in the coming weeks, but I will take into account what the Senator has being saying.  The routing of gas pipelines or the connection of towns to the gas pipeline network are matters for Gas Networks Ireland, a commercial State-sponsored body under the control of the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, and for the Commission for Regulation of Utilities, CRU, the statutory independent energy regulator, which conducts consultations on its regulatory decisions.</p> <p>Gas Networks Ireland is mandated under section 8 of the Gas Act 1976 to develop and maintain a system for the supply of natural gas that is both economical and efficient.  The Commission for Regulation of Utilities has, since 2002, been charged with all aspects of the assessment and licensing of prospective operators who wish to develop and-or operate a gas distribution system in the State, under the Gas (Interim) (Regulation) Act 2002.  Therefore, the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications has no direct statutory function on the connection of towns to the gas network.  I understand Gas Networks Ireland continues to engage with Longford County Council and relevant stakeholders that seek to build an economically-viable business case to extend the network further to the town, as per the requirements set out in the Commission for Regulation of Utilities' approved connection policy.</p> <p>Despite the formal regulatory process, it is difficult to see how extending the gas network to new towns would be in keeping with the Government's overall climate and energy targets.  With regard to the Government's upcoming climate action plan, I confirm it is not intended to include extensions of the gas network to new towns as a means of decarbonisation.  The connections policy there allows for the appraisal of a new town, either on its own, or as part of a regional group of towns, and appraises both domestic and industrial commercial demand.  Proximity to a major pipeline or a large industrial or commercial gas load tend to be the most significant factors in town appraisals.</p> <p>Gas Networks Ireland is mandated, under section 8 of the Gas Act 1976, to develop and maintain a system for the supply of natural gas that is both economical and efficient.  In terms of the engagement between Gas Networks Ireland and Longford County Council, there was a recent assessment under the connections policy, in 2017, which found connecting Longford to the gas network remained, at that time, unviable in the absence of significant new demand.  That is the honest situation in which we find ourselves.</p> <p>At the same time, every town in Ireland has to find a way to decarbonise.  If it is moving people away from solid fuel and oil and will not be to natural gas, it has to be to something else.  As the Senator said, biogas is certainly one option.  Heat pumps are another option.  Retrofitting is a part of the answer as well, but it is not the case there is no answer.  What comes out in the climate action plan will be important to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#G00300"><p>I do not know what to say, to be honest.  I am disappointed.  The application is cognisant of the fact of developments in anaerobic digestion and injecting biogas.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MichealCarrigy&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is not a case of just looking for a pipeline in a business case scenario because the reality is that the business case is not strong.  It is strong, however, when other things are taken into account, such as providing that AD and injecting biogas into the system.  It ticks the boxes as regards climate action, in my opinion.  I ask that this be taken into account rather than being ruled out.  We are based in the midlands.  Lough Ree power station has closed, as has the Bord na M&oacute;na plant.  We have an entire site there as part of the just transition.  It was a priority from Government that alternative infrastructure, and maybe an energy park, be put there.  I ask that this be looked at in tandem with that if possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#H00200"><p>The Senator agrees that it is unlikely that, under a strict cost-benefit analysis, extending the gas network will be found to be viable.  He has also said that there is a project of investigation to see whether biogas can be injected and whether we can make progress on that.  I support that.  The midlands have been targeted for just transition funding.  We need to find ways forward and biogas has not been developed in Ireland in the past in the way it has been in other countries like Germany.  That will certainly be an important part of the climate action plan.  I am happy to engage with the Senator further and put him in contact with the Minister if that helps, although, as pointed out, Gas Networks Ireland technically comes under the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage.  However, it is obviously an energy matter and a matter of heating homes.  The key thing is that we need to help towns in places like Longford and the midlands to find a way to transition to something different and that certainly could be AD or biogas.  I would be keen to do anything I can to help in that regard.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.29" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#H00300">Work Permits</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#H00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this matter.  The reality is that the economy is starting to recover, probably at a more rapid rate than was expected.  That is very welcome but one of the biggest challenges we face, if not the biggest, is the shortage of skilled labour.  We are hearing that from employers right across the sector.  We are very familiar with the shortage of skilled labour in the tourism and hospitality sector, which we debated in this House.  We are hearing about it in haulage, from companies in the agrifood sector, in manufacturing, medical employment, and in the technology spaces where a lot of high-end jobs remain unfilled because we do not have skilled workers.  We are certainly hearing about it in construction, where we need significant numbers of additional skilled workers if we are going to achieve the plans we have laid out in Housing for All.</p> <p>While it is very welcome that the Government is investing heavily in our higher and further education and training programmes, and we have seen all the new apprenticeship models, it is going to take a period before we have enough skilled personnel here in Ireland.  It is absolutely essential that non-EEA workers are able to come here to work, that that process be as smooth as possible and that the delays will be minimal.  The problem, as the Minister of State knows, is that there are very long delays, even for trusted partners or IDA Ireland companies.  My understanding is that, as of today, the Department is only now processing applications from trusted partners that were made on 15 July and standard applications that were made on 29 June.  If a company makes an application in order to get a work permit for somebody to come here to fill a vacant post, it is waiting three months.</p> <p>If we are to come out of this very difficult period we continue to experience, we need a strong and robust economy.  This is a country whose economy is very much based on skilled labour, and we recognises the importance of such labour.  Quite frankly, however, the work permit and visa system is not fit for purpose.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is neither fit for those seeking employment in all the sectors we have talked about nor for employers.  It is probably the biggest barrier to our economy growing as quickly as we need it to over the next period.</p><p>I know other colleagues in this House have asked about this and it is something that is regularly raised by employer representative organisations but we need to streamline the visa and work permit system and we also need to ensure we are not seeing three or four-month waiting lists before processing even starts on any of these.  Government Ministers will be coming into this House next year telling us that houses are not being built because we do not have the necessary construction workers.  We will still see the problems in tourism and hospitality and the jobs in the tech sector and our hospitals cannot be filled.  The primary reason that is so is because of an inadequate work permit and visa system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#J00200"><p>I am taking this matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy English, who sends his apologies.  I thank the Senator for raising this matter, which is pertinent and timely.  Policy responsibility for the granting of visa permissions is a matter for my colleague, the Minister for Justice.  The employment permits system is designed to facilitate the entry of appropriately skilled non-EEA nationals to fill skills and labour shortages, or both, in the short to medium term, in circumstances where there are no suitably qualified Irish or EEA nationals available to undertake the work and where the shortage is a genuine one.</p> <p>The system is managed through the operation of the critical skills occupations list and the ineligible occupations list.  These are subject to twice-yearly evidence-based reviews in consultation with other Departments, sectoral representatives and the economic migration interdepartmental group.  Where shortages are clearly evidenced, the employment permit system is flexible enough to address them in real time.  The current review will close by the end of October with a final report setting out recommendations for approval.</p> <p>The employment permits (consolidation and amendment) Bill consolidates the existing legislation to provide a more accessible statutory basis for our economic migration system.  Specific changes include the introduction of a seasonal employment permit, modernising the labour market needs test, moving operational criteria to regulations to increase responsiveness, and streamlining requirements to make the grant process more efficient.  The draft Bill is almost finalised and we await the report of the Joint Committee on Enterprise, Trade and Employment before bringing a memorandum to Government to seek approval to publish.</p> <p>Recently, as the Senator has alluded to, processing times have been impacted by a significant increase in demand and by the HSE cyberattack.  These factors resulted in a significant additional administrative burden in dealing with applications associated with the July doctors' rotation which were submitted either manually or by other non-standard methods.  It is also worth noting that there was a 41% increase in the number of permits issued to the end of September when compared with the same period last year.  It is important to point out that when set against other international employment permit regimes, Ireland continues to compare extremely favourably.  However, my Department is conscious of the recent lengthening of timeframes for processing applications and is taking a range of measures to clear the backlog as quickly as possible.  This includes the redevelopment of the current employment permits IT system, which should drive further efficiencies in processing and result in increased productivity.  My Department advises employers to take current timelines into account as part of their recruitment plans.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#J00300"><p>I smile when the Minister of State mentions that the number of applications for work permits in September 2021 represented a 41% increase on September 2020, given that people were not allowed to travel and that we were in the middle of some of the big Covid challenges.  I am disappointed, although I appreciate that the Minister of State is answering on behalf of his colleague.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The name of the Minister of State's Department is the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment.  If we want to support enterprise then where job vacancies exist we must ensure they are filled.  It is not good enough that we have not seen as much progress as we should have.  While I would be grateful to get a timeline on the employment permits Bill, I also seek an assurance that in six months' time, we will not be experiencing these difficulties because if we continue to do so, I predict that sectors of the economy will grind to a halt. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#K00200"><p>I, too, share the Senator's frustrations.  My constituency office is just as much contacted, maybe more so given that I am a Minister of State in the Department, by industries that seek to have permits processed as a matter of urgency.</p> <p>As I have said, measures have been undertaken by my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy English, to improve efficiency in the processing time of permits through the Department.  It would be wrong of me not to acknowledge that there has been a delay and I encourage people to take account of the delay when advertising positions.  I urge people to link in with the almost 10% of people who are unemployed, because they are ready, willing and able to take on job opportunities.  In my own constituency, the Department of Social Protection has been linked with local companies and has matched good quality staff with the demands and needs of companies.  I encourage other people to do likewise.</p> <p>The new Bill in this area is currently with the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Enterprise, Trade and Employment.  When the committee finalises its report it intends to bring a memorandum to Government for approval and then to enact the Bill thereafter.  I can assure the Senator that there is no desire on the part of my Department to delay that and once the Oireachtas committee publishes its report, we will move at pace to have the Bill enacted.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.36" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.47 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.37" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#L00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#L00200"><p>Today is Spain's national day.  Ireland's shares a common past and a centuries long friendship, which goes all the way back to the 16th century with the Treaty of Dingle which was signed in 1529.  Through our shared history there has been a constant flow of Irish people to Spain, from medieval pilgrims on the Camino de Santiago through to the many Irish who found refuge in Spain at the time of the Flight of the Earls.  The many Irish colleges founded during that period helped not only to preserve the distinct cultural identity but also facilitated Ireland's engagement in the wider world.</p> <p>There is an increasing number of Irish citizens resident in Spain, estimated at 40,000, and as many as 2.3 million Irish people visit Spain every year, and more than 20,000 Spaniards live in Ireland.</p> <p>Spain is the fifth largest market into Ireland in terms of visitor numbers.  For decades Spain has been Ireland's second largest EU market for English language training.  This connection has seen many prominent figures in public life from Spain visit Ireland, including its Prime Minister, Pedro S&aacute;nchez, who spent time in Ireland during his adolescence.  I wish the ambassador, Mr. Castro, and all the Spanish people in Ireland a happy national day.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.39" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#L00300">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#L00400"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on budget 2022, to be taken at 5 p.m. and to conclude at 8 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the Minister&rsquo;s opening speech not to exceed 12 minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given no less than 12 minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#L00500"><p>I call the Deputy Leader, Senator Chambers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#L00600"><p>As today is budget day, I will have an opportunity to address the House later on my views on the budget that has just been announced.</p> <p>I wish to raise two items on the Order of Business.  The first is a radio interview I heard as I was driving to Leinster House.  I am not sure if other colleagues heard it.  One of my colleagues beside me is nodding.  It was the story of a young boy, Adam Terry, and his mum, Christine.  It was one of the most heart-breaking radio interviews I have ever heard.  This boy who is ten years of age has been waiting for years for scoliosis surgery and he can no longer go to school because of the pain.  He was told he would have his surgery in February of this year but it has again been kicked down the road a little further.  The most heart-breaking and devastating part of that interview was to hear the news from his mum that because he did not have the surgery sooner, the surgery he will have at the some point will not produce the same outcome that it could have done.  He will never be as well as he could have been had he got the surgery when he was meant to get it.  He spoke on the radio, which was an incredible act of bravery for such a young child, about the pain he is suffering, that he cries himself to sleep and that he wants his voice heard.  The reason he and his mum, Christine - they are a very private family - have done this is that they want those in a position to be able to do something for them to listen and to hear their story.</p> <p>I ask that a letter go from the Cathaoirleach&rsquo;s office to the Minister for Health asking him to contact that family immediately, to sit down with them and give them a date for surgery.  I do not care what it takes.  If we have to send that little boy to the UK and bring him home for the aftercare - whatever it takes to get him the surgery - that is what needs to happen.  The word "disgraceful" does not cut the mustard, having listened to that boy's story and what his mum has to endure as she watches her child in pain every day.  That is so wrong in a first world wealthy country.  It should not be happening.  They deserve to have that contact directly with the Department and the HSE.</p> <p>The second issue I want to raise is Brexit.  People will be aware it is back on the agenda, not that it ever went off it.  Today, the UK's Brexit Minister, David Frost, will deliver a speech.  Unfortunately, it is a day in advance of when the EU will publish its new proposals on the Northern Ireland protocol.  That has been the subject of many months of negotiation, engagement in Northern Ireland, in particular, with citizens and businesses understanding the crux of the problem and what it will take to make the protocol work more smoothly, using what flexibilities we have to make what we have work better.  That can be done.</p> <p>It is unfortunate that here we are yet again - it is almost like Groundhog Day - at another cliff edge with another ramping up of tensions between both sides, but at the end of the day who loses out?  It is not the politicians at the table making the decisions.  It is the ordinary citizens and businesses on this island and in the UK.</p> <p>An update on Brexit from either the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, or the Minister, Deputy Coveney, at the earliest opportunity would be welcome.  We will see what happens over the next couple of days.  One of the strong messages coming back from the engagement Maro&scaron; &Scaron;efovi has had in the North and with the Irish Government is that people are worried about matters such as having food on supermarket shelves, the customs union and imports and exports, essentially the general day-to-day working of the protocol and trading in what is a new environment.  What they are not concerned about, or have not raised issues about, is the European Court of Justice having a say over the protocol, which was built into Article 12 of the Northern Ireland protocol.  It was there from day one.  Its job is to adjudicate on matters of European Union law, which is what the Single Market and customs union are.  It is unfortunate that at this late hour a new issue has been thrown into the mix, which makes it very difficult to see this being solved in the near future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#L00700"><p>I too want to raise the heart-wrenching interview that I heard on "Today with Claire Byrne" this morning.  Any parent who heard that interview could feel the pain that family is in.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Emer Currie:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=EmerCurrie&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My wee girl underwent an operation in Crumlin children's hospital some years ago.  Everything went smoothly, but I remember waiting for the date.  It is terrible that a child who has been on the urgent list since August 2019 and who was told his surgery would take place next spring has now been told that he must wait another six to nine months.  That is despite the fact very day his parents can feel the pain he is in and can see that is quality of life is what it should be.  I completely agree with my colleague that we need to send a letter to the Minister for Health.  That would let this family know that they have been heard and that there is a solution.  The family are considering travelling to London but it would be better if the procedure took place here because this is where the little boy's family and friends are.</p><p>I take this opportunity to welcome the budget and the focus it has on quality-of-life issues such as remote working.  There are incentives relating to the latter, including extending the personal tax relief to 30%, not just for broadband but also for heating and electricity.  That is a positive step.  At the same time, however, we are in a period of transition whereby employers are trying to figure out what their offices and teams will look like into the future and identify where they can make savings.  Ideally, if employers make savings then they should pay for people's utilities.  You can claim a &euro;3.20 expense tax-free if it comes from your employer.  We need employers to think seriously about that because it might become mandatory at some stage.  However, we need to know what savings employers are making.  Let us not forget about the hubs.  By supporting hubs, we are supporting towns and villages.  I am sure there is more in the budget relating to the opening and supporting of local hubs.  Let us not forget how important they are to local communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#M00150"><p>At the outset, I wish to remember Paddy Moloney, who sadly passed away earlier today at the age of 83.  Paddy was a great ambassador for Ireland and for Irish music.</p><p>Chinese aggression towards the democratic island of Taiwan is intensifying and should be giving rise to concerns that China will try to take over the island by force.  We have already seen how Beijing used a heavy-handed approach to impose its authoritarian ways in Hong Kong.  Ireland is a member of the United Nations Security Council and must speak out against any and all aggression by China.  As an act of solidarity, now might be a good time for the Government to open an office in Taipei.  In addition, we have spent months if not years talking about the fate of Richard O'Halloran who is still in China.  It is simply not good enough that he continues to be detained there at this stage.</p><p>The Irish Coast Guard and its volunteers, the Royal National Lifeboat Institution, RNLI, and the search and rescue helicopter service form the backbone of first responders for rescue at sea.  At the weekend, one of the Sunday newspapers carried a headline, &quot;Coast guard 'has to fix toxic workplace'&quot;.  I was not surprised to see this headline because for some time I have been receiving reports of problems within the Irish Coast Guard.  Despite the fact that the acting director of the Irish Coast Guard has rejected the claim that volunteers have been targeted or subjected to unfair disciplinary inquiries, the evidence suggests that he must be totally out of touch.  As a result, the Irish Coast Guard is now in a crisis situation and there has been a complete breakdown of trust between volunteers and management.  The volunteers have been forced to set up their own representative body because they are so afraid of the way things are going.  Coast Guard members voiced their concerns following two separate incidents that shook the organisation.  First, a report by the Marine Casualty Investigation Board, into the death of Cathr&iacute;ona Lucas in September 2016 off the coast of County Clare after an inflatable boat she was in capsized during the search mission, was critical of the safety management systems in place at the time.  Second, the long-awaited report on the accident involving Rescue 116 in March 2017 with the loss of four crew will, I believe, be damning of the corporate governance of all of the organisations involved with search and rescue, and will be particularly damning of the oversight of the Irish Coast Guard.</p><p>Equally damning is the fact that the officers in charge of a number of stations around the country have been forced to resign or have been dismissed.  The officer in charge of Dunmore East was dismissed in 2019 despite having served for more then 20 years with the Coast Guard.  The officer in charge of the station in Youghal, County Cork, having spent ten years in the position, resigned in January 2019.  At the time, he complained about the poor treatment of volunteers in recent years and wrote in his resignation letter, &quot;I feel I can no longer serve an organisation that values its volunteers so poorly&quot;.  Another officer in command of the station at Killala Bay, County Mayo, resigned after 20 years of service.  If this is not a crisis, then nothing is.  We need urgent action to bring about a resolution in respect of this matter.</p><p>Finally, on behalf of those of us who visited the naval base in Cork last Friday, I want to thank the flag officer for his downright openness and honesty with respect to the crisis that is in the Naval Service.  That is a matter I will raise in the coming days. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#M00200"><p>Ba mhaith liom comhbhr&oacute;n &oacute; chro&iacute; a dh&eacute;anamh ar bh&aacute;s Paddy Moloney, comhbhunaitheoir an bhanna ceoil The Chieftains.  Ba laoch m&oacute;r ceoil agus cult&uacute;ir na h&Eacute;ireann &eacute; at&aacute; imithe anois ar shl&iacute; na f&iacute;rinne agus go nd&eacute;ana Dia tr&oacute;caire air.</p> <p>I thank the Leader for outlining the Order of Business.  As other colleagues stated, we will have an opportunity to outline our views and perspectives on the budget in the allocated time this afternoon.  For now, I want to raise a number of issues.  I welcome the announcement by the EU that it will provide free rail travel passes to 60,000 18- to 20-year-olds across the Union .  As they say in Irish, b&iacute;onn si&uacute;lach sc&eacute;alach.  This is a fantastic opportunity for young people to broaden their horizons, and it is particularly good when it is free.  I am sure that the initiative will be welcomed across the board.  I will make my own inquiries in this regard, but I suggest that it would be useful to find out if people across the Thirty-two Counties will be able to apply for the passes allocated to this State.  It is important that people aged 18 to 20 in the North will not be not excluded from this very welcome and exciting scheme.</p> <p>Yesterday, the High Court in Belfast found that the refusal by Democratic Unionist Party Ministers of the Executive to attend meetings of the North-South Ministerial Council - a core component of the Good Friday Agreement institutions - is unlawful.  That should give us all cause for concern.  We should all recommit ourselves to ensuring that we work the institutions of the Good Friday Agreement to the fullest extent.  I look forward to attending, along with colleagues from across this House and from across the Oireachtas, to attending the plenary meeting of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly next Monday.  The meeting comes at a crucial time for relations between Britain and Ireland.  It is also a time of great challenge and difficulty, but we must remember that it is always better to talk. </p> <p>My colleague, Senator Currie, spoke about remote workers.  I again met with representatives from the Cross-Border Workers Coalition this morning.  Senator Currie and others have previously mentioned the potential for double taxation in respect of people from this jurisdiction who are employed in the North.  We need to ensure that workers can work from home as much and as efficiently as they possibly can.  For people who live in Letterkenny, Milford, Muff, Dundalk or wherever and who work in the North, we must ensure that they are protected and that there is no threat of double taxation coming at them down the line.  Is &eacute; sin an m&eacute;id at&aacute; le r&aacute; agam.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#N00100"><p>Likewise, I am going to refer to the measures that were taken in the budget during the allocated time we have.  Today, I want to raise the issue of the prohibition on men who have sex with men from donating blood in the Republic of Ireland.  The remit of the Irish Blood Transfusion Service is to provide safe, reliable and robust blood supply for the health system and it can continue to perform this role and minimise the risks while removing the 12-month automatic prohibition.  The ban is not reflected in many countries across Europe, including our closest neighbours.  In fact, because of the pandemic, I understand that this year, the Irish Blood Transfusion Service bulk-imported blood from England due to a shortage of blood here.  It came after Britain had moved to an individual risk assessment system for all prospective donors, and the same has recently happened in Northern Ireland.  As England accepts blood from Irish donors, this means that an Irish man who has sex with men could have donated blood in the Irish supply system in Manchester but not in Dublin or anywhere else in Ireland.</p> <p>I was contacted earlier this week by a man who has been travelling to donate blood in Northern Ireland and London since he has been able to do so, in a hugely altruistic act.  At the end of August this year, that person gave his 18th blood donation.  He has O negative blood, which is always in great demand and short supply because it can be given to any blood group.  These 18 donations could not have been given in the Republic of Ireland and 18 patients potentially would have gone without the blood they needed.</p> <p>It is unreasonable that the men who contacted me, who are so willing to help others and who would much prefer to donate safe and needed blood here at home, cannot do so in their own country because of the very outdated viewpoint of the Irish Blood Transfusion Service.  We have not adopted an individual risk assessment system.  I call on the Minister and the Irish Blood Transfusion Service to reassess the 12-month automatic ban on blood donations for men who have sex with men and to assess the individual risk assessment management system in order to ensure the safest and most reliable blood supply is available in Ireland and that we get the blood we need within our own system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#N00200"><p>I ask the Leader to consider holding a debate in due course on anti-Semitism in the Republic of Ireland.  Most Members here will have seen the type of toxicity that is on Twitter and other social media in regard to members of the Jewish persuasion.  A recent report by David Collier highlights this in a very serious way.  If Members want to research him online, I assure them they will not find it very pleasant reading, given that some of the comments, tweets and posts are of the most heinous nature.</p> <p>We all know the history of anti-Semitism.  It is as old as time.  It has been throughout Europe and all over the world, culminating, naturally, in the Holocaust, which was the worst example of it.  We see the programmes all the time on the concentration camps and I hope they will be continue to be seen on our television screens so younger generations will know what the Jewish people had to undergo at that time.</p> <p>I am happy to be from Listowel, which is one of the few places in Ireland which has a Holocaust memorial, which was erected about 20 years ago by the late, lamented Mervyn Taylor of the Labour Party, who died just recently.  Most Irish people are very reasonable about racial differences and all the rest of that but there is definitely an element somewhere that seems to be unable to escape this atavistic anti-Jewish sentiment that is so evil.</p> <p>It is in that context that I have to express regret at the decision by our very well known, popular and successful author, Sally Rooney, to deprive her fans who like to read in Hebrew of being able to read her any further in Hebrew because she is not allowing her books to be published in Hebrew hereafter, ostensibly as a protest against Israeli policies.  First, not all Hebrew readers are living in Israel, so it seems a very ill-judged protest to me.  It sort of opens the door to that sort of cultural hatred that we have witnessed in the past.  Book burning was one of the most prominent ways of attacking people of the Jewish persuasion and whereas this is not book burning, it is not altogether unaligned to it.  I think it is ironic that this should be her decision.  Are we going to have a situation where authors will disallow their books from being published in Chinese because of the totalitarian regime in China, or in Russian in Russia?  Will Irish authors stop allowing their books to be published in the UK because of the despicable English Brexit policies?  Where is it going to end?  The Leader might be able to organise such a debate for us at this time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#N00300"><p>I thank the Senator for raising that important issue.  I know she has issued a statement in that regard.  I thank the Senator for his comments this morning.  I call Senator Aisling Dolan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#N00400"><p>Today, we have budget 2022, which has &euro;87.6 billion of supports.  It is there to help people get back up on their feet again after this pandemic and lockdown.  For jobs, we are seeing a continuation of the wage subsidy scheme and the raising of the standard income band by over &euro;1,500.  For young families, there is the largest budget ever allocated for Housing for All.  For older members of our community, there is an increase in the fuel allowance by &euro;5 and &euro;5 for the pensions.  There is an increase in the minimum wage and in the USC rate bands to accommodate that rise.  We are also seeing a focus on healthcare, with the increase in acute beds and in mental health as well.  For young people and students travelling to work or college, that 50% off public transport with the youth travel card is going to make a massive difference, in particular as many students are commuting as they are unable to find accommodation.  In further and higher education, there are over 7,600 new places and over &euro;200 million is being allocated for students under the Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, scheme.  In our primary schools, the staffing ratio has been reduced by a point, with 350 new teachers and 1,165 extra special needs assistants, SNAs, bringing their number up to 19,200.</p> <p>With regard to my area of Roscommon and Galway, the remote working income tax reduction will encourage people to live and work in rural and remote areas, in regional areas and in towns and villages outside of urban and city centres.  That is proposing an income tax reduction of 30% in regard to heating, broadband and electricity.  For hospitality and for pubs, caf&eacute;s and hotels in our local areas, the VAT rate is maintained at 9%.  The zoned land tax is crucial to getting developers moving and building homes.  Retrofitting of homes is also crucial and it is happening in our estates and in my own town of Ballinasloe.</p> <p>Some &euro;11.1 billion in 2022 is allocated for the national development plan.  That is about getting the 50-bed unit Portiuncula Hospital, it is about getting the new national rehabilitation unit in Roscommon hospital and it is about getting another 50-bed unit for the Sacred Heart care home in Roscommon.  It is also about getting the Galway to Athlone cycleway, which was launched yesterday.  It is incredible to see that work is starting and progressing on the bridge over the River Shannon.  That is investment into the west.  We are also seeing the importance of sport and physical activity, which, of course, is linked to mental health - it is good for heads and good for hearts.  We are seeing an increase, hopefully, to the funding allocated to sports capital.</p> <p>This is a budget to support all and I look forward to more discussion on it.  It is important that it is bringing benefits to rural areas as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#N00500"><p>I would like to follow up on and commend Senator Ned O'Sullivan on what he had to say about anti-Semitism and the decision by author Sally Rooney to refuse permission for her novel to be translated into Hebrew.  Perhaps somebody needs to remind her that Israeli people are normal people as well.  Perhaps this is an example of when virtue signalling can actually turn quite vicious, wittingly or unwittingly.</p> <p>It is in that context that I wanted to raise the recent 48th session of the UN Human Rights Council in Geneva.  After that session, 48 countries, led by Austria, the Czech Republic and Slovakia, issued a statement pledging to combat the growing international scourge of anti-Semitism, and Ireland was not a signatory to that statement.  I would like to know, and I would like a debate at which we can ask the Minister, why not.  What possible reason could there be for the Irish Government not to sign up to such a statement?  This very strange omission by the Government comes at a time of growing evidence of anti-Semitism here.  Within our political system, in academia, on our streets and, of course, on social media, we see the problem increasing by the day.  We have seen it in politics.  We have even seen it in these Houses on occasions, and I will not mention the people or the parties, but we see subtle and tacit support being given to individuals and groups who are on the record as supporting the genocide of Jewish people.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Much of this arises from the ongoing conflation of Zionism with anti-Semitism.  In other words, some people seem unable to draw the line between opposing Israel's actions as a state on the one hand and opposing Jewish people on the other.  I am on the record of this House as being very uncomfortable, to put it mildly, with how the state of Israel conducts itself at times, particularly in regard to settlements.  There is an increasing trend among the Irish political class to strongly criticise that country while remaining mute about anti-Semitism.  Last week, the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, stated that he seeks to be balanced and fair, that he has criticised Israel's foreign policy towards Palestinians and that he has been extremely critical of violent movements such as Hamas.  That has to be acknowledged, but at the same time I do not like it when, one week, he excoriates Israel in the D&aacute;il for its retaliation against Hamas and then days later meets the Foreign Minister of Iran, the very country that is arming Hamas with rockets designed to kill Jewish citizens.  <i>Mit Brennender Sorge</i>, I ask for a debate on this important issue as early as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O00200"><p>I am sure the Leader will point out the following but, as the Senator will be aware, the meeting with the Foreign Minister of Iran was in regard to our membership of the UN Security Council and our designation in regard to the ongoing agreement on the nuclear issue in that country.  I remind Members that when speaking about people outside of the Chamber they should be mindful that such people are not here to defend themselves and that when in the same contribution they speak about anti-Semitism they must be careful when they speak about an individual and their actions and other issues.  I do not want Members to infer or make allegations against people who are outside of this House who are not able to defend themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O00300"><p>That is true.  We can always call out foolishness or, at least, I hope we can in this House.  There is a lot of it abroad in the culture at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O00400"><p>We do not have enough time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O00500"><p>Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O00600"><p>Last night on "Claire Byrne Live", Irish entertainer and comedian, Rory O'Connor, spoke openly and candidly about his challenges with gambling and its impact on his life and family.  An hour earlier, on BBC One, the famous soccer pundit and ex-Arsenal footballer, Paul Merson, had a special show detailing his lifelong battle with gambling and how he has lost &pound;7 million to gambling.  He was left penniless and living in rented accommodation, never mind the impact on his mental health.  </p> <p>Over the last year, I have spoken extensively in this Chamber about the scourge of the gambling sector in this country.  I was glad to hear the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Michael McGrath, announce in his budget speech that funding is being made available for the establishment of the gambling regulatory authority.  However, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, in his speech announced a tax relief credit for the digital gaming sector at the rate of 32% of expenditure up to &euro;25 million on the design, production and testing of a game.  This is a wide encompassing sector, primarily focused on children and teenagers in the area of gaming.  In recent years, the gambling industry has sought to rebrand its online gambling casino products under the name "gaming".  This includes digital technology adopted from the gaming industry.  I am asking that in the Finance Bill, where this is to be fleshed out, we make clear that products developed by these independent companies for the big gambling companies, which are billion euro enterprises, do not qualify for this particular relief.  It was explained on "Clare Byrne Live" last night that these companies have analytic technicians who detail the cookies of addicts so that they are then able to further fuel their addiction.  They create case studies on these people.  They know through their analytics that these people are addicts and they keep fuelling that addiction with these products.  What an irony it would be if we were to afford them a tax credit to allow them to further enhance their research to keep people addicted to this drug.  I am aware of the area at which this is primarily focused, but I would hope that the Finance Bill can be strengthened to make sure that no company developing products for the gambling industry can qualify for this relief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O00700"><p>I am seeking clarity on when the legislation for the regulation of e-scooters is to be introduced.  The Minister of State, Deputy Naughton, announced that it would be introduced in the autumn of this year, but it is important to have that clarified as soon as possible.  In most European countries, there is a lack of regulation of e-scooters and active travel and as a result this area has become a bit like the wild west, with companies setting up in capital cities and doing whatever they want in terms of bringing in e-scooters.  I am an advocate of active travel and e-scooters.  It is important we get the legislation right in Ireland to ensure there is a positive view of e-scooter use in this country.  I attended the United Nations pre-conference on climate action in Rome, which is one of the cities in which there is no regulation of e-scooters and as a result there are e-scooters parked anywhere and everywhere on the streets, which causes a real issue for people with disabilities and people with visual impairment.  It is a form of littler as well in that one is constantly dodging obstacles on the footpaths.  We have to change people's mindset in regard to transport and to convince them that active travel is better than the car.  For active travel to work, the system has to be as flawless as possible.  We can ensure that it is flawless by providing in legislation that the tender process must make clear to e-scooter providers coming into this country that e-scooters can be parked only in designated areas, similar to Dublin Bikes.  We must provide in law for designated parking for e-scooters and, also, that they must be well maintained, properly parked and not present any obstacles on our footpaths.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O00800"><p>I too will reserve my comments on the budget until later.  I cannot let go uncountered what was said in this Chamber today about a particular author.  It is important that facts matters.  It is clear from the statement made by the author that it is not the language to which she objected in regard to the translation of her book.  This is part of the Boycott, Divestment, Sanctions, BDS, campaign which is a non-violent campaign and should be supported, in the same way that this country proudly supported South Africa against apartheid.  It is important to put on the record that the objection was not about the language.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O00900"><p>There is a big difference.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O01000"><p>The book is open to being translated into Hebrew by any publisher that is not covered by the BDS campaign.</p> <p>Today, I want to focus on the comments last night of Mr. Owen Keegan, the chief executive of Dublin City Council, to the UCD students' union.  I support the Sinn F&eacute;in council team in saying that his position is now untenable.  He has proven himself to be ideologically opposed to policies that will benefit the people of Dublin city.  Last week, I raised the destruction of the social and cultural fabric of our capital city.  The comments made yesterday to the students' union were significantly lacking any form of empathy with regard to what students' are experiencing in terms of the accommodation crisis.  One academic spoke about a student in her class who gets up at 4.30 a.m. to travel from Cavan to Dublin because there is no accommodation.  Other students are renting hostel beds, with nowhere to study or put down roots during the academic year, or deferring their opportunity in life.  For the chief executive to dismiss the concerns of the students' union about student accommodation, which was built in this city against the wishes of the vast majority of those communities, being converted into tourist accommodation when there are students who have no roof over their head is astounding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#O01100"><p>Like Senator Craughwell, I too, once again, call for a debate on our policy on China.  I remain disappointed by the approach of the Department of Foreign Affairs in regard to the Richard O'Halloran case.  It is clear there has been no progress made.  It is now a matter of urgency on a whole range of issues, including the genocide against the Uyghur, the treatment of the Tibetan minority and what has been happening in Hong Kong.  We need to have that debate on China.</p> <p>I also want to raise a question of abuse of power closer to home, that is, what has been happening in Poland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is very clear that the overwhelming majority of Poles support European Union membership.  The Polish community, which is now our largest ethnic community, has enriched and contributed enormously to Irish society and, indeed, the European Union is enhanced by Poland's participation.  What we have seen in recent years through the Law and Justice Party is a deterioration in the rule of law.  Any modern democracy has to function on the basis of checks on power.  We value enormously the independence of our Judiciary but what has now happened in Poland is that there is a politically appointed constitutional tribunal at the behest of the government that is seeking to undermine the core pillars of the European Union.  We have seen how the Polish Government has treated minorities, including the LGBT minority, and this is a crucial question about the values of the European Union.</p><p>This House needs to send a message of solidarity to the Polish people.  Polish people have a long history of rebelling and standing up against authoritarianism and authoritarian regimes.  I ask that, on behalf of this House, the Cathaoirleach write to the Polish ambassador expressing our concerns and that we have a debate on the questions of the rule of law within the European Union and European values.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#P00200"><p>There will be statements on the budget later but as I am not due to speak until tomorrow, I wish to touch on a measure in the budget which was announced a short time ago, that is, the extension of the help to buy scheme.  This has been pivotal in assisting 28,500 individuals and families to build or purchase their first home.  It has been an essential measure to assist them in getting their deposit together.  Under the Central Bank rules, that is 10% of the price.  People my age seeking to get on the property ladder for the first time, tell me that this scheme has been important in enabling them to buy their first home.  That is why it is a very positive decision by the Government to extend that scheme in the budget for the coming year.</p> <p>All Opposition parties want to abolish that scheme, which is absolute madness.  What is their solution for those people trying to get their 10% deposit together to get on the ladder?  It is all well and good to saying they will build affordable homes, but under the Central Bank rules you still need a 10% deposit to get on the property ladder and purchase that affordable home.  I would welcome a debate in this Chamber where every party can lay its cards on the table in regard to what its affordable housing plans are.  Under both our schemes, which will commence next year, an equity stake is being taken in the property whereas in other schemes being touted, you will not own the land on which the property is built and you will be restricted on who you can sell the property on to.  If I was a first-time buyer, I know which scheme I would prefer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#P00300"><p>Like my colleague, I will not be speaking on the budget today but I want to welcome the disability budget that was announced today.  I especially welcome the single biggest increase in personal assistants hours, totalling 3 million.  This is a very welcome announcement.</p><p>On another note, I propose that this House has a series of debates where each Department could show how it is going to implement the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, UNCRPD. <font color="#202124"> </font>The UNCRPD needs to be implemented.  We will be ratifying and implementing that protocol, hopefully next year.  Departments have a role to play in that implementation and I would like to see their strategies.  They would be very welcome to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#P00400"><p>Last Friday 88 branches of the Bank of Ireland throughout the country closed.  This is another blow to the rural economy.  Along with that went the only ATM machine in a number of towns.  One of those towns was Granard in County Longford where the local credit union has applied for planning permission to install an ATM at its facility.  When that happens, I urge people to support their credit union and their post office.  As a postmaster, I am naturally biased.  We have those facilities available but I would urge people to support the financial institution that remains in many towns in rural areas because the reality is that within the next 24 months, it is likely many other branches of other banks, such as AIB, will also close.  I would ask people to support the financial institutions that remain.</p> <p>As Members are aware, I am still battling to get support for the post office network.  The reality is that within the next 12 to 15 months, unless there is a significant increase in social protection payments going into post offices, which decreased at an alarming rate specifically after Covid-19, we are looking at in the region of 300 post office closures in early 2022.  That is a reality and people need to grasp that.</p> <p>When a post office closes - a number have closed, in particular in Dublin - I ask people to transfer those payments to another post office rather than to a bank, which is more than likely going to close its branch.  We have always used this analogy of use it or lose it, so I ask the public to support those financial institutions that remain because otherwise they will be gone within the next 24 months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#P00500"><p>I wish to bring up two issues, one of which is the takeover of Lufthansa in Shannon by the Atlantic Aviation Group, AAG.  While 300 of the staff will be subsumed into the new company, it is uncertain what will happen with the further 180 staff.  I call for immediate Government intervention in regard to this.  The unions are due to meet in the coming hours and I hope the Government will not be found wanting, which I am sure it will not.</p> <p>The other issue is University Maternity Hospital Limerick, UMHL, which has gone green for mental health month.  It is doing this every day.  It is the only perinatal health clinic outside Dublin, which was established in 2018.  It has a staff of nine.  However, it has seen a huge increase of more than 50% in terms of women and their mental health, especially in light of Covid-19.  I would like to see more supports being put in place to support the perinatal unit and to see more perinatal units established throughout the country to support women.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#P00600"><p>I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on the National Ambulance Service.  This issue has been raised by a number of Senators over the past while and by various radio stations throughout the country.  It is quite obvious that the National Ambulance Service is not working efficiently.  I was approached recently by a very worried citizen who was in a desperate state one night trying to get an ambulance for his wife.  There was no ambulance available.  The ambulance service is not working properly and that is why I ask the Leader to arrange for a debate.</p> <p>We have the National Ambulance Service and a private ambulance service also.  We have the 90 second window where, when you phone 999 and get through to the ambulance service, it despatches an ambulance within 90 seconds but that ambulance could be two or three hours away.  At the same time, a private ambulance could be available in the nearest town, or in the same town.  It would seem there is no joined-up thinking in regard to the National Ambulance Service and the private ambulance service.  It is important that we have a good debate in this House on this issue and put the cards on the table in regard to the National Ambulance Service and the private ambulance service to see how they can work together for the betterment of communities and people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#Q00100"><p>I know we will have statements on the budget later but I have to express my delight at the announcement this afternoon of the change of the national childcare scheme, NCS, to include projects such as those in the Dublin 8 After School Alliance, including the Robert Emmet Community Development Project and the Solas Project.  Those organisations have been advocating for that change because as an unintended consequence of the introduction of the NCS, children in disadvantaged areas in particular were unable to avail of after-school care.  Now the criteria have been changed such that this anomaly is over.  I also want to pay tribute to the Leader because when she was Minister for Social Protection, she brought in the school meals programme as a pilot for 36 schools and today we have seen it extended.  It has been such a great success so I pay tribute to the Leader and to our Fine Gael colleague, the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, for the increase in that provision.  It was also strongly advocated for by our colleagues, Councillors David McManus and Clodagh Higgins.</p> <p>I seek a debate on sexual health education in this House.  Yesterday was International Day of the Girl Child and Plan International launched its report, KnoWhere To Go.  That report detailed from where young people get their information on sexual health, as well as their understanding of consent.  In that context, I know the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Harris, has done a huge amount of work on consent education at third level but we need a discussion on primary and secondary schools, particularly in light of the fact that some of the school patrons are promoting their own version of sexual education.  I would value a debate on that in this House and I am sure it has been called for before.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#Q00200"><p>I would like to join with other Members who remarked on the passing of Paddy Moloney, who was a Blackrock resident.  He will be missed for his good humour and patience with people as much as for his skill and music.  He was a great member of the community and someone who contributed at every level.  I was aware he went into hospital last night but I am sorry to hear that he passed away.  He will be greatly missed.</p> <p>I also want to comment on what has been said about anti-Semitism.  I join with calls for a debate on that subject but I advise that Members should be careful about throwing that moniker around in respect of somebody who makes a conscious and justified decision to boycott Israel for a specific reason.  That is justifiable and just because one is opposed to Israeli policy in the Middle East does not make one an anti-Semite.  It is tremendously important to recognise that.</p> <p>I would like us to talk about bus services.  We have heard there will not be a resumption of the Nitelink service after the Covid-19 restrictions are lifted and that is a retrograde step.  We need to move towards a 24-hour bus service for the communities on the outer parts of Dublin.  If one takes D&uacute;n Laoghaire, for example, which was served by the 46N, that bus will not come back to it.  That area relies on the 46A and other buses but I am calling for a 24-hour service.  This is not just for late-night revellers but for people who work in town as part of the entertainment industry.  To get home from town to D&uacute;n Laoghaire, Blackrock, Dalkey, Loughlinstown, Bray or anywhere in the outer suburbs of Dublin is an expensive trip by taxi.  We must put in place public transport solutions for those people.  The DART does not run late but the buses did and now we are being told they are not going to resume that service.  We must put in place 24-hour services for people along certain key routes that will allow people to work in town and live in the suburbs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#Q00300"><p>I would like to speak on an announcement in the budget as well and I welcome the significant &euro;898 million funding towards the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment in particular.  There is a &euro;91 million increase in capital funding in that Department, which represents a 21% increase.  I want to focus on decisions that were made on the employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS, the extension of that until April and the significance of that to businesses across the country.  We expect that almost all public restrictions will be eased in the coming weeks but that does not mean businesses are back to normal.  The extension that is being announced today up until 30 April will be beneficial to businesses that need time to get back to where they were pre-Covid.  That is significant, along with the waiver of rates for quarter four, but it is also important that we support councils in the loss of those rates up until the end of quarter four.  The Government has proven that it is here to support businesses, including employees and employers.  I mention the change in the tax bands of &euro;1,500 between the lower and higher rates of tax.  The increase in the employee tax credit of &euro;50 is significant, as is the announcement on remote working.  People who are working from home are being supported to claim back 30% of their electricity, broadband and heating costs.  That is a hugely significant change and it acknowledges the number of people who are working from home.  It will benefit approximately 500,000 people.  That is hugely significant and I encourage people to apply for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#Q00400"><p>Before I call on the Leader to respond to the Order of Business, I will join with colleagues in extending our sympathies to the family of Paddy Moloney, one of the great musicians of our time.  He was a great ambassador for Ireland and Irish culture.  We will always remember the visits the Chieftains made to China when Irish music was performed in the Great Hall of the People.  That was a great honour for Ireland and a great example of how Irish culture can be used in diplomacy and reaching out to people.  We extend our sympathies to the family on its sad, tragic and sudden loss.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#Q00500"><p>I add my condolences to that.  Many of us of a certain age had the Sunday ritual that after Mass, we came home and the old record player was put on.  Certain LPs were played and the Chieftains was one of the big ones in our house along with the Dubliners.  Sometimes when these things happen so suddenly it is hard to even take it in but he will be sadly missed by every household in Ireland.</p> <p>Senator Ahearn raised the welcome addition of nearly &euro;900 million in resources to the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment for budget 2022.  It is significant recognition that our businesses have struggled over the past 18 months and that we need to be there for them to make sure they recover.  Some businesses excelled; they do not need our help and they have helped to recover the economy.  Those businesses that are viable and vulnerable at the moment need to our continued support and that is welcome today.</p> <p>Senator Ward raised the lack of a 24-hour bus service and the recent announcement that the Nitelink will not return.  It is kind of bizarre and I am sure no one will thank me for saying that only a short number of months ago, we announced a provision for a night-time mayor to have a night-time economy.  I recall standing here and wishing I was young enough to think I could be out until 2 a.m., 3 a.m. or 4 a.m. but nobody will be out until that time if they have no way to get home.  A little bit of joined-up thinking would not go amiss in this.  If we are going to have a night-time economy, we have to have ways for people to get into it and get home from it so that is something that needs to be brought to the Minister's attention.</p> <p>Senator Seery Kearney talked about the welcome changes to the NCS and what gives me hope is when something is amiss and then somebody listens and fixes it.  That is positive and for that to happen as quickly as it did is welcome.  It gave me a little bit of pleasure this morning to see that the hot school meals programme has increased tenfold from when it was first introduced as a pilot programme a couple of years ago in Dublin 8.  I hope we get to a situation soon where every school gives a hot meal to our children every single day.  The Senator is also right that we need a debate on sexual education for our younger children and on age appropriateness so I will ask for that debate to be organised in the coming weeks.</p> <p>Senator Burke asked for a debate on the National Ambulance Service and other colleagues have raised that in recent weeks.  The request is in with the Minister but I will go back and see if we can get it moved up the list.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne talked about the maternity hospital in Limerick and the sole perinatal services outside of the capital that we have there.  She is right that it is a requirement for every one of our 19 maternity services and hospitals to have their own perinatal support services for our women and their partners.</p> <p>Senator Carrigy talked about the 88 Bank of Ireland branches that closed and one of them was in Skerries, where my office is.  On Friday evening, people were crying and hugging staff who had served the town for decades.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Senator is correct, and a pattern is evident.  When one of our pillar banks leaves a town, the second pillar bank then automatically moves because there is no competition left in that town.  The second bank does not need to be there.  There has been a shift in banking culture.  What is poor about this change is that every Irish citizen had no choice but to support our pillar banks for the past ten to 15 years because of the bloody mess they got themselves into.  Those banks feel now that making decisions like this supports communities.  There is something amiss.  I support and commend the Senator on what was said.  Those organisations, such as our credit unions and post offices, that remain in our communities to serve the people should get our thanks and support.  We should support those organisations by using our feet.  I commend that happening.</p><p>Senator McGreehan talked about the welcome addition to the disability budget this morning.  She is right, however, that a debate is needed on how Departments and Government agencies are going to ensure that they adhere to the criteria relating to people with disabilities.  We must ensure that we honour people with disabilities and treat them with dignity and respect.</p><p>Senator McGahon referred to the extension of the help-to-buy scheme.  It has helped many young couples to buy houses and will continue to do so for the next year.</p><p>Senators Malcolm Byrne and Craughwell asked for a debate on China.  That request has been made.  Our colleague, Senator Buttimer, raised the matter last week or the week before.  I will chase it up again today.  I will also send a letter to the Polish ambassador today to question the actions, some of them outrageous, over the weekend.  We will wait to see what kind of response we will get.</p><p>On the point made by Senator Ruane, the response from Owen Keegan to the student's union says a lot about him.  I am sure that reaction will probably cause him to reflect on and consider his comments in the days to come.  That is all I will say about the matter.</p><p>I concur with Senator McGahon regarding scooters.  He is only just home from spending time in Rome at the weekend.  I spent a few days there during the summer and scooters were scattered about everywhere.  It was necessary to step over them.  It must be a minefield for people who have small children in buggies and for people in wheelchairs.  When our scooter scheme regulations come into effect, we must ensure that we treat it like our bike scheme, which is well managed and maintained in Dublin and some of our other cities.</p><p>Senator Cassells spoke about the moving stories recounted by Rory O'Connor.  He is right.  I do not suppose for a second that the extension of tax reliefs announced by the Minister for Finance earlier is to encourage the gambling industry in the same way as was done by the welcome move to encourage the film industry in recent years.  It is incumbent on us to be careful to ensure that we do not allow companies in certain sectors to gain tax reliefs through the back door.</p><p>Senator Mullen talked about anti-Semitism and the need for a debate on that issue.  I will arrange that as soon as I can.</p><p>Senator Dolan welcomed the budget, and especially those aspects relating to her home county of Roscommon.</p><p>Senator Ned O'Sullivan spoke of his surprise at the growing sense of anti-Semitism here and of the need for a debate on the issue.  I will organise that.</p><p>Senator Moynihan raised an issue that my colleague, Senator Buttimer, addressed only a few weeks ago.  I refer to the donation of blood by gay men.  It seems ludicrous that we have not updated our standards and assessments to meet European norms.  I will raise this issue with the Minister.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile talked about European rail travel passes.  I will check with the Minister, but I am certain we ensured that INTERREG and all the PEACE funds remain applicable to the island of Ireland.  We will continue to act on behalf of the people of the island of Ireland.  I will double-check that for the Senator, though, and respond to him today.</p><p>Senator Craughwell spoke about Chinese aggression against Taiwan and the need for a debate on this topic.  More importantly, he again eloquently described some of the conditions in our Defence Forces and in the Naval Service and his worries in that regard.  I will raise his concerns with the Minister today.</p><p>Senators Currie and Chambers opened today's proceedings by talking about the little boy, Adam Terry, featured on the radio this morning.  I had tears in my eyes listening to the report.  I suppose most of the women listening to the programme did and maybe most of the men as well.  I do not say this lightly, but it is reflective of us and our State that a mother of a ten-year-old boy finds herself having to go on a national radio programme to plead for the supports and the bloody operation that her child needs to have a chance at a normal life.  What was most heartbreaking this morning was listening to her and knowing that the best opportunity that he had has already come and gone.  I do not know how she was as eloquent and dignified as she was.  I will send a letter to the Minister today.  I ask all the Senators to send letters to the Minister because I am not sure how effective my one little letter will be.  We, as parliamentarians, must respond to the situation of this mam and her little boy.</p><p>I will not have an opportunity to speak on the budget later.  We will all have our ding-dongs as to whether this or that was included or whether enough was allocated.  Some &euro;1.5 billion of taxpayer's money has been directed to be spent today in order to allow our country to recover from what has probably been the most horrendous 18 months for people and to restore the services interrupted during that time.  Most important for me is the need to rebalance our economy and restore order to our finances.  We needed to be generous for the past 18 months.  I have no doubt about that.  A tremendous amount of money has been spent, but it was well spent.  We must now get back to being prudent, however, and to ensuring that the value for money we get out of allocating taxpayer's money is achieved by making sure that funds go to the most required and urgent services.  The case of that little boy this morning is a prime example of where our money needs to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#R00200"><p>The Leader needs to take a bow.  As Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, she motivated and led her Department through what must have been the greatest crisis it ever faced.  We must recognise that as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#R00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#R00400"><p>I do not normally allow interruptions after the Leader has outlined the Order of Business, but we can allow it since it was praise for her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.78" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.79" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.37 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.80" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#U00100">Budget 2022: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#U00150"><p>We are joined by the Minister of State at the Department of Finance, Deputy Sean Fleming, who will address the House on budget 2022.  He is very welcome. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#U00200"><p>I am pleased to have the opportunity to appear before the Seanad today to contribute to the debate on budget 2022, which the Minister for Finance presented to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann a few hours ago.  This year's budget has been prepared against a much more positive backdrop than the situation we faced this time last year.  Forecasts of GDP growth in the economy have been revised upwards to around 15.5% this year, with modified domestic demand &ndash; a better measure of domestic conditions &ndash; expected to grow by about 5.25%.</p> <p>We are now finally emerging from an unprecedented period which saw our economy and our society suffer at the hands of a terrible virus.  I am acutely conscious of the impact the Covid pandemic has had on people&rsquo;s lives and livelihoods.  It has not been easy, yet we have shown immense resilience.  We prioritised each other, limited our interactions, respected public health restrictions and got vaccinated in massive numbers.  As we take the next steps on the road to recovery, we remember those loved ones whom we have lost and acknowledge the tremendous efforts we have made to get to where we are, particularly the dedication and commitment of our front-line workers.</p> <p>Our collective efforts have helped facilitate the reopening of the economy and return to a more normal social life, and will see the removal of almost all of the remaining public health restrictions late next week.  While we will remain vigilant, we must embrace this next phase in shaping our future.  Budget 2022 will play an important role in this regard, adding to the significant policy actions that we have already taken to mitigate the impact of the pandemic.  To date, the Government has made over &euro;48 billion available to support household incomes, businesses and our healthcare system.  This response was only feasible because of the careful management of our national finances in the years leading up to the pandemic.</p> <p>This year&rsquo;s budget represents the next phase of our national policy response.  It will help us to prepare for a sustainable recovery that renews our public services and living standards, strengthens our economy and repairs our public finances.  The approach the Government is taking is two-pronged.  First, we will continue to invest in the productive capacity of our economy and, second, we will return the public finances to a sustainable trajectory on a phased basis.</p> <p>Given the continued levels of uncertainty, the budget is based on a number of underlying assumptions.  One of the most important is that the virus remains contained at levels that do not jeopardise the capacity of our healthcare system.  Over recent months, the successful vaccination programme and associated easing of public health restrictions have supported a strong rebound in economic activity.  In the second quarter, modified domestic demand surpassed its immediate pre-crisis level.  It must be acknowledged that the relatively fast return to pre-pandemic levels of activity is not uniformly reflected across all sectors.  As such, supports continue to be required to facilitate the transition of workers and businesses to a more secure position.</p> <p>Overall, the strong near-term outlook is feeding through to the labour market, where the number of people in employment is expected to increase by around 275,000 in 2022.  Unemployment is expected to ease to approximately 6.5% by the end of next year.  The Government remains committed to supporting the transition to employment for those who need help, including through training and reskilling programmes.</p> <p>All of the actions we take must be consistent with maintaining stability in our public finances.  A key budgetary objective is to ensure the deficit remains manageable and is steadily brought down to a balanced position over the medium term.  Public expenditure will amount to &euro;87.6 billion next year, which is below the ceiling set in the summer economic statement.  The improving economic outlook is feeding through to the public finances, with the combined deficit forecast for this year and next reduced from just over &euro;34.5 billion to &euro;21.5 billion.  However, while we are reducing our borrowing, the amounts involved remain substantial.</p> <p>The budget represents an appropriate balance between tapering supports and continued investment.  By 2023, the remaining deficit will solely be due to capital spending.  The deficit is expected to be around &euro;8 billion next year, but almost &euro;11 billion of this is capital expenditure.  We are, therefore, borrowing only for investment in 2022, which is a year earlier than targeted.</p> <p>The staged repair of the public finances is crucial to our recovery and to insulate the economy from future shocks.  It will ensure fiscal sustainability, bringing our borrowing needs back down within the limits established by EU fiscal rules.  It is in this context that budget 2022 sets out a range of measures to support the recovery in the economy.  The budgetary package amounts to &euro;4.7 billion.  Some flexibility has been built in to allow for any unexpected deterioration in the outlook and exceptional supports for Covid-19.  The expenditure measures amount to &euro;4.2 billion, with a further &euro;500 million allocated to tax measures.</p> <p>Turning to specific budget measures, the employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS, will remain in place until 30 April 2022 to support vulnerable but viable businesses.  For the period from December this year until February 2022, a two-rate structure of &euro;151.50 and &euro;203 will apply, with a flat-rate subsidy of &euro;100 in place for March and April.  Businesses availing of the EWSS on 31 December will be supported until 30 April 2022. </p> <p>On remote working, the Government wants to facilitate a blended approach and support a better work-life balance.  As such, an income tax deduction amounting to 30% of the cost of vouched expenses for heat, electricity and broadband while working from home is being introduced.</p> <p>On income tax, a package of over &euro;500 million will be introduced to support workers in light of cost of living pressures.  The standard rate band will be increased by &euro;1,500 and the personal tax credit, employee tax credit and earned income credit by &euro;50 per credit.</p> <p>On the universal social charge, USC, the ceiling of the second USC rate band will be increased to &euro;21,294 to ensure that the salary of a full-time worker on the minimum wage remains outside the top USC rates.  The exemption from the top USC rate for all medical card holders and those aged over 70 years earning less than &euro;60,000 per annum is being retained.  In addition, the national minimum wage is being increased by 30 cent to &euro;10.50 per hour.</p> <p>Housing is a key priority for this Government, with the recent Housing for All strategy setting out clear targets in this area.  In this regard, a zoned land tax is being introduced which will apply to land that is zoned suitable for residential development and is serviced.  It will be linked to the market value of the land, with the rate set at 3% per annum. The tax will replace the existing vacant site levy.</p> <p>Also on housing, the help-to-buy scheme is being continued at the current rates for 2022 and will be subject to a review next year.  In addition, the relief for pre-letting expenses for landlords is being extended for a further three years to encourage landlords in the residential rental sector to return empty properties to the market as quickly as possible.</p> <p>Another key priority I will highlight is climate change.  The Finance Act 2020 provided for annual increments in the carbon tax of &euro;7.50 out to 2030.  In order to ensure a just transition, the additional revenue will be used to fund climate-related policy measures, including a socially progressive national retrofitting programme, and to address fuel poverty.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Sean Fleming:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=418"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=418&amp;amp;pid=SeanFleming&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A modest tax disregard is also being introduced on personal income received by households who sell surplus electricity back to the national grid.  In addition, further changes to the vehicle registration tax system are being introduced to help reduce road transport emissions, with the VRT relief for battery electric vehicles being extended to the end of 2023.  The scheme for gas vehicles and refuelling equipment is also being extended for three years and hydrogen powered vehicles and refuelling equipment are being included in that scheme.  I want to say very clearly that supporting farming families will play an important role in protecting the environment.  As such, various farming stock relief measures are being extended.<br/><br/>Entrepreneurs and the business sector are another integral part of our domestic economy.  Budget supports will include amendments to the employment investment incentive, extending it for three years and opening it up to a wider range of investment funds.  The innovation equity fund, which is due to be launched in early 2022, will increase the availability of financing for Irish SMEs.  In addition, corporation tax relief for certain start-up companies is being extended.  A new tax credit for the digital gaming sector is being introduced to support digital games development companies by providing a refundable corporation tax credit for expenditure incurred on the design, production and testing of a game.  The relief will be available at a rate of 32% on eligible expenditure of up to a maximum limit of &euro;25 million per project.<br/><br/>In terms of revenue raising measures, excise duty is being increased on a pack of 20 cigarettes by 50 cents, with a <i>pro rata</i>increase on other tobacco products.  The bank levy will be extended for a further year and will be subject to a review next year.  The transposition of the anti-tax avoidance directives will be completed in the Finance Bill 2021.  As regards preparing for future needs, the work of the independent Commission on Taxation and Welfare, which is due to launch a public consultation shortly, will be crucial in ensuring that the Government supports a sustainable recovery over the coming years.<br/><br/>The key objectives underlying today&rsquo;s budget are to ensure that we recover from the pandemic, restore our public services and living standards, and repair the public finances.  The budget package and individual measures seek to balance these three priorities, harnessing our resilience and determination to deliver a sustainable economy and a truly inclusive society.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#V00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comments.  The running order for speakers who are present at the moment is Senators Casey, Norris, Maria Byrne, Pauline O'Reilly and Paul Gavan.  I call Senator Casey on behalf of Fianna F&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#V00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  It is a busy day for him, as well as for the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1675" speakername="David Norris" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#V00400"><p>Excuse me, could I just ask how long each speaker has?  I am sorry to interrupt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#V00500"><p>Priority speakers have eight minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1675" speakername="David Norris" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#V00600"><p>Thank you very much.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#V00700"><p>This is the second budget of this historic Government coalition, which aims to give the people of Ireland value for the money they pay in taxes by investing wisely in public services such as health and education, and strategically investing in the needs of our people, particularly in the area of housing.  We also need to begin the budgetary policies required to make a meaningful contribution to the global problem of climate change.  As if achieving these tasks were not serious enough, we also have to take into account the shattering effects of the Covid-19 pandemic on our society and our economy.  The value of our front-line workers in the health service, and those in essential economic services such as food production, has been brought home as never before.  The people of Ireland have risen to this challenge with a remarkable solidarity.  That solidarity must be reflected in Government policy and that is exactly what this budget does.</p> <p>Fianna F&aacute;il in government has to deal with the reality of the ability of the Irish economy to provide the taxation income that drives our investment policy while ensuring our economy remains attractive for economic growth and business opportunities.  There are populists in our politics who promise spending left, right and centre - or should I say left, left and left again - while also cutting taxes on people.  This fantasy economics, based on populist communication strategies that would make Donald Trump and the Brexiteers blush, is being heralded as the change that Irish people want.  Change indeed, but it would lead to an economic disaster that would decimate Irish jobs, shatter our public investment portfolios in health and housing, and condemn a generation to rebuilding a shattered society.  It is important that the fantasy budgetary policies of the main Opposition party are challenged by all who regard themselves as patriots.</p> <p>Unlike many on the front line of Irish politics, I know what it takes to run a business in Ireland.  I know the sacrifices that family-run businesses make to create sustainable jobs, pay our taxes and grow our businesses from year to year.  I have lived through several recessions and, being involved in the tourism industry, I know better than most the shattering consequences of the economic shutdown caused by Covid-19 on the tourism and hospitality sector.  Budget 2022 is an ambitious budget by the Government, which is internationally recognised as having steered the State correctly through the Covid crisis.  This Government is ensuring, through this budget, that all the people of Ireland receive solutions based in reality, on the problems we face in rebuilding our economy, building homes and ensuring we have a health and education service to be proud of.  As a rural businessman I also am very much aware of the challenges facing the rural economy and farm families as we make the transition to an Ireland where all people are treated equally regardless of where they live or the significant challenges we face.  Childcare supports, increased fuel allowances, social protection payments and pensions are proof that Fianna F&aacute;il and this Government are delivering for all people, not just promising fairy tale stories that have no basis in reality.  An increase in the income tax bands will give a tangible and progressive reward to all Irish workers and help those who are the backbone of our economy to benefit from their work and their contribution to our tax base. </p> <p>The guiding principle of Fianna F&aacute;il has always been and remains the common good of all Irish people.  We do not demonise any part of our great nation.  We value the contribution of businesses, workers, farmers and our public servants.  Housing, healthcare, climate change and the cost of living are all being heavily invested in by this budget.  The common good of the people of Ireland demands a Government that has a vision based in the reality of the challenges and opportunities we face, not just empty slogans, populist rhetoric and political division.</p> <p>I will move on to the specific measures that were announced in the budget today.  I welcome the overall budgetary package of &euro;4.7 billion, including expenditure measures of &euro;4.2 billion, taxation measures of &euro;500 million and revenue-raising measures of &euro;230 million.  I also welcome the contingency fund of &euro;4 billion that has been created.  We are not out of this crisis yet.  Sometimes we think we are because of the way we are going but we are not quite there.</p> <p>On personal taxation measures, I welcome the income tax deduction of 30% of the cost of vouched expenses for heat, electricity and broadband incurred while working from home.  As the Minister of State pointed out, the budget includes &euro;520 million in income tax packages, increasing the band rate by &euro;1,500 and increasing the personal tax credit, employee tax credit and earned tax credit by &euro;50.</p> <p>It is an objective of this Government to tackle, once and for all, this housing crisis.  Financial measures relating to housing include the extension of the help-to-buy scheme for another year and the introduction of the zoned land tax.  The Minister of State will be aware of the vacant site levy and how it really has not worked as it was implemented differently across the different local authorities.  While I welcome this measure, there is a huge amount of work to be done to work out exactly how this is going to work, how transparent it will be and how each local authority will apply it.  If it is to be implemented it has to be done universally across the board.  That has not worked with the vacant site levy.  On the extension of pre-letting expenses for landlords, while people criticise supporting landlords, they are a critical part of the housing solution.  We have seen landlords vacate the housing market and we need to keep them in it so I welcome that.</p> <p>I refer to the specific business supports.  The employment wage subsidy scheme has been the lifeblood of the survival of many businesses across this country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pat Casey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2431"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2431&amp;amp;pid=PatCasey&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I thank the Government for those supports.  While I also welcome today's news that the supports will be in place in some form until the end of April next year, I will make an observation to the Minister of State, which he might relay to the Minister.  Applications for supports will close from January of next year.  The Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Michael McGrath, mentioned today that 115,000 people have been displaced to a different sector.  One sector that has been most affected by the hollowing out of staff has been the hospitality sector.  To bring in this measure in January, when we will be at our lowest employment levels and when we are trying to build our employment up for the season, will have severe implications for the industry.  I ask the Minister of State to see if can he do anything about that.  Finally, while I welcome the extension of the VAT rate to the end of August 2022, equally, the Minister should look at that over the next nine months to see if there a way that we can extend that VAT rate further because I do not believe the hospitality sector will be anywhere close to the position it was in in 2019, before Covid-19 hit.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1675" speakername="David Norris" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#W00300"><p>First, in the Minister of State&rsquo;s speech, he refers to changes in the vehicle registration system introduced to help reduce road transport emissions.  That will not work.  He needs to put the tax on petrol, on the basis that the polluter pays.  This is the only way that it will work.  I had this out with Ministers before and they agreed but they said it would be politically unpopular.  I believe the Government needs to take unpopular choices.</p><p>I want to raise the question of children and books in school.  We have a history here.  Until 2008, primary schools received funding to stock libraries with new books to help students to learn and develop and to support their well-being.  That was an excellent idea.  It was forward looking.  This grant, however, was cut in 2008 and has never been restored.  I ask that the Minister restore this grant.  Allocating just &euro;10 to every primary school child in the country to help schools buy books for the libraries would mean a budget 2022 allocation of only &euro;5.68 million.  That would be well worth it as an investment into our future.  We are always told people come to Ireland because of our well-educated young people.  While that is true, we need to continue to help support them. </p><p>I received a good briefing, as usual, from Fr. Se&aacute;n Healy and Social Justice Ireland.  As a preface to this, I notice that flats are being bought up <i>en masse </i>by hedge funds, which is dreadful.  I see the Government has moved to stop them doing this in respect of houses but that must be extended to take account of flats as well, as an increasing number of people in this country live in flats.  </p><p>I will raise what I might describe as a slightly sectarian matter, namely, the question of the Church of Ireland school, Ballinlough National School, County Roscommon.  As I am a member of the Church of Ireland, I acknowledge special pleading here.  However, it is important that we look after our minorities, particularly in light of the Covid-19 pandemic.  They are looking for a retention number of eight pupils, thereby allowing minority-ethos schools to hold onto their second teacher.  As this was the retention number for many years prior to the 2008 recession, I ask for this to be continued.  </p><p>As for the Irish Cancer Society - again I have some special interest here because I am a survivor of cancer and have had cancer three times - I wish to pay tribute to St. Vincent's Private Hospital and the superb work of Mr. David Quinlan and his staff there.  Without them, I am not sure I would be alive today.  I ask the Government to provide &euro;45 million in new funding for cancer services, on top of supporting improvements for the wider healthcare system.  Unfortunately, all of us actually are going to die.  That is one of two facts of life.  One is taxes and the other is death.  I am asking for supports for people to die well at home.  That would cost a mere &euro;500,000.  That is cheap.  Funding improvements in the delivery of person-centred pilots of end-of-life and bereavement care in residential settings would cost &euro;1.5 million.  Investment in bereavement community support would cost &euro;250,000.  Supports for people to plan for their end-of-life care would cost &euro;150,000.  Again, this money would be well spent. </p><p>I want to ask for an increase in basic social welfare payments, especially those that help support people with disabilities to live independently.  People with disabilities face particular difficulties, especially in time of pandemic.  I am 77 years old and I never remember anything remotely like this Covid-19 pandemic.  It really is an emergency.  I ask for a focus on unemployment issues for people with disabilities, including improving supports on the wage subsidy scheme.  I also believe that tax reliefs should be fully extended to counselling and psychotherapy as a qualifying health expense.  People's mental well-being is an important aspect.</p><p>I have received a submission from Tr&oacute;caire, which I believe is a fine organisation.  In 2021, one in 33 people worldwide will need humanitarian assistance.  Despite the fact that around the world, more than enough food is produced to feed the entire global population, 9.9% of people worldwide are going hungry.  Some 82.4 million people fled wars, violence, persecution and so on.  It is estimated that due to the Covid-19 pandemic, the time that it will take for the gender gap to close grew by 36 years in the span of just 12 months.  The estimated trajectory is now 135 years.  I point out this has the approval of the Irish people, in that 77% of those surveyed by D&oacute;chas in January and February 2021 felt that it was important for the Irish Government to provide overseas aid and 81% - a huge majority of those surveyed - indicated that they feel that Covid-19 has reinforced the need for international co-operation in addressing global problems.  Tr&oacute;caire continues by urging the Government to outline a pathway to reach the historic UN target of spending more 0.7% of gross national income, GNI, on overseas aid.  This is something that has been going on for years, as has the situation of women.</p><p>I received an amusing submission in this regard or the title was amusing at least, &ldquo;We are not sitting in our corner knitting&rdquo;.  This came from women who wrote to me.  They say that as women have greater unpaid care responsibilities and are more likely to be in low-paid, part-time, or carer work, it is more difficult for women to qualify for the full pension.  On average, women have 29% less pension income than men.  Women account for only 33% of those in receipt of a full State contributory pension, even though women outnumber men among the over-65s.  Only 28% of women of pension age have an occupational or private pension, compared with 55% with men. </p><p>Finally I ask for some special consideration to given to artists, particularly those in the entertainment industry.  I seek an increase in the allocation to the independent live entertainment industry from &euro;50 million in budget 2021 to &euro;75 million.  I also seek the implementation of the pilot universal basic income for artists and the creation of a pilot scheme for artists with disabilities.  Once again we come back to the question of disabilities.  </p><p>I am grateful to the Minister of State for listening to everything I have to say.  I realise that in these difficult times, not everything can be granted but I ask him to look with particular favour at the issues I have raised.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#W00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House on this historic day.  The Government has a proven track record in managing the economy and helping Ireland to recover from the economic crash.  We were beginning to recover back in 2011.  Then, when the pandemic struck in 2020, because our finances were in such good stead, the Government was able to bring in exceptional measures such as the pandemic unemployment payment, PUP, and wage support schemes.  Many lives were lost and many livelihoods were destroyed by the pandemic.  The Government has provided supports amounting to over &euro;48 billion for over three years.  I welcome that there are now approximately 100,000 people in receipt of the PUP, which is a reduction from a figure of more than 500,000 people.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I pay tribute to the Government for putting in place supports for businesses.  People are going back to work and employment.  Some &euro;17.5 billion was paid through the pandemic unemployment scheme, the employment wage subsidy scheme, and supports to individual families and businesses.  I thank the Minister of State and the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, for keeping in sight the three "Rs" for our public finances, namely, recovery, restoration and repair.  This gives us a clear and concise plan for pathways to the future.</p><p>Quality of life issues and rising costs have been considered in the budget.  It will invest in our future while meeting the needs of today.  Our domestic economy seems to be recovering ahead of schedule and consumer spending is growing.  There is a strong increase in spending but also rising costs, with price inflation expected to reach 3.7% in September, the highest rate since 2008.  There are many challenges such as labour and material shortages, as well as rising energy prices, combined with Brexit.  The unemployment rate is expected to fall to about 6.5% next year but this is still higher than prior to the pandemic in 2020, when it was about 5%.  It is forecast that 400,000 more jobs will become available by the end of next year, which is most welcome.  This will bring us back on track to reach our target.</p><p>The budget strikes a balance between the tapering of supports and investment in the domestic economy.  Core current expenditure will grow by 4.6% in line with our economy.  By 2022, it is expected we will only be borrowing for capital spending, which is to be welcomed.  We have to remember that the pandemic is still with us.  Senator Casey referred to what many hospitality businesses are going through.  Having listened to many of them, I agree with the Senator that they will not be at a respectable level of activity by April or August of next year.  I implore the Minister of State and the Ministers, Deputies Donohoe and McGrath, to revisit and review this matter.  The incentives put in place by the Government have kept many businesses afloat and many employees in employment.  I welcome the reduced VAT rate of 9% for the hospitality sector.</p><p>I know that Sinn F&eacute;in is proposing &euro;1 billion of taxes on high-income earners, including employer PRSI for all workers.  This would be a direct tax on jobs.</p><p>I welcome that &euro;126 million has been available for the aviation sector.  I am from the mid-west.  Shannon Airport is core to the region and I welcome that it will now come under the regional airport support scheme.  It was announced today that an aviation company has been taken over by another company, leaving 180 people in fear of what will happen to their jobs.</p><p>The budget provides for a tax allowance for 30% of the costs for remote working, a &euro;1,500 increase in the standard rate tax band and a &euro;50 increase in tax credits.  These changes will benefit all who pay income tax.  The cost of living is increasing.  The minimum wage is being increased by 30 cent early next year.  The universal social charge will change.</p><p>Housing is important to all of us.  The Housing for All strategy, which was great, was launched a couple of weeks ago.  Many Opposition Members have said the Government is not reaching its targets.  Some 89,000 social houses have been built since 2016.  That is not to be laughed at.  Some 33,000 houses per year will be delivered under Housing for All.  I welcome that the help-to-buy scheme will be extended because this has been a successful initiative to date.</p><p>We have to listen to and think of future generations when considering climate change, which is why a carbon tax is so important.  Studies have shown that carbon taxes are likely to be the single most efficient and effective climate change policy which can be pursued by government.  It is not the only one and it will not deliver the required emissions reductions on its own.  For this reason, money raised will be used and invested in targeted social welfare initiatives to help to prevent fuel poverty and ensure a just transition.</p><p>Additional revenue from carbon tax will also be invested in a progressive national retrofitting programme.  The Labour Party alternative budget refers to a retrofitting programme which would be limited to households with incomes of less than &euro;50,000.  Most couples living in a house would fall outside that threshold.  In addition, houses would have to have a building energy rating of less than B2.  This would exclude many couples from availing of retrofitting, as well as recipients of fuel allowance.  I believe the plan put forward by the Government is to be welcomed.</p><p>There is an extension of the tax relief on battery-powered electric vehicles because many people are waiting for cars to arrive due to the current shortage of microchips.  That is welcome.</p><p>There are reliefs for agriculture.  It is important to make farms more sustainable and support young farmers.  The stamp duty and general stock reliefs are welcome.</p><p>There is support for businesses, especially start-ups.  I had a Commencement matter debate with the Minister of State, Deputy English, on the wonderful work that local enterprise offices do.  They have been instrumental in many businesses starting.  This support is, therefore, welcome.</p><p>There is a 50 cents increase in the price of most tobacco products.  The number of cigarettes in a packet should not exceed 20.  We are playing into the hands of some tobacco companies, which are lowering prices.  We have to stamp out smoking.</p><p>Families are at the heart of budget 2022.  The &euro;23.3 billion social welfare package supports the most vulnerable in society, from our youngest to our ageing population.  That is most welcome.  I look forward to working with the Minister of State to deliver this budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#X00200"><p>It is nice to see the Minister of State.  I apologise in advance as I need to head to a meeting later but I will take note of his comments at the end.  I appreciate his understanding about that.</p> <p>In addressing this budget, I will start by saying that on television last night, RT&Eacute; quoted Government sources as saying this budget was quite socialist.  I smiled to myself and thought it was great because we would see taxes on the super-wealthy and the Government finally tackling the rental crisis and committing to capital expenditure on public housing.  Unfortunately, that Government source was mistaken, much to the relief of Senator Casey, no doubt, given his contribution earlier.  Let us start with the facts.  As the Minister of State will know, like many other Senators, I am passionate about housing.  This budget does nothing for renters.  I met some people in my village of Castleconnell yesterday who are paying rents of &euro;1,300 a month.  Once people heard that we were in the village, they came out just to talk to us about how desperate the housing crisis is and how much they are struggling.  The Government has done absolutely nothing for them in this budget.  It is a failure of the highest order.</p> <p>The talk of a zoned land tax is so disappointing.  We all know about the crisis with vacant sites and the need to get people to develop on those sites.  Rather than take action, what we have seen today from the Government is an action plan to delay and dither for at least another two years and to reduce the tax on vacant sites.  This plays to the heart of the ideological differences in this House.  I make no bones about that.  I am proud to be on the left.  This Government is firmly on the right.  Rather than tax vacant sites effectively and get them back into play, the Government is determined to avoid taxing them at any cost.</p> <p>We must also acknowledge that nothing was done in this budget to tackle the ridiculous tax breaks for vulture funds.  It is some contrast.  There are tax breaks for vulture funds, while working families face tax hikes to heat their homes.  It is an incredibly regressive tax.  A point I made to the Minister of State last year about the regressive nature of carbon taxes was that the fuel allowance just does not cover ordinary working people.  It is a narrowly focused allowance.  The budget has broadened it but it is only ever so slightly.  People working for the minimum wage still do not qualify for the fuel allowance.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What answers does the Minister of State have for working families throughout the country facing hikes to their fuel bills in addition to the already outrageous increases in energy prices this year?  His answer is to do nothing.  He had an opportunity to makes choices which we should consider for a moment.  Some argue that the Government cannot do everything and accuse others of being populist if they say that, as Senator Casey highlighted.  Let us get down to brass tacks.  The Government could have made different decisions, including scrapping the special assignee relief programme which is a real humdinger.  It is a tax break which helps multimillionaires avoid paying two thirds of their tax bill to the tune of &euro;1 million each.  Some 55 millionaires in 2018, for which is the last year we have figures, helped themselves to &euro;110,000 each of tax breaks and cost &euro;42 million.  On the one hand, there are people in poverty struggling desperately and the Government decided it could only give them a &euro;5 increase while on the on there hand, the Government believes there is no problem in keeping those multimillionaire tax breaks rolling in for the richest people in this State.  Another example is the gold plated pensions.  The Government could have raised &euro;183 million by cutting back on those gold plated pensions, which only benefit the super-rich in this country, but it chose not to.</p><p>Tonight, people face the news that they will get a &euro;5 rise in their unemployment payment.  Let us put that into perspective.  In 2009, the unemployment benefit was &euro;197 per week.  Following the Government's increase today it will increase to &euro;208.  Over the last 13 years of Fine Gael-Fianna F&aacute;il Governments we have seen a total increase of &euro;11 per week in unemployment benefit.  Why was this done?  It was done because the Government chose not to exact fairness in this budget, not to tackle the super rich and not to introduce a solidarity tax for which I make no apologies for suggesting.  Sinn F&eacute;in's solidarity tax would apply only to individual incomes of &euro;140,000 and above.  It would be a 3% tax which would be a moderate tax that would have shown solidarity and would have distributed funds to give us a more equitable and fair society.  However, it is clear this Government has no interest in that.  One of the real benefits of this budget - it is clear to all of us now - is that there is absolutely no pretence of any difference between Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael.  This is a sound conservative Government introducing conservative policy year after year at the expense of our people, and at the expense of the ongoing housing crisis and the entire failure to tackle the health crisis.</p><p>I met with the management of the University Hospital Limerick last Friday.  Yesterday morning, there were 87 people on trolleys and management knows the hospital is 200 beds short.  We need a massive investment in our health services but the Government has not made that choice today.  It made different choices for different classes of people.  "Class" is a word we do not use often enough in this Chamber.  I come from a working class family and am proud to represent working class people and ordinary workers who have nothing to gain from this budget.  The facts show that Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il consistently support the elite in this country.  That special assignee relief programme is shameful.  Funnily enough, I recall two years ago the then Minister of State, Michael D'Arcy, defend it passionately.  Whatever happened to him?</p><p>Childcare is another missed opportunity.  I want to be fair here and I welcome the fact that the Government has ring-fenced money for the joint labour committee that will be established.  That is a welcome initiative and I hope it will deliver some kind of justice for workers in the sector.  I credit my union, SIPTU, and the Big Start campaign in that regard.  It has campaigned vigorously for years on this issue.  The Government had the opportunity to make a real difference to working people.  Sinn F&eacute;in's budget outlined how the cost of childcare could be cut by one third this year and the next year.  What the Government has done is lock in the cost of childcare.  We know the average cost is &euro;750 per month.  That is like a second mortgage to many families.  This should be compared with anywhere else in Europe, where people in many countries typically pay less than &euro;100 per month.  We have not invested in childcare and the Government had the opportunity to do so.  It could have not given that ridiculous tax break, which only benefits two out of ten taxpayers, and instead ring-fenced the &euro;300 million to fix childcare and cut its cost for all working families, but it chose not to.  When one looks into the detail, this budget looks after those at the top and ignores those at the bottom.</p><p>How does the Government believe a &euro;5 increase in social welfare is, in any way, enough?  The Green Party Minister of State, Deputy Joe O'Brien, said to me at a sitting of the social protection committee that we need to see a significant shift in social welfare rates this year.  He did not receive that because, once again, the Tories in Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il triumphed at the expense of our people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#Y00200"><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Sean Fleming, is very welcome.  It is good to see him in the Chamber.  I should say <i>bienvenido al Ministro de Estado</i>because it is the national day of Spain and I did not get the opportunity to say it earlier.</p><p>In speaking about this budget, I will use factual data because much of what the previous speaker said was untrue.  On disposable income, for instance, this budget increases it by 0.85% with the lowest 20% of earners gaining the most.  It is factually untrue to say that people have been left behind when their disposable income has increased, with the poorest in society benefiting the most.  On carbon tax, we made it very clear in the programme for Government that funding was ring-fenced and this was done three ways.  First, for the poorest in society, we increased the fuel allowance last year in budget 2021 and we continued that this year.  We also ring-fenced funding in the carbon budget for those in social housing to ensure retrofitting could be carried out.  Third, we supported small farmers which is an obligation in the programme for Government and continued into this budget.</p><p>On childcare, the previous speaker would do well to remember the fact that there is a crisis for childcare workers which this budget deals with.  It is not enough to simply reduce all fees because who would pick up the tab for that?  It would be the people working in the industry.  We have to ensure that people's incomes are increased and that children have continuity of care because, at present, workers are leaving the childcare industry.  There has been a massive increase in the childcare budget this year and, not only that, but there will be a significant budget next year in childcare to deal with this issue, and this is welcome.</p><p>The zoned land levy was raised.  I understand how people on the outside might look at the old 7% versus the new 3% rate.  Let us be clear on this, last year the vacant sites levy generated &euro;21,000 from across the whole island.  If one considers the zoned land levy, a parcel of land worth &euro;1 million would generate a levy of &euro;30,000 per annum.  That amount is more than the entire island generated under the vacant sites levy.  Let us be honest and not pull the wool over people's eyes.  We know there are many people who have not paid the vacant sites levy which is the primary problem.  In the context of the zoned land levy, 50% of residential zoned land will be applicable which will generate a lot more money with which more can be done.  Anyone who cares about housing or generating funding should not focus on the 7% versus the 3% rate, but should instead look at it in real practical terms, which is what I do and what the Government must do.  It must be practical in finding money to bring about the changes it wants, and that is exactly what we are doing.</p><p>I will consider the detail of the budget and what the increases are.  In every Department there is an increase in core funding.  I have no problem with the Opposition seeking transparency, however, that transparency must be seen in reverse as well.  There is a 11.2% increase for the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications.  We have a 9.7% increase for the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media and a 7.8% increase for the Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pauline O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=PaulineOreilly&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The area for which I am my party's spokesperson, education, has received a 5.6% increase and at third level we have a 5.3% increase.  I could go on and on.</p><p>There is an 8.5% increase for housing.  The Housing for All strategy was announced a couple of weeks ago.  We have already discussed all its details.  We also know it is &euro;4 billion per annum, and that is what is in the budget.  Thus it is nonsense to say there is not enough in housing.  There is never going to be enough but this is the most funding we have seen since 2008.  That is actually what is in this budget.  Let us be honest with people.  Nobody deserves to have to worry unnecessarily that the Government is not doing its job regarding these Departments because we take it incredibly seriously.  That is why we stepped up to the mark.  It is very easy to point the finger but I would rather people pointed the finger with actual facts.</p><p>On climate action, I believe the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, mentioned earlier that the planet is on fire.  This is our number one priority.  This is why the Green Party went into government and this budget continues the work we did in the last budget.  Not only that, we now have the climate Act in place, so as far as I am concerned, this is act 2.  The climate Act is passed and act 2 is putting in place the measures we need in order to make everybody's lives better but also to make the future secure for our children and their children's children.  We have continued our &euro;360 million on active transport and we also have over &euro;1 billion for public transport.  We have, as I said, 11.2% on other measures in the area of environment, climate and communications.  Part of that is to roll out broadband and since we came into government we have decreased the length of time it is going to take for people across the country to get broadband.  We are now putting in place more funding for retrofitting.  The list could go on and on but my time is nearly up.</p><p>I wish to address in detail some of the measures in education.  We know difficulties have been faced with upskilling, probably across the globe.  We have passed the climate Act but how do we ensure that we have the workers in place for the new future and the green economy?  This means training people.  There is much that needs to happen in primary and secondary school in order to make it attractive for people to go into apprenticeships and other kinds of craft skills but this budget has record funding.  In fact there are 35,000 green skills places in this budget, along with numerous other initiatives related to apprenticeships and other green funding.  That is essential.  We need the workers but we also must create the opportunities for people right across the island.  Sometimes people hear of green opportunities and think it is just a cycle lane in a city.  It is not.  It is retrofitting, it is jobs, it is energy.  It is everywhere.  It is every single part of this country and that is what this budget is doing.</p><p>On education, because of the amount that actually went into the budget last year, I was a little worried we would not see increases this year but again I was stunned to see over 1,000 new SNA posts, 350 extra teaching posts, a further reduction from last year on class sizes of one pupil per class and record funding for DEIS schools to bring more and more children into them.  This is a budget for the most vulnerable in society.  People can pick one or two holes.  Obviously, I am always going to say we could have done this and ask why we could not do that, but I believe that overall this budget is a really good budget for every family, especially those most vulnerable.</p><p>My last point is the amount of measures that are in the budget regarding women's health.  I could go on and on about those.  In this Chamber, the Greens brought a motion on free contraception.  It is now being funded in this budget and I thank the Minister for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1672" speakername="Rebecca Moynihan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#Z00200"><p>I am really delighted to address the zoned land tax and what it actually is because it has been raised by the previous speaker and is important.</p> <p>From a housing perspective, this budget contains three measures.  It is a budget for landlords and landowners.  There is absolutely nothing in the budget for renters.  There is nothing in the budget for people who are on the housing assistance payment, HAP.  HAP limits have not changed since 2016 and in that time rents have gone up by 25%.  What is in the budget is a tax cut for land hoarders and no incentive for those who own empty homes to either sell or rent them.  There is no mention whatsoever of an empty home tax.</p> <p>I begin with the issue of the zoned land tax, which is effectively a tax reduction for landowners.  The criticism of the vacant site levy and its enforcement is valid.  With respect to what has been raised, the &euro;21,000 last year is a disgrace but local authorities have not been resourced to go after it.  There were arguments it should be going through Revenue, and that is happening.  There were many sites which should be on it.  There were too many get-out clauses, including, for example, landowners saying sites were being used for car-parking and were thus in use.  That should be taken out of it.  There were, as such, plenty of operational issues with the vacant site levy but it could have been reformed, given to Revenue and the site size abolished.  What this is doing is putting some lipstick on a pig and saying this is being changed but effectively bringing it down from 7% to 3%.  Senator Pauline O'Reilly says it is up to the Government to bring in the money and the levy was not bringing it in.  However, when I was listening to the Minister, Deputy O'Donohoe, he was saying it is not a revenue-raising measure; instead the idea is it is going to activate land.  The problem was that land was not being activated.  One does not cut tax to try to activate land management.  That was the problem and that was the issue with it.  This is just dressing up what is a tax cut for land hoarders and that is the headline issue that comes from it.</p> <p>We can also look at what is happening for renters.  Is there anything included for renters or for people on the HAP?  The answer is "No".  The one measure announced for the rental sector is that landlords are able to claim more expenses when they are turning it around, which is the equivalent of void funding.  I have no problem with that.  I do not want landlords feeling it is too expensive for them to do a property up in order to be able to rent it out.  I do have a problem when there are tax breaks for landlords and none for renters.  I have a problem in terms of the affordability.  Let us look at the root causes of the housing issue, which the Government keeps on saying is supply.  Indeed it is but supply is being hindered by the vested interests who at every single step frustrate the policy framework of getting us to affordable housing.  In Housing for All we saw the mention of 20% affordable housing.  I acknowledge we went from 20% to 10% of land value but we see a situation where we are now announcing it is going to be 10% social housing and an additional 10% affordable but that is not going to kick in.  We can look at things like the vacant homes tax, where in my own area build-to-rent institutional investors leaving homes empty in order to artificially keep rents high.  We see it in things like build-to-rent apartment standards which are not in line with apartment standards.  In the long term we will have people who will not be able to have balconies in such developments.  We see it with apartments being brought under the stamp duty rules at the time when there was outrage from first-time buyers about institutional investors buying properties instead.  What happened was the rules were put in place for people who lived in suburban areas and those who lived in dense cities were not included.</p> <p>The Labour Party would introduce a vacant homes tax.  We would increase a vacant site levy, or zoned land levy, or whatever one wishes to call it, to 10% and tackle the underlying issues of land speculation and hoarding.  That was a question of the operation of the tax, not the fact, amount, or rate of it to begin with.  The Government keeps on saying it is in favour of homeownership.  For some reason this seems to give them a get-out clause and ignores the need of renters, who are a growing cohort of people in this country.  There have been no changes to the HAP limit at a time of runaway rents when rates have increased by 25% during this time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rebecca Moynihan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RebeccaMoynihan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is the housing section of this budget and what it proposes does not give much flesh beyond Housing for All.</p><p>I will address the working from home tax breaks because it is a serious issue that we need to discuss.  We must not sleepwalk into essentially subsidising the private sector for its employees.  The proposal will lead to a massive transfer of expenses that employers would have incurred to the State, employees and taxpayers.  The costs of running an office have been shifted from the shoulders of employers to employees for the days that the latter are working at home.  The costs of infrastructure involved in that, such as adequate housing or access to a spare room from where to work, are being shifted onto the shoulders of workers.  That is fine for someone who has a spare room many people do not have a spare room.  Are we locking people from working-class backgrounds out of access to the professions because they cannot afford the infrastructure that would enable them to work remotely?  That is a serious issue that we need to think through before we sleepwalk into a revolution whereby employers get out of that.  My Labour Party colleague, Senator Marie Sherlock, published a working from home Bill which would have required employers to make daily payments in respect of utility costs rather than receive a State subsidy.</p><p>I spoke last week about an arts capital programme.  I welcome some of the measures in this area in the budget.  The Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, fought hard for the arts sector and arts groups.  However, I draw attention to a missed opportunity, namely, the absence from the budget of an arts capital programme.  Since 2015, there has been a crisis in working spaces for artists in Dublin city.  We are seeing studio space after studio space for artists close down.  The first was Broadstone Studios on the north side, which estimated it had paid &euro;1 million in rent to its landlord.  Now, in my area of Dublin 8, Pallas Studios will have to close down.  The Arts Council gives artists money to pay for rent but they must keep moving on.  We need to take a serious look at long-term funding for arts infrastructure and provide loans to arts organisations to allow them to pay off a mortgage.  The failure to include something like that in the budget was a missed opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#AA00200"><p>In discussing the budget, I will look at more than the question of what and how much we are spending.  The problem is that we have missed the opportunity in this budget to spend better.  The fiscal rules have been suspended for years and we are allowed to do things for the long-term benefit of the State.  The balancing of the books is no longer a constraint because the fiscal rules have been suspended.  We are always told we cannot do certain things because we would have to create a special vehicle to do them and the State is not allowed to give much in terms of public investment.  Those restrictions did not apply, so this was the budget where we could have spent better on strengthening long-term public services and public supports.</p> <p>The budget should also have been used to spend better on gender and equality proofing.  Remember that.  Five years ago, we supposedly made the decision to gender and equality proof all budgets.  This used to get referenced but now seems to have vanished because I do not see evidence of gender and equality-proofing in this budget.</p> <p>We should also be spending in a way that will allow us to achieve our commitments such as implementation of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities and our international climate commitments, to name but two.</p> <p>The suspension of the EU fiscal compact rules was not only a response in terms of the emergency measures to deal with Covid but also a recognition that the constraints on public investment had left EU states in a situation where their social fabric was not as resilient and their public services were not as robust as they should have been facing into a crisis.  We talked about recovery, restoration and repair.  I worry that the language all seems to be about bringing back what we had before.  The challenge at European and international level is to create resilience, build and protect ourselves from the next crisis, have services and infrastructure that are better and reimagine.  This is the "better" in "build back better" and it seems to have been lost.</p> <p>On housing, we still see the routing of public money into private profit.  If we want to talk about the figures, we see it specifically in the &euro;1.37 billion for the delivery of 2,600 houses through leasing schemes.  That figure includes local property tax, and I wonder why this local revenue is being included in the national figures.  Despite what we have heard, leasing schemes are still at the centre of housing provision planning, even though we know that the plan for five more years of signing leases, with implications for perhaps 20 years, is a problem because it is doing out the next generation and giving a profit when, in fact, we could be creating a public asset.  Dermot Desmond has described this as investment funds "having a laugh".  The rationale given for leasing in the correspondence released this week was that it had to be off balance sheet.  That does not apply.  Leasing should be nowhere in this budget.</p> <p>Senator Moynihan spoke clearly about the land valuation tax.  The vacant site levy is a cut for land hoarders.  The levy was not being collected and it should be collected.  I would appreciate clarification from the Minister of State on what plans are in place to collect the &euro;21.5 million that is still owed.  This change in policy should not get that money out of the mix.  It still needs to be collected.</p> <p>The idea is that we will move from a 7% liability to a 3% liability.  If the Government will not impose a levy of 7% or 10% for all, as has been proposed, a 7% levy should be paid on strategic housing developments for which fast-track planning permission has been availed and which have not been commenced or built.  That is a failure to deliver not only on land with potential zoning for development but land which has received active planning permission and has not been delivered.  Where does this leave apartment buildings which have been built and are lying empty?  A vacant property tax has been called for.  There is a crisis with vacant properties.  Is this measure, a new rebranding and a slight dilution, another way of getting owners off the hook?  The capital flight arguments we usually hear when the Government is busily reducing the tax that we ask for do not apply in this case.  I do not see the rationale for a reduction rather than an increase in liability.</p> <p>People have said there is nothing in this budget for renters.  I would disagree to the extent that there is one thing, which is a big warning sign in terms of inflation.  We heard in the Minister for Finance's speech how inflation can spike and be driven by external factors.  There is a concern, if we end up with rent tied to inflation, that unusual spikes in inflation will be allowed to become an opportunity for landlords.</p> <p>It is extremely disappointing that the opportunity to address the shameful exemption from stamp duty liability for apartments was not taken.  That measure is the product of lobbying on what developers want.  In fact, the measure has been extended.  We heard this week that own-door apartments will somehow also be exempt from the stamp duty.  That is what is happening this week.  Yet again, we see more giveaways rather than the Government seizing this moment for the State to be the leader in this area.</p> <p>Let us be clear on the issue of tax avoidance and the 15% rate we are proudly boasting of having reduced.  The measures from the OECD will not address global tax inequity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They still will not address the issue of the carve-outs and the exemptions and the fact that the developing world is losing $100 billion to $200 billion every year in terms of tax breaks.  I commend Christian Aid and Oxfam on their detailed analysis of the OECD measures.  We are aware that those exemptions include research and development and the research and development knowledge box, which has so little information.</p><p>I will ask the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, one last thing as I conclude.  I will be speaking to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform about pensions.  Why we are still seeing the variable rate tax relief for private pensions?  Why have we not addressed the gender inequality bit?  In the modelling of households, given that lone-parent households comprise 20% of the households in the State, why are they not there in the sample families that we look at?</p><p>Lastly, I note that climate financing is entirely separate to overseas development aid, ODA.  It would be a disgrace and a shame if there is any attempt to reframe ODA as delivering on our climate financing obligations to the developing world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" speakername="Shane Cassells" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#BB00200"><p>I am delighted to address the Chamber this evening on budget 2022.   I thank the Minister of State for his work, along with his Department and his colleagues, the Ministers for Finance and for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputies Donohoe and Michael McGrath, for this budget.  I listened to both Ministers that afternoon and I recalled George W. Bush's famous quote on receipt of his first budget when he said, "It's clearly a budget.  It's got a lot of numbers in it."  The budget this afternoon clearly has a lot of numbers, some &euro;88 billion.  I thought about that and when, as a kid in the 1980s and the 1990s, my parents could never have imagined such an amount of money in public expenditure.  We should not forget that as the debate ranges here this evening, including those who want to bemoan it.</p> <p>Sometimes, the importance of budgets like today's can get lost in the swathe of huge figures and what those figures really mean for people and their lives and how it will impact them when they come home this evening and reflect on that.  The fact that there was not a screed of a protester at the gates here this afternoon is indicative that people know this budget provides stability.  It provides improvements in a range of key areas, including housing.  On the subject of housing, when they are talking in here, Members forget that 12,000 social homes will be provided next year.  The budget also provides for improvements in health, including real things such as dental care and GP care, which will make a difference in people's lives, and improvements in education and energy costs also. </p> <p>I will start on the issue of childcare.  Last year people were bemoaning its omission from the budget, and rightly so.  The sector gets plenty of plaudits from politicians of all hues, but I wonder if politicians really know what they are talking about when they address the topic.  My wife of 21 years has worked in this sector for all her life as the county childcare co-ordinator in Meath.  She holds a doctorate in this topic.  I am privy to better daily briefings than the Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, receives.</p> <p>The childcare sector and the particular issues involved are varied and many-layered.  When the Department of Children was created, and really strengthened under the stewardship of the late Brian Lenihan 20 years ago, the sector as a regulated entity was in its embryonic and formative stage.  People forget that 20 years ago there really was no childcare sector in the State.  We were grappling with seeing its establishment.  It coincided with a huge population surge, urbanisation and the demand for good, high-quality childcare.  A lot has been done in that 20 years but, critically, a lot was done badly in the formative times.  We looked primarily towards the private sector to provide this crucial education, which is the first rung in the education ladder.  There were flawed policies in the past when cash was thrown at parents rather than looking at the fundamentals of the actual system.  It must be remembered that we expect all childcare providers to implement government policy and HSE standards in these private settings, with staff working on a minimum wage.  I really welcome the intervention of the State today and look towards the payment of staff properly under the implementation of the joint labour committee report.  As the Minister, Deputy Michael McGrath, has said, this is a turning point in the approach towards the early years sector, with &euro;716 million in funding and &euro;78 million in additional core funding.</p> <p>Senator Gavan made a political charge that Fianna F&aacute;il only represents the elite of this country.  When we see the &euro;68 million in additional investment in higher education today and a total spend of &euro;3.7 billion, with &euro;35 million in new supports a new supports for students who need assistance to cover the costs to get to higher education, is this looking after the elite?  Consider the free GP care for six and seven-year-old children, who can always be at the doctors and need that assistance the most and whose parents had to fork out the &euro;60 fee.  Is that looking after the elite?  There are an extra 1,200 special needs assistant posts for the most vulnerable children in our society.  Is that looking after the elite?  There is provision for 800 extra garda&iacute;, to take the scum and the drug lords off the street in this country and to deal with antisocial behaviour.  Is that looking after the elite?  I think boys need to have a hard look at themselves and wonder who are the elite and who are the ordinary people.  The ordinary people were always looked after in Fianna F&aacute;il.  Those who will benefit from the widening of the tax bands and who will have extra money in their pocket are the ordinary people.  That is what this budget does.</p> <p>I want to touch on one technical point and I ask the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, to raise this with the Minister, Deputy Donohoe.  This afternoon, the Minister announced tax credit relief for the digital gaming sector at a rate of 32% of expenditure of up to &euro;25 million on the design, production and testing of games.  This sector deals primarily with games targeted at teenagers but the gambling industry has sought to rebrand itself under the gaming sector title.  Casino products and so on want to be branded as gaming.  When this tax credit relief is detailed in the Finance Bill I ask that the Minister of State and the Minister for Finance look at this in order that we do not allow a loophole for the companies that provide gaming casino platforms for online gambling.  I ask that they not be allowed to avail of a loophole that would provide tax relief for something that actually fuels addiction to gambling in the State.  The Minister, Deputy Michael McGrath, announced funding today for a gambling regulatory authority.  It would be a travesty if with the one hand we do that and with the other, we might provide assistance for those who want to get people addicted to gambling.  I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#BB00300"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome to the Chamber to discuss the budget today.  I thank the Minister of State and the Ministers, Deputies Donohoe and Michael McGrath, for their stewardship of our economy throughout the pandemic and for making sure that supports for families and businesses were put in place.</p> <p>I want to concentrate on the measures in the areas in the Department for which I am the spokesperson, which are the areas of arts, media, tourism and sport, rather than across the budget because Members have already spoken on those issues.</p> <p>Tourism has been devastated through the pandemic and it probably will take at least until 2024 to recover.  I welcome the business continuity supports of &euro;50 million, as well as the &euro;39 million for tourism promotion and product development to help the industry to recover and grow in a sustainable way.  I welcome the extension of the VAT rate in hospitality until August 2022, which was brought in previously.  I feel, however, that we need to extend this for longer.  This is a big mistake we have made here.  It was shown previously back in 2009 and 2010 that when we extended that low VAT rate for a number of years, it helped to reboot our economy and brought us up to a situation where we had nearly 300,000 working in tourism.  This is one thing we have missed in this budget.</p> <p>The projections for international tourism in 2022 are that Ireland will be down at least 30%.  This is based on advance bookings.  I welcome the aviation fund that will help to restore the connectivity from key markets, which is lacking at present and was highlighted by Members with the Minister of State, Deputy Naughton, just a few weeks ago.</p> <p>As for the bus and coach industry, bar I had missed it in the booklet, that industry is not capable of claiming back VAT on diesel for their vehicles.  This is the industry that will ferry the tourists around Ireland when they do come.  The reality is that the bus companies in Northern Ireland are capable of claiming that tax back but our bus companies are not and are at a distinct disadvantage with regard to tendering for work.  I ask that this measure be looked at again.</p> <p>On the arts, the decision to maintain the funding of &euro;130 million for the Arts Council is significant.  This will help to promote and develop Ireland's world-class artistic and creative strengths.  I recently met Mona Considine, the artistic director of the Backstage Theatre, and with a number of other people involved in the arts industry in Longford.  They highlighted to me - and I brought it to the floor in the Chamber - that this funding should be maintained.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MichealCarrigy&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They highlighted that, thanks to the funding, a significant amount of work took place during the pandemic, for example, workshops, in order to have material ready for the stage for when crowds were able to return to their venues.  They also highlighted the basic income guarantee scheme.  As such, I welcome the &euro;25 million that is being allocated towards that as well as the &euro;25 million in supports for the live entertainment industry.</p><p>Recently, Fine Gael made a submission to the Future of Media Commission.  One of our core proposals was the replacement of the television licence with a public services media charge, which would increase the funding available to the media industry by between &euro;50 million and &euro;70 million.  That funding would also be available to all regional newspapers, regional radio stations, community radio stations and so on instead of 93% of it just going to RT&Eacute;.  I welcome the funding that has been put in place for the establishment of the media commission, which has an important role to play, particularly in light of the online safety and media regulation Bill, which will be published in the coming months.</p><p>I am disappointed with the additional funding that has been allocated to sport.  There have already been applications totalling nearly &euro;200 million to the sports capital programme this year, yet it only has a &euro;40 million budget and the additional funding to be put in place will only be &euro;6.6 million.  A significant number of sporting clubs throughout the country will be disappointed and their projects will not be funded.  We are allocating millions of euro to Sport Ireland's high-performance units, yet we will not even be sending representatives from it to the boxing world championship.  This needs to be examined.</p><p>Overall, it is a good budget for everyone and I wished to highlight a number of its specifics, particularly those relating to the areas for which I am spokesperson.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#CC00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  It is incredible that, in budget 2022, we are discussing the spending of such large amounts of money across so many sectors when we are still coming out of the pandemic and recovering from what has been an extraordinarily difficult time for Ireland.  Given that there are other jurisdictions very close to ours that are looking at their budgets and proposing cuts to spending rather than additional spending, we can be proud of our country and Government for delivering a budget that provides for every citizen and will ease the burden in many ways, particularly the cost of living.</p> <p>I am pleased to see a budget that, for the first time ever, really seeks to tackle women's health.  For the first time, I saw a Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform get to his feet and discuss all of the spending that the health sector will provide for women's health initiatives across many areas.  I commend the Minister for Health, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, on securing the necessary funding for the free contraception scheme.  It was no easy task, but that scheme will be transformative for the country and assist many young girls and women in having full control and access to reproductive healthcare.  Providing free access to contraception was one of the key ancillary recommendations of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution.  Those in the 17 to 25 age cohort have been identified as the most vulnerable to not being able to afford the contraceptives that are most appropriate for them.  As such, this is a welcome initiative.</p> <p>In the women's health package, we will see the following: more obstetric consultants and funding for our national maternity strategy; additional funding supports for specialist menopause clinics in Dublin, Cork, Limerick and Galway; measures to tackle period poverty; the opening of six additional see and treat gynaecology clinics; the expansion of our endometriosis specialist service in Tallaght; and additional funding for our sexual health units across the country.  It is a remarkable budget in terms of what it will deliver, and is already delivering, for women's health and I am proud to be in a Government party that is doing that.  This is the first time in the State we have seen this level of investment - in excess of &euro;30 million - for women's health initiatives.</p> <p>I welcome the childcare package.  Many colleagues have mentioned it today and many more will do so over the coming days.  The more than &euro;700 million for the childcare sector is a substantial investment that will have a significant impact.  It is right and proper that these supports be targeted in the first instance towards childcare workers, who are considerably underpaid.  This will help to stabilise the sector so that we can, piece by piece, build the type of community childcare sector that we need and reduce the cost burden on families.</p> <p>The funding that is being allocated for young people is welcome.  Many times over the past year, we have spoken in the Chamber about the impact that the pandemic has had on young people and how they have suffered the most, and given up the most, in the past year and a half, which they did primarily to protect the most vulnerable and older people in society.  We have commended them for that, but it was important to reward them in this budget for their hard work.  It is commendable and significant to see half-price public transport for our young people aged 19 to 23 years.  I am sure that young people across the country are saying that they can for the first time see a budget that caters for them and not just older people, which is something that we have not seen for many years.  This is tangible and will make an impact in the daily lives of those travelling to socialise, to college, to work or to school.  There is also a &euro;200 increase in the Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, grant.  More importantly, accessing that grant will be made easier.  The threshold will be increased and many more families and students will be able to access it, thereby ensuring that every young person in this country can have access to third level if he or she so wishes.</p> <p>It is important to acknowledge the increase in the minimum wage, which predominantly affects younger people in lower paid jobs.  Following the past year and a half, we now more than ever realise the importance of those jobs in the service industry, retail and hospitality, where many young people start their working lives and many continue to make their careers.  It is important that the minimum wage was increased.</p> <p>While there are many aspects of the budget that I welcome and it has been a fair budget for everyone, the support for carers is particularly fantastic and welcome.  The carer's allowance will increase by &euro;5, the weekly earnings disregard will increase as well, and the capital disregard has gone from &euro;20,000 to &euro;50,000 in acknowledgement of the considerable work, sacrifice and service that carers across the country make in caring for their loved ones.  It is only right and proper that they be front and centre in budget 2022 and will be rewarded financially for the work they do on behalf of the State and for their loved ones.  There is no greater gift than to care for someone in his or her own home and to keep that person at home in the community, but carers need to be helped in doing that.</p> <p>I have touched on the few key aspects that I believe are ambitious and visionary and have shown the resilience necessary to deliver for many people as we come out of the pandemic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#CC00300"><p>I am proud of this budget and am delighted that it will tackle the cost of living for families, with a record &euro;716 million investment in childcare as well as the extension of a range of housing, health, education and welfare supports.</p> <p>Addressing the cost of childcare has been a top priority for Fine Gael.  The investment total of &euro;716 million in early years services includes a new &euro;69 million funding stream for childcare providers from next September that will ensure the sustainability of those services and attract others into the childcare sector.  That is a provision of &euro;200 million in a full year.  These moneys are planned to support the outcome of the joint labour committee under my party colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy English, who is working in conjunction with the Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, and establish minimum rates of pay and conditions for workers in the childcare sector.  These much-needed supports will help providers and their staff.  Some 4,700 employees across the country will benefit.  A condition placed on this investment is the cap on childcare fees, which will be of great help to parents.</p> <p>We will see the continuation of the EWSS until April 2022.  There will also be a one-off bridging scheme to span the period between April and September when the new scheme will kick off, costing &euro;5.5 million per month, to ensure that there is no cliff edge for childcare providers.  The national childcare strategy, NCS, universal subsidy is being extended to all under-15s from next September, bringing an additional 40,000 children into its provision.  I am delighted that the practice of deducting the hours spent in preschool and school from the entitlement to NCS subsidised hours will be stopped, thereby bringing 5,000 children from low-income families into the net.  This will address an anomaly that caused the risk of exclusion for children from disadvantaged communities, as was particularly highlighted in my home constituency of Dublin South-Central.</p> <p>The budget sees us build on the previous Fine Gael Government's initiative and continues the implementation of the universal early childhood care and education, ECCE, programme, which provides for more than 100,000 children for the two years before they begin primary school.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We see the continuation of AIM - access inclusion model - workers to support children in the ECCE programme who have special education needs.</p><p>Fine Gael is focused on assisting families with financial pressures through a range of measures targeted specifically at parents and children.  Along with childcare, housing remains an issue of concern for families with many looking to own their own home and provide security for their children.  I am thrilled that the help-to-buy scheme, which has already helped over 28,300 people previously locked out of the property market to own their first home, will be extended for another year.</p><p>A range of supports from the Department of Social Protection under the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, will also help families.  Parents will feel the benefit of budget 2022 and see an uplift as children return to school, with a &euro;10 increase in the back-to-school clothing and footwear allowance by June of next year.  The duration of parent&rsquo;s benefit, introduced under a Fine Gael-led Government in 2019, will increase.  Parents will receive an extra two weeks off as leave rises to seven weeks from July 2022.  The income threshold for the working family payment will also be increased by &euro;10 for all families.  Children aged six and seven will now also benefit from free GP care, with the intention of extending this to all children up to the age of 12.  The financial burden of hospital charges for children under 18 will also be reduced.  An additional 980 special education teachers will be hired, alongside an unprecedented 1,165 new special needs assistants, bringing the total number of SNAs in Ireland to a record 19,169.  This will bring investment in special education to the highest level in history. </p><p>This is a budget for parents and children.  It will help families with the high cost of living and, critically, it will tackle rising childcare costs which will come as a great relief to many families across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#DD00200"><p>For all the climate measures in the budget today, we are still completely in the dark about what it will achieve in terms of emissions reductions.  Renters in particular are no better off in terms of knowing how private rental accommodation will be retrofitted and how the split incentive can be addressed.</p> <p>It is disheartening to see the disconnect between today&rsquo;s fiscal budget and the carbon budget to be announced later this month.  Earlier this year, a report by the Irish Fiscal Advisory Council stated that our climate change targets need clear costings and revenue raising mechanisms.  I have no doubt the disconnect is because of the decision to accept last-minute amendments to the Climate Action and Low Carbon Development (Amendment) Bill in this House, which have delayed the carbon budget process.</p> <p>We also have no idea what the climate impact of the measures announced today will be.  We could do with taking a leaf out of the Scottish Government&rsquo;s book and assessing the carbon cost of all the measures in the budget.  Greater transparency around the emissions associated with Government measures would clarify the debate around getting a whole-of-government approach.  For example, if we had proper carbon assessments of the Fine Gael, Green Party data centre policy, it would become clear that it is costing billions in tax write-offs for such centres to set up here.  This comes at a huge cost, not only to the climate and environment but also to electricity bill payers through the PSO levy.</p> <p>As we know, fiscal policy is climate policy.  The budgetary process is so important in implementing change in terms of how we spend or do not spend and how we tax or forgo tax.  I hope the Government takes steps to integrate its fiscal budgets with its future carbon budgets.</p> <p>I will now focus on a few measures in the budget in the context of the climate and biodiversity crises.  We face a biodiversity crisis.  Indeed, we declared a biodiversity emergency just over a year ago but one would not know it from listening to the Ministers in the D&aacute;il today.  Biodiversity was not mentioned once by the Minister for Finance or the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  Worse, there was no additional allocation for the National Parks and Wildlife Service, NPWS, which is at the forefront of the biodiversity crisis.  Sinn F&eacute;in supports the NPWS being put on a statutory footing and would have increased its budget by &euro;5 million this year.  The lack of any reference to the biodiversity crisis does not bode well in terms of the urgency to establish a citizens' assembly on biodiversity.  We still have no date or funding allocation for it.  In fact, the Government recently admitted in response to a parliamentary question that it has not even agreed the terms of reference or the scope of such an assembly.  </p> <p>I welcome the Minister for Finance's expansion of the accelerated capital allowance scheme for energy efficient equipment to include machinery powered by renewable hydrogen.  Hydrogen undoubtedly has an important role to play in our energy system but we do not need a piecemeal approach to it.  We need a fully thought-out approach but unfortunately Ireland is one of only two EU member states that does not have a full strategy.  If we want investment in this sector, we must have a plan to encourage such investment.</p> <p>I also welcome the additional spending on animal welfare.  However, I wish the Government had gone further because this was a missed opportunity to make real change.  I am glad to say that Sinn F&eacute;in&rsquo;s alternative budget promised 20% more for animal welfare organisations, which are on their knees.  Only today there were further reports of shelters having to turn away animals due to a lack of capacity.</p> <p>We know politics is about choices.  The choices Governments make reveal their priorities and those priorities were laid bare today.  What does this budget do to tackle sky-high rents, unaffordable childcare or a health system bursting at the seams?  There was nothing in today's budget for renters; nothing at all.  There is no tax break or rent freeze.  Renters are forced to suck up the increased costs of energy while tax breaks for landlords are extended.</p> <p>Another clear example of the Government's priorities is in the changes made to the tax bands.  Moving the standard rate by &euro;1,500 costs the Exchequer &euro;312 million.  This tax break will only benefit 24% of workers yet it will more than double the estimated annual cost of returning the State pension age to 65.  It is clear where this Government&rsquo;s priorities lie.  It is time for a new Government that puts the interest of ordinary people first, a Government that is in touch with the cost of living crisis that we currently face, particularly those in the rental sector who have been left behind once again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#DD00300"><p>I will focus on some of the climate action measures in the budget, as I did last year.  Some weeks ago, I said in the House that I was worried by a report from the Department of Finance on plans to increase VRT, including on electric vehicles.  I am happy to see the Government realised the importance of extending the VRT relief for electric vehicles until the end of 2023.  At the time, I referred to Finland which has seen a massive uptake of electric vehicles in the space of three or four years thanks to various financial measures, including an eco-tax on diesel and petrol.  In Finland, it has reached the point where it is financially insane not to drive an electric vehicle.  The Finns have also invested huge sums in improving their electric vehicle charging network, which I would like to see addressed in next year's budget.  We already have a substantial network but we need a dedicated financial strategy to improve our charging systems, particularly in the major cities of Dublin, Cork and Galway.  If substantial funding is put into the charging network, it will make the shift to electric vehicles easier.</p> <p>Today's announcement on the retrofitting scheme is extremely impressive, with &euro;202 million provided to retrofit 20,000 homes over the next year.  In County Louth, &euro;2 million has been given to the local authority.  It has started retrofitting homes already and I have seen how well that is going.</p> <p>I also welcome the measures related to apprenticeships.  People do not need to go to college and we need to show them that an apprenticeship provides an equally good chance of a good career, salary and future.  That was not the belief for the last ten or 15 years in this country, for whatever reason, but I am pleased to see what we are doing with apprenticeships.  They will feed into the retrofit schemes in terms of the creation of green jobs.</p> <p>I also welcome the youth travel card initiative under which &euro;25 million has been provided for people between the ages of 17 and 25.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John McGahon:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=JohnMcGahon&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That, too, is an excellent initiative.  It is a progressive way of getting people onto public transport while saving them money.  I would love to see it extended at some stage in the future.</p><p>While we are on the issue of travel cards, it would be remiss of me not to mention the idea of introducing a three-day taxsaver ticket for commuters.  As the Minister of State will be aware, as a result of 1997 legislation, taxsaver tickets must be provided on a monthly or annual basis.  Last week, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, clarified the issue when he stated a legislative change was not necessary and we could introduce a 100-day taxsaver ticket or similar.  I would appreciate if the Minister of State and the officials conveyed to the NTA the message that legislative change is not necessary and, consequently, there should be no delay in introducing a simple ticket that will save commuters money.  We have known for some time that these tickets are required.</p><p>On green hydrogen, it is important that hydrogen features in the budget and that the Government recognises it.  A hydrogen strategy is necessary and I hope one will be published in the climate action plan, which is due to be published imminently by the Government.</p><p>Considering the points I have made, this budget, as with all budgets in the past few years, has been very progressive.  A huge amount of money has gone into it but it is being spent well in a smart and strategic way.  We can see that in the area of climate action.  The Ministers, Deputies Donohoe and Michael McGrath, and their officials should be commended on the work they have done.  It is important to have so many green initiatives with so much funding in the budget.  More than &euro;360 million has been provided for active travel and greenways.  So much funding in this budget is aimed at getting people out of their cars and into active travel modes such as cycling.  Safe access to schools is also important.  If we are to make any headway with tackling the climate crisis, it must be done in a financially viable way that is financially accessible to people from every sector of society.  We will ensure people are able to do that by investing in addressing the climate crisis in the budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#EE00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I will comment on the finance side of the Budget Statement, which was made by the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe.  We have come through a severe pandemic.  Thankfully, owing to the solid foundations put in place over the last decade, including balancing the books at the end of 2019, the nation had the resources to cope.  We restored our good name and reputation which meant we could afford to borrow the money required to invest and support businesses throughout the country.</p> <p>I acknowledge the supports provided for workers in the budget through the increase in the standard rate band of &euro;1,500 and increases in the personal tax credit, employee tax credit and earned income tax credit of &euro;50.  Cutting the rate of tax might get bigger headlines but increasing the bands is also important.  If we stand still and do not change the bands, everyone eventually ends up paying the higher rate of tax.  It is important that they keep pace with income.  I welcome the 30 cent increase in the minimum wage, bringing it to &euro;10.50 per hour, and the associated increase in the USC band.  We do not want people who benefit from the increase in the minimum wage losing out by paying additional USC.  I also welcome the tax deduction for working from home, which amounts to 30% of the cost of vouched expenses for heat, electricity and broadband.  Covid, by necessity, has increased the popularity of remote working and working from home.  There are many positives from that but the costs were a concern raised by many people.  Thankfully, the budget has responded to that concern in providing a 30% flat rate for these costs.</p> <p>I welcome the support for businesses on the tax side, including tax credits for the digital gaming sector.  In my area of Galway we have seen growth in this area recently.  The budget also provides relief from corporation tax for start-up companies under section 486C and additional funding for the innovation equity fund.  The employment wage subsidy scheme, which has been extremely important and has done a great deal to protect jobs and companies, is to be extended to April 2022.</p> <p>Foreign direct investment is very important in many parts of the country, including Galway.  Recent discussions about changes in corporation tax caused concern.  I compliment the Minister for Finance and his team in the Department on agreeing to the recent deal and also on taking a strong stance and achieving the best deal for Ireland by ensuring a minimum corporation tax rate of just 15%.  They also ensured many companies here will continue to pay the 12.5% rate because their revenues are less than &euro;750 million.  This is a very important issue for the country.  These companies have done much for the tax take and employment up and down the country.  It is important, therefore, that we got the best deal for Ireland.  I compliment the Minister on that achievement.  That goes for the team at the Department of Finance, including the Minister of State, Deputy Sean Fleming.</p> <p>I welcome the extension of the help-to-buy scheme to the end of 2022.  The zoned land tax is, as the Minister highlighted, not a revenue-raising initiative but one to boost the supply of houses.  That is important because there is always a strong focus on the demand side initiatives on housing, whereas it is the supply side that needs to be boosted.  There are many examples of people sitting on serviced zoned land.  If this initiative helps to kick-start moves by some of them to advance to the planning and construction stage soon, that will be a welcome boost to supply.</p> <p>Those are some of the issues on the finance side of the budget as we recover from the pandemic, restore our public services and living standards and repair our public finances.  I thank the Minister of State for his work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#EE00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it go dt&iacute; an Teach.  Doing a national budget is very difficult, especially coming out of a Covid pandemic.  Despite all we have been through, I feel positive and hopeful about this budget.  That is what people need to hear at this time. Is maith an t-iom&aacute;na&iacute; an fear ar an gcla&iacute;.  The hurler on the ditch has the easy job but we were busy playing senior hurling when we were working very hard on this budget.  I commend everyone involved, including civil servants, NGOs that made submissions, voluntary organisations, the Minister and all his staff.</p> <p>There are lots of problems in lots of sectors and in this budget the Government is trying its best to deal with many of those issues.  Senator Boylan remarked that there is a biodiversity emergency.  She obviously did not realise what job the National Parks and Wildlife Service does given that its budget was increased by two thirds from last year.  Maybe she does not know because she lives in a nice house in Dublin but where I live the whole job of the NPWS is biodiversity protection.  Maybe the Senator will look up what the service's job is and be happy about what the Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, did on that.  There was a lot in this budget for biodiversity.  That is just a point of information for the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#EE00400"><p>On a point of information, I used to work for the NPWS.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#EE00500"><p>I am the Green Party spokesperson on enterprise, trade and employment.  We did much work on submissions around helping the SME sector go green because that is the way we must now move forward.  There will be &euro;10 million in the climate transition fund to help businesses to decarbonise.  I made a submission to the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment on this.  It was good to see we can work together in coalition.</p> <p>There was also &euro;5 million for regional enterprise development fund to help encourage small businesses.  They are the backbone of the economy where I live as we do not have any big businesses in north County Clare.  We have a few in Shannon but most of the jobs in Ireland are in small businesses.  It is good, therefore, to see that sector getting serious funding in the budget.</p> <p>As the mother of a 22-year-old who got into college through the Access programme, it is good to see the Access programme getting more support and the SUSI grant being increased.  The number of students who will now be eligible has also been increased.  These measures make third level education more accessible to all.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RoisinGarvey&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The significant supports for apprenticeships is extremely important.  Apprenticeships are rated up there in importance with the achievement of six A1s and qualifying for medicine because we need those who complete apprenticeships to retrofit this country.  It is great to see them validated.</p><p>On rural transport, there are wins in the budget for LocalLink and safer routes to school.  Even in the case of rural schools children deserve to be able to walk or cycle to school safely or at least cross the road safely.  There are also wins for greenways, which are not only good tourist attractions but they link people and communities who, otherwise, might not meet each other.  I have seen that in Mayo and Waterford.  You meet old people on them and they get to meet their neighbours and friends again and people from all over the world.  It is good that the development of greenways is not only considered a Green Party policy but they provides social and mental health benefits which are empowering.</p><p>It is important to recognise the great supports the Minister, Deputy O&rsquo;Gorman, secured for childcare provision, for young people and for those supporting young families.  Childcare provision has long been an issue for this State.  Finally, there will be serious investment in this sector, which recognises the importance of investing in our youngest in society - not only those at third level - and the people who give of their time to care for them.</p><p>The budget provides for a &euro;90 million innovation equity fund, which will invest in early stage companies for potential growth to scale.  That is also welcome.  </p><p>The provision of free contraception for girls aged 17 to 24 is welcome.  I would like that provision to be followed up with free contraception for boys, so they can share the responsibility for contraception.</p><p>The provision of 60 new posts for community workers under the social inclusion and community activation programme, SICAP, is extremely welcome.  Community development workers operating through local development companies do amazing work all over Ireland.  It is great to see that improvement coming through the offices of the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, and the Minister of State, Deputy O'Brien.</p><p>The allocation of &euro;60 for a low cost retrofit loan scheme is vital.  The carbon tax yield has been ring-fenced to retrofit the social housing stock, which is great for the people who are in social housing.  We also have the squeezed middle, for want of a better term.  They will be able to get low cost loans to retrofit their homes.</p><p>This budget is helping us all move towards the future we want to see for ourselves, our children and our grandchildren.  It is important we bring a message of hope to people today.  We cannot get everything right in one budget.  It is easy to throw mud at it from across the room.  A great deal of work has gone into this budget.  There are many positive wins in it for people in every sector of society.  We are trying to do our best here.  They must be acknowledged today by everybody.  You will never get it all right and no one is perfect, but this is a good budget and something we should celebrate. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#FF00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and wish him well with the budget.  I have seen many budgets come through this House.  This is a very fair budget.  The Minister of State will be well aware that even in the boom years no matter how much money was available it was not enough.  That is the reality.  I have seen budgets coming through this House and the budgetary spending provided was never enough for people.  In this budget with its package of measures covering personal taxation, the minimum wage, health services, infrastructure, climate action, social welfare and small businesses, there is something in it everybody.  It is a very balanced budget and very fair to many people.  It will help many people, particularly the less well off.</p> <p>Those in the small business sector have gone through a very difficult time during the past year and a half.  The incentives for those in that sector are to be welcomed.  After all, they are the risk-takers in this country and risk-takers should rewarded.  Whether you are starting up or in a small business, you need certain supports.  Those in this sector go through very difficult periods.  It is not plain sailing to be in business.  Those in the sector are always worried about whether the business will survive, there are difficulties in employing staff and they have to plan ahead.  Those are all difficult decisions that must be made by the business person.  I am delighted there are some small rewards in the budget to help small businesses because they are the backbone of this country.</p> <p>I am delighted the deficit, which is forecasted to be &euro;13.2 billion, or 3% of GDP, this year, will be reduced next year to &euro;8.3 billion, or 1.8% of GDP.  I am delighted the Government recognised this must be provided by way of tax measures.  We cannot have a runaway train.  We cannot have money for everything and that is why decisions have to be made.  Some people in these Houses would provide money for everything and not factor in that the finances must be structured and certain proposals must be put in place.</p> <p>The help-to-buy scheme and the employment wage subsidy scheme will be extended to 2022.  That will be welcomed by people who are trying to buy a house, particularly first-time buyers.  Those employing people will also welcome that the wage subsidy scheme will be extended into 2022.</p> <p>The tax on vacant sites is a big issue whether it be on vacant or greenfield sites.  The Minister of State will know in some towns, particularly provincial towns, there are quite a number of listed buildings.  There are quite a number in Dublin's inner city.  Substantial funds would be needed to restore those buildings.  It is not viable for any developer to do that.  If local authorities acquire those buildings, the taxpayer would be saddled with the task of funding the cost of restoring those buildings, be it for accommodation or commercial purposes.  I suggest a special low interest rate should be provided for works to listed buildings.  They are in every town throughout the country and quite a number of them are in the capital and they are all derelict.  It is not viable for any developer or builder to progress work on them, develop them or whatever.  Do we want the taxpayer to be saddled with the cost of putting them back into use, be it for commercial or residential purposes?  A very low interest rate should be provided for such works.  The Government can borrow funding at very low interest rates.  If a very low interest rate was offered it would be possible to incentivise the owners or developers to proceed with such works.  I welcome the budget.  Did the Acting Chairman ring the bell?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#FF00300"><p>I did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#FF00400"><p>It was very lightly struck.  I wish the Minister of State well with the budget.  I hope he will take on board the latter point I made.  It should be taken on board because those derelict listed buildings are eyesores throughout the length and breadth of the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#FF00500"><p>I support the Government's 2022 budget of &euro;87.5 billion in spending announced by Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe.  All the steps the Government took to protect people's lives and income through the pandemic unemployment pay and the temporary wage subsidy scheme have now proven to be effective in saving jobs.  Close to 0.5 million people were in receipt of the pandemic unemployment payment and 100,000 are in receipt of it this week.  There is a clear commitment to extend the employment wage subsidy scheme until April 2022..  The Government has committed to a balanced budget to restore public finances, only borrowing for capital expenditure.  Under a Fine Gael Government we went into this pandemic with a &euro;2 billion surplus due to prudent spending.</p> <p>As spokesperson on further and higher education, research, innovation and science, I am heartened by the supports for students.  The Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, grant will be increased by &euro;200.  The qualifying distance for the student grant will be reduced from 40 km to 30 km.  That is crucial in the regional area I come from in east Galway and Roscommon, where people have to travel a distance to get to college, people of all ages who are studying.  There will be 3,320 extra CAO places to accommodate the extra demand with the points system.  That is vital for universities.  We have a clear policy and a strategy on future funding.  We also have our new technological universities, including the Technological University of the Shannon: Midlands and Midwest in Athlone and Limerick and the Connacht-Ulster Alliance, comprising Galway-Mayo Institute of Technology, GMIT, Institute of Technology Sligo, ITS, and Letterkenny Institute of Technology, LIT.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aisling Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AislingDolan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are a wide range of opportunities apart from the traditional routes to college.  People can also earn and learn.  Another way to get into college and acquire a qualification, including a degree or PhD, is through an apprentice.  There is also a focus on skills development and Skillnet has been extended to include a scheme called Skills to Advance.<br/><br/>I am an advocate within Fine Gael of increasing expenditure on research and development as a percentage of GDP and supporting research as a way of meeting the challenges ahead as we move out of the pandemic.  Research has been integral to us surviving this virus.  It was researchers who developed vaccines and accelerated clinical trials at a rate that had never been done before.  The speed of progress in the past 18 months has been incredible in scientific terms.  We now know how important it is to support researchers in the arts, science, engineering and medicine.  That is how we have embedded multinationals in Ireland.  Research is more important than ever, considering developments with corporation tax.<br/><br/>Science Foundation Ireland is doing roadshows around the country.  Research is no longer done behind the high walls of colleges; it is in communities.  Science Foundation Ireland is rolling out a roadshow that will visit every county in Ireland between now and 25 October.  It will be in Ballinasloe, County Galway, on 22 October.  Members of the public will be able to have a chat with researchers and tell them what research they want us to invest in for the future.<br/><br/>Our researchers in laboratories at third level are also developing solutions.  I am delighted that funding was allocated in the budget to the disruptive technologies innovation fund, DTIF.  A total of 29 projects were successful under the fund this year.  The projects will share &euro;95 million over the next three years.  The funding was announced by the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Leo Varadkar, the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Simon Harris, and the Minister of State at the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment, Deputy Robert Troy.  The areas covered are<b></b>life sciences, medtech, ICT, artificial intelligence, manufacturing and environmental sustainability.  All of the projects involve collaborations between three and eight partners and include small and medium enterprises, multinational companies and research organisations.  It is incredible that there are 62 SMEs among the 111 organisations involved.  These are Irish companies participating in world-class research.  This will link universities with healthcare and small and medium enterprises.  Projects include research on a regenerative treatment for knee osteoarthritis using hydrogel-based therapeutics and to develop an adhesive that will stick broken bones together following a fracture.  These are technologies and healthcare that will change our lives.<br/><br/>A sum of &euro;30 million has been allocated to the innovation equity fund through Enterprise Ireland.  This has been done through the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund.  The allocation will be combined with a previous commitment of &euro;30 million and the European Investment Fund will match the funding.  Therefore, &euro;90 million will be allocated to seed stage Irish SMEs.  These projects come out of campus spin-outs.  How do they get the investment to go ahead?  They are high risk and are at a stage where development is necessary.  This funding of &euro;90 million is crucial in this regard.  The Government has said it will support Irish start-ups and campus start-ups, and I back that.<br/><br/>The fund will promote regional development and build on the links with technological universities in every region.  It will support female entrepreneurship and climate action.  All of this is timely in the west because we can see in Galway the innovation triangle of top global medtech companies working with the National University of Ireland Galway, companies and the Saolta University Health Care Group.<br/><br/>Remote working is crucial for Counties Roscommon and Galway.  We need to keep people working and living in towns and villages as they will support local shops by shopping locally, especially if they use the connected hubs that are being built around the country.  We must develop communities centres and there is a grant that will help fund them.  Funding for LEADER programmes, rural regeneration and grants for community centres have also been increased.<br/><br/>Sinn F&eacute;in Senators commented on taxes and housing.  Sinn F&eacute;in's alternative budgets do not stand up.  How can Sinn F&eacute;in Senators come in here and tackle us on a budget that will deliver for so many people in communities?  All I can say is that the housing budget in 2022 will be over &euro;3.7 billion, which is the largest budget that has ever been allocated to housing.  A moratorium was put in place for renters this year and legislation will come through for renters this year.  As a renter and somebody who hails from a small farm in the west, I am delighted to say that Fine Gael represents every town, village and county in this country.  I am very proud to be part of Fine Gael.  It is not a party for people who come up with budgets that cannot withstand scrutiny.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#GG00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Seanad.  The Chamber is full of representatives of the Government but there are no Opposition Senators present.  If there is anything telling about today's announcement by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Michael McGrath, and the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, it is that no Opposition Senator has been here since before I arrived to make a contribution.  Budget day is the most significant day of the year, yet I have a choice of all of the seats on the Opposition side.  That is telling in terms of the response to today's announcements.</p> <p>The budget is welcome.  I am sure people will recognise that the budget supports families, communities and businesses and recognises the challenges we have faced over the last 18 months.  We could talk about many issues but I will focus on a couple of significant announcements made today.  As someone who hails from Tipperary, I welcome the announcement of extra funding for law and order and the Department of Justice.  Next year, there will be 800 new garda&iacute; which will increase Garda strength to 14,600.  The programme for Government committed to having a Garda force of 15,000 by the end of the Government's term.  The extra 800 garda&iacute; will mean we will be close to hitting that target by the end of 2022, which is significant.</p> <p>I welcome the continuation of the first-time buyer's grant.  The scheme has benefited people throughout this country.  Many people in Tipperary, including friends of mine, have benefited from the first-time buyer's grant to build their own homes.  I do not understand how some parties in this House do not see the benefit of giving people the opportunity to build or buy their own homes.  Certain parties talk about giving a month's rent to somebody.  The Government is trying to get people a house to own, not one month's rent.  We want to give people the opportunity to buy and build their own home and live in rural Ireland if they so choose.  That is the statement being made by this Government with the scheme.  More than 26,000 people have built houses using the first-time buyer's grant.  How does Sinn F&eacute;in expect people to save money if we do not help people by providing a first-time buyer's grant?  I welcome the continuation of the scheme.</p> <p>The Government will invest &euro;716 million in childcare.  I have a young child and understanding the costs and implications that having a child has on parents is new to me.  This funding shows that the Government will tackle childcare, both by supporting parents with the cost of childcare and supporting childcare providers to provide a service and pay their staff what they deserve.  The service provided by childcare providers is top-notch.  My child goes to the Play and Learn cr&egrave;che in Clonmel, County Tipperary, which provides a top-quality service.  Childcare providers need the support of the Government and today's budget shows the priority we will attach to childcare in the coming years, which is welcome.</p> <p>It is important to acknowledge carers and the supports we have announced for them.  For the first time since 2008, the income threshold for carers has been raised.  The income disregard for carer's allowance will increase from &euro;332.50 to &euro;350 per week for a single person and from &euro;665 to &euro;750 for a couple.  Family carers have called for an increase for a long time.  Fine Gael Senators met Catherine Cox from Family Carers Ireland and Councillor Richie Molloy in Clonmel.  One of their asks was to increase the income disregard.  This increase will allow many people who did not qualify for carer's allowance until now to do so for the first time.</p> <p>I appreciate the Acting Chairperson has been very lenient as regards time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#HH00100"><p>Senator Ahearn may continue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#HH00200"><p>In that case, I have a number of initiatives to welcome but Senators from the Opposition are free to come in and interject.  From my own perspective, as someone coming from a rural constituency I welcome that as a Government, we have decided to again increase funding for all rural projects across the country.  Since its establishment in 2017, the Department of Rural and Community Development has been very beneficial.  The rural regeneration and development fund, LEADER, the town and village renewal scheme and CL&Aacute;R will get extra funding in 2022.  I acknowledge the role of the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, in that regard.  This is extremely positive.  The public will see it as a way out of Covid.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#HH00400"><p>I have welcomed the opportunity to listen to the contributions of Senators for more than two hours.  I kept note as best I could of all of the contributors.  It is worth noting that 18 Senators contributed, 13 of whom were Government Senators.  That says a great deal.  I have been a Member of the D&aacute;il for many years.  I remember a time when on budget day voting in the D&aacute;il could go on up to 12 midnight. but these days, the D&aacute;il sometimes adjourns at 7.30 p.m. or 8 p.m. because the Opposition has nothing to say.  We are in that space here tonight, as reflected by the number of contributors here.  I take on board everything said by Government Senators and by the Opposition.  I was intrigued by the marked contradiction in some of what was stated by the Opposition Senators.</p> <p>I will not reference what every Senator said because several Senators touched on the same topic.  The first topic touched on by Senator Casey was the new zoned land tax, which is an important issue.  I found the debate on that very interesting.  In terms of how the new 3% rate will work, the maps will be prepared by the local authorities but, importantly, the scheme will be administered by Revenue such that we will not have a situation whereby no tax is being levied or some tax is being levied but not properly collected.  In terms of taxes that require to be collected, it is up to the local authorities to collect that money.  They should not be approaching the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage next year looking for additional funds if they have not collected the debts validly owed to them.  They must make all reasonable efforts in that regard.  Some of those will have to work their way through the system.  This is a worthwhile scheme.  It is not about collecting money.  Rather, it is about forcing people who are sitting on zoned land, serviced by Irish Water and open to connection to the sewerage system, to move on it or pay tax on it.  We want them to move on it.  They can either develop houses on the land themselves or move the land on to somebody who can do that.  If local authorities and landowners have agreed zonings in local authority area plans over a period of years and there is land lying idle, serviced at significant cost to the taxpayer, it is only right that those lands should be used for housing.  It is an asset that belongs to all of us.  If it is not being used, it is fair that the landowner should make some contribution back to the State.  This tax might encourage people to move on land.  </p> <p>I found it interesting that an Opposition Senator stated this was really a tax cut for the wealthy farmers and landowners on the edges of various towns and that all the Government is doing in this measure is cutting the tax rate from 7% to 3%.  The next Opposition Senator - there were many of them in the House during the course of the afternoon - stated that under the existing regime, nothing is being collected.  I do not understand how going from zero tax being collected to a new regime of 3% to be operated by the Revenue Commissioners is a reduction in tax.  Those Members were looking at what we call the headline rate, which does not exist.  The actual rate of what was being levied was almost zero in most cases.  I am sure that under these new arrangements, the tax will be collected by the Revenue Commissioners.  People know that.  I encourage people in that situation to get moving.  We need houses.  If landowners are sitting on an asset, it is important they move on it.  Those who own zoned land on the edge of towns and cities, which is very valuable, will be well compensated for the disposal of that land, in particular those in the farming community.  They will also find land elsewhere that is not zoned at a much better price and as such they may be able to increase their landholdings should they wish to continue farming.  </p> <p>Many Senators complimented the retention of the EWSS, in particular in the hospitality sector, but they also said that to make the changes in January will be difficult to do.  That is a fair point.  I will raised that directly with the Minister, Deputy Donohoe.  The VAT rate for the hospitality sector will continue up to the end of August 2022.  It was requested that it be extended.  We take everything on board.  A Senator said that the quickest way of getting people off the road is to increase the tax on petrol and diesel.  That Senator lives in Dublin city centre and so it is easy for him to say that.  Those of us who do not live in Dublin 1 or 2 would have a different view on that.  </p> <p>Another Senator raised issues that are more relevant to a debate on public expenditure, including the pupil-teacher ratio in particular schools.  The budget provides for an increase in teacher numbers and a reduction in the pupil-teacher ratio by one.  There was also a request for more funding for cancer and palliative care, which is also addressed in today's budget.  On the question of reaching our overseas development aid target of 0.7% of GDP, this year, more than &euro;1 billion, the largest amount ever in this particular area, is being provided.  It is important to acknowledge that.  </p> <p>Other Senators mentioned that the number of people in receipt of the pandemic unemployment payment, PUP, is now under 100,000, which is a fantastic improvement from where we were, and that the issues of inflation and remote working will have to be closely monitored.  They also welcomed the measures in regard to carbon taxes and retrofitting.  The latter was mentioned by a number of Senators.</p> <p>The fuel allowance was mentioned, with the increase being deemed too narrow.  There will be further improvements in this area.  As we all know, those who are living alone and in receipt of the fuel allowance and the State pension will see their incomes increase by &euro;13 per week.  It is welcome that the &euro;5 fuel allowance comes into force at midnight tonight.  That is a good measure.  </p> <p>The childcare initiative, SIPTU and the Big Start campaign were mentioned.  Many of us met the SIPTU representatives in recent times.  I am pleased to see the matter is progressing through the Labour Relations Commission.  There is funding in the budget for childcare, to which the Minister specifically referred.  There are a lot of improvements provided for in the childcare area in terms of funding.  I note the preference of those involved in this area that it be referenced as the early years sector rather than the childcare sector.  I rap myself on the knuckles for getting that phrase wrong.  I note it is also wrong in some of the documentation before me today.  I was told by the people from the Big Start campaign that it is not about childcare; it is about the first start in children's education.  That is the way we should look at it.  </p> <p>What we are doing today will help everybody.  It will help parents in that costs are to be contained.  It will also help the service providers.  Once the arrangements come through the Labour Relations Commission and an employment regulation order, ERO, is available to set the pay rates, that will help the staff working in those areas.  Everybody is a winner in that situation.  We have laid the ground work for that here.  There will be funding to deal with an ERO as required in the course of the coming year.  We all look forward to that being agreed on behalf of that dispersed group of employees countrywide.  I credit SIPTU on the effort it put into recruiting up to 7,000 members such that it was able to satisfy the Workplace Relations Commission in regard to that particular issue.  In fairness, SIPTU is entitled to credit for doing that.  The Government is responding appropriately.  I hope that everything will work out.  </p> <p>I was intrigued by the comment of one Opposition Senator, who said it is all well and good spending all of this money while at the same time challenging everything we are doing today by saying that we should be spending better.  I thought that was hilarious.  We are providing money for childcare, increasing the fuel allowance from midnight tonight, increasing the living alone allowance and helping carers in terms of the means test.  The back-to-school clothing and footwear allowance is being increased next year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Sean Fleming:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=418"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=418&amp;amp;pid=SeanFleming&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=10&amp;amp;day=12"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are several measures in respect of workers such as, for example, increasing the standard rate tax band, increasing tax credits and increasing the minimum wage.  We will also introduce an income tax deduction for remote workers.  We are extending free GP care for six- and seven-year-olds.  For the first time, we are introducing free contraception for 17-year-olds to 25-year-olds.  I take the point that it should not always be the responsibility of the female to deal with that.  Us fellas have a responsibility in this area, too.  That point was well made.<br/><br/>Regarding students, we are increasing the SUSI grant by &euro;200 and its threshold by &euro;1,000.  Importantly for those of us in rural areas, the distance threshold for the higher education non-adjacent student grant is being reduced from 45 km to 30 km.  In old English, that is a reduction from nearly 30 miles to nearly 20 miles and is very important.  Many people in County Laois where I live are a little too close to Carlow or wherever the case may be.  This is a fantastic change and will be a major advantage to people in every county because more will be able to get the non-adjacent grant.  This is the grant that makes it possible for some people to get to third level.  They can get the SUSI grant, but the costs they incur are still high.  If they will now be able to get the non-adjacent grant, it will make the difference between them being able to get third level education and not being able to get it.  The youth travel card was also mentioned.<br/><br/>Most of this is appropriate to the debate that the Seanad will have tomorrow on public expenditure, but I was intrigued when I was told that we were not spending the money well.  I suppose that the Opposition has to say something when it is here, but I found that to be an extraordinary comment.<br/><br/>Childcare has been mentioned by several Senators.  Regarding VAT for the hospitality sector and coach and bus tour companies, I will convey the comments to the Minister for Finance.<br/><br/>We were challenged on the gender proofing of this budget.  I will read from the document that was circulated to everyone today:</p><blockquote>	The CSO has conducted an equality data audit and a data strategy is currently being drafted to ensure this data source is kept up to date, addresses gaps identified during the audit, and ensures the information is utilised in the intended way.  A focused equality data audit has been conducted on all national data sets held by Tusla and a report on that audit has been published alongside Budget 2022. </blockquote><p>The audit is out there for people to follow up on, so I found it extraordinary that such a challenge was made.  As one Senator mentioned, we have a dedicated women's health package of &euro;31 million in the budget.  This includes access to free contraception from next August for women of between 17 and 23 years of age, further investment in measures identified in the women's health task force, progress in the period poverty implementation group, additional funding for sexual assault treatment units, the implementation of the national maternity strategy and gynaecological model of care, and dealing with endometriosis and the many other issues that women must deal with.  How could someone say that the budget was not gender balanced?  It is the most gender-balanced budget that I have encountered, and I have been around here for a few years.<br/><br/>I commend the budget and I thank the Senators.  I will not take their time, but if I had another ten minutes, I could go on more.  I have responded as best I can.  We all look forward to what is in the budget being implemented.  Its measures are for the benefit of families, parents, children, older people, workers and renters, and the public have been seeing that over the past couple of hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#JJ00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021101200002#JJ00300"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-10-12a.128" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 7.24 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 13 October 2021.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>