<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Colm Burke that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection to consider amending legislation to permit notaries public to perform civil marriage ceremonies, given that registrars are not available at weekends.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Paudie Coffey of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to review the eligibility criteria for receipt of a primary medical certificate.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to conduct a review of the pricing structure for Bus &Eacute;ireann services in west Cork.</blockquote><p>The matters raised by Senators Colm Burke and Paudie Coffey are suitable for discussion and will be taken now.  I regret that I have had to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Tim Lombard on the grounds that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800002#A00400">Civil Marriages</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800002#A00500"><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Pat Breen, is very welcome as ever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800002#A00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming into the House to deal with this matter.  </p>  <p>In the past few months a number of people have been in contact with me to raise the concern that registrars for marriages are not available on Saturdays and Sundays.  I know that, traditionally, in Ireland weddings take place six days a week, although not necessarily on a Sunday.  There has been a change in that regard.  People have said, in particular, that registrars are not available on a Saturday.  A proposal that has been put to me is that notaries public could perform this task, as they have to go through a robust system before being appointed in the courts system.  As there is a notary public in every major centre of population throughout the country, he or she might be a suitable person to be appointed.</p>  <p>The Irish Institute of Celebrants runs a course which leaves people with all of the qualifications required to conduct wedding ceremonies, but they are not recognised as official registrars.  The institute has contacted me because people are taking the course and possess the qualifications and although they can conduct ceremonies, they are not recognised as official registrars.  It costs approximately &euro;2,500 to take the course which is quite intense.  The rules and regulations must be complied with, but it does not cover the registration of marriages.  There is an issue on Saturdays and Sundays as registrars are not available to conduct ceremonies.  Could amending legislation be introduced to deal with the matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800002#A00700"><p>I thank the Senator for his interest in this matter.  As he stated, lifestyles and the number of marriages taking place are changing.  We are living in a very different society.  I thank the Senator for raising the issue which I am taking on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, who sends her apologies as she cannot be here.</p>  <p>The legal basis for the appointment of civil marriage registrars may be found in Part 6 of the Civil Registration Act 2004, as amended.  Sections 53 and 54 provide for the establishment of a register of solemnisers of marriage and the making of applications by bodies for the registration in the register of solemnisers of members nominated by them.  A body may include the Health Service Executive for the registration of a registrar who is employed by it; a religious body, as defined in section 45 of the Act, for the registration of a member of that body; and a secular body, as defined in section 45A of the Act, for the registration of a member of that body.</p> <p>The register of solemnisers is maintained by an t-&Aacute;rd Chl&aacute;raitheoir, the Registrar General, and holds the names of all solemnisers who have been approved to conduct valid marriages.  Under the Civil Registration Act 2004, the Registrar General has the authority to make decisions on approved bodies and the registration of nominated solemnisers.  The only people who can legally solemnise civil marriages are those whose names are entered in the register of solemnisers.</p> <p>As a grouping, notaries public do not belong to an organisation or body that qualifies to nominate marriage solemnisers under the Act.  It is not possible for an individual to apply for registration on the register of solemnisers.  Applications for entry in the register of solemnisers may only be made by the HSE, a religious body or a secular body as defined in sections 45 and 45A of the Civil Registration Act 2004.  There are no plans to amend the legislative provisions for the appointment of marriage solemnisers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800003#B00200"><p>I am just not satisfied with that answer as it still does not deal with the problem of individuals being available to solemnise a marriage on a Saturday.  If the person is a member of the religious body that has clearance from the Registrar General, it is possible but what if he or she is not a member of that religious body and there is no registrar available on a Saturday?  This matter must be dealt with.  I have suggested notaries public because, as I mentioned, there is one in every major centre of population throughout the country.  There is a problem as people are not available on a Saturday or a Sunday to solemnise marriages, unless one gos to one of the recognised religious bodies.  There is, therefore, a deficiency in the scheme.  I ask for the matter to be examined to see if the process can be broadened to include persons who want to be available to solemnise marriages on Saturdays and Sundays.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1272" speakername="Pat Breen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800003#B00300"><p>I can see where the Senator is coming from.  As he knows, the registration of marriages is governed by Part 6 of the Civil Registration Act 2004.  The marriage provisions regulations commenced on 5 November 2007, replacing legislation which dated back to 1844.  The main changes were the requirement for all couples to give notice in person of their intention to marry, the introduction of common preliminaries for all marriages and a choice of venue for civil marriages.  I will take on board the Senator's legitimate views and convey them to the Minister.  I will ask her to look at them, but I cannot guarantee anything in that regard.  There are many solemnisers who can perform marriage ceremonies.  The total number of solemnisers is approximately 5,766.  In 2016 there were 5,630 religious solemnisers, with 113 civil solemnisers and 23 secular solemnisers.  I can see the Senator's point about availability on Saturdays and Sundays and will convey his comments to the Minister to see if there is anything we can do.  I cannot promise anything, but I thank the Senator for raising the matter.  I am sure it will not go away and will be raised again in the future.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800003#B00400">Primary Medical Certificates</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800003#B00500"><p>I thank my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Michael D'Arcy, for attending the Seanad to listen to my concerns about the primary medical certificate and how it is issued, as well as the scheme to which it applies in the qualification of people with severe disabilities under the disabled drivers and disabled passengers scheme.  We know that it provides relief from vehicle registration tax, VRT, VAT and motor tax to assist people with disabilities in the provision of transport so as to improve their mobility which we all agree is very important.  I am sure the Minister of State will agree with me as people in his constituency may have applied for the primary medical certificate.  They are people with very severe disabilities, but, unfortunately, some of them have been turned down.  </p>  <p>I will explain why I am seeking a review of the primary medical certificate process and how people qualify under it.  The qualifying criteria have been in place since the 1980s.  There are six very strict criteria.  Essentially, one must be without limbs or the use of both arms to qualify.  The Minister of State and I, with many others, know people with severe disabilities who are wholly without the use of their limbs but who still do not qualify for receipt of the primary medical certificate.  It causes much stress, anguish and frustration for people with disabilities.</p>  <p>I will quote one case in which I have been involved for some time.  A young, 22 year old lady has had her life shattered by a chronic spinal condition, a degenerative disc disease called congenital spinal stenosis.  It started when she was 17 years old.  Already in her young life she has had three failed surgeries, two lumbar disectomies and instrumented spinal fusion on two levels.  She has been left with intractable pain in both of her legs and back, resulting in significant mobility issues.  She has been prescribed an horrendous amount of opioid medication that leaves her bedridden for most of the day and which is taking a toll on her internal organs.  She was attending a degree course at the National University of Ireland, Galway, but she has been unable to return because of her spinal condition, as it brings chronic pain, there are serious mobility problems and she is on medication.</p>  <p>Despite all of this, an application was made for a primary medical certificate and she was devastated to discover that it had been refused.  It was her one hope she would receive some support to improve her mobility, well-being and independence by being able to drive an adapted car.  She uses two crutches to get around the house and a wheelchair outside it.  It is really frustrating for her and her family.  I undertook to try to assist her and have written to the Minister of State with responsibility for people with disabilities, Deputy Finian McGrath. who, in fairness, has offered support, but he has also said he is restricted by the scheme in place.  Therefore, I ask for the review of the scheme for genuine cases involving a serious disability.  A review is long overdue, as the scheme was introduced in the 1980s.  I am interested in hearing the Minister of State's comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1364" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800003#B00600"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  </p>  <p>The disabled drivers and disabled passengers (tax concessions) scheme provides relief from VAT and VRT, up to a certain limit, on the purchase of an adapted car for transport of a person with specific severe and permanent physical disabilities, payment of a fuel grant and an exemption from motor tax.  To qualify for the scheme, an applicant must be in possession of a primary medical certificate, PMC.  To qualify for a PMC, an applicant must be permanently and severely disabled within the terms of the Disabled Drivers and Disabled Passengers (Tax Concessions) Regulations 1994 and satisfy one of a number of conditions which, as the Senator can see, have been detailed.</p>  <p>The senior medical officer for the relevant local Health Service Executive administrative area makes a professional clinical determination as to whether an individual applicant satisfies the medical criteria.</p> <p>A successful applicant is provided with a PMC which is required under the regulations to claim the reliefs provided for in the scheme.  An unsuccessful applicant can appeal the decision of the senior medical officer to the Disabled Drivers Medical Board of Appeal, DDMBA, which makes a new clinical determination in respect of the individual.  The regulations mandate that the DDMBA is independent in the exercise of its functions to ensure the integrity of its clinical determinations.  In the event that an appeal is unsuccessful, a citizen can reapply for a PMC after six months if there has been a deterioration in his or her condition.</p> <p>The scheme represents significant tax expenditure.  Between the VRT and VAT forgone and fuel grant provided for members, the scheme represented a cost of &euro;65 million in 2017.  This figure did not include the revenue forgone in respect of the relief from motor tax provided for members of the scheme.</p> <p>The Minister for Finance recognises the important role the scheme plays in expanding the mobility of citizens with disabilities and that the relief has been maintained at current levels throughout the crisis, despite the requirement for significant fiscal consolidation.  He understands and fully sympathises with any person who suffers from a serious physical disability and cannot access the scheme under the current criteria.  However, given the scale and scope of the scheme, any possible change could only be made after careful consideration and taking into account other schemes that also seek to help with the mobility of disabled persons.  The issue of mobility grants for disabled persons needs to be examined in a broader context to include all schemes that serve disabled persons and recognise the current scale and scope of the disabled drivers scheme.  There are no further plans to review the medical criteria for eligibility.</p> <p>To a degree, the response is accurate.  The Senator has outlined an experience similar to what I have seen on the ground in representing people in my constituency of Wexford.  The medical officers and those who decide on appeals can only apply the rules.  While there is a degree of discretion, it only applies if the criteria are met.  The case outlined by the Senator does not meet the criteria.  A larger conversation is required in that regard, but since there are no plans, it is a matter for others in this or the Lower House to propose an expansion of the medical criteria under the scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800004#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I accept that the Department and medical officers must apply the criteria, but, for the reasons outlined, many others and I believe they are too rigid.  For example, they do not allow for people with serious spinal injuries or who are in pain and suffering.  The mobility and related issues of such persons are not being recognised.  I have no problem in saying this seems to be a budgetary rather than a mobility and health issue.  The scheme was designed to improve the mobility of people with serious disabilities.  While the criteria allow for that to happen in many cases, they exclude many others.  I have used a live example of a person with a degenerative disease and a spinal condition.  There is a fear within the Civil Service that the floodgates would be opened if the scheme was to be expanded further, but the Minister of State knows as well as I that there are people with serious disabilities who should qualify for such supports but who, unfortunately, do not under the current regime.  I will continue to work on this matter and ask for the support of the Minister of State and other colleagues in having the scheme reviewed at some stage to take into account the real needs of disabled people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1364" speakername="Michael D'Arcy" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800004#C00300"><p>A number of improvements were made in January 2016.  First, for those citizens who required extensive modifications to their vehicles to take account of their disabilities, where the cost of the modifications exceeded the cost of the vehicles, a category of extensively adapted vehicle was provided for drivers and passengers.  The VRT and VAT relief on such vehicles can be up to a figure of &euro;22,000.  A category of specifically adapted vehicle was provided for drivers with disabilities who had made significant adaptions to their vehicles.  VAT and VRT relief up to a figure of &euro;16,000 is provided in the purchase of such vehicles.  The criteria under which an organisation could avail of relief were amended to allow many more charitable organisations involved in the care and transport of citizens with disabilities to become beneficiaries under the scheme.</p>  <p>The Minister for Finance, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, removed some unnecessary and burdensome criteria to improve the functioning of the scheme for beneficiaries.  The improvements included an increase in engine size limits from 2 l to 6 l and removing the authorised person requirement.  Further to this, he amended the regulations in the budget for this year to widen access to the scheme for charitable organisations, the purpose of which was to provide services for disabled persons.  This matter was raised by Members in both Houses, to whom we listened.</p>  <p>My personal view on the scheme, of which the Senator is probably aware, has been outlined in both Houses, but I am responding to him in the name of the Department.  It is a matter for the Houses to decide and I encourage them to examine it further.  As we showed in the budget, we were listening and changes were made to increase flexibility under the scheme.  Perhaps the next opportunity to increase it further might be in the next budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800004#C00400"><p>I welcome Mr. Ryan Tubridy to the Chamber.  I am sorry that I missed most of his programme.  I miscued at 9 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.22" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800004#C00500">Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800004#C00600"><p>The Joint Committee on Health has completed its consideration of the following orders:</p><blockquote>(i) Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 4(7)) (Membership of Council) Regulations 2017, and<br /><br />(ii) Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 4(2)) (Designation of professions: counsellors and psychotherapists and establishment of registration board) Regulations 2017.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.24" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.25" nospeaker="true" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800005#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800005#G00200"><p>Before I call the Acting Leader on the Order of Business, as this is International Women's Day, it is important to acknowledge and reflect briefly on all the women who have not only made such a valuable contribution to both Houses of the Oireachtas but who have contributed and made society such a better place for all of us and everyone's dear mums who bore us and gave us life.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800005#G00500"><p>I, too, acknowledge International Women's Day and echo the sentiments.  The Order of Business is No. <i>a</i>1, motion regarding the sixth report of the Committee of Selection, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 1, motion regarding the address to the House by Mr. M&iacute;che&aacute;l &Oacute; Muircheartaigh on Wednesday, 21 March 2018, to be taken on conclusion of No. <i>a</i>1, without debate; No. 2, motion regarding membership of An Bord Plean&aacute;la, referral to committee, to be taken on conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, statements on flooding (resumed) to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to conclude no later than 1.45 p.m. with the Minister to be given not less than five minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 4, Technological Universities Bill 2015, Report Stage (resumed) and Final Stage, to be taken at 2.30 p.m. and to conclude not later than 6 p.m. if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800005#G00600"><p>The Senator said 6 p.m. rather than 5 p.m.  I thought that was 5 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800005#G00700"><p>I will check my notes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800005#G00800"><p>We can alter it later if needs be.  I thank the Acting Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800005#G00900"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.  He opened his remarks by saying that today is International Women's Day, a day that is rightly celebrated around the world.  I am leading off today because our leader, Senator Ardagh, is not able to attend because she is at the funeral of an extraordinary woman who was 106 years of age.  Not only did she have grandchildren and great-grandchildren, but she had great-great-grandchildren and she featured in the documentary "Older than Ireland" and was able to give of her wisdom and knowledge of a long life, well lived.  She was buried this morning.  She was Esther Nolan from Drimnagh, better known as Bessie.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam.</p>  <p>As we reflect on the fact that today is International Women's Day and that next Sunday is Mother's Day, we must also reflect on the fact that, in this society, it is 100 years since women were given the vote.  Considering that the Greeks came up with the idea of voting thousands of years ago, women have only had the vote for the last 100 years and even today, in this society, women struggle for equality and equal treatment.  That equality still eludes us in this society.  We must and should do better.</p>  <p>There is ongoing controversy about the treatment by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na of two female civilian members who appeared before the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality yesterday to outline the extraordinary treatment that they were subjected to by senior garda&iacute; to manipulate figures relating to homicide statistics.  When one looks at the world we live in today, a world of alternative facts and where fake news is being purported to be carried out by the man who is the epitome of fake news, what does the fact that the Central Statistics Office cannot rely on the figures being put forward yearly by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na about murders say about the system that the garda&iacute; have?  It is not just the system but the culture within senior management of the garda&iacute; that is shocking and appalling.  If this was an isolated incident, we would be saying this in itself is a concern but add to that the treatment of Garda McCabe and many others within An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p>  <p>The problem is that there are no consequences for this type of behaviour within An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Guys are promoted, get their pensions, retire, are never fired and never go to jail because there are no consequences in this society for people who treat their staff, society and this State with such disdain.  I am concerned on this International Women's Day about the Garda figures on homicide because of the issue of domestic violence, how that is being reported and how deaths that occur in the home are not being recorded properly.  Action is not being taken on that most serious of issues which women face on a daily basis - domestic violence, which results in injury, harm and, tragically, in murders as well, which garda&iacute; do not want to report properly.  What is wrong with the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na?</p> <p>One of the institutions of the State that we hold in high regard is undermining our confidence in it because we cannot believe the figures it provides on murders.  Furthermore, when the problem was identified, rather than fixing it, the Garda went after those who highlighted it.</p> <p>The recent whistleblower legislation is not sufficient to protect whistleblowers.  The purpose of the legislation should be to protect whistleblowers and promote the idea of rewarding those who bring to light any information they have.  Unfortunately, rather than reward people, the system is punishing and crushing them.  On International Women's Day, we see what happened to two female civilian Garda employees who tried to do their job and were treated appallingly and with disdain by senior Garda management, mainly men, who put them under severe pressure to lie to the people of Ireland.  Senior management wanted them to manipulate the figures to lie to the public.  These individuals must face consequences.  They must be exposed and fired, rather than being allowed to retire on a pension.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800006#H00200"><p>Senator Daly will have to give evidence to the Charleton tribunal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800006#H00300"><p>Ba bhre&aacute; liom tr&eacute;asl&uacute; le mn&aacute; na h&Eacute;ireann, agus mn&aacute; Gaelach na h&Eacute;ireann ach go h&aacute;irithe, ar an L&aacute; Idirn&aacute;isi&uacute;nta na mBan seo.  I, too, congratulate and thank the women of the world on International Women's Day.  I thank, in particular, the women who, whether for specific periods or on a more indefinite, continuous basis, have brought joy and happiness into my life.  I also salute the many achievements of the international women's movement and the efforts of colleagues in the House in reminding us of the significant milestone that is the 100th anniversary of the introduction of women's suffrage.  We only have to read the daily court reports to see that society has a long way to go before men respect women and their dignity, and women's equal right to dignity and respect is fully recognised.</p><p>While it is only fair to salute the achievements of the international women's movement, I also wish to be a friendly critic.  There are two blind spots in the movement at activist level.  The first is the denial concerning abortion which, far from being a liberator of women, is actually a betrayer of women, not only of the girl child in the womb but the women who feel they have been betrayed, have not been supported and have been pressurised by others.  The easy access to abortion in our world is often a tool for selfish men who view abortion as an easy way out.  We need to hear more feminism for life and I hope we will do so in the coming weeks and months.</p><p>The second issue is in the area of gender equality.  Equal pay should be a given and should go without saying.  While it is provided for in law, whether it is always provided in practice is another matter.  We also have a long way to go on family friendly workplaces, including in the Oireachtas.  Requiring women to work at equal rates of intensity in the workplace regardless of whether they wish do so is not authentic feminism.  While I do not often quote David Quinn in the Chamber lest Senators conclude we are twin brothers, he has something pungent to say today by way of an observation on International Women's Day.  He states that radical feminism paradoxically makes men and their achievements the measure, and that everything feminine, meaning home and motherhood in particular, is to be demeaned.  All women should work, like it or not, he adds, and women must be able to live and work as though they have no children so they can compete equally with men.  This view, he points out, leads to an agenda for abortion and universal cheap day care, an aim that does a gross disservice to ordinary women.  To that extent, radical feminism is, he says, anti-woman.  This is a useful point to include in the debate.  It is not a million miles away from the view expressed by Victoria White in a fine article in the <i>Irish Examiner</i>today, which I commend.  While International Women's Day is to be celebrated and a great deal has been achieved, much more must be done and some things must be changed. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800006#H00400"><p>Last night's decision of the D&aacute;il to unanimously agree to ratify the Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities was regarded as a reason to celebrate.  My celebration was to go home with my daughter, Ruth, who visited the Houses for the debate, and have a cup of tea with my wife, Liz.  The celebration part was that I was allowed to have a biscuit.  We chatted about who said what during the debate.  I visited the D&aacute;il for the debate to listen to speakers from all parties and none and I respect the interest they showed in the issue.  Many disabled people were in the Public Gallery and references were made to individuals who should have been present for the occasion.  Apart from sadness, I was also struck by the thought that there is no time to lose in this work.</p>  <p>This is the morning after and today we celebrate International Women's Day.  My celebration was appropriate because we have only secured agreement to get on with the major challenge we face.  As a result of the decision of the Oireachtas, Ireland is finally acting to make its disabled people free and equal.  The commitment given by An Taoiseach on his election to deliver ratification by the end of 2017 was a critical moment of leadership.  As politicians, we love to speak.  Last night's agreement to ratify the convention moves us out of the realm of speaking and into the difficult and dangerous space of taking action.  Action must be purposeful and skilfully executed. </p>  <p>In August 1942, the allied attack on Dieppe was a disaster from which the allies learned that land, sea and air forces must work together.  Government must act as a unit and An Taoiseach must show leadership and relentless drive.  He and all of his Ministers must act as one to form what I describe as a disability inclusion strategic implementation unit.  When the boss smells gas, we all smell it because it becomes everyone's job.  I am grateful to the Leader for the commitment he gave to hold a debate on the implementation of the convention.  Senators have control over the work of the House.  With only 60 Members, the Seanad is a small House and we should work together, not sheepishly but critically and with respect.</p>  <p>I will suggest a few steps we can take.  The first is to debate the implementation of the convention.  Every Senator is either a party or group spokesperson or member of a joint Oireachtas committee and all of us are members of a parliamentary group.  We must think about disability inclusion at every meeting.  We must meet people with disabilities and listen directly to their experience of life in Ireland today.  Let us consider inviting people with disabilities to the Seanad to listen to them and set a good example.</p>  <p>I am about to write to the leaders of every political party and group seeking a meeting to discuss their plans for implementing the convention and ensuring implementation becomes a whole-of-Government project.  Ten years from now, on International Women's Day 2028, it would be great if our disabled citizens could say Ireland is theirs and is a great, hopeful and warm place for disabled people to live in and in which they can thrive.</p>  <p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach commenced proceedings by referring to International Women's Day.  As I have stated previously, women are often the great backstop when it comes to disability and chronic illness.  Delivery of the UN convention would provide great practical emancipation and support to many women.  I thank all Senators for the support and encouragement they have offered me in my work since entering Seanad &Eacute;ireann. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800006#H00500"><p>I wish the Leas-Chathaoirleach and all Senators a very happy International Women's Day.  This is a day on which we acknowledge the achievements of women, their survival and the progress made in tackling some of the injustices they face.</p> <p>I want to remember carers, in particular.  I refer to carers of the elderly, vulnerable people and children and adults with disabilities.  One of our main achievements in the Seanad was the passing of the Domestic Violence Bill.  I ask the Leader to express our concern to the Minister that the Bill has not yet been passed in the D&aacute;il in order that it can be enacted.  I have no doubt that the Bill will save lives and years of abuse for some women.  Perhaps we might be told today when this will be done.  The #MeToo campaign has facilitated and opened up a discussion on the abuse of women.  However, unless we act, we are failing all women who have suffered abuse, including those who are being abused this very day and who will be abused tomorrow and into the future.  The Domestic Violence Bill is hugely important, but it is only one of the urgent necessary actions needed.  Yesterday we heard from the two Garda civilian analysts who said they had been belittled and their credibility attacked at Garda headquarters.  I am referring to when they raised concerns about the incorrect classification of some homicides.  This is not just disgusting; it is also extremely dangerous as it puts the lives of women in danger.  Thousands of women disclose domestic abuse to front-line agencies such as Women's Aid and Safe Ireland, as well as to rape crisis centres, women's refuges, family resource centres and other projects, which I also commend for their work.  </p> <p>I also want to remember, in particular, the investigation which is needed and necessary into the shooting of Ms Siobhan Phillips who was left for dead with Garda Tony Golden when her partner opened fire.  Why was Mr. Adrian Crevan Mackin not convicted?  I have permission from Ms Phillips to read a small element of her statement which we have to remember was made before the shooting.  Ms Phillips says Mr. Mackin pinned her to the wall, kneed her to her ribs, grabbed her by the throat and squeezed her windpipe.  He was looking at her and told her to look at him in the eyes when he was choking her.  He said she liked it and spat in her face.  She went on to say she was afraid that he would do to her, or her family, what he had done previously.  That was her statement, as read to and confirmed by her as being correct.  </p> <p>After hearing from the two individuals at the committee yesterday, I was so mindful of how we needed to act, why we needed the Domestic Violence Bill and a change to protect women.  The facts are that there are men who are walking in the corridors of power right now across the country, donning uniforms every morning, members of organisations and clubs who have abused women.  They have used the power and control that come with their positions to do as they wish to women and get away with it.  It has been happening for decades.  I encourage women to come forward and commend those who have,  some of them after decades of abuse.  I encourage women to come forward to tell their stories and be supported by the agencies.  It is never too late to tell.  I commend the agencies involved.  However, as legislators, we need to make sure they are given the funding and resources they need to be able to help the women in question.  </p> <p>I really need to say some of the media reporting of sexual abuse cases brought to trial is absolutely deplorable.  I want some of the media outlets to walk in the shoes of women who are thinking, "This has happened to me.  I have been abused.  I have been raped.  Will I come forward?"  Looking at some of the commentary on some cases in the broadcasting and print media, it acts as a deterrent and must be addressed.  I ask them to walk in the shoes of some of the women who have been abused before they open their mouths.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800007#J00200"><p>On International Women's Day the Government is to be commended for publishing the text of the proposed referendum to repeal the eighth amendment.  Every day I think of the children I taught in an all-girls' school on Sheriff Street.  They inspire me.  Knowing that - I hope soon - with the votes of the people, they will have full bodily autonomy in the future is something that should be celebrated.  As the famous song "Bread and Roses" goes, women and men will be "marching marching" to mark today's announcement by the Cabinet leading, I hope, to a referendum on 25 May.  All sides of the House have a role to play in that regard.</p>  <p>Next week the Taoiseach will visit the White House and it is appropriate that he do so.  He has diplomatic responsibilities that need to be respected.  I hope he will take the opportunity to speak about things which are important to Irish people.  However, there will be another event held in New York next weekend.  I am thankful that Mr. Colum Eastwood of the Social Democratic and Labour Party, SDLP, is boycotting the White House event.  Instead he will attend an event called "Irish Stand" to be held in New York to try to give voice to the real experiences of the Irish nation and the immigrant nature of Irish people who have been all over the world and who now stand shoulder to shoulder with other peoples in America who feel under threat, be they Mexican or Muslim Americans.  It is important that any political representative who finds himself or herself in America next weekend use that opportunity to stand up against the racism, misogyny and homophobia emanating from the White House and not find himself or herself rubbing shoulders with those concerned at fundraisers.  Instead he or she should stand in solidarity with the true meaning of what it is to be Irish - standing up for things which are universally important.  What is happening in America is being reflected across the world, including in Britain with Brexit, Austria, Germany and Italy.  It is not good enough for politicians to speak about equality at home and then to rub shoulders with members of the National Rifle Association, Republicans and Congressmen such as Mr. Pete King in New York who effectively is writing and supporting such xenophobic and racist policies.  As we celebrate Irishness next week and what it means to be Irish, we should remember that the Irish were once at the bottom of the social ladder in America.  We should, therefore, be very mindful of those who are now suffering discrimination and from rhetoric which is very hurtful and painful for them and who need the Irish to stand up for them.  What they do not need is a bunch of Irish politicians in America fundraising and staying quiet when this rhetoric which is so hurtful is used.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800007#J00300"><p>It is welcome that it is International Women's Day.  I was asked what woman I had found inspirational during the years.  It has to be Mrs. Mary Robinson who was elected as the seventh President of Ireland.  It was a great day for women.  She was inspirational.  As she said, she had been elected by the women of Ireland, that instead of rocking the cradle, they had rocked the system. It was an iconic moment which opened up a very liberal Ireland.  She is one of many women who have been inspirational and came from Crossmolina.</p>  <p>I heard with interest what the two civilian members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na had to say.  It pains me sometimes to see what is happening in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  My grandfather who fought for the freedom of this country was the first member of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  It is an occupation that escaped me because I do not have the skills or discipline to be a garda.  However, I will not join in the chorus of those who are undermining the integrity of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na which has defended the institutions of the State since its foundation.  It defended the State when there were actually people and parties that were trying to undermine it.  Therefore, I will not join anybody who is undermining the integrity of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p> <p>I have seen what happens.  They undermine their respect and integrity and take away all of the good they have done.  We saw during protests about water people who were not fit to lace their shoes shouting, "Shame, shame on you".  Sometimes we have to stand firm and say what has to happen within the structures and frameworks which exist.  If garda&iacute; are seen to misbehave, they should deal with the rigours of the law.  I will not join a weak political movement which blames garda&iacute;.  The Garda is doing a difficult job and protects us and our State.  As a politician and somebody who has always had huge respect for the Garda, I will not join that chorus.  It is simple and cheap, and it has a very short future.</p> <p>We saw what happened in Tallaght last week.  Thankfully, the Garda had a contingency plan, a plan of which I was not aware.  I am proud of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the work it does.  It makes mistakes, but I will not undermine it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800008#K00200"><p>I would like to agree with Senator Feighan.  As the House is aware, Fianna F&aacute;il is a heavy supporter of the Garda and institutions of the State.  I am sure there was no slight meant on us.</p>  <p>A senior serving fire officer in Mullingar brought to my attention the fact that while alarm companies are able to sell their wares and provide security for burglaries and fires, there is no regulation requiring those companies to provide Eircode postcodes for the properties they are protecting.  In recent times, the link between Google maps and the Eircode system has meant Eircode has taken off.  If alarm companies are required to provide Eircode postcodes for the properties they are minding, it would help essential services to get to people's homes, buildings and businesses within the quickest time possible.  I have no doubt it will save lives and some properties.  I call on the Minister to make it compulsory for any alarm company which has a contract to protect a home, building or business to provide the Eircode postcode for that property.  When emergency services are contacted by the company, they should, therefore, have the precise location of the property.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800008#K00300"><p>On International Women's Day I would like to remember the women who influenced my life.  I would like to remember my mother, my eight sisters, my wife, my daughter, my granddaughters and my daughters-in-law.  They are very important people and I would not be standing here today without them.  I would also like to remember the women in uniform who serve everywhere.  They serve equal to men and some of them get a rough time.</p>  <p>I ask for the Minister of State at the Department of Defence to be brought to the House as soon as possible.  Today I received information that four senior officers are to resign from the Air Corps, three of whom are instructor pilots.  This will devastate the Air Corps.  They are all fixed wing instructor pilots, which means they train people on the Casa.  The Minister of State has tried to put in place a retention system in order that we do not lose people, but this is a crisis.  We lost half a ship's company from the Naval Service last month and now we are about to lose four of the most senior flying officers in the country.  I understand there are two captains and two lieutenant colonels.  We simply cannot afford to continue losing people.</p>  <p>The memory of rescue 116 is sitting very firmly in my mind and has done ever since the fateful night when the aircraft was brought down.  We cannot allow the Defence Forces to continue to stumble from disaster to disaster.  I have spoken to the Minister and I believe he is trying his damnedest to put things right.  We need to hear from him where the impediment is, who is blocking it and why money is not available to retain personnel.  What will it cost to recruit three instructors?</p>  <p>Even if we brought back retired officers, they cannot become instructors immediately.  Some 107 cadets passed out of the Curragh recently, but those going into the Air Corps cannot jump into an aircraft and start flying.  It will be five years before they are qualified to fly on their own and ten years before they are eligible to fly the Casa.  We heard a lot about the Garda on the Order of Business today and I resent the manner in which we are watching it wash its dirty linen in public.  Clearly, some people at the top have serious questions to answer but most are decent people.</p>  <p>What bothers me is that what is going on in the Defence Forces is going on behind closed doors.  Nobody seems to be aware of what is happening.  We recently saw photographs of soldiers in Blessington who had to be brought from Dundalk to clear the roads of snow.  This is outrageous.  Fuel consumption in Finner Camp alone has increased by 600% because soldiers are travelling from Donegal to do barrack duties in Dublin.  This is now beyond a joke.</p>  <p>We need the Minister of State to come to the House so we can get to the bottom of whether it is the Government, Civil Service or senior Army officers who are causing the problem.  I am not one to put the blame on anybody.  I met the Minister of State, Deputy Kehoe, and believed everything he said to me when he said was trying to put things right.  I want to give him an opportunity to put his position on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="11:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800008#K00400"><p>Ba mhaith liom, le linn Seachtain na Gaeilge, comhghairdeas a dh&eacute;anamh le mn&aacute; na h&Eacute;ireann agus le mn&aacute; go hidirn&aacute;isi&uacute;nta freisin.  People have been thinking about the women who have inspired them the most.  Many of us look to international figures who have had a real impact on the world.  I have looked closer to home and thought of my grandmother who lost her husband when she had an eight old and a six year old to raise and a farm of rushes to try to keep from the banks.  Some things do not change.  She succeeded in doing so and lived to the ripe old age of 97.  She was still involved in stocks and shares until she was 95 years of age.  She is not the woman who inspires me the most.  That would be my wife, who would not take "No" for an answer or lie down under a diagnosis of hopelessness, and devoted her time to rearing her children, in particular our son who has autism.  Following a diagnosis of mental handicap and not worrying too much, she pursued and persisted, along with our son, to bring him to the point where he has not just one university degree but a masters, and is now studying for a PhD.  Today, as they often do, they are speaking to parents of children with autism in the midlands.  There is nothing like seeing someone who has had a very severe diagnosis and did not talk till he was five years old or attend a normal school until he was 11 years of age stand and talk to people.  I salute her and all of the women like her.</p>  <p>Last May I published a Bill looking for a national strategy for autism spectrum disorder, ASD.  The House passed it unanimously in October or November. I want to ask the Minister to come to the House and advise us of the status of the Bill.  It is one of many which the Department of Health has to deal with.</p> <p>The Bill has been passed unanimously by this House and I have no doubt it will get the support of the Lower House.  When I spoke on this matter here previously I think 10,000 people had signed an online petition and there are now more than 71,000 signatures.  I wish to ask where the Bill is, what is delaying it and to remind the Minister and the Department of its necessity- I know the Minister's heart is in the right place in this regard.  There is no question about that.  This issue will not go away and I am not going to stay silent on it.  I will raise it every single week until I see the Bill in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L00200"><p>That was a wonderful story.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L00300"><p>Today is International Women's Day and I wish to highlight the fact that there is a very important march this evening in Dublin, kicking off at the Garden of Remembrance at 5.30 p.m.  It is a "votes for repeal" march and I appeal to all of those who support the cause of repeal to come out this evening and unify.  It is not a party-political march, it is a march for everyone who is concerned about the health of women and supports the call for repeal.  I regret that I cannot be there due to a family commitment but I think it is a very important event and it would be great to see an important turnout there.</p>  <p>I have friends and colleagues who do not share my views and I think it is extremely important that we respect each other in terms of the referendum vote, and that we respect the different sides of the debate.  However, as public representatives we do have a duty to say where we stand on repeal.  I find it very disappointing that there are colleagues in this Chamber who are ducking and diving and refusing to say where they stand.  I do not think that is good enough for public representatives, regardless of what side of the debate one is on.  I accept it is a difficult issue but some things are more important than mere electoral gain and on some issues we need to say where we stand and stand by our principles and respect each other's principles.  The people in this Chamber who disappoint me are not those on the other side of the debate but the people who continue to hide.  I think we can do better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L00400"><p>I am glad Senator Gavan was not looking at the Chair in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L00500"><p>I do not wish to obtrude my religious views on this House but I speak today as a practising Christian and somebody who is very concerned about religious matters.  This is International Women&rsquo;s Day and the Voices of Faith organisation, an international organisation of committed Roman Catholics who deal with women have a conference in Rome about why women matter.  Two women have been excluded and banned from the group, by an Irishman as it happens, Cardinal Kevin Farrell.  It reminds me of the time when the Irish judge in the European Court of Human Rights voted against gay rights.  We can always find one of our own to stab us in the back.  Mrs. McAleese and Ms Ssenfuka Joanita Warry, who is from Uganda, and is extraordinarily courageous in defending the rights of gay people who are routinely murdered at the behest of the Christian churches in Uganda, have both been banned.</p>  <p>They join an enormous number of people who under the recent regimes have been persecuted, isolated and their careers destroyed.  I think of people like Archbishop Hunthausen, Charles Curran, Leonardo Boff and the Reverend Professor Dr. John O'Neill.  I could spend the whole morning listing them.  They have driven out the greatest spiritual thinkers of the Roman Catholic Church to its immense detriment, to a point where Mrs. McAleese, a former President of Ireland, has described the entire leadership of the church as mediocre.  I am afraid that is what they are.  Mary McAleese has been President of Ireland and she has been gratuitously insulted.  I think the Government should raise this with Rome.  This is an insult to a former President of Ireland by a foreign state.  Archbishop Martin, a decent man, who is Archbishop of Dublin was not consulted or even informed until Mrs. McAleese rang him.  She said the church's hierarchy has reduced Christ to a rather unattractive, misogynistic, homophobic, anti-abortion politician.  That is a pretty interesting charge for a former head of State of one of Europe's significant countries to make against the church to which she still belongs.  I pay tribute to her for hanging on in there and trying to operate from inside the church.  She speaks of misogynistic codology.  She describes the theological works she has read as complete codology.  They are of course.  I read Ratzinger's rubbish, his theological drivelling about sexuality.  I would fail a first year student for the kind of nonsense he went on with, but of course he is a Pope so he must be a genius because of his automatic connection.  He is another mediocrity.</p>  <p>Mrs. McAleese says the church has become an "empire of misogyny".  That is something that needs to be addressed by Seanad &Eacute;ireann on International Women's Day.  When a former President of Ireland, a brilliant lawyer and a remarkable campaigner is treated in this manner by the Roman Catholic Church I think we need to ask questions right at the top.  I think we need to raise the issue at Government level with the Vatican.</p>  <p>I do not really know the circumstances but Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in mentioned Sheriff Street.  I heard part of a programme just before I left the house about the cr&egrave;che which is being closed down.  It is a remarkable place which housed a whole complex of children's resources in that very deprived parish and an attempt is being made to close it down.  The centre is also home to a group known as the Little Larriers, after St. Laurence O'Toole, to whom the church is dedicated.  Those are people who dragged themselves up in an area that is polluted with drugs and alive with poverty yet they have made something and they are being stopped by bureaucracy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L00600"><p>Does Senator Norris know that he is in injury time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L00700"><p>Okay.  In that case thank you for warning me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L00800"><p>I should have warned the Senator two minutes ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L00900"><p>I will follow Senator Norris on a yellow card yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01000"><p>There is discretion for the father of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01100"><p>Those people are doing productive work in their parish and I think they should be encouraged.  Thank you very much for your indulgence, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01200"><p>On International Women's Day we were asked to think of the women who have inspired us.  In my case it was my wonderful and beautiful sister, Nicky, who died four years ago this month.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01500"><p>She was one of the kindest and most compassionate people I have ever had the privilege to know yet she was also one of the toughest and most determined women I have ever met.  Her toughness and determination helped her win a general election in 2011, for which she had fought for a very long time.  Unfortunately, she did not have enough time to enjoy it.  It also allowed her to fight a most awful disease, namely, motor neurone disease.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01600"><p>With great bravery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01700"><p>She fought it with great bravery and great dignity.  We need more people like Nicky McFadden in politics and in business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L01900"><p>Given that yesterday was Research Day, I ask the Leader to call on the Minister for Health to look at budgets for research.  Motor neurone disease is an unknown quantity.  Nobody knows what causes it or anything about it.  There is no cure for it.  A lot of research is being done in Trinity College and Beaumont Hospital with Professor Orla Hardiman but as with everything of that nature money is an issue.  I ask the Leader to urge the Minister to look into funding for research.</p>  <p>Yesterday, I spoke in the House about the fact that there are not enough women in politics or in business.  On this day I ask women and also men to encourage women to get involved in local and national politics and to get involved in business, on their merit, because they are good enough to do the job and not because of gender quotas.  What better way could we pay tribute to the people who pioneered votes for women in the early part of this century than to work towards gender parity in Parliament and society in general?  Let us take on the motto of those women, namely, "deeds not words".  Let us not just talk about gender parity, let us work towards it and let us make it happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="11:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800009#L02000"><p>I also wish to say a few things about women on the day that is in it.  It is not the easiest subject as it can be quite tricky with all the political correctness that is going on nowadays.</p> <p>Maurice Chevalier had a great song one time about how to handle a woman.  I do not think he would be allowed get away with a title such as that one these days.  However, I want to put on the record that I like women.  I love women, I respect women and I trust women.  It was my trust in women that informed my view and vote when I was a member of the recent Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution and it is that trust which will inform how I will act and canvass in the forthcoming referendum.</p> <p>This country has not quite decided on whether to trust women-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00200"><p>Fair play to you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00300"><p>-----and a lack of trust in women is at the core of much of the rhetoric we are hearing from the anti-choice groups.  The people of Ireland will shortly get an opportunity to articulate how much trust they have in the women of Ireland and I am fairly confident the people will not come up short.  Today I think of Kit Ahern who was a cousin of mine and a Senator in this House.  I worked for her and with her politically.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00400"><p>I remember her well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00500"><p>The Senator would.  She was a Senator in the 1960s and 1970s before she was elected to the D&aacute;il in 1977.  It was through her and arising from an admiration for her that I came into politics.  I will never forget what she had to undergo from sexist commentary by the male-dominated bear pit that was north Kerry politics in the 1960s and 1970s.  Expressions of anti-feminism used to issue regularly at comhairle ceantair and county council meetings and on the hustings.  It was a disgrace but she had the bravery and the guts to see over that and to best all those people.  It is women like her that were the leaders.  I congratulate women on the great strides they have made in this country within my own lifetime - we do not have to go back 100 years - and it is changing all the time.</p>  <p>For me, Senator Norris struck the key note in today's discussion.  I, too, am remarkably impressed by the courage and consistency of former President Mary McAleese.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00700"><p>She is obviously a committed Catholic.  I was born a Catholic and think I still am one, although I am regularly informed by theologians on Facebook and Twitter that I have been excommunicated several times.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00725"><p>That is the best kind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00750"><p>I continue to believe that I am a Catholic, however.  She is a committed Catholic and has the courage to call it as it is: an empire of misogyny.  What a thing to say in the year we are in today.  I will not concern myself with the affairs of the Catholic church but I congratulate the former President, Mary McAleese, who has uttered her views strongly and in a way that everyone understands.  One would not have to go to the Oxford dictionary to understand what she says, and I commend her on that too.</p>  <p>The day is gone when the women of Ireland are stereotyped as Mrs. Doyle making tea and sandwiches at the meetings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00800"><p>Go on, go on, go on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M00900"><p>Upwards and onwards, I say, to the women of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M01000"><p>I wish to raise two issues this morning.  One relates to St. Patrick's Day.  This is always a big day from an Irish point of view, with many Ministers travelling abroad, including to the United States.  I wish to raise the issue of having a more structured approach with the US House of Representatives and Senate.  When I served in the European Parliament, I had the privilege of serving on a joint committee of the European Parliament and the US Congress which met once every six months.  I have discussed with Senator Lawless the need arising from the fact that the UK, an English speaking country, is leaving the European Union, how one of the biggest places outside of Europe to which we export is the United States and the need for a structured approach on how we will deal with the States.</p>  <p>Many Irish companies work in the United States and many State agencies sell Ireland there and they are doing a very good job.  We should consider making direct contact with the US Senate and having a joint approach with it, even if it was only once every 12 months.  The visit of the Canadian delegation to the House yesterday was extremely helpful and useful.  There was an exchange of views.  We should look at this further because we should not just focus on America around St. Patrick's Day.  There is a far bigger issue now and we need to make that contact.  We should explore the possibility of having a direct link with the US Senate.  We should use the connection that is Senator Lawless to examine and develop this proposal further.</p>  <p>The second matter relates to my Commencement matter this morning about those who are available to perform marriage ceremonies on Saturdays and Sundays.  Currently, registrars of births, deaths and marriages perform the ceremonies from 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., Monday to Friday, but they are not available on Saturdays.  I pulled the figures on registered solemnisers and found out that there are 5,630 religious solemnisers, 123 civil solemnisers and 31 secular solemnisers.  That is not a proportionate representation in terms of the numbers of those who are available to preside over marriage ceremonies on Saturdays and Sundays.</p>  <p>My Commencement matter considered whether notaries public could be appointed to fill that role where registrars are not available.  I want to explore this further because I believe we need to examine the issue.  The Minister of State's reply was that there are no proposals at present to deal with this issue but we should be examining it and the current registration process.  As I understand it, the Humanist Association of Ireland has 30 people registered and Aisling &Aacute;rann Teoranta has one.  They are secular solemnisers.  There are also 123 civil solemnisers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M01100"><p>What are secular solemnisers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M01200"><p>There are 31 people registered-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M01300"><p>What are they?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M01400"><p>They are those in the Humanist Association of Ireland and Aisling Arran Teoranta.  We should not leave this as it is because the situation around the issue is changing.  We have had marriage equality legislation and there have been changes in a number of other areas.  The process for religious marriage ceremonies remains the same, however, and we need to examine it.  The Minister of State told me this morning that it was not being examined but we need to put it on the agenda in this House and open up the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="11:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800010#M01500"><p>It is genuinely great to hear inspiring debate, conversation and insight from every single one of my colleagues this morning.  It was a good quality debate on a whole lot of aspects, particularly relating to International Women's Day.  This is not just a pet for Christmas but something for life.  It is fundamentally important.  As the House knows, I am involved in business and I would say that 75% of all senior management is female.  This is because they have a skill set, ability and talent to achieve.  I wish to speak about the team of females who work with us.  Ms Bridget Doody and her team are the backbone and they help us function and achieve what we aim to achieve.  I ask that we all acknowledge the team of female support in leadership roles and others in the Seanad and the D&aacute;il and what they do to help make this place function and be effective.</p>  <p>I have been very involved in entrepreneurship over a number of years and have chaired the entrepreneur of the year judging panel for years.  We get quite a small number of female entrepreneurs coming forward and it is reducing a little.  After the recession the number of entrepreneurs coming forward is reducing anyway.  This is a big issue.  People are afraid or are concerned about taking a leap or risk because they do not want to lose their house and everything that they have and they know what it is like to deal with the banks.</p> <p>I am asking everyone in this House to work collectively as a team.  This is not political.  We need to see what we can do to support entrepreneurship and to help male and, in particular, female entrepreneurs who have incredible ability to achieve in line with their talents.  Unfortunately, I did not meet Nicky McFadden, but I have heard a lot about her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N00200"><p>She was a great woman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N00300"><p>From what I hear, Nicky and her sister, Senator Gabrielle McFadden, were cut from the one cloth.  I congratulate Senator McFadden.  I mean that.  While I am speaking about entrepreneurship and job creation, I would like to say that one of the best things a person can do in life is to give somebody a job.  When a person gives somebody a job, he or she gives that person a choice and an opportunity and puts money in his or her pocket to spend as he or she wishes.  To me, entrepreneurship is key to a functioning economy.  As Enterprise Ireland has recognised, female entrepreneurship is essential in that regard.  The chief executive of Enterprise Ireland, Julie Sinnamon, has a team that is focused on female entrepreneurship and is creating incredible success, way above the European average, in supporting the development of female entrepreneurship.  I ask all Senators to support this in every way possible.  I would like to make a final point about something I have a huge issue with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N00400"><p>You have exceeded the time available to you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N00500"><p>I am in injury time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N00600"><p>You are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N00700"><p>We can have a penalty shoot-out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N00800"><p>We have plenty of time.  There is no hurry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N00900"><p>I thank the Deputy Leader.  This morning, I saw a newspaper headline, "Use bank profits to write off more debt, says EU", on an issue that has been bothering me for a while.  I do not think there is anyone in this House who was not directly or indirectly hit during the recession when the banks were giving people hassle and seeking to get their pound of flesh.  The banks are making huge profits now.  Quite frankly, it is criminal that no tax is being paid on those profits.  Will the Deputy Leader impress on the Minister for Finance the need, which is now being supported by the European Commission, for the profits being made by the banks to be put back into the economy, into entrepreneurship and into hospitals?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01100"><p>I do not know how many Members of this House have been to any of our hospitals over the past two or three weeks.  I have been a frequent visitor for a particular reason.  The doctors and nurses are amazing people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01300"><p>The carers are incredible people too.  One of the big issues in our hospitals is that the vast majority of people leave their lunch or breakfast on the tray because they cannot eat it.  These meals are picked up again an hour afterwards without having been eaten because our hospitals do not have sufficient staff to feed people who are sick.  Quite simply, this means that people go day after day without eating any food.  I apologise for going so far into injury time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01400"><p>Yes.  I know Senator Devine will be more to the point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01500"><p>I will try.  The Chair will give me some leeway because it is International Women's Day.  I commend and respect Senator Ned O'Sullivan for what he has said.  I think his journey, which he has shared, will help this country to make its decision on the eighth amendment.  I thank him for his thoughtful contribution which was devoid of spin.  I would have to be forgiven if I did not talk about women on International Women's Day.  It is important to talk about women given that we comprise over half, perhaps 52%, of the population of the world.  I love Irish women and I love to reach out internationally to other women throughout the world who are in very difficult circumstances.  I was at Richmond Barracks in Inchicore this morning with the women from Palestine.  I want to repeat in this Chamber an extract from a poem, Here We Shall Stay, that was read at this morning's wonderful event:</p><blockquote>We shall remain<br /><br />a wall upon your chest,<br /><br />clean dishes in your bars,<br /><br />serve drinks in your restaurants,<br /><br />sweep the floors of your kitchens<br /><br />to snatch a bite for our children<br /><br />from your blue fangs.<br /><br />Here we shall stay,<br /><br />sing our songs,<br /><br />take to the angry streets,<br /><br />fill prisons with dignity.<br /><br />In Lidda, in Ramla, in the Galilee,<br /><br />we shall remain,<br /><br />guard the shade of the fig<br /><br />and olive trees,<br /><br />ferment rebellion in our children<br /><br />as yeast in the dough.</blockquote><p>Free Palestine.  Go raibh maith agat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01600"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01700"><p>Mar fhocal scoir, before I call the Leader, I want to say that International Women's Day is of particular significance this year as we commemorate the centenary of women's suffrage in Ireland.  It is most welcomed in this House through the leadership of Senator Bacik on the V&oacute;t&aacute;il 100 working group, which is playing a central role in ensuring the importance of this historic event is highlighted.  Perhaps I should have said that at the beginning, but I did not want to speak for too long.  I call the Deputy Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01800"><p>I thank the 18 Senators who spoke on the Order of Business today.  I would like to confirm that 6 o'clock is the time I was given by the Leader's office today for the conclusion of the debate on the Technological Universities Bill 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N01900"><p>I appreciate that the Deputy Leader has returned to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N02000"><p>I just wanted to provide clarity.  The debate could very easily be completed in advance of that.  Senator Mark Daly and many other Senators spoke about International Women's Day.  Senator Daly mentioned a 106 year old lady who has passed away.  It is a phenomenal age for anyone to achieve.  I think the statistics show that more ladies than men live to the age of 100.  Obviously, they are doing something right.  They are probably living healthier lives than men.  We should be following their example in many ways, particularly in terms of health and the ability to live longer.</p>  <p>Senator Daly also referred to the two brave ladies who gave evidence at the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality yesterday.  I attended that meeting and I found their testimony breathtaking.  That they were treated in such a cavalier fashion by senior management is a reflection of the challenges that have been faced by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  As everyone in the House will agree, the rank and file members of the force do a great job but there have been serious deficiencies at senior management level.  We hope those deficiencies will be dealt with.  The Policing Authority has been in place since 2016.  There has been a call to take the politics out of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  The Policing Authority represents an attempt to do that.  I note that representatives of the authority will come before the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality in two weeks to address the serious issues that were raised by the two ladies yesterday.  I look forward to hearing what they have to say.</p>  <p>Senator Mullen spoke about the issue of gender equality in the context of International Women's Day.  All Members of this House agree that gender equality should just happen, rather than being something we merely aspire to.  I certainly agree with the Senator's viewpoint on this issue.</p>  <p>With regard to what the Senator said about abortion and the eighth amendment issue, I note that the Cabinet signed off today on the wording of the referendum.  That legislation will come before the D&aacute;il tomorrow and will certainly come before this House after the St. Patrick's Day break.  At the end of May, the people will have their say on whether the eighth amendment should be repealed.  Like everybody here, I hope the debate will be respectful.</p>  <p>I agree with Senator Dolan that yesterday was a great day for people with disabilities, but it is really only the start.  I am standing in for the Leader today.  I think it is the first time somebody with a disability has taken the Order of Business in the House.  I thank the Leader for that opportunity.  It is the first time I have done this in my seven years in the House.  I think it is fitting that it is happening the day after D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann ratified the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N02100"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="11:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800011#N02200"><p>I hope it is the first of many occasions on which I will take the Order of Business.  I agree with Senator Dolan that we should have a debate on the implementation of the convention.</p> <p>He is quite right.  A commitment was given in this House by the Leader that such a debate would happen.  I also agree with what he said about bringing in people with lived experience of disability because disability is a broad church.  Everybody who experiences it has different stories and testimonies.  In the spirit of the public consultation committee chaired by the Cathaoirleach, perhaps we could have that type of civil engagement with people with disabilities within that type of structure.  I pay tribute to the ongoing work of Senator Dolan through his role as chief executive of the Disability Federation of Ireland and as a Member of Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  He is always discussing the issue.  In many ways, he has very sensible and logical solutions.  He is quite right when he contends that it should be an all-of-Government response and that all of us here in our roles as spokespeople should be factoring in our responsibilities and advocating for the ethos of the convention to be embodied and embedded in every element of work we do across Departments.  Yesterday will be a day that will go down in history but I hope it will be for the right reasons.  I look forward, as does Senator Dolan, to 2028 when, hopefully, we will be a country that not just talks about equality but can turn around and say we are a country of equals for all our citizens.  </p> <p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in spoke about the eighth amendment and when he taught in Sheriff Street.  I have no doubt that he was an inspiring teacher.  As has been said, people will have the opportunity to vote on the eighth amendment when the referendum comes before us.  Hopefully, people will make the right decision based on their conscience but they will have the vote and the opportunity to vote, which is important.  </p> <p>Senator Feighan also spoke about International Women's Day.  He spoke about not taking potshots at An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Yes, there are issues at senior management level but the vast majority of garda&iacute; do a good job on a daily basis keeping us safe in our homes and ensuring that people can walk the streets in safe way.  It is also worth noting that the Behaviour &amp;amp; Attitudes survey which is carried out each year about the public's view of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na shows that the figure of people who have absolute confidence in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na fluctuates between 75% and 86%.  This should be noted and amplified.  Many people have confidence in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.</p> <p>Senator Conway-Walsh spoke about the domestic violence legislation that passed through this House.  I will speak to the Leader and ask him to make contact with his colleagues in the Lower House to see what the timeline is.  I am sure he will get back to the Senator on that in due course.</p> <p>Senator Davitt spoke about the situation with eircodes and security companies.  What he said makes sense, which is that security companies should be required to have the eircodes of their customers.  Eircodes are there for a reason.  It is supposed to make things efficient.  I cannot understand why they would not have them.  We have seen significant advancements in regulating the security industry.  Ten or 15 years ago, the security industry in this country was not properly regulated at all.  Now that situation is totally different.  There is proper Garda vetting and licences that clubs and various other facilities that use security must possess.  Perhaps this is something the security industry regulator could look at because the proposition makes sense.  </p> <p>Senator Craughwell requested a debate on defence, the situation in the Air Corps and the fact that so many people are leaving.  Yes, it is worrying and I am sure we can organise a debate here with the Minister of State with responsibility for defence in due course.</p> <p>Senator Reilly spoke about the women who inspire him.  I must agree with him that a lot of the time, the women who inspire us are those closest to us and those who we love and who help us achieve what we do achieve.  I know Senator Reilly's son.  He is a remarkable person.  I also know Senator Reilly's wife who is also a remarkable person.  They make up a remarkable family and can be very proud of what their son has achieved.  I know their son will go on to achieve an awful lot more in the years to come.  I am delighted that he is sharing his story with schoolchildren around the country because it is seeing and hearing living examples of people overcoming challenges and difficulties that creates role models for other people.  He is right to raise every week the Bill about a national strategy for autism that was passed unanimously here.  I will certainly talk to the Leader and see if he can establish what the situation with the Bill in D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann is.</p> <p>Senator Gavan spoke about the march on the eighth amendment that is taking place this evening.  He is right to highlight it.  If people believe in that, they should go to the march.</p> <p>Senator Norris spoke about Mary McAleese and the lady from Nigeria.  I heard the media reports where the former President described the Roman Catholic Church as an empire of misogyny.  It is very hard to argue with her to some degree but I admire her for staying in the Catholic Church and trying to change it from within.  She is doing good work in that regard.  I suggest that Senator Norris submits the matter of the cr&egrave;che in Sheriff Street as a Commencement matter to get some clarity on what the situation is.</p> <p>My good friend, Senator McFadden, spoke about her sister Nicky, who was a good friend of mine.  Nicky was one of the ladies who would inspire one just by speaking to her in terms of her kind personality and steely determination.  I met Nicky for the first time in 2007 when she was standing in the Seanad elections.  I instantly developed a bond and a friendship with her.  She went on to win her seat in the D&aacute;il in 2011.  Those of us who were Members of the Houses at the time saw at first hand how she battled motor neurone disease.  Senator McFadden is cut from the same cloth.  We could highlight the issue she raised, namely, research and funding for research into motor neurone, at some stage in a future debate.  I acknowledge the research into this area carried out by Professor Hardiman in Trinity College, which is very welcome.  </p> <p>Senator Ned O'Sullivan spoke about his journey and experience and what he learned from serving on the Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution.  He certainly articulated that very well.  We all learn from the women in our lives and the women we work and interact with on a daily basis.  The Senator's aunt, Kit Ahern, sounded like an amazing woman.  As soon as he heard her name, Senator Norris had an affectionate response.  It is not easy to impress Senator Norris so she must have been a formidable lady.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P00100"><p>He spoke the truth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P00200"><p>Indeed.  </p>  <p>Senator Colm Burke discussed relationships with the US Congress.  As an island nation, we need to export to the United States, with which we have good ties, including the visit on St. Patrick's Day, but we should probably be developing a more structured interparliamentary relationship.  In Deputy John Deasy we have a colleague who is representing us in America, specifically on the matter of the undocumented Irish.  Perhaps the Leader might arrange for him to come to the House to update us on his work.  We could also consider inviting the Minister of State with responsibility for the diaspora to attend the House.  Having a more structured and formalised link with the US Congress Washington is something that could be considered.</p>  <p>The Leader might revert to the Senator in due course on the question of wedding solemnisers.</p>  <p>Senator P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh raised the issue of women in business in the context of International Women's Day.  He referred to how women with whom he had worked were on his senior management team and operated in the various units of his business, how they had made a significant contribution to it and how he had learned from them.  As a nation, we need to determine how we can fund and challenge more women to become entrepreneurs.</p>  <p>Senator M&aacute;ire Devine also mentioned that it was International Women's Day.  The poem written by the women from Palestine that she read said it all.  There is nothing more I can add, except to say we should listen to their words.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.106" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.107" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P00400">Committee of Selection: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P00500"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the Sixth Report of the Committee of Selection be laid before the Seanad.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.109" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.110" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P00700">Address by Mr. Mchel  Muircheartaigh: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P00800"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann agrees with the recommendation of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges that, in accordance with Standing Order 57(2) of the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, Mr. M&iacute;che&aacute;l &Oacute; Muircheartaigh be invited to address Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 21st March 2018 and, unless otherwise ordered, the following arrangements shall apply.<br /><br />The proceedings, in respect of the address, which shall not exceed two hours, shall consist of-&ndash;<i>(a) </i>a speech of welcome by the Cathaoirleach,<br /><br /><i>(b) </i>an address by Mr. M&iacute;che&aacute;l &Oacute; Muircheartaigh,<br /><br /><i>(c) </i>a contribution not exceeding five minutes by a spokesperson from each Group,<br /><br /><i>(d) </i>a contribution not exceeding three minutes from other Senators,<br /><br /><i>(e) </i>a contribution not exceeding three minutes from the Leas-Chathaoirleach,<br /><br /><i>(f) </i>a concluding response of not less than ten minutes by Mr. M&iacute;che&aacute;l &Oacute; Muircheartaigh,<br /><br /><i>(g) </i>a speech of thanks by the Leader of the House.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.112" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.113" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P01000">Planning and Development Acts 2000 to 2017 (Increase in Number of Ordinary Members of An Bord Pleanla) Order 2018: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P01100"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Order in draft:Planning and Development Acts 2000 to 2017 (Increase in Number of Ordinary Members of An Bord Plean&aacute;la) Order 2018,copies of which have been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 21st February 2018, be referred to the Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government, in accordance with Standing Order 71(3)(k), which, not later than 29th March 2018, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.115" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.116" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P01300">Flooding: Statements (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P01400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Kevin Boxer Moran.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="12:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800013#P01500"><p>I, too, welcome the Minister of State.  On a personal note, as this is my first one-to-one engagement with him since our last engagement in the chamber in Mullingar a mere two years ago, I congratulate him on his elevation to ministerial office in that short period.  Unfortunately, that is where the plaudits end.  I know his background.  He is very passionate about this issue which he has dealt with locally.  As someone who lives on the banks of the River Shannon and is an able and eager fisherman, he is more aware than many of the problems experienced.  He inherited his role, as well as many of the issues about which I have a gripe, but I would like to see improvements in the future.</p>  <p>The major issue is the underspend.  We were promised an allocation of &euro;45 million per annum between 2011 and 2017 for the provision of flood defences.  To date, there has been an underspend of &euro;53 million.  In the national development plan for the period 2018 to 2027 the predicted spend has been increased to &euro;100 million per annum.  I hope this does not mean there will be an equivalent increase in the underspend in the area within the Minister of State's remit.</p>  <p>The provision of an effective national flood warning system is at least five years down the line, which is not acceptable in the light of current circumstances.  Flooding issues seem to recur daily.  I will not get into the debate on climate change, but flooding seems to be occurring more frequently.</p>  <p>Flood defences and warning systems aside, the main issue remains the insurance industry which is cherry-picking customers.  Quotations and refusals even to give people a quote are based on catchment flood risk assessment and management, CFRAM, studies and areas that flooded previously.  Fianna F&aacute;il's Flood Insurance Bill 2016 would address these issues, but it is being stymied by the Government's refusal to issue a money message.  If the Government is not going to do something about the issue, why is it stopping us from trying to do something positive?</p>  <p>I may not be happy with the amount of work done, given how much more needs to be done, but insurance companies are not even recognising the great work that has been done.  The Minister of State's predecessor, Deputy Se&aacute;n Canney, agreed that, although a &euro;140 million flood investment programme was in operation in Cork, the insurance companies would not cover properties in the area once the work had been completed.  This issue has to be addressed immediately.</p>  <p>It has been proved that a &euro;280 million spend on flood defences will result in a net saving of &euro;1.2 billion once the work is completed.  In some cases work is not being done quickly enough because of planning delays.  The Government needs to get the local authorities on side in the affected areas.  This is a major issue.</p>  <p>I am informed that there have been 107 applicants under the voluntary homeowners relocation scheme, 26 of whom have been told that they do not qualify, while only eight have been approved.</p> <p>Where are the other 73 people?  I would like to hear that from the Minister of State.  What is their current status?  They are in limbo.  People had to do a great deal of soul searching before they even agreed to apply for this scheme.  For a person to move from his or her home where that person was probably born and lived all his or her life is a serious and difficult decision for anyone to make, but having made that decision and submitted the application, only eight out of 107 applications have been approved.  I accept that the 26 who have not been approved know where they stand, but there are 73 people in limbo in this regard and I would like to know their current status.  I would like to know also if the 26 people who have been told they do not qualify for relocation will be prioritised for remedial schemes.  What is their current status?</p> <p>I refer to the River Shannon which, as I said at the outset, I am aware is dear to the Minister of State's heart, but it should be the main focus of our attention.  It is Ireland's first and foremost river.  It rises in the Shannon Pot, in County Cavan, and continues for approximately 360 km until it disgorges its waste into the Atlantic Ocean at Clare, Kerry and Limerick.  Fianna F&aacute;il, building on the recommendations of a 2021 report by the then Joint Committee on the Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht, advocates a single agency to cut through the bureaucratic layers.  I almost addressed the Minister of State as "Boxer".  I was thinking of the chamber in Mullingar again.  How long were we discussing this issue at that level?  Westmeath and the Minister of State's home town, Athlone, form an integral site on the Shannon.</p> <p>The current Shannon flood risk State agency co-ordination working group simply reconstitutes a non-statutory body that Fine Gael abolished in 1994.  What is needed is a legislative basis with real teeth to avoid bureaucratic delays and take whatever action is necessary to manage the Shannon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.120" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Acting Chairman (Senator John Mahony)" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800014#Q00200"><p>The Senator must conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800014#Q00300"><p>Time is against me.  We seem to be concentrating on flood defences.  The Shannon and other rivers need to be looked at and we need to consider seriously, through a new agency, dredging these rivers.  I am spokesperson on agriculture and while tackling the flooding of people's homes is and must be a priority, it is not even considered that thousands of acres of farmland are lost to water every year.  Dredging and proper management of the Shannon would alleviate the pressures for those individuals also.  I do not want to take from the grief, the hardship and the priority that should be given to people's homes, but flood defences are in ways a makeshift solution in areas, whereas if the River Shannon and other similar size rivers were dredged properly, it would not only alleviate the homeowners' problems but would also free up the thousands of acres that are unworkable for six to eight months of the year in many cases for our agricultural community.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800014#Q00400"><p>I will probably not take the five minutes.  My two colleagues, Senator Conway-Walsh and Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn, spoke previously.</p>  <p>The Minister of State is very welcome to the House.  It is good to see him.  I want to speak from a Dublin perspective about the impact of coastal erosion along the east coast of Dublin.  The Office of Public Works has several flood defences mapped out under the eastern regional flood risk and assessment management plan.  I will be parochial in saying that some of them have been delayed or postponed, some for years.  Will the Minister of State give me an update on the Camac and Poddle rivers?  The Camac runs through Kilmainham and Inchicore and the Poddle through Kimmage and parts of Crumlin.  In terms of the Camac river, I walked around the area two weeks ago.  There is a greenway proposed from the HSE headquarters at Dr. Steevens' Hospital right up to Military Road for pedestrianisation and for cycle lanes but also for a widening of the Camac because there was severe damage from flooding in 2011 at Our Lady's Lane and around that low lying area of Kilmainham.  There is a difficulty, which seems to be top secret, with the plan for the new Garda operations centre at Military Road.  That seems to be impacting now upon the widening of the Camac river in that area.  Will the Minister of State give me an update on whether that greenway, which will prevent flooding in the future, will go ahead?  A culvert collapsed there in 2015.  All that needs to be managed but it seems a Garda top secret planning application may override that, leaving that area very vulnerable to flooding in the future.  I do not have more to say other than to ask the Minister of State to elaborate on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800014#Q00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House for the second time this week.  I will raise with him an issue I raised on the Order of Business two days ago but first I will speak in a general way to the issue of flooding throughout the country and the fact that this will be an ever-increasing problem as a result of climate change, which we have to acknowledge.  It does not fall to the Minister of State but we need to start thinking outside the box, particularly in terms of all the farming sheds throughout the country that could be covered in solar panels and photovoltaics.</p>  <p>The other issue I have raised here numerous times and will have to raise again on the Order of Business is the lack of guidelines for local authorities on solar farms.  We should be helping and encouraging people into the renewable energy sector and not making life more difficult.  I know of one local farmer who had his application refused on the basis that there were no guidelines.</p>  <p>In the short time available to me I want to address a local issue but I want to acknowledge the great work done by the Office of Public Works, OPW, and the great amounts of money that are being spent and are due to be spent such as the &euro;140 million to be spent in Cork, the issues in Clonmel that we saw on television every year but which have been addressed, and the &euro;10 million that was to be spent in Crossmolina, the town my father hailed from, among many others.</p>  <p>The issue I want to focus on is the coastal erosion in north Dublin, particularly in Portrane but also in Rush.  We have an emergency in Portrane.  We have a family living in a house that is literally 3 ft from the edge of the cliff.  There is nothing like standing there to realise the precariousness of the situation.  The corner of the building is literally 3 ft from the edge of the cliff and a 20 ft drop.  Three generations of a family live in the house - Grainne, Amy and Fay - and their house will fall into the sea.  I was down there in 2012 with the then Minister of State, Brian Hayes, when we had serious coastal erosion.  I recall the struggle locals got involved in to put bags in place to protect the cliff.  Those bags are now nearly 40 ft from the cliff edge.  They were at the foot of the cliff at that time.  We were told this was a once in a lifetime event but we have it again now, and as I said earlier, with climate change we will see more of it.</p>  <p>I know the Minister of State is working to try to address this issue with the local council and the local authority.  I have appealed to Fingal County Council to take emergency action on it because it is a humanitarian issue and we do not want to see this family made homeless, but that is what will happen.  In all, there are 13 houses in danger in a very immediate way, but as I said the other day, if the water breaches a small mound a few more yards in, it will flood and dislocate the Burrow from the rest of the peninsula, where 1,200 to 1,500 people live.  That will cost considerable sums of money to correct so why can we not do something now to bring people together?  I called for that 12 months ago.  I know that is the Minister of State's intention and I wish him well with it, but he needs to knock heads together and get the interested parties who are involved in this to come up with a solution.  The time for talking is long passed.  I refer to Fingal County Council, the OPW, the Department of Culture, Heritage and the Gaeltacht and planning officials.</p>  <p>While we are very interested in the environment and special areas of conservation, we cannot have a situation where lives and livelihoods are to be lost for the sake of a rigid interpretation of special areas of conservation.  I was never one of the people who kept blaming Europe for all our ills, and I will not blame it for our ills in this case either.  It is up to us to negotiate a realistic settlement and find a way of dealing with this problem.  Lives and livelihoods are at stake as well as a person's right to their home.  This house has been in that location since before 1963 so let there be no talk of other issues.  This family are entitled to feel safe in their own home, and as we speak they are not safe.</p>  <p>This area will be seriously afflicted in the very short term if some action is not taken.</p> <p>This family is in immediate danger.  There is no greater neglect than when one knows the danger and does nothing about it.  Again I appeal to Fingal County Council.  I recognise all the great work it has done during the weather crisis of recent days, all the good work it does and the plans it has for a coastal greenway which would be brilliant for people from north County Dublin, people coming in from the airport, and the people of Dublin generally because we are well served by trains all the way down the track.  However, we need urgent action for this family.  I appeal to the Minister of State to use his influence to encourage people to come together to find an immediate solution for this problem while we work on a more medium-term solution.  A win-win situation is possible here because the works to be done can be done in such a way as to set the scene for the ultimate coastal greenway which will be put in.  Time and tide wait for no man, woman or child and they will not wait for this family.  It will be on our heads if we do not take action.  That would not be a good reflection of all the excellent work which has been carried out to date by both the local authority and the Minister of State's Department, which I commend for the work it has done in keeping us safe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800015#R00200"><p>To refer to the expression that time and tide wait for no man; tide, time and climate change will wait for no man, woman or human being on this planet.  My party's stance on the issue of planning and construction on flood plains is well known to the Minister and State and others so I will not labour it too much today.  However, I do think it bears repeating that any approach to flood prevention must consider the climate future at which we are looking.  Global warming, rising temperatures, increased rainfall and greater instability will mean that areas on flood plains and near major watercourses which are currently designated for the development of housing will simply have to be abandoned.  It is better to do that before construction commences and before people make these areas their homes.</p>  <p>To refer again to what Senator Reilly said, what is happening in terms of coastal erosion is incredible.  I see it around my home town of Tramore.  We have to start thinking of the families living in properties on the coastal fringe, close to the sea.  We have to start making mitigation plans.  As Senator Reilly said, this has to be done now because houses are falling into the sea in some places.  It is happening in Dublin and in Wexford.  We have a huge problem on our hands.  All national legislation, local area development plans and, indeed, the national planning framework must reflect and react to this oncoming reality, lest we box ourselves and future generations into very unsafe corners.</p>  <p>I would also like to address the preservation of the natural barriers to flooding which we enjoy in some places.  Coming from the town of Tramore and having seen the violent storms we have experienced - the end of a hurricane like Ophelia and Storm Emma - I note that we were told that events like this would happen only once in our lifetime.  We are not seeing them once in our lifetime however, but multiple times.  It is not that we are living longer.  We are seeing this as a result of global warming and climate change.  Everything must be done to support communities.  We must defend natural defences to make sure that they function when the high tides and big waves come in.  This applies to riverside natural defences and wetland areas that can cushion the force of high water levels at times of peak rainfall.  </p>  <p>There is an area in Tramore called the Back Strand.  It is a special area of conservation covering 500 ha.  Mitigation work was carried out there a few years ago.  Part of the Back Strand area that used to flood was opened up.  Back in the early 1900s there had been defence mechanisms there.  It has been opened up to create a sponge area.  It will mitigate the force of flooding and it will save our sand dune system for a time.  There are actions that can be taken and which we must take to ensure that communities, farmers and agricultural lands are supported in this regard.</p>  <p>I have also addressed an issue in the Seanad previously in respect of the people of Cork, our Seanad Leader's county.  The people of Cork - men and women who love their city - are coming to us in the Green Party, calling us and sending us emails because of their concerns for the River Lee and their love of their natural surroundings and their city.  They are adamant that the proposals for thicker walls on the river within the city are inappropriate, disproportionate and will fundamentally alter the feel and the look of the city, cutting it off from its very core.  I ask the Minister of State to engage with the people and campaigning groups in Cork and to let the conversation go on.  I am a great believer that if one consults well with communities they will give one the answers.  They know the answers.  They live there.  They have that feel for the environment and the experience of living in it.  They will help us to get the solutions.  I ask the Minister of State to engage with the people of Cork and with the people who are concerned about the area of Cork city in order to ensure that whatever defences are put in place are appropriate to protect the city of Cork not just for now but for the medium and long term.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800015#R00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and commend him for the work he is doing.  I also thank him for his proactivity and his presence here today.  This is a very important debate.  I want to begin where Senator Grace O'Sullivan ended in terms of Cork city and the need to protect it from future flooding.  The history of flooding in Cork city is well documented and well known.  The effect on homeowners and businesses is devastating with the costs of damage running into the hundreds of millions of euro.  It has a profound effect and impact on the lives of people and business owners.  Senator Grace O'Sullivan is right.  We all love our city and want to see it protected.  There is a debate going on regarding alternative proposals and there has been consultation.  I was at a public meeting in City Hall and I know that there is consultation ongoing regarding Morrison's Island.  I commend the OPW for its work in drawing up proposals.  I agree with Senator Grace O'Sullivan that we should not allow projects for Cork to be lost or further delayed.  It is imperative that we act now.  I am sure there can be a meeting of minds between the two groups.</p>  <p>Flood relief and flood defence are very important.  We have a duty of care to the people affected.  We should picture and put ourselves in the minds of the business people and home owners who hear a weather alert about the possibility of future flooding in Cork.  Imagine how they felt last week when Paschal Sheehy was on the 6.01 p.m. and 9 p.m. news speaking about potential flooding due to the snow.  It has a devastating impact.  I stood in people's kitchens, living rooms and business premises that had been damaged and affected by flooding.  We must look after such people.  That is our duty now.  </p>  <p>I welcome the &euro;6 million plan for the regeneration of Morrison's Island.  It is about enhancing the public realm, but also about putting in place a flood defence project.  There are many talking points and topics of discussion emanating from the public consultation and the information days that have been held.  There is another such day tomorrow.  As the Senator correctly said, that is the benefit of public consultation.  People can feed into the process and present their viewpoints.  The OPW must work with all of us - which it is doing - to ensure that we create a flood defence plan.</p> <p>Tidal flood events in Cork are becoming more prevalent.  I commend the Save Cork City group on its interaction and engagement.  It has helped stimulate debate and presented many different viewpoints that perhaps would not otherwise get heard.  We cannot allow a position where there will be a decision to stall rather than move on this plan.</p> <p>I was very hopeful when I read the national planning framework, which speaks about Cork.  It indicates that further to completion of the lower flood relief scheme, the issue of flood management must be addressed as part of any future strategy for Cork, particularly with respect to the edge of the city adjoining the River Lee.  That is to be welcomed.  I know the Minister of State is sincere and very genuine in his work on the Cork issue.  We cannot allow a position to continue where there is fear of flooding and actual flooding.  We have seen a genuine attempt made to ensure Cork is protected and we must act as the people of Cork will not forgive us if we do not.  This is a time for leadership by all of us.  If it means knocking heads together - I know the Minister of State is good at that and getting things done - we should do that.  I thank the Minister of State for his interest, his courtesy and availability to meet at all times.  I have always found him very accessible.  We have a duty to the people of Cork to ensure a flood defence mechanism can be put in place, and I hope we can do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1363" speakername="Kevin  Moran" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800016#S00200"><p>I am guided by Senators.  I am delighted to be here today to finish the debate, and flooding is a major issue around the country.  For every Member in this and the other House, there are constituents who are worried and concerned about it.  As some Senators have said, when we hear of rain and commentators on television speaking about flooding, alarms can be raised in everybody's mind, none more so than my own.  When I came to the House the last day, there were a number of questions.  Will I reply to the questions from today and provide a written response to the others or read the response to all the queries?  I can leave it in the hands of the Acting Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800016#S00300"><p>We have until 1.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1363" speakername="Kevin  Moran" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800016#S00400"><p>I will go ahead so.  A number of Senators raised questions relating to climate change.  It is a major concern for each and every one of us and it faces us on the doorsteps.  Some politicians want to ignore it but I was very impressed coming here as so many Senators spoke about climate change, both on the previous day and today.  We must all deal with climate change; we cannot ignore it.  It is coming down the tracks.  Every flood defence, including embankments and walls, takes climate change into consideration, especially with the rise in sea levels and increased rainfall.  The Office of Public Works, OPW, is very much on its game with respect to climate change.</p>  <p>Senator Paul Daly, along with a great number of others, raised the matter of insurance.  Working with Insurance Ireland and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, I have come a long way since my first discussion about insurance.  There is 78% coverage where we build flood walls or embankments, so insurance companies are insuring.  There are issues but this is a matter for the Department.  People here and in other places maintain that once a flood embankment is built, it is up to the OPW to insure them.  We have a memorandum of understanding with insurance companies and we liaise with them, giving them information.  In the past two years there has been a major improvement in insurance matters.</p>  <p>Catchment flood risk and assessment, CFRAM, is another matter that has long been spoken of.  I spoke about it at a local level for ten years.  It has identified 130 schemes right around the country.  We are talking about 40,000 maps right around the country.  In the process of delivering on those 130 schemes, we saw Galway, Donegal and Mountmellick being flooded, along with places like Bandon.  CFRAM identified those.  I am happy to say I have the 29 flood maps back from the Department and we are meeting the week after next to finalise a date for announcing CFRAM.  It will be announced in Athlone in the coming weeks.  I assure every Member in the House that I have put much effort into this.  I have put much time into travelling around the country and meeting so many people affected by the issues.  When Senators put down questions they come to me and the reply usually speaks about waiting for CFRAM.  We are now coming to an end and CFRAM is to be delivered in the coming days.</p>  <p>Everybody believes the home relocation scheme is a fix for all people but it is not.  Some people may have spent hours protecting their homes over three, four and five weeks and others would have seen their houses flooded.  We set up a home relocation scheme to see what we could do for those people.  There were 107 applications and 21 did not make the grade.  My Department has asked those applicants to come back in.  Some, particularly those along the Shannon, have said to me that if I can keep the water at the level it was this year, they would rather stay in their house as they do not want to relocate.  At the same time, some people want to relocate.  We have a roadshow at present which is meeting those people and trying to speed up the process of delivery.  I am happy at the pace as it is not simple; we cannot just turn around and present this.  It is a major issue for people to hand over the keys of their houses and not live where their sons and daughters were reared.  Some people do not want to go.  We are giving much consideration to this and working very closely with local authorities to ensure that the people who want to go and who qualify for the scheme will get a result.  I am happy in that regard.</p>  <p>In the past number of weeks we have sped up the process.  There are approximately 75 eligible applications and we are working through it.  I do not deny it is a slow process from both sides.  Senator Paul Daly said some people are wondering why it is taking so long.  We have written to some people who have not come back to us yet.  People have contacted me by phone and have told me they do not want to move.  I must take all that into consideration.</p>  <p>A number of Senators raised the minor works scheme.  We give &euro;3 million per year for minor works and some local authorities around the country are better than others in coming for that money.  Some are very slow to act.  I say to Senators to go back to local councillors and local authority personnel and tell them where there are flooding issues.  We have changed the criteria and this has made more authorities and schemes eligible for the fund.</p>  <p>I will deal with some of today's questions.  Senator Paul Daly spoke about a potential lack of spending but he is wrong.  Fianna F&aacute;il has put out that information.  In 2015, &euro;16 million was not spent.  For 2016 and 2017, I could have spent more than I had; I have spent all my allocation and I have not let any money go back.  I looked for this ministerial job and I will spend every shilling available to me, as the Senator knows better than most.  I fought tooth and nail in the capital budget for &euro;1 billion for the people of this country and I got it.  I intend to spend every shilling of it.  I want to put a plan in place so whoever follows me as Minister of State with this responsibility will bring an end to flooding in many places right around the country.</p>  <p>There were queries about speeding up the planning process.  I will meet officials from the Departments dealing with housing and heritage to see how we can speed up the process.  I agree that the time between announcing a scheme and seeing shovels on the ground is far too long.  I want to see if I can speed up that process.</p>  <p>The Senator spoke about a single agency dealing with dredging of the Shannon.</p> <p>Senator Conway asked about an application relating to Cloghauninchy.  I am happy to say that the planning application has now been submitted and is due on 9 March.  We hope to proceed with that scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800017#U00200"><p>The Minister of State has five minutes left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1363" speakername="Kevin  Moran" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800017#U00300"><p>Those are all the questions that were put to me and I will finish there.  I would be glad to update the House at any time that it wants me in here but I would say to every Member in the House that nobody is working more sincerely with the people of this country and every local authority to deliver on flooding issues than me.  The issue is close to my heart and I know it is close to that of Senators.  I want to deliver on it and will deliver on it if I am given the time.  It is not easy to protect every house.  When I announce catchment flood risk assessment and management, CFRAM, of 130 schemes, 48 major schemes will be announced.  The rest of the schemes will have to be biannual, with another one or two added every year.  It will not be easy to fix everything.  I will have 80 schemes to be worked on over the next years for the people of this country.  I will put every effort into delivering on them all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800017#U00400"><p>That concludes statements on flooding.  I ask the Acting Leader to propose the suspension until 2.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="12:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800017#U00500"><p>I propose the suspension of the House until 2.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.136" nospeaker="true" time="12:50:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.30 p.m. and resumed at 2.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.137" nospeaker="true" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800018#Z00100">Technological Universities Bill 2015: Report Stage (Resumed) and Final Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800018#Z00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor, and wish everybody a happy International Women's Day.  I also wish Senator Grace O'Sullivan a happy birthday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.139" nospeaker="true" time="12:55:00" ><p>Amendment No. 6 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800018#Z00500"><p>I move amendment No. 6a:</p><blockquote>In page 15, between lines 19 and 20, to insert the following:&ldquo;<b>Ethos</b><br /><br /><b>11. </b>In addition to the entrepreneurial elements as well as education and research a technological university shall acknowledge as a fundamental moral and intellectual foundation for the teaching and research practice an ethos that supports creativity, autonomy, intellectual inquiry, innovation and engage citizenship.&rdquo;.</blockquote><p>As I understand it, I will have one opportunity to speak and another to reply.  I thank the Minister of State for her illuminating remarks earlier in the discussion when we took on the idea of ethos.  She made a significant number of points which I believe I have included in the amendment.  It will be interesting to see in what intellectual gymnastics she will engage in an effort to find against the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800018#Z00600"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="12:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800018#Z00700"><p>The original amendment referred to &quot;functions promoting an ethos that supports entrepreneurship, creativity, autonomy, innovation and engages citizenship&quot;.  The new amendment includes all of the elements, including those towards which the Minister pointed us.  Amendment No. 6a reads:</p><blockquote>In addition to the entrepreneurial elements as well as education and research a technological university shall acknowledge as a fundamental moral and intellectual foundation for the teaching and research practice an ethos that supports creativity, autonomy, intellectual inquiry, innovation and engage citizenship.</blockquote> <p>We acknowledge in the new amendment entrepreneurial elements, as well as education and research.  However, it states - this is the point we argued in the previous discussion - that, in addition, universities would acknowledge that an ethos represented a fundamental intellectual and moral basis on which a university operated and underpinned all of its intellectual activity.  It reads, "a technological university shall acknowledge, as a fundamental moral and intellectual foundation for the teaching and research practice an ethos that supports creativity, autonomy, intellectual inquiry, innovation and engaged citizenship".  It seems to be difficult to disengage from this definition or avoid a situation where the fundamental principles underlying a university are enunciated in a Bill establishing it.  This appears to be an important and critical matter.  I will make a further contribution when the Minister of State responds, but this is a fundamental aspect of the Bill.  It would be regrettable if the Government was to find itself unable to accept the amendment, particularly as it takes into account the remarks made by the Minister of State in the previous debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800019#AA00200"><p>As Senators will be aware, we recently discussed at some length an amendment on the elements they considered appropriate to the ethos of a technological university related to section 9.  They are seeking to include such elements or a further elaboration on them in a new stand-alone section.  I do not take the view that such an approach is appropriate.  The Bill does not purport in any section to establish or dictate the ethos of a technological university.  What it does, however, is specify the functions of the technological university and requires it, under section 91(1)(k), in so far as possible in the performance of these functions, to serve the community and public interest in certain ways.</p>  <p>It is a matter for each technological university to be autonomous in its own right in the flexibility of its approach to the precise nature of its ethos.  In so doing, it shall have regard to the performance of its functions, including the right to academic freedom, as set out in the Bill, rather than there being some generic version enshrined in legislation.  As I have highlighted in some considerable detail, the various elements cited by the Minister in his latest amendment - creativity, autonomy, intellectual inquiry, innovation and engaged citizenship - are adequately provided for in other sections.  It is also noteworthy that under section 10 which relates to academic freedom, the Bill, in section 10(1)(b) refers explicitly to the independent ethos of the technological university, thereby copperfastening the underlying principle that the ethos of the technological university is not to be generically or legislatively set out but is to be established independently by each relevant institution.  As such, I consider the amendment inappropriate and do not accept it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800019#AA00300"><p>I greatly welcome the inadequacy of the Minister of State's response.  I found it immensely flattering that she referred to me as the Minister.  If I were, the amendment would be instantly accepted.  I will not delay the House on this matter, although I will call a vote on the amendment.  A number of matters arise.  The Minister of State said the Bill did not purport to establish the ethos of a technological university.  Of course, it does not purport to do so.  That is the reason I am seeking to do so in my amendment.  It is very important to understand the principles on which universities work.  This should be the foundation of any legislation governing technological universities or universities of any description.  Members of the public are entitled to know the ethos of the institution their children will attend.</p>  <p>The Minister of State argued that each technological university should be autonomous.  Of course, they should be and we all respect academic freedom, but I remind her that I had an amendment to universities legislation passed which underpinned academic freedom.  It inserted a large new section in legislation and was so successful it was adopted word for word by several Scandinavian countries in their universities legislation.  There is no conflict between allowing autonomy, academic freedom and intellectual licence for a university, while also establishing an ethos.</p>  <p>In addition, I cannot imagine a technological university that would turn its face against an ethos that included entrepreneurial elements, education and research and acknowledged, as a fundamental moral and intellectual foundation for the teaching and research practice, an ethos that supported creativity, autonomy, intellectual inquiry, innovation and engaged citizenship.  I note the letter "d" is missing from the end of the word "engage" in the text.  That is a spelling mistake.  Is the Minister of State aware of any technological university that would not adhere to these principles in practice?  If this were to be provided for in legislation and a divergence from these principles were to occur, it would be necessary to resolve the matter. </p>  <p>I take as granted the independent status of a technological university.  The Minister of State indicated that the ethos was not to be set out but was to be established independently.  What technological university would wish to dissociate itself from the principles I have set out in the amendment?  Would a technological university be against creativity?  I cannot imagine any university setting its face against creativity.  Autonomy, the very issue of which the Minister spoke, is provided for in the amendment.  I taught for 30 years in Trinity College Dublin and intellectual inquiry, as provided for in the amendment, was what the university was all about, particularly on the research side.  Innovation, also provided for in the amendment, is what we want from universities and the reason they are part of the intellectual lifeblood of the country.  Likewise, surely we all want engaged citizenship.</p>  <p>As I stated, I am grateful to the Minister of State for the complete inadequacy of her reply.  Having accepted her words and altered the amendment we tabled on Committee Stage, including by providing for the suggestions she had made, her continued rejection of the amendment will make perfectly obvious that she has received instructions not to accept any amendment in the Seanad.  That is an abrogation of the responsibility and role of Seanad &Eacute;ireann in the world of parliamentary politics.  That is all I have to say on the amendment which I will press to a vote and I hope I will receive the support of my colleagues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1247" speakername="Mary Mitchell O'Connor" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800019#AA00400"><p>I will repeat myself by pointing out that I have highlighted, in considerable detail, the various elements cited by the Senator, specifically creativity, autonomy, intellectual inquiry, innovation and engaged citizenship, all of which are included in the text.  The proposed amendment is surplus to requirements because all of these elements are written features on pages 11, 12 and 13 of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800019#AA00500"><p>Is that the end of the discussion on the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800019#AA00600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800019#AA00700"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800020#BB00100"><p>Is the amendment agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800020#BB00200"><p>No.  Is what agreed to?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800020#BB00300"><p>I think the Senator just said he was against his own amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800020#BB00400"><p>I was trying to read through the documents to see if the Minister of State was accurate in saying-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800020#BB00450"><p>I am putting the question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.155/1" nospeaker="true" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800020#BB00475"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 11; Nl, 23.</p><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators David Norris and Grace O'Sullivan; Nl, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.155/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2018-03-08" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800020#BB00475">
            <divisioncount ayes="11" noes="23" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" vote="aye">Frances Black</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="aye">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="aye">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" vote="aye">Alice Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="aye">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" vote="aye">Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" vote="aye">Grace O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="no">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="no">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="no">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" vote="no">Aidan Davitt</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="no">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="no">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" vote="no">Jennifer Murnane O'Connor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="no">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="no">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="no">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="no">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.155/3" nospeaker="true" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800020#BB00475"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC00100"><p>I wish to make a very serious point of order.  We had a very useful debate in the House on Committee Stage and the requirements that the Minister suggested at that time were incorporated in the amendment, so it is rather astonishing that her Fine Gael colleagues voted against it.  However, the real point I wish to make is that many of my colleagues on the Fianna F&aacute;il benches quietly agreed with the amendment but phone calls were made to their offices.  It is a very important point and it is------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC00200"><p>It is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC00300"><p>It is a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC00400"><p>Members may vote as they wish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC00500"><p>It is entirely a point of order.  I am sorry, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, but they did not vote as they wished.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.161" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC00700"><p>They voted as they were told to by a person who is not a Member of this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.163" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC00900"><p>Senator Norris will resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC01000"><p>It is an outrage against democracy that a debate in this House should be dominated and Members should be told what to do by people who are not Members of this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.166" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC01200"><p>The Chair is on his feet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC01300"><p>I cannot see the Chair and maybe,------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC01400"><p>This is the Seanad Chamber, not Senator Norris's one man show.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC01500"><p>------on a point of order, the Leas-Chathaoirleach should-------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC01600"><p>I have ruled.  The amendment is lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC01700"><p>-----be defending this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.173" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC01900"><p>Is Senator Norris insistent on being disobedient?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC02000"><p>I cannot hear the Leas-Chathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC02100"><p>Is Senator Norris insistent on being disobedient?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC02200"><p>Am I what?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC02300"><p>Is Senator Norris insistent on being disobedient?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC02400"><p>Yes, absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800021#CC02500"><p>In that case, I will suspend the House for ten minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.181" nospeaker="true" time="13:15:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.05 p.m. and resumed at 3.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00100"><p>We are moving on to amendment No. 7.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00200"><p>Without reopening the previous debate, I just wish to say that I will be writing to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges on the subject of Seanad independence because those in Fianna F&aacute;il apparently did not know what their party's policy was, agreed with us and then telephoned a Member of the other House to be given instructions.  That interrupts the autonomy of Seanad &Eacute;ireann and I protest against it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00300"><p>The Senator is entitled to protest.  However, I want to make a statement.  With regard to the matter which gave rise to the suspension of the House, I must make clear that Senators may vote on a matter before the House as they see fit.  The way in which Senators choose to vote is not a matter of order.  Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00400"><p>I beg your pardon.  I am not allowing the Leas-Cathaoirleach's statement to remain on the record of the House without correction.  Members on the other side did not vote as they saw fit.  They voted as they were told by a Member of the other House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00500"><p>Whether they did or not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00600"><p>That is a completely different thing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00700"><p>Having received that, if they received it, they then cast their vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00800"><p>I am leaving this House in protest at the Leas-Cathaoirleach's failure to condemn the situation-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD00900"><p>With respect, the Senator is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01000"><p>-----and the inaccurate remarks he put on the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01100"><p>The Senator may leave.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01200"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01300"><p>I do not want any more on it.  It is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01400"><p>When Senators operate on instruction from outside the House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01500"><p>I am not responsible for any of that.  I have ruled on the matter and am moving on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01600"><p>It is extraordinary that Senator Humphreys is leaving the House.  He took instruction for long enough.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01700"><p>Senator Bacik is leaving as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD01800"><p>I am moving on to amendment No. 7.  Amendment No. 7 is ruled out of order as it could pose a potential charge on the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.200" nospeaker="true" time="13:20:00" ><p>Amendment No. 7 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD02000"><p>Amendments Nos. 8 and 11 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="13:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018030800022#DD02100"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p><blockquote>In page 16, line 11, after &ldquo;purpose,&rdquo; to insert the following:&ldquo;and at least one of whom has expertise and/or experience in representing the interests of students, nominated by the student union,&rdquo;.</blockquote><p>Senator Ruane had hoped to be here today to speak on the amendment as she has strong feelings on this issue.  Amendments Nos. 8 and 11 are variations on the issue we raised on Committee Stage around ensuring that there is a strong student voice on the governing boards of technological universities.  Unfortunately, our previous amendments on increasing the number of student representatives on governance boards were ruled out of order as they may have incurred a charge on the State.  We have now adopted a different approach that recognises a different way in which the interests of students can still be appropriately represented in how the universities are governed and it may even be an improved way.</p><p>We need to give the student voice statutory protection in how it contributes to the management of the universities.  Student unions in the new universities will be just that - new - and they will not be able to benefit from the decades of institutional knowledge and experience built up in existing student unions in current universities.  Our amendments rectify this and try to ensure that among those external representatives on the governance boards of the new universities there will be at least one external individual who has expertise or experience in representing the interests of students in previous university governance scenarios.  The individual could be a former student union officer or representative in one of the constituent colleges or institutes of technology.  He or she could also be someone who has experience in a different university context or perhaps even an international university context.  We believe that our amendment would ensure that the officers of a new student union would have an expert and experienced yet independent and external voice on the governing body to support them in representing the interests of students and to ensure that student interests were properly considered in matters of governance.</p><p>This is a constructive and helpful amendment.  It has the endorsement of the Union of Students in Ireland.  I hope the Minister of State will be able to accept it and assuage some of the concerns, which we have previously discussed, of unions around the strength of their voice in the governance of the new universities.</p><p>In a further amendment I will come back in on the Bologna process which the Minister of State will be aware commits to the importance of student representation also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-03-08a.203" nospeaker="true" time="13:20:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>