<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>Maidir leis an athbhreithni&uacute; ar acmhainneacht an chabhlaigh iascaigh at&aacute; idir l&aacute;mha ag an Roinn Talmha&iacute;ochta, Bia agus Mara, an g&aacute; at&aacute; ann go dtabharfaidh an tAire soil&eacute;iri&uacute; maidir le c&eacute;n uair a fhoilseofar na haighneachta&iacute; at&aacute; tagtha isteach ar shu&iacute;omh idirl&iacute;n na Roinne agus c&eacute;ard &eacute; an t-amsc&aacute;la le haghaidh cinneadh &oacute;n Aire i nd&aacute;il leis an athbhreithni&uacute;.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to consider establishing a dedicated investigative fire safety unit to investigate, identify and take remedial action to ensure there is adequate fire safety in self-certified housing and apartment developments and that there are no more unidentified defective developments.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator James Reilly of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to outline how he can assist in ensuring the sports lands at Lusk, County Dublin, for the Lusk 2020 sports hub are ceded to Fingal County Council; to outline how his Department can assist with the development of this key sports amenity landbank; and if he will consider funding sports facilities there under the Lusk 2020 multi-use sports plan.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerard P. Craughwell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to outline the projects that will be funded from the &euro;3.6 billion earmarked for public transport in the Exchequer capital transport envelope 2016-21; and to outline how much of this will be used to enhance public transport outside Dublin, specifically in Cork city and county.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Leas-Chathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to develop a strategy for increased funding, recognition and participation for women's sport.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of Education and Skills to consider providing an ASD unit for every school.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to confirm when all outstanding 2016 GLAS 1 and GLAS 2 payments will be made to farmers; and to provide assurance that this matter is receiving urgent attention.</blockquote><p>I regard the matters raised by Senators &Oacute; Clochartaigh, &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, Reilly, Craughwell, Lombard and Boyhan as suitable for discussion.  I have selected Senators &Oacute; Clochartaigh's, &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's, Reilly's and Craughwell's matters, and they will be taken now.<br/><br/>I regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Byrne on the grounds that it is a repeat of a similar Commencement matter raised on 10 May 2017 and anticipates the debate on Second Stage of the Autism Spectrum Disorder Bill 2017, which takes place in the Seanad this Wednesday.<br/><br/>Senators Lombard and Boyhan may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#B00200">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#B00250">Fishing Vessel Licences</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#B00300"><p>The Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Creed, is as welcome as ever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#B00400"><p>Go raibh maith agat, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.  Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  T&aacute; m&eacute; thar a bheith s&aacute;sta gur th&aacute;inig s&eacute; f&eacute;in isteach leis an cheist seo a fhreagairt agus faoin suim at&aacute; aige san &aacute;bhar seo.</p> <p>I am grateful that the Minister has taken the time to take this Commencement matter, which relates to the ongoing review of the management of the fishing fleet's capacity.  We are both from coastal areas and realise the importance of the fishing fleet to coastal and rural communities.  The figures in my area are stark.  There has been a significant contraction in the Ros a' Mh&iacute;l offshore fishing fleet since 2003, with it more than halving at an unprecedented and alarming rate.  Fifteen boats have been extracted from the fleet, ten of which were owned by people from the Aran Islands.  Currently, nine Ros a' Mh&iacute;l and Aran offshore fishing boats are licensed.  One is not fishing and seven are owned and skippered by Inishmore fishermen.</p> <p>The contraction is particularly alarming for the Ros a' Mh&iacute;l Harbour area, which was the subject of an independent technical report commissioned in 2013 and undertaken by the Ros a' Mh&iacute;l Harbour centre, entitled A Socio-economic Profile of Ireland's Fishing Communities.  It stated that, in terms of the number of boat owners per thousand of population, fishing was approximately 20 times more important to the local economy than to Ireland as a whole.  A 2016 report on the harbour calculated that 92% of annual economic turnover in the Ros a' Mh&iacute;l area relied on the seafood sector.</p> <p>At least &euro;22 million was spent on Ros a' Mh&iacute;l Harbour between 2004 and 2014.  Therefore, the contraction of the fleet raises serious questions about the future return on the State's investment and the need to ensure a vibrant fishing community in the area.</p> <p>I welcome the review of the management of the fleet's capacity and the tonnage that is available to boats.  A number of issues arise in this regard and fall into two categories - the safety of the boats in question and the viability of the fishermen's businesses.  The number of fatalities and sinkings in the past 20 years is shocking.  According to figures with which I have been supplied, there have been 40 sinkings and 30 fatalities in that time.  Given that the majority of those fishing vessels were under 40 m in length, smaller vessels seem to be more prone to sinking and fatalities.  When one breaks down the figures, a high percentage of the boats that sink are wooden and tend to be older vessels.</p> <p>There are issues that need to be addressed and we must ensure all fishermen are as safe and remain as viable as possible.  If that means they must upgrade their boats, the technicalities around tonnage and so on need to be addressed and the Department should not stand in the way.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2363"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2363&amp;amp;pid=TrevorOClochartaigh&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I appreciate that is the purpose of the review, but it needs to be progressed as quickly as possible, as stated by the Minister a number of months ago when he set the review in train.  I would like the Minister to clarify today when the submissions in regard to the review will be published on the Department's website and the timescale for the implementation of the review given there are currently a number of boats tied up and unable to fish and others that need to be upgraded from a health and safety perspective, sooner rather than later.  I look forward to the Minister's clarification of this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh for raising this matter and for giving me the opportunity to update the House on certain matters pertaining to the review of replacement of capacity requirements under sea fishing boat licensing policy.</p><p>As the Senator may be aware, under the Fisheries (Amendment) Act 2003 the function of sea fishing boat licensing was transferred from the Minister to the licensing authority for sea-fishing boats, which operates on an independent basis, subject to criteria set out in that Act and ministerial policy directives.  As Minister, I have responsibility for policy in relation to sea-fishing boat licensing under section 3(3) of the Fisheries (Amendment) Act 2003, as amended by section 99 of the Sea-Fisheries and Maritime Jurisdiction Act 2006.  In this context, and as referred to, section 3 of the 2003 Act makes provision for ministerial policy directives to issues to the independent licensing authority for sea-fishing boats.  I am, however, precluded from exercising any power or control in regard to individual cases or a group of cases with which the licensing authority is or may be concerned under section 3(5) of the 2003 Act.  </p><p>I received proposals from a producer organisation, which, in summary, relate to the possibility of reducing the requirement to provide 100% replacement capacity with the relevant track record to 80%, the balance being sourced from capacity without track record.  The producer organisation subsequently clarified that this request covered all aspects of fleet policy and replacement capacity policy, including flexibility between segments of the fishing fleet, flexibility between sub-segments and flexibility in regard to fishing effort relating to cod recovery for area VIa and area VIIa, and scallop effort.</p><p>Separately, another producer organisation has regularly raised the issue of a review of the effort regime in place for vessels in the RSW pelagic section of the fleet.  I undertook a public consultation process on these proposals and made available a consultation paper which set out the background to fleet policy and carried out an analysis of the current situation.  The consultation paper examined the implications of the proposals made by the producer organisations and also put forward alternative options.  This consultation concluded on 28 February 2017 and 26 submissions were received, seven from industry representatives and 19 from individuals or companies.  A number of respondents supported the <i>status quo</i>and are opposed to any change in the current replacement capacity requirements.  Some expressed concern that a change could result in an increase in the value of capacity and others are concerned about the impact on vessels of certain sizes.  Others support the proposal of the producer organisation regarding the 100% capacity requirement, indicating, <i>inter alia</i>, that it would allow for upgrading of vessels for enhanced safety and efficiency while some respondents support some degree of flexibility with regard to replacement capacity but are not in favour of that specific proposal.  A smaller number of respondents commented on the RSW pelagic effort regime proposal.  Differing views were also expressed regarding a potential alternative option put forward in the consultation paper, that is, that polyvalent vessels to be licensed in the tiered - mackerel - and-or ringfenced - herring - portions would be able to source up to 10% of the required replacement capacity from non-tiered and non-ringfenced vessels in the same sub-segment at a ratio of 4:1. </p><p>The Senator will appreciate that diverse views have been expressed in the context of the consultation process, particularly on the proposal of the producer organisation regarding the 100% capacity requirement.  All submissions are currently being examined in detail and they are now available to view on my Department's website.  I will carefully consider, following any further analysis needed, the case for amendments to current licensing policy taking into account the submissions received.  I will have my conclusions published on my Department's website at the earliest possible date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#D00100"><p>I welcome the Minister's response, particularly that the submissions can be viewed on the Department's website.</p> <p>Since 2011, the Department has been made aware of these issues.  This review was called for by the Minister on 9 September 2016.  It is an issue for older and smaller vessels under 40 m, and it is essential they are upgraded as quickly as possible.  Will the Minister give a guarantee that, within a year of him calling for this review, namely, by 9 September 2017, he will have come to a decision and we will have clarity around these issues concerning the boats in question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#D00200"><p>I am reluctant to commit myself to a date.  However, I would not have undertaken the review and invited submissions from the industry, from which many varied and conflicting views have been received, if I did not intend to act on them at the earliest possible opportunity.  I want to study in detail the competing voices proffered in the context of this capacity review.</p> <p>It is also important to bear in mind that, under the Common Fisheries Policy, we are obliged to keep a balance between the capacity and the fishing opportunity.  It is abundantly clear there is little point in facilitating greater capacity if the fishing opportunity in terms of quotas is not available.  There are many parameters within which this decision will have to be viewed, not least the opinions offered in the consultation process.  I would like to conclude it within the 12 month period, but I do not want to commit myself absolutely to a date today.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.16" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#D00300">Fire Safety Regulations</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#D00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, to the House to discuss an important concern which he shares with me.  Many public representatives are concerned we are living in a city full of what are in effect tinder boxes and that fire regulations need to be strengthened or reflected upon.  The fire safety of buildings constructed in the past 20 years is raising much concern for residents and their representatives.</p> <p>There is a particular difficulty in that when questions are raised about the fire safety of houses or an apartment block in an individual estate, there is a reluctance among residents to use the normal engagement process with their public representatives, with councils or with the media because they are terrified the value of their properties will collapse.  They are stuck in a bind of wanting to do something about the fire safety concerns around the places in which they live.  They are also worried that the obvious resolution mechanisms they would normally go through are closed off from them because they do not want hurt the value of their properties.  This is completely understandable.</p> <p>We are coming to the conclusion that we need a dedicated agency where people can make confidential reports about fire safety concerns.  In turn, these can be dealt with on a confidential basis to bypass this issue about the value of properties being undermined.  In many of these cases, the issues can be rectified without any reputational damage to the properties in question as well as the significant investment people have made in them.  The last thing we need is where people make a determination about the value of their property versus the value of their lives and those of their families, taking a risk their home will never go on fire.  We cannot have them deciding that, because the mortgage on the property is so huge and debilitating to their quality of life, they take a risk on the property&rsquo;s fire safety.</p> <p>This is an issue that has been going during the lifetime of for several Governments.  The former Minister with responsibility for the environment commissioned a report after five houses in the Millfield Manor estate in Newbridge, County Kildare, were completely destroyed by fire in less than half an hour.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2301"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2301&amp;amp;pid=AodhanORiordan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I understand that this report has been completed and that the current Minister is in possession of it. I am anxious to know what the report contains.</p><p>This matter relates to the overall general standard of fire safety throughout the country.  Fire safety is the responsibility of the local authorities, but the level of resources varies from council to council.  The responses of councils also vary.  It is the responsibility of the Department of Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to oversee this issue and ensure that there is a mechanism in place whereby people can raise their concerns and by means of which we can conduct an effective audit of all construction carried out in the past 20 years, when regulations were not as tightly controlled in respect of dwellings where people's lives are at risk.  We all know of individual apartment blocks in our localities and constituencies that are fire hazards.  The risks exist but the residents are terrified of raising concerns about them lest the value of their properties collapses.</p><p>I appreciate the Leas-Chathaoirleach's patience in allowing me to put my point of view.  This is a serious issue and I know the Minister of State will appreciate that.  I look forward to his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this.  As he has outlined, it is a serious issue.</p> <p>The Building Control Acts 1990 to 2014 set out a clear statutory framework for construction activity.  The 1990 Act provides for the making of building regulations and building control regulations to protect the health, safety and welfare of people in and around buildings.  The Second Schedule of the Building Regulations 1997, as amended, sets out the statutory minimum performance requirements for the construction of new buildings.  In particular, Part B of the Building Regulations 1997, as amended, sets out the legal requirements relating to fire safety in respect of new buildings and in respect of existing buildings undergoing works involving an extension, material alteration or a material change of use.  The requirements under Part B represent the national statutory minimum standards of fire safety provision applicable to the construction of new buildings, including dwellings.</p> <p>Under the Building Control Acts 1990 to 2014, primary responsibility for compliance with the requirements of the building regulations rests with the designers, builders and owners of buildings.  Enforcement of the building regulations is a matter for the 31 local building control authorities, which have extensive powers of inspection and investigation under the Acts.  Fire authorities have no powers of inspection in respect of dwelling houses occupied as single dwellings.  The Fire Services Acts 1981 to 2003, however, apply to premises providing sleeping accommodation, that is, apartments.  Furthermore, section 18(2) of the Fire Services Act places the responsibility for fire safety on the person or persons having control over the premises, which in the case of an apartment block includes the owners and management companies.  This is appropriate in a situation where there are some 2 million housing units in the State.</p> <p>In response to building failures that have emerged over the past decade, the Department of Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government introduced the Building Control (Amendment) Regulations 2014, which provide for greater accountability regarding compliance with building regulations, in the form of statutory certification of design and construction by registered construction professionals and builders, lodgement of compliance documentation, mandatory inspections during construction and validation and registration of certificates.  The Building Control (Amendment) Regulations 2014 were reviewed following their first 12 months in operation and it is clear from this review that the reforms have brought a new order and discipline to bear on construction projects.  To complement these reforms, work is at an advanced stage in the Department of Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government on the general scheme of a Bill to place the Construction Industry Register Ireland, CIRI, on a statutory footing and to provide in law for the registration of builders.  This is seen as an essential consumer protection measure giving consumers who engage a registered builder the assurance that they are dealing with a competent and compliant operator.</p> <p>One of the two proposals outlined by the Senator relates to a dedicated agency for making confidential reports.  My understanding of what he suggested is that this agency would also conduct an audit of buildings constructed in the past 20 years.  Perhaps he will clarify that.  As regards the report in the Department, I have not had an opportunity to speak to the Minister about it but I will ask him about the status of the report and when and how it will be made public.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#E00300"><p>I have with me a response to a parliamentary question tabled by Deputy Clare Daly on 22 June 2016.  It is disappointing that the Minister of State's response is effectively a cut-and-paste job from that.  In fact, I was flicking through it and I could read, word for word and sentence for sentence, the reply given by the Department to the Minister of State to be read in the Seanad today.  It is exactly the same as the reply in June 2016, almost one year ago.  Without any disrespect to the Minister of State, it appears that the Department has not moved on very much in a year, particularly in view of the fact that it has provided - word for word - the same response.  What we are discussing here is lives that are at risk in apartment blocks and estates across the city and the country.  We are also discussing the capacity of individuals or groups of individuals, residents associations or public representatives to make representations to the Government about the nature of the risk that exists.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2301"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2301&amp;amp;pid=AodhanORiordan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need a confidential facility for any person or group of individuals to make a complaint about a concern they have, which they will not make lightly.  It is not a light thing for anyone to say they think there is a fire safety issue in his or her block of apartments or in his or her estate.  The person would make this confidential request to the Department which would then conduct an audit.  However, a more robust audit has to be carried out nationally and must not be dependent on councils.  Either that or we must demand that councils conduct these audits because otherwise cases will continue to arise throughout the country.  It will take until the fire actually happens because although residents are concerned by fire safety, they are restricted by their concern for the value of their properties and worry over reputational damage.  I am not trying to have a political go on the response given to me.  I understand what happens here, that cut-and-paste jobs are done all the time for ministerial responses, but we cannot wait for another estate or apartment block to go on fire.  A proactive response is needed.  The councils are not doing it and we must ensure they do it and that have a confidential information line that groups and residents can use to have their fire safety complaints rectified.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1295" speakername="Eoghan Murphy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#F00200"><p>It must be very disappointing if the response is similar to the one received by a colleague a year ago.  I do not think that it is an indication that no work or progress has been done in this area in that time but nevertheless I will raise it with the Department, following the Senator's contribution.  He is correct that people should not take the unacceptable risk of not reporting concerns they have regarding the conditions in their building because they are worried about it having an impact on the value of the property.  We have to find a way of making sure that people are comfortable reporting risks and making sure they are dealt with adequately and in an appropriate timeframe, because that is essential.  Before looking at the idea of setting up a new agency or body, which might be warranted, it requires further study and examination.  Let us look at the report which the Minister has already.  Let us see what that says, publish it and go from there.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.23" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#F00250">Sports Facilities Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#F00300"><p>We welcome the Minister, Deputy Ross.  He is welcome back from the riviera and the sunshine of the south west.  I call Senator Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#F00400"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him for taking this matter himself.</p><p>I begin by quoting from a submission from Lusk Community 2020 Sports Club Committee to the Fingal County Council open space strategy:</p><blockquote>The Lusk Community 2020 Sports Plan is developed on the basis of ... Community participation in line with Government strategies ... Recreational Hub development in line with the 'Keeping It Green' strategy ... Understanding the social, recreational/sports and economic benefits that can accrue to a community based on high quality open space development within a community ... The need to develop linkages between and across the 'green infrastructure' in order to deliver maximum community benefits ... [and] The need to have strong liaison between communities and local authorities in order to design and develop open space that meet current and future community needs.</blockquote> <p>The plan includes a floodlit area containing a 100 m by 400 m all-weather playing pitch, a 1,200 m cycling and running track, and a 400 m running track with track and field facilities for shot-put, discus, long jump, hammer and others.  Seamus Flynn has been behind Lusk athletic club for many years, and he is determined to train an Olympic medal winner from the town of Lusk.  We have five tennis courts, two juvenile training pitches, a senior grass pitch of 140 m by 90 m, an 80 m by 50 m all-weather training area, and a cricket crease where more cricketers can train to represent Ireland.  As the Minister knows, rural Fingal has a very strong cricket tradition.  A few years ago, when I was in India on St. Patrick's Day to represent the Government, I was informed by the Indian people there that the only reason they had heard of Ireland was because of cricket and our having beaten Pakistan, so the power of this particular sport to promote our country abroad should not be underestimated.</p><p>These planned facilities are located beside Lusk soccer club with 19 teams and 325 playing members and rising, Round Towers GAA club with 600 members and growing, Rush and Lusk Educate Together national school, with 420 pupils, Lusk community college, now at 350 pupils but with a new extension planned for later in the year which will bring it to 1,000 pupils, and Lusk national school with 850 pupils and new classrooms under construction.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator James Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2180"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2180&amp;amp;pid=DrJamesReilly&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Three Government cranes dominate the skyline of Lusk at the moment and we expect a fourth later in the year.</p><p>The population of this area was around 500 to 700 when I started in practice many years ago.  It was 7,000 in 2011 and has now grown to 10,000.  It is expected to grow to 12,500 in the coming years.  As the Minister knows, it has excellent bus and rail links and is in proximity to Dublin, Dublin Airport and Swords.  It is an attractive place to live and to start a home and young family.  Therefore, the demand for these facilities will continue to grow.</p><p>In short I have two requests of the Minister.  First, I ask him to consider communicating with Fingal County Council to encourage it to continue to press for the release of these promised open-space lands from the developer, as per the planning permissions granted and the master plan for the area.  I commend and acknowledge the determination and commitment of all the volunteers from all the Lusk clubs who have campaigned and engaged in planning this excellent sports facility.  The Lusk sports hub committee has lobbied Fingal county councillors, including Councillor Tom O'Leary, to get this key strategic open-space land made available to the community as soon as possible.  In fairness, I understand the process is nearing completion but a ministerial letter might just give it the push towards completion it needs.</p><p>Second, taking into account the well thought out, future-proof plan for sports facilities for Lusk the sports hub group has produced in conjunction with the community and Fingal County Council, I ask the Minister to favourably consider assisting the Lusk community sports hub group and Fingal County Council in funding this excellent plan, which seems to be a very fine example of best practice in community sports development and planning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#G00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this very important matter.  I will certainly try to address those two specific questions in a few minutes, probably in the second part of my reply, after he has responded to what I have to say.</p> <p>In respect of securing lands required for the sports facilities set out in the Lusk 2020 sports plan, as the Senator knows and has acknowledged, this is obviously primarily a matter for Fingal County Council.  I understand, however, that the council is at an advanced stage of taking the land bank referred to into charge and I look forward to being kept informed of progress made. </p> <p>On the Government's role in the provision of sports facilities, the sports capital programme, as administered by my Department, is the Government's primary vehicle to support the development of sports facilities and the purchase of sports equipment.  It aims to foster an integrated approach to developing sports and physical recreation facilities throughout the country.  The programme has transformed the sporting landscape of Ireland with improvements in the quality and quantity of sports facilities in virtually every village, town and city.</p> <p>We are committed to ensuring this progress continues and on 21 December 2016 it was announced that &euro;30 million was being made available under the 2017 sports capital programme.  The application process was open from 23 January to 24 February.  By the closing date, a record 2,320 applications had been received.  All applications are currently being assessed with allocations expected later this year.  I understand a number of applications have been received from the Lusk area.  More generally, the sports capital programme has already invested heavily in facilities in Dublin with &euro;34 million provided for sports infrastructure and equipment since 2011.  Fingal County Council itself has benefitted from almost &euro;1.3 million in grants in the same period.  This is separate to the substantial funding many sports clubs in Fingal have drawn down from their own developments.  Furthermore, a number of clubs associated with the Lusk 2020 sports plan have benefitted from funding under recent rounds of the programme.  </p> <p>The programme for Government contains the aim of allocating sports capital grants annually in future.  My Department is engaging with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform about how best to implement this commitment.  In this regard, once the necessary land for the Lusk proposal is in council ownership, it can apply for sports capital programme funding for any suitable project under future rounds of the programme.</p> <p>Regarding the Government's policy for funding of sports facilities in the future, last November the Minister of State, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan, and I launched a major consultation process for the development of a new national sports policy framework.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Shane Ross:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1974"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1974&amp;amp;pid=ShaneRoss&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The examination of responses received is being finalised and we expect to present the framework to Government before the summer recess.  Several key challenges will be addressed in the framework, with the overriding principle being the investigation of how to increase the number of people participating in sport and physical activity.  All people, regardless of their age, gender or ability, should be able to participate in sport.  The new framework will consider how best to ensure access to facilities nationally, regionally and locally.  The new framework will also consider how programmes and initiatives can be developed in tandem with newly-constructed facilities to connect with traditionally non-participant groups.  The framework also considers how local authorities could play an enhanced role in getting people involved in sport.  It is pleasing, therefore, that the overall objectives of the Lusk 2020 plan are in accordance with these principles.</p><p>In terms of the funding of sports facilities, I mentioned the aim of running the sports capital grant programme annually.  Furthermore, as part of my Department's submission to the mid-term review of the capital plan, additional funding has been sought for large-scale sports infrastructure.  If the additional funding is received, it will allow consideration of the funding of large facilities requiring more than the maximum amount available under the sports capital programme.  It would be open to all local authorities, including Fingal County Council, to submit applications under the terms that will apply.  I reiterate the Government's commitment to improving the stock of sports facilities throughout the country.  The Lusk 2020 plan is welcome, particularly in terms of setting out how a local community and relevant local authority can work together to get more people to participate in sport.  As the council advances the project, my Department will consider any applications for capital funding from the council.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his response.  I welcome his acknowledgement that the Lusk 2020 plan aims to foster an integrated approach to developing sports and physical recreation facilities and that this is the Government's aim.  I welcome the Government's commitment to sport and the grants that have been allocated in recent years.  I welcome that the Minister said that it is pleasing that the overall objective of the Lusk 20020 plan is in accordance with the Government's overriding principles and that the plan is welcome, in particular in terms of setting out how the local community and relevant local authority can work together to get more people to participate in sport.  I also welcome that the Department will consider the application for capital funding.</p><p>We have an opportunity to buck the former trend for houses to be built in an area, followed by roads and, latterly, facilities.  We have an opportunity.  We know that Lusk will grow and that there is a housing issue.  We know that a place such as Lusk, which is in central Fingal, will be the site of further development.  Facilities should be built in anticipation of housing development.  The facilities are needed now but will be needed even more in the future.</p><p>As Members know, this is the month of mental health awareness.  As the Romans used to say, &quot;<i>mens sana in corpore sano</i>&quot;, which means &quot;a healthy mind in a healthy body&quot;.  Childhood habits can stay with a person for life.  Outdoor exercise, healthy competition, learning about teamwork and the value of volunteerism are all embodied in this worthwhile project.  I call on the Minister to facilitate it.  He could play a pivotal role were he to accede to my two requests.  He has indicated that the second of my requests will be considered by the Department.  In terms of my first, if the Minister were to write a letter encouraging Fingal County Coucil to acquire these lands from the developer - who has agreed as part of planning permission to hand them over - it would give great heart to the many people in Lusk who have worked very hard to make this plan a reality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#H00300"><p>The case being made by the Senator is very powerful and compelling.  He knows that it will be considered on its merits, which are great.  I will not make any specific promises.  It would be inappropriate for me to do so because, as the Senator knows, there is huge competition for this type of funding.  The Lusk 2020 plan for a sports hub and development is in accordance with the principles of the Government's plan and will be considered favourably.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.31" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#J00200">Public Transport Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#J00300"><p>I thank the Minister for recent correspondence on the issue I raise.  While I was pleased to receive a comprehensive account regarding some public transport projects being funded from the Exchequer capital transport envelope, I am disappointed it is proving difficult to draw a clear line between investment in the greater Dublin area and the rest of the country, specifically Cork city and county.  The most recent figures from the Central Statistics Office indicate that 44% of the State's total urban population lives in Dublin.  We must also remember, however, that 11% of the population lives in Cork city and the recent census indicated the city's population had increased by 5.4%.  In addition, 37% of the population of the State lives in rural areas.  The population of Cork county showed one of the largest increases in population in the country.  The percentage population growth in Cork city and county is comparable with growth in any of the local authority areas in greater Dublin, with the exception of Fingal.</p> <p>My independent colleagues in Cork city and county councils, in particular, Councillor Marcia D'Alton, inform me that in the recent joint submission to the national planning framework, Cork 2050, the councils identified a sustainable transport network to underpin spatial, social and economic expansion as being of critical importance.  The councils believe the transport network should facilitate the prioritisation of public transport, walking and cycling.  The joint councils correctly identified Cork city and county as a complementary location to Dublin with strong international connections and as a primary driver of economic and population growth in the southern region.  While the councils are working hard to achieve these goals, how can their plan be progressed if essential figures on a breakdown of capital transport expenditure are not readily available, particularly when this is such an important part of A Programme for a Partnership Government and the strategic investment framework for land transport?</p> <p>I am disappointed and bewildered that while the Government is in the process of undertaking a mid-term review of the infrastructure and capital programme, the figures for projects in cities and regions outside Dublin are not readily available.  Without such information, we are to assume that most of the investment is being directed either towards the greater Dublin area or, failing that, towards other metropolitan areas and is not being quantified.  Either scenario is a disaster for citizens, elected representatives, planners and businesses.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for his time and hope his Department or the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform will be able to throw some light on this issue for me and independent councillors, particularly in the Cork city and country area. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#J00400"><p>I thank Senator Craughwell for raising this important matter, particularly in respect of Cork city and county, and for the opportunity to address the House on the issue.  As the Senator pointed out, funding of &euro;3.6 billion has been allocated for public transport in the Government's capital plan.  The funding for the transport elements of the plan is for a seven-year period from 2016 to 2022.  The focus of this investment, particularly in the early years of the capital plan, is on achieving essential steady-state maintenance of our existing public transport network, particularly the heavy rail network, throughout the country to ensure it remains safe and fit for purpose.</p> <p>From time to time, a misunderstanding arises that there is a vast sum of money available to develop motorways countrywide.  As the Senator will be aware, we are still struggling to maintain the roads at current standards and even this will not be fully possible for another year or two.  Expenditure on new roads or motorways will result in reduced funding for other projects meaning other roads will suffer.  From 2019 onwards, however, we will spend much more on new infrastructure.  While I accept that is a long time to wait, that is the financial reality.</p> <p>In recent correspondence to the Senator, I provided an overview of how the &euro;3.6 billion allocation for public transport will be spent.  As I outlined, it is not possible to draw a clear line between investments in the greater Dublin area and outside the area in all cases.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Shane Ross:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1974"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1974&amp;amp;pid=ShaneRoss&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For example, the funding of approximately &euro;1.3 billion allocated in the capital plan for the maintenance of the heavy rail network, which is more than one third of the total funding available for public transport, will benefit all areas of the heavy rail network within and outside the greater Dublin area.</p><p>The Senator specifically requested details of the funding available for capital investment in Cork city and county.  I will outline recent and planned investment in public transport in Cork.  Funding is provided under the capital plan for sustainable transport projects and accessibility programmes in the regional cities of Cork, Galway, Limerick and Waterford.  These programmes are administered by the National Transport Authority.  Over &euro;70 million has been allocated over the period of the capital plan for sustainable projects in the regional cities and for accessibility programmes.  Between 2014 and 2016, more than &euro;15 million was allocated to Cork city and county councils under the regional cities and accessibility programmes.  Over the remaining years of the capital plan, it is anticipated that public transport investment in the Cork metropolitan area will represent a continuation of the current focus of the investment programme.</p><p>In the case of the Cork City Council area, this investment has been focused on the implementation of the city centre movement strategy on a number of radially-based strategy transport corridors linking the city centre with the city suburbs and county environs.  The principal objective of the city centre movement strategy is to improve access to the city centre through the reallocation of road space, leading to an improvement in the environment for public transport vehicles, pedestrians and cyclists.  The overall city centre movement strategy was approved by the city council and phases 1 and 2 are already at construction stage in 2017.</p><p>The full strategy includes a further six phases and these are intended for implementation over the coming years.  Three strategic corridor studies were completed with funding provided between 2013 and 2017.  These focused on the south east, south west, south central and north sides of the city.  The purpose of these studies is to inform the development of a high-quality core bus network and improve walking and cycling links over time, complementing the objectives of the city centre movement strategy.  Several schemes have already been progressed in Mahon.  The intention is to continue on this basis with further schemes being progressed on corridors in the south east, south west and north city areas over the coming years.</p><p>In the case of the Cork county metropolitan area, the regional cities investment programme will continue to be focused on the Douglas area based on the recommendations of the Douglas land use and transportation study.  The principal objectives of that study are to reduce congestion, improve local connectivity by sustainable transport modes and improve the performance of the many bus services operating through the area.  The aim is to complement the transport investment in the city centre and strategic corridors.</p><p>The Senator will be aware that a mid-term review of the capital plan is currently under way.  I will be seeking to significantly improve the funding available for public transport over the remaining years of the plan to meet increasing demand, to tackle congestion in the greater Dublin area and our regional cities, including Cork in particular, as well as to help to deliver on meeting our climate obligations by reducing emissions from the transport sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#K00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his comprehensive answer.  I suppose that when we are talking about capital investment and projects such as this one it might be helpful to publish figures upfront for the various metropolitan areas or large urban areas outside the greater Dublin area.  The Minister will be aware of the number of times people like him and me, who live in the capital, are accused of ensuring that the capital is well-looked-after while the rest of the country is forgotten.  When the plan is published, if the details for each of the cities and counties were published at the same time, it might move the focus away from that type of accusation.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for his time and for the answer he has given me today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#K00300"><p>I understand the frustration that some people outside Dublin feel.  The view is that maybe the Dublin area gets undue attention and some believe it gets disproportionate funds.  While I do not think that is the case, I can understand why some hold that view.  When high-profile projects like Luas cross-city and others come along - the metro north project probably will not be coming along for another ten years - perhaps some people associated with regional cities believe they are somewhat neglected.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Shane Ross:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1974"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1974&amp;amp;pid=ShaneRoss&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Perhaps I should repeat the figures.  The NTA allocated funding of more than &euro;15 million to Cork city and county councils between 2014 and 2016, of which &euro;11.7 million went to Cork City Council and &euro;3.6 million to Cork County Council.  In excess of &euro;5 million has been provisionally allocated by the NTA to Cork city and county councils under the regional cities programme.  The council to which the Senator referred approved the overall city centre movement strategy last year or the year before.  Phases 1 and 2 are already at construction in 2017.</p><p>A battle for funds is inevitable between the main cities.  Dublin is bigger, and therefore congestion is worse here.  I take the Senator's point.  I was in Cork the other day and became very aware of the congestion that is prevalent there.  However, the scale of the problem in Dublin is much greater.  We will address the issue of Cork in as equitable a way as possible, particularly in the mid-term capital review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.38" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.39" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#O00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#O00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re EU insolvency proceedings, referral to committee, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, motion regarding legal acts in the area of justice, referral to committee, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, statements on the migrant integration strategy, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to conclude not later than 6.30 p.m. with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given five minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 4, Criminal Justice (Offences Relating to Information Systems) Bill 2016 &ndash; Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at the conclusion of No. 3.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#O00300"><p>I wish to discuss the issue of homelessness again.  I would like to discuss the fact that very urgent reform is needed for people who live in emergency accommodation.</p> <p>On a daily basis there are evictions and the human rights of the people who live in emergency accommodation are encroached.  I call on the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to establish an office or extend the powers of the Private Residential Tenancies Board, PRTB, to deal with complaints made by people who live in emergency accommodation.  These people are without a voice and are continually treated like second and third class citizens.  We have failed them by not providing sufficient housing.  We cannot continue to fail them and encroach on their rights when they are living in emergency accommodation.  I ask the Leader of the House to bring this issue to the attention of the Minister.  I hope that the Minister will consider this matter.</p> <p>I would like to discuss the ransomware or malware virus.  There has been a massive ransomware attack in the past few days but the virus and its negative effects have been around for the past few years.  Many small businesses and large State bodies have been affected by the virus.  I shall outline what happened to one small business that employs fewer than five employees.  The hacker took a picture of the person seated at the computer and forwarded a message seeking $500, and froze all of the documents and applications on the desktop.  Fortunately, the hacker did not attack the company's server.  Ultimately, the attack resulted in the computer having to be cleaned and the installation of an expensive firewall.</p> <p>Small businesses struggle to pay such costs.  I ask the Leader of the House to request the Minister to consider establishing a fund to help small businesses cope with data breaches and computer hackers.  Small businesses are targeted as well as the HSE and large businesses.  Small businesses do not have the same amount of IT support as larger organisations.  Small businesses employ the majority of people in this country.  Therefore, we should look after them better and help them cope with ransomware attacks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#O00400"><p>I wish to raise the issue of the Intoxicating Liquor (Amendment) Bill and the opening of licensed premises on Good Friday.  The legislation was the subject of some discussion in this House prior to the break and passed Second Stage unopposed.</p> <p>The proposers of the Bill understand that it is the intention of the Leader to make Government time available in the near future to deal with Committee and Remaining Stages of the Bill in this House.  It was suggested that the Bill should be amended to cover registered clubs, hotels and restaurants as well as public houses.  I ask the Leader to confirm that he will make Government time available for Committee and Remaining Stages.  I also ask him to indicate whether the Department of Justice and Equality wishes to draft the amendments or whether the Department is happy to allow the amendments, that have been canvassed to extend the Bill to cover clubs, hotels and restaurants, be drafted by the proposers and to improve the legislation, if necessary, at the relevant Stage.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I ask the Leader to clarify his intentions regarding this matter and to confirm that it will be dealt with quickly and before the summer recess.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#P00200"><p>We were very disappointed last week not to get cross-party support, particularly from Fianna F&aacute;il, for the motion we tabled regarding the review of the areas of natural constraint, ANC, scheme.  The reason given by Fianna F&aacute;il for not giving its support related to the timing of the motion, which coincided with the deliberations of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  To avoid any excuses this week, I want to inform the House that I will be putting the motion forward for debate tomorrow because inequalities in farm incomes must be addressed.  This ANC review is a significant opportunity to ensure that payments reflect the challenges faced by those farming in areas of genuine natural constraint.  I look forward to that debate tomorrow and I hope Fianna F&aacute;il will have caught up by then.</p> <p>We learned today that several universities have tens of millions of euro in private trusts and foundations that they have not declared in their accounts.  We learned that Galway University Foundation Ltd., has assets in excess of &euro;57 million while University College Cork has assets of &euro;17 million and the University of Limerick has assets of &euro;15 million.  The independent audit also cites widespread non-compliance with procurement rules as well as over-the-top salary payments worth hundreds of thousands of euro.  How can we have confidence in any sector in this country any more?  It is shocking that external intervention can only take place with the agreement of these universities.  If emergency legislation is needed in order to facilitate proper scrutiny of exactly what is going on, then it must be drawn up and the Minister for Education and Skills must put it in place immediately.  Once again, we have seen that there is absolutely no accountability and transparency on the part of individuals or sectors - individuals who are paid enormous salaries to manage public funds.  This is not acceptable at a time when many institutions are struggling to retain staff and many staff are surviving on term-to-term rolling contracts.  At a time when parents are struggling to pay fees in order to send their children to university and are being denied SUSI grants, it is appalling that these institutions would have millions in these trusts and not even show them on their accounts.  The Cassells report on the future funding of third-level institutions called for an immediate injection of &euro;75 million in current funding and &euro;30 million in capital funding for universities.</p> <p>In Mayo, we are witnessing an attempt to downgrade the Castlebar campus of GMIT by stealth.  The Minister for Education and Skills continues to sit on his hands while staff at the Mayo campus are pressurised-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.45" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#P00400"><p>-----to transfer to the Galway campus.  I want to highlight the inequalities.  The universities in question do not even include these huge amounts of money in their accounts.  Meanwhile, what University College Galway has in a loan would keep the Mayo campus of GMIT going for 15 years.  This is not acceptable.  I want the Minister for Education and Skills to come before the House and explain to us how these universities are getting away with stashing away this money while institutions in other areas in education, such as the Mayo campus of GMIT, are starved of funding and are on their knees.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#P00500"><p>I note that we will be discussing obesity and autism.  In that context, I draw attention to the fact that this is Huntington's Disease Awareness Week.  Huntington's is a horrid condition that affects people's motor and cognitive ability and behaviour and causes very severe difficulties for family members.  The fact that it is an inherited condition is another issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.48" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#P00700"><p>Senator Dolan can make his own contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Q00100"><p>I am very pleased to mention that this Thursday, 18 May, the pontiff will hold an audience for people and their families with Huntington's disease from around the world.  Pope Francis has a particular interest in this disease because a lot of people in certain countries in South America are affected by it.  The huntingtin gene was identified by a Galway-born doctor Professor Michael Conneally in 1993 in the United States.  I wish the folk who are travelling to Rome the very best on Thursday.  I should mention that 18 May is also the birthday of John Bruton.  I thought that might be useful to know.  It was also the date of birth of a former Pope, namely, Pope John Paul II.  Huntington's disease is a difficult condition.  Many people have the huntingtin gene and a great many people live with the possibility of the condition.  When it hits, Huntington's disease has a significant effect on families because it happens at a time when people are in young adulthood.  This is an important issue as we look the Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, CRPD, the budget and things ahead. </p> <p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for the opportunity to speak on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Q00200"><p>Go raibh maith agat.  I seek leave to amend the Order of Business to table the Order for Second Stage for the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission (Gender Pay Gap Information) Bill 2017.</p> <p>I raise with the Leader the issue of the ongoing Garda controversy and question marks over the tenure of the Garda Commissioner, senior Garda management and the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality.  To bring it down to street level, while great emphasis has been put on this controversy, the Garda is dealing with ongoing community issues daily.  In fairness to the Taoiseach, when the north inner city was in the media spotlight for violent crime, he made a significant commitment to engaging with the community and established a commission to report on the situation.  The Taoiseach was very well received, as was the commission report by Mr. Kieran Mulvey.  I ask the Leader to update Members on that report.  These issues have faded from the public eye but people still live in these communities.  I was a school principal in that area and taught in that community for 11 years.  It should not take a killing, a feud or criminal activity for us to notice what is happening in the north inner city.  It is a vibrant community.  A lot is going on there but the implementation of this report will be very important.  While the headlines and the political comings and goings around the Garda Commissioner and other Garda issues in the public domain are very important, garda&iacute; on the ground are doing their best to police a vibrant community in an area which faces major challenges.  The commission report needs to be implemented.  The chairmanship of that report is I believe still to be determined.  </p> <p>May I pay a tribute to the Taoiseach?  The Taoiseach visited my local GAA club, Scoil U&iacute; Chonaill GAA club on the Clontarf Road, which is attended by a significant number of children from the north inner city.  He was incredibly well received and to be honest he really was very engaged with the children, the club members and what was happening in that club, which does a great deal of work.  In fairness, nobody on our side of the House wishes to question his commitment to dealing with what was happening in the north inner city but at this juncture, it is important for us to see the implementation of the findings of that report.  We cannot really wait for the next shooting, the next episode of gangland violence or the next headline before that debate happens in this House.  It is at this stage, while we are in a period in which there is relative calm and people are getting on with their lives and want to go to the next level, that we should start talking the rebuilding of communities in that proud area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Q00300"><p>May I clarify the Senator is requesting that No. 16 be taken before No. 1?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Q00400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Q00500"><p>That can be seconded later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Q00600"><p>I wish to raise an issue that appeared on the front page of yesterday's edition of the <i>Irish Examiner</i>to the effect that there were 10,000 complaints of anti-social behaviour to local authorities nationwide over a two-year period.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In that two-year time period only 12 evictions arose.  That level of complaint seems to indicate that local authority officials are spending a huge amount of time dealing with this issue.  We need to have a debate on whether there is adequate legislation and support for local authority officials in dealing with anti-social behaviour.  The vast majority of tenants in local authority houses are law abiding and want to live their lives in a normal way.  It might be one out of 500 who causes a particular problem not only for their immediate neighbours, but for the entire neighbourhood.</p><p>When I was first elected to Cork City Council in 1996, I found that the tenancy agreements people were asked to sign were totally inadequate.  The local authorities had very little say in real terms in dealing with this issue.  As a result of raising this at the time at Cork City Council and, in fairness, with the support at the time of Deputy Miche&aacute;l Martin who was the leader of the Fianna F&aacute;il group in the council at the time, amending legislation was introduced.  As we are now 13 years on, we now need to ascertain if that legislation is adequate.  We need to put in place the necessary supports for people in housing departments in local authorities throughout the country.  This amount of money should not be consumed in this way when local authority officials could do much more in trying to provide adequate housing for the many people on the waiting list.</p><p>We should have a debate in the House with the Minister.  We should also have reports from local authorities outlining the changes they want.  Are they getting the necessary support from the courts?  We need to look at that issue.  I ask the Leader to organise a debate in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R00200"><p>I note the disappointment of Senator Conway-Walsh at our voting against an amendment to the Order of Business last Tuesday.  I put on record that we voted against an amendment to the Order of Business, contrary to Sinn F&eacute;in press releases, etc., stating that we voted against motion.  We, in fact, agreed with the main principles of the motion, but we will-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R00300"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il should have voted for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R00400"><p>-----not be brought into knee-jerk reaction without discussing; it was to be accepted without discussion.  While we agree with the main principles of the motion, the wording, as stated, is too narrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R00500"><p>Flip flop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R00600"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in brought it in and played politics with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R00700"><p>The Leader will get to wind up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R00800"><p>Senator Paul Daly was gracious, in fairness to him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R00900"><p>Order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R01000"><p>Sinn F&eacute;in played politics with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R01100"><p>The Leader will respond at the finish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R01200"><p>Sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R01300"><p>As the Senator rightly said at the outset, I was at a meeting of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine where I felt duty bound to be, and I expected all the agriculture representatives of the parties would have been, when this kind of political, cynical stroke was pulled last Tuesday evening.</p> <p>We agree in principle with the motion, but we feel that the wording as it stands is too narrow.  The motion ignored multiple biophysical constraints.  It referred specifically to mountain and hill areas, which is unrepresentative of the farming community at large.  We need a debate on the matter.  We got an email on Friday indicating that there would be a proposal to amend the Order of Business again today which we again will not support in a knee-jerk fashion.  If and when the Leader can give us a commitment that the Minister will come to the House with the facts and figures as to how the current underspend in the RDP, TAMS and GLAS will be allocated towards the ANC scheme where we can have a full debate and are allowed the opportunity to make amendments to the motion, we will then agree to an amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#R01400"><p>Tonight's "Prime Time" programme will feature a piece on the Defence Forces.  I commend PDFORRA and RACO on their excellent work on behalf of their members.  The Leader will be aware that neither of these two representative bodies has the full rights of a trade union and therefore they are extremely limited in what they can and cannot do.  Anybody watching what is going on at the moment hears the harrowing stories of soldiers on duty 24 hours a day, seven days a week, 365 days a year who are there at times of floods and forest fires, and are there when the nation needs people to work through 24-hour cycles.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We see young men and women who, after they have paid their bills, have &euro;27 per week left over, and that is because they are paid family income supplement.  This is outrageous, especially when we see the Department, having sent 75 emails to the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, seeking permission to create a new assistant secretary job in the Department at a salary of between &euro;128,000 and &euro;149,000 a year.  What do we need the assistant secretary for?  The advertisement says he or she is needed to deal with people.  They only have 440 people working in the Department.  The Defence Forces have their own HR department.  We see a ship sold this week for &euro;110,000.  Galway County Council and Galway City Council asked for it to be handed over as a museum on the docks.  We gave it away for &euro;110,000.  This is not the Government's fault - I am not saying it is - but it is a lack of oversight, and when we talk about oversight, we move into the area of national security.  Six individuals are charged with the security of the State.  The Defence Forces' network system went down because they had no one to manage it as the soldiers who manage it were on duty.  We have 11 bomb disposal officers available out of the 35 we should have.  The Defence Forces are running at 36% of their establishment in strength.  The Defence Forces' loyalty to this nation is being thrown back in their face, and no one gives a continental damn.  At the end of the day, someone somewhere will have to do something for them.  They do not have the tools that are available to trade unionists.  They cannot go on strike and they cannot withdraw their services, although they never would anyway.  We need to start dealing with them and treating them with the respect they are due.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#S00200"><p>I refer to the issue of the GMIT Castlebar campus, which Senator Walsh raised a few moments ago, and the lack of action on the part of the Minister.  It is important that there is a little balance in this debate.  The Leader might ask the Minister, Deputy Bruton, to come to the House to explain the progress on the working group he has set up regarding the GMIT Castlebar campus.  He has already visited the campus, and my understanding is that the working group is up and running and that it held a meeting yesterday with the staff and students of the GMIT Castlebar campus.  It is important we find solutions and not use the matter as a populist political football.  GMIT has a long and distinguished history in Castlebar, and the Minister has given assurances that there is no threat to it.  We should certainly get an update on it but we should not kick it around the place for the sake of populist politics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#S00300"><p>We have had a very happy start to the week.  Fianna F&aacute;il is not happy with Sinn F&eacute;in.  Perhaps we are threatening them too much, but the bluster on my left-hand side from Fianna F&aacute;il in its attempt to get over its embarrassment and a failure to follow its own policies, as stated by my colleague, Senator Conway-Walsh, is cringeworthy-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" speakername="Paul Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#S00400"><p>I have just made it clear how we are following our policies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#S00500"><p>Senator Daly, please.</p> <p>I wish to raise two matters.  I was at a conference on the values of nursing and midwifery held in Dublin Castle this morning with 500 nurses.  I want this House to congratulate the chief nursing officer of Ireland and the HSE on what was a wonderful discussion and workshops on our values.  They will incorporate and bring back compassion and care, which has been eroded so much in our health service.</p> <p>I congratulate the Simon Communities on their hard work on the piece they launched this morning on renting in Dublin.  Rents across the country are an issue, but I would focus on rents in Dublin in particular.  The report is called Locked Out of the Market.  I will support the campaign.  It is extremely important that the Minister examine the report.  Rent supplement in Dublin city centre for a single person is &euro;660, yet the going rent for a one-bedroom property is &euro;1,130.  There are no units available to rent for &euro;660.  For couples, it is similar; rent supplement is &euro;1,275, yet the average rent for a two-bedroom property is &euro;2,700.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->No properties are available on the market in their range.  Neither are there properties for people with children.  This is a damning indictment of what we are doing.  Among other suggestions, the Simon Communities have recommended the urgent implementation of Rebuilding Ireland and a tax on empty units.  I call on the Minister, Deputy Coveney, to attend the House to discuss this report and implement its recommendations swiftly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T00200"><p>Today, the European Court of Justice, ECJ, issued a ruling on the Singapore free trade agreement, specifically on the question of whether it is a mixed agreement or can be negotiated exclusively by the EU.  The ECJ's ruling is clear: in any investor-state dispute mechanism, which are the corporate courts that the House has debated, ratification by all member states is required.  This important ruling vindicates to some extent the stand that the House has taken.  The European Commission told us that it has exclusive competence in this area, but it was wrong.  It also told us that the comprehensive economic and trade agreement, CETA, between Canada and Europe was entirely legal in EU law.  However, we will not know that until it has been tested before the ECJ.  The court made clear that today's ruling merely relates to who has the competence to agree and that it does not deal with the question of legality, which will be dealt with by means of separate process.  Under Article 218.11 of the Treaty of the Functioning of the European Union, Ireland has the power to refer CETA to the ECJ at any time so that a ruling can be made.  I hope that someone does refer it so that we can make decisions about ratification that are fully informed by the ECJ.</p> <p>In the meantime, Ireland will need to decide on whether we want to move the extra step from provisional application, which contains all of the benefits of tariffs and so forth that we have heard about at length, to ratification and bring upon ourselves investor-state dispute mechanisms.  There is no time limit on us staying in a stage of provisional application, so we can remain there for as long as we wish.  I ask all Senators to consider whether we should be moving to the next stage at this point.</p> <p>Mr. Barnier was clear that the second stage of his Brexit negotiations will relate to a trade agreement with the UK.  We must ask ourselves whether any such trade agreement, which would need to be voted on by every parliament in Europe, would be acceptable or passable if it contained an investor-state dispute mechanism.  I suggest that it is in Ireland's interests to ensure that our trade agreements move past the inclusion of these mechanisms.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T00300"><p>I wish to raise the issue of air pollution, particularly in the context of what Ireland is doing to incentivise the use of electric cars.  I also formally second Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T00400"><p>I was going to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T00500"><p>I am sorry.  I did not mean to steal Senator Norris's thunder.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T00600"><p>Not at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T00700"><p>Far be it from me to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T00800"><p>Senator Norris will be next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T00900"><p>According to health experts, life-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T01000"><p>I have left it too late.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T01100"><p>I believe I have the floor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T01200"><p>Senator Noone, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#T01300"><p>According to health experts, life expectancy is being reduced by nine months because of the ingestion of toxins contained in car fumes.  One thousand Dublin buses have diesel engines.  In London's transport system, there has been a substantial move away from diesel towards electric and hybrid vehicles.  We should take a leaf out of Norway's book in this regard.  It has been implementing incentives for 25 years, so it will not happen overnight in Ireland, but according to the latest figures, 37% of new cars bought in Norway last January were electric.  This represents the highest rate of electric vehicle adoption globally.  In Ireland in 2008, we had an ambition of 200,000 electric cars over the course of ten to 15 years.  To date, however, only 2,000 electric vehicles are on the road despite the infrastructure having been put in place.  Those who purchase electric and hybrid vehicles in Ireland pay a lower rate of VRT, but Norway has many other incentives than this such as, for example, paying no VAT on new cars, free parking in public car parks, driving in bus lanes, free access to toll roads, free road ferries and lower annual road taxes.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In the 25 years Norway has been working on this, the number of electric cars there has reached almost 50%.  While I accept that we cannot achieve a great deal over night, we do need to implement, without delay, a lot more policies of the type implemented in Norway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U00200"><p>In London last weekend there was an important meeting of authorities and experts on opera.  They voted Wexford Festival Opera the best opera festival in the world, which is remarkable and a great tribute to Wexford and the people who, over many years, have supported this festival.  It is an amateur effort set up by the late Dr. Tom Walsh, who had a great collection of gramophone records and so on.  It operates from a small 18th century theatre that has been considerably extended and modernised.  Many international stars made their debut in Wexford.  A galaxy of internationally famous people had their first start in Wexford.  They put on operas by great composers that are very rarely performed.  It is fitting that Seanad &Eacute;ireann would congratulate Wexford on this very important honour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U00400"><p>We might go down to see one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.91" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U00600"><p>I would like to raise two issues, one of which has already been raised by  Senator Colm Burke, namely, anti-social behaviour.  In the last few years, there has been a lot of anti-social behaviour that has not been addressed through local authorities.  The reason it has not been addressed by local authorities is because there is no mechanism available to families to have it addressed.  When a person raises the issue of anti-social behaviour on the part of a neighbour with a local authority, he or she is asked to either keep a record of what is happening or to lodge an official complaint against the neighbour.  Families are afraid to do that.  They will not do it because they are afraid of their neighbours, which is the reason they take up the matter with the local authority.</p> <p>The same applies when a person raises this issue with the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, namely, the person is told to either keep a record of what is happening or to lodge an official complaint.  The Minister needs to step in and to introduce legislation to protect people who are being victimised by anti-social behaviour.  Currently, the only basis on which a tenant can be evicted from a local authority is for non-payment of rent.  We need the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to come to this House to address this issue.</p> <p>I would also like to raise the issue of revaluation of commercial rates across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U00700"><p>The Senator knows the rules.  She cannot raise two issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U00800"><p>Other speakers have raised two issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U00900"><p>I am sorry, Senator, but only leaders can raise two issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01000"><p>Everybody who has spoken thus far has raised two issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01100"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01200"><p>I never get the opportunity to raise two issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01300"><p>The Senator is out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01400"><p>On the first issue, I agreed with Senator Burke.  The issue I want to raise is the revaluation of commercial rates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01500"><p>There was a letter issued about this last week.  The Senator knows that she is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01600"><p>This happens to me all of the time.  There has been a revaluation of commercial rates in Carlow in the last few months.  Commercial rates-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01700"><p>The Senator has run out of time to revaluate Carlow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01800"><p>-----have been addressed.  What I am asking-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U01900"><p>The Senator will have to raise the matter another time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02000"><p>No, I feel-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02100"><p>The Senator will have to raise the matter on another day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02200"><p>This is the fourth or fifth time the Leas-Chathaoirleach has done this to me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02300"><p>The Senator must accept the ruling of the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02400"><p>I have just agreed with other speakers and I now want to raise my own issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02500"><p>I am sorry Senator you cannot-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02600"><p>I am very disappointed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02700"><p>Senator, you cannot raise the matter now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02800"><p>I am very disappointed that I cannot raise an issue about which I am seriously concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U02900"><p>With respect, Senator, you have gone way over time.  The Senator will have to raise the matter another day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U03000"><p>I will raise it tomorrow.  I am very disappointed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U03100"><p>We can discuss that afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#U03200"><p>Last Friday was a very significant day, as were the other two days of the visit of Prince Charles and Camilla to this country.  I was in Glasnevin Cemetery when Prince Charles visited the graves of Michael Collins, &Eacute;amon de Valera and James Joyce's parents and unveiled the Victoria Cross.  This is very significant, which some people may not realise.  I was also in the British Ambassador's residence and it was great to see the leaders of the other parties there.  It was very significant that the leader of Sinn F&eacute;in, Gerry Adams, shook hands with Prince Charles.  There is a normalisation of politics on both islands.  With Brexit on the horizon, we need more of these interactions between the island of Ireland and the island of Britain.  It is important that we not let this day pass without recognising the symbolic success of another visit.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frank Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Prince Charles has said he wants to come back to most of the counties in Ireland.  I believe the people of Ireland are welcoming and it is amazing how things have changed in the past six years since the Queen&rsquo;s visit.  Relations between ourselves and the United Kingdom are at an all-time high.  This augurs well in facing the difficult challenges of Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#V00200"><p>Well said Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1429" speakername="Billy Lawless" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#V00300"><p>Further to Senator McDowell's proposal to finalise the Good Friday alcohol sales Bill, I remind the Leader he gave a commitment to have it completed by Thursday, 1 June.  I hope he will stand by his word.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#V00400"><p>Eleven months ago, First Stage of the Seanad Bill 2016 was taken in the House and seven months ago, Second Stage was passed.  While I do not support every aspect of the legislation, Sinn F&eacute;in believes it is of the utmost importance that Seanad reform be prioritised.  It is no longer acceptable for this House to be exclusive, unrepresentative and unaccountable.  We can and must do better.  Nobody else and no other Chamber will prioritise this issue.  If and when Senators stand for re-election, will they be content with their work to reform this House?  Again, no one else will prioritise this issue.  The onus is on us to bring urgency to Seanad reform.  Will the Leader update the House on the progress of the Seanad Bill 2016?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#V00500"><p>Today the media reported about grants which will become available over the next several weeks to encourage people to live outside of Dublin in rural towns and villages.  There will be grants and incentives towards the renovation of such homes, particularly older ones.  Encouraging people to live in rural towns and villages is to be welcomed.  This funding is welcome, especially in the west and other areas, as people have tended to gravitate towards and move to Dublin.  I welcome this news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#V00600"><p>I want to raise the issue of the so-called welfare cheats campaign of the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Leo Varadkar.  He made some outlandish claims that with this campaign, his Department will have made &euro;500 million in savings so far.  My colleague, Deputy Eoin &Oacute; Broin, looked into this to discover the savings claimed were based on estimates of what would have been saved over 52 weeks, or in some cases, over 136 weeks, however.  In fact, the actual savings were more like &euro;41 million.</p> <p>This compares with &euro;375 million of moneys owed by employers to the Social Insurance Fund.  I have raised this issue in Commencement debates before and have asked the Department to explain why specific companies continue to trade while they owe moneys in this regard.  I am still waiting for a response from the Department.  When one takes into account the &euro;375 million which the Department is not bothering to chase and the &euro;13 billion owed by Apple which the Minister does not want to touch, it is quite clear that this is a nasty right-wing campaign from a man who wants to brand himself as the future leader of the Fine Gael Party.  It reminds me of Norman Tebbit and Mrs. Thatcher.  It is mean-spirited from the hard right of Fine Gael which, unfortunately, looks like it will lead the party into the future.</p> <p>I would like to have the Minister for Social Protection into the House to explain his spurious claims about &euro;500 million in savings.  It is a disgraceful and shameful campaign, showing where Fine Gael stands.  It wants to tramp on the little people and let the lads at the top off every time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#V00800"><p>It is now time to call on the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#V00900"><p>How does one follow that, a Leas-Chathaoirligh?</p> <p>I thank the 19 Members for their contributions to the Order of Business.  I agree with Senator Ardagh on the issue of homelessness and that reform needs to continue in this area to address the availability and supply of social housing, as well as affordability.  I would be happy for the Minister to come to the House on this issue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The issue of cyber security gained national and international prominence over the weekend.  I commend the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, and the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten, for their proactivity with the staff of the IT department in the HSE.  The Minister, Deputy Naughten, brought a memorandum to the Government this morning setting out the events and the issues in terms of how this country deals with them.  The national cyber security centre at the Department of Communications, Climate Action and Environment has been proactive and worked strongly over the weekend.  I know from talking to people who were brought into work in the HSE over the weekend that the work was taken very seriously.  Thankfully, there has been regular communication and contact over the weekend.  I used the word "proactivity" and there was strong work done by the HSE.  I commend all the staff in the IT department.</p><p>Obviously it is a matter on which we must be vigilant.  We must work to ensure that all parts of our ICT are safe.  At a personal level for all of us it is about how we can ensure we are not open to interception of our emails or any of our activity online.  Equally, there is a collective responsibility on the part of the State in regard to cyber security.  We have seen media reports of other interactions in elections in America and the attack on the NHS at the weekend.  However, I commend the Minister on his work.  The issue Senator Ardagh raises in terms of small businesses is one that requires a whole-of-government approach.  She is correct that these people are at the coalface and are not, perhaps, able to tap into the Government, as in the case of the HSE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W00200"><p>We need a director of national security.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W00300"><p>There is a need to ensure the impact is limited, that there is a whole-of-government response and that the people in small and medium enterprises mentioned by Senator Ardagh have access to support.  I will be happy to work with her in that regard.</p> <p>Senators McDowell and Lawless raised the Good Friday Bill proposed by Senator Lawless.  I hope the Bill will be back before the House as soon as the Department has finished with it.  I have been in touch with the Senator and I have liaised with the Department on his behalf.  As Leader, I will not delay the Bill from being brought before the House again.  From my discussions with the Department I am aware that it is also working on the Sale of Alcohol Bill, which is important legislation.  All of us wish to see that Bill brought to the House.  Equally, I have given the Senator a commitment in regard to his Bill and I do not have an issue with it returning to the House.  I am working with the Department to ensure it will be returned.  I am sure the Senator will give me some latitude if it is plus or minus a few days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W00400"><p>Does the Leader want us to draft the amendments or is the Department doing it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W00500"><p>The Leader without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W00600"><p>Sometimes the Senator's form of drafting could be open to misinterpretation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W00700"><p>We will not have an argument about it here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W00800"><p>I would prefer independent draftspersons to do it.  However, as I said-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W00900"><p>We can give the Leader a dig-out if he wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W01000"><p>-----I am endeavouring-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W01100"><p>He will take advice from the Attorney General, but that is a position Senator McDowell held.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W01200"><p>If Senator Craughwell is in government some day, I perish to think that he will take advice from anybody.  I look forward to that day, although not really.  However, I am working with Senator Lawless and the Department to bring the Bill back before the House.  It is subject to events, but both I and the Minister, to be fair, are endeavouring to have it back here.</p> <p>Senator Conway-Walsh spoke about a motion she is putting before the House tomorrow and Senator Paul Daly raised the issue with regard to agriculture.  I commend Senator Paul Daly on his approach to this.  To be fair to him, he did not try to play naked politics last week, as the Senator did.  Last week I offered to invite the Minister to the House for the Sinn F&eacute;in Members.  They refused that offer.  I am offering it again now to the Sinn F&eacute;in Party and particularly to Senator Paul Daly, because he is right that it is a much broader and wider part-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W01300"><p>They are like peas in a pod.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W01400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#W01500"><p>Order, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00100"><p>Sometimes it is good to listen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00200"><p>Everybody listen, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00300"><p>If Senator Paul Daly is agreeable, I am happy to have the Minister, Deputy Creed, come to the House next Wednesday, 24 May, to discuss the issues to which he referred rather than the wider, narrow focus that is in the Sinn F&eacute;in motion.  It merely seeks to play politics with farmers.  I commend Senator Daly on his work and the approach he has taken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00400"><p>We will not have a debate now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00500"><p>There are school students in the Public Gallery.  What they would like to see is us working together for the betterment of our communities, which is why later I will accept the motion from the former Minister of State, Senator &Oacute; Riord&aacute;in.  In this case it is the farming community, rather than the narrow prism through which Sinn F&eacute;in comes to everything.  Sinn F&eacute;in is for nothing and opposes everything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00600"><p>No, we oppose Fine Gael.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00700"><p>That is so populist.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00800"><p>They could well have got what they wanted, but they choose not to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X00900"><p>We will not encourage further debate, Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X01000"><p>The love bombing from Sinn F&eacute;in gets to me sometimes.  It is unbelievable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X01100"><p>They love bombing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#X01200"><p>The Senator is right there.</p> <p>On GMIT, I join Senator O'Mahony in again asking about this issue.  The Government is committed to a multi-campus provision in all institutes of technology.  As Senator O'Mahony rightly said, there has been engagement with GMIT in a genuine attempt to make the institute economically sound and put it on a firm financial footing.  An independent adviser has been appointed and the Minister, Deputy Bruton, has established a working group with the aim of putting together a sustainable plan for the future development of the Castlebar campus.  It is important that we allow that work to be done and brought to a conclusion.  The HEA has already made it clear that it is committed to this and the Minister and the Government have a whole-of- government approach to that commitment.  The working group's report should be submitted at some point during this quarter.  I am happy for the group to be allowed to do its work.  We must all ensure that there is a strong GMIT presence.  </p> <p>Senator Dolan raised the issue of Huntingdon's disease.  He mentioned that Pope Francis is hosting a gathering of people with Huntingdon's, the first such meeting with a pontiff, which I think is on tomorrow.  I commend the people from Ireland who are travelling.  I know from my time as Chairman of the Oireachtas committee on health when we held hearings on issues relating to rare diseases, of which Huntingdon's was one, that approximately 750 of our fellow citizens have Huntingdon's disease.  It is a rare disease and one for which we need to develop a strategy and an all-Ireland approach.  I would be very happy to work with the Senator on that issue.  I also join him in wishing former Taoiseach, John Bruton, a happy birthday on Thursday.    </p> <p>I am happy to take on board Senator &Oacute; Riord&aacute;in's amendment to the Order of Business.  He raised the issue of the inner city and the Mulvey report and I join him in commending the people of the inner city and that community.  He is right that it must not be about gangland crime or the reaction to an event, such as a death or shooting, but about an investment in people and in the community.  As someone who has spent a lot of time working with communities and developing them, it is important that, as a Government and as a country, we invest in people.  I am confident the Mulvey plan, which is a three-year plan of action, will be driven not only by the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, but also by all the stakeholders, including education, community, voluntary and sporting groups.  The Senator is right that it is about people making communities, and the Government must deliver and implement that plan.  There is a commitment to reopen Fitzgibbon Street Garda station and money has been ring-fenced but I share the Senator's view that there must be staging posts along to the way on the points he raised.  I would be happy for the Minister or the Taoiseach to come to the House to discuss this issue.  </p> <p>Senator Burke and Senator Murnane-O'Connor raised the issue of anti-social behaviour and the lack of implementation.  I am open to correction, but I think the Senator is incorrect and that there is legislation on this matter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important that we allow for city and county councils to take action, if needed, in respect of people who are involved------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y00200"><p>The legislation is not working because people are afraid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y00300"><p>It is about fear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y00400"><p>The Senator should raise that matter tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y00500"><p>I am not quite sure it is about fear.  To be fair, I know from my own city council that different interventions take place.  Those interventions do not necessarily involve evictions or throwing people out.  There can be other points taken in that regard and it is a matter to which we can return.  I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House to discuss that matter.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell again spoke about the Defence Forces in a very passionate way.  As he knows, we will be having a debate on the matter in the House on Wednesday of next week, when the Minister of State at the Department of Defence, Deputy Kehoe,  will be present.  There are different points to be raised and we will debate the matters the Senator raised.</p> <p>Some of the points the Senator made in regard to Galway City Council are erroneous.  It was asked to provide the Minister of State with a fully-costed feasibility study for its suggestion, as he was keen to give it his fullest consideration.  As far as I know, the council did not do that.  It was estimated that the retention of the relevant vessel between its decommissioning and its sale would have cost the State approximately &euro;370,000 because there would have been a need to assign a skeleton crew.  If the Senator looks at the issues of the cost of tug hire and the usage of the vessel, the figure of &euro;750,000 that has been mentioned today is speculative-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y00600"><p>I am not for a moment-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y00700"><p>-----particularly in the context that there has been no offer.  The Senator should listen to the remarks made by Dominic Daly on local and national radio today.  Mr. Daly is a very eminent Cork-based agent - the Senator mentioned Cork in his Commencement matter earlier- and an expert in that area.  There is speculation around the whole cost of the vessel.  Let us deal with the facts.</p> <p>On the points Senator Craughwell made in respect of our Defence Forces, the Minister of State, Deputy Kehoe, has, to be fair, demonstrated his respect for and absolute pride in our Defence Forces.  He is a very proactive Minister of State and he has not been afraid to stand up for and represent our Defence Forces.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y00800"><p>Soldiers are living in poverty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y00900"><p>The issue the Senator has raised regarding members of the Defence Forces living in poverty is one of which the Minister of State and many of us are acutely aware.  There has been a reduction in terms of the FEMPI legislation and there has been a suite of other measures.  I am not sure that the concept of members of the Defence Forces or garda&iacute; being able to go on strike is something I would personally support.  As somebody who has been a member of a trade union and who recognises the importance of trade unions-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y01000"><p>They would not do so.  No soldier would ever go on strike.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Y01100"><p>I know.  That is a different issue but we will have the debate next week.</p> <p>Senator Devine raised the issue of today's conference.  I join her in commending the Chief Nursing Officer.  The previous Government was the first to appoint a Chief Nursing Officer.  The Senator also raised the issue of the campaign in respect of rents previously.</p> <p>I wish Liam Doran well in his impending retirement from his role as general secretary of the Irish Nurses and Midwives Organisation.  He has announced his intention to step down as general secretary at some point this year.  In the context of Senator Devine's contribution, Mr. Doran has been a very strong voice for nurses.  In my former role as Chairman of the Joint Committee on Health and Children, I found him to be a pleasure to deal with.  He is a very straight talker and a very good advocate for nurses.  We might not always have agreed on certain points along the way but I always found him to be a gentleman.  I wish him and his family well.</p> <p>Senator Higgins referred to the ECJ ruling on the Singapore free trade agreement.  I would be happy to invite the relevant Minister to come before the House to discuss that issue.</p> <p>Senator Noone raised the very important matter of air pollution and the fact that we can do so much to preserve life and ensure that people live longer.  The figures she supplied in respect of ingestion of pollutants reducing life expectancy by nine months are frightening.  I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House with regard to the matter she raised.</p> <p>On behalf of all Senators, I join Senator Norris in saying "Bravo" to the Wexford Festival Opera on the warm tribute it was paid by being deemed the best opera festival in the world.  It is important to recognise that huge things grow from little acorns.  In this case, a renowned opera festival has developed.  I join Senator Norris in commending all involved.</p> <p>Senator Murnane O'Connor referred to the revaluation of commercial rates.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Senator Feighan raised the issue of the visit of Prince Charles and his wife, Camilla, to Ireland in the past week.  I join the Senator in welcoming the couple to Ireland.  It was fantastic that the visit was such a success and that Prince Charles enjoyed the garden party at the British Ambassador's residence and the more formal events in Glasnevin Cemetery.  As Senator Feighan says, the normalisation of his encounter with the leader of Sinn F&eacute;in, Deputy Gerry Adams, and other groups around the country makes it all the better.  It is through high-profile events such as this that we can see that the relationship with the British royal family has been normalised.  I commend Senator Feighan for his work on promoting relations between the North and the South and also between Ireland and the UK.  He has been a prolific member of committees, as has the Cathaoirleach.  However, to be fair to Senator Feighan, this event was one of his signature political involvements and I commend him for it.</p><p>I have already responded to Senator Lawless on the issue he raised regarding Good Friday.</p><p>Senator Warfield asked about the issue of Seanad reform.  It is a work in progress.  An implementation committee which has been set up is awaiting the appointment of a chairman.  It is beyond my remit to appoint that chairman.  Members have changed how the House does business.  This is evident from the increased number of Senators seconding Private Members' Bills, the business group that discusses the business of the House and the broad-minded way in which I approach issues, although some Sinn F&eacute;in Members may not agree with that last point.  Members may not ever be in unison on the issue of Seanad reform but I accept that we need to consider how it can be brought about.</p><p>Senator Byrne raised the important issue of people being encouraged to live outside Dublin.  I join her in welcoming the living grant scheme in towns and villages outside Dublin and I hope it will receive take-up.</p><p>Senator Gavan raised the issue of social welfare and the work of the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Varadkar.  The Senator should join me in the welcoming the Minister's campaigns on many issues such as maternity, paternity or, in this case, social welfare fraud.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z00200"><p>It is a farce.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z00300"><p>It is important that we recognise that the purpose of this campaign is to ensure-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z00400"><p>It is disgraceful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z00500"><p>-----that there is reporting of social welfare fraud so that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z00600"><p>It is a campaign of hate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z00700"><p>------money can be saved and invested by the State.  That money can be invested in different Departments.  Every &euro;1 that we save can be given to a person who genuinely needs intervention or support.  The Senator may huff and puff-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z00800"><p>It is absolutely no money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z00900"><p>Employers owe &euro;375 million to the Social Insurance Fund.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z01000"><p>The Department of Social Protection has an annual budget of &euro;20 billion.  The campaign is designed to ensure that people do not abuse the system and that the money saved is spent on people who need it.  It suits the Senator to use the rhetoric he has today but it does not serve the purpose of the campaign.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z01100"><p>The truth hurts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z01200"><p>I am happy to accept Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in's proposal.</p> <p>I know Senator Conway-Walsh intends to table a motion tomorrow regarding the review of the areas of natural constraint, ANC, scheme but I am happy to have statements next week and that the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Creed, come to the House as Senator Paul Daly has requested.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z01300"><p>Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 16 be taken before No. 1."  The Leader has indicated he is prepared to accept the amendment.  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.178" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.179" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z01500">Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission (Gender Pay Gap Information) Bill 2017: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z01600"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to require certain employers to publish information relating to the pay of employees for the purpose of showing whether there are differences in the pay of male and female employees and, if so, the nature and scale of such differences; for that purpose to amend the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission Act 2014; and to provide for related matters.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z01700"><p>Is there a seconder?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z01800"><p>I second the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.183" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z02000"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z02100"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#Z02200"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.187" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 23 May 2017.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.188" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#AA00100">EU Regulation on Insolvency Proceedings: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#AA00200"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to accept the following measure: Regulation (EU) 2017/353 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 15 February 2017 replacing Annexes A and B to Regulation (EU) 2015/848 on insolvency proceedings, a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 13 April, 2017, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3)(<i>k</i>), which, not later than 31 May, 2017, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 74, and Standing Order 76(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.190" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.191" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#AA00400">Legal Acts in the Area of Justice: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#AA00500"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure: Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council adapting a number of legal acts in the area of Justice providing for the use of the regulatory procedure with scrutiny to Article 290 of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 12 January, 2017, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3)(<i>k</i>), which, not later than 31 May, 2017, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 74, and Standing Order 76(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.193" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.194" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.35 p.m. and resumed at 4.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.195" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#CC00100">Migrant Integration Strategy: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#CC00150"><p>We now move on to statements on the migrant integration strategy.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, and invite him to commence the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017051600002#CC00200"><p>I welcome the opportunity to discuss the migrant integration strategy, which the Government launched on 7 February 2017.  I have arranged for copies of the strategy to be made available to Senators in the Seanad anteroom.</p> <p>The strategy is intended to help us to chart a way forward along the path of successful integration, building on the positive outcomes we have already achieved and setting achievable and realistic goals for the future.  We consulted widely on the strategy, which has been developed over an extensive period.  I thank all those who contributed, not least Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, whose leadership in the early stages of the process helped us to reach this important milestone.</p> <p>Over the past two decades, Ireland has become an increasingly diverse country.  Census 2016 reveals that just over 800,000 of those currently resident in Ireland were born outside the country.  A little over 600,000 people speak a language other than English or Irish at home.  This in an increase of 19% over the 2011 figure.  At the same time, the figures reveal a strong commitment to Ireland among those born elsewhere.  Just over 100,000 people are now dual citizens of Ireland and another country.  This confirms the strong interest among many persons of migrant origin in becoming Irish citizens and in making a permanent commitment to Ireland.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Ireland&rsquo;s record on integration has been quite positive so far.  Significant progress has been made over the past two decades to integrate migrants into Irish society.  The actions taken by successive Governments, as well as by the business sector, civil society organisations and local communities, have achieved positive outcomes for migrants in key areas.  The degree to which migrants have integrated into many Irish workplaces is a particular success story.  Social inclusion measures have ensured that migrants do not experience significantly higher risks of poverty because of their migrant status.  In 2012, the differentials in the "at risk of poverty" rates for citizens and third country nationals were narrowest in Ireland of all EU member states.  </p><p>Integration plans have been devised for key sectors.  The intercultural education strategy has focused on enabling students to experience an education respectful of diversity while assisting education providers to ensure that integration becomes the norm within an intercultural learning environment.  The National Intercultural Health Strategy 2007-2012 provided a framework for action by the health service to respond to increasing cultural diversity.  A new intercultural health strategy will be developed as one of the actions foreseen under this integration strategy.</p><p>Equally, many businesses recognise the importance of managing workplace diversity successfully.  Some 50 companies in Ireland representing well over 100,000 employees have signed up to the diversity charter to demonstrate their commitment to diversity.  Many more companies have developed expertise in managing workplace diversity well.  However, we cannot be complacent.  We know that there will be challenges ahead.  The record of other EU countries demonstrates that ghettoisation, isolation, or indeed poorer outcomes, particularly for second generation immigrants, can create problems very quickly.  We also have to avoid the growth of racism within the host population.  If we are to realise the benefits of integration we need firstly to avoid some of the pitfalls that have developed in other countries.  There are great benefits for Irish society if we get our integration model right.  </p><p>This migrant integration strategy has been framed in the understanding that the integration process is becoming increasingly complex.  The composition of the migrant population is ever more diverse.  Migrants come from diverse cultures, religions, backgrounds and experiences.  Some are English-speaking and some are not.  While the recent focus has been on the refugees coming to Ireland under the Irish refugee protection programme, many migrants are now well-established in Ireland and have been here for some time.  The strategy needs to be sufficiently flexible to encompass refugees and economic migrants, those who are new to Ireland and those who have spent their lives here.  </p><p>The context within which this strategy has been developed is also complex and subject to change.   We are currently experiencing a migration crisis on Europe&rsquo;s borders.  It is likely that this crisis will continue for the years ahead, with migrants continuing to try to come to Europe to escape conflict, persecution and limited economic opportunities.  Undoubtedly the countries of origin of those migrants may change but the pressure to move northwards and westwards may not.   Brexit introduces another variable into the equation.  Its impact is not yet known.  What is known is that it will be an additional factor that migrants will take into account when considering future life choices.  The risks of populist, anti-immigrant movements and the radicalisation of some of those of migrant origin in other EU countries have been well signalled.</p><p>We have the opportunity to avoid the mistakes of other societies.  We must avoid in particular the segregation and isolation of migrant communities.  Segregation can fracture shared understandings between migrant and non-migrant populations.  This can lead to the growth of racist sentiment.  It can also lead to the loss of economic and social opportunities for migrant communities.      </p><p>The principal aim in this strategy is to promote the ability of migrants to participate actively in Irish society and to foster a sense of belonging within this society for them.  The strategy builds on the foundation of what has been achieved so far.  It recognises that mainstream services have to place a renewed focus on integration to ensure that migrants gain equal access to such services.  Equally, it proposes a range of targeted measures to address barriers which prevent migrants from realising their full potential.  We have to recognise that some migrants, particularly the refugees coming into Ireland under the Irish refugee protection programme, may have complex needs and may need targeted services.   </p><p>The migrant integration strategy is intended as the framework for the Government&rsquo;s action on migrant integration for the period from 2017 to 2020 and has been devised to respond to the new challenges that we anticipate in the years ahead.  It will run from 2017 until 2020 and is targeted at EU and non-EU nationals, including refugees.  It is also targeted at foreign-born Irish citizens and their children.  </p><p>Our focus for this strategy is to build on the good practices already in place and to provide further supports where necessary.  We must replicate existing successful initiatives.  Equally, we must ensure that areas needing attention are identified and measures taken to address any problems.  The actions and recommendations contained in this strategy cover a wide range of very important areas including, among others, access to public services and social inclusion, education, health and employment.  It builds on the existing approach to combine mainstream services and targeted initiatives to address specific needs.  Its key message is that integration is a two-way process that will involve change and responsibilities both for migrants and for Irish society.  It aims to communicate the message that successful integration is the responsibility of Irish society as a whole.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It seeks to encourage action by Government, public bodies, service providers, businesses, NGOs and local communities, and encouraging action by local communities will be a key element of the strategy.</p><p>One issue that emerged repeatedly in the consultation process for this strategy was the need to ensure individuals and families are fully integrated into local communities.  They risk being unaware of information or opportunities if they are not linked to the community and official networks on which others rely.  The strategy puts forward a number of initiatives to reach out to groups and families that may be isolated from mainstream society.  It proposes to use networks as a means by which migrant and non-migrant groups and organisations can get to know one another and through which migrants can raise issues of concern.  Dublin City Council, for instance, will set up a network targeted at hard to reach migrant groups building on a model pioneered by New York city.</p><p>Similarly, a network will be established for schools outside the established system to inform them of child protection and health and safety obligations.  We intend to use this network as a means of establishing relationships with such schools, many of which operate outside any form of oversight but which are interested in being compliant on child protection etc.  It is intended that such networks will be used as a means of communicating information but also of building shared understandings with regard to norms and expectations.</p><p>Reaching out to young people is a particular concern within the strategy.  Older teenagers and young adults can turn away from existing youth structures, particularly if they experience family pressures not to mix in opposite sex groups.  The strategy proposes that the youth sector will look at ways of engaging with these young people of migrant origin in order that they get the chance to develop and maintain relationships with their peers within Irish society.</p><p>The strategy seeks to address areas where migrants are under-represented.  It includes actions that seek to improve the representation of migrants throughout the public service.  It proposes that a target of 1% will be established for the employment of European Economic Area, EEA, nationals and people from minority ethnic communities within the Civil Service.  This will be monitored for progress towards the target.  Initiatives will be taken to raise awareness within migrant communities of the opportunities presented by careers in the Civil Service.  I see this as an important step towards ensuring the Civil Service is more representative of the population of Ireland as a whole.</p><p>Similarly, an awareness-raising initiative is planned to encourage under-represented groups, including migrants, to apply for appointment to State boards.  The aim is to raise awareness among migrants and persons of migrant origin of opportunities on State boards in order that they can be encouraged to apply for such opportunities.  Getting more diverse voices onto State boards should yield benefits in two directions.  Migrants will gain access to wider decision-making opportunities in society.  In turn, State boards will benefit from a wider pool of talent and expertise.</p><p>The consultations held with migrant groups during the process of drafting the strategy confirmed that migrant organisations are especially interested in the area of political participation.  They want to see higher turnout by migrants in relevant elections.  They also want the political parties to encourage more migrants to become involved, including as potential candidates.  In response, the strategy includes a number of actions to encourage greater participation in political life by migrants.  The first step is to encourage more migrants to register for and vote in elections.</p><p>Ensuring mainstream services understand and are responsive to migrant needs is very important.  The strategy proposes that integration will be mainstreamed into the work of all relevant Departments and agencies.  It proposes ongoing intercultural training for front-line staff of Departments.  It also reiterates the need for information for migrants in language-appropriate formats.  English language proficiency emerged as a key concern in consultations with migrant groups.  They want to see more targeted language training and greater opportunities for progression.  The strategy proposes to include a language component in education and training programmes for unemployed migrants with a poor knowledge of English.  The role of the education and training boards will be crucial in ensuring these opportunities are available, including to enable migrants to develop the language skills to access skilled employment.</p><p>While employment rates are broadly similar for migrants and non-migrants, one group, namely, Africans, have much lower rates of employment than the norm.  The Department of Social Protection is undertaking an initiative to examine the reasons Africans have lower than average rates of employment.  Our concern is to ensure employment opportunities are available to African migrants on an equal basis with other groups.  We also want to tackle any risk that Africans might get locked into intergenerational exclusion from the labour market.  More broadly, initiatives are planned to ensure migrant needs in skills acquisition and labour market activation are addressed.</p><p>As I have said, many employers have gained experience in managing diversity effectively.  Many businesses have developed expertise in managing diversity in their customer base.  There is a role now for business to communicate that expertise within the wider society.  The strategy seeks to encourage businesses to focus more on using their corporate social responsibility activities to promote integration.  The work to engage with the business sector to encourage its ongoing activities to manage workplace diversity will continue.  Equally, initiatives are being undertaken to promote migrant entrepreneurship using EU funding streams.</p><p>The health service is a very good example of a system that has adapted to meet the challenges of diversity.  However, some of the refugees coming into Ireland at the moment have complex health needs.  This may require additional resources within the health service to deal with their needs.  The proposed second national intercultural health strategy will provide a framework for addressing the needs of this vulnerable cohort.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-05-16a.200" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>