<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh that, on the motion for the Adjournment of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:<blockquote><br />Go dtabharfaidh an tAire Talmha&iacute;ochta, Bia agus Mara briseadh s&iacute;os ar na h-&iacute;oca&iacute;ochta&iacute; at&aacute; d&eacute;anta ag a Roinn leis na h&Uacute;dar&aacute;is &Aacute;iti&uacute;la &eacute;ags&uacute;la i leith 2011 agus 2012, chun capaill ar strae a th&oacute;g&aacute;il, an chostas measta do 2013 agus m&iacute;ni&uacute; c&eacute;n chaoi an bhfuil s&eacute; i gceist aige an fhadhb seo a r&eacute;iteach ar bhonn n&aacute;isi&uacute;nta.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance to consider setting aside an unused building for a temporary alternative purpose such as the currently unused old Ballymun Garda station to accommodate a worthwhile cause in the community.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Mark Daly of the following matter:<blockquote>To ask Minister for Health to clarify the number of paediatrics tracheotomy patients in Ireland by county and clarify the number of registered paediatrics nurses who have been assessed and deemed competent as per the ABA guidelines 2000 to nurse these children in their homes and who regulates this process.</blockquote>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:<blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to outline the new procedures he intends to put in place to audit the substantial funds given by the HSE and the Department of Health to section 39 organisations.</blockquote>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion on the Adjournment and they will be taken at the conclusion of business.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600003#B00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600003#B00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill 2013 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600003#B00300"><p>It is Government business that the Seanad should deal with the matter on today's Order Paper but we have a fundamental objection to the proposal to deal with Committee Stage of the Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill on Thursday.  That is very wrong.  This is serious legislation that will have a lasting impact on tens of thousands of pensioners and there is a deliberate attempt by the Government to hush it up and ram the legislation through the Seanad at the earliest possible time.  I have been contacted by a number of pensioners&rsquo; organisations and pensioners themselves who are very concerned about the Bill.  They feel this possible major change to the pension structure of many older people and future pensioners is being hidden by the Government.</p><p>Unless the Leader can give a commitment in that regard we will oppose the Order of Business and we would also oppose any motion this evening to have Committee Stage on Thursday.  That would be a retrograde step.  I acknowledge that the Leader has been most co-operative on such matters in recent weeks.  We are most grateful for that on this side.  I am particularly grateful for the acknowledgement last week by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform of the referendum result and for accepting amendments to legislation concerning the Seanad.  I am most grateful to him in that regard and for the co-operation of the Government side.  It would be an injustice to the people who voted to save the Seanad to allow such a major piece of legislation as the Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill to be railroaded through the Seanad this week.  I urge the Leader to reflect on that.  I ask him in a co-operative way but we will have to oppose the Order of Business and any further motions on the matter this evening.</p><p>I briefly wish to allude to another matter, I will not say too much about it, namely, the notorious Rodolphus Allen trust.  I raised the matter in the Seanad last July.  I described it as a scam and I encouraged people not to get involved.  I reported it to the Garda.  I am pleased to see action has been taken at last and some of those involved have been arrested and are before the courts.  I repeat my warning to people about such scams.  They should not deal with them but they should contact appropriate advisers, banks and organisations that deal with people in mortgage difficulties.</p><p>I would appreciate the Leader&rsquo;s co-operation on the Order of Business.  I know he is sympathetic but I realise the pressure he is under from the Government on the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600003#B00400"><p>I welcome the reports in today&rsquo;s newspapers that the Government will introduce legislation to extend the right to vote in Seanad elections for the university panel seats at least, and that we will see an expansion of the electorate for the six university seats to cover all third level graduates in the various institutions across the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600003#B00500"><p>It was Senator Terry Leyden's Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600003#B00600"><p>All of us on the university panel have always called for such an extension.  When the Taoiseach was in the House speaking on Seanad reform in the aftermath of the referendum he gave a commitment in that regard.  It is most welcome to see today's newspaper reports that the Government is now considering a Bill to extend the university franchise.</p> <p>It is a step on the way to ensuring we see reform of the Seanad through legislation.  We should have another debate on this in the new year.  I hope we will and that at that point we will see more concrete proposals coming forward, not just from the Government but from all parties.  We already have two Private Members' Bills which have passed Second Stage in this House and which provide for reforms through legislation.  I would welcome further debate on the issue that would look at the sort of concrete reforms we can make through legislation.  I welcome the reports on the expansion of the university electorate, which is hugely important.  It is great to see the institutes of technology, the DIT and the other institutes, becoming part of the electorate.  The DIT graduates had a vote for the university seats for some years, prior to it getting the right to award its own degrees.  Therefore, it is not true to say no institute of technology graduates were represented in the Seanad.  The three of us here from the University of Dublin represent some DIT graduates.  It is great to see the expansion of the vote to all third level institutions.</p><p>I also welcome the CSO data published today, which shows an increase of 58,000 people at work over the past year and a rise in employment of 3.2%.  This small rise is welcome, but must be taken with caution.  The data also shows a parallel decrease in the unemployment rate, from 13.6% to 12.8% in the last quarter.  This is welcome.  It is particularly welcome that long-term unemployment has reduced.   Will the Leader arrange a debate in the new year on the unemployment data and the measures we can take to allow this pattern continue?</p><p>The Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton, has promised to bring before us her implementation plan for the youth guarantee before Christmas and we will debate job creation in that context.  However, we should have an opportunity in the new year to debate job creation, in particular the sort of measures and policies that can be implemented by the State in this regard.  The Minister has spoken of the role the family income supplement can play in helping people return to work, by allowing a top-up payment to employees on low pay with children to ease the transition from welfare to employment.  Currently, more than 40,000 working families are covered by the scheme.  This is the sort of scheme that can assist in helping people return to work and we could usefully debate this in the new year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600004#C00200"><p>I too welcome the announcement of the Bill relating to Seanad reform, but it is only a small step.  When the Taoiseach was in this House, he said there would be a meeting with leaders on reform, but I have not heard of any date for that meeting.  Will the Leader advise us on whether a date has been set for that meeting?  The people voted and gave us a mandate and we now need to see reform.  We need to see all Senators involved in that debate.</p><p>I wish to raise again the issue of the Bill to deal with smoking in cars with children.  I am not happy with the answers we have received on this.  I do not believe there is an any real block, other than the lack of political will to move forward on the Bill.  Senators Crown, Daly and I have put considerable effort into a Bill.  Will the Leader advise us when the Minister for Health will be able to bring to us the amendments he would like to see?</p><p>In regard to youth unemployment, Senator Bacik mentioned the debate on the youth guarantee.  We have yet to receive a date for that debate, although the time is fast approaching for Ireland to submit its plan to the European Union.  One of the small concessions we won in the Seanad when we debated the Social Welfare Bill was that we would have this debate on the youth guarantee.  Will the Leader advise us whether the Minister, Deputy Burton, has given us a date for that debate?  Many of the organisations involved, who are in contact with various Senators, await that debate so that we can give voice to and articulate their views in regard to the proposals to be put forward to the European Union in Ireland's name. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600004#C00300"><p>I also give a ritual welcome to the idea of reforming the Seanad.  However, during the referendum campaign the Government showed an extraordinary degree of cynicism and dishonesty.  I do not believe the leopard changes its spots much.  I have always called for the expansion of the electorate for the university seats, but we were told during the referendum campaign that none of us ever did.  We need to look at the implications of expansion of the electorate.  There are already approximately 200,000 voters in the combined university electorate.  This will increase to 500,000.  That is fine, but there must be an accurate register or the system will not work.</p> <p>It will mean young candidates will have very little chance because high-profile candidates in a six-seater constituency will have a much greater chance of getting in.  There will be a question of funding.  Printing 500,000 leaflets is an onerous financial task for young people.  It took me ten years and six elections to get in and I had an overdraft which I could hardly bear.  We should be facilitating young people in getting into the Seanad.  For example, all graduates of Trinity College Dublin have retained their @tcd.ie e-mail address.  This is a cheap and easy way for candidates to communicate with their electorate.</p><p>We have been calling for the reform of the university seats for a long time.  I have been in this House for 26 years and the only target of reform has been the university seats.  We need real reform to include the other seats.  The only democratic element, which has 200,000 voters, will increase to 500,000 voters while the political panels, in the control of the political parties, will have their vote base reduced from 1,000 to 500 because of the diminution this wonderfully democratic Government is inflicting on local authority membership.  On the one hand, we are having this vast increase in the electorate for the universities and, on the other, a comparable decrease in the electorate of local authority members.  That is not democracy.  That is the kind of slyness and hypocrisy about which I spoke earlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D00200"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D00300"><p>Yes.  I am calling for a debate on this.  There should be some degree of finance available to young Seanad candidates.  I believe young people who run for the Seanad, whether they are successful or not, and who reach a certain number of votes should get some recompense in these difficult days.  I put this down as an amendment to a Bill recently but it was thrown out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D00400"><p>The Senator is over his time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D00500"><p>The Taoiseach has already met with the party leaders in the D&aacute;il about the Seanad - about us - yet he has not met with us, which I believe is treating us with contempt.  Last week the Seanad had to cancel business and not sit because, out of 30 Ministers, they could not find one to come into this House.</p><p>I congratulate the Union of Students in Ireland, USI, and its president, Mr. Joe O&rsquo;Connor, who have disassociated themselves from this ridiculous DrinkAware campaign, funded by Diageo to the tune of &euro;10 million, which is intended to get people drinking as hard as they possibly can.  Arthur&rsquo;s day?  What a laugh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D00600"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D00700"><p>They have eliminated the whole Guinness family from the company.  It should be called Diageo day.  We know they make submarines, planes and lavatories.  It is not Arthur&rsquo;s Day, a national day.  It is a squalid-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D00800"><p>I call Senator Conway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D00900"><p>-----capitalist plot.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D01000"><p>I believe in positive politics and looking to the future.  Today&rsquo;s announcement by the Government that it will extend the university franchise to graduates of Dublin Institute of Technology and every other third level college is a step in the right direction.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D01100"><p>We all believe in positive politics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D01200"><p>I did not interrupt the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D01300"><p>Senator Conway without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600005#D01400"><p>It makes all graduates equal, a badly needed development.  It is a significant reform in the right direction which we should be embracing.  We should offer to facilitate the legislation in this House.  If we need to sit extra days in the run-up to Christmas to facilitate getting this legislation through, then we should.  It would be a good day for the Seanad.  I admire the Government for listening to the people and moving forward positively following the result of the Seanad referendum.  It is a major and significant step in the right direction for the fundamental reform of this House.</p><p>It is also a great day in that we welcome the fact that the unemployment rate has gone below 13%, to 12.8%.</p> <p>That is significant.  We in this House played a role as the result of an initiative by Senator Mullins, who had debates here on job creation in which citizens of this country came in and outlined their views and ideas on how we could create jobs.  This informed the Department and Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  The process has worked well and we should consider continuing it in the new year.  The one way to create an equal-opportunity society is to give people work and allow people to gain access to it.  We have made significant progress in this.  We all have our part to play and I look forward to more people getting jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600006#E00200"><p>When will the Bill be published?  I have already published a Bill, which took me some time.  We could run the two Bills together in the House and compare notes.</p><p>I compliment the Garda Commissioner, Martin Callinan, and his team, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, the emergency response unit and all associated with the successful capture of seven people detained for the robbery in Killenaule, County Tipperary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600006#E00300"><p>That case is before the courts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600006#E00400"><p>It is before the courts but it is still public knowledge.  I want to make a point about this and compliment the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na on its speedy action.  It is a matter for the courts to decide what the penalty will be for this crime.  Emma and Mark Corcoran's house was robbed.  Their three children were threatened with having their hands cut off, and yet these-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600006#E00500"><p>We will not discuss the specifics of the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600006#E00600"><p>Coming up to Christmas people should be on guard and alert to the robbery of gold and jewellery around the countryside.  Shops have been opened up inviting people to bring gold jewellery to be melted down and sold with no restrictions.  I am getting tired of free legal aid being granted to people who commit crimes, come out on bail and commit more crimes.  The judges, without even questioning the fact that they may have assets, like some of the people in "Love/Hate", grant free legal aid willy-nilly.  The best lawyers are employed at the best fees to defend these people, who are indefensible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600006#E00700"><p>As Senator Leyden well knows, that is a matter for the judges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600006#E00800"><p>Yes, but it is no harm for us to discuss it.  We pass the legislation.  I call on the Minister for Justice and Equality to review free legal aid.  I want to put people on alert regarding the threats coming.  They have closed the Garda stations and it is an encouragement to crime.  This is a battle between law and order and the gangsters.  We must ensure the Garda is fully funded to defend citizens against robbers and people who are prepared to kill, murder and maim in the pursuit of their own aims.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600006#E00900"><p>I welcome the fact that the first case has been concluded through the Insolvency Service of Ireland, resulting in the write-down of 70% of the debts of the individuals concerned.  Given that one petitioner has submitted 20 cases, if the Leader is agreeable we should have a debate early in the new year on the progress made by the Insolvency Service of Ireland in dealing with distressed mortgages.  There is a particular difficulty in resolving mortgage arrears where a couple is in a marital breakdown situation.  To deal with that there will be a need for a change in the law, and we need a review of that.</p><p>I was recently at a meeting at which Traveller accommodation in the Dublin City Council area was discussed and I was disturbed to discover that a number of Traveller families were living in approved Traveller accommodation which lacked basic facilities such as electricity and water.  I ask the Leader to invite the Minister with responsibility for housing, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, here to discuss the national strategy on Traveller accommodation.  We cannot stand over a situation, in spite of our economic difficulties, in which any family in this country has no access to basic facilities such as running water and electricity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600007#F00100"><p>I wish to raise the issue of Seanad reform.  In as much as we can, we welcome the news the Government may extend the vote in Seanad elections to all third level graduates.  At one level this is a step forward, but we can all agree it is not real reform; it is not what people want and it will not go far enough.  As long as all citizens in the State do not have a vote for the people in this Chamber the House will suffer as a consequence.  I genuinely believe in a republic all citizens should be able to elect the people sent to any arm of Parliament, whether it be the D&aacute;il or the Seanad.  I would like to see universal franchise.</p><p>We must also look at the powers and responsibilities of the Seanad in the spirit of the referendum result.  It was very clear from the result, and from the debate, that many people who campaigned for a &quot;No&quot; vote campaigned for reform.  In my view citizens voted for real reform of the Seanad and not piecemeal reform.  Will the Leader arrange a debate on this issue in advance of legislation coming forward, so the Government will be able to signal to us and elaborate on what other reforms will come with regard to the Seanad?  I hope we will not end up after the next D&aacute;il general election with the election to the Seanad being exactly the same as it was for previous elections, with the exception perhaps of the university panel.  This is an important issue and I hope the Leader will arrange for a debate on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600007#F00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600007#F00300"><p>Many hospice associations throughout the country provide services.  Men and women from throughout the country give up their time and take time off work to transport very sick and ill people to various hospitals in Dublin.  Those who volunteer consider it an honour and an act of mercy but there is an issue I wish to take up with the Minister for Health.  In many cases these people have costs with regard to tolls and petrol but the cost of car parking at hospitals in Dublin is astronomical.  Last week I spoke to a young man who took a very ill person to Dublin.  He collected him at 6 a.m. and he did not get home to his lonely cottage until almost 6 p.m.  He waited for four or five hours in Dublin for his appointment.  Is it possible to discuss the matter of hospital car parks in the House?  I am sure it is of concern to other colleagues in various parts of the country.  The car parks are run by private concerns.  Concessions in hospital car parks throughout the country should be considered for the volunteers doing an act of mercy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600007#F00400"><p>Will the Leader organise a debate on the headlines which appeared in the <i>Sunday Business Post</i> on Ireland's cancer survival rate, which is among the worst in Europe?  The House has led the way in terms of a consultation process on cancer which provided the information that one third of cancers are caused by lifestyle choices.  As my colleague, Senator van Turnhout, pointed out, a Bill brought to the floor of the House more than two years ago, which is supported by the Government, with regard to banning smoking in cars where children are present, got stuck in bureaucracy.  This is an area where the Government could take action and on which it stated it would take action but nothing has happened.</p> <p>It is one of the areas where the Government could take action and said it would take action, yet nothing happened.</p><p>I also welcome the news that the Government is going to expand the franchise.  However, I am disappointed because the Taoiseach came in here and told us that he was going to consult with the leaders in this House about how reform should take place, yet now we read about the reform in the press.  Will the franchise be expanded to the Irish living overseas?  Will it be extended to the Irish living in the North?  We are one of the few countries in the world that does not give votes to its citizens living outside the State, yet that will continue under the Taoiseach's proposal.</p><p>I would like to call for a debate on the BBC &quot;Panorama&quot; programme from last week.  It was shocking.  In a litany of what has happened in the North of Ireland, what was exposed by that programme was nothing short of outrageous.  Earlier in the week, the DPP for the North of Ireland, Mr. Larkin, suggested that there should be no prosecutions as a result of what had happened in the past in the North.  In this programme we saw members of a British army unit, the rapid reaction force, boasting about what they had done and saying they would do it again.  They went on the programme not for reasons of remorse; it was about recognition and reward.  They wanted to be recognised for what they did.  They went around Belfast and they shot innocent civilians.  Some of them got promoted for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G00200"><p>You are way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G00300"><p>If that was happening in Argentina, Central America or the Far East, they would call them "death squads".  The most shocking part of the programme - this needs to be questioned by our Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade - is that a memo to the British Prime Minister at the time, Mr. Ted Heath, stated that when the unit was being disbanded, special care should be taken to ensure that the British army replacement squad operated within the law.  That suggested the British Prime Minister was well aware that the unit being replaced was acting outside the law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G00400"><p>You are way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G00500"><p>What did he do about it?  What is our Government doing about asking the current British Prime Minister why no action was taken------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G00600"><p>I call on Senator Mullins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G00700"><p>-----when a former British Prime Minister was well aware that there was a British army unit going around the North of Ireland killing people at will, acting like a death squad in Central America.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G00800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G00900"><p>I want to join in the optimism this afternoon and welcome the significant increase in employment that we have seen to date in 2013, with a total increase of those at work of 58,000.  It shows that the Action Plan for Jobs is working and I applaud the Minister, Deputy Bruton, and the Cabinet for keeping the pressure on to deliver on the action items that were contained in that particular plan.  I hope that the trend continues into 2014, and that the budget measures taken, such as extending the lower rate of VAT to the hospitality sector and the tax incentive to people to upgrade their homes, will have a significant impact on employment in 2014.</p><p>There is grave concern across the country about the possibility of an ESB strike before Christmas.  We all know the implications of a strike by ESB workers for all citizens, but in particular for the elderly.  It also has implications for employment and the health service, including our hospitals.  I call publicly today for the company and the unions to get back into discussions as a matter of urgency.  We need a debate with the Minister about the contingency plans being put in place in the event of a strike taking place.  We also need a wider debate on whether it is right that any group of workers would be in a position to hold the country to ransom and shut down vital national strategic services.  I ask the Leader to organise a debate with the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources on that particular issue, especially on the plans the Government is putting in place in the event of a strike in a few weeks' time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600008#G01000"><p>The group which visited earlier was from Derry, Donegal and Fermanagh as part of the peace process, and I did not get the chance to welcome them.  Apropos of the other discussions we have had, a critical thing the university constituencies did was to enrol people resident in Northern Ireland.  The State has been spectacularly unable or unwilling to do that ever since the partition of Ireland, so I hope that the new university constituencies will not be partitionist, as the State typically is and the universities were not.</p> <p> I wish to express the hope, particularly as we will discuss pensions later, that the ESB workers do not strike on the basis of their grievance about pensions.   </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H00300"><p>This is the place that they can bring their concerns.  I am sure that the Leader and the Minister will take their views on board.</p><p>I agree with Senator Mullins on the increase in employment, which is most welcome.  It is incumbent on the Government not to allow property booms, bubbles, false optimism or grandiose plans to reassert themselves.  We seem to be going in the right direction and that is to be welcomed.  Go raibh maith agat. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H00400"><p>I strongly agree with the comments made by Senator Thomas Byrne on bogus trusts.  People need to be extremely wary in all of these cases.  We have already seen some instances of trusts being without legal standing.  That is enough about the matter for the moment.</p><p>I welcome the announcement of the Luas cross-city rail project.  It is tremendous that a loan for it has been arranged with the European Investment Bank.  The project will transform rail transport in Dublin city and hopefully, as indicated, it will take up to 3 million cars off the road.  </p><p>I wish to comment on the remarks made by Senator Daly.  I urge him, as ever, to exercise more caution and less haste in levelling criticism.  In the past the force to which he referred to was rather unsavoury, to say the least, but I do not think that we can be so assertive as to say that things happened at will.  We should wait until the US special envoy releases his report on all legacy issues.  When we have the report then we can calmly reflect on the matter and debate the entire situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H00500"><p>As Members will know, the HSE's service plan is supposed to be announced today and I wonder what is in store for us.  Let us recall the &euro;119 million overrun last September.  What is it now?  What about the proposed cut of &euro;666 million?  What about the notional achievement of &euro;113 million in cuts to medical cards?  In parallel, there are 29 CEOs in hospitals throughout the country being paid additional money from other sources.  In addition, 34 out of 63 disability service providers receive HSE funds.  That breaches the guidelines for HSE CEOs at a time when we saw, for example, St. Michael's House writing to families whom it caters for to inform them that it would have to cut services due to a reduction in funding.</p><p>All of these anomalies exist against the backdrop of the Government continuing to insist that there will be free GP care for under 5s even though, on the lunchtime news today, we heard the chairman of the National Association of General Practitioners call the plan laughable.  The same applies to the overall plan to provide universal health care for all.  It does not seem to be consistent with Government policy and certainly outcomes so far.</p><p>I wish to amend the Order of Business and call for the Minister for Health to come to the House today to discuss the blunt instrument that is called a &quot;probity drive&quot; which is used to assess and review medical cards.  As so often is the case with anomalies in the health service, it takes a high profile intervention before finally some progress is made.  We can hardly have a more high profile instance than what developed today.  I refer to Ms Marie Fleming and her poor family.  Ms Fleming went to the Supreme Court to seek the right to die but was unsuccessful.  I apologise for mentioning names but I must use privilege in the public interest on this occasion.  Her partner, Tom Curran, was on the lunchtime news today to highlight her individual case.  He said that he was contacted as part of a review of her medical card and asked whether her condition had changed.  He made contact by telephone with the HSE who asked him to fill out a form to give details of her medical condition.  This was not good enough for the HSE and it followed up by seeking proof of her medical condition.  It seems that he telephoned another three times to be asked to fill out further documentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H00600"><p>Absolutely disgraceful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H00700"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate on the matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H00800"><p>Mr. Curran rightly pointed out to the nation that the medical card review was a waste of resources, money and time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H00900"><p>And inhumanity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H01000"><p>Is it not possible to log the fact that somebody suffers from multiple sclerosis-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H01100"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H01200"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600009#H01300"><p>-----and that his or her situation will not change.  I ask the Cathaoirleach to indulge me, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600010#J00100"><p>The Senator's time has expired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600010#J00200"><p>This is far too blunt an instrument.  There is not a member in this or the other House who has not had personal experience of a lower profile case that is equally needy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600010#J00300"><p>Is the Senator proposing an amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600010#J00400"><p>Yes.  I move an amendment that the Minister come to the House today.  I do not care how busy he is with the media launch for the service plan for the HSE.  We must have progress in this area where people's human needs are taken into account rather than this blunt instrument to save money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600010#J00500"><p>Bureaucrats, not medics, are doing it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600010#J00600"><p>I too welcome today's employment figures from the CSO which highlights some good news.  That the employment rate has increased by 58,000 in the course of the year and approximately 90% of those jobs are full-time roles is hugely welcome.  The trend is accelerating with 1,200 jobs being created per week, an incredible figure of approximately 5,000 on a monthly basis.  That follows on from a situation where for the three years before the Government came into office 1,600 jobs per week were being shed.  To stop that trend was an achievement.  That we are now creating 1,200 jobs per week is a huge success story.  While the unemployment figures are still unsatisfactory it is a sign of good things to come.</p><p>Employment in the accommodation and food sector is up 11.9% or 1,470.  Again, this shows how the employment activation initiatives, such as the 9% VAT rate, are working.  It is a real vindication of the macroeconomic policies of the Government.  Certainly today's news is good for a change.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600010#J00700"><p>There is little surprise in today's story in <i>The Irish Times</i> that our students who attend third level are mainly from prosperous areas, fee-paying schools and Gaelscoileanna.  They are all advantaged in achieving that over children attending school in socioeconomically disadvantaged areas.  In this context I am worried about the Minister's proposal to replace the junior certificate with a school-based or school-examined school certificate.  I do not know if people realise this is going to happen.  The State examination at junior certificate level will be gone.  I have been thinking about this development.  Who will this disadvantage?  It will not disadvantage those who are making it to third level but will disadvantage the early school leavers, the one in eight or one in ten students who drop out before leaving certificate who will then have no State certification.  Those children may travel and may emigrate.  When they present for jobs abroad they will be asked to forward a copy of their examination results from Ireland.  What good will a school report be?  That is all it will be.  Education is meant to be the great equaliser.  If the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn, moves ahead with this proposal he will ensure that it will be the great unequaliser and will reinforce inequality, particularly where children drop out early from school.  In this regard I ask the Minister to revise his plans to replace the junior certificate with a school certificate.  I ask the Leader to invite him to the House for a debate on the junior certificate reform examination only.  There is much I like about his ideas on reform but not on his proposal to replace the junior certificate examination with a school-based examination only.  That is not good enough for the children who drop out early.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600010#J00800"><p>I second Senator Marc MacSharry's amendment.</p><p>I wish to raise with the Leader issues that have arisen from some recent documentaries on Irish and English television channels, particularly the atrocities committed where collusion was a very prominent feature.</p> <p>While the Leader and others, including me, who followed the coverage of Mr. Justice Barron's reports will not be in the least surprised that there were shoot-to-kill gangs from the British army going around killing innocent civilians in the North, it is appalling to hear and see the evidence of those directly involved, just as it was appalling to watch last night the coverage of the atrocities perpetrated by the IRA during the Troubles.  Recently I was at the launch of Anne Cadwallader's book on collusion by British forces in Northern Ireland, particularly in the murder triangle of Dungannon, Portadown and south Armagh, about which members of the committee heard over a number of years.  We heard from people who had knowledge of the crimes and also from the victims.  I would like a debate on these issues because there has been no closure for the families of victims of the atrocities.  Families are still crying out for the truth about what happened to their loved ones.  Unfortunately, as I believe our report indicated, the State failed them as much as any other authority.  One of the great champions of human rights in this House was the President, Mr. Michael D. Higgins.  I hope his great commitment will be in evidence during his official visit to Britain.  I hope he will champion the need for the British to make available the documentation, evidence and information they have available which, no doubt, will incriminate many within the British establishment.  If the truth is out, I hope we can at least progress from there and that the victims will be able to find closure.  I would like to believe Senators, as a body in this House, will be supportive of this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600011#K00200"><p>Figures reported in the press in recent days from a reputable medical report on different cancer rates of survival across the OECD nations make for very sobering reading for people in Ireland.  I will not go into all the details; suffice it to say the statistics indicate we are doing very poorly.  In the case of some cancers, we are doing nearly as poorly as any nation in the OECD can do.  In the case of one cancer, we are beaten only by a country that is relatively newly liberated from Soviet communism.  There has been a slight tendency here, administratively and bureaucratically, in the past decade to indulge in self-congratulation of a near-orgiastic level over alleged improvements in cancer services.  It is important for people to realise that most or much of what has happened has involved reorganisation, shuffling and changing bureaucracies.  There has been an increase in the number of cancer specialists, which I welcome, and there have been improvements, which I also welcome.  There have been improvements all across the world, including Europe and the western countries that have relatively developed medical systems.  This is because cancer treatment has got better.</p><p>The second most important point to note is how poorly our near neighbour, the United Kingdom, has done in similar league tables, recently presented in the same study.  The UK model is the one to which we seem to aspire most.  If one wants to improve cancer treatment outcomes, there should be enough people doing the treating, enough access to treatment and good access to the drugs available.  Historically, we were poor in the first two categories and good in the third, but now we are becoming poor in all three.  This is really a time for honest reflection.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600011#K00300"><p>Senator Thomas Byrne referred to the Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill 2013, with which we will be dealing today.  There is no time limit on Second Stage, nor will there be a time limit on Committee Stage, within reason.  There will not be a time limit on Report Stage.  We can deal with today's business for as long as we want.  Such an important Bill will be allowed the time it deserves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600011#K00400"><p>The deadline for submitting amendments was this morning, although we have not even considered the Bill on Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600011#K00500"><p>I cannot give the Senator any further information.  Committee Stage has been ordered for Thursday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00100"><p>Could the Leader give a commitment that amendments will be accepted at least until after the debate this evening?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00200"><p>It is not within my remit to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00300"><p>The Seanad can decide.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00400"><p>It is not within my remit.  Notice would have been given of when amendments could be tabled.</p><p>Senator Bacik and several other Senators spoke about the expansion of university seats to all third-level colleges and institutions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00500"><p>On a point of order, Senator Byrne has raised an important point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00600"><p>The Leader is replying to the questions raised during the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00700"><p>The point of order is about the ordering of business in this House.  The Leader, who is an honourable and decent man, has stated that his hands are tied; it is outside his remit.  Within whose remit does it lie?  It is quite extraordinary that before the Bill is introduced to the House, we are forbidden to table amendments.  By whom - some kind of anonymous bureaucrat?  The Leader stated it was not him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00800"><p>The Leader to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L00900"><p>Is it the Government?  I insist on knowing who it is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01000"><p>The Leader is replying to issues raised on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01100"><p>Perhaps the Leader would be kind enough to let me know.  He may well have a satisfactory answer, but at present the matter is unresolved and I am deeply unhappy about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01200"><p>We had a meeting of leaders last week where the schedule for this week was agreed.  That is all I can say.  That business was tabled as it has been tabled this week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01300"><p>I attended that meeting and the Leader is quite correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01400"><p>Senator Norris should allow the Leader to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01500"><p>However, there was no question that we would not be allowed to table amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01600"><p>Senator Norris should resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01700"><p>I am sure the Leader will confirm that the question of amendments was not raised at that meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01800"><p>Senator Norris should allow the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L01900"><p>On a point of order, when this has happened on occasion we have objected to it, but it has always been the case that amendments were accepted until Second Stage was completed.  It was always allowed by this House, not by some bureaucrat or the Bills Office.  This House tells the Bills Office the rules.  They do what we tell them.  Let us tell them that amendments will be accepted until this evening.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02000"><p>I will certainly-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02100"><p>Standing Orders allow the Cathaoirleach to accept amendments and waive notice.  The Leader to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02200"><p>Will the Cathaoirleach be disposed to do that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02300"><p>I have no objection whatsoever-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02400"><p>Is the Cathaoirleach willing to do that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02500"><p>I look at each case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02600"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  We will send them in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02700"><p>I have no objection to extending the time if it can be extended.  There is no question about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02800"><p>I thank the Leader for his courtesy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L02900"><p>Senator Bacik spoke about Seanad reform and the expansion of the University seats to all third-level institutions.  This is a matter that has been raised by several other Senators.  As Leader of the House, I have no indication of when this Bill will be before us.  I certainly have no indication that, as reported in the newspapers, it may be here before Christmas.  I have no indication whatsoever in that regard.  As I hear news on it, I will certainly inform the House.</p><p>Senators van Turnhout and Daly raised the issue of smoking in cars in which there are children.  I wrote to the Minister for Health last week on that matter asking for a progress report.  I indicated that it was said to me that there was some legal problem with one aspect of the Protection of Children's Health from Tobacco Smoke Bill 2012, and I asked the Minister to clarify that and let me know when the Bill would be taken.  After 18 months or whatever - the Bill came before us in 2012 - it is most unacceptable that this short Bill could not have been dealt with and completed in the Seanad by now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L03000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600012#L03100"><p>Senator van Turnhout also called for a debate on the youth guarantee.  The Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Burton, will be here with us all afternoon.  Prior to the debate, I will ask her when she can come in to debate that issue.</p><p>Senator Norris raised the need for reform of the vocational panels.  That was the subject of a couple of Bills that were before the House before the Seanad referendum.</p> <p>Until Senator Norris informed me of the fact, I was not aware that the Taoiseach had held meetings with the leaders in the Lower House in respect of these matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600013#M00200"><p>That may not be true.  I only read it in a newspaper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600013#M00300"><p>Such meetings may have taken place but I am not aware that they did.</p><p>Senator Conway and others referred to the unemployment figures and the fact that 1,200 jobs are being created each week.  That is a wonderful improvement on the position which obtained up to two and a half years ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600013#M00400"><p>At that rate we will have solved the problem of unemployment in 30 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600013#M00500"><p>Prior to 2011, some 250,000 jobs were lost in a three-year period.  However, everyone will acknowledge that there is a long way to go in respect of this matter.</p><p>Senator Leyden complimented the Garda on its efforts in combating crime and called for a review of the free legal aid scheme.</p><p>Senator Hayden referred to the first case involving the Insolvency Service of Ireland and requested a debate on the matter.  A number of months will have to elapse before we can examine the position with regard to debating a progress report on this issue.  It would be March or even later before such a debate could be held.  I agree with the Senator's call for a debate on Traveller accommodation and the standards relating thereto.  I will ask the Minister of State at the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan, to come before the House to address that matter at the earliest possible opportunity.</p><p>Senator Cullinane called for a further debate on reform of the House.  We have engaged in many debates on this issue and what is required now is action.  One of the matters to which we should probably give consideration is people who raise matters on the Order of Business and who then do not have to courtesy to remain in the Chamber for a reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600013#M00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600013#M00700"><p>Either the House or I should be able to address that issue.</p><p>Senator Brennan referred to hospice services and volunteers who transport people to appointments.  Those volunteers do wonderful work and it should be appreciated.  The Senator called for concessions to be made in respect of car parking charges in hospitals.  I do not know who has responsibility in this regard.  It is probably a matter for the hospitals themselves.  I agree with the Senator that hospitals should re-examine the position.  Concessions should be made in respect of those volunteers who transport people to hospital appointments.</p><p>Senators Daly and Crown referred to cancer survival rates, a matter which was the subject of a report in a Sunday newspaper.  I note Senator Crown's comments in that regard and his acknowledgement that cancer treatments have improved and that the number of consultants has increased.  There is, however, a need for this issue to be reviewed on a continual basis, particularly in the context of the comments made in the newspaper report in question.  That report did not make for pleasant reading.</p><p>Senators Daly and Walsh referred to the &quot;Panorama&quot; programme on the activities of some elements within the British forces in the past.  What was shown in that programme was reprehensible, as was the murder and maiming of people on all sides.  That which was detailed in the programme was dreadful.  I note Senator Walsh's comments on collusion between the British Army and loyalist paramilitaries in the zone to which he referred.  The Government has exerted pressure in respect of this matter.  There is a need for the British Government to provide the necessary information in order to give the families of the victims some closure in respect of the dreadful activities which took place at that point in our history.</p><p>Senator Mullins referred to the situation relating to the ESB and the unions.  The threatened dispute is unnecessary, particularly as, according to the Pensions Board, the ESB pension scheme is fully funded up to 2018.</p> <p>A couple of hundred million euro was injected in the company and its pension fund a couple of years ago.  A funding plan must be agreed to restore the ESB to financial health.  The House will debate the Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill when the Order of Business concludes.  Every second pension fund is in trouble.  The pensions and jobs of workers in the ESB are not under threat and pay cuts are not required.  I hope that, arising from the meeting between management and unions later this week, this unnecessary action will not proceed.  A strike would have devastating consequences for businesses, schools, primary health centres and everyone else.  I appeal for calm and common sense to prevail.  Senator Sean D. Barrett has also noted that while the country is moving in the right direction on jobs, it still has a considerable way to go in that regard.  </p><p>Senator Paul Coghlan welcomed the decision of the European Investment Bank to endorse a proposal to provide a low interest loan for the construction of the Luas cross-city line.  This is a major project and the EIB's decision is welcome.</p><p>Senator Marc MacSharry referred to the Health Service Executive's service plan and the waste of resources in the health service.  I could not agree more with him.  The case he has highlighted is appalling and should not have arisen.  Such practices lack all common sense.  I cannot agree to the amendment to the Order of Business to discuss a specific issue.  The Senator may seek to have the matter discussed on the Adjournment.  I hope the House will have an opportunity to debate the HSE service plan once it has been approved by the Government.  The HSE has submitted its proposals for the Minister to examine. </p><p>Senator Catherine Noone also welcomed the success of the Government's initiatives on job creation.</p><p>Senator Fidelma Healy Eames called for a debate on changes to the junior certificate syllabus.  I will ask the Minister to come before the House, although the matter was debated previously.  Continuous assessment has been encouraged by many educational practitioners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1131" speakername="Fidelma Healy Eames" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600014#N00200"><p>We debated the content of the syllabus, rather than the examination.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600014#N00300"><p>I have referred to the concerns raised by Senators Jim Walsh and John Crown.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600014#N00400"><p>Senator Marc MacSharry has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That a debate with the Minister for Health on the method of assessment of eligibility for a medical card be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" speakername="Marc MacSharry" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600014#N00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.122/1" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600014#N00550"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 19; Nl, 27.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.122/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-11-26" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600014#N00550">
            <divisioncount ayes="19" noes="27" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" vote="aye">David Cullinane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="aye">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="aye">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="aye">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="aye">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="no">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="no">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="no">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="no">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="no">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="no">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.122/3" nospeaker="true" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600014#N00550"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="15:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600014#N00700"><p>Senator Eamonn Coghlan inadvertently voted "T&aacute;" instead of "N&iacute;l" and the vote result has been amended.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.124/1" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600015#Q00050"><p>Question put: "That the Order of Business be agreed to."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 27; Nl, 18.</p><p>Tellers: T, Senators Paul Coghlan and Aideen Hayden; Nl, Senators Ned O'Sullivan and Diarmuid Wilson..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.124/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2013-11-26" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600015#Q00050">
            <divisioncount ayes="27" noes="18" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="aye">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="aye">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1151" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="aye">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="aye">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1166" vote="aye">Jim D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1160" vote="aye">Michael D'Arcy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="aye">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="aye">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="aye">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1173" vote="aye">Lorraine Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="aye">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="aye">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" vote="aye">Fiach MacConghail</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="aye">Marie Maloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="aye">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="aye">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="aye">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" vote="aye">Hildegarde Naughton</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="aye">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1176" vote="aye">Katherine Zappone</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="no">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="no">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="no">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="no">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1149" vote="no">Marc MacSharry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="no">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1146" vote="no">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="no">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="no">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="no">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" vote="no">Denis O'Donovan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1154" vote="no">Averil Power</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1155" vote="no">Kathryn Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="no">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.124/3" nospeaker="true" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600015#Q00050"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.125" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600016#S00100">Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill 2013: Order for Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.126" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>Bill entitled an Act to amend and extend the Social Welfare Acts; to amend and extend the Pensions Act 1990; to make additional provision for the discharge of liabilities in the winding up of certain occupational pension schemes and to provide for the discharge of liabilities of such schemes where employers are insolvent on or before the date of the wind up of such schemes; to provide for the payment, in certain circumstances, by the Minister for Finance of moneys to secure the discharge of certain liabilities in respect of certain occupational pension schemes that are being wound up where certain employers are insolvent on or before the date of the wind up of such schemes; to make additional provision for the restructuring of certain occupational pension schemes and for that purpose to provide for the reduction in the benefits being paid to certain persons under such schemes; and to provide for related matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600016#S00300"><p>I move: "That Second Stage be taken today."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.128" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.129" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600016#S00500">Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill 2013: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.130" nospeaker="true" time="15:55:00" ><p>Question proposed: &quot;That the Bill be now read a Second Time.&quot;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600016#S00700"><p>The key provisions I am introducing today relate mainly to occupational pensions.  They address difficult issues of equity and fairness and have been under careful consideration for some time.  The issues date back over much of the past decade and have been raised in both the 2007 Green Paper on pensions and the 2010 national pensions framework, both of which were published with much fanfare by the previous Government.  However, this is the first time these issues have been comprehensively addressed.  The aim of the Bill is to ensure a fairer deal for workers and sufficient protection for pensioners while allowing employers to tackle their pension problems.<br /><b></b>Defined benefit schemes are private pension schemes in which those contributing to the scheme - the employer and the members - pool their contributions, which are then invested in order to pay a pension on retirement.  The primary role of the employer as the sponsor in these schemes is an underlying principle in forming this legislation.  So too is the sufficient protection of pensioners in these schemes, given the importance of security of income in retirement.  Members of occupational pension schemes contribute to them in the expectation that the pension promised to them will be delivered in the future.  This Bill acknowledges their role in the scheme and realigns that role to an extent.  The stakeholders share both the benefits of the fund and also, in principle, the risks to the fund.  The State's role as regulator is to watch over these private occupational schemes and ensure they can live up to their promises.  The State recognises that it has obligations under EU law and it will address these obligations.  This legislation does that.</p> <p>The State also has a policy role to ensure all people have an adequate income in retirement.</p><p>It is well known that defined benefit schemes have had considerable funding difficulties for several years.  I have brought legislation on occupational pensions into this House every year for the past number of years to help defined benefit schemes help themselves.  Changes were made to give the trustees of defined benefit schemes options and help them improve their funding position.  Last year, for example, after a period of suspension to allow schemes to get on with assessing their funding positions, I reintroduced the regulatory structure and schemes had to return their funding positions to the Pensions Board by June this year.  The previous Government suspended the funding standard, believing that it would be like the bank guarantee but the problems continued.  I am relieved to report the position is not as difficult as we had feared.  Over 40% of schemes are fully funded.  Although 20% are poorly funded, many of these schemes have put in funding proposals to the Pensions Board to get them back on track.  The board is now engaged on an individual basis with schemes.  We are in a more managed place.</p><p>This Bill introduces changes to the existing priority order.  The priority order comes into play when a defined benefit scheme winds up.  It basically outlines, step by step, the order in which the assets of the pension scheme are distributed when the scheme is winding up.  Existing legislation comes from a time when defined benefit schemes were carrying surpluses.  There is no issue for a scheme winding up when the scheme is funded, as all benefits can be met.  It is when a scheme is underfunded that difficulties arise.  The key issue with the existing priority order is that it gives 100% protection to pensions that are in payment and then distributes the rest of the funds to the current and former members of the scheme.</p><p>It can arise that pensioners receive all or almost all the pension fund and the members who have contributed but not retired receive considerably less than expected.  This issue has been of concern for some time and considerable calls have come from employee and employer representatives, as well as the pensions industry, to address the current inequities.  Detailed examination of these issues has taken place.</p><p>After considering all the factors, I am replacing the existing priority order to introduce two priority orders in this Bill.  I am making provision for the situation where the pension scheme winds up and the employer is solvent.  I am also providing for where both the employer and pension scheme are insolvent, happily a rare occurrence.  This is to ensure the State meets its obligations under the insolvency directive following the ruling by the European Court of Justice in April this year.</p><p>In a single insolvency, the first priority will be given to defined contribution assets in a defined benefit scheme which should not be part of the distribution of defined benefit assets.  This next priority is given to pensioners.  They will still be given a significant level of priority but there will now be provision for a redistribution into the scheme from higher pensions at the initial distribution of the scheme assets.  I am retaining 100% protection up to an annual amount of &euro;12,000 for pensions and then providing priority of 90% for those between &euro;12,000 and &euro;60,000 and 80% for those over &euro;60,000.  This reprioritising of an element of pension benefit over &euro;12,000 will contribute to the benefits of current and former employees which will be prioritised at 50%.  This will apply only if the scheme is underfunded and its impact will depend on the degree of underfunding.</p> <p>If there are sufficient funds in the scheme, any initial reductions to pensioners will be regained once the current and former members have been provided for and as the distribution of funds moves through the order outlined.  Limits have been put in place in the legislation on how the reductions of 10% and 20% are applied to ensure these are proportionate.</p><p>This change is carefully balanced between the existing pensioners and the current and former contributors to the scheme who have not yet retired.  This change also recognises that all of the beneficiaries of the scheme - all members and pensioners - need to share the risks when a scheme is underfunded.  The limit of &euro;12,000 takes into consideration that the median private sector defined benefit pension is &euro;11,000, the average pension is &euro;18,000 and 55% of private sector pensions are below &euro;12,000.  Pensions of up to &euro;12,000 are 100% protected for existing pensioners.</p><p>The following is important, although it is often not mentioned in discussions.  The vast majority of pensioners, separately to what they may be entitled to from a defined benefit scheme, receive the State pension, which is not affected in any way by these changes.  I have fully protected the State pension since becoming Minister in light of its critical importance to older people.  So a pensioner who has a State pension of &euro;12,000 and an occupational pension of &euro;12,000 will retain an income of &euro;24,000, which is two-thirds of the average industrial earnings.  By international standards this is quite a good level of pension provision.</p><p>This Bill also changes the priority order in the very particular situation of a double insolvency.  This is when an employer goes out of business and the pension scheme is also underfunded.  It is a particular situation which is covered by the EU insolvency directive.  Article 8 of the directive requires that the State have measures in place to ensure that at least 49% of the expected benefits of the contributors to the scheme can be met.  In April this year, the European Court of Justice found that the State was not meeting its obligations under Article 8, and this provision addressing the obligation by changing the order of priority in a double insolvency situation as follows.  As before, first priority is given to defined contribution assets, which should not be part of the distribution of defined benefit assets as they are two separate structures.  The second and third priorities are given to 50% of pensioner and member benefits.  Then priority is given to protecting pensioner benefits up to &euro;12,000.  The remaining steps of the order continue to provide for the benefits of pensioners and then for benefits of current and former scheme members.</p><p>These changes to the order do the following.  First, they meet the requirements of the directive by ensuring that scheme funds are distributed in a way that ensures that all members, including pensioners, receive 50% of their benefits.  The next priority ensures that significant protection is in place to ensure pensioners receive a pension of &euro;12,000.  Again, much depends on the funding of the scheme.  If the scheme is sufficiently funded, the distribution of funds can move through the various steps of the priority order and provide for the 50% requirement under the directive and then for pensioners' benefits up to &euro;12,000, with the remainder going to pensioners' and other members' benefits.</p><p>In addition, this Bill provides that in a double insolvency, where a scheme has insufficient resources to provide 50% of benefits and protect &euro;12,000 of pensioner benefits, the Minster for Finance shall provide for the shortfall in scheme assets.  The Minister has agreed that some of the funds obtained from the pension levy can be used to fund any costs that arise.</p> <p>In such situations, which I am happy to say are rare, it is proposed there would be a transfer of funds from the State to the scheme trustees by way of a once-off settlement.  What is provided for here is a mechanism which can also provide for any historic situations which have arisen.</p><p>The aim of the Bill and the entire package of measures is to ensure as far as possible we have the minimum number of double insolvencies.  The Pensions Board will introduce secondary legislation and will tighten up the regulation on underfunded defined benefit pension schemes with a view to ensuring such schemes take action to manage and improve their funding position.  These measures and actions are all aimed at minimising the risk of double insolvencies arising in the future.  Pensions are based on a promise by the employer and agreed levels of contributions by the employer and the employee.  Protecting people's retirement income is critical.  This is with regard to those who have retired, active members paying into the scheme, and deferred members, including those who went to work elsewhere or took redundancy, and have not yet reached pensionable age.</p><p>The Bill broadens the category of benefits that can be reduced where a defined benefit pension scheme is being restructured to improve its funding position and remain viable for all members.  The reduction is progressive and the limits are as I outlined with regard to single insolvency.  Pension benefits up to &euro;12,000 are fully protected; annual pension amounts of between &euro;12,000 and &euro;60,000 can be reduced by up to 10%; and annual pension amounts over &euro;60,000 can be reduced by up to 20%.  This again brings increased fairness to the scheme, improves the position for the current and former scheme members and may, I hope, help a scheme stay open.  I also want to emphasise the fact the provision provides for reductions of up to 10% and up to 20%.  The trustees have discretion as to the percentage that needs to be applied.  For example, a scheme with a high number of pensioners with high average pensions which applies a 1% reduction could mean an injection of funds of 2% to 3% back into the scheme for current and former workers.</p><p>I will also table a number of amendments to the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 on Committee Stage, which are required to address issues raised recently in the High Court concerning the legal powers of deciding officers and appeals officers to revise decisions in certain cases.  This is a complex issue.  Legislation allows officials of the Department of Social Protection, including appeals officers, to revise decisions in a range of circumstances.  These include situations where new evidence shows the original decision was wrong, and also situations where there has been a change of circumstances since the original decision.  In the past, this flexibility has been seen as an asset, but when viewed in the context of a more modern interpretation of the law it also conveys an obligation.  Last week the High Court confirmed if a deciding officer or appeals officer has the power to revise a decision, he or she also has an obligation to do so if requested.</p><p>Until now, in most cases it has been the practice of the Department that once a claim is refused and all review and appeals processes are finalised, if a customer seeks a revised decision based on changed circumstances he or she is advised to make a fresh application.  The new claim is then fully assessed in the light of all the circumstances of the case.  In light of the High Court decision, the Department can no longer require people to make a fresh claim, but must reopen a claim, even if it was closed many years previously.  The purpose of the amendment is to address this issue, but in a limited range of circumstances.  I stress that where the original decision was wrong, and if new facts and evidence emerge, the customer will still be able to seek a revised decision; the amendment does not change this.  Where a claim is in payment, it will still be possible to revise the decision if circumstances change, but where a person was refused a social welfare payment in the past and their circumstances change the correct channel is to make a fresh application so the application can be considered in light of his or her current circumstances.</p> <p>Where a person was refused a social welfare payment in the past and his or her circumstances change, the correct channel is to make a fresh application so that the application can be fully considered in the light of the person's current circumstances.  The amendment aims to ensure that this will be the practice in all cases.</p><p> In light of the High Court decision, I have asked Department officials to carry out a more wide-ranging review of the legislation on social welfare decisions and I will bring forward any necessary legislation at a later date.  In order to facilitate the inclusion of these amendments on Committee Stage, section 2 of the Bill provides for two minor changes to the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005.  The inclusion of these amendments in this Bill necessitates a change in the Title of the Bill, as published, to the Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill, and this in turn will facilitate the inclusion of the amendments to the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 on Committee Stage.</p><p> In the area of pensions, I will be tabling a number of amendments to the Bill on Committee Stage to provide for the drawing down of benefits in the event of a shortfall arising in a double insolvency and to make consequential amendments to some of the provisions of Part 3 of the Bill as published.  I will be making two technical amendments to provide for references to the Act of 1990 rather than the principal Act, and co-ordinating the text of section 48(1)(<i>d</i>) with the text of the Committee Stage amendment.</p><p> I will now outline the main provisions of the Bill.  Section 1 provides for the Short Title, construction and collective citations.  Section 2 provides for the correction of an erroneous reference and the deletion of an obsolete reference contained in table 2 of Schedule 3 to the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005, which lists certain items of income that are excluded from the assessment of means for social assistance payment purposes.  Part 3 and section 3 define the term &quot;Principal Act&quot; as used for the purposes of part 3 as meaning the Pensions Act.  Section 4 amends section 41 of the Pensions Act to affirm that the changes to the wind-up priority order apply to all defined benefit pension schemes subject to the statutory minimum funding standard.  Section 5 inserts five new subsections to provide for the amendments to the priority order to replace the existing order with two new priority orders to deal with the scheme wind-up when the employer is solvent and when the employer is insolvent.</p><p> Section 6 broadens the category of benefits that can be reduced where a defined benefit scheme is being restructured because it does not meet the minimum funding standard.  Sections 7 and 8 cross-reference section 50B and section 50C with subsection 1B.  Section 9 amends section 59B to provide that the prohibition on reducing pensions in payment shall not apply to directions under section 50(1B).</p><p> In conclusion, this legislation achieves three things.  It ensures that the State meets its obligations to put measures in place under the EU insolvency directive.  It addresses the equity difficulties with the existing priority order.  It also goes further by providing a further option to enable schemes to stay viable and open.  People need to have a decent income when they retire and we want occupational pensions to be viable and effective.  This legislation achieves a fine balance between the needs of the various parties and protects the State and the taxpayer.</p><p> I would like to reiterate that the Bill deals with defined benefit pension schemes and does not affect in any way the State's contributory and non-contributory retirement or old age pension.  We should be clear about that, because sometimes when people hear the word &quot;pension&quot;, they think of whatever pension they themselves may have.  However, I wish to emphasise that this applies to people who are members of defined benefit pension schemes.  I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="16:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600021#X00100"><p>Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agat.  I welcome the Minister to the House.  She has made great play of emphasising that the situation does not apply to the State pension but the legislation hides a number of inadequacies in the Bill.  We believe that the legislation is too little, too late.  Over the past three years the Government has repeatedly failed to address the inequality that stems from the current pension priority order, that is the order in which assets are dispersed when a defined benefit pension scheme winds up.  The Government said it was committed to keeping defined benefit schemes intact but the uncertain legislative framework that it allowed to continue created incentives for companies to close them.  A quarter of defined benefit schemes will close this year alone and full scheme wind ups are becoming more common.  Over the three years many defined benefit schemes have closed and active and deferred pensioners have lost a part of their pension rights.</p><p>If the legislation is passed, pensioners will no longer be totally insured against any collapse of their pension scheme after they retire unless they have a relatively small pension.  If benefits are reduced in order to secure the pensions of deferred or active employees then it must be done in a transparent manner with a right of appeal for affected pensioners.</p><p>Potential problems with the legislation are as follows.  The Government is almost certain to face a legal challenge from pensioners over the loss of what are considered property rights.  The new law continues to allow profitable employers to walk away from pension problems by winding up schemes that are in deficit.  In fact the additional regulatory burden implicit in the legislation actively encourages them to do so.  The OECD recommends that a minimum of 90% funding should be achieved before a scheme can be closed in a case where the parent company is in financial health.</p><p>The Government has not resolved what level of payment would accrue to deferred pensioners in a double insolvency case.  The Waterford Crystal case was sent back to the Irish High Court after the ruling by the European Court of Justice, and the High Court has yet to decide what level of pension should be protected.  In the UK a similar case saw almost 90% of pension rights protected after an earlier European Court of Justice ruling.  Waterford Crystal staff representatives have said that the 50% rate of protection is inadequate so the Government is faced with a dilemma.  I know that the Government awaits the High Court decision and, therefore, cannot make an input.</p><p>The legislation appears to pave the way for the pension levy to be made permanent.  The Minister for Finance claimed that extending the levy would &quot;make provision for potential State liabilities which may emerge from preexisting or future pension fund difficulties&quot;.  His statement underlines the unfairness of the levy as it will also hit defined contribution pension schemes even though they cannot benefit from such a scheme.  It will undermine the incentive to save for retirement.  Earlier today the Minister for Social Protection said that pension benefits up to &euro;12,000 will be fully protected.  However, given the manner in which State benefits for the elderly have been systematically eroded by the Government, there has never been a greater need than now for such a safety net.</p><p>There is nothing in the legislation about thresholds rising over time in line with consumer prices to ensure consistency.  The Bill ignores the thousands of workers who have lost pension rights while the Government dithered over recent years.  We suggest the following: thresholds should be increased annually in line with inflation; the legislation should apply to schemes wound up since 2010, keeping in mind those that have been wound up over the past few years; a going concern should not be permitted to wind up its defined benefit company pension scheme unless it has reached a minimum of 90% funding; an appeal mechanism should be introduced where trustees have decided upon reduced benefits for members so that pensioners can be assured that they have not been unfairly treated in a restructuring arrangement; and the Pensions Board should commit to urgently updating its statutory guidance on aspects of the Pensions Act for trustees following the introduction of the Bill.</p><p>I shall list the more long-term measures required.  We believe that there is a need for a Minister for pensions as only someone with a seat at the Cabinet table would have the clout to insist that the situation is addressed, as a matter of extreme urgency.  Action is also needed to improve pension coverage.  Among OECD countries, only Ireland and New Zealand do not have compulsory saving for a pension.</p><p>Pension costs need to be tackled.  One of the persistent criticisms of the private pension industry is that it is designed to make vast sums of money for the pension manufacturers, that is the fund managers, administrators and intermediaries.  As I have said before, during various debates with the Minister, pension funds are often described as opaque, confusing and offering only mediocre to poor value for pension holders.  A report compiled by the Department of Social Protection last year showed the impact of high charges, particularly in the case of small schemes.  It showed that someone who saved &euro;250 a month from the age of 35 could end up with a fund of &euro;200,000 after 30 years.   This would leave him or her with an annual pension of &euro;10,000 in retirement, if there were no charges.  According to the report, an average charge of 2.18% a year would reduce the fund by &euro;62,000 and thus leave a pension of just &euro;6,900.</p> <p>In an extreme case, under current rules, if a scheme collapses, a person one day short of retirement can have his or her entire pension wiped out, while a person who has just retired will retain 100% of his or hers. </p><p>In the Waterford Crystal case, up to 1,200 workers were affected by the collapse of the company's defined benefit scheme when the company went bust in 2009.  The scheme was understood to be worth &euro;82 million, but liabilities to employees are estimated at up to &euro;380 million.  In a British case, in 2007 the European Court of Justice stated a figure of 49% was insufficient and the British Government subsequently paid out 90% of the fund.  The Waterford Crystal workers took their case against the State to the High Court and it was then referred to the European Court of Justice.  In April it ruled the State had failed to protect the pension interests of the Waterford Crystal workers in a case of double insolvency but gave no indication of how much of the shortfall the State should meet.  That issue needs to be addressed urgently. </p><p>On the extension of the pension levy, the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, said the 0.15% increase in 2014 would raise an extra &euro;135 million a year and that the proceeds could be used &quot;to make provision for potential State liabilities which may emerge from pre-existing or future pension fund difficulties.&quot;  Under the terms of the Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill 2013, the levy has been given a specific purpose as a method of compensation for schemes in difficulty; therefore, it is likely to be extended indefinitely.  </p><p>According to the National Pensions Board, only 54% of the workforce have pension coverage.  This is a real problem, one that the previous Administration tackled also.  Within the working population there are wide disparities.  The level of coverage in the public service is more than 90%, while in some areas of the private sector the level of coverage is very low.  The national pensions framework published by the previous Government in 2010 cited the examples of the hotel and restaurant sectors in which the level of pension coverage was 23%, while level in the wholesale and retail trade was just 36%.  </p><p>Independent consumer research carried out on behalf of the National Pensions Board indicates that almost eight out of ten people who do not contribute to a pension scheme said the State pension would not meet their needs in retirement.  Although employers are obliged by law to offer employees access to a pension scheme, 43% of those interviewed had not been offered such access, of whom 93% had never asked an employer about access to a pension scheme.  Although the level of awareness of tax relief on pension contributions is relatively high at 73%, the majority did not know or had incorrectly understood the amount of tax relief that applied to them.  The reason for the high level of awareness of the tax relief was the pension industry's own actions and activities in the weeks leading up to the deadline when there was a concentration of advertising.  Therefore, it is not surprising that people would be so aware.  However, it is interesting that they have not followed through, as the other statistics indicate. </p><p>The key issue for the Minister and the Government is how to improve the level of coverage.  This will have to be done through a combination of incentives, including a soft-hard initiative.  The issue of mandatory pension contributions will have to be given serious consideration.  Among OECD countries only Ireland and New Zealand do not provide for compulsory pension contributions.  In 2008 the Comptroller and Auditor General estimated the scale of pension liabilities in respect of public sector pensions at a staggering &euro;108 billion.  The amount has grown since.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="16:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600022#Y00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to address the Social Welfare and Pensions (No. 2) Bill 2013.  We have all read about pension funds becoming insolvent in recent years, the most notable case being that of the Waterford Crystal workers who had to deal with the issue of double insolvency when both the company and the pension fund became insolvent.  This is cold comfort to any person who has spent a lifetime working hard, paying into a defined benefit pension scheme in order to provide financial security for themselves and their partner in older years.  In making pension provision, people want to ensure they will not fall into a poverty trap in old age and that they will have a reasonable disposable income based on their financial needs at this time and that they will have access to adequate health care support.  However, in recent years some people who had worked for many years and contributed to a pension fund had to face the awful realisation that their fund was insolvent and that there were insufficient funds to provide adequate pension cover.</p><p>I have read the briefing documents the Department has provided and it is clear that there has been widespread concern within all sectors - employers, employees, the Irish Congress of Trade Unions and pension actuaries - that the issue of adequate funding of pension schemes needs to be addressed.</p> <p>The Minister facilitated a consultation process earlier in the year with the relevant stakeholders to identify what is needed to protect all those contributing to a defined benefit scheme.  I note the amendment to section 50 of the Pensions Act and the inclusion of three subsections, subsections (1B), (1C) and (1D), to broaden the category of benefits that can be reduced where a defined benefit pension scheme is being restructured because it does not meet the statutory minimum funding standard.  Section 50 of the Pensions Act permits the Pensions Board to direct the trustees of a pension scheme to reduce the benefits of current and former scheme members or post-retirement increases in benefits for pension scheme members whose scheme does not meet the statutory minimum funding standard.</p><p>The proposed subsection (1B) provides for reductions to the benefits payable to pensioners by certain percentages within certain limits.  The proposed subsection (1C) prohibits any reduction of an annual pension that is &euro;12,000 or less.  For pensions greater than &euro;12,000, a reduction of up to 10% can be made where the annual pension is between &euro;12,000 and &euro;60,000, and up to 20% where the annual pension is greater than &euro;60,000.  The proposed subsection (1D) prohibits any reduction that would reduce a pension to below &euro;12,000 or that would reduce a pension to below &euro;54,000 if the annual pension is &euro;60,000 or more.</p><p>I am glad to see there will be no change to the State contributory pension of &euro;12,000 per year.  However, for the purpose of clarity, could the Minister advise on possible reductions affecting those currently in receipt of a defined pension?  Is there a disregard for the first &euro;12,000?  For example, if a person is in receipt of a total pension of &euro;40,000 per year, with &euro;12,000 being the State pension and the balance, &euro;28,000, being a defined benefit pension, is the 10% applicable on the &euro;28,000 or on the total pension of &euro;40,000?  Likewise, if a person has a pension in excess of &euro;60,000, which includes the State pension of &euro;12,000, how is the 20% applied?</p><p>There is justifiable concern among those currently in receipt of a defined pension that it may be reduced, albeit in a temporary capacity, until there are adequate moneys in the fund to provide for those coming on-stream.  Hence, I would like clarity on the aforesaid figures.</p><p>It must be noted that the purpose of this Bill is fairness and to ensure there is enough money in the pension pot for everybody.  I understand the State can intervene to ensure a fairer deal for workers and sufficient protection for pensions while allowing employers address their pension scheme problem.  I have no doubt that this Bill will be widely debated and amendments tabled but we must ask ourselves in our discussion whether it is fair that a person who has contributed all his or her life to a defined benefit pension scheme could have no pension entitlement on reaching retirement if the fund is insolvent.  Can the State be expected to solve all pension deficits when a pension fund becomes insolvent?</p><p>Social protection is vital, particularly as we get older.  To ensure adequate social protection, pension provision is fundamental. It is important to address the common concept that pensions are for old people.  Investing in a pension needs to commence when we enter the workplace in order to provide some financial security to ensure we will have a certain level of comfort on reaching retirement.  There is a tendency to address pension needs only when we are in our fifties, which is quite late given that we reach pension age at 66 years and may not have contributed sufficiently to provide the financial support required in our later years.  </p><p>I commend the Minister on addressing this issue comprehensively.  It has been noted that although several reports were published under the previous Administration, including the Green Paper on Pensions, 2007, and National Pensions Framework, 2010, nothing was done.  I congratulate the Minister on what she is doing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1167" speakername="Fiach MacConghail" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600023#Z00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  On the Order of Business this morning, my colleague Senator van Turnhout, who cannot be here, requested a debate with the Minister before Christmas on the youth guarantee.  Could we have a date for this before the Irish submission on the guarantee is made to the European Union?  The Leader encouraged us to ask this on the Order of Business.</p> <p> This is a crucial and sensitive piece of proposed legislation.  A majority of citizens do not consider their pension or possible entitlements until they are well into their working life.  Often these issues arise as one moves into middle age and close to retirement.  I have lived the life of a freelancer.  I do not have a defined benefit pension but, thankfully, I copped on a couple of years ago and set up a PRSA.  I can also afford it and I am aware many find it difficult to support such a retirement plan these days.</p><p> I have had the recent and unfortunate experience of closing down a defined benefit scheme at the Abbey Theatre.  It was a terrible and anxious time for all members concerned, but particularly the deferred and current active members.  As a Senator or artistic director of the national theatre, I never thought I would become an expert on pensions.  The fact is that our scheme was fully funded and up to date at the end of 2007 and within a couple of years, we were showing a significant deficit in the scheme through no fault of our own or of the employee.  As I learned, the concept of defined benefit is flawed and we were placing an unequal burden on some members over others.  There are more than 200,000 members of defined benefit schemes.  They were popular with employees as they placed the burden of funding of the pension on the shoulders of the employer.  As an not-for-profit NGO, it placed tremendous pressure on an arts organisation such as the Abbey.</p><p> We had a substantial deficit in our scheme, despite the fact that a contribution totalling &euro;2.27 million was made by the Abbey over that period of time.  It deteriorated, as, indeed, is the case with over 80% of all defined benefit schemes.  The reasons include that life expectancy has increased substantially pushing up the cost of pension provision and investment performance has been poor in recent years, in particular, since the worldwide financial crisis which began in 2008.  Another reason is that interest rates have fallen to record levels making low the assumption for future growth of schemes' assets.  Also, falling interest rates had the effect of increasing the value of future liabilities as discount factors used to reflect the diminishing value of money over time are based on these rates.  Finally, the more onerous funding requirement implemented by the Pensions Board had that impact.</p><p> The Public Service Reform Plan Critical Review, published in April 2013, states:<blockquote>Occupational [defined benefit] pension schemes continue to face financing challenges due to a range of factors.  These include an under-estimation of longevity, poor investment returns, the impact of the downturn in financial markets (in which significant declines in asset values were exacerbated by rapid increases in the valuation of liabilities as interest rates dropped) and the imposition of a tax levy of 0.6% of assets from 2011 to 2014.  Following the 2008 financial crisis in excess of 80% of schemes fell into an underfunded position, ...</blockquote>The position referred to is the position which I experienced in my organisation.  It caused a tremendous amount of anxiety, particularly for our current members and deferred members, but also for the pensioners who had benefit from their contributions and the employees' contributions.</p><p> Senator Mooney mentioned the index-link for inflation.  Is there provision in the Bill for this to be reviewed every couple of years as that adds security?  The Minister is quite a good communicator when it comes to pensions matters.  One of the issues we must address in the debate, both here and in the D&aacute;il, is to minimise the level of anxiety.  Some of those questions, and, indeed, some of the questions Senator Hildegarde Naughton raised, are important.  I thought the Minister's performance on &quot;Morning Ireland&quot; the previous morning was very good, but we need to continue that to avoid increased anxiety, of which I have personal experience.</p><p> Also, on what date, subject to democracy and votes, does the Minister imagine this Bill will be enacted because that might cause a particular concern for schemes which have been winding down?  As the Minister will be aware, there is a deluge of schemes being wound down, particularly in the single insolvency category.  Perhaps there could be clarity about a cut-off date because there will be unfortunate overlaps in that regard.  Clarity is required.</p><p> I am supporting the Bill, as is my colleague Senator van Turnhout, who unfortunately cannot be here with us at this session.</p> <p>The clarity with which the information relating to the issue of double and single insolvency is set out in the Bill is most welcome.</p><p> The legislation is about fairness and sharing the burden.  I am aware of a terrible situation where one employee was only ten months away from retirement when we shut down our scheme.  As we proposed to wind down the scheme, it emerged that his rights and entitlements were completely different from those of a person who had retired just a year previously.  That is a terrible position in which to be placed.  I am supporting the Bill because it proposes to rebalance matters in this regard.  Essentially, in the situation to which I refer, those already in receipt of pensions had first dibs and the person with ten months remaining in employment was placed at the end of the queue.  The Bill will, as I understand it, ensure that all members in a pension scheme will share some element of the deficit, regardless of how unsatisfactory that may prove to be.  We did nothing but try to fund our scheme to the limit.  There are many organisations - NGOs, not-for-profit charities, etc. - which are in a very difficult position whereby their need to continually fund and top up their pension schemes will threaten their sustainability and solvency.  It is regrettable that schemes of this nature often have to be wound down in order that the organisations themselves might survive.</p><p> The Bill will also ensure that the assets in a scheme will be distributed more fairly.  As a recent editorial in <i>The Irish Times</i>noted, it makes provision for &quot;a rebalancing of risk in a more equitable way&quot;.  It is an example of a reasonably swift response by the Minister and the Government to a most distressing and current challenge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Maloney" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600025#BB00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  She is becoming a regular visitor.  I hope she will come before us on a few more occasions prior to Christmas in order to take Committee and Report Stages of this Bill and engage in a debate on the youth guarantee.</p><p>Defined benefits mean exactly what they imply, namely, when one finishes making contributions - more than likely the point at which one will also finish working - what one is paid is defined.  A person with a defined benefit pension enters into a contract with his or her employer and expects what has been defined or promised to be paid out in the end.  Unfortunately, however, many pension schemes are in trouble at present.  Trustees placed funds in what they anticipated would be reliable and rewarding investments but this has not proven to be the case, particularly in view of the fall in the value of stocks and shares and the position of the economy in general.  As a result, schemes are completely under-funded.  I understand that some funds were invested in bonds held by the famous bondholders, whom people wanted to burn.  If the latter had happened, many pension schemes would have gone under.</p><p>If a pension scheme in this country is under-funded, the trustees of that scheme are required to take action in order to bring them back into a funded position.  Of the 800 schemes here, some 40% are fully funded.  However, the remainder are either under-funded or poorly funded.  What the Minister and the Government are setting out to do in this Bill is to ensure equity and fairness to all who have contributed during their working lives.  The legislation relates to pension schemes which are being restructured, single insolvency and - where both a scheme and a company are insolvent - double insolvency.  Under the provisions of the Bill, the Minister and the Government are seeking to ensure that those who paid into pension schemes for their entire working lives will not be left with nothing when they retire.  Senator Mooney referred to circumstances where a person who is only one day away from reaching the pension age might be left high and dry.  The Minister is attempting to rectify the position in that regard and to bring some equality to the situation.  At present, the bulk of pension funds are being paid out to existing pensioners.  These people, who also contributed during their entire working lives, are entitled to their pensions.  If, however, a company and a scheme are to be restructured or both become insolvent, then workers who have made contributions for all of their lives would not get much of - or perhaps any - pension.  This simply would not be fair to those who have yet to retire.</p><p>What is proposed in the Bill will apply to the private sector only.  All pensioners will have an entitlement to the State pension, which the Minister has continually protected since entering office.  She has given a commitment to the effect that she will continue to protect it.</p> <p>Existing pensioners who have an occupational and State pension will have percentage protection under the new legislation.  As the Minister noted, people with pensions of less than &euro;12,000 per annum have nothing to fear as they will be fully protected, while those with pensions in excess of &euro;12,000 will have 50% of the value of their pension exceeding &euro;12,000 protected.  I welcome the commitment by the Minister to protect occupational pensions of less than &euro;12,000 as the individuals in question have the smallest pensions and will have been hard-pressed to contribute to their pension scheme during their working years.  They did so to provide a decent income for themselves and their spouses in their old age.  The measures in the Bill have been taken to ensure fairness in the distribution of pension funds to all those who have contributed.  The Bill changes the position from 100% priority to pensioners to 50% priority to all members of the scheme.</p><p>Senators will recall that the pay-out under the defined benefits scheme came to a head this year when workers at Waterford Crystal took a case to the European Court of Justice.  This was an appropriate course of action as it was devastating for the workers to find their pension entitlements had been seriously eroded due to a shortfall in funding and the insolvency of their pension scheme.  It took courage and determination to take their case to the European Court of Justice, which ruled in their favour in April last.  We must now meet our obligations and address the court's ruling on the insolvency directive.  This requires that we put in place measures to ensure at least 49% of expected benefits are paid to members when the employer and pension scheme are both insolvent.</p><p>As I stated, the Bill does not affect people on defined contribution pension schemes or the State contributory pension.  The State, that is, the taxpayer, cannot fund private pensions.  This means trustees must find ways to increase pension funds to a level that meets their members' requirements.  The Bill provides trustees with the option of restructuring a scheme.  If they see fit, they may reduce a higher pension and they are also given discretion on the final amount.  Trustees will be able to reduce higher pensions of between &euro;12,000 and &euro;60,000 by 10% and pensions of more than &euro;60,000 by 20%, thus ensuring that those who are better off pay most.  </p><p>The legislation will ensure, in the case of double insolvency, that the State will guarantee that existing pensions of more than &euro;12,000 per annum will be protected to the amount of 50%.  I welcome the Minister's announcement that she has secured agreement from the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, to use funds from the pension levy to honour her commitment.  It also provides for a scenario where the pension scheme were to remain viable and could, depending on its future investment performance, restore benefits to those whose pensions had been reduced.  </p><p>The Minister has invested considerable work in this legislation and consulted all relevant stakeholders.  In the case of a single insolvency, is legislation required to force employers to honour their commitments?  Currently, an employer can walk away from a business and establish a new company under another name.  Is legislation required to safeguard workers in such a scenario? </p><p>I note the Bill makes amendments to the Social Welfare (Consolidation) Act.  In light of the High Court decision that it is not necessary for new applications to be made for claims and that old claims must be reopened, what is the position regarding arrears in such cases?  If a decision is made on the basis of a change of circumstances, will it be necessary to backdate payment to the date of application or only as far as to the point at which the relevant changes took place?  Opening up an old application could have ramifications in terms of how much will be paid in arrears.  I ask the Minister to examine this issue before Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600027#DD00100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Tom Hayes.  He chaired a committee related to these matters at one time.  The Minister, Deputy Burton, has a background in accounting and has always taken an interest in this issue.  She has really pushed it forward.</p><p>  I was pleased the Minister found that 40% of the schemes are fully funded, because there has been something of a panic in the pensions sector.  She also found that 20% are poorly funded, but many of these schemes have put funding proposals to the Pensions Board to get them back on track.  The problem, as Jill Kirby observed in <i>The Sunday Times</i>, is that we have new rules but we retain many of the same old pensions problems, although there are fewer according to the Minister's findings.  The situation relating to defined benefit schemes looks a little more optimistic than we thought.</p><p>  We approach this after the problems in many financial institutions and banks, with accountants not performing and, indeed, pension funds as well.  Many of the funds are in deficit, so one must ask, if the problems are not to recur, what new rules there will be to ensure the trustees of pension funds do not get into these bankrupt situations.  Their duties were defined by the Pensions Board in 2010.  They include acting in the best interests of beneficiaries, acting fairly between beneficiaries and acting prudently and diligently.  Perhaps, just as stricter regulation of bankers and their accountants was required, stricter regulation of pension funds is required as well.</p><p>  Some of the reasons the pension funds have put forward for the difficulties they got into strike me as more a tribute to their lack of competence than anything intrinsic.  They underestimated longevity.  Lloyd George introduced the old age pension for people of 65 years of age at a time when the majority of people did not live until 65.  It appears to me that it is quite easy to predict longevity and the fund managers should have factored that in, not offered it as an excuse as to why they ran out of money and had to be rescued through this Bill.  They also cite poor investment returns.  That is, in a sense, an acknowledgement of their incompetence as investors.  Yet again, the taxpayer is invited to bail them out.  I hope they will up their performance in respect of poor investment returns.  They also cite the downturn in financial markets.</p><p>  The briefing documents we received refer to the reluctance to raise the retirement age.  I have no such reluctance.  When the pension age of 65 years was introduced it was greater than life expectancy.  If we are living for many extra years we should at least find out, on a voluntary basis, how many people would prefer to work and thereby reduce the strain on pensions funds.  In fact, the troika included that requirement in its early look at the situation in Ireland.  If people are living much longer, the cost to the funds will be greater and the contributions could be increased by asking people to work for longer.  Many would be prepared to do it.  I know people who retired very much against their better judgment.  They missed being at work and the comradeship and so forth.</p><p>  There are elements of moral hazard in this, in that the taxpayer must pay, through the levy, as well as those in well-run defined benefits schemes and those in defined contribution schemes.  That is a trend we must get away from in financial management in Ireland.  It is always the good guys who are required to pay for somebody else.  I do not think the Minister could have avoided that, but I will mention some quotes later to show that we need a much stricter regime for the regulation of this sector.  It is coming here after the banks with their accountants and so forth to tell us it is broke and is seeking yet another bailout.  There are also the credit unions.  We all know the list; it is very long.  We must require the sector to improve its performance.</p><p>  With regard to some of the criticisms, one is that pensioners could face losing up to half of their income under the planned rule changes.</p> <p>I do not see it.  </p><p>Another complaint is that a sum of &euro;12,000 will leave people in poverty, but the Minister has explained there are two payments of &euro;12,000, that is, the minimum amount from the defined benefit scheme plus the State pension.  I understand the maximum one will lose is 20%.  One newspaper article suggested a pension of &euro;36,000 could be cut by up to &euro;18,000 in the worst case scenario.  I do not see this from what has been said.  The same article also claimed someone on a defined benefit pension of &euro;20,000 could lose up to &euro;2,000, which is considerably less than half.  On the claim that 50,000 people could be out of pocket, the situation in respect of defined benefit schemes may be better than we have been led to believe and the Minister has noted that many of them are solvent.  We must look at the reasons the schemes got into trouble and how the trustees conducted themselves.  Stricter rules should be applied to them.</p><p>The expert group made an interesting observation on the public service reform plan for integration of the regulatory functions of the Pensions Board and the Central Bank.  If we are moving to defined contribution schemes, we need a different scheme of regulation as per normal financial services.  I hope we have put such a scheme in place.  The group noted that defined contribution pension schemes shifted responsibility for savings and investment decisions to members and also transferred the associated risks to members.  Effective regulation and supervision of these schemes, therefore, require a different mix of expertise, authority and programmes than for defined benefit arrangements.  It went on to argue that such schemes necessitated a focus on the integrity of the fund transfers from employers to investment managers, the reliability of record keeping for the accounting of individual fund balances, the suitability of investment products, the quality of investment management and the appropriateness of fees.  That makes their oversight more akin to the supervision of retail investment products than occupational defined benefit schemes, in which the sponsors underwrite these risks and are, therefore, regulated with a focus on the probity of governance and long-term financial solvency.</p><p>We need new institutional arrangements not only for defined benefit schemes but also for defined contribution schemes.  There are transfers, albeit smaller than the transfers to the banks, and we still have not caught up with the accountants who advised on them.  The message from this legislation has to be that the State is doing its bit with the levy to impose costs on some pensioners to fund badly run schemes.  The Central Bank was a party to the document to which I referred on integrating the Pensions Ombudsman with the Financial Services Ombudsman.  Given our dreadful experience with the figure of &euro;64 billion, a figure that is expected to increase, and the problems in the pensions industry, we need tighter and more conservative financial regulation.  I hope that will be part of what we are proposing.</p><p>Some Members argue that we should have more time to debate this Bill rather than take all Stages on Thursday.  We may have suggestions that would be of value to the Minister and her Department.  I commend the Bill to the House.  It is something that needed to be done because we require much better performance from the pensions industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="17:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600028#EE00200"><p>I assure Senator Sean D. Barrett that we will not be taking all Stages on Thursday.  We will be taking Committee Stage when we will have ample time to discuss amendments.  Report Stage will be taken next week.</p><p>When I heard Senator Paschal Mooney state this was too little too late, I was reminded of the EU directive and when it was introduced in the first place. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.148" nospeaker="true" time="17:10:00" ><p>Additional text to follow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600029#GG00100"><p>I would hazard a guess that there are few, if any, functioning as they should.  In many instances the people at the top of these organisations are marking time on enhanced salaries until they get their pensions, which will not be cut or contributing to the scheme.</p><p>  I have a letter from somebody in the ESB, and we all know that we may be facing an industrial relations crisis with that company.  My understanding from this correspondent is that something like &euro;80 million was being taken from the ESB fund by the State because of the pension levy.  The Minister for Finance gave a commitment at the outset that this measure would exist for four years at 0.6% and with the 2012 budget he went on record in the House as saying it would be discontinued this year.  That is not happening.  If one cannot believe a Minister for Finance on a significant taxation issue, what confidence can anybody have in this regard?</p><p>  The Minister did not highlight another element in her speech.  These people are not getting 50% of final salary in pensions and in many cases, an inflation factor is built in.  Where such an inflation factor is built in, it would range from 3% to 5%.  The Minister can correct me if I am wrong but these people will be deprived of that sum.  In a company where I worked, people left on a fixed pension and within a period of years, it had eroded to almost insignificance because of inflation levels.  Currently, there is a worry about deflation in Europe but following a financial crisis, it is very likely we will end up at some stage with hyper-inflation, as that is a normal cycle.  That would have a serious effect on these pensions, and there is no commitment, as far as I can see, to any of these people that their position will be addressed by way of a review of their pensions.  This is a bit like shifting the chairs on the <i>Titanic</i>, taking provisions from one person and giving them to another.  We are doing too much of that.  I would like to see a real root and branch analysis of the pension scheme.</p><p>  The Minister has not highlighted the capital cost that will be required in order to meet the deficits that will arise.  I am sure the Department or the Pensions Board has done some assessment in that regard.  Even with the private pensions into which people have paid, there is a very low volume of people in the private sector with any pensions other than the State provision.  That is not good when the demographics are changing, as they are, and we have done nothing to tackle the major deficit of approximately &euro;120 billion or &euro;130 billion in the public sector.  Something more serious and fundamental will have to be done with pensions.  I am particularly disappointed in this Bill, as it only scratches the surface.  Two years after the Minister identified the problem - she is an accountant so she understands the issue as well as I do - it must be tackled in a much more comprehensive manner than is evident with this Bill.  It is a pity that has not happened, and the opportunity has been missed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600029#GG00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, who makes very reasonable arguments.  She has indicated that she has brought in this legislation to help defined benefit schemes help themselves, with changes made to give the trustees of defined benefit schemes options and help them improve their funding position.  My only difficulty with that is it seems to rebalance the equation in favour of the trustees and against the pensioners.  The trustees are people charged with the responsibility of looking after this money.</p><p>The Minister also indicates she is relieved that the position is &quot;not as catastrophic&quot; as feared and 40% of schemes are fully funded; that sounds fairly catastrophic to me.  Perhaps it could be much worse but by God that is a frightful indictment of the people in control of these schemes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" speakername="Sean Barrett" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600029#GG00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600029#GG00400"><p>She continued by saying that everything was okay when the defined benefit schemes were in surplus.  This is true and nobody could possibly deny it.  In the case of a single insolvency, it seems extraordinary that a company can continue to trade and make a profit but welsh on its responsibility to employees and pensioners.  Will the Minister address that by way of amendment?</p><p>As I am on the subject of amendments, the Minister will no doubt be charmed, amused and entertained to know that we had a discussion on the Order of Business today as to whether we would be allowed have amendments at all on the Bill, as two days notice were not given.  I do not know where that came from but I am delighted to see the Minister introducing amendments.  We had a good discussion on the Order of Business and it has been decided that we will have amendments, which is appropriate.  We must be very careful and examine how business is conducted in this House.  There should never be a case where for technical reasons within the Bills Office, amendments are not allowed, as this House has a principal function of providing such amendments.</p><p>I noticed certain gaps in the Minister's performance of her written script, unlike some other Members, who read extensively from provided scripts or scripts they had made.  I am not arguing about it and such practice is fair enough.  I am only pointing this out in self-defence, as they may appear more grammatically correct than I do.  The Minister left out a sentence in her script stating &quot;Technical advice was undertaken on the provisions and a consultation with all the stakeholder groups took place.&quot;  That seems to be contradicted by a briefing from the Ireland Senior Citizens Parliament, which seeks the right of audience for pensioners and indicates that this is not being dealt with by the Bill.  They are being deprived of a right of audience.  It has made the point that employers have always asserted pension payments and the sponsorship of pension schemes to the benefit of an employee as a valid and compulsory part of remuneration.  Until the 1970s, pensioners had a right of audience to the industrial relations machinery of the State.  A successful pensioner case was then reversed by the then Minister for Labour in the 1970s.  In dealing with the matter of pensions, which is sensitive and a matter of fairness, all stakeholders should be included.  My understanding is that not all stakeholders were included in the process, although I am not accusing the Minister of being involved.  I am sure it was a Freudian slip when she left out that line from the speech.</p><p>The Minister has also indicated that the majority of pensioners received a State pension.  I should receive part of a State pension but I did not think it right to take it as I thought others needed it more.  The net result was newspapers in this country printing stories indicating I defrauded the Trinity pension scheme.  They also argued that I am a tax cheat.  The College of the Holy and Undivided Trinity of Queen Elizabeth near Dublin did not bother its fanny to come near me and put out a statement of fact, although I asked it to.  It need not think it is getting a shilling in my will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600029#GG00500"><p>The Senator has 30 seconds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="17:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600029#GG00600"><p>I will make them a long 30 seconds and as we know, according to Einstein, time is flexible.  The Minister indicates the Minister for Finance shall provide for the shortfall in scheme assets, which is a very welcome matter.</p><p>The Waterford Crystal pensions case is instructive and interesting.  It was determined that pension scheme members are to be protected where insolvency occurs.  Where the company continues to trade, it should not be allowed walk away from obligations.  Employers should be made pay the debt of pension promises rather than making existing pensioners and the State pick up the debts.  In the United Kingdom, Conservative and Labour Governments have protected work pensions through legislation which makes employer pension promises a debt that much be honoured.  The Waterford Crystal case was a tragedy and an absolute disgrace.</p> <p>It was known as Waterford Wedgewood originally.  Look at the difference in the way the Wedgewood employees were treated.  That was a shocking reproach to all of us.</p><p>Regarding equalisation, the figure of 80% and all the rest of it, speaking personally, my head is above water again, financially, thank God.  There is a social obligation on people like me who have a little bit of money or extra cash to support those on very small pensions or whose pensions have been abolished.  I would have no objection to this.  I would regard it as an honour to take a cut in any pension I have in order to help others.  I am sure everybody else in this House feels the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600030#HH00200"><p>I have received many letters from former colleagues of mine who are still working in the ESB.  These are very disappointed and dedicated workers who are deeply concerned about how they are being treated, not alone by the Government but also the previous one.  All of my former colleagues are compulsory members of a contributory defined benefit pension scheme.  It was obligatory for them on joining the ESB to sign up to the scheme.  They are very fearful of what the position will be when they reach retirement age.  For many of these men and women, it was their first job.  Some came out of college or university and went straight into the ESB which always was a great employer.  Many of them will not be entitled to the State contributory pension and they believe they carry all of the risks in the new pension scheme.  Is this the case?</p><p>Since 2011, the Government has been accepting accounts from the ESB, wrongly, in my view.  These accounts describe the scheme as a defined contribution pension scheme which was never known as a defined contribution scheme.  There is no basis whatsoever for the change in its description since 2011 other than for accountancy reasons.  Because of a deficit in the ESB accounts, the company will not provide funds to address whatever deficits occur.  The company has categorically stated it will not meet the deficit under any circumstances.  I also understand the Government plans to take in the region of &euro;600 million from the company, but the ESB pension scheme badly needs that money.  Under the new rules, many ESB employees will only have 3% pension coverage and will receive no State pension.  The ESB is not prepared to accept any of the risk owing to its new accountancy system.  I do not think it is fair that an ever diminishing number of dedicated staff in the ESB should carry all of the risk for a scheme to which they contributed 7% of their gross wages for all their years of employment to obtain their rightful entitlements.  The mismanagement of the scheme was and continues to be the responsibility of the ESB and its owners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1133" speakername="David Cullinane" time="17:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600030#HH00300"><p>I welcome the Minister.  Senator Maurice Cummins made a very passionate contribution on the plight of the former Waterford Crystal workers.  He spoke about the injustice visited upon hundreds of former workers who had to take the State to court to get their pension entitlements.  He expressed the hope the High Court case would be heard as soon as possible and mentioned that it might be heard next week.  He said he hoped there would be a positive outcome for the former workers.  It is important that they receive their payments as soon as possible.  They took a case to the High Court which referred the issues in the case to the European Court of Justice which found in favour of the workers on all counts.  However, as the Minister knows, the former Waterford Crystal workers are still waiting for their money.  They should get their proper entitlements as soon as possible.</p><p>One of the fears of the workers is that there is every possibility that the court case could be deferred again.  I hope that does not happen, but if it does, I ask the Minister to negotiate with the trade union Unite which is representing the workers to make sure they are paid at least the 50% of the money to which we know they are entitled and not have this issue dragging on in the courts for months, if not years, to come.  I very much hope the outcome of the court case will be quick, decisive and positive and that the workers will get their money.  However, we know the nature of courts and things do not always work out in the way one hopes.  If a positive resolution is not arrived at next week, I hope the Minister will assist the workers.  I heard her speak on local radio in Waterford recently and she empathised with the workers and acknowledged that they had taken a court case and won.  She recognised the fact that an injustice had been done.  Senator Cummins Maurice has rightly pointed out that a number of former workers have died and that we do not want to see a situation where more workers will die before justice is done.  This is a very emotive issue for people in Waterford, the former workers in particular.  There is a moral and political responsibility on the Government to make sure justice is done and the workers get their money as soon as possible.</p><p>On the Bill before us, I sit somewhere between the two Fianna F&aacute;il contributors, in that I do not believe it goes far enough, but it is an improvement.  The Bill lists six priorities to govern the distribution of a fund in the event of a scheme wind-up.  Sinn F&eacute;in proposes eight priorities.  Recognising that some scheme members are not eligible for the State pension or a contributory pension, our proposal sets out to ensure a minimum safety net for all scheme members through, first, purchasing the requisite contributions record for a State pension for all scheme members who did not have such a record.  Second, we would protect those on low pensions and with low pension expectations.  Third, we would look at the age-related portion of current and former members' benefits.  On the fourth, fifth and sixth priorities, we would continue the distribution back and forth across the retirement divide in an income-linked manner.  This means that once we had ensured existing pensioners had a full State pension of &euro;12,000, plus his or her full occupational pension benefit of up to &euro;12,000, we would immediately turn to the protection of future pensioners.  This has to be about protection for existing, as well as future, pensioners.  This would be a fairer distribution than the one proposed by the Government in the Bill.  </p><p>The Bill will bring about an improvement in the current position which can leave workers who have accrued future pension entitlements with little or nothing.  Anything which improves this must be welcomed.   However, my party genuinely believes the Bill still does not get the balance right.  Fundamental inequalities have been left unaddressed.  In order to protect high-end, gold-plated pensions, workers approaching retirement age will remain woefully unprotected.  In October 2011 the Minister suggested a more equitable style of pension reform and I find it amazing that after two years in government she seems to have been won over by her Fine Gael colleagues and is now just tinkering at the edges instead of implementing fundamental reforms.  The Government is now stating the pension levy will be used to fund shortfalls in a case of double insolvency.  However, as the levy has already been allocated to meet the Exchequer deficit, is this a case of double accounting?  That is one of the practices that got us into the mess we are in.  I give some credit to the Government for improving the situation, but I do not believe the Bill goes far enough in achieving the appropriate balance.</p> <p>I appeal to the Minister to do what she can to help those former Waterford Crystal workers who should be protected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1121" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600031#JJ00200"><p>I welcome the Minister and the legislation.  I listened to the previous speaker, and while I do not disagree with his comments on the former workers at Waterford Crystal, I appreciate this legislation is not the final set of proposals on the broader issue of pensions and pension schemes and I look forward to further progress in this regard.  Senator Cullinane mentioned the Minister's views and statements in October 2011 and all of us must have a mature debate on pensions, be they occupational pensions or State pensions, over the coming years.  We must consider charting a different course on the concept of pensions, pension entitlement and pension funding.</p><p>  The majority of people take out a pension to provide security and certainty in their older years.  Many situations have changed <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i> the elderly and pensions in recent years.  People now wish to work longer and lifestyle and health changes ensure, thankfully, people live longer.  We must try to reflect this new lifestyle and life choice in our debate on pensions.  The Minister's primary pension responsibility is with regard to the more conventional social welfare pension and this is why it is so important she has fought successfully in Cabinet to maintain a reasonable standard of pension for elderly people.  Our baseline of defence and argument should be that every person upon reaching retirement age, be it 66 today or 67 or 68 in years to come, is guaranteed a reasonable State pension.  Alongside this reasonable guarantee of a State pension we must try to ensure our elderly, or shall I say our mature citizens because I do not believe people of 67, 68, or 69  consider themselves to be elderly, have certainty about health care, housing and long-term nursing home care if required.  This must also become part of the equation.</p><p>  When I think of the people who through generations invested virtually all of their spare resources in pension schemes, expecting particular bonanzas on reaching retirement age and then finding the returns are so modest, I ask myself how the money could have been spent in an alternative way in homes and on families.  This must become part of the argument also.  Occupational pensions and private pensions taken out must be protected, but if we can guarantee a standard and certainty of living for our mature and older citizens it would be a very positive beginning.  If we can tell the elderly, who are not the 66 or 67 year olds, that if necessary their housing needs will be looked after by the State, their health services are guaranteed, whether one is a medical card patient or holds private health insurance, and if the time comes nursing home or sheltered accommodation needs will be provided, it would remove many of the fears, doubts and concerns which have obliged many people to pour huge resources into pension schemes which have turned out to be very different to what they would have expected.</p><p>  I know my few words are not particularly appropriate to this legislation but I hope they are appropriate to a broader debate which all of us need to have as a society on behalf of mature and elderly people.  We are speaking about people who in some cases seem to be reaching a disappointing conclusion to their pension investments.  The Minister is attempting to put in place a balanced solution which will not satisfy everybody and will have pain as well as gain.  We must be realistic, and it is as good as the Minister, the Oireachtas and the taxpayer can do under the circumstances.  In so far as it goes, I wholeheartedly welcome it and I encourage the Minister to restart what may have been her initiative of 2011.  It will not be in the Minister's time, my time or in the time of anybody in the House where this thinking will come to pass and come to really matter, but it will happen in 20, 25, 30 or 40 years and we need to begin thinking and talking a new dialogue on pensions, retirement, certainty and security.</p><p>  I look forward to Committee Stage of the Bill.  I hope the issues of concern raised by my colleagues on all sides of the House can be taken on board.  I look forward to hearing the Minister's thinking on other ways of ensuring certainty and security for the growing number of people who live into their 70s, 80s and 90s.  This is sometimes seen by the Department and the Department of Health as a problem, but we should see it as something to welcome and embrace although it requires new planning and thinking and a new approach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="17:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600031#JJ00300"><p>As Senator Bradford stated there are a number of reasons pension funds in Ireland got into trouble.  Most importantly, significant promises and commitments were made by employers in good faith about levels of pension coverage when people retired but, unfortunately, the Irish economy crashing was a key contributor to very difficult performances by pension funds.  Another issue is that funds established 30 or 40 years ago were for people who may not have had a life expectancy of much in excess of 15 years but this has all changed dramatically.  Some of the promises made were large and significant, but as time has passed we have had a huge increase in the number of pensioners, who if they are in a scheme are all contributing, and in the longevity of the pensioners, and the fund was never intended to cover this level of longevity.</p><p>In fairness to most trustees and members of most schemes, and employers and trade unions in particular, enormous efforts have been made, including in the ESB, over a prolonged period of time to address the gaps and deficits which have arisen.  The Bill addresses very difficult issues of equity and fairness which have been under very careful consideration for some time.  The legal issues involved are incredibly complex.  The issues date back over most of the past decade and they were raised by Fianna F&aacute;il in the 2007 Green Paper on pensions and the 2010 national pensions framework.  As far as Fianna F&aacute;il was concerned, the economy was booming in 2007 but it did absolutely nothing much in this regard, except very shortly after the economy was hit by the bank guarantee in 2008 it decided to suspend the funding standard, no doubt in the hope things would turn around because there were always green shoots around the corner.  When Fianna F&aacute;il is being critical of legislation being brought forward now it must explain to us in all honesty the long decade in which it did nothing but suggested everything was wonderful.</p><p>It is not the case the levy on direct contribution schemes will assist defined benefit underfunding.  The levy was set and established by the Minister for Finance prior to the previous general election at the request of significant sections of the pensions industry.  Let us not forget it was the pensions industry which came up with proposals for the levy.  A bit like people in the former Government party, there is a little amnesia on the part of those who suggested the levy.  It was actually the pensions industry, accompanied by very large advertisements.</p> <p>In fairness, Fine Gael adopted that policy in its manifesto and went to the people with it.</p><p>In his recent Budget Statement the Minister for Finance highlighted the fact that the 0.6% levy, in place on all schemes since 2010, would terminate at the end of 2014.  He also announced that a separate levy of 0.15% would apply to all pension fund assets to continue to help to fund the jobs initiative, including the continuation of the reduced 9% VAT rate in the hospitality sector, for which I have heard much praise in the Chamber, and to make provision for potential State liabilities which might emerge from pre-existing or future pension fund difficulties.  I welcome that second indication from him in the context of this Bill.</p><p>The trustees of defined benefit pension schemes have a fiduciary duty under trust law and the Pensions Acts to act in the best interests of all scheme members.  There are three kinds - pensioners, those on an existing pension and active members currently paying in.  This difficulty was highlighted.  Somebody who is 65 or 67 years and has retired is receiving full benefits, whereas without the protection of this Bill, somebody who is 62 or 63 years and within shouting distance of retiring could be left with absolutely nothing.  The Bill is being brought forward to balance that position.  There are regulatory safeguards and oversight by the Pensions Board in the case of restructuring.  Before the trustees make such an application, they have to consult the employer, the scheme member and any person receiving benefits from the scheme, and the authorised trade union representing scheme members in advance of an application to the Pensions Board.  It is very important that there be all-round consultation with the different stakeholder interests.  The Pensions Board will have discretion as to whether it should issue a direction following an application by the trustees.</p><p>I am considering in some detail the OECD review of the Irish pensions system and will come back to the Government with proposals.  This will include proposals to gradually achieve universal pensions coverage, with a particular focus on those on low incomes and those in atypical employment where they are moving from employment to employment.  As Senator Terry Brennan pointed out, defined benefit schemes were set up in the days when a boy joined the ESB at 16 years of age and expected to retire at 66, having served his time and moved up through the ranks of the company.  However, very few of us now know people who take up employment at 16 years of age and are still in the same job at 66; therefore, we have to bring forward arrangements to meet the changes in employment to ensure low-paid workers, including women who may be in and out of the labour force, and other atypical workers have adequate pension coverage.</p><p>To answer Senator Hildegarde Naughton's question, in the case of a single insolvency, an individual on &euro;40,000 and subject to a reduction of 10% will have the reduction applied to the total pension of &euro;40,000, that is, &euro;4,000.  However, this will be subject to the funding level of the scheme.  The better funded the scheme is, the less that will apply.  An individual on a pension of &euro;60,000, where the State pension accounts for &euro;12,000 of it, will be subject to a reduction of 10% on &euro;48,000.  I re-emphasise that the State pension, contributory and non-contributory, is not affected in any way by this legislation.  It is important to clarify that aspect.</p><p>In respect of the indexing of pensions, future benefit entitlements will be calculated by trustees on a scheme by scheme basis in accordance with the trustee rules applying to a scheme.  Senators Fiach Mac Conghail and Jim Walsh both raised that issue.  Legislation in 2009 gave trustees the option of not paying those affefcted by a wind-up to facilitate a fairer distribution of funds.  Post-retirement increases are provided for in about one third of schemes as per the trust arrangements of a scheme, but the 2009 legislation, brought forward by Senator JIm Walsh's party, gave trustees the option of not paying in the event of a wind-up to facilitate the distribution of funds.  Perhaps the Senator look back at this and see whether he still agrees with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600032#KK00200"><p>It is now mandatory.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/946" speakername="Joan Burton" time="17:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600032#KK00300"><p>The new provisions include post-retirement increases if they form part of the figure of 50% for expected benefits in a double insolvency, or if payment of the increases is the final point in the order of priorities order in the case of a single or double insolvency.</p><p>On retrospection, based on advice received, the legislation will apply to any scheme which is wound up after the legislation has been enacted and will not apply retrospectively.  It is important to have regard to the negotiations undertaken and agreements between the parties in a wind-up.  Generally, where schemes have been wound up, the process to date has been managed through dialogue between the stakeholders, the trustees, the employers and the members, whereby efforts are made to reach agreement on the steps to be taken when a scheme is no longer considered viable and the decision to wind up is made.  This nvolves negotiating arrangements which are unique and particular to each case in terms of the benefits the beneficiaries will ultimately receive and the substitution of the defined benefit pension model with other pension arrangements such as the defined contribution or a hybrid model.</p><p>In regulating schemes to a better funding level we have been concentrating on ensuring measures are put in place to make sure schemes have sufficient assets to meet the pension promises made and that this is done through regulation and implementation of the funding standard which the last Government relaxed.  I reinstated it some time ago with a view to having pension schemes make sustainable arrangements in respect of the promises made to members.  Responsibility rests with the employer, as the sponsor of a scheme, and the trustees for ensuring the scheme is properly funded and managed.  Many Irish pension schemes were very unfortunate and many comments have been made on this issue by pensions experts on the imbalance in equities and the poor returns from certain types of investment and on the general dislocation of global financial markets.  The changes needed to encourage underfunded schemes will be aimed at seeking funding of about 70% of that required in the funding standard which the Bill seeks to strengthen.</p><p>The key provisions of the Bill address difficult issues of equity and fairness.  The aim of the Bill is to ensure a fairer system for workers and sufficient protection for pensioners, while allowing employers to tackle their pension problems.  Representatives of employers, employees and the pensions industry have all been encouraging action in this area for some time.  I am heartened that there has been a broad welcome for the measures contained within the Bill.  We would all have wished that the pensions industry in Ireland and pension funds had not entered into the dreadful crisis in 2008, but it did happen and we are now trying to ensure as much stability as possible, as well as sustainability, for those pension schemes that remain in place.  There were 2,500 pension schemes in existence 20 years ago; only ten years later there were 1,000 fewer.  Throughout this period there has been a dramatic fall in the number of defined benefit schemes for many reasons.</p> <p> The process for distributing the assets of underfunded defined benefit schemes is very complex.  It is a very sensitive issue and terribly important to people as they grow older and come to rely on a pension as their major income.  The concept of intergenerational risk-sharing would suggest that maintaining the <i>status quo</i>, whereby people of working age can potentially lose their entire benefits before scheme pensioners make any contribution, is not sustainable.  At its most fundamental level, while a good degree of priority should be retained for the pensioners who are older, it is also fair that some measure of protection be afforded to all members of defined benefit pension schemes.</p><p> As I pointed out earlier, there is a &euro;12,000 limit, plus, in the majority of cases, people have an entitlement to roughly the same amount through the State retirement pension.  That brings the amount to &euro;24,000, and the average industrial wage is in the region of &euro;36,000.  Somebody with a combination of the two would be in a relatively good position in terms of a pension on retirement.  I wish it were more.  If we bring in some of the proposals made by the OECD and others, we will, I hope, start to extend coverage on a more intensive basis, particularly to low-paid workers.  That is very important.  </p><p> I thank all of the Senators who spoke on the Bill.  In conclusion, the Bill addresses the State's obligations in a double insolvency, but also goes further.  A fundamental aim of the Bill is to encourage schemes, through regulatory measures, to move from an underfunded position towards an appropriately funded position and further minimise the risk to the members, pensioners and taxpayers.  People need to have decent incomes in retirement and it is important that occupational pensions be viable and sustainable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.165" nospeaker="true" time="17:55:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL00300"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL00400"><p>Next Thursday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL00500"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.169" nospeaker="true" time="17:55:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Thursday, 28 November 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL00575"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL00600"><p>At 10.30 a.m. tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.172" nospeaker="true" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL00700">Adjournment Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.173" nospeaker="true" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL00800">Animal Welfare</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL00900"><p>Cuirim c&eacute;ad f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire agus t&aacute;im thar a bheith bu&iacute;och d&oacute; as teacht isteach ar an cheist seo.  Ceist &iacute; seo faoi chapaill, ceist at&aacute; ag tarraingt go leor cainte i nGaillimh le tamall anuas, idir an chathair agus an contae.</p><p>As I have outlined to the Minister previously, stray horses in Galway city and county have been the subject of a lot of debate in recent times, particularly at the joint policing committees of the city and county and in other forums in the area.  I tabled my motion in order to get a handle on the situation in Galway and nationally, if possible.  The matter was debated in a fair amount of detail when we discussed the Animal Health and Welfare Bill.  I commend the Minister's commitment to the health and welfare of stray animals.  </p><p>A recent meeting of the joint policing committee in Galway was attended by Mr. Eugene Cummins, director of services who deals with the issue in Galway.  He astounded us with the information that &euro;212,700 will be spent this year as a result of the neglect of horses in the county.  I know that a similar issue pertains in the city.  I believe the cost is due to a number of different factors.  It has been indicated that people from certain ethnic backgrounds have an issue with regard to the welfare of horses, but I believe the problem is much broader than that.  People who bought horses during the good times but are not now in a position to keep them leave the animals to stray.  Stray animals have caused many issues in the city and county.  Obviously the health and welfare of animals is the biggest issue, but stray horses also pose a danger to local communities.</p><p>At that same meeting, Mr. Cummins gave us another figure.  He stated that 98% of the horses seized by the county council were not chipped and did not have equine passports, which makes it difficult to trace their owners.  Many changes have been made to legislation in recent times.  However, &euro;212,700 is a large amount of money and must be an even greater expense on the State.  I am not sure if Galway is a particularly expensive county when it comes to this issue.  </p><p>I sought clarification from the director of services on the day of the meeting.  I asked him whether the money came out of the coffers of the local authority or whether it could be claimed back from the Department.  My understanding from what the Minister said previously was that local authorities could claim it back from the Department.  He might also indicate whether that has happened in the case of Galway City Council.</p><p>We all come from the same place and want to respect horse culture and traditions.  We certainly want to facilitate, in any way possible, communities who have such a culture.  However, that must be managed and done in a regulated and responsible manner.  Above all, the safety, health and welfare of the animals must come first.  We need to work on a cross-agency basis at local level in conjunction with the Department to ensure this work is done properly.  Policing and passports for animals is also an issue.  That is why I want to know how much has been spent in these areas and what can be done to eliminate the difficulties in the area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="17:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600033#LL01000"><p>I was anxious to come here to answer the question myself because this is a serious matter.  The issue costs a lot of money and resources but it is one that I, as a Minister, am personally committed to.  We need to change attitudes towards the welfare of horses among some communities in Ireland and we are taking action to ensure that happens at present.</p><p>Rather than read my answer, which the Senator will receive anyway, let me give some figures and commentary.  The first year the Senator asked about was 2011.  In 2011, we gave just over &euro;2.7 million to local authorities, which claimed for the seizure of fewer than 3,000 horses in the year.  In 2012, the sum was &euro;2.2 million, or just under that figure, and 2,969 horses were seized.  So far this year we have spent about &euro;1.8 million and exactly 3,288 horses have been seized across all county council areas.  </p><p>We have acted, and are acting, in a way that is consistent with the Control of Horses Act 1996.  The legislation allows my Department to work with local authorities and pays them the cost of dealing with stray horses.  Since then there have been more regulations and legislation, which has led to a more focused response to the issue of stray horses, or horses that are vulnerable to potential welfare issues.  We have the Animal Health and Welfare Bill, which we debated for many hours in the House.  We now have regulations that require horse identification in the form of a microchip and passport.  Horse owners now have an obligation to have a registered equine address for their animals in order for them to be deemed the legal owner.  That provision, combined with the Control of Horses Act 1996, allows us to take a more comprehensive approach towards dealing with stray horses.</p><p>This evening I want to send a clear signal to people.  We are approaching the issue from one perspective only - the welfare of animals.</p> <p> If my Department deems that horses are at risk of being abused or having their welfare compromised, we will act.  We have been acting across the country in partnership with local authorities, consistent with the legislation, and in some cases with the Garda.  For example, last week in Cork we seized 82 horses in an operation co-ordinated with the Garda, vets and Cork City Council.  The horses are now impounded and their former owners can claim them back if they can show they have a passport for them and an equine-registered address where they can put them to be looked after.  If they cannot show these, we will not give the horses back because we do not believe it would be in the interest of the horses' welfare.  We now have the legislation to back up our position.  We had an unfortunate revolving-door system whereby horses were being confiscated by local authorities for all the right reasons only to re-enter the system on being reclaimed by their owners.  This was crazy and the unfortunate victims were the horses themselves.  We are now going to put a stop to that.</p><p>If it is the case that 98% of horses seized in County Galway this year had no identification in the form of a microchip and passport, we will microchip them.  One will not be able to reclaim them unless one accepts full responsibility for their ownership, pays for their identification documentation and shows proof of an equine-registered address for them to go to.  In other words, the days of allowing horses to roam across publicly owned land, NAMA-owned land or abandoned development land are over.  We will be starting to confiscate horses from such areas if we believe their welfare is likely to be or is currently being compromised.</p><p>With regard to the horses confiscated in Cork, for example, eight had to be put down because of welfare concerns.  Two of them may have been claimed back and we are seeking to re-home a large proportion of the others.  We are having some success in that regard, which is great.  Ireland is a horse-loving country, as is the United Kingdom, and a considerable number of people are willing to take horses on a compassionate basis and put them out to grass.  However, we need to be realistic about how we deal with this issue.  I suspect that by the end of this year, we will have spent over &euro;3 million on horse seizures with local authorities.  The Senator can say to the county manager in Galway that we will, of course, work with him as long as he can show and guarantee an efficient management system associated with the seizure of horses.   A number of local authorities are now working together to have more efficiency in the system, which is why there is an increase in the number of seizures and a reduction in the overall cost, although costs this year will be higher because the number of seizures will be much higher.</p><p>My first concern is the welfare of the animals.  I am obliged to do what I can to guarantee and protect the welfare of animals, regardless of who owns them.  We have an animal welfare hotline number, 1850 211990.  If people have concerns about the welfare of horses or any other animals, I want to hear about it.  The telephone number is the same welfare number people used during the fodder crisis.  We will act on reported cases.  If there are horse owners who feel that, for whatever reason, they do not have sufficient resources, land or fodder to feed animals over the winter months, we need to hear about it.  We will intervene and I will provide a budget to do so.  We will change the way in which horses in some parts of Ireland have been treated.</p><p>I do not want to hear anything about tradition as an excuse for compromising welfare.  I want to see us proactively examining ways in which we can support communities that may not have access to land, but which may have a very strong traditional link with horses.  This needs to be done in a regulated, supervised and controlled manner to ensure we look after the welfare of the animals first and foremost.  In the absence of that, we will act and are acting.  There is growing evidence to suggest we are taking this more seriously as the months go by.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600034#MM00200"><p>An bhfuil an Seanad&oacute;ir s&aacute;sta?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600034#MM00300"><p>T&aacute;im thar a bheith s&aacute;sta.  That was a very comprehensive answer and I appreciate it.  I concur with almost everything the Minister said.  Can I take from his figures that he and his Department would consider supporting a cross-agency approach to people from groups such as the Traveller community who have a tradition of keeping horses?  Does he believe that, where appropriate, areas could be set up in places such as Galway where the tradition could be practised and where horses could be kept safely?  Could it not be done in a regulated manner with people taking responsibility for the horses they own?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600034#MM00400"><p>The Senator is broadening the question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/991" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600034#MM00500"><p>I would really like to see that happen but I cannot pay for it.  My job under the Control of Horses Act is to provide the finance to allow local authorities to deal with stray horses.  However, I strongly encourage local authorities to try to find the resources to allow for managed settings to permit the Traveller community, in particular, to interact with and own horses.  Its members have a strong emotional connection with horses.  It is a powerful connection but it is not an excuse to allow for the welfare of animals to be compromised.  When stray horses are vulnerable, we will act.  We will insist on the regulations being abided by in terms of the microchipping of and issuing of passports for horses and knowing the addresses where they are kept.  This is now a requirement under EU regulations and Irish law.  Following the passage of the Animal Health and Welfare Bill, there is also a responsibility on animal owners to look after the welfare of their animals, be those owners farmers, pet owners in an urban environment or members of a minority community.  We will enforce the regulations and send out a very strong and clear signal that owning an animal is not only a privilege but also a responsibility.  Of course, I would like to see local authorities assisting communities that want to own horses, but this has to be in the context of looking after the welfare of those animals and abiding by the regulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="18:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600034#MM00600"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it go dt&iacute; an Teach.  Regeneration is great and has certainly helped communities.  The most recent glowing example of regeneration's potential is in the Ballymun area of Dublin.  The residents of Ballymun will benefit and are benefiting enormously from it.  It is said that one cannot make an omelette without breaking some eggs, but sometimes there are eggs within the community that are too precious to be broken.  One is a community group that has been operating in the Ballymun area for over 30 years, Dogs Aid.  Not alone has it a proud tradition of caring for and looking after dogs but it also provides a very valuable resource to low-paid families and provides support to their pets, sometimes free of charge but in the majority of instances for a very low cost.</p><p>As part of regeneration in Ballymun, an area called Balbutcher Lane has effectively ceased to exist.  That is where Dogs Aid had its centre and clinic; it is where it looked after the dogs.  Unfortunately, the organisation is now homeless and has been operating from the back of a van with a battery-operated generator for the past three weeks.  I am sure the Minister can appreciate that, during the recent inclement weather, that has not been satisfactorily from the perspective of the volunteers, animals or those who bring their animals.</p><p>Ballymun Garda station was closed as part of the Government's policy of streamlining Garda stations and channelling resources in a more efficient way.  I understand the OPW is in charge of the building.  It would be an ideal building in which to house Dogs Aid, even on a temporary basis.</p> <p>The Minister needs to consider what benefits the community and look at organisations that have proven themselves and lasted the test of time as being ones that are there for the genuine betterment of the community.</p><p>As was stated in the previous Adjournment matter, animals are precious but they also bring with them responsibilities.  The responsibility for animal welfare does not only reside with the individuals who own them.  As a State, we have a responsibility to ensure that we provide the structure where animals can be treated properly.</p><p>I hope that what is a sensible solution to a problem that has presented itself as a result of progress is something that the Minister's colleagues in the OPW will take on board and that we will see Dogs Aid in Ballymun getting a temporary home in the disused Garda station.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1069" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00200"><p>I thank Senator Conway for bringing this matter to the attention of the Oireachtas and assure him that the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, will be made aware of his comments directly.</p><p>The property in question is leased by the OPW from Dublin City Council.  It was originally leased from the local authority in 1972 for use as a Garda station.  Following the completion of the more modern Garda station in Ballymun in August 2008, the property was vacated.  The OPW is in consultation with the local authority with a view to surrendering the lease.</p><p>Any decision on the future use of this property is a matter for Dublin City Council.</p><p>On the State's property assets, the Government is committed to reforming property asset management in the public service to ensure value for the taxpayer.  The stated policy for closed Garda stations is to identify, first, whether other State bodies, including Departments and the wider public sector, have a use for them.  If no State requirement is identified, the OPW will consider disposing of the property on the open market in order to generate revenue for the Exchequer.</p><p>If a decision is taken not to dispose of a particular property, the OPW will consider community involvement, subject to the receipt of an appropriate business case which would indicate that the community or voluntary group has the means to insure, maintain and manage the property and there is no cost to the Exchequer in the short, medium or long term.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy O'Dowd, for a factual and comprehensive reply.</p><p>It would be extremely helpful to Dogs Aid in Ballymun if the Minister of State with responsibility for the OPW, Deputy Brian Hayes, were to let it be known to the city manager that it would be his wish that Dogs Aid would be accommodated here on a temporary basis until such time as it can find more suitable long-term accommodation.  I suggest a letter or communication from Deputy Brian Hayes's office to the city manager.  Obviously, the Minister of State does not have power to direct the city manager to do it but I am sure the city manager would take seriously a proposal from the Minister of State at the Department of Finance with responsibility for the OPW.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1069" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00400"><p>I will bring the Senator's views to the direct attention of the Minister of State.  If they have not already done so, it might be useful if the community groups, the support services or those who are interest and support Dogs Aid would so communicate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00500"><p>I will advise them to do that.  I thank Deputy O'Dowd.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.187" nospeaker="true" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00550">Hospital Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy O'Dowd, for coming to the House.</p><p>I raise this matter to clarify the number of paediatric tracheotomy patients in Ireland and the number of registered nurses who are able to perform the procedure, how many of those are in the hospitals around the country and also how many are able to show parents how to perform the procedure.</p><p>Unfortunately, there have been some tragic cases in the past while where, because of the parents' inability to perform the procedure, children have died.  In some cases when looking for assistance from nursing staff who have not been properly trained in the procedure, tragedies have occurred.</p><p>I ask the Minister to outline to the House what the Government is doing to ensure that as many of the health care professionals throughout the State as possible are properly trained and qualified and that procedures are in place to ensure that tragedies, such as those that occurred in Kilkenny and in Cork, do not happen in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1069" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00700"><p>I thank Senator Daly for bringing this matter before the Seanad.  I would assure him that I will bring it to the attention of the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Kathleen Lynch.</p><p>In answer to the Senators specific questions in relation to the number of paediatric tracheotomies and nursing care, I will put the following on the record of the Seanad.</p><p>Information available from the hospital inpatient inquiry database would indicate that the number of children between zero and 16 years who have had this procedure and have been discharged from hospital is relatively small.  Of the 74 such discharges between 2010 and 2012, the majority have been from Crumlin children's hospital, 41 discharges, and the Children's University Hospital, Temple Street, 21 discharges.  However, it is not possible to say how many of those children were discharged with the tracheostomies still in place.</p><p>The active register of the Nursing and Midwifery Board of Ireland has a total of 4,274 individuals holding a children's paediatric qualification.  This does not mean that all of these are actively practising in this discipline.  Individuals may hold more than one qualification and as such may be practising in another division of the register.  It is also possible that individuals may not be practising at all, but still pay annual retention fees to maintain their names on the register.  Under new requirements set out in the Nurses and Midwives Act 2011, future registration will capture more defined information on current employment.  This will allow for more accurate analysis of the active register, including numbers of practising paediatric nurses.</p><p>The HSE established a working group to examine the discharge of infants or children with complex health care needs from the acute paediatric hospitals in Dublin mid-Leinster in July 2012.  The group comprised representatives from the paediatric hospitals, HSE primary care, nursing agencies, Jack &amp;amp; Jill Foundation, LauraLynn House and University College Dublin.</p><p>The group is finalising its report and will submit it to the national director for quality and patient safety.  Findings indicate the following needs: establish a clinical governance model for children discharged into the community; ensure that all staff providing care to children with complex needs are fully trained; and develop a support package for parents.</p><p>It is proposed that these recommendations will apply throughout the HSE.  A key recommendation concerns the need for a detailed paediatric home care package to be agreed prior to the child's discharge from hospital, with a detailed specification outlining the care requirement for each child and family.  A paediatric home care package needs to include a key worker to advise everyone within the family on all aspects of the child's care and trained nursing-care staff.</p><p>The provision of safe home care for children who are well enough to leave hospital, such as these children, is a priority for the Minister for Health.  He has highlighted care at home for children who have had to undergo tracheotomies as a priority service area for the HSE in planning its services in 2014.  The Minister is meeting the advocacy group tomorrow.  The HSE has informed the Minister that, following publication of the national service plan for 2014, officials will meet in early December to discuss future steps to deliver on the working group's recommendations in 2014.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00800"><p>An bhfuil an Seanado&iacute;r s&aacute;sta?  Is the Senator happy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN00900"><p>I do not know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN01000"><p>The Senator can ask a brief supplementary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="18:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600035#NN01100"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy O'Dowd.  I note this is not his specific area.  I wish that the Minister for Health would come into the House.</p><p>I asked the Minister to clarify the number of paediatric tracheotomy patients and to clarify the number of nurses who are competent to carry out and train in the tracheotomy procedure.  In brief, the answer to the first question was it is not possible to say how many children were discharged with tracheostomies in place.  The other answer, in a page and a half, was basically that the Department does not know how many nurses are trained to do this.</p> <p>Perhaps the Minister of State will indicate whether I have got the wrong end of the stick.  I must inform him, however, that the question I posed was not answered in the two pages of script he read into the record.  It said a lot but it also said very little.  I am not criticising the Minister of State; rather, I am stating that the two-page reply supplied by officials from the Department of Health to a matter raised on the Adjournment by a Member of the Oireachtas contains only one line in reference to that matter, namely, "it is not possible to say how many of those children were discharged with the tracheostomies still in place".  The fact that the information I am seeking could not be supplied is a cause for concern.  In addition, the Department does not know the exact position with regard to the qualifications of nurses.</p><p>Instead of insisting on the Minister of State reading out the reply in the House, the officials to whom I refer should have been honest and stated that they do not have a clue.  That would have been the best answer they could provide.  I ask the Minister of State to return to those officials and state that it is not acceptable that a public representative be provided with a reply as disgraceful as that which has been read into the record of the House.  I do not blame the Minister for Health or the Minister of State in respect of this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1127" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600036#OO00200"><p>The Senator's lack of pleasure with the reply is noted.  However, the Minister of State is not the line Minister.  If he wants to make a brief comment-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600036#OO00300"><p>Absolutely, and I do not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1069" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600036#OO00400"><p>It is very important that the views of all Oireachtas Members - including those of Senator Daly - should be brought to the attention of the Minister.  The Minister stands over the reply because it comes from him.  Notwithstanding what the Senator stated, the most important aspect to note is that there will be a meeting with representatives from the advocacy group tomorrow.  In other words, the people involved, who have deep, abiding and very real concerns, will be met and the issues outlined by the Senator - who also has concerns - will be dealt with tomorrow and will be the subject of direct answers from the Minister.</p><p>Another important point is that the existing requirements did not allow for the capture of the data which the Senator, quite rightly, is seeking.  Under the new requirements, future registration will capture more defined information in respect of those who are working and practising in this specific area.  I am satisfied that the solution to this problem is contained in the relevant legislation, which was passed in 2011.  In other words, the lacuna in our knowledge is being filled.  Information on the counties from which the patients come is not provided but statistics are supplied with regard to the hospitals at which they presented and had procedures carried out.  The data gap is quite small and really relates to patients' point of origin.  We are aware of the number involved and the hospitals where they were treated.  However, we do not know if patients had tracheostomies in place when they were discharged.  These are all important matters.  I am assured that no one was allowed to leave the hospital without the proper discharge protocols being observed and adequate and proper care policies being in place.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.198" nospeaker="true" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600036#OO00450">HSE Funding</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600036#OO00500"><p>This matter arises on foot of a reply I received on 17 October to a question in respect of section 38 and section 39 organisations which I submitted to the Joint Committee on Health and Children in September.  I have in my possession the appendix to the 2012 annual report of the HSE, which indicates that some 2,680 organisations are receiving funding from the executive.  The total amount of that funding is &euro;3.27 billion, which is over 25% of the health budget.  As already stated, I received a reply on 17 October last to a question I posed in September as to whether moneys additional to those set out in the guidelines laid down by the HSE were being paid.  While I was supplied with a generic answer, people in the media seem to have been given many more details two weeks later.  However, that is how the political system works and I must accept it.</p><p>I am now specifically concerned about the fact that salaries paid out by section 39 organisations do not have to correspond with the guidelines set out for HSE employees.  It is in that context that I raise this matter.  As already indicated, 2,680 organisations - hospitals, etc. - are receiving funding from the HSE.  In view of the debate that has taken place in the past two weeks, will new procedures be put in place in respect of section 39 organisations to ensure both accountability and proper disbursement of the funding allocated?  I fully accept that the HSE and the Department of Health are involved in work to revise the position in the area to which I refer.  Will the Minister of State indicate where we go from here in respect of this matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1069" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="18:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600036#OO00600"><p>I take Senator Colm Burke for raising this important matter.  There is a long history of non-statutory service providers providing health and personal social services in Ireland.  While many of these organisations have access to financial resources through fund-raising, they rely substantially on the HSE to fund the services the provide.  The  HSE funds a range of service providers under either section 38 or section 39 of the Health Act 2004.  Section 38 arrangements involve the funding of organisations to provide services on behalf of the HSE, while under section 39 the executive grant-aids a wide range of organisations to a greater or lesser extent.  As the Senator pointed out, some of the section 39 providers receive very substantial amounts from public funds.  Staff of bodies funded under section 38 are classified as public servants and are subject to the standard salary scales for the health sector, as well as having public service pension schemes and being counted in public service employment numbers.  Employees of agencies that receive grants from the HSE under section 39 are not public servants and are not specifically subject to the pay scales approved for public servants.  I acknowledge the contribution of such service providers to the development of health and personal social services.</p><p>The HSE is committed to the development of effective working relationships in line with the provisions of the Health Act 2004, which provides that the executive may, subject to resources and on such terms and conditions as it considers appropriate, fund services provided by non-statutory providers.  Significant progress has been made in improving the governance and management framework between the HSE and voluntary service providers.  In line with the Comptroller and Auditor General's 2005 report on value for money in the disability sector, a register of non-statutory agencies' service arrangements and grant aid agreements is in operation.  This provides local, regional and national management information on more than 2,600 separate agencies which operate more than 4,300 discrete funding arrangements to a value of approximately &euro;3.3 billion.  This register is managed by the HSE business support unit and has created a unique identifier for each agency.  It allows for the maintenance of key information on each separate funding arrangement, including current and historic funding, compliance with national standards, governance documentation and key contact details.</p><p>To ensure that the HSE and the non-statutory sector meet their obligations, the executive has developed a formalised national governance framework with national standard governance documentation to manage the funding.  This governance documentation was developed in 2009 with the agreement of all major service providers and came into operation in 2010.  Governance documents ensure a national standard consistent application of good governance and eliminate the need for individual contracts to be created each time the HSE funds an agency.  This process represents value for money, in that there is a ready-made contract for all funding arrangements, and provides governance that is robust and effective, ensuring that the HSE and the agencies meet their respective obligations.  The national suite of documentation is applied according to the nature and scale of the funding and services involved and contains the appropriate corporate, clinical and financial governance requirements.  This documentation is the subject of regular review.  In 2011 significant changes were introduced, including an extension of the section 38 clause to ensure that only salaries within public sector norms would apply to all funded agencies.  In 2013 an additional information return was added to all section 38 and section 39 arrangements.  This requires agencies to report separately on all individual staff paid at grade 8 level equivalent or above and provide details on their salaries, including those relating to allowances and any other benefits.</p><p>The HSE ensures a continuous focus on compliance with the governance framework and has included this as a key performance indicator for both corporate and regional reporting.  At the end of 2012, almost 98% of funding was covered by the governance document.</p> <p>Given the significance of the sector, all senior management in the Health Service Executive have key responsibilities within the governance framework.  A national support structure is in place which includes local and regional heads and a national governance group forum supported by the national business support unit.  Various guides and process control forms are maintained alongside a comprehensive operational manual which is in the approval process and awaiting formal adoption.  </p><p>Since the introduction of the governance framework in 2009, a number of projects have been undertaken to examine the management structures to ensure they are effective.  The key recommendations from these projects relate to the need for the HSE to build on the management processes which the national standard governance documentation and operational procedures have established.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600037#PP00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  He indicated an additional information return was added to all service arrangements in 2013 requiring agencies to separately report on all individual staff paid at grade 8.  I was not informed of this when I received a reply on this matter in October.  At that time, it was stated that the Health Service Executive did not have the power to seek such information.  Has this information been received from all relevant agencies?  In other words, has the new requirement to provide information on all staff at grade 8 or above been complied with?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1069" speakername="Fergus O'Dowd" time="18:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2013112600037#PP00300"><p>Senator Burke is seeking transparency in respect of the requirement to provide information and whether it is has been supplied.  As I am not a Minister in the Department, I will ask the Minister to revert to him directly on this important issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2013-11-26a.204" nospeaker="true" time="18:35:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 6.35 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 27 November 2013.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>