<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Neale Richmond that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to provide an update on the registration requirements communicated by Tusla for early years childcare service providers. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aidan Davitt of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to outline the timeframe for the completion of the technical assessment of Stepping Stones Special School, Kilcloon, County Meath.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on plans for reform and maintenance of the electoral registers.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Michelle Mulherin of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to consider the expansion of the Rebuilding Ireland home loan scheme to include those who lost their home during the financial crisis but have now settled their mortgage debt and are in a financial position to buy a new home and service a loan, but to whom the banks will not lend. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to make a statement on the upgrade of the N71 road from Bishopstown to Castletownbere. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the capital funding available for the upgrading and modernisation of the Cuisle accessible holiday centre, County Roscommon. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected those raised by Senators Richmond, Davitt, Boyhan and Mulherin and they will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill on the ground that it is a repeat of statements on the imminent closure of the Irish Wheelchair Association&rsquo;s Cuisle accessible holiday resort held in the Seanad on 27 November 2019.  Senator Lombard may give notice on another day of the matter he wishes to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#A00400">Early Childhood Care and Education</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#A00500"><p>This issue has dominated headlines and is a cause of increasing concern.  I have a personal interest in the matter as the parent of a young child attending childcare and the spouse of a childcare provider.  Although my wife does not operate her own facility, she works in the sector.  I have received a significant number of emails and calls on the issue and will meet several providers this week in Leopardstown and Stepaside.  The services in those areas are totally oversubscribed.  Without an abundance of childcare facilities, parental choice is limited.</p> <p>There is confusion among providers regarding the regulations and requirements and shifting dates.  Although I fully acknowledge the need to have the best standards of care for our most vulnerable, particularly our children, the current situation is of significant concern.  It is my worry that many facilities will not reopen in the new year.  Several facilities have written to parents to inform them that they do not have the resources to comply with the regulation requirements or complete the relatively onerous online portal.</p> <p>I am appealing to the Minister to provide clarity and guidance such that I can go back to the providers and underline that this is not an attempt to punish or disrupt services but, rather, aims to ensure the best level of care is provided, and that it will incorporate an element of flexibility such that services can be delivered in a timely manner and, crucially, parents will not go through a period without a childcare provider.  We must all work together to ensure that children are protected in a way that allows such flexibility.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#A00600"><p>I welcome Senator Richmond's question on the re-registration of early learning and care services and the opportunity to update the House on the current arrangements.  I appreciate the spirit in which he raised the matter and will attempt to provide the clarity he requests.</p> <p>As he is aware, the Child and Family Agency Act 2013 provided for the establishment and maintenance by Tusla of a register of early years services providers.  All services are required to re-register every three years and the majority are required to re-register by 31 December 2019.  This deadline has been known to providers since 2016 and appears on their registration certificate.  Over the past 18 months, Tusla has been engaging with providers regarding requirements for re-registration, including through a consultative forum of stakeholders.  In August 2019, Tusla issued further guidance to service providers on specific planning permission documentation required as part of the re-registration process.</p> <p>In recognition of the difficulties many providers were experiencing in completing re-registration, Tusla decided to revise the timeline for submission of supporting documentation for re-registration.  Under the revised arrangements, although providers must apply to Tusla by 12 December, they have until 30 June 2020 to provide some of the supporting documentation required, including documentation on fire safety and planning requirements, which stakeholders identified as the most onerous.</p> <p>My Department has been working closely with Tusla on the matter.  Although the health and safety of children is the primary concern in decisions on the regulation of early learning and care services, I recognise that a balanced approach to the re-registration process is required.  In that context, I fully support Tusla's decision to extend the period.  On 27 November, my Department issued a letter informing providers that Tusla has revised the timeline for submission of supporting documentation for re-registration.  The letter provides clear guidance on what documentation is required by the 12 December deadline and what can be submitted up until 30 June.  Although the 12 December deadline is close, I am confident that the changes announced by Tusla mean it is very achievable for providers.  I urge all providers to complete their applications on time for this important legal process in order to be on the register of services in January.  If they do not do so, they will not be eligible for public funding.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Katherine Zappone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2392"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2392&amp;amp;pid=KatherineZappone&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My Department has been working closely with Tusla to ensure adequate numbers of staff are in place to process applications on time and ensure effective communication with providers.  In addition, my Department has supported city and county childcare committees to give advice and assistance to providers that need help with re-registration.</p><p>Most services are compliant with fire safety requirements and have not faced additional costs for re-registration.  Those that are not compliant have to make changes.  I am sure we will all agree on the importance of addressing fire safety concerns.  In recognition of this, my Department awarded &euro;330,000 in capital funding to community-based, not-for-profit services in 2019.  This has helped to address fire safety issues that had been highlighted in inspection reports.  A further, related round of capital funding will be provided in 2020 for the same purpose.  When the Tusla early-years inspectorate identifies fire safety issues during inspections, it notifies the local authority fire services, which have responsibility for this.</p><p>On 12 December, providers will have to provide documentation that they should have such as proof of Garda vetting, proof of identity, a safety statement and proof of insurance cover.  This is reasonable and necessary to ensure the safety of children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B00200"><p>I appreciate the Minister's clarification, particularly on future capital funding that is coming on stream.  However, a couple of issues still need to be addressed, one being communication with providers.  We have to remember that the vast majority of childcare providers are not even SMEs; they are one- or two-person operations.  They are facing an administrative tsunami.  When dealing with Tusla, the only way to get through to it is via the portal.  This can be frustrating when someone only has half an hour or 45 minutes in the day and there is a deadline, albeit extended.</p> <p>I have raised other issues in the House regarding delays in Garda vetting.  I realise this subject is not under the remit of the Minister's Department but I have raised it multiple times.  Vetting causes delays when planning to take on temporary staff or other new staff.  I refer to circumstances that might have happened in recent months, including in respect of insurance companies providing only minimal documentation.  It all adds up and causes considerable concern.  I welcome, however, the Minister's clarity and the progress.  I urge her Department to do anything it can to lean on, or work with, Tusla to make it a little more front facing and responsible.  I am not necessarily referring to major chains but to independent providers that are struggling to deal with this issue, despite the fact that everyone involved wants the best conditions for our children.  There are those within the sector who need a little more help than others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1358" speakername="Katherine Zappone" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B00300"><p>I thank the Senator again.  I appreciate the spirit of his question and the manner in which he has raised further concerns.  Tusla and my Department were aware of the issues he raised, especially those affecting smaller providers.  There has been an attempt to ensure flexibility.  My Department has tried to make sure staff are available to support the providers.  There has been communication.  Providers have known what is required of them for some time, as I understand it.</p> <p>Having said that, I acknowledge what the Senator is saying about paperwork and processes concerning Garda vetting and insurance.  It is important to be aware of this.  I will communicate with my early years unit.  We have had this exchange.  The Senator's request is that we make sure there is additional support, provided in whatever way possible, especially for the small providers.  We must determine their circumstances and whether they need additional support so they can remain open.  Of course we want them to remain open.  As he said, the providers with just one or two staff are running a business.  There are certain requirements to ensure children are safe.  At the same time, however, it is a matter of supporting the providers in the best way to meet those requirements.  I will go back to the Department and make the request.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B00400">Schools Building Projects</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B00500"><p>The Minister of State, Deputy English, is very welcome, as ever.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B00600"><p>I am delighted the Minister of State is present.  He is a hard-working Minister of State and a neighbour from only up the road.  I am delighted to see in the Visitors Gallery a prolific author, Councillor Mattie Ryan, the man who wrote the book, <i>Cuttin' or Atein' the Bushes</i>.  He is accompanied by a few friends from Tipperary.</p><p>The Minister of State will be well aware of the specific problem faced by Stepping Stones school, Kilcloon, County Meath, which is close to his backyard.  Many representations have been made on this matter by his Oireachtas colleagues, including Deputies Thomas Byrne and Shane Cassells, and Councillor Damien O'Reilly.  There was huge fanfare six months ago and great news was delivered, but nothing has followed since.  The Minister of State might be able to put some flesh on the bones in regard to this and harden up some of the deadlines.  I would appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B00700"><p>I thank the Senator for raising the issue of Stepping Stones school, Kilcloon.  It is a school with which we are all very familiar.  It is providing a great service and great opportunity to many young people and young adults going through the system.  It represents all of County Meath and even beyond that.  The issue has been raised with the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy McHugh, the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy McEntee, the Senator, Deputies Cassells and Thomas Byrne and others.  We are all familiar with families who have great success stories and who have had a great journey through Stepping Stones school.  When it first opened many years ago, it provided an opportunity for young children who might not have had the opportunity before that.  It leads to positive outcomes.  It is a positive school and we want to build on that.</p> <p>I am responding on behalf of the Minister for Education and Skills, who is not available.  He would like to have been here.  I understand he visited the school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B00800"><p>He did six months ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B00900"><p>He has an interest in it and certainly wants to try to make progress on plans, if possible.</p> <p>Stepping Stones is a special school located in accommodation on a site provided by the school authority.  The school currently has a principal and five teaching posts.  The school caters for students ranging in age from six to 18, or young adults.  The current enrolment is 30 pupils, which is consistent with enrolment numbers over the past five years.</p> <p>The most recent correspondence from the school, in November 2019, requested formally the provision of a new school building.  The current position relating to the school's request is that the school is not included in the Department's current building programme, set out a couple of years ago.  It is not officially in that but the Minister is committed to working with the school in that regard.  In the meantime, the Department approved an additional temporary mainstream classroom for the school earlier this year.  I understand the school authority has begun the process of applying for planning permission for this room.</p> <p>I advise the Senator and others who are listening that it is open to Stepping Stones school to apply to the Department for additional temporary accommodation to cater for its immediate accommodation needs or an emergency works grant to address any health and safety works at the school.  The bottom line is that, on a temporary basis, the Department will work with the school to accommodate it and meet its needs.  If it needs additional space, that can also be addressed.</p> <p>With regard to the new school applied for in November, departmental officials will be in contact with the school authority to arrange a meeting early in the new year in the Department's offices in Tullamore to discuss the schools future accommodation needs and plans.  There was talk of a site visit but that is probably not necessary just yet.  It is more important that we get everyone sitting down together around the table in the offices in Tullamore to ascertain the exact needs and design.  There are some lovely designs for special schools around the country.  I am familiar with the work St. Mary's special school is doing in Navan and the design it has opted for.  The Department will be interested in engaging on that.  The first process is to agree on the aims and then to get the project into the capital plan.  The Minister, who visited along with the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, is committed to trying to help the school with its long-term plans.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B01000"><p>I appreciate the answer.  As the Minister of State said, the school takes children from a wide area.  There is a child in attendance who is from not too far up the road from me.  I am delighted the Department is to take some temporary measures and that its officials were happy to meet to push this forward.  I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#B01100"><p>I again thank the Senator for raising this important issue.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.22" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#C00100">Electoral Register</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#C00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy English, here and thank him for coming to the House.</p> <p>This Commencement matter is on the plans to reform and maintain the electoral register.  I was reminded again why I brought this issue up by the very low turnout in the recent by-elections.  I spoke to a number of candidates who could tell me that people were five, ten or 15 years on the register of electors.  We have a very bad system in place.  It does not serve democracy and politics well that we have such an archaic system.  I was also reminded of the fact that on Thursday, 22 September we had an opening statement by the Minister of State, Deputy Phelan, in which he set out all of his ideas and reforms and told us that we were going to have legislation on the electoral commission.   A memorandum was presented to us and it talked about independence, membership, accountability, the streamlining of the electoral registers, there was a regulatory analysis done on this Bill, and finally we had the Standards in Public Office Commission, SIPO, expressing serious concerns on the whole electoral process.  </p> <p>There are challenges.  SIPO called for the electoral commission in respect of legislation to deal with digital political campaigning.  It talks in its recent report about the influence outside of this State and stated that the unregulated nature of social media campaigns, and I am quoting SIPO directly here, "allows for foreign actors to influence Irish elections and referendums, with potentially significant consequences".  We have serious issues in this regard.</p> <p>The last time I made some inquiries into the franchise section, there were between eight and ten people working in that section in the Custom House, who effectively run the elections and the referendums.  That is a great pressure on them, albeit they do a good job.  The time has come where we need a proper, structured and independent oversight of how we conduct our elections, how we manage and deal with SIPO and financial returns and all of these issues.  The body politic has received a lot of blows recently and it is time we put in place the necessary legislation and Bill for the governance of any election or referendum in the State.  More importantly, the key issue is what are the Minister of State's plans to clean up, smarten up and have an up-to-date and fit-for-purpose register of electors in this country?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#C00300"><p>I thank Senator Boyhan for raising this issue here today.  He is right, as anyone who spends time canvassing the doors knows that the register is not always in perfect condition.  One can come across people for different reasons, of their own accord, who may not have taken time out to be registered, or might have tried in the past and failed.  There are often complications.  They may be on the register but in a wrong way or in the wrong catchment area.  I try to engage in door-knocking most weeks all year round, election or no election, which is always an enjoyable experience.  When it comes close to an election, people become very concerned if they are not on the register or something has gone wrong with their processing.  It is important therefore that we do have that right and up to date.  The Senator  referred to the turnout for the recent by-elections being low and there can be different reasons for that.  If, however, we wish to encourage people to come out and vote, the first step is to ensure that people are registered properly and have the option to vote in the first instance.  It is then up to us to convince them to come out and vote for some of us along the way.  It is not always about voting for people, as people often vote for other issues as well, such as in referendums and so on.  It is important therefore that the register is in order.</p> <p>While the existing electoral registration system has served us well and enjoys a high level of public confidence, successive Oireachtas committees, as well as Senator Boyhan himself and external reports, have identified a number of improvements that could be made to the process.  In March 2017, the Government decided that work should commence on the modernisation of the voter registration process and I believe I also took a debate on this in this House at the time.  This project will give effect to improvements that, along with improving our national registration process, could also ultimately facilitate the registration of voters resident outside the State, in the event of the referendum on extending the franchise in presidential elections being passed.</p> <p>The key policies being proposed are largely based on recommendations by the then Oireachtas Joint Committee on Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht in its report on the establishment of an electoral commission published in January 2016.  This report considered the electoral register in some detail in the context of it being a function for the proposed electoral commission.  The aims of the policy proposals are to enable a better service to the public, modernise the administration of the register and maintain and enhance the integrity of the register, which is of the utmost importance.</p> <p>Following an initial consultation with local authorities on a set of policy proposals, my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Phelan, launched a public consultation on the electoral register modernisation project in December 2018.  Some 187 submissions were received from a broad range of stakeholders and a report on the consultation will be published very shortly.  The seven key policy proposals included in the consultation document were the simplification of the registration process and the forms used, the introduction of a rolling electoral register rather than the current annual one, optional online registration and secure self-service, a move to individual registration only, enabling a single national electoral register database with unique identifiers, a move to verified identity using one's personal public service number, PPSN and the provision for some limited data-sharing between public bodies and electoral registration authorities to maintain accuracy and comprehensiveness.</p> <p>As well as proposing the removal of the provision that requires an edited register to be produced, three further policy proposals have also been put forward with the aim of making the register more accessible to all.  These are the provision of a system of anonymous registration for people whose safety may be at risk if their details are included on the register available for inspection, improved provision for registration for those with no fixed address and pre-registration for 16 and 17 year olds, with the registration becoming active on their 18th birthday.  We are all very familiar when we are out campaigning and one comes across a person who is going to be 18 on the date of the election and would be very anxious to have a vote.  Certainly, if they are going to vote for the person canvassing, one would be happy to help that person get that vote.  It is important that that is cleared up as well.</p> <p>The responses to the consultation are informing ongoing work in the Department on various aspects of the project, including, most immediately, the development of a simplified, standardised registration form.  The Senator is right in saying that the franchise section of our Department works extremely hard and are very honourable and detailed in their work.  It is a busy section but it is committed to doing this, as is the Minister of State, Deputy Phelan.  We will have a further update for Senator Boyhan shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#C00400"><p>To wrap up, I thank the Minister of State for that reply and I note he is aware of the issue of modernising the administration of the register of electors and enhancing the integrity of those registers.  I do not believe we will have all of this in place for the next general election, looking at the political landscape ahead of us.</p> <p>I will make one further comment.  It is important that we do not keep reinventing the wheel.  A very significant and important body of work was done by Professor Richard Sinnott, the Geary Institute, John Coakley and John O'Dowd and I have brought a copy along here today.  I will put it in the post to the Minister of State.  They prepared a very detailed and substantive document in UCD on a whole range of the issues that we have discussed this morning.  I have been in touch with them and it is important to tap into this very expert resource, where we not have to spend any more money on committees and research.  This is very important document which should be worked into the process.  I again thank the Minister of State for his very detailed response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#C00500"><p>I have no doubt that the Minister of State, Deputy Phelan, will be happy to avail of the document, and I have no doubt that the gentlemen may have submitted it as part of the consultation process, which I hope they did because it would have then fed naturally into the consultation process.  We, in our Department are very open - as we always are in all matters, be it in the franchise, housing or planning sections - to take on board outside analysis, information, ideas and data.  We believe in tapping into the world of academia, which has much to offer when it comes to research.  We do not, as a country, avail enough of their expertise.  We certainly will in our Department.  If the document is there, I am sure the officials already have it but if not, I will ensure that they do.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.27" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#C00600">Home Loan Scheme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#C00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.</p> <p>One undoubted fallout of the financial crash, which happened not too long ago, is that many of our citizens ended up getting into both mortgage and personal debt and some of them even lost their homes.  Thankfully many people have managed to get through a very difficult time and have gone through the debt resolution process.  We see also that unemployment figures have gone from 16.1% to the all-time low figure of today.  People are in a much better position as to their finances and can afford to service loans.</p> <p>The problem for some people at this juncture is that they find that they cannot borrow.  These are people who have gone through the debt resolution process, settled their debt - they are not just people who went bankrupt - but who now wish to acquire a house, buy a home, as opposed to renting, and have found they cannot get a loan from the high street banks.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I know the Government has provided the Rebuilding Ireland home loan scheme to allow first-time buyers to acquire a home mindful of the market and to encourage more housebuilding and house ownership.  However, as the Minister of State is aware, this does not apply to people who are second-time buyers.  This might arise where people have lost their homes and have gone into mortgage debt.  They may find that their credit ratings are shot or poor and they cannot get loans.  I am asking that such people are catered for under the Rebuilding Ireland home loan scheme.  I believe this is required to facilitate the increasing number of people who have gone to the mortgage-to-rent scheme.  The scheme in its current incarnation has been far more successful than the original scheme, for which there was poor take-up.  Basically it is a scheme for people who had owned houses but cannot afford the mortgage.  They now rent the property but at some time in future there is the prospect of buying it.  These people equally need to be catered for in terms of how they will borrow to buy their houses.  This is another cohort of people who need to be catered for.</p><p>As part of the solution the Central Bank and other banks should be pressed to make their position clear in respect of lending to people in this situation.  The banks should make it clear to people that there is a finite time for the credit record to be blackened.  After that the people should have a clear and clean slate.  There is much confusion and people are missing out.  Many people are frustrated.  The scheme should operate in keeping with the philosophy that people did not cause the financial crash.  People lost their jobs through no fault of their own and could not service mortgages.  Now, they have put themselves on an even keel and need a fresh start.  We need to support policies that allow them the fresh start we envisage for all our citizens in the wake of the financial crash.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Mulherin for raising this issue of the Rebuilding Ireland home loan scheme and the issue in general of people who have gone through difficult times in this country but wish to get back on their feet again.</p> <p>Senator Mulherin mentioned the mortgage-to-rent scheme, which I will come back to in a moment.  It is another important scheme.  I am glad we were able to reform it to make it more workable and user-friendly.  Many more people are now interested in using that scheme.  They are finding it as a solution to remain in their family home.  That is what it is about.  The mortgage-to-rent scheme is about keeping people in their family homes.  It is a successful scheme and I hope more will avail of it.  Despite the scaremongering some go on with, we are in the business of protecting people in their family homes.  The courts respond to that.  Certainly, as a Government we have responded to that and changed legislation to accommodate it.</p> <p>The Rebuilding Ireland home loan scheme enables creditworthy first-time buyers to access sustainable mortgage lending to purchase new or second-hand properties in a suitable price range where they cannot obtain sufficient mortgage finance from a commercial lender.  To be clear, the lending criteria in terms of creditworthiness is probably the same for the Rebuilding Ireland home loan as it would be for the banks.  It is to do with making it more affordable because there is a lower interest rate.  It is for people who could not get enough money from the bank.</p> <p>As with the previous local authority loan offerings, the Rebuilding Ireland home loan is available to first-time buyers only.  The availability of loans through local authorities are for first-time buyers.  This is set out in the regulations governing the scheme and ensures the effective targeting of limited resources.  Like the help-to-buy scheme, we are trying to intervene for first-time buyers because we do not have the resources to stretch for everyone.  The taxpayer cannot be involved in everyone's home.  We try to match the resources where they are needed most.  Historically, that is where the schemes have been targeted.</p> <p>If an individual has previously defaulted on a mortgage he or she is obviously not a first-time buyer.  That is why such a person would not qualify for the scheme as it stands.  We do not have any immediate plans to change this provision because it has been in place for a long time.  Again, it is about trying to stretch our resources as best we can.  That does not mean we cannot try to find other solutions for that category of people.  This is something we can look at again and I will be happy to engage with Senator Mulherin on it.</p> <p>Applicants for the Rebuilding Ireland home loan must be of good credit standing and have a satisfactory credit record.  The Housing Agency provides a central credit assessment service to local authorities and credit checks are undertaken as part of the credit assessment process.  A person who has been discharged from bankruptcy and is eligible in all other respects, including being a first-time buyer, for a Rebuilding Ireland home loan may apply for a loan and will be subject to the same credit assessment process that applies to all applicants.  Even if such a person is involved in other debt-forgiveness mechanisms and insolvency arrangements, being a first-time buyer will not preclude the person from being involved in the scheme.  The final decision on loan approval is a matter for the relevant local authority and its credit committee on a case-by-case basis.  Decisions on all housing loan applications must be made in accordance with the regulations establishing the scheme and the credit policy that underpins the scheme to ensure prudence and consistency in approaches in the best interests of both borrowers and the lending local authorities.</p> <p>The Senator referred to the credit history of people.  I have been involved in helping several people in recent years through difficult times.  I have worked with them as a Deputy and I have a general interest in the area, coming from a finance background.  Many are able to turn their affairs around, clean up their credit rating and go back to a bank to secure finance, whether through the bank or credit union.  I urge people not to despair.  If someone has had difficult credit times or credit history it is possible to turn it around and work with professionals to clean up the credit rating and credit history.  My understanding is that there is a time limit and a point when the position changes.  The banks only look back for a given number of years.  The banks have different proposals but we can get clarity on that for the Senator.  If people have been through difficult credit times it is important that they immediately try to correct the situation and keep their affairs in order in future.  Banks generally focus on the most recent years and whether people have managed to pay bills on time and manage their accounts.  Everything is looked at when it comes to credit history.  It is not only what happened in the past but what is happening at present as well.</p> <p>The mortgage-to-rent scheme is successful.  We have changed it.  The initial scheme did not have the best design although it had the best intentions.  We made changes during the past year or two.  There are now more players or stakeholders in the market.  I believe the mortgage-to-rent scheme is an opportunity for families who are still living with an unsustainable mortgage.  The mortgage-to-rent scheme is a good scheme to keep people in their family homes.  These people end up renting their home from the local authority or housing body, but the option is available in the years thereafter to buy back the house if they wish.  It is a good scheme and a great solution for many families who are stuck with an unsustainable mortgage and who do not see any plan.  Generally, the banking and lending institutions work with people to try to find a solution to keep them in their home.  I always find that.  We always hear stories in the media about those affected but if people engage with the banking system and try to find a solution then an effort is made by all sides.  The courts look for that and judge that.  Anyone being brought forward is asked to try to find a solution to enable them to stay in their family homes.  The mortgage-to-rent is a good solution thereafter.  If everything else fails the mortgage-to-rent is a good endgame solution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  We have covered a good deal.  I am bringing up this issue because I am aware of several constituents who are having this difficulty with the banks and with their credit rating.  One person has sorted out a previous mortgage debt after falling into arrears.  The mortgage is now settled and the person is looking for a fresh start but the high street banks are not playing ball.  Perhaps as the Minister of State suggested, we can get some clarity from the Central Bank.  It is appropriate for the Central Bank to send out the message that a poor credit rating or history is not a life sentence.  The banks should be monitored in respect of how they are operating the rule or consideration when they are deciding whether to give someone a loan.</p> <p>One of the conditions for the mortgage-to-rent scheme is that applicants in future might be able to buy back the house when they get into a sounder financial position, which is fantastic.  However, some of these people will get into the same problem that I have described if they have lost a home previously.</p> <p>More work needs to be done in this area.  I welcome the fact that the Minister of State is willing to engage.  I know that is his general disposition.  He might provide clarity for me on several of those points.  I would appreciate it.  It would enable me to go back to people and give them some comfort about their situation and give them hope.  It is important that they are not stuck in limbo, renting forever when they can financially afford to get a loan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#D00400"><p>I will absolutely engage to get some more answers for Senator Mulherin.  We will address some of the questions to the Department of Finance.  I cannot comment for that Department but we will certainly engage with the Department of Finance.</p> <p>Senator Mulherin is right to say a poor credit rating is not a life sentence.  It can be cleaned up and corrected over time.  Time is a great healer in this regard.  Banks are in a position to make judgments on the existing record of people and how they are handling their affairs at present.  It is important that people know that.</p> <p>We went through difficult times when probably everyone was affected in some way by what happened.  It is not that long ago, although most people seem to have forgotten it.  It was only seven or eight years ago when some of the people I met while out knocking on doors were concerned for the future of the country.  Thankfully, this has been turned around but there are still many individuals who have difficulties.  They are still dealing with legacy debts from the past.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to help them through that journey and get them back on the right track.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.34" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.10 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re exempted development regulations (ports), referral to committee, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, statements to mark International Day of Persons with Disabilities, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and to conclude not later than 2.15 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given not less than five minutes to reply to the debate; No. 3, Social Welfare (No. 2) Bill 2019 - Second Stage, to be taken at 2.15 p.m., and to conclude not later than 4.15 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given not less than seven minutes to reply to the debate; No. 4, Prohibition of Nuclear Weapons Bill 2019 - all Stages, to be taken at 4.30 p.m. and to conclude not later than 6 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons on the debate on Second Stage not to exceed eight minutes, and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given not less than five minutes to reply to the debate, with Committee and Remaining Stages to be taken immediately thereafter; and No. 5, Private Members' business, Civil Law (Costs in Probate Matters) Bill 2017 - Committee Stage, to be taken at 6 p.m. and to adjourn after two hours, if not previously concluded.</p> <p>I warmly welcome you back, a Chathaoirligh.  It is great to have you back with us in good health.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00300"><p>I thank Senator Buttimer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00400"><p>I echo the sentiments of our esteemed Leader and welcome you back, a Chathaoirligh.  It is wonderful to see you back in your rightful place in the Chair.  I think all of us, right across the Chamber, have missed you and we wish you very well in the future, in particular a very happy Christmas.  This is not scripted as I was not expecting you to be here, but it is great to have you back.</p> <p>There are a few points I want to make and this morning when I was thinking about what I might say, I believe it is reasonable for me to say that I have never played the person in this Chamber nor will I.  I always talk about the issue.  There are many issues on which I could have played the person but I wish to raise the resignation of a Member of the Lower House today and the behaviour in terms of signing in and fobbing in.  While there has been much discussion about the person's entitlement to expenses or otherwise, the reality is that regardless of the expenses, which are far more generous than a lot of other people's because the Member in question is further away, he was being paid a salary of approximately &euro;90,000 a year to do a job and it appears that he has been doing another job, quite effectively it seems, somewhere else yet he was still being paid.  That reflects badly on everybody.  It reflects badly on Fine Gael but it also reflects badly on every single Member of both Houses.  I think there is probably an issue in terms of how people are entitled to their salary and, equally, to their expenses.  I know of a school not too far from where I live where everybody fobs in every morning with his or her fingerprint.  Ten minutes after a student should have arrived in the school, parents get a text to say so and so is not in today if he or she has not fobbed in.  That is fine if such students are at home in bed because they are sick, but if they went off to school in the morning and did not arrive, at least their parents are aware of that and they can do something about it or investigate it further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00500"><p>I would not like the Order of Business to focus on an issue that is happening in the other House.  It is a matter of propriety.  The issue is a matter for the commission.  I know the Taoiseach has commented but I do not want this debate to be a matter of focus here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00600"><p>I acknowledge and appreciate-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00700"><p>I do not mind if Senator Horkan touches on it but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00800"><p>I do not want to cause any stress to you, a Chathaoirligh, on your first day back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G00900"><p>It is not so much a cause of stress, but we have to keep an even keel.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01000"><p>I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01100"><p>I am not sure if it is an issue for the Leader or for the Taoiseach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01200"><p>I accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01300"><p>It is a matter for the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission.  It is perhaps a debate for another House on another day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01400"><p>That may be, a Chathaoirligh.  I appreciate that you get advice, no more than I did when I was in the Chair last night for approximately four and a quarter hours on the Finance Bill.  I appreciate the advice I get.  I will leave it at that but I acknowledge to those looking in on proceedings that it reflects badly on all of us.</p> <p>On a separate matter, it is fantastic that we have even more corporation tax than expected.  It is plugging more holes and more gaps in the system.  I wish the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, well in everything he does.  He does it pretty well.  As Vice Chairman of the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach, I see him a little bit more than most people, as well as his two Ministers of State who ably help him.  To be fair, it is a long time since the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, was in this Chamber himself.  He is a very distinguished former Member of this House.  I ask the Leader to bring in the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, himself.  We see a lot of the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, who is very able, and the Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, but it would be helpful to have the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, here, ideally before Christmas but if not then, soon after that.</p> <p>As somebody who did cycle in this morning, as I regularly do, I think we should have a debate on the benefits to all people of cyclists-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01500"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01600"><p>-----because every cyclist pretty much takes a car off the road.  I am sure the odd person does not have a car but most cyclists also have cars and when they cycle they are not driving a car and clogging up the roads for everybody else.  Equally, they are hopefully improving their health somewhat, as long as they do not get hit by somebody.  Senator Craughwell is not present but he did an exercise recently where he went out on a bike, having not been on one for a long time.  I did not cycle for a long time but I have been cycling for the past eight to ten years.  Once one gets up the courage to do it, cycling is a fantastic way of getting around Dublin.  I encourage everyone in this House, including the Leader, to try cycling, as there are benefits to both the cyclists themselves and everybody else.  A debate with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, or his very able Minister of State, Deputy Griffin, would be very helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01700"><p>It is great to see you, a Chathaoirligh.  Welcome back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01800"><p>I was actually going to call Senator McDowell but he is has decided not to speak, which is his right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G01900"><p>I am happy to give way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02000"><p>I saw a photograph on Facebook a couple of days ago of an event of 20 years ago and I was going to say to him that he has not aged a day, but he did not want to speak.  I still will get my tuppenceworth in.  Senator Gavan should proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02100"><p>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02200"><p>It must be the hairstyle.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02300"><p>It must be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02400"><p>Senator Gavan and Senator McDowell could nearly be mistaken for each other.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02500"><p>Senators should please not interrupt.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02600"><p>That is harsh on him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02700"><p>Is that ideologically or otherwise?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02800"><p>Perhaps otherwise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G02900"><p>We will leave the hair events to the barber and we will move on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#G03000"><p>I wish to raise a serious issue today.  It is one on which I would hope to gain all-party support, namely, the continuing plight of the secretarial assistants who work for each and every one of us in the Seanad.  I was shocked to find out when I came here three and a half years ago that their starting salary was as low as &euro;23,000.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That equates to &euro;428 a week which is a pretty abysmal salary.  They are represented by my union, SIPTU, which put in a pay claim over a year ago that has sat in the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform and no progress is being made.</p><p>I speak on behalf the staff whom I know, but I suspect it must apply to all of the staff, are an exceptional body of people who work extremely hard.  They do, effectively, the same job as personal assistants in the D&aacute;il, by writing speeches, researching and fact-finding.  They have not had a pay increase since 2002.  Is that not shocking?  It is behoves all of us to respect these people and demand action from this Government.  I am saying this in a non-party political way because it is in the interests of the Seanad that we pay people properly.  To be quite clear, these secretarial assistants are not being paid properly at all; they are being paid poorly.  I call on the Minister for Finance to come into the Chamber to debate this issue and I ask the Leader to support this request.  This should not be a secondary issue that we put on the back burner.  We are all guilty of putting this on the back burner for too long, and I include myself in that.</p><p>As a union activist, if I was in their shoes, I would make sure I was a member of the union because SIPTU has negotiating rights.  Moreover, if I did not see progress in the coming weeks, I would ballot for industrial action.  One action that would grab the Minister for Finance's attention would be a picket line outside the Oireachtas and I would stand with our staff.  It should not have to come to that.  These are young professionals who work hard.  At the moment, they have to do eight hours overtime just to try to make ends meet.  A living wage in Dublin is &euro;500 a week and these people are earning &euro;50 less than that each week.  </p><p>I propose that the Houses of the Oireachtas should be a living wage employer and I hope that is something for which we can have all-party support so that anyone working in these buildings, whether they are cleaning, doing professional work or working in the canteen, can at least earn a living wage.  That should be a value to which all of us subscribe.  I ask colleagues to join together and support our secretarial staff and make sure they get the pay rise for which they have been waiting, in some cases, for 15 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#H00200"><p>I welcome the Cathaoirleach back.  I would be intrigued to see the changes that have taken place since the photograph to which he referred was taken; we all need to be depressed from time to time.</p> <p>I echo what Senator Gavan said about the remuneration of staff in the Oireachtas.  We should be mindful of the issues he has raised.</p> <p>I welcome to the Gallery fifth class pupils from St. Pius X girls' national school in Terenure - Ms Barron's class - who are guests of Senator Ardagh.  I know two of the pupils, Lucy Breen and Joni Long, and I hope they enjoy their tour here today.  Also in the Gallery is a young gentleman named Noah Makris who does not attend the girls' national school, for obvious reasons, but who is shortly to go to Carnegie Hall to perform on the double bass.  He is a very talented young man.  I pay tribute to all of those people.</p> <p>I will revert to a theme that I mentioned last week.  I was listening to the radio last night and learned that the House of Representatives in Washington has adopted legislation to place sanctions on the red Chinese Government in respect of what is happening in Xinjiang province where the Uighurs are being herded into concentration camps and treated in an abominable way.  Their human rights are being systematically destroyed, they are being politically brainwashed, told to speak Chinese rather than their native language, and they are, effectively, being kept in until they mend their ways, which means they cease to be Uighur and become more acclimatised as Chinese citizens.  I mentioned to the Leader last week that we need to have the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade here to deal with this issue and to outline the Government's attitude to what is happening in the Xinjiang province and what the Government proposes to do at national, international and EU levels.  We need to clearly express the condemnation of all right-thinking people about what is happening in red China.</p> <p>There is considerable unrest in Hong Kong due to the absence of real democracy in the election of the local assembly.  There are no elections at all worth talking about in red China.  There is one portion of China - Taiwan - where there are free and fair elections and yet we, as a nation, have turned our backs on the area of China where there are free and fair elections, changes of government and freedom of speech for economic reasons, which is shameful.  I would like the Minister to come in and explain clearly what Ireland's position is on this absolute undermining of human rights in Xinjiang province.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#H00300"><p>I welcome the Cathaoirleach back.</p> <p>I join Senator Gavan and others who raised the pay scale for secretarial assistants.  We cannot go into an election without addressing this matter.  I do not know if the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe, realises the work these people carry out, especially secretarial assistants to Independent Senators who do not have party structure.  In such cases, it is just the Senator and a secretarial assistant who provides more than just secretarial assistance.  It is an abuse of staff in a way, and I come in here with a considerable amount of guilt every day watching the workload of Sebastian who works in my office.  I think of Bill that has come through this House from me, successful policy changes within Departments and amendments that have been successfully won in this Chamber.  I might come in and speak on those issues but it is not me who has sat there and worked with the different offices to draft the amendments and worked with the different agencies.  The work that I do as a politician is definitely not of more value than the work that is done by the background staff in my office and I join others in calling for a debate on the issue.</p> <p>I also want to raise a very special football match that is happening tonight.  We were talking about a photograph of Senator McDowell from 20 years ago but I am sure he could still manage to put on a pair of runners and come out and join us on the field tonight.  Oireachtas staff, politicians and journalists are playing against players from a special programme in Clondalkin called the Breakthrough Programme.  The programme recognises that sometimes one needs a masculine route into addressing the issue of mental health.  It was supported by Straight Blast Gym, SBG, in the first year and then the FAI and Shamrock Rovers in the second and subsequent years.  It has combined sport and psychotherapy through group-led activities and has been a huge success for young, disadvantaged males in the Clondalkin area.</p> <p>We are playing tonight's game on the Shamrock Rovers academy ground.  The FAI cup will be there, courtesy of Shamrock Rovers.  We appear to have a full team but things get in the way sometimes.  One of our players, Senator Warfield, has just entered the Chamber.  I hope that people will attend if they have time later.  I have organised food.  This is a great initiative and programme and people can come out to help raise its profile.  Senator Feighan is looking a bit worried.  He is still claiming an injury from three years ago when Kevin Kilbane took him off his feet but we are not going to accept that.  We have six politicians saying that they will play in goal.  I do not think we will be allowed to have six goalkeeping politicians.  If people have a few hours tonight, it would be great to welcome them to Tallaght to be a part of a positive event before Christmas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#H00400"><p>I welcome the Cathaoirleach back; it is good to see him back with us.  I commend all our colleagues who are taking part in Senator Ruane's football match tonight.  It is good to hear about it and may the best team win.</p> <p>I support Senators McDowell, Gavan and Ruane on the issue they have raised about the pay of secretarial assistants in the Seanad.  It is something we have all been aware of and Senator Gavan is correct that we have not been giving it enough attention.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The issue needs to be urgently examined given that the secretarial assistants in the Seanad are on a different pay rate from parliamentary assistants in the D&aacute;il.  There is not an equivalent rate for the Seanad.  We must consider this matter given the workload and the great work being done by all of the secretarial assistants in the Seanad.  Of course, I include in that Ms Ursula N&iacute; Choill who works with me and does an enormous volume of work.</p><p>As Senator Gavan said, SIPTU has raised this issue for some time on behalf of the secretarial assistants.  I raised this issue with my parliamentary party yesterday and I encourage all Senators to do the same with their own groupings and parties.  My party leader, Deputy Brendan Howlin, told me that he has raised the issue on a number of occasions and it is being raised at various levels, particularly at the Sub-Committee on D&aacute;il Reform and so on.  All Members need to push this matter within their groupings and as individuals, which I am happy to do.  I also join others in calling for a debate, in the first instance, but seeking movement on this issue by the Government.</p><p>I join others in calling for a debate on cycling.  I have raised the issue on a number of occasions of facilities for cyclists in the Oireachtas.  Next week there will be a meeting of the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission and I have asked for facilities for cyclists to be on its agenda.  I ask colleagues to support this issue, particularly to raise it with any of their colleagues who are on the commission.  We should have covered cycle facilities in the Oireachtas and we should be seen to encourage cycling instead of an always having an emphasis on car park spaces.  Cycle facilities and promoting cycling are important.  We must be seen to lead on it for all of the health and environmental reasons that have been raised, which is something that I will continue to do as a regular and committed cyclist.</p><p>I refer to the points that Senator McDowell made about China.  I was intrigued to hear him speak about red China.  We have referred to his age on a number of occasions-----   </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J00200"><p>It is the People's Republic of China.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J00300"><p>The term red China seems slightly dated but I jest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J00400"><p>It is not red anymore.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J00500"><p>On a more serious note, the Senator will be glad to hear that the issue of human rights abuses in China has been raised on a number of occasions at meetings of the Joint Committee of Foreign Affairs and Trade, and Defence, of which I am a member.  We hope to have a meeting on such abuses in the new year.  Clearly, the dreadful crackdown on the democracy protests in Hong Kong has been a issue of concern for all of us.  There are Irish students in Hong Kong on exchange programmes who have been affected by this.  I support the Senator raising this concern.</p> <p>Finally, I ask the Leader for a debate on hate speech.  Yesterday, at a meeting of the UN committee on the elimination of racial discrimination in Geneva, the deputy Secretary General of the Department of Justice and Equality is reported to have said that given the recent raising of concerns about speech by different candidates in the by-elections, this State needs to do more on hate speech.  We must bring forward legislation to ensure that we have adequate legislation in place to ensure hate speech is adequately tackled in our laws, which is long overdue.  The University of Limerick has done a great deal of work on the matter, as well as the Irish Council for Civil Liberties and others.  We need to frame the legislation sensitively and clearly to ensure that it is not an undue restriction on freedom of expression.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J00600"><p>I congratulate Senator Ruane on arranging the football match tonight.  It is no harm for us to get out of our bubble and socialise with people, and I congratulate her on connecting us with the Breakthrough Programme.  I look forward to lifting the FAI cup tonight because, as a Sligo Rovers fan, we have lifted it three times in the past 15 years, and there is only one rovers - Sligo Rovers.</p> <p>I welcome the confirmation by the US House of Representatives of its support for the Good Friday Agreement and I thank Tom Suozzi and Peter King.  The House of Representatives has, more or less, acknowledged the shared relationship between the US, the UK and the Republic of Ireland.  They believe that Brexit does not appropriately protect the Good Friday Agreement and threatens to undermine the process.  They have reaffirmed their support for the Good Friday Agreement.  With the British general election coming up, it is nice that our friends in the US have stood up to be counted.  On behalf of the Seanad, I thank them for their support at this time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J00700"><p>I join my colleagues in welcoming the Cathaoirleach back.  I am delighted to see him in the Chair in this new Chamber.  I wish him and his family well.  I was delighted to meet his grandchildren at the turning on of the Christmas lights in Leinster House yesterday.  The Cathaoirleach and the Leas-Chathaoirleach made excellent speeches.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J00800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J00900"><p>I take this opportunity to wish my colleague, Senator Feighan, every success in the next general election.  He will be a very good representative of the people of north Roscommon, Leitrim and Sligo.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J01000"><p>And south Donegal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J01050"><p>And west Cavan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J01100"><p>I thought Senator Leyden was wishing Senator Feighan well with the match tonight.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J01400"><p>I thank Senator Leyden for his good wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J01500"><p>Let him enjoy Christmas first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J01700"><p>Senator Feighan and I reconciled last night at the turning on of the lights when we sang together, and those who sing together, stay together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J01800"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J01900"><p>I generally support Senator McDowell's comments about Taiwan.  There is a representative office of Taipei in Dublin, which was opened many years ago.  It was a compromise to appease the People's Republic of China.  We should have representatives in Taipei.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J02000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J02100"><p>We should have good strong relationships.  I have had the honour of travelling to Taiwan.  I learned that there is an Irish school in Taiwan where hundreds of people study Irish dancing.  Taiwan is a wonderful country with a population of 25 million and it offers great opportunities.  People do not realise that Taiwan has enormous investments in China and, therefore, both countries enjoy a strong business relationship.  We tend to be reluctant to establish an office or base in Taiwan to project into the rest of that region.  When I was a Minister of State with responsibility for trade, I visited the Islamic Republic of Iran, which had an Irish embassy.  We should open the embassy again as there is a significant relationship between the Islamic Republic of Iran and Ireland.  One street is called after an Irish person.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J02200"><p>Bobby Sands.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J02400"><p>Yes, and it is located right beside the British embassy.  We should immediately open an office in Tehran.  When I was a Minister of State, I sold beef from Ireland to Iran.  We brought our veterinary people over and we had a tremendous relationship.  Human rights are vital and the situation in China is very serious.  There is no doubt that we should raise this matter at every opportunity at that level.</p> <p>We have an opportunity now of going into Taiwan, establishing an office and expanding our trade right into China. Taiwan would give us a great foothold in the region.  The expansion of embassies is a marvellous investment because trade is created.  When I was in charge of An Bord Tr&aacute;cht&aacute;la, the embassy was our base to which representatives were invited.  When the President of Ireland goes on a trade mission, there is always a marvellous response to trade.  I agree with Senator McDowell that we should be realistic.  Deputy John McGuiness is chairman of the Friends of Taiwan in Leinster House and our Whip is a close friend of the Taiwanese people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J02500"><p>I thank the Senator for all the advertisements.  I am sure the next major roundabout built in Taiwan will be called the Senator Terry Leyden roundabout.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J02600"><p>I would be pleased.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#J02700"><p>I welcome back the Cathaoirleach; it is great to see him.</p> <p>I support the call for the secretarial assistants issue to be resolved.  Their long years of waiting for a resolution received a muted response from in the House.  I suggest that members of the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission should meet staff representatives to speedily resolve this issue. </p> <p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business.  I believe that the Cathaoirleach is aware of the situation concerning a sarcoma consultant specialist in St. Vincent's Hospital.  In June 2016, the Minister for Health agreed to the post.  We had an excellent consultant at the hospital who specialised in sarcoma but, for some reason, St. Vincent's decided not to extend her locum position.  As a result, the 200 people per year diagnosed with sarcoma are in limbo and, unfortunately, many of them have passed on.  It is a specialist cancer that needs a specialist, which has been agreed.  Two and a half years after an interview, the candidate who was abroad decided not to take up the post.  My patience has been tested.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Moreover, the patients' patience has been more than tested, in that they have lost some of the campaign group through not having specialist experience and knowledge in this regard.  I seek an amendment to the Order of Business to ask the Minister for Health to come to this House.  I have tried six times over the past few months to get him to come here for a Commencement matter.  I know he will probably use the defence that the HSE has no involvement with St. Vincent's, yet it pledges to follow the HSE terms and conditions.  One of those conditions is that a post must be taken up within three months.  I smell something odorous in what is going on here.  Two and a half years is a long time to allow somebody to not make a decision and then make one at the very last minute, leaving vulnerable and very frail patients and those desperate to avail of treatment to which they are entitled.  I ask the Leader to support that amendment. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K00200"><p>I endorse the call for a debate on cycling.  If the Minister comes in, he might also ensure that he is briefed on cycling to school and the equality issues in cycling because very few girls are cycling.  There has been a 90% drop in girls cycling to school in Ireland, which is very unfortunate.</p> <p>I also join Senator Feighan in welcoming the vote by the US House of Representatives.  It is extraordinary that it is unanimous because very few unanimous decisions emerge from that House now.  </p> <p>I endorse the call about the secretarial assistants in the Oireachtas and specifically the Seanad.  An election could have been called yesterday, not that it would have been required.  If we had gone into an election this issue would not have been resolved and it has been pushed for approximately two years.  The secretarial assistants have been actively seeking some form of recognition for their work.  Many of them start on the scale at a salary of &euro;23,000.  It is far less than a living wage.  The scale is extraordinarily low when they start.  There is no way to recognise the experience and skills they bring in.  If, for example, somebody studies for a bachelors degree or a masters in areas such as public policy, which are valuable to us as Members, there is no way to recognise that on the scale because it is set at leaving certificate level although many people come in with extraordinary experience and choose to work with us.  Many have stayed out of loyalty.  It is something to ask people to take five years out of their career for loyalty when they could be progressing.  We need to consider the work of this House.  This House has passed more than 35 amendments on behalf of my group since September, and I am sure other groups have done the same.  Numerous items of Private Members' legislation have passed through this House and gone to the other House.  Two Private Members' Bills have become law.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K00300"><p>We have had two Presidents.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K00400"><p>We have had an extraordinary number of achievements and legislative work.  It is detailed and important work.  The work of tracking legislation and bringing it through takes a year or two.  People may have to see their secretarial assistant move on twice or three times in a term, not out of lack of loyalty or because they do not love the work but because they need to progress, they want to be able to have families or to perhaps get a home.  They should not have to choose between these things.  We really need to make sure action is taken.  The Houses of the Oireachtas Commission has supported the call for action on the pay claim.  Now it sits with the Government and with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  We have all had the experience of brilliant people who are passionate about the work coming in here but having to make the hard choice to leave.  Can we make sure that we try to recognise their work?  Could the Leader try to progress this in any way that is appropriate, including, if appropriate, a discussion in the House?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K00500"><p>I welcome the Cathaoirleach back.  He was missed by all of us.  They were even trying to get me into the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K00600"><p>Get a tie.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K00700"><p>In time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K00800"><p>Get a tie.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K00900"><p>The Senators should not take from Senator Warfield's concentration.  He has an important matter to raise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K01000"><p>I echo the call for a debate on cycling.  I am looking forward to the Oireachtas football match tonight organised by Senator Ruane with the Breakthrough programme, which uses sport to help the mental health and suicide issues in young working-class people.  I hope I do not have to wear a Shamrock Rovers jersey.  We will wear the bibs.</p> <p>I too want to raise secretarial assistants' pay.  Senators are only as good as the support we receive.  Our ability to research and scrutinise legislation, to propose and oppose that legislation, good or bad, can only be measured by the resources available to us.  As good legislators and public representatives, we are entirely dependent on our ability to recruit and retain good-quality staff.  Many Senators will attest to the excellent staff quality but the pay and conditions on offer to them make retention difficult.</p> <p>This is not a case of personal assistants, PAs, or political advisers looking to top up already high wages.  A starting salary of &euro;23,000 a year, that is, a weekly wage of &euro;444 before tax, is not sufficient for anyone living in Dublin.  It is the wage I earned as a councillor.  Councillors get a lot of airtime in this Chamber and rightly so because this is the link between local and national government.  This too should get airtime and today I am glad to hear it being raised by all Senators.  For an institution that saw fit to pay &euro;1.6 million for a printer and all the issues around expenses I would like the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform to respond to the pay claim submitted by SIPTU and the secretarial assistants in October 2018.  I would like the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe, to come to this House to hear the views of Members who can speak of the staff&rsquo;s value and contribution and how their pay and conditions are wholly inadequate. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K01100"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K01200"><p>The amendment proposed was not seconded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K01300"><p>I second it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K01400"><p>I will allow the Senator to do that; not that I am condoning a vote.  I call on the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K01500"><p>While the Leader is composing his thoughts, I welcome the Cathaoirleach back to his rightful position.  He was very much missed by us all.</p> <p>I endorse the comments of Senator Gavan on the staff of this House.  I ask the representatives of this House on the Oireachtas Commission to meet and discuss with representatives of the various political groups what we can do to advance those concerns.</p> <p>I also endorse the comments of Senator McDowell about China, which Senator Leyden also supported.  I would like a debate on that country and our relationship with mainland China.  I know where the Leader's heart lies and from where his comments have to come but I ask for that debate as a matter of urgency. </p> <p>Finally, could the Minister for Education and Skills be brought to the House to update us on the education and training boards, the amalgamation of which in the form of vocational educational colleges, VECs, was intended to save money?  I would like a detailed report on that.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#K01600"><p>Before I call on the Leader, I would like to thank a few people.  On 25 October last, as many Members will know, I had what is called a near-death experience and was fortunate to survive and lucky to be in Dublin when it happened and that my wife spotted me going into a seizure, which I believe was caused by low sodium levels.  I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach for his wonderful work and the Acting Chairmen, who have kept the ship afloat while I was out.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I received a significant amount of good wishes across all parties and none.  I am not sure if I deserved them all but I would like to put on record my grateful thanks to the emergency services.  Sometimes we criticise hospitals here.  Once my daughter dialled 999, they had a specific voicemail helping my son-in-law to do CPR on me at that stage.  The first emergency responders on the scene were the firemen, who I believe were excellent.  I have no memory of it but they were a bit harsh on my ribs and after the event, I felt as it I was in the front row of a scrum in the World Cup but that is part of recovery.  I thank the fire brigade.  I have no names.  I also thank the 999 operator, the ambulance service and in particular, St. James's Hospital, where I went in as a public patient.  I was there for six days and six nights and the treatment I received was second to none.  Some time, when I am in better form, I will go back to thank them for what they did.  We hear a lot about bad situations and cases where there are delays and so on but on 25 October at about midday, all the emergency services saved my life and I want to acknowledge and show respect to them for the wonderful work they do.  Sometimes we never appreciate what the emergency services do but I have many thanks to offer them.  I am not sure if I will ever be able to thank my wife for raising the alarm, because if she had not done or had left the room and left me on my own for 15 minutes, I would have gone to another abode, whichever place I am not sure.  I am back to haunt the House again and I thank Members for their welcome.  It was important to put that on the record because we often hear complaints about and criticism of our emergency responders and the ambulance service.  I have nothing but the utmost and sincerest praise for them and some day, I hope I will be able to thank some of them in person.  With that, I ask the Leader to respond.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#L00200"><p>I thank the 11 Members of the House who contributed to the Order of Business.  I reiterate on my behalf and that of the Members a great welcome back to the House for the Cathaoirleach.  His very genuine words are certainly ones we are glad he could utter in this Chamber.  He was missed, not just because of his impartiality in the Chamber but because of his huge presence.  I join with him in thanking all of the people involved in bringing him back to us today.  Eileen deserves our utmost praise.  It was great to see her here last night to be able to enjoy the turning on of the Christmas lights and to celebrate.  It is important that we recognise the important work done by our first responders and those in emergency departments and the importance of being able to live life.  We wish the Cathaoirleach many more years of being here and being with us.</p> <p>Senators Gavan, Ruane, McDowell, Bacik, Devine, Higgins, Warfield and Wilson made reference to the issue concerning secretarial assistants in the Seanad.  It is important to recognise the important work they do every day and the professionalism they bring to their job on our behalf.  All of us agree on a number of things.  One of them is that the starting point of pay is far too low.  Second, there is a need for either the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform or the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission to look at the role and work of secretarial assistants of Members of Seanad &Eacute;ireann in particular because many of these people now bring a skill set, experience and educational qualification to bear in our offices that must be looked at in terms of just and fair pay.  The role of the Seanad secretarial assistant has changed since it was first introduced in respect of the issue of social media.  Senator Higgins referred to issues on amendments to Bills and being able to write Bills and amendments.  The role has also changed in terms of communication, research and writing press releases, legislation and in many cases, engagement with members of the public and other bodies.  The pay scale is one that has grown beyond what it was.  This then needs to be addressed and I, and all of my colleagues in this side of the House, will support any endeavour that will ensure there is change and movement regarding the pay scale.  Perhaps the Cathaoirleach could guide us in terms of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges of Seanad &Eacute;ireann being able to look at that as way of beginning the process from our position.  It is one on which we will all find unanimity.  </p> <p>Senators McDowell, Leyden, Bacik and Wilson spoke about China and the issue addressed by Senator McDowell around Red China.  I might have missed somebody else.  It is important to recognise that the West embraced China on the pretext that there would be democracy and a greater adherence to human rights and that it would lead to a better democracy.  Many of us recognise that this has not happened to the degree that we would like.  This has manifested itself in the problems in Xinjiang and Hong Kong.  This leads on to the importance of China to this country and to the West.  I know President Trump and the House of Representatives in the US have made a number of issues around that in recent times.  There is a need for an honest debate on our relationship with Taiwan.  If we look back at what has happened since the 1980s in terms of democracy in Taiwan and the movement to a more open and democratic society, we can see that it is a flourishing and positive state.  I personally would support the call to have a representative office in Taipei.  The EU has an office there.  I understand that it is a matter that needs to be addressed by Government.  We have a "One China" policy and I am not going to rehash the debate we had last week.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#L00300"><p>On a point of order, most other European countries also have their own offices in Taipei.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#L00400"><p>I am not sure that it is not a point of order but I think he is trying to clarify something.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#L00500"><p>I would be happy to support that and to have a debate on the matter with the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade.  What goes in tandem with that is the importance of human rights issues and the camps.  I read during the weekend that the Chinese authorities were describing these camps as vocational training camps.  That is the preposterous position they take.  I am happy to support a debate on the matter.</p> <p>Senators Horkan, Higgins and Bacik asked for a debate on cycling, which I would happy to facilitate.  Senator Horkan also made reference to corporation tax.  I will endeavour to have the Minister for Finance come to the House to discuss the matter.  I know it has gone but I welcome the class from St. Pius X boys national school in Terenure and I wish Noah well in Carnegie Hall.  It is a huge honour to be able to say that one played in Carnegie Hall.  Those of us from a certain generation remember the Clancy Brothers and other great Irish acts playing there.  To have a young Irish student playing there is a wonderful honour and we wish him every success.  </p> <p>I congratulate Senators Ruane, Warfield and Feighan on the game tonight.  It is important that sport is a unifier and that we can advocate through sport, particularly with regard to the issue of mental health, and I commend the Senators on participating in the event and wish them well.  It is important that we continue to highlight the issue of mental health.  It is through events like tonight's game that we can shine a visible light on the matter.  </p> <p>Senator Bacik also raised the issue of hate speech.  I would be happy to have that debate in due course.  Senators Feighan and Higgins raised the vote in the House of Representatives last week, which was a wonderful decision to endorse the Good Friday Agreement and as Senator Feighan said, to ensure it is protected in light of Brexit because it is a very important document and it is important that we continue to protect it.  I congratulate all involved in the matter.  </p> <p>To be fair to Senator Devine, she has raised the issue of the sarcoma consultant specialist in St. Vincent's hospital on a number of occasions in the House.  I have met with patient representatives regarding the matter.  It is wholly unacceptable that there is a delay in the appointment of a consultant because, as the Senator rightly said, this is a very specialised cancer that requires a specialist consultant and I support her in this regard.  I am advised that the recruitment process is under way and that as of 8 November, St. Vincent's University Hospital has short-listed candidates for interview.  As the Senator is aware, it is a voluntary hospital with its own board and recruitment policy and has full discretion around the appointment of a consultant.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Rather than divide the House on the matter, I ask the Senator to allow me to try to have the Minister come to the House next week.  The Senator may then call a vote if I am unsuccessful or the Minister is unavailable.  He is not available this afternoon.  It is an important matter and I ask the Senator to work with me, as Senators Humphreys, Leyden and Hopkins did yesterday, and allow me the space to ensure the Minister comes to the House.</p><p>I believed I have addressed all of Senator Higgins's comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M00200"><p>Is Senator Devine pressing her amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M00300"><p>I will not press the amendment, though I am not happy about it.  It has been a long time and this in the interest of patients.  I feel responsible for the people we have lost from sarcoma, as well as the ones still trying to fight with enormous difficulties and ill health.  I do not want to divide the House as I am a reasonable individual.  However, I am disappointed with the way this has gone.  I am aware that it goes beyond the Minister for Health but he needs to put down the strong hand.  I will withdraw the amendment pending the Minister's appearance in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M00400"><p>The Leader has made a fair offer and stated that he will endeavour to bring the Minister in next week.  If that does not occur and I am in the Chair, I will allow the Senator to raise the matter again.  She can push it to a vote at that point if she feels she is not making progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M00500"><p>I think I will call a strike of the Seanad next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M00600"><p>The Senator will not get paid if she does so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M00700"><p>As Senator Devine knows, I am very supportive of the matter she has raised.  I have met with family members and patient advocates in this area and while the situation is unacceptable, it is a matter for St. Vincent's hospital.  However, we will talk about it and endeavour to have the Minister come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M00800"><p>Senator Devine has agreed to withdraw her amendment, under protest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M00900"><p>Under protest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M01000"><p>That has been acknowledged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M01100"><p>She is protesting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.125" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.126" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.127" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M01400">Planning and Development (Amendment) Regulations 2019: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M01500"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:   	Planning and Development (Amendment) Regulations 2019,  a copy of which was laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 2 December, 2019, be referred to the Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government, in accordance with Standing Order 71(3)(<i>k</i>), which, not later than 10 December, 2019, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.&rdquo;  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.129" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.130" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M01700">Message from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#M01800"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Housing (Regulation of Approved Housing Bodies) Bill 2019 on 3 December 2019, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p> <p>Before we suspend, I thank my esteemed Clerk and Clerk Assistant for their patience and endurance with everyone else while I was absent.  They kept the ship afloat, for which I thank them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.132" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.24 p.m. and resumed at 12.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.133" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#O00100">International Day of Persons with Disabilities: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#O00200"><p>I thank Members for the opportunity to speak this afternoon about disability.  It is important that we have these debates to keep the disability issue live in mainstream politics.  I am particularly pleased to have this opportunity in the context of the International Day of Persons with Disabilities, which was marked yesterday.  This is a UN sanctioned day, which is celebrated internationally on 3 December each year.  This year's theme is "Promoting the participation of persons with disabilities and their leadership".  The theme encourages us to work together to ensure that the barriers to full equality and participation for people with disabilities will become a thing of the past.  It focuses on the empowerment of persons with disabilities and recognises disability as a cross-cutting issue.  I will speak about the work that is under way across government to support these overarching principles and objectives.</p> <p>The national disability inclusion strategy, NDIS, is the major framework for policy and action to address the needs of people with disabilities.  It contains 114 measurable and time-specific actions that relate to eight key themes, including education, employment, health and well-being and transport.  Its overarching objective is to improve the lives of people with disabilities in a practical sense and to create the best opportunities for people with disabilities to fulfil their potential.  When I launched the strategy in July 2017, it was never my intention that it would be set in stone for the duration.  The strategy is a living document and must be capable of responding to emerging priorities and developments.  That is why it contained a commitment to a mid-term review.  The aim is to ensure that the strategy remains relevant for the rest of its lifetime.</p> <p>It is always a priority for me to hear the views of people with lived experience and their families and from disability organisations.  It is important, therefore, that the review be informed by a consultation process.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We had two events last month aimed at getting the views of all the stakeholders.  The first was held in Dublin on 13 November 2019 and focused on hearing perspectives of disability organisations, and I attended that myself as Minister of State.  The second event was held on 26 November 2019 in Tullamore and was oriented towards people with disabilities and their families.  The next step is the publication of the consultation report and the development of a refreshed set of actions for consideration by the steering group.  </p><p>As we look forward to renewed strategy, it is important that we acknowledge the achievements that have been realised since the launch in 2017.  These achievements include: the ratification of the UNCRPD, something which was an absolute priority for me and which I was delighted to work on and to help to get over the line; work to facilitate the commencement of the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015, including the codes of practice and the establishment of the decision support service, I will be returning to this later in the debate; publication of the Make Work Pay report, with 24 practical recommendations, many of which have already been implemented; introduction of new ballot papers for referendum to facilitate private voting; introduction of the AIM supports for children accessing the ECCE; the report of the task force on personalised budgets; the development of the three-year plan under the comprehensive employment strategy, which I will be talking about shortly; finalisation of the report on the review of career guidance in schools; and the preparations for the commencement of the Irish Sign Language legislation.  </p><p>While acknowledging these achievements, we also know, and I know, there is more work to do.  I accept that argument.  My vision for what I want to have happen is quite simple.  When the strategy concludes in 2021, my aim is for Ireland to be a better place for people with disabilities to live in, a place that does not tolerate discrimination or exclusion.  It should be a place where people with disabilities are involved and consulted with on matters and decisions that affect their lives.  It should be a country where people with disabilities can enjoy full equality, participate fully in our society and enjoy a quality of life on a par with the rest of the population.  It should also be a country where the focus is not on what people cannot do, but on what they can do, in other words we focus on the person's ability rather than disability.  This is an ambitious vision, but I am confident that the NDIS is capable of triggering real change focused on targeted and specific outcomes.  I look forward to bringing the renewed strategy to Government in January for approval, but I stress also that the strategy success will depend on the shared engagement with all of the stakeholders in building a fairer society.  I look forward to taking an active part with everyone and taking this work forward.  </p><p>Before I conclude, I wanted to return to the area of employment for people with disabilities.  While progress has been made, the rate of unemployment among people with disabilities still remains too high.  According to the results of the census of 2016, there were 130,000 persons with disabilities at work, which represents 6.5% of all people at work, or 22.3% of the total disabled working population of 584,045 people.  People with disabilities are still only half as likely to be in employment as others of working age, so this is a serious issue for me.  That people with disabilities want to work is evidenced from the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection 2015 survey of disability allowance recipients.  It showed that of those people who are not currently working, 35% expressed an interest in working part time while 8% expressed an interest in working in full-time employment.  The Government is committed, and I am committed, to addressing this issue through the implementation of actions under the comprehensive employment strategy for people with disabilities from 2015 to 2024.  I have spoken in this House previously about the strategy, and that is a good opportunity to let the House know that in common with the NDIS, the CES is also going through a period of renewal.  The second phase of the strategy was launched yesterday in the form of a new three-year action plan.  The plan includes a range of actions to advance the six strategic priorities and provide the focus for the work on the implementation group for the next period in the lifetime of the strategy.  The aim is to consolidate progress made in the last number of years and to start to deliver real results.</p><p>One of the areas that has been identified for particular focus is the next phase of the CES in strategic priority 6, "Engaging Employers".  This is why one of the key initiatives in the new action plan is a planned multi-faceted awareness campaign to promote awareness among employers and other stakeholders of the opportunities represented by employees with disabilities.  This programme will include capacity building for employers and positive action measures to support the recruitment and retention of people with disabilities in employment.  I have to say some employers have shown great examples of good practice regarding this particular issue.  </p><p>The key issue in relation to the disability inclusion strategy and the employment strategy is setting worthwhile targets and ensuring Departments and agencies work together to deliver on them.  That is not about money or extra money, but of course money is important too.  It is also changing mindsets of all of us, both those with a disability and without.  The mindset has to change in the broader society.  When one sees somebody with a disability, one sees beyond the wheelchair or the cane.  One sees the person and all that he or she can bring to one's workforce.  Equally, for those with a disability, do not label oneself or allow oneself to be labelled.   A person's disability is but a part of him or her.  It must never define him or her.  The Government, through the HSE, is committed to protecting frontline services for people with disabilities with targeted improvement and identified priority areas.  The national service plan in 2019 provides for a significant level of funding of &euro;1.9 billion to deliver essential frontline services for people with disabilities.  </p><p>These core services span a spectrum of essential interventions, ranging from the clinical therapeutic support to the rehabilitative and training and day services, homecare support, as well as respite and residential provision.  All funded service providers, including non-clinical service delivery focused organisations, are required to deliver safe and effective services within a defined budget allocation.  The HSE must also ensure that it prioritises available resources on the basis of meeting the health and social needs of all people with disabilities.  Our current policy promotes a non-condition specific approach to disability service provision based on the needs of the individual rather than on the provision of services based on a specific disability diagnosis.  A Programme for a Partnership Government commits this Government to improving services and increasing supports for people with disabilities.  Significant resources have been invested by the health sector in services for people with disabilities over the past number of years.  In terms of health spending, substantive expenditure has been agreed in recent budgets to support increased provision for people with disabilities and their families.  I am pleased that we have been able both to build upon significant existing resources and to obtain additional funding for disability services in the budget 2020.  We are in the middle of this process at the moment with the HSE service plan.  With these additional moneys secured, the overall budget for disability and services in 2020 is in excess of &euro;2 billion.  That is right: &euro;2 billion.  The increased level of funding in 2020 will enable us to continue to provide residential support to over 8,600 people with disabilities at more than 1,240 locations.</p><p>Upon taking office, one of my priorities was to ensure that all young adults leaving school or rehabilitative training would have access to supports and services which meet their needs at one of the most critical transition points of their lives.  Additional funding of &euro;13 million will provide supports and day services to approximately 1,600 young people with disabilities who leave school and training programmes next year.  I recognise the critical importance of respite for loved ones and families of those with a disability.  I am pleased to confirm that an additional &euro;5 million will be provided in 2020 to build on the capacity of our respite services so that we can respond to the changing needs of service users and their families.  Specifically, this funding will provide intensive support packaged for children and young people in response to the changing needs of service users and their families.  This initiative will include intensive in-home visiting support, planned overnight, specialist behavioural support and extended day weekend and day-based activities for families.  </p><p>Sl&aacute;intecare is centred around providing services and support at the lowest level of complexity.  An additional &euro;5 million in this budget is provided for the emergency protocol to support people with disabilities who have high support needs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This includes funding for emergency placements and the provision of intensive home support and respite packages, which are intended to delay the need for residential care for vulnerable users.  Finally, an additional &euro;2 million will be provided in 2020 to support the implementation of the autism plan, which includes a range of measures to improve services for people with autism and their families.</p><p>I thank the Acting Chairman for facilitating the debate and look forward to the contributions of Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Q00200"><p>As there are no Members from Fianna F&aacute;il or the Independent Group present, I invite Senator Conway to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Q00300"><p>I will give way to Senator Devine if she would like to begin.  The usual protocol, Acting Chairman, is that an Opposition Member goes first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Q00400"><p>That is fine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Q00500"><p>We are the real Opposition.  Members of the other Opposition are absent, which is not unusual.  I thank Senator Conway for giving way, which is decent of him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Q00600"><p>It is very democratic and inclusive here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Q00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State back to the House.  Any criticisms I make relate to issues which I am very concerned to see resolved, and that can only happen through genuine dialogue and commitment to achieving full equality for citizens living with a disability.  There are 643,000 such people in this country as well as 200,000 unpaid carers.</p> <p>Two weeks ago, when the Minister of State was present for statements on disability services, we asked that he intervene to allow for time to work out a solution to prevent the closure of the Cuisle centre in County Roscommon.  I realise there are issues involving the Irish Wheelchair Association, IWA, but the Minister of State was asked in this House, the other House and by protestors outside Leinster House to intercede.  Even a six-month or 12-month delay would allow time to work out the difficulties and that would mean a great a deal to those affected.  I welcome his increased budget for next year but it is a pity he cannot borrow from it to secure the continued operation of the Cuisle facility.  The protestors stressed how unique their situation is, which is based on the particular offering Cuisle provides to its users.  They told the Minister of State how no hotel could possibly provide the facilities and, most important, the privacy and independence available to families at Cuisle.  There was a major show of support for the centre in County Roscommon, which should have left no one in any doubt how vital this service is.  I ask the Minister of State to ensure this matter remains on the agenda and is not forgotten.</p> <p>I wish to highlight the progress that has been made by the Oireachtas disability group, which brings together politicians of all parties and five major disability advocacy groups.  Its job is to provide a vital link between the needs of persons with a disability and the services that are delivered.  I commend the work of Senator John Dolan and my colleague, Deputy John Brady, in this regard.</p> <p>In March last year, 20 years after Ireland signed the UNCRPD, the Government finally ratified the convention.  This was an important and welcome decision, albeit many years late.  Sinn F&eacute;in stressed at the time that ratification was only a first step and that the real measure of delivery in respect of the rights contained in the convention would be in its implementation.  Sadly, the Government did not ratify the optional protocol to the convention, as it had promised.  We have consistently pressured the Government since March last year to do so and to progress delivery of the hope and promise of the convention as speedily as possible.  However, the process has been slow.  For example, almost two years after legal effect was given to the official recognition of Irish Sign Language, we still have not seen the required resourcing for its full and anticipated promotion and development.</p> <p>We need to see rights made real  For this to happen, provision and resourcing must go hand in hand with the announcements that are made to great fanfare by the Government.  Sinn F&eacute;in is acutely aware of this requirement, as reflected in the provision in our alternative budget for 2020 for 1.5 million personal assistant hours.  The Minister of State and his Government have the power to make rights real for people with disabilities.  I urge him to step up to the plate and champion the cause.  He has little time left to make his mark.</p> <p>Implementation of the Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015 is at a standstill.  Funding is needed for its full implementation, and the measures it contains require speedy advancement.  On International Day of Persons with Disabilities, I urge the Government to make this work a priority in early 2020 and to make good on the promises it has so far failed to keep.  One of the bodies involved in the Oireachtas disability group is Independent Living Movement Ireland.  The ability to control and organise one's life independently is essential to restoring dignity to those living with a disability.  Yesterday, a report by Inclusion Ireland stated that more than 2,000 people with intellectual disabilities are still living in institutional settings, despite Government policy that all such facilities were to close by the end of 2018.  The housing adaptation grants administered by local authorities are gone as soon as they are announced because the waiting list is so long.  I have spoken here previously about the 18 year old man I met in St. James's Hospital three years ago.  He went in not feeling great and was given an awful diagnosis of a degenerative disease, which saw him swiftly progress to a lack of mobility and having to use a wheelchair.  His only option, because the grants were not available either for people in private homes or in social housing, was to go into a nursing home.  He has been there for two years, surrounded by much older patients, and his situation is dire.  Other young people are ending up in the same situation, where a nursing home is the only facility available.  The local authority adaptation grants scheme must be given additional funding.  We need to view this from a rights perspective in that these are citizens whose rights are being denied.</p> <p>On International Day of Persons with Disabilities, I extend my best wishes to those living with disability in Ireland and their family members.  There are 643,000 people with disabilities in the State and 200,000 unpaid carers.  I also extend good wishes to the wider advocacy sector, which works hard on behalf of all who depend on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Q00800"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank the Leader for his assistance in facilitating the request from Senator Dolan and myself to mark International Day of Persons with Disabilities in the Seanad.  Senator Dolan asked me to convey his apologies for being unable to attend the debate.  We have worked closely together on this issue and I remind colleagues of the important legislation he has presented to the House.  Will the Minister of State indicate whether he has made any progress in considering those proposals before we proceed to Committee Stage?</p> <p>This is a day to celebrate people with disabilities.  However, in doing so, we must also reflect on the many barriers society places to their well-being and active participation.  It is a source of significant disappointment that despite clear communication by the disability community of its requirements, budget 2020 did not deliver any of the shared ambitions expressed.  The statistics illustrate starkly that the recession continues for people with disabilities.  Some 24% of adults with a disability live in consistent poverty, compared with 11% in 2011.  Disabled people in Ireland are four times less likely to be employed than those without a disability.  Just 31% of working-age people with a disability are at work, compared with 71% of the general population.  People with disabilities who are capable of living independent lives are trapped in their homes, residential homes or nursing homes due to a lack of personal assistance services and home supports.  More than 1,400 are living in nursing homes, many of whom could live independently with the right supports.  In other cases, parents are providing unsustainable support into their 70s, 80s and beyond.  In a small recent sample of just 18 organisations, 183 people were reported to be living with a carer aged over 80.</p> <p>There is an unprecedented crisis in disability services, with many struggling to maintain existing service levels.  The sector is struggling with a &euro;40 million shortfall in funding due to austerity cuts that have not been reversed, the additional costs of compliance and regulation, an ageing infrastructure, and general inflationary cost increases as the economy continues to grow without an equivalent increase in State funding for the services provided.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Ruane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2481"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2481&amp;amp;pid=LynnRuane&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In addition, there is a growing level of unmet need, which calls into question the value the State places on services and, more important, how it prioritises the rights of people who need such services.  Insufficient money is being spent to support people to live independently in their community.  Only 0.3% of people with disabilities receive a personal assistance service under the HSE service plan.  As far back as 1996, it was identified that an average of ten hours of personal assistance per person per week could only respond to essential personal care needs and not quality of life requirements.  Certainly, it would not enable full participation in the community.  There is no current legal right to personal assistance in Ireland.  However, on 19 November, a motion on the right to a personal assistant unanimously passed in the D&aacute;il.  We can build on it in 2020.</p><p>There remain significant obstacles and barriers in everyday life for people with a disability.  Daily, people struggle to access vital healthcare, housing, education and supports.  Figures show that one in four people with a disability lives in consistent poverty.</p><p>Many of the issues I have raised are not in line with the UNCRPD, which Ireland ratified in 2018.  It is important that the State provides leadership and takes measures to address these issues, whether through budgetary measures, legislative reforms, the implementation of proactive policy initiatives and programmes or all of the foregoing.  The important role played by Ireland internationally in supporting disability rights should be noted, as should the importance of campaigns such as the "Put us in the Picture" campaign run by Sightsavers Ireland.  These have led to disability rights being a central focus of Ireland's overseas aid contribution and coincided with the refresh of Government's international development policy, A Better World.  It is vital that this approach be maintained, given that 80% of the estimated 1 billion people with disabilities throughout the world live in low or middle income countries.  We should be proud of the State's foreign policy in this area.</p><p>Among the main areas that need to be addressed to meet our obligations under the UNCRPD and the NDIS is that people with disabilities have an equal right to live in the community with choices equal to others, as outlined in Article 19 of the convention.  The State must take effective and appropriate measures to facilitate this right and the full inclusion and participation of people with disabilities in their community.  The public sector equality and human rights duty imposes a statutory obligation on public bodies to have regard to the need to eliminate discrimination, promote equality of opportunity and treatment, and protect human rights.  Furthermore, Article 5 of the UNCRPD requires states parties to take appropriate steps to ensure reasonable accommodation is provided to promote equality and eliminate discrimination.  As per Article 9 of the UNCRPD, states parties to the convention to ensure that people with disabilities have access on an equal basis with others to the physical environment, transportation, information and communications, including information and communication technologies and systems, and other facilities and services open or provided to the public in urban and rural communities.</p><p>The articles of the UNCRPD are interconnected; to realise one, the others must also be realised.  As Departments respond to the obligations placed on them by the convention, they need to develop a cross-departmental focus.  Although one Department may need to take the lead on delivering an action, collaboration from the outset on planning the service will be required for it to be effective.  Cross-departmental collaboration will be required to fully implement the principles of the UNCRPD and bring them to fruition.</p><p>The theme of this important day is the promotion of the participation of persons with disabilities and the development of their leadership, acting on the 2030 development agenda.  It calls for the empowerment of persons with disabilities regarding the decisions that affect them, which is key in the Irish context.  I was, therefore, concerned to learn yesterday that the National Platform of Self Advocates will close in January due to a lack of funding.  It is exactly the sort of organisation we need to align with the theme of this International Day of Persons with Disabilities.  What actions can be taken to support such groups in the future?</p><p>What progress has been made towards ratifying the optional protocol to the UNCRPD, which allows for individuals to lodge complaints against Ireland with the UN?  It is needed to give teeth to this conversation.  What is the status of the only disability legislation brought forward by the Government, namely, the Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2016?  It has been before the D&aacute;il for three years but has progressed no further than Committee Stage.  On a day such as today, we need to reflect on the progress we have achieved for people with disabilities over the past year.  I ask the Minister of State to update the House on my queries on the Government's plan to further address issues affecting people with disabilities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#R00200"><p>T&aacute; f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it go dt&iacute; an Teach.  It is always a pleasure to have him in the House.  His address referred to the interesting theme of this International Day of Persons with Disabilities, which is the participation of people with disabilities in leadership.  I have always adopted a positive disposition.  I believe in looking at the glass as half full.  As a Senator with a disability, I like to think that having people with disabilities in politics pays testament to the theme of the International Day of Persons with Disabilities.</p> <p>We have made significant progress in the past two decades as a result of many organisations lobbying, working hard, collaborating and developing and delivering policies.  When I went to school in integrated education in County Clare, there were no SNAs or resource teachers.  A visiting teacher who specialised in vision impairment came to the school for an afternoon once a year.  The required supports did not exist then, but they do now.  There are more than 10,000 SNAs, and rightly so, because it allows people to reach their potential at an early age.  By and large, they do a good job.  The system should be structured slightly differently in certain cases.  As a young person gains in confidence and develops his or her abilities and skills base, he or she may not necessarily need as many hours of support from an SNA or resource teacher.  In such a circumstance, the support provided should be reduced because doing so will allow the young person to develop his or her independence.  Our goal is for people with disabilities to be independent.  Interventions and the usage of SNAs and resource teachers need to be constantly monitored.  Just because a young person receives ten or 15 hours of support for the first five or six years of his or her educational cycle does not mean it is needed for the final phase of the cycle.  The structures within education need to be constantly calibrated and considered because the first leg in equipping people to be independent is through educating them and allowing them to develop their skills base, whether in the world of academia, apprenticeships or elsewhere.</p> <p>I am regularly contacted by people with disabilities who wish to discuss their experiences and what they wish to achieve, and who seek suggestions and advice and so on.  I try to give them and their parents support because those of us who have been successful in our careers have a duty to reach out to others, provide reassurance and make the pathway easier for them.  I refer to how the political system has responded to the quest for equality to which every citizen rightly aspires.  When I started in politics in 2004, the notion of a Minister of State with specific responsibility for disability issues sitting at the Cabinet table was often discussed, but it was an aspirational goal.  There have been very good Ministers of State with specific responsibility for disability since I was elected to the Oireachtas in 2011.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I remember the work Kathleen Lynch tried to do at a time when we were very challenged economically and the country was broke in many ways.</p><p>To be fair to the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, and his group of Independents, they made it a priority to have a Minister of State with responsibility for disabilities sitting at the Cabinet table.  He met a Fine Gael Party that had evolved into believing in that position in no small way because of the constant highlighting at parliamentary party level and with party leadership of the necessity for this to happen.</p><p>In 2016 two willing participants joined and we got a Minister of State with specific responsibility for disability at the Cabinet table with an interdepartmental brief to stress-test every decision made at Cabinet from a disability perspective.  Things get done by being at Cabinet, the epicentre of where decisions are made.  We are very fortunate to have the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, who has personal experience of how disability affects people's lives.  He has been there for more than three years and knows that opportunities can be denied if it is not properly structured.</p><p>A further step in the political cycle and a coming of age came when Deputy Varadkar became Taoiseach.  I had had many discussions with him over 20 years, prior to his becoming Taoiseach.  He and I both became local authority members on the same day and were involved in Young Fine Gael prior to that.  We have had countless discussions on how to break down the barriers to equality, and what practical structures can be put in place to allow people to achieve their potential.  In his first speech as leader of Fine Gael, on the eve of becoming Taoiseach, he spoke extensively about disability in the Mansion House.  He spoke about the need to ratify the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, not in an aspirational timeline but in a very tight timeline.  Working with the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, that happened by the end of 2017.</p><p>There have been incremental positive steps, reflecting not just our international responsibilities, but also our moral and ethical responsibilities.  That by no means suggests the job is done - far from it.  Too many people with disabilities, who have benefited from a good education, remain unemployed.  I know there are strategies seeking to address that.  While progress is being made, it is painstakingly slow.  The first cog in giving people independence is giving them a job, which gives them a way to contribute to society and earn a living from contributing to society.  That breaks down more barriers than one could ever imagine.  The next time the Minister of State comes to the Chamber to speak on disabilities, I would like him to specialise on the area of employment and how we might work together.  He was here two weeks ago to respond on my Private Members' motion on the need for eye clinical liaison officers in our hospital groups.  I am very confident that as a result of that motion we will see eye clinical liaison officers in our hospitals.  That is another cog in equipping people for independence.</p><p>We need to remember that our population is ageing, meaning that an increasing number of people will have disabilities.  This is good government, proper government and what should happen.  I sincerely hope it will become a natural form of government to have a Minister of State with responsibility for disabilities at the Cabinet table.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#S00200"><p>Yesterday was International Day of Persons with Disabilities and today we recognise those living with disability.  This is the 28th year that the world has observed the International Day of Persons with Disabilities.  This year's theme focuses on the empowerment of persons with disability for inclusive and sustainable development.  The United Nations 2030 agenda for sustainable development pledges to leave no one behind.  Unfortunately, too many people in Ireland are still being left behind.  The survey on income and living conditions published last week showed that households with people not at work due to illness or disability are particularly vulnerable to poverty and social exclusion.</p> <p>Almost seven years have passed since the mobility allowance was discontinued and we are still awaiting a new scheme.  Progress in expanding personal assistance has been far too slow with the number of hours provided to people with disability considerably short of what is needed.  The number of children, whose assessments under the Disability Act 2005 are overdue, has increased by 15% this year.  Thousands of children are waiting far too long for essential therapy services and assessments.</p> <p>The Government has ignored repeated warnings about a funding crisis in the disability sector.  The independent review group established to examine the role of voluntary organisations in health and social services found that two thirds of disability services are provided by the voluntary sector.  They are enduring a funding crisis and there is concern about the viability of many of these organisations.</p> <p>Waiting lists for assessments and intervention have been allowed to spiral out of control under Fine Gael and there are serious issues with staffing and access to residential care.  This combination is resulting in families waiting months and in some cases years for help.</p> <p>People not at work due to illness or disability are particularly vulnerable to poverty and social exclusion.  The latest data demonstrate that there is no recovery for many people not at work due to an illness or a disability.  People with disabilities are not feeling the effects of economic recovery, and have poverty and deprivation rates significantly above the national average.  It is imperative that the Government gets to grips with this issue and addresses why the at-risk-of-poverty rate for this group remains stubbornly high and is going in the wrong direction.</p> <p>The situation is further compounded by the Minister of State's insistence on pointing to the disabled drivers and passengers scheme as a viable alternative and workable support for those with mobility issues.  The reality is starkly different.  The Minister of State is fully aware that the Ombudsman has raised serious concerns about the equity of this scheme.  People with serious disabilities are being told they do not qualify for the scheme due to the stricter criteria.  Furthermore, the Minister for Finance has confirmed that he has no intention of changing the criteria for the scheme despite the Ombudsman having raised this red flag with him.  I have grave concerns about this and the Minister of State needs to address them.</p> <p>I ask for the Minister of State's assistance in the case of a young girl from Carlow who was left paralysed from the chest down following a car accident in County Laois last year.  She has a severed spinal cord and she will never walk again.  Two year old Amira Anne O'Toole Rough is currently in Temple Street Hospital.  Her mother, Caroline, contacted me this week as she is at her wits' end over her daughter's care.</p> <p>Her medical team and her mother differ on the child's treatment and now she feels that her daughter. having been fitted with a tracheal tube against her family's wishes. is trapped without adequate provision for rehabilitation or the possibility of a home care package in her native Carlow because of this intervention.  </p> <p>Amira could attend rehabilitation in the UK but because she has an older sibling he cannot be left at home.  Ultimately, Amira's mother, who herself is suffering from post-traumatic stress from the accident, would like her daughter to receive rehabilitation in Ireland.</p> <p>Currently Amira's family is seeking legislation for children with severe needs such as Amira for the right to have rehabilitation care in Ireland </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#S00300"><p>The Senator should not really be naming somebody.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#S00400"><p>No bother.  I asked for and got permission from the mother.  There are no supports for children with a tracheal tube in Ireland.  The local community has, as usual, been faultless with its support but these families should not have to do this.  Nobody should be in such circumstances where they need to be fighting for this.</p> <p>Access to rehabilitation can offer the best chance of recovery for someone like Amira to live the best quality of life which maximises her full potential and ability.  To force her to travel to the UK for treatment at such a young age is wrong.  There is an appalling lack of rehabilitation services in this country for those who have suffered life-changing injuries, for those who have had brain injuries and for those suffering from mental health issues requiring rehabilitation through no fault of their own.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2470"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2470&amp;amp;pid=JenniferMurnaneOConnor&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have got to look at this.  There was a plan in Sl&aacute;intecare to look at this very issue and I hope my message today will be heard loud and clear that we have to examine funding for rehabilitation so those with acquired disabilities will reach a full life.  It worries me that the mother in this case has made several attempts to meet with the HSE and it has refused her.  I would like the Minister of State to set up that meeting.  That is unfair on the child's mother and the family.</p><p>I also want to ask the Minister of State about another issue.  I addressed this in the Seanad last week when the Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, attended.  I contacted the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, as I know did the Minister of State, Deputy Byrne, about confirmation of the &euro;62,000 for Holy Angels in Carlow to keep the centre going.  There has also been a new plan for a school and I want to know the update on that plan.  The HSE has made land available at Kelvin Grove for the new centre.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T00200"><p>That is not really relevant to the debate we are having.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T00300"><p>It is about disability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T00400"><p>Perhaps it is something that the Senator could talk to the Minister of State about afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T00500"><p>I could not get him last week so I have to take the opportunity now when he is here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T00600"><p>It is not appropriate.  The Senator can engage with him on that issue afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T00700"><p>The Senator should put down a Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T00800"><p>The problem is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T00900"><p>Senator Conway, please stay out of this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T01000"><p>I am just trying to be helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T01100"><p>Can Senator Murnane-O'Connor please address that issue with the Minister of State privately afterwards?  It is not relevant to this debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T01200"><p>I have.  The Minister of State has always been courteous.  However, we need to look at Commencement matters because the Ministers we are looking for at the time through no fault of their own are never able to attend.  That is the biggest issue.  If we could get the Ministers we require to be here when we put in the Commencement matter, we would not be bringing up issues that we need to see the Minister for.  That is something the Cathaoirleach needs to address.  I thank the Minister of State for being here today.  That &euro;62,000 is vital for Holy Angels.  I wrote to the Minister of State about it and I will meet with him when this is over.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#T01300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  It is welcome this week that we are marking International Day of Persons with Disabilities, which was yesterday.  It is a United Nations day aimed at promoting the rights and well-being of people with disabilities in all spheres of society and development, and increasing awareness of the situation of persons with disabilities in every aspect of political, social, economic and cultural life.  It is worth remembering the purpose of the day when we are reflecting on the current state of society for persons with disabilities here in Ireland.  I have listened to the other contributions and acknowledge the work done on this issue by our colleagues, particularly Senator Dolan, whom Senator Ruane rightly commended for his unstinting work in highlighting issues for persons with disabilities and inclusion and equality since the start of his time in this Seanad in 2016.  I also acknowledge Senator Conway, who has really been to the fore on this issue for Fine Gael.</p> <p>As Senator Conway says, undoubtedly we should acknowledge the immense progress that has been made on advancing the rights of persons with disabilities in recent years.  In schooling and education we now have much greater resourcing and recognition of the need to ensure supports for children with additional needs and to ensure accommodation for persons with disabilities in education.  That is fairly well established.  We also have increased awareness about inclusion, which is part of the United Nations aim, through initiatives like those which others have mentioned, the exhibition that was launched yesterday, Someone Like Me at City Hall, and the Purple Lights campaign that has been promoted by the Disability Federation of Ireland.  The Labour Party website went purple yesterday to mark the Purple Lights campaign.  These are all important initiatives to enhance and increase visibility.  I am a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade and we have pushed to ensure that there is inclusion of disability and disability-proofing in our international development programmes.  I commend Irish Aid and the Government's work on that issue.  That is all positive.</p> <p>I note that the Minister of State has also referred to highlights and milestones that the Government has reached.  However, it has to be said that there is still a significant gap in achievement and some really serious issues are being raised.  The Minister of State mentioned the issue of employment of persons with disabilities.  He cited the figures from census 2016 that only 22.3% of the total disabled working population is in work.  It is a stark figure.  People with disabilities are still only half as likely to be in employment as others of working age.  Clearly that is a major concern, particularly when the theme of yesterday's United Nations day was promoting the participation of persons with disabilities and their leadership, taking action on the 2030 development agenda.  A key component of that must be the support and promotion of workplace opportunities for persons with disabilities and clearly that is somewhere we are falling down.  I ask the Minister of State to address this in the work that is being done on the national strategy, which is most important.  Senator Conway has also rightly highlighted it.</p> <p>Another glaring issue that has been raised in this House on a number of occasions, even just in recent weeks, is the issue of funding for disability groups, NGOs and those who are providing essential services and supports.  We had a debate in this House on the Save Cuisle campaign, which was raised by colleagues on all sides of the House.  It is very worrying to see the closure of a crucial respite centre in the west.  Just yesterday we saw the launch of the Disability Action Coalition, which seeks to highlight how rising insurance costs threaten the future survival of disability organisations.  That is a particular issue and I would like the Minister of State to address it in his response.  I was shocked to see the figures.  Enable Ireland says its insurance premium this year alone rose by &euro;100,000.  We know the impact of rising premiums on small businesses.  We have had debates on that and are well aware of it.  This is a really particular issue for disability organisations.  When budget 2020 was announced in October, the Disability Federation of Ireland highlighted the more general issue of the lack of funding for disability groups and indeed referred to persons with disabilities as the forgotten vulnerable, given that the budget, as they said, will not alleviate the fact that the number of those with disabilities who are in poverty has increased.  These are really serious problems that need to be addressed.</p> <p>Senator Ruane referred to the impending closure, announced yesterday, of the National Platform of Self Advocates.  We are seeing signs of organisations closing.  We all received an email about that.  I am not sure if the Minister of State received the same email.  These are worrying developments at a time when there should be funding available for these groups and organisations.  It links closely with the promotion of opportunities in the workplace and in employment for persons with disabilities.  It is crucial that we see organisations that are adequately funded that can provide the necessary supports.  I had the pleasure and privilege of being invited to speak recently with a group of young people with Down's syndrome as part of Down Syndrome Ireland training and to hear from them about their experiences in the workplace, the difficulty some of them have experienced in getting work but also about the enormous pleasure and satisfaction and indeed the importance of receiving a pay package that comes with being employed.  As others have said, there are some really notable employers that are doing a lot across the country to ensure opportunities for those with disabilities and that have really strong positive action programmes.  There are private sector organisations delivering but we need to ensure that organisations like Down Syndrome Ireland which provide the necessary training and supports for young people and all those with disabilities seeking to enter the workplace are adequately funded so they can continue to provide training programmes.</p> <p>I refer also to the welcome ratification by Ireland last year of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  The Minister of State referred to it.  I commend the ratification but I also wish to ask when we will be in a position to ratify the optional protocol, which I understand has not yet been ratified and which would enable individuals to make complaints against Ireland at the UN Committee on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  That is an important part of the international legal framework for recognition and acknowledgement of the rights of persons with disabilities.  It is unfortunate that we have not yet been in a position to ratify it.  Last year the Minister of State told the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Justice and Equality that he hoped to ratify as soon as possible but at the latest in two or three years' time.  That is clearly beyond any projected lifetime of this Government.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Following last night's vote in the D&aacute;il, the lifetime of this Government is looking increasingly short.  Nobody is putting it at any longer than five or six months from now.  It is a worry that we will not see ratification of the optional protocol in the lifetime of this Government, unless the Minister of State can enlighten us further on it.  It is important when marking International Day of Persons with Disabilities that we note the importance of ensuring there are transnational frameworks in place through which people who are still suffering discrimination and exclusion and who are not getting the equal opportunities that others get have a mechanism for making complaints under the convention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#U00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State and his officials.  He is always willing to come to the House when he is invited.  I will not repeat everything that has been said.  It is fitting to have this debate and hear the contributions of Members, given that the International Day of Persons with Disabilities is this week.</p> <p>The Minister of State referred to the NSID, which we all welcome.  There is no question that we all want the best opportunities for people with disabilities.  As Senator Bacik said, we welcome the fact that the Government ratified the UNCRPD.  We spoke on it and supported it on numerous occasions, and I commend Senators John Dolan and Martin Conway on their contributions.  I also welcome the &euro;2 million the Minister of State mentioned for the autism plan.  I do not know if it is enough and I would love to hear his opinion on that.  Senator Reilly introduced a Private Members' Bill in the House dealing with autism.  Is that included in the plan for the &euro;2 million in 2020?</p> <p>I commend the Government on having a Minister of State with responsibility for disabilities at the Cabinet table.  It is very important.  I commend the Minister of State on many measures but despite all the measures that I consider to be positive, I am concerned about one matter all the time, which I have mentioned to him previously.  I do not like using the particular phrase but it has been quoted to me so I will use it.  Services for people with disabilities are considered to be low hanging fruit, and when money has to be cut, it is cut from disability services.  I am being parochial in referring to CHO 8, but it is my local CHO and it covers counties Laois, Offaly, Longford, Westmeath and part of Meath.  Life plans are drawn up for people with disabilities, be they intellectual or physical disabilities, and people who need a personal assistant.  The occupational therapist, psychologist or whomever draws up business plans and presents them to the HSE for funding so people can live in their homes and communities, where they want to live, and should live.  These business plans take time to complete.  People have to be assessed and it all costs money.  The business plans are written and submitted to the HSE, but they are either unanswered or the answer is "No".  There is something wrong.  We must examine how these budgets are spent, and the Minister of State can do this.</p> <p>I am dealing with a case involving a gentleman who has mild intellectual disability and a physical disability.  He is starting to struggle and his family is struggling to look after him at home.  He needs residential care.  We do not want people in residential care and prefer to move them into the community, but there are situations where they need residential care.  It should be in small settings that are suitable for them, not vast settings that are unsuitable.  This gentleman needs that and I am aware of a service that likely could help with this.  If there was a little jigging about with a budget, this service could provide a service for this gentleman and a couple of others.  It requires an open mind about budgets and how they are divvied out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#U00300"><p>Flexibility.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#U00400"><p>Yes, a little flexibility.  This is something we must examine.  Staff in the HSE have been very helpful to me and are trying to support me to get the result I seek, but this is something we should examine overall to ensure there is flexibility in budgets.  If a little tweaking was done, the service I know could provide services for others as well.  It is a domino effect where one moves a person into one house and one moves somebody else out to facilitate him.  All of that could be done if there was flexibility.  Perhaps the Minister of State will examine that.</p> <p>I commend him on his work.  It comes from his heart and I respect him for that.  However, we must examine the budgets, how they are spent and the flexibility thereafter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#U00500"><p>I thank Senators for their contributions.  They have a genuine interest and regularly attend these debates.  I always make it my business to come to the House to deal with this issue.  Plenty of people have different issues and problems, but that is my job and I have no problem with that.  I thank all Members for their genuine interest and for advancing the position of people with disabilities in society.  That is very relevant and we see that today.</p> <p>In addition to the various matters I mentioned earlier, Senators will be interested in the progress on meeting the terms of the CRPD.  My approach and that of the Government is one of sustained and ongoing improvement.  Work is continuing on the reforms needed for optimum compliance with the Government's requirements.  As an Independent Alliance member of the Government, I particularly thank Senators Conway and McFadden for their support on the UN convention.  I would not have got it through the Cabinet without that support.  I thank them because that was essential.  However, it is only the start as far as I am concerned.</p> <p>I will go through the issues and then return to matters concerning individuals.  First, we will consider ratifying the optional protocol once we have completed the full reporting cycle on the UNCRPD.  It is important to have a full picture of our obligations before we consider ratifying the protocol.  I accept the Senator's point that we need to do that.</p> <p>The funding for the national platform is a valid issue to raise.  I know the people involved well.  I work with them and I have given them interim funding for the past three years.  Many organisations look for funding.  Work has been undertaken on a model to involve people with disabilities in policy development, in line with the UNCRPD obligations, and these proposals will be finalised early next year.</p> <p>With regard to Irish Sign Language, additional funding has been provided for the sign language services and work is well advanced to prepare for the commencement of the Irish Sign Language legislation.</p> <p>The UNCRPD imposed a series of obligations on Ireland, and Departments are working collaboratively to plan for their implementation.  I am working within the framework of the national disability strategy to implement them.</p> <p>Funding is another issue.  Funding from the Dormant Accounts Fund has been secured for the initiative to engage with employers on the employment of people with disabilities.  It will provide seed funding for long-term initiatives in this area.</p> <p>The insurance issue was raised by a number of Senators.  The Government is concerned about the negative impact of insurance costs.  It has established a cost of insurance group to examine this matter.  From my point of view, we are working on the HSE service plan for 2020 and the service providers will raise those issues, and have raised them, in respect of their funding.  There is also an issue with deficits.  I have set up a group to examine that.</p> <p>Cuisle was raised again.  I want to ensure that people with disability have greater choice.  I want to move away from providing respite in congregated health service settings to integrated holiday settings and to provide people with more options, as long as that supports the need to maintain the service.  It is not correct to say that I sat on the pot or was like Pontius Pilate on this issue.  I have been involved with it and I reject the comments made by Senator Leyden.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#U00600"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#U00700"><p>I have engaged with the IWA and the HSE.  I raised the concerns the Senator raised in the House last week with regard to staff, the way they were treated, funding and so forth.  That is ongoing.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What I am saying to colleagues is that I am in favour of choice and respite services.  I spent yesterday meeting disabled people who use Cuisle and I made a point of listening to what they were saying to me.  I have made my views well known.  I cannot intervene in the day-to-day running of a section 39 organisation but I can make my views known, in addition to the views the Senators' reflected to me and those on other issues.</p><p>The Irish Wheelchair Association is saying most of its people want the hotel model.  That is their choice.  I am always available to meet the association and the HSE.  Should the association wish to discuss any future proposal with me, my door will never be closed.  I listen to people and to common-sense advice but I will not take any lectures from Senators such as Senator Leyden, who are saying I closed down Cuisle.  I did not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#V00200"><p>Correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#V00300"><p>The board of the Irish Wheelchair Association made a decision.  Incidentally, one third of the board is made up of people with physical disabilities.  That decision was the board's choice.  While I had nothing to do with the situation, I am always open to working with people to resolve conflict.</p> <p>With regard to the assessment of need, it is absolutely correct to state there is an issue.  I take that on board.  The up-to-date position on the recruitment process to deal with the delays is that, in last year&rsquo;s budget, we got the go-ahead for 100 new speech and language therapists and occupational therapists to try to reduce the waiting list.  The bad news is that it has taken us a long time.  We have recruited only 63.  The good news is that the other 37 will be in place by the end of this month.  I hope that will make a difference.  We had a problem.  There are to be additional therapy posts, ranging from speech and language therapists, occupational therapists and physiotherapists to social workers and psychologists.</p> <p>I am conscious that timely access to assessment services is imperative in a child's development.  I take the point in this regard and I understand how delays in accessing services are a source of great concern to all Senators.  I am confident, however, that the 100 therapists will be in place.  We need to keep this rolling.  There also were internal trade union matters associated with the assessment of need.</p> <p>I mentioned Cuisle and note that Senator Devine talked about the Oireachtas group and I agree with her.  I have dealt with the optional protocol.  The Senator made a very relevant point on the resourcing issue.  I want to be able to draw on the UN convention &mdash; Senator Conway mentioned this &mdash; as an international convention.  The real point, however, is that made by Senator Devine, which is about making rights real for people.  That is essential and what we need to achieve.  We need to ensure follow-up.  That is my job at the Cabinet table.  I have to make that a top priority, and I will do that.</p> <p>I agree on congregated settings.  As far as I am concerned, I want as many people out of them as possible.  So far this year, we managed to get 132 out.  I would like to do more.  The same goes for the nursing homes situation.  It is unacceptable to have young people, particularly those with disabilities, living with patients with dementia, Alzheimer&rsquo;s disease and so on.  There is no debate about that.</p> <p>Senator Ruane mentioned the poverty issue.  It is important.  I dealt with the protocol issue.  We have brought the Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill as far as Committee Stage.  It is stuck there and we are trying to resolve the impasse.  I have the Bill ready to roll.  A couple of colleagues have issues but I hope there will be movement on this in a matter of weeks.  The Senator is correct that it is unacceptable to have high rates of poverty among those with disabilities.  I am trying to tackle that.  Senator Conway touched on the idea that the best way to deal with the problem is to realise there are many people with disabilities who have many abilities and to get them a job.  They will not lose their medical card, as is being suggested.</p> <p>Senator Conway said that, when he was going to school, there were no special needs assistants and that there are now well over 10,000.  When my daughter, who has a disability, started primary school 25 years ago, there was no such thing as a special needs assistant.  She was the only child with Down's syndrome in the mainstream class in Killester girls' national school.  There were fantastic staff there; it is a very inclusive school but it had absolutely no resource hours or special needs assistants.  While circumstances have improved, we need to move on this.</p> <p>Senator Conway mentioned having a Minister of State at the Cabinet.  This is important because Governments have many priorities and one has to remind colleagues constantly that it is not just the Minister of State responsible for disabilities who has a role, because every single person around the table has responsibility with regard to disability.</p> <p>Senator Murnane O'Connor mentioned transport in Carlow the last time I was here.  I am working on that and have been on to the various transport officials about it.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#V00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#V00500"><p>Part of the remit of those associated with the national disability inclusion strategy concerns transport.  This fits in with what Senator Conway is saying, namely, that the UN convention is not just aspirational and that we need to give it teeth and make it deliver.  Having a special debate here at some time on employment for people with disabilities would help me.  Having such a debate in the Seanad Chamber would give us another push.  There is a lot going on at present and there are examples of good practice.  Nearly 7,000 people with some form of disability are working across all the county and city councils and public services.  That is a step in the right direction.  There is a target of 6%.  It used to be 3%.  Some educational institutes and some places of employment have gone over the 6% target in examples of good practice.  We do not acknowledge that and it is important to mention it.  I strongly support the call for a debate.  I wish the Senator the best of luck in having it here.</p> <p>With regard to Senator Murnane O'Connor&rsquo;s point, I mentioned the assessment of need.  I will talk to her about the Carlow case and Holy Angels day care centre.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#V00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#V00700"><p>With regard to the mobility scheme, I should not say it but there are two Bills.  I have mine and the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform has its one.  There is a bit of a debate on the mobility aspect.  The Senator is right that we need to get on with it.  Behind the scenes, I am pushing the view that the scheme is too narrow.  There is no debate about that.  We all know there is a bit of a blockage.</p> <p>Senator Bacik referred to employment, which is important, and to insurance costs.  I have mentioned insurance.  The social care plan negotiations are still taking place.  That is something we have to deal with.</p> <p>I have also mentioned the national platform.  We have given the National Platform of Self Advocates a few bob as part of an interim agreement but, as I stated, we need to secure stable funding for it.  I have been working with the organisation for the past two years.  It is a fantastic organisation.  I have given it some interim funding to keep the show on the road.  What I really love about the organisation is that people with disabilities are running it and speaking up for themselves.  Guess what, that is in line with the UN convention.  That is something.  The Department of Justice and Equality is examining all these issues.</p> <p>I commend Senator McFadden on her comment.  She also mentioned the autism plan and the figure of &euro;2 million.  It is not enough because we will always be looking for more.  It is a start, however.  The Senator's point about low-hanging fruit is highly relevant if people feel as described but I try to fight the funding battle regularly.  The funding we are planning for 2020, of more than &euro;2 billion for services, will represent an increase of 7% if we get it over the line.  There is no other Department that got a budget like that this year in the context of the no-deal Brexit budget.  I have to make sure what the Senator described is not the case.</p> <p>The Senator also referred to CHO area 8 and the need to be open-minded and flexible about budgets.  These are sensible proposals.  I will deal with those when dealing with the social care plan.  When the Senator talks about residential settings, she is talking about the 132 individuals we took out of such settings year.  They are gone to small four-bedroom units with support staff in them.  They all have their own room and television, and they have their meals when they want.  These are the kinds of residential places we are talking about now.  The young man mentioned is included.</p> <p>We are having the debate on personal assistant hours this year.  I accept that many people who are pushing the physical disability issue saw a lot of the money going towards the intellectual disability sector.  Some of them were accusing me of bias in regard to that issue.  I push for funding for emergency residential places.  Some of the packages can cost between &euro;100,000 and &euro;200,000 per person per year.  The cases are extreme, however.  The adults are very high dependency and are very disruptive, and they have to have the care in question.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->When one sees those cases on one's desk, one puts them for priority and sadly, other disabilities do not get to the top of the queue.  The two issues that I am pushing in the service plan negotiations on which I had a significant debate are personal assistant hours and emergency residential places because we need to assist those families that are in a bad situation.  Senator McFadden named one and Senator Murnane O'Connor named another.  We must pick those issues.  There are difficult decisions to be made when one is dealing with a disability issue, and one sees very sad cases.  I assure Senators that I listen as much as possible and I am interested in the person with a disability and what his or her needs are.</p><p>In addition to this work, Senators will also be aware that there are a number of legislative developments to support the implementation of the convention.  The Assisted Decision-Making (Capacity) Act 2015 is one such reform.  Indeed, in 2015, the Act was framed to specifically meet Ireland's obligations under the convention.  It is significant reforming human rights legislation.  I say this for three reasons.  First, it emphasised the personal will and preferences.  Second, it ensures respect for the rights of persons.  Third, it supports the person achieving greater autonomy.  Crucially, the Act was designed to meet the needs of people who have age-related conditions; people with disabilities; people who have acquired brain injuries; and people with mental health issues.</p><p>The Act conferred on the Mental Health Commission the substantial important function of establishing the decision support service.  This service will play a crucial role in vindicating human rights and assuring those who require a service a focus on their needs.  It is estimated that the number of adults in Ireland who require the level of support to make decisions is 220,000.  No doubt, this figure will only increase in the coming years given our population increase.  There will always be other people involved.  Decision-making supporters, for example, are people who would be notified of a decision-making support arrangement to be registered with the decision support service.  As a Government, we are providing the necessary supports for this.  The 2019 Revised Estimates include an allocation of &euro;3.5 million in the Justice and Equality Vote for the services while &euro;3 million was provided last year.</p><p>Essentially, we need to ensure that disability is brought into the mainstream.  We have a long way to go - I accept the arguments made in the debate - but we have started.  We also need to ensure that the necessary administrative process and support measures are put in place and we are committed to doing that before the substantial provisions of any Acts are brought into operation.</p><p>I thank Senators for their contributions and for their interest in the disability issue.  If there are any particular one-on-one issues where they want me to meet families or have a word with the HSE about particular matters, my door is always open.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#W00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  As always, he had a comprehensive response to our point.  I thank his officials as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.179" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.03 p.m. and resumed at 2.24 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.180" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Y00100">Social Welfare (No. 2) Bill 2019: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.181" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Y00300"><p>I am pleased to be in the Seanad to outline the contents of our new Social Welfare (No. 2) Bill.  As Senators will know, the key purpose of this Bill is to enable the implementation of the social protection measures contained in budget 2020, while also serving a number of other purposes.  It includes important measures to ensure I will be in a position to implement the Low Pay Commission's recommendations to provide for an increase in the minimum wage rate.  It also includes measures which address the consequences of a Supreme Court ruling which found that the provisions of the Act which automatically disqualifies prisoners from entitlement to social welfare benefits are unconstitutional.  Furthermore, the Bill includes provisions to provide reports on a number of important policy issues, as agreed in the D&aacute;il.  It also provides for a number of technical amendments to the social welfare code to clarify issues which have arisen or been identified over the past few years.</p> <p>I will outline the Bill's various provisions shortly but I will first comment on the budget 2020 aspects of this Bill.  Senators will recall that the budget was developed against the very real threat of Brexit.  While it may seem to be in the distant past right now, it may loom again from next Friday.  Brexit poses a threat to our economy and, consequently, a prudent approach to the public finances was absolutely necessary and the scope for increasing welfare rates was very limited.  Against that background I was pleased that we succeeded in introducing measures which should provide real support to those who are most reliant on the State.  In 2020, we will spend &euro;21.2 billion on social protection.  That figure includes more than &euro;170 million in additional social welfare expenditure specifically targeting those most in need.  In particular, an increase of &euro;5 per week in the living alone allowance will benefit more than 216,000 older people and people with a disability who are living alone.  We are also building on the increases introduced in last year's budget, such as the increase for a qualified child payment and the provision of higher rates of support for older children.  From next January, families with children aged 12 and over will receive a weekly increase of &euro;3 for each child and those with children under 12 will get a weekly increase of &euro;2 for each child.  I am glad to confirm that the increases in payment rates included in the Bill will take effect from various dates at the start of January rather than at the end of March, as has been the case in the past number of years.  Those include an increase in the earnings disregard for claimants of the one-parent family payment, an increase in the income thresholds for claimants of the working family payment, and changes to the age-related rates of jobseeker's payments and supplementary welfare allowance.</p> <p>Some of the measures contained in the budget do not require primary legislation and so are not reflected in this Bill.  These include an increase of &euro;2 per week in the fuel allowance to &euro;24.50 from January, and extending the household benefits package for free gas and electricity to people under 70 who have another adult living with them.  Funding of &euro;2.5 million is being provided and ring-fenced to target specific job activation and training supports for those who are most distant from the labour market or who are prevented from accessing existing schemes by specific challenges.  We have also extended the hot school meals programme introduced last year.  The number of hours carers can work will be increased from 15 to 18.5 per week.  We have also provided funding for important research into an issue which has been exercising Senators from all sides of the House, namely, how best to address difficult issues around maintenance payments.  We will increase the earnings disregard for those in receipt of jobseeker's transition payment as well.  I am also pleased to have received Government approval for the payment of the social welfare Christmas bonus, for which I wish we could find another name, at a rate of 100% again this year.  That will be paid to some 1.2 million recipients this week.  It benefits all recipients of long-term payments, including carers, people with disabilities, pensioners and lone parents.</p> <p>I will now briefly outline the contents of the Bill.</p> <p>Section 1 provides for the Short Title of the Bill, its construction and citations, and commencement provisions.  Section 2 provides for definitions of terms used in Part 2 of the Bill, which relate to amendments to the Social Welfare Acts.</p> <p>Section 3 arises out of the provisions of section 28 and both relate to the national minimum wage.  Section 28 amends the National Minimum Wage Act to provide me with the power to introduce an order providing for the implementation, in full, of the latest recommendation of the Low Pay Commission, which was to increase the minimum wage from &euro;9.80 to &euro;10.10 per hour in the event of an orderly Brexit.  This amendment is needed because, as it stands, I have no powers to cater for the Brexit situation.  This section also specifically recognises that this is a once-off situation by including a sunset clause, which means the section will cease to have effect once the next report of the commission comes to the Minister of the day.  Section 3 is related to section 28 as it provides that when I introduce the order for the increase in the minimum wage, I will also be able to introduce a parallel order to increase the earnings threshold at which the higher rate of PRSI is paid to ensure that, as in previous years, employers are not doubly hit.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Section 4 provides for amendments to the qualifying conditions for a number of working age payments to address the consequences of a Supreme Court judgment which found that provisions of the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 relating to the entitlements of prisoners were unconstitutional.  I am sure that some Senators will recall that the court found that the automatic disallowance of entitlement to benefits when a claimant is imprisoned is unconstitutional since this represents an extrajudicial punishment.   </p><p>I should say that it will be necessary in a future Bill to introduce further measures arising from this judgment but my Department was not able to finalise these in time for this Bill.  The measures contained in section 4 relate solely to working age payments and are concerned with the qualifying conditions for various illness and disability related payments.  The effect of the amendments is to reinforce a core principle of eligibility for these working age payments, which is that the unavailability for work is as a direct result of a physical or mental illness.  In other words, the customer is not in receipt of a payment for the illness or disability itself and the sole or principal reason why the person concerned is not available for work is because of the illness or disability and no other reason.</p><p>The amendments respond directly to the findings of the Supreme Court and will have no impact whatsoever on the overwhelming majority of claimants.  In practical terms, they provide that where a person is in receipt of one of these working age benefits but becomes unavailable for work for a secondary reason, such as incarceration, that person will no longer fulfil the eligibility conditions for the payment.  This type of conditionality is already in place for other working age schemes and that is why we do not need to introduce changes to those schemes.  For jobseeker's payments, for instance, it is a requirement that a claimant must be available for full-time work in order to qualify. </p><p>Section 5 is a technical amendment which brings the definition of "confinement" for maternity benefit purposes into line with the definition used in the Civil Registration Acts.  By bringing the definitions into line with each other, we are ensuring that where a child is unfortunately stillborn and has a birth weight of 500 grammes, the child's mother will qualify for maternity benefit irrespective of the child's gestational age.  While this is a small change, it is an important one for the few mothers who were affected in the past and I am very happy that it has been brought to my attention and to be in a position for us collectively to be able to fix this. </p><p>Section 6 provides that the reduced rate of jobseeker's allowance for claimants aged 18 to 24 will no longer apply where the claimant lives independently and is in receipt of housing supports.  The full rate of jobseeker's allowance will be paid to these persons with effect from 1 January 2020.  Section 7 is an amendment which I was happy to accept in the D&aacute;il and provides that a report on the effects of reduced jobseeker rates must be presented to the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Employment Affairs and Social Protection within three months.  Section 8 provides that, from 1 January 2020, the age-related reduced rate of jobseeker&rsquo;s allowance will no longer apply to younger claimants once they have attained the age of 25. </p><p>Section 9 is a technical amendment and updates the legislative provisions governing entitlement to carer's allowance.  The amendment confirms that the definition of a relevant person, that is, a person who requires full-time care and attention, means, in the case of a person aged under 16, a person in respect of whom a domiciliary care allowance is in payment.  Sections 10 and 11 provide that the age-related rates of supplementary welfare allowance will no longer apply where the claimant lives independently and is in receipt of housing supports and that age-related rates generally will no longer apply to those who attain the age of 25.  These are mirror images of the amendments to jobseeker's payments contained in sections 6 and 8. </p><p>Section 12 is an important budget measure that provides for an increase of &euro;10 in the weekly income thresholds which determine the level of working family payment for families with up to three children.  This change will take effect from 9 January 2020.  Section 13 is a technical amendment to make it absolutely clear in the legislation that the payment of guardian's payments to a guardian in respect of an orphan does not affect the right of the guardian to claim welfare payments in his or her own right.  Section 14 is a technical amendment which updates section 247 of the Act to set out the payments which may not be paid concurrently with the working family payment.  Section 15 is another technical amendment which brings the legislative provisions relating to social welfare payments after the death of a claimant fully into line with long-standing policy and practice.  In particular, it makes it clear that such payments are made to the surviving spouse, civil partner or cohabitant of the deceased. </p><p>Section 16 provides for the repeal of section 282 of the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005, which currently provides for reduced cost life event - birth, marriage or death - certificates.  This is a matter which is more appropriately dealt with under civil registration law and the equivalent provisions in the Civil Registration (Amendment) Act 2014 will be commenced in parallel with this repeal.  Those provisions will allow regulations to be made by the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection for the purpose of setting the fees, if any, for the provision of life event certificates. </p><p>Section 17 provides for amendments to the existing provisions relating to the recovery of certain benefits where a compensator, typically an insurance company, is also paying compensation in respect of the same injury, accident or disease that gave rise to the claim for a social welfare payment.  First, it adds supplementary welfare allowance to the list of specified benefits which may be recovered and second, it adjusts the period within which a request for a statement of recoverable benefits must be issued to a compensator from four weeks to 25 working days. </p><p>Sections 18 and 22 are key sections of the Bill since they provide for a &euro;2 increase in the rate of the qualified child payment for children aged under 12 from &euro;34 to &euro;36 per week, as well an increase of &euro;3, from &euro;37 to &euro;40 per week for children aged 12 and over.  These sections also provide for an increase of &euro;5 per week in the rate of the living alone allowance.  Depending on the scheme involved, these measures come into effect on dates between 1 January and 10 January 2020.  Section 19 provides that the blind welfare allowance, a payment made by the HSE, will be disregarded in the means test for certain social assistance payments and in particular for disability allowance.  This measure comes into effect from 10 January 2020.  Section 20 provides for an increase in the earnings disregard for one-parent family payment from &euro;150 to &euro;165 per week, with effect from 9 January 2020. </p><p>Section 21 is another technical amendment which updates references set out in the means-testing provisions contained in table 2 of Schedule 3 to reflect changes in structures, for instance with the establishment of Tusla, the Child and Family Agency, and changes in practices, by recognising that certain payments may be made by agencies contracted by the HSE, as well as being made directly by the HSE itself.  Sections 23 to 27, inclusive, are all amendments that were added to the Bill in the D&aacute;il and require that reports be prepared on a number of issues, including the qualifying conditions for treatment benefit; the adequacy of treatment benefit supports towards the cost of hearing aids; the impact on low-income families of increases in carbon taxes; the qualifying conditions for the fuel allowance scheme, and the most appropriate State pension age.  Part 3 of the Bill provides for amendments to the National Minimum Wage Act 2000 and the National Training Fund Act 2000.  I explained earlier the purpose of section 28 and why this is needed in the context of the uncertainties caused by Brexit.  Section 29 is the final section of the Bill and it provides for a 0.1% increase, from 0.9% to 1%, in the National Training Fund levy payable by employers in respect of reckonable earnings of employees in class A and class H employments with effect from 1 January 2020. </p><p>This Bill clearly demonstrates our continued commitment to providing a better deal for families and older people as reflected particularly in the increased rates of payment for qualified children and the increase in the living alone allowance.  While the 2020 budget had to be especially cautious in light of the risks associated with Brexit, we have nevertheless succeeded in further building on the significant increases of recent years and we have been careful to maintain the focus on the most vulnerable groups in our society.  I commend the Bill to the House. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#Z00200"><p>Fianna F&aacute;il is acutely aware of the threat of a no-deal Brexit that the Minister has alluded to on a couple of occasions.  In 2016 Fianna F&aacute;il met the challenge and has since then provided stability and continuity that has stood the country in good stead during the ongoing Brexit uncertainty and the political instability in Westminster.  It was and remains the right approach and the fourth budget under the confidence and supply agreement, which gives effect to this Bill, is a testament to the responsibility and maturity of Fianna F&aacute;il's approach.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aidan Davitt:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2475"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2475&amp;amp;pid=AidanDavitt&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Bill gives effect to the Government decision to defer the increase in the national minimum wage until Brexit uncertainty is resolved.  Fianna F&aacute;il was the party that introduced the national minimum wage in 2000.  We have also protected and promoted workers' rights.  We recognise the threat that a no-deal Brexit poses to Ireland's economic prosperity.  In its latest quarterly bulletin, the Central Bank projects that employment will be 73,000 lower in 2021 and unemployment is forecast to rise to 5.8% in 2020 and 6.9% in 2021.  This is over two percentage points higher than in a deal scenario.  It is therefore imperative that if a no-deal scenario arises jobs are protected inasmuch as possible.  However, once the threat of a no-deal Brexit is removed, the Minister should act immediately and implement the recommendations of the Low Pay Commission.</p><p>Ultimately, budget 2020 was not our budget and it is far from perfect.  Fianna F&aacute;il is disappointed that there is no primary welfare increase for pensioner couples or carers of people with disability.  Fianna F&aacute;il makes no apologies for use of influence, inasmuch as is feasible, to fight for modest gains for the most vulnerable in our society.  To that end we welcome the increases in targeted payments, including the living-alone allowance, fuel allowance, qualified child increase and the increase in the income thresholds for the working family payment.  The one-parent family payment is amended in this Bill too.  I thank the Minister for coming to the House to discuss the Bill with us today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA00200"><p>Our next speaker is Senator Devine.  Senator, do you wish to share time with Senator Gavan or do you wish to use your full eight minutes?  I do not mind either way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA00300"><p>I might not use the full eight minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA00400"><p>If there is any time left over I will allocate it to Senator Gavan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA00500"><p>He still has five minutes, does he not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA00600"><p>He does if he wants it, but he has indicated that he only wishes to speak briefly.  It is only if there is time left over.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA00700"><p>We will share it.  If I find some sort of impetus to go on, I will do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA00800"><p>Go ahead.  You have eight minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA00900"><p>I welcome the Bill and I hope to see its speedy passage in order to have enacted by January next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.194" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#AA01100"><p>I acknowledge that the Minister worked in a collaborative spirit in the Lower House to achieve this timeline and I look forward to working in a similar vein as it passes through the Seanad.</p> <p>The main purpose of the Bill is to make the necessary legislative changes to allow the provisions contained in budget 2020 to be commenced, including the social welfare payment increases from January 2020.</p> <p>Social welfare increases are only welcomed by recipients and stakeholders because the payments are inadequate in the first place.  They welcome the changes but could do with far more to live on.  The increase of certain payments by &euro;2, &euro;3 and &euro;5 is not making social welfare payments adequate.  Moreover, the increases are not based on evidence.  When we bring forward legislation it should be done through the lens of an evidence base.  We should be working towards making all social welfare supports adequate for those who rely on them and we should be moving to an evidence-based approach.</p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in has put forward a fully costed and workable solution.  We envisage a social welfare commission that would use evidence, including the minimum essential standard of living as set out annually by the Vincentian Partnership for Social Justice to make recommendations to Government on social welfare rates annually ahead of the annual budget.  I know the Minister is looking at this type of work.  We will be pushing this further in the new year.  It could transform the way social welfare is provided in the country.</p> <p>I wish to raise my concern regarding young jobseekers.  The Bill stipulates that those aged between 18 and 24 years will see their payment rate increased to the full rate if they live independently and in receipt of State housing support.  We all know the housing crisis affecting our young people.  People are waiting over 13 years in some areas for permanent housing while the rest are reliant on the housing assistance payment.  We know of the extreme difficulty people on HAP are having in renting private accommodation.  Many need a top-up payment.  These young adults are living at home with their parents on the decreased rate.  I cannot imagine a scenario where a young person will be able to live independently with social housing support while unemployed.  I guess this is a chicken-and-egg scenario, further trapping our young people in poverty.  How can a young person live independently to get the social welfare rate needed to live independently?</p> <p>I commend my colleague, Deputy John Brady.  He successfully tabled a motion in the D&aacute;il to address this.  The Minister alluded to this in her statement.  The amendment requires the Minister to present a report on the poverty impact of reduced rates of jobseeker payment for young jobseekers aged between 18 and 24 years to the joint committee within three months of enactment.  I look forward to reading the report and I hope the Minister pays attention to the findings.  I truly believe the discrimination against our young job seekers is causing them harm.  Without pre-empting the results of the report, if I am correct in my beliefs the Minister and her Department will have a serious obligation to right these wrongs.</p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in also amended section 25 in the D&aacute;il, calling on the Minister to undertake an impact statement on the current and projected future increases in carbon tax on low-income families and to report within six months.  As a member of the Joint Committee on Climate Action I have been arguing against the carbon tax consistently.  I believe it is regressive.  Following decades of failure it will serve only to increase the cost burden on households without offering any feasible alternative, particularly for those on lower incomes who can least afford it.  We need to be more dynamic, positive and creative in dealing with climate change.  The carbon tax is none of these things.  I recommend that once the report is published it should be presented to the Joint Committee on Climate Action for consideration.</p> <p>I wish to raise a serious omission from the Bill.  This is the issue of a lacuna in statute that excludes married same-sex male adopters from accessing 24 weeks of adoptive leave.  Since 2016, the Government has consistently stated that it would address this loophole.  This group is the only family type that cannot receive this leave.  Given its recent omission from the Parent's Leave and Benefits Act 2019, the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Stanton, stated he would address it in this Bill.  Yet, it seems to be on the missing list.  In the D&aacute;il on Second Stage, the Minister said it would be inserted via amendments on either Committee Stage or Report Stage, but that has yet to happen.  I am aware the amendments are taking more time than expected but the Government committed to Senator Norris in 2016 that it would address this loophole.  Had the Government started the work on those amendments, it would have been well enacted by now.</p> <p>I was discussing this issue with Senator Warfield.  He said he has lost count of the times the Government has committed to addressing LGBT parent's rights.  This arises usually via a press release, for which the Government gets great praise.  However, it then fails consistently as other legislative priorities take precedence or take over.  The Government needs to stop making commitments to LGBT parents if it ultimately chooses not to keep those commitments.  I urge the Minister to take the steps necessary with the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, whether it be hiring an external drafter or having a stand-alone Bill.  It is beyond disappointing for same-sex parents to be told yet again that they must wait.</p> <p>Finally, I wish to raise the issue of our unsung heroes - our carers.  We know 200,000 of them are unpaid in this State.  Some concerns have been raised by them and their advocacy groups.  The Bill allows for an increase in the hours carers can work but not an increase in the amount of income disregarded.  Did I miss something?  This seems illogical.  If we increase work, we increase pay.  Carers should not be punished for this.  I would appreciate if the Minister could address this.  If not, I will consider tabling amendments to address the matter on Committee Stage.</p> <p>Overall, I have no wish to delay the Bill passing.  I know there are many people who need it passed by the end of the year to realise their small social welfare changes.  I believe the Bill is a missed opportunity to see real change in our social welfare system.  Sinn F&eacute;in has worked hard in the D&aacute;il to strengthen this Bill by reaching out to the Minister.  We will do the same as the Bill passes through this House.</p> <p>I will finish with an aside in the Christmas spirit on the Christmas bonus.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I was thinking of Santa's little helper but then one often has to be on the often complicated good list to qualify.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#BB00200"><p>I am sure the Senator would qualify.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#BB00300"><p>I would qualify.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#BB00400"><p>I welcome the Minister to debate this very important legislation that enacts changes made in the budget.  One of the things I have always liked about that is the smart way we used our money.  Rather than giving people straightforward cash, we used it in different ways so that people get benefits across the board rather than simple payments.  We must recognise that over the past number of years, the budget in the Department has increased dramatically.  This year, it has gone up by &euro;700 million, which works out at an average of &euro;145 per man, woman and child in this State.  That is a sizeable sum of money.</p> <p>I know the Minister is not directly associated with the training fund but the Department is the one Department that increases it.  Over the past three years, it has gone up from 0.8% to 0.9% to 1%.  I estimate that this will bring in about &euro;900 million next year based on the fact that in 2019, it brought in about &euro;744 million while in 2018, it brought in &euro;166 million.  Working off those figures, it should bring in almost &euro;900 million next year, of which &euro;300 million was not used in 2018 and has been set aside as part of the training fund.  While the Department does not have a direct input into where that money is being sent, will the Minister do something to monitor how it is being spent?  Some of us remember the debacle that was F&Aacute;S and the training fund being used to let people go away on foreign trips to the US.  We need proper oversight of how that fund is being used because many small businesses struggle.  </p> <p>Although the Minister does not run Springboard courses, to qualify, an unemployed individual must have been in receipt of a payment for nine months.  There are people who will fail that test because of their means.  It is important that we do something to help those people who would not qualify in respect of the nine months.  Once they can do the nine months, they are off their social welfare payment and get nothing.  Therefore, they do not qualify for the courses.  Could the Minister look at reducing the period from nine months to six so that people who have been on social welfare for six months can qualify?  Does the Minister understand where I am coming from?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1338" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#BB00500"><p>Yes</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#BB00600"><p>The Department runs the free travel scheme, which is very welcome and will be worth &euro;95 million in 2020.  It is roughly 10% of the revenue of the CI&Eacute; group.  This is a large amount of money and the Minister should have some say over the quality of the service it provides.  I see old age pensioners waiting at bus stops with no shelters.  I know it is not the Minister's function but perhaps she could say something.  Buses do not arrive on time.  A train was five minutes late this morning.  I do not understand how a train can be five minutes late.  There was nothing to block it and there were no signalling problems.  People are waiting for a service to arrive.  I visited Japan, where everything arrived like clockwork.  Why can we not set that as our standard?  The Department is paying 10% of the revenue of the CI&Eacute; group so the Minister should have a say.</p> <p>On 15 May 2012, I launched a report that suggested that we move to an hour-based system for social welfare payments.  We are now at full employment.  Certain people would like to work part time but if they work three out of five days, even if it is for one, two, three or four hours, or if they work one, two or three hours per day for four out of five days, they will not qualify for a payment.  It is a day-based system.  If we moved to an hour-based system that allowed people to work for three days and receive three days payment.  If we allowed them to spread 24 hours over the week rather than having the three days, it might work better and encourage more people who are full-time unemployed to go back to work and still maintain their social welfare payments.  I produced a report in 2012.  I might send it on to the Minister.  </p> <p>I get a number of requests from people who are looking for the fuel allowance and have a small pension in addition to the State pension and are marginally over the level.  Could we mark out a little grey area so that they might not get the full allowance but could get 50% of it?  It would help people who are sometimes struggling.  They are on their own and have a small pension that suddenly puts them over the limit, whereas if there were two of them, there would be no problem.  Could the Minister look at that to help people who are marginally over the limit?  </p> <p>I welcome this Bill.  It is imaginative.  I would look at the overall package, which includes some health measures that were brought in, including increases relating to medical cards.  We cannot take this in isolation.  There is an overall package, which is the way I see things going.  Sometimes when people get cash in their hands, they do not spend it on what it is supposed to be for but on something else.  I know there are people who will argue that this is a decision for people to make but sometimes we need to help people to make the decision that is right for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019120400002#BB00700"><p>The Minister is very welcome.  I am here today because I want to raise a specific related matter, which is the planned increase in the pension age the year after next to 67.  I know that the joint committee asked the Minister on an all-party basis to pause this decision.  The report recommended that the Minister review the disparity between the retirement age and pension age and that the proposed increases in pensionable age should be suspended.  I do not know if the Minister is aware that at the recent SIPTU biannual conference, which is a conference of the largest union in the country with about 180,000 members, this was the biggest issue.  The union has decided that it will campaign vigorously in the run up to the election next year and ask all parties to pause this increase for the very simple reason that it is grossly unfair.  This affects people who have worked for a living all of their lives.  I am thinking of SIPTU colleagues working in security, contract cleaning and manufacturing, most of whom have no private pension provision.  When it comes to the age of 66, they are then told that as their retirement age falls the following year, they must work for a further 12 months.</p> <p>A myth has grown up around demographics in this country.  I will set the record straight with regard to that.  Ireland's current pension age of 66 stands in contrast to an EU average of 64 yet we have far fewer older people, nearly 30% less than other EU countries.  The Government intends to increase the pension age to 68 by 2028.  The OECD projects that based on current policies, the average EU pension age will only rise to 66 by mid-century.  The Government intends to increase the pension faster than almost any other European country even though in 50 years' time, Ireland will still have the lowest number of older people, nearly 20% less than other EU countries.  We have far fewer older people but we have and will continue to have one of the highest pension ages in the EU.  There is no logic in this unless it is seen by Government as a crude revenue-saving measure introduced at the expense of retired workers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-12-04a.203" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>