<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.2" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 12:00:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.4" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.5" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media to make a statement on the establishment of a digital legal deposit for Irish web archiving. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Fitzpatrick of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science to make a statement on the actions taken by his Department to address student housing poverty and the delivery of affordable student accommodation. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Marie Sherlock of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Social Protection to make a statement on the steps being taken to reduce the backlog in birth registration and birth certificate services. </blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on the assessments that have taken place into the fire that occurred in November at a halting site in Bantry, County Cork. </blockquote><p><font color="#FF0000"> </font>I have also received notice from<font color="#FF0000"></font>Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the cyberattack on the health service in May 2021, including estimated costs and the impact on hospital procedures. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Loughlin of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on plans for the development of a hospice in the midlands. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Aisling Dolan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on the Delivering Equality of Opportunity in Schools, DEIS, identification model and the timeline for schools to apply for DEIS status. </blockquote><p><font color="#FF0000"> </font>I have also received notice from<font color="#FF0000"></font>Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the straw incorporation measure. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Transport to permit category B licence holders to drive category AM vehicles. </blockquote><p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Warfield, Fitzpatrick, Sherlock and Lombard and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.8" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#B00150">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.9" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#B00200">Digital Archiving</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, for coming to the House.  I hope he will share the details of this discussion with the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin.  I would have appreciated the Minister's presence here today, but I know she will be at the Oireachtas committee meeting on Wednesday.  I thank the Minister for State for his time.</p> <p>We are losing web records at an alarming rate.  Some 60% of the national libraries across Europe have in place adequate copyright law to allow them to collect appropriately the contents of state domain websites, which in our case is the .ie domain.  The relevant legislation here is the Copyright and Other Intellectual Property Law Provisions Act 2019.  I have been covering this issue for many years.  I met representatives of the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment when that Bill came before these Houses.  The Seanad passed an amendment to that Bill that I brought forward, but it was later removed by the then Minister, John Halligan.</p> <p>Section 108 of the Act stipulates that, within 12 months of enactment, the Government shall bring forward a report on the feasibility of establishing a digital web archive or digital legal deposit.  Twelve months have well and truly passed.  In fact, the President signed the Act into law on 26 June 2019.  As it stands, the National Library of Ireland is anxious that we are losing web records at an alarming rate.  I am anxious the Government is breaking the law because it has not brought forward that report.  The National Library of Ireland is concerned, and understandably so, that by not copying websites with the .ie domain, it is in breach of current copyright law.  The library's representatives recently told the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media that for each year they are unable to collect or disseminate the contents of the .ie domain websites, approximately 50% of web records are lost.</p> <p>As I have said before, a black hole will be created in our country's memory if we continue to fail to put in place a digital legal deposit.  The hold-up seems to be in the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, which I understand was given the responsibility for producing a report on the feasibility of establishing the scheme.  What is the Minister's view of what the scheme should look like?  When will the report be brought to Cabinet?  As I mentioned, the Government is now breaking the law on this issue.  We are facing excessive loss of online material for the current and future generations.  It seems there is no urgency from Ministers to take ownership of the issue and to set up a digital legal deposit scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#C00100"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  I apologise on behalf of the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, who is unavailable this morning to take this Commencement matter.</p> <p>Legal deposit legislation is an important instrument in national cultural policy.  In Ireland, as in most countries, it is relied upon to ensure the published output of the nation is collected and preserved by one or more prescribed institutions in order that citizens and researchers, within the country and abroad, are guaranteed permanent access to the intellectual and cultural memory of the nation.  Some countries have amended legal deposit legislation to incorporate the deposit of their published digital output, for example, websites and electronic publications.  This is digital legal deposit, and it exists to various extents in the UK and some EU countries, including France, Germany, Spain, Latvia, Lithuania and Estonia.</p> <p>Section 29 of the Copyright and Other Intellectual Property Law Provisions Act 2019 introduced a provision for copyright libraries to request a publisher to deposit a copy of a digital publication first published in the State.  This introduced digital legal deposit in Ireland.  Further consideration is being afforded to a wider initiative that would capture the web, particularly the .ie domain.  At present, the National Library of Ireland, NLI, collects a wide range of websites and stores them permanently.  All the websites collected by it are collected with the consent of the owners.</p> <p>Section 108 of the 2019 Act provided that the Government would bring forward a report on the feasibility of establishing a digital legal deposit scheme to serve as a web archive for the .ie domain contents and advise of the steps taken towards that goal.  Within a year of publication, 50% of web resources are gone or are unrecognisable, but the work of the NLI means Government publications and online websites documenting most aspects of public life in the 21st century will not be lost to future researchers.</p> <p>Since 2011, the NLI has been selectively archiving the web, moving towards the creation of an archive of Irish websites.  There are several practical and administrative limitations to that process, but perhaps the greatest concern is the fact that it does not provide for a complete record of Irish-content websites.  The library has a statutory mandate to collect for the benefit of the public.  It can also meet the resource requirements to gather and preserve the information.  Legislation could be introduced to give the library the right to conduct a full domain trawl of all .ie websites of Irish interest periodically.  To capture a complete record of Irish websites, the domain trawl would include the collection of content behind paywalls.  The intention would be that the NLI would make the content available on its premises, as with other resources.  This is not a simple issue.  However, the owners of websites whose content lies behind a paywall have rights as publishers in general and are important stakeholders in that context.  The agreement of relevant publishers would be appropriate and desirable in respect of any legislation.</p> <p>On progress, the Department of Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media is working with the NLI on exploring the feasibility of expanding the library's capacity to establish a digital legal deposit scheme to serve as a web archive for the .ie domain.  Work is ongoing in this regard.  There are differing views on the introduction of a digital legal deposit, and it is important that consultation incorporate all those views.  It is hoped to bring forward a report in the coming months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the response from the Department.  I have not learned anything new.  On his reference to the Act introducing a provision allowing copyright libraries to request a publisher to deposit a copy of a digital publication, the scheme is not really a scheme at all.  We are aware that the NLI is understaffed by comparison with its equivalent national libraries and, therefore, actively requesting it to make copies of records is hardly realistic.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is extraordinary that the Government accepts that we are losing material but has not produced a report that it is legally required to produce.  I hope to see the report in the coming months, as per the response to parliamentary questions for a number of months.  I hope to see the report before the end of the year.  I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, for coming to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Warfield for his remarks and I absolutely understand his frustration in this context.  I am working with what the Minister, Deputy Catherine Martin, has provided to me.  This is not my area of responsibility, but I will revert to the Minister and express the Senator's concern about the response he is getting.  My scripted reply is very clear that the report is due but, as the Senator said, the replies to his questions have said it will be a number of months.  I will raise the concern the Senator has expressed and his view that valuable material is being lost.  That is critical to our State, so I undertake that I will raise that with the Minister, Deputy Martin.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.15" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#D00300">Student Accommodation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#D00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, for coming to the House.  I mean no disrespect to the Minister of State when I say I would have preferred the Minister, Deputy Harris, to be here.  I appreciate the Minister of State's time.  I understand that the Minister is at a Cabinet meeting.</p> <p>The issue I wish to raise is access to third level education and, most importantly, the affordability of third level education.  The introduction of free education in Ireland in 1967 was a historic moment.  It is one that we as a country experience the benefit of every day, not just socially but economically, and something we are recognised as a nation around the world for having achieved and led on.  Today, outside Leinster House, students will protest about the financial barriers preventing students in Ireland from accessing third level education.  Education is not just good for the individual, society and our economy but is also an investment in our collective future.  Financial barriers are preventing an increasing number of students from accessing education.  I appreciate that the Government in place over the past year has recognised those barriers and taken action to address some of them.  The recent improvements to the SUSI grant in the budget, specifically the increase in the income thresholds and the qualifying distance and the enhanced funding of &euro;17 million which the Minister, Deputy Harris, secured for the enhanced student assistance fund, were really welcome.  I have also engaged with the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, as has the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, on the caps on rents, the caps on upfront payments for student accommodation, the reduction in the notice period for students to give on accommodation and the direction given to local authorities not to allow purpose-built student accommodation to be converted to short-term lets.  That is all very welcome.</p> <p>The reality, though, is that the research that has been conducted indicates that the cost of a four-year degree is &euro;50,000 on average, which is still too expensive.  In Housing for All, the &euro;20 billion commitment that has been made to address the housing crisis is welcome but, on top of that, Covid has had an impact.  The number of digs has reduced.  Families are no longer willing to take additional residents into their homes, quite understandably.  The pressure on students is therefore enormous.  I know that the third level institutions have been given &euro;170 million or &euro;180 million in funding to build purpose-built student accommodation and that the technical universities have been given funding.  However, we need an urgency on the provision of affordable student accommodation because the accommodation element is proving to be a very significant cost.  The Union of Students in Ireland is asking the Government to take action to remove these financial barriers.  It requests specifically that the &euro;3,000 student contribution charge be abolished.  It also asks for further reform of the SUSI grant scheme.  More than anything, it is asking the Government to take urgent action to ensure that student accommodation is affordable to all students.</p> <p>I hope the Minister, Deputy Harris, has sent the Minister of State here with some good news.  I look forward to his reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#D00500"><p>I apologise on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Harris.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Peter Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2457"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2457&amp;amp;pid=PeterBurke&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->He was keen to attend but, unfortunately, but due to Cabinet meeting commitments, he will be unable to do so.</p><p>The Government has taken action to address affordability in student accommodation.  Rent increases in student accommodation are capped under the rent pressure zone provisions.  From this year onwards, students cannot be made to pay more than two months rent upfront when commencing a tenancy, ending the practice where students had to pay several thousand euros upfront to secure accommodation.</p><p>A number of supports are available to students facing financial barriers to attend higher education.  The principal one of these is the student grant scheme, which assists more than 70,000 students annually to access third-level education.  The student grant scheme includes a non-adjacent rate of grant, which is a higher rate of grant that takes into consideration the additional costs which may be associated with living further away from college, such as accommodation costs.</p><p>From September 2022, the distance for the non-adjacent rate will be reduced from 45 km to 30 km, meaning that more students will qualify for this higher grant rate.  Students experiencing exceptional financial needs can apply for support under the student assistance fund.  The allocation to the student assistance fund for the 2021-22 academic year is &euro;17.2 million, which includes an additional &euro;8.1 million on the Covid-19 return to education funding.  </p><p>Fundamentally however, this challenge is one of supply.  As a country we need to dramatically increase the supply of all types of housing and accommodation, including student accommodation.  That is why the Government has launched Housing for All led by my Department.  This sets out a series of actions to be delivered to fix the housing crisis.  The plan is backed up by the largest ever housing budget in the history of the State, at in excess of &euro;20 billion, to transform our housing system.</p><p>The programme for Government, Our Shared Future, contains a commitment to work with higher education institutions to ensure that more accommodation is built on- and off-campus using cost-rental and other models.  An important element of this is to ensure that the higher education institutions have access to low-cost financing.  </p><p>Since 2017, the Housing Finance Agency has approved a total of &euro;157 million in loans to support the provision of more than 1,400 new students bed spaces across three universities.  At present the technological universities, TUs, are unable to borrow to build their own student accommodation.  Housing for All contains a commitment to support our TUs to develop purpose-built student accommodation through access to appropriate financing such that TUs borrowing from the Housing Finance Agency.</p><p>The Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science and the Minister, Deputy Harris, have been engaging with representatives from the higher education sector on this issue to better understand how they can be supported to build more student accommodation.  Together with these stakeholders and the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, we are looking to develop a stronger pipeline of affordable student accommodation which we know is critical.  As part of that work we will examine the potential for the use of funding models such as cost rental in the education sector as well as examining existing barriers to the building of student accommodation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his reply.  I accept and welcome the innovations that the Government has made in enabling the TUs, the consideration of the affordable cost-rental model, the other innovations in the capping and limiting of the rents and upfront payments and the reduction of the notice periods.  We have to go further, however, to fully ensure that any of the purpose-built student accommodation that has been built is hit with a vacant property tax if it is not being used and that students who are struggling financially are supported through the assistance funds which are in place.  The Government and the Minister of State need to be ambitious to ensure that every person and citizen in our society has access to third-level education.</p> <p>Education makes people smarter and better and enables people to make better choices for themselves, to live smarter and better and to make a greater contribution, not just to their own immediate community and family but to our society at large.  We have the proof of the value of investment in education.  As we move out of Covid-19, let us make an investment in our future to ensure that every citizen has access to third-level education that is affordable and, ideally, free.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#E00300"><p>I thank the Senator for her Commencement matter.  There is great ambition contained in Housing for All.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Peter Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2457"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2457&amp;amp;pid=PeterBurke&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In his role in higher education the Minister, Deputy Harris, has brought additional technical universities together, tried to navigate borrowing capacity for low-cost loans, which will be very important, and brought a guaranteed 10,000 more apprenticeships into the economy every year.  This is a big statement.  Now we have it on the CAO form and students considering their third level options can see there are more alternatives and more stable careers, which is very important.  We want to try to get as many people as possible into further education.  We want to eliminate all barriers to access.  Education is the key to unlocking all our potential.  Throughout the history of the State we have seen how important this is.  The Minister, Deputy Harris, will be to the forefront working to ensure we build more low-cost affordable housing in our institutions throughout the State.  Be it at a technical university or the university network, on-campus accommodation is very important.  We continue in our singular focus to do this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#F00200"><p>This is a very important matter.  My son could not find a place to live for college this year so is commuting from Clare and burning lots of fossil fuels because the public transport is not yet there.  It is a huge issue.  We are all aware of the fact that we need to build more houses and the empty sites issue is massive.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.23" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#F00250">Registration of Births</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#F00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House.  At this point, there is a very real and serious problem with families being able to register the births of their newborn babies and get a birth certificate for that child.  A child born in Cork today will have a birth registered in two to three days.  If that same child was born in Dublin the wait for an appointment for registration would be weeks and in some cases months.  I know of a child born four weeks ago and the date for the registration of the birth is 16 December.  Waiting matters because families cannot access child benefit or the GP card.  We know that in some instances it delays housing applications.  I know of families that have had to pay for an infant baby to go to a GP because they do not have the free GP card.  For low-income families or single parents having to pay for everything themselves or for families with a good income but paying exorbitant rents, the waiting matters because of the GP card, child benefit and other supports from the State.</p> <p>There is a failure on the part of the HSE and the Department of Health to address the enormous backlog that exists in Dublin.  There is an irony that if I had a baby today I could drive to Meath or Louth in two or three days' time and register the baby's birth but in Dublin I would be waiting for many weeks.  Nobody should have to commute any number of miles, particularly after the birth of a baby, to get the baby registered.  There is a very real question as to what the HSE is doing.  I understand there is a backlog of between 500 to 600 applications for the registration of births that arose from the time when people could only apply online.  We have the culmination of those applications online plus people waiting for an appointment.  It is intolerable that in November parents and families are waiting.</p> <p>This is not the totality of the problem.  Trying to register the birth of a child is one thing; trying to get a birth certificate is another matter.  When I came to these problems there was a strong whiff of the wild west about trying to purchase a birth certificate in this country.  At present, people in Dublin are directed to order a birth certificate online.  It is made clear there is no facility to order a birth certificate over the phone.  The HSE website suggests there is no walk-in facility.  Last week, I informed the Seanad that families had come to me who in desperation had rung the civil registration office and were told to put money in an envelope.  They received the birth certificate within a few days.  A family told me they needed a birth certificate to get the child baptised and the church directed them to the civil registration office in Kilkenny from where they received the certificate in a few days.  Another family told me an official in the office told them there were 19,000 unread emails regarding applications for birth certificates.</p> <p>Of most concern to me is that families told me they were able to purchase a birth certificate from third parties.  This day four weeks ago, we engaged in an experiment of sorts whereby a family allowed me to purchase a birth certificate for a baby who was only a few weeks old.  The mother went through the civil registration service on Lombard Street on the same day.  I paid &euro;46 and she paid &euro;21.50.  I received the baby's birth certificate within six days.  She is still waiting four weeks later.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is something wrong with a system where families are forced to pay extra to get a birth certificate.  If these third parties and companies are able to go to civil registration offices outside Dublin and purchase birth certificates at a profit to sell back to families, the question must be asked as to why is the HSE not doing something similar.  Why is it not distributing the caseload that has built up in Dublin to other civil registration offices across the country?  Not only does it make a mockery of the State, but it is unnecessarily forces parents to pay extra.  It is also important to note that there is a risk, when people are handing their money over, that they may never see the birth certificate.  One company, Births, Deaths and Marriages, which was taking up to &euro;50 from people, went belly-up in the past number of weeks.  People handed over the money and ended up with no birth certificate.  I look forward to hearing the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#G00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this most important Commencement matter, which I am taking on behalf of the Minister for Social Protection.  I pass on her apologies.  I also understand the Senator has had discussions with the General Register Office, GRO, on the issues that she has raised,</p> <p>We share the concerns expressed by her.  The issue is of huge concern to the Government.  I understand that some parents have suffered delays in excess of 12 weeks, and perhaps longer, in having their children's births registered.  These delays and backlogs are being experienced in the eastern regional registration area.  Thankfully, other registration areas appear to be less affected.  </p> <p>The House will be aware that the HSE is responsible for the day-to-day delivery of civil registration services.  The Minister for Social Protection has only limited functions with respect to how the HSE delivers the service and has no direct role in the performance of any of the operational areas.  I wish to emphasise that what we are dealing with is clearly a performance issue and not a weakness in policy.  </p> <p>The HSE has advised that the cyberattack significantly impacted its computer systems in mid-May 2021, and that it continues to struggle with the impact, particularly in its largest office in Dublin.  Allied to these difficulties are those caused by the restrictions on public access and staff of registration offices both in Dublin and nationally.  I understand that the cyberattack resulted in the local registration services being out of action for five weeks from mid-May.  It was not until much later in July that some of the critical systems were passed fit for servicing, resulting in severe disruption to service provision and backlogs that are proving difficult to clear. </p> <p>Senators will be aware that many civil registration offices are located within other health services in clinics or close to maternity hospitals that continue to be subject to restricted public access.  The staff, to their credit, have continued to maintain the civil marriage services, and continue to manage notifications from couples wishing to get married.  Some 1,500 births fall to be registered in eastern areas, placing a continued pressure on the service.  Not unusually, the eastern area has suffered some short-term staff shortages due to the promotion and retirement of key staff over the past few months.  Recruitment is under way to fill vacancies, but it will take time for new staff to get up to speed.  Additional temporary staff have been recruited to tackle the backlogs and provide additional support with respect to its customer service channels.  Staff are also working at weekends.</p> <p>The Senator has identified additional concerns that the Minister wants to address.  PPS numbers are automatically allocated once a birth has been registered.  Parents do not need to do anything for the PPS number to be allocated.  Adjustments follow automatically to child benefit payments and the Minister has committed to ensuring that any delay in child benefit resulting from the backlog will be made good and arrears will be paid quickly.  The Senator also asked if there is any relationship between the websites she mentioned and the HSE or the GRO.  To my knowledge, there is no connection, contractual or otherwise.  My understanding is that they operate as third-party certificate resellers.  </p> <p>I am encouraged by the manner in which the service has recovered, having suffered such a significant setback earlier in the year.  It would be useful if communications could be improved so that any person looking for a certificate is encouraged to look to their local registration office or to the GRO, which provide a similar service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#G00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I am conscious that he is responding on behalf of the Minister for Social Protection.  I thank her for the response.  I originally submitted the matter to the Minister for Health but it was redirected to the Minister for Social Protection.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am glad to hear from the reply submitted by the Minister for Social Protection that this is a performance issue.  Indeed, it is a performance issue for the HSE to address and, therefore, it is one for the Department and the Minister for Health, who have responsibility for the HSE, to address.  I am glad to hear efforts are being made to address recruitment, but as the written reply makes clear, "Not unusually, the eastern area has suffered some short-term staff shortages".  It is simply unacceptable that families will be waiting 12 weeks to register the birth of their baby.  This could be so easily resolved by allocating some of that work to other offices.  While I accept efforts are being made, they are simply not good enough.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#H00200"><p>I thank the Senator for her comments and appreciate the frustration she has expressed.  I will raise the issue with the Minister for Social Protection and the Department of Health in the context of any jurisdiction it has over the HSE in this regard.  As a parent, I appreciate how frustrating it can be when trying to get a child registered, given many key services flow from that.  I will raise the matter with the Minister and try to accelerate the provision of those resources.  The prepared contribution indicates staff are working at weekends and trying their best to alleviate the backlog.  The addition of new staff will, I hope, make the key difference.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.30" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#H00300">Traveller Accommodation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#H00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I tabled this matter to seek clarity on how the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage is dealing with a major fire incident that happened at a halting site in Bantry on 9 November.  Has a report on the fire been filed and a fire hazard safety assessment completed?  What is the long-term housing plan for the people who live on the site?</p> <p>On the night of Tuesday, 9 November, a major fire happened at a halting site in Bantry.  One unit was totally burned to the ground.  It was a significant fire, covered widely on social media and also in the press.  The issues regarding the site go back generations, in many ways.  What has the Department done about the fire and what assessments has it carried out on the site?  Has it examined its cause and how it could be prevented from happening again?  How safe is the site now?</p> <p>As the Minister of State will be aware, unfortunately a very significant fire happened at a halting site in Carrickmines in 2015, in which ten people lost their lives.  Some of the recommendations that came from the coroner's court are worth reflecting on.  The coroner recommended that the exemption from fire and planning regulations for emergency sites be changed.  There is an exemption in regard to planning and fire safety on temporary halting sites.  The site in Bantry is 25 years old, yet is considered to be of a temporary nature.  Are there, therefore, no planning or fire regulations for the site?  It would be a significant issue, not only for the patrons, one whom was injured in the fire, but for the entire town if there are no planning or fire regulations for the site.  The coroner's report on the Carrickmines fire further recommended that the powers for establishing emergency halting sites be used for the shortest possible time.  The Bantry halting site is 25 years old, one quarter of a century.  Are we really saying that is a short period?</p> <p>The report on the Carrickmines incident is something I want to reflect on.  We got an awful rude awakening in 2015 when ten patrons lost their lives.  There was a really significant fire in Bantry a week and a half ago and the same could have happened there.  There could have been a real tragedy.  Having spoken to people who attended the scene that night, I know it was by the grace of God that other units were not lost, with more people affected.  The site is located on a dead-end road and access is a big issue.  There are commercial units all around it, so the fire could have spread to them and had a significant impact on the entire commercial entity of Bantry.</p> <p>What is the long-term plan for the site?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->How are we going to work on the health and safety issues there?  What is the Department doing with regard to the judgment of the coroner's report on the Carrickmines incident?  Has it taken on board the point made regarding the absence of planning and fire regulation in respect of these sites?  Can we put in place a structure to ensure these sites are managed appropriately?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#J00200"><p>I thank Senator Lombard for raising this matter.  Many vulnerable people rely on Cork County Council to keep them safe.  The Housing (Traveller Accommodation) Act 1998 provides that local authorities have statutory responsibility for the assessment of the accommodation needs of Travellers and for the preparation, adoption and implementation of multi-annual Traveller accommodation programmes in their areas.  My Department's role is to ensure there are adequate structures and supports in place to assist local authorities in providing such accommodation, including a national framework of policy, legislation and funding.</p> <p>The National Directorate for Fire and Emergency Management led and oversaw a programme at national level to review fire safety in local authority-provided Traveller accommodation following the tragic loss of life at the Carrickmines halting site, which the Senator referenced.  We never again want to see an absolutely horrific event like that, where so many vulnerable people lost their lives.  Under direction from the National Directorate for Fire and Emergency Management, local authorities undertook a major exercise aimed at enhancing fire safety in Traveller accommodation in 2015 and 2016.  One of the core objectives of the project is the development and roll-out of a community fire safety awareness initiative appropriate for the Traveller community.  The aim of this initiative is to get fire safety messages disseminated into the Traveller community, enabling Travellers to take practical steps in respect of fire safety issues commonly associated with living on halting sites.  To support this process, the national directorate, in consultation with key stakeholders including Traveller representative groups, developed an information leaflet and booklet on fire safety in the Traveller community.  </p> <p>My Department continues to engage with local authorities regarding fire safety on Traveller sites.  Fire safety matters are discussed at national Traveller accommodation consultative committee meetings.  From its contact with Cork County Council in respect of the halting site in Bantry, which operated for more than 25 years, my Department understands that fire safety inspections are carried out annually by the council on all Traveller-specific accommodation.  Cork County Council has carried out significant fire safety works on the site in Bantry.  These works protected the other families on the site on the night of the fire.  The council is working with the family affected to secure appropriate accommodation.</p> <p>I assure the Senator that the Department is doing everything it can.  Again, we have to look at the facts.  Last year was the first year in which all the capital expenditure funding in the budget was utilised.  The chief reason for this was the Covid pandemic.  We have increased the amount available in the capital budget for Traveller accommodation by 25% over the last two years.  Cork County Council needs to take advantage of that.  With regard to my responsibility, the money is there to support the members and executive of the local authority in making appropriate decisions to ensure the Traveller community has secure and sustainable accommodation.  We are working through an expert report.  I have established a programme board to respond to the 32 recommendations given to me by the all-party committee.  This board is having quarterly meetings with a view to driving that forward to ensure that Travellers have secure tenancies and that their conditions are improved.  However, we have to be very clear as to where responsibility lies.  I commissioned an audit last year during the Covid pandemic which looked at the HSE response in respect of 250 sites.  We must be clear that the money is there.  the funding is there and I call on every one of the 31 local authorities in this country to stand up to the mark and draw down funding to ensure that Travellers have sustainable accommodation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#J00300"><p>I am slightly disappointed with the Minister of State's response to the question I raised on the fire safety assessment of the halting site.  I asked whether it had been completed.  It is important that we get clarity as to what assessment has actually been carried out on site since 9 November in respect of this incident.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The crux of the issue is that the coroner's statement on the Carrickmines incident states that the fire and planning regulations make these sites exempt.  Has that exemption stood?  If one looks at what is happening in Bantry, there is no way one could stand over the planning and exemptions when it comes to fire safety on these sites.  These are significant issues.  This is about learning from a tragedy that occurred in Carrickmines, taking note of what happened in Bantry in November and making sure, first, that there is appropriate planning and fire safety for these halting sites.  It was stated in the coroner's report that there was none.  When it comes to having the report on what happened that night published, we have no detail or knowledge of what happened.  I ask the Minister of State to make that report available to me as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1595" speakername="Peter Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#K00200"><p>I thank Senator Lombard for his concern on behalf of the community in Bantry about this fire.  I wish to be very clear about the line of responsibility.  It is primarily with the local authority in the first instance.  The local authority has advised me, on foot of the Senator's Commencement matter, about the work that has been undertaken as a result of the inspections that took place in Cork.  I will refer back to the Senator regarding whether the assessment has been carried out.  However, the Senator will note one of the sentences in my response was that the works Cork City Council had already carried out protected other families on the site from a worse potential outcome, but I will refer back to the Senator about the assessment.</p> <p>In addition, I emphasise that local authorities must step up to the mark in delivering Traveller accommodation through their plans.  The Office of the Planning Regulator is now conducting assessments of the plans to do that across the 31 local authorities because it is very urgent.  They have to step up to the mark.  As regards all the planning issues the Senator referred to, the local authority has primary responsibility to do that.  When the local authority comes knocking on my door for the funding, I can assure it that it will be wide open.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.37" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#K00300">Teachtaireacht ón Dáil - Message from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#K00400"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Child and Family Agency (Amendment) Bill 2021, without amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.39" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.47 p.m. and resumed at 1 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.40" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#N00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#N00200"><p>Before I call the Leader to outline the Order of Business, I wish to inform the House that Christy Kelly in the Oireachtas print facility is retiring after 40 years of service to us all.  He is one of the great gentlemen of Leinster House.  He does a lot of quiet work and helps out Members in all sorts of ways in trying to get their message out.  We all know how hard it is to communicate in the modern world, but the print facility, under Christy, has been a phenomenal resource for Members and Senators down through the years.</p> <p>Christy said that he came here when he was 26 and had a full head of hair, and teeth.  I believe that he still has both but I am not too sure.  Christy and his wife, Paula, plan to take a long trip to Australia after Christmas.  We hope that they have a grand time Down Under, celebrate appropriately and think of us when they are on the beach while we get a bit colder here.</p> <p>My only advice to Christy comes from a message that was posted on the window of a shop in Kenmare.  After 48 years of delivering bread to all the shops in the area, the three Moriarty brothers retired.  They wrote in beautiful script on the window a message to all their customers, thanking them for their service and loyalty down through the years, and then said, "Now we must learn the art of how to spend time without spending money."  When Christy learns that in Australia, he might come back and impart all of that wisdom to us.  We wish Christy and his wife, Paula, and all the family a long and happy retirement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#N00300"><p>I echo the Cathaoirleach's comments.  We often talk about the wonderful people who work in the environs of this place we call our job, and I have always stated that there are some incredibly special people who mind us, look after us and help us every day.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have always stated there are some incredibly special people who mind and look after us and help us every single day.  Christy is an absolute gem of a gentleman.  I cannot believe he is here 40 years.  It is a real testament to the character he is.  Not very many people can cite 40 years' service in any particular job, certainly not for my generation and younger.  I wish him and Paula continued happiness and I hope they have a fabulous trip.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.44" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#O00200">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#O00300"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Planning and Development (Amendment) (Large-scale Residential Development) Bill 2021 &ndash; Report and Final Stages, to be taken at 2.15 p.m and the proceedings thereon, if not previously concluded, to be brought to a conclusion at 4.30 p.m. by the putting of one question from the Chair which shall, in relation to amendments, include only those set down or accepted by the Government; No. 2, statements on children in care and children leaving care, to be taken at 5 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 1, whichever is the later, and to conclude after 90 minutes, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, those of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, and those of all other Senators not to exceed four minutes, and the Minister to be given not less than ten minutes to reply to the debate; No. 3, statements on paediatric scoliosis services, to be taken at 6.45 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 2, whichever is the later, and to conclude after 60 minutes, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed six minutes, those of all Senators not to exceed six minutes, and the Minister to be given not less than six minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 4, Residential Tenancies (Amendment) (No. 2) Bill 2021 &ndash; Committee Stage, to be taken at 8 p.m. or 15 minutes after the conclusion of No. 3, whichever is the later, and to adjourn at 10 p.m. if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#O00400"><p>I support the Order of Business and congratulate Christy Kelly on behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il team in the Seanad.  He is a true legend.  Not many people have a 40-year career in the Oireachtas.  The best of good health and happiness to Christy, Paula and family.</p> <p>I also wish to congratulate a wonderful Kildare man, Christy Moore, a pure legend, on receiving a lifetime achievement award last week.  Christy is very much cherished by the people of Ireland, not just the people of Kildare.  He is authentic and has great honesty and integrity in both his singing and his writing and of course in terms of his story.  We are very proud of Christy and indeed of all of the Moore family in Kildare.  I am good friends with his sister Terry and his brother Barry.  When any of us think of Christy, we think of the ordinary man in particular and the way he has really given voice to the voiceless over seven decades.  It is an incredible achievement and I congratulate him and wish him well.  I want to mark the very profound impact he has had on music in Ireland.</p> <p>Yesterday the Oireachtas all-party group on dementia had a very interesting presentation from a team led by Professor Sean Kennelly, co-director of the Tallaght University Hospital memory clinic, about current innovations and trends in dementia research.  A lot of what he told us was eye-opening.  For example, there are new studies being done and they are going to be elevated to just a simple blood test that will identify the onset of Alzheimer's or dementia 25 years before it happens through proteins in the blood, which is quite incredible.  It struck home with me that 40% of dementia can be preventable in terms of lifestyle changes, particularly when we look at brain health around the age of 50.  We need to have a debate on brain health and the possibility of it being checked along with cardiac health and other areas we have checked at that age.  I would like to see a debate in the House on that.</p> <p>Especially in my own county of Kildare, we have significant housing issues.  We cater for two D&aacute;il constituencies.  There is a real need for extra staff in the housing department, particularly in social and affordable housing.  We need two more project teams to be able to deliver on the commitments that have been made under Housing for All.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I would like to see a strong message going from the Seanad for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#P00200"><p>I, too, would like to be associated with the comments that were made on the retirement of our colleague Mr. Christy Kelly.  He gave great service here for four decades and was always fantastic to deal with.  He is very amenable and very accommodating, which is not easy at times.  I wish himself and his wife Paula all the very best.</p> <p>We have been very successful in this country with our vaccination programme. Ireland has one of the highest rates of vaccination in the world with nearly 95% of our population vaccinated.  This is a marvellous achievement.  It is a reflection on how seriously the people of Ireland take Covid and the challenges and threats caused by the pandemic.  I do not believe, however, that we are using to its optimum the vaccination infrastructure we have built.  The Covid-19 certificate should be used far more widely.  I cannot understand why it is not required for access to gyms, hairdressers, hotels and events that take place throughout the country.  The use of the Covid-19 certificate needs to be extended.  It is appropriate that it would be extended because it is a very effective way of protecting public health.  I cannot understand why a person can go into hairdressers, for example, without showing a Covid-19 certificate, given that he or she spends so long in the company of the hairdresser.  I cannot understand why the Covid-19 cert is not used in gyms.  I cannot for the life of me understand why it is not required in hotels, or at least when using the facilities in hotels such as bars, restaurants and gyms.  I want to see the Government coming out in the next few days with a measure for the increased use of the Covid-19 certificate, a certificate 95% of Irish people have bought into.  Such a measure will absolutely help to prevent the spread of Covid and it will be a very important public health measure.</p> <p>We have seen stories about nightclubs in Dublin opening at 6 p.m. until 12 midnight, which is a method to get around the restrictions.  The Government did not close the nightclubs.  In my view, the Government should have closed the nightclubs.  The Government should never have reopened the nightclubs.  Be it as it is, the problem now is that the nightclubs in rural Ireland are being discriminated against.  It is totally unrealistic for a nightclub in west Clare or other parts of rural Ireland to open at 6 p.m. until 12 midnight.  They must continue to pay their insurance and continue to pay their fixed costs whereas if the Government had closed the nightclubs, they would have some chance of dealing with their insurance and other fixed costs.</p> <p>In the absence of the Government doing the right thing by nightclubs and by the people who work in nightclubs, I would like the Minister of State with responsibility for insurance, Deputy Sean Fleming, to come before the House to explain how he will deal with this.  I am told by clubs around the country that they are not getting a waiver on their insurance because the Government has not closed them.  I look forward to the Leader's response on these important issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#P00300"><p>I thank the Leader for setting out the draft Order of Business today.  I will start by congratulating Dublin city councillors for approving an 853-home development.  It is a very important decision and it took a long time coming.  There was much debate about Oscar Traynor Road and that site with regard to the quota and percentage of social houses, affordable houses and council-owned houses.  It is a council site and the councillors exercised their powers and functions, and they must be commended on doing so against a lot of resistance and negative commentary by a lot of people.  Dublin City Council members have approved these new plans for the development of 853 social and affordable homes.  The council's decision, which was backed by most councillors last night, is very important because 40% will be used for social housing, 40% will be used for cost rental units, and 20% will be for sale to low- and middle-income workers who qualify for the upcoming affordable purchase scheme.  I acknowledge the Government's role in that scheme.  This is a positive day.  It is positive in giving power back to local government and giving power back to councillors, in this case Dublin city councillors.  I commend them and acknowledge them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I note from an email that the Leader and Senator Gallagher are bringing in a Bill in regard to peat and doing a briefing tomorrow.  I look forward to attending that briefing.  I welcome the recent comments by the T&aacute;naiste, Deputy Varadkar, on the availability of peat in the horticultural sector.  That is available in one of his statements issued two or three weeks ago in which he recognised that there were no viable alternatives to peat for the horticultural sector and that the Government needs to find a solution to the problem.  That is a very important statement from him, recognising that fact.  I now use this opportunity to call on the Minister of State at the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Malcolm Noonan, to publish the final report without any further delay.  It is feeding into much uncertainty in regard to the horticultural sector but particularly the mushroom sector.  The Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke<b>, </b>will be familiar with the horticultural sector in Lusk, north County Dublin, which is a huge, viable business.  In terms of organics and pursuing the horticultural food sector it is an important sector and one that we need to embrace and support.  It is madness that we are importing peat from Baltic states.  It should stop.  It is not appropriate.  We need to address limited resources of peat and use peat from Ireland for specific targeted areas for the horticultural sector.  I commend the Minister of State on his initiative in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Q00200"><p>I want to raise an issue I am concerned about.  As spokesperson on enterprise, trade and employment I am all about accessing EU funding for the SME sector to support it in any way we can.  I am also all about Ireland never waning on its neutral stance when it comes to being involved in war.  I have deep concerns on the vague wording used about an event happening this weekend.  An event entitled EU Funding for Irish Defence and Security, Enterprise and R&amp;D - Maximising the Opportunities, is happening this weekend.  The Minister for Defence, Deputy Coveney, will be attending.  It is very important that we do not move towards ever encouraging any SME, no matter how stuck we are for jobs, in getting involved in any way in manufacturing anything that can be used as weapons of war even if it is only a small component or something that can be used.  We are a neutral country.  I organised the very first anti-war protest at Shannon Airport before the Iraq war started.  I have protested outside the gates of Leinster House to maintain our neutrality.  This kind of event is deeply worrying.</p> <p>I do not know if I have to appeal to the Minister or to the SME sector.  Just because there is funding for something does not mean we have to go and get it.  There are many other ways of getting jobs and we are working very hard at creating other jobs including the green economy.  I would beg that our SME sector does not go down that road, that it holds on to its morals and ethics around what it gets funding for.  We do not want to turn into a small neutral nation that all of a sudden is supplying in any shape or form anything to do with war.  If wars ever solved anything we would not still be having them.  War is one of the biggest moneymakers in the world.  We know it is a huge global industry.  I have read many books about it.  I try not to get emotional about the money wasted on weapons of mass destruction and on small weapons because it is so wrong.  The terror has never resolved any issues, not in Iraq, not in Afghanistan, not anywhere.  We should have no hand, act or part, and I implore the Minister to tread very carefully with this kind of event.  I implore the SME sector to hold onto its moral compass and never take money that will enable it to manufacture anything that will be used in war.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Q00300"><p>I want to raise the launch of the Society of St. Vincent de Paul Impossible Choices appeal because we are in no doubt now that winter has finally arrived in Ireland with freezing temperatures being felt throughout the country.  This is at a time when inflation and rents are rising and energy costs are skyrocketing.  In its report released today the Society of St. Vincent de Paul said it is expecting as many as 200,000 calls to its organisation by the end of the year.  It is talking to people who face the impossible choice of heating their home, paying their rent and putting food on the table.  One in four people it has spoken to are cutting back on food and utilities.</p> <p>The St. Vincent de Paul appeal comes on the back of another report that came out recently from the Free Legal Aid Advice Centres, FLAC, the Pillar to Post report, which warned of rising household debt that has built up over the pandemic.  At least 36,000 payment breaks have been granted during the pandemic but due to a lack of data that might just be the tip of the iceberg.  We need emergency measures to address the perfect storm we now face this winter.  Sinn F&eacute;in called for a discretionary fund to be put in place to help people with their heating bills.  This was rejected by the Government.  We were told that the budget would increase the eligibility criteria for the fuel allowance.  However, the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Humphreys, has confirmed to my colleague, Deputy Kerrane, that that will only benefit 4,500 households and will not come into effect until 1 January.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Humphreys, confirmed to my colleague, Deputy Kerrane, that the increase in eligibility criteria will only benefit 4,500 households and will not come into effect until 1 January.  People need help now.  They need to heat their homes now.  The impact of energy poverty on households is not just about discomfort, it has real long-term consequences.  There are nearly 3,000 deaths a year related to fuel poverty on this island and children who grow up in poorly heated homes are more likely to develop respiratory diseases and have prolonged absences from school and, therefore, poorer outcomes in their overall life.  However, we still have no energy poverty strategy from this Government.  The last such strategy lapsed in 2019.  Where is the urgency to address what is happening in this country right now with rising energy bills and poverty?</p><p>It is all well and good to tell people to stop burning solid fuels but often, when one lives from week to week, the only way to manage one's budget is to burn solid fuels.  Sometimes that is wood collected from laneways, as was reported in the survey I did, or wood taken from skips to heat a home.  That is how people are heating their homes right now.</p><p>While I commend the Society of St. Vincent de Paul for the launch of its appeal and I would encourage anyone to donate to the organisation, it cannot be an excuse to allow the Government off the hook when it comes to energy poverty.  We need to hear from the Minister for Environment, Climate an Communications, Deputy Eamon Ryan.  We should have a debate on the subject.  Where is the energy poverty strategy?  What are we doing to help those households who cannot afford to heat their homes right now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#R00200"><p>I am passionate about improving breastfeeding supports in this country.  I have been pleased to see that there has been an improvement in supports this year.  That is very much due to the work of Bainne Beatha and Ciudi&uacute;, and is a result of this Government listening to women talk about the need to support those who want to breastfeed.</p> <p>I must put on the record that I am appalled at the attitude within the Passport Office at the moment with regard to what it classifies as a medical emergency.  To give some context, we know there are long delays for first-time passport applicants at the moment.  I know a woman with a young baby whom she is breastfeeding.  She is a Czech citizen but has residency here.  She needs to travel to the Czech Republic on 5 December for urgent surgery and, of course, needs to bring her baby with her because she is breastfeeding that child.  There are long delays in the Passport Office.  I understand it can take up to eight weeks after a passport has been submitted for the Passport Office to begin to process that application.  Because of that long delay, that Czech woman wants to withdraw her passport application but she has been told that she must wait for eight weeks.  She cannot get her own passport back from the Passport Office.  Not alone is she not able to travel at the start of December for her surgery, she cannot bring her baby either because she cannot get a passport for the child.  We have asked about medical emergencies and been told that breastfeeding a baby does not qualify as a medical emergency.  We must see a shift in the mindset within the Passport Office with regard to these exceptional cases.  We must be seen to be promoting and supporting women who choose to breastfeed in this country.</p> <p>I have listened to the arguments about the pandemic unemployment payment, PUP, and why it should not be reopened to applicants and why the cuts that were imposed last Tuesday were justified.  It is worth reminding the House that the cut was imposed on the day restrictions were reimposed for certain elements of the night-time economy.  There have been reports that the Department of Finance has stated that in order to get more construction workers off the PUP and into the sector, the payment needs to be cut.  We must ask what dignity and respect we are affording to workers who are losing their jobs because of the restrictions.  What are we saying to DJs, musicians and people who work as bouncers on the doors of nightclubs about their skills and livelihoods?  We are telling them to go and get a job in a caf&eacute;.  There is a real issue here.  At the start of the pandemic, we did respect people's livelihoods and skills but that has gone over the past week, in particular.  It sends a poor message to those in the arts and culture sector, and to those in the night-time economy, about our respect for their livelihoods.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#S00100"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business, namely, that the Horticultural Peat (Temporary Measures) Bill 2021 be taken before No. 1 on the Order Paper.  We all know the Bill is really important.  I commend the Leader on her work on it.  It is necessary to stop the hypocritical practice of importing peat.</p> <p>I wish to highlight the report of the Ombudsman, Mr. Peter Tyndall, called Grounded: Unequal access for people with disabilities to personal transport schemes.  I have stood here on many a morning raising the inaccessibility of transport services.  I have outlined how each Department is failing in respect of its responsibility to implement the provisions of the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  The scheme for the motorised transport grant and mobility allowance has been closed since 2013.  Many of us have raised issues concerning the disabled drivers and passengers scheme and the ridiculous hoops people have to jump through to get a primary medical certificate from the HSE.  In 2001, the scheme's criteria were highlighted by a former Ombudsman as being extremely limited and excessively restrictive.  I call for a debate on these schemes so we change our rigid, bureaucratic system to allow people to gain access to transport and services and live like the valued people they are in our country.  Every day, I receive emails from people who are just blocked out of, or barred from, our society.  The time is up on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#S00200"><p>I join Senator O'Loughlin in congratulating Christy Moore on his lifetime achievement award.  I am not from Kildare and do not have any connection with the county but I am a lifelong fan of his.  I tried to get tickets with my son for his next concert but they were just gone when I did so.  Maybe if he is listening, he will send complimentaries to me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#S00300"><p>That might be a breach of standards in public office regulations but there is no harm in trying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#S00400"><p>I wish the Ceann Comhairle, Deputy &Oacute; Feargha&iacute;l, well and a speedy recovery from Covid.</p> <p>I have two specific questions for the Leader, which I will follow with one point.  When will the gambling control Bill be before the Oireachtas?  Are there any answers to my questions on the need to deal with the waiting lists affecting child and adolescent mental health services, CAMHS?  I would like those questions addressed.</p> <p>I have two practical solutions to propose in the context of dealing with climate change.  First, given the threat to energy supply, there should be community wind turbines looking after every community and feeding energy into the grid and sometimes making money for them.  This could be based on the co-operative model that worked and developed Ireland at the end of the 19th century and in the early 20th century.  It should be done immediately.  It can be done and should be done in every community.  A wind turbine should be put in each community for that community.  That is the first point on which I would like the Leader to follow up.</p> <p>Second, a small section of each farm in the country could be planted rather than having an ambitious plan to plant whole tracts.  A few acres of each farm could be planted.  This could be incentivised.  Most farms, certainly in the part of the world I come from, have a few non-arable acres, a few difficult acres or a few acres in a bad place.  These could be planted.  They would comprise a carbon sink.</p> <p>I had better observe good timekeeping because I will assume the Chair and cannot ask others to do what I do not do myself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#S00500"><p>I do not know what it is with Fine Gael and these free tickets.  If its members are not looking for Kylie Minogue tickets, they are looking for Christy Moore tickets.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The United Nations 16 days of activism begin on 25 November, which is International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women, and end on 10 December, which is Human Rights Day.  Human trafficking, which is a $150 billion global industry, is one of the greatest examples of violence against women and girls.  In addition, millions of women and girls are forced to marry and to work in terrible conditions for little pay and no chance of education.</p><p>Ireland's Actions Against Trafficking in Human Beings, which is the submission of the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission, IHREC, to the Council of Europe Group of Experts on Action Against Trafficking in Human Beings, came out in October.  According to that report, Ireland is both a destination and a transition country for trafficking in persons.  Overall, more women than men are trafficked in Ireland, and almost all are migrants.  Certain sectors, such as hospitality, fishing, agriculture and construction, may rely on a workforce of people in vulnerable situations.  At the same time, victims of trafficking for sexual exploitation are almost exclusively migrant women.  Trafficking for the purpose of sexual exploitation in Ireland is highly gendered.  Based on the sources to date, it is established that at least 34 minors, mostly girls, have been trafficked in Ireland since 2013.  The UN special rapporteur on the sale and sexual exploitation of children, including child prostitution, child pornography and other child sexual abuse material, visited Ireland in May 2018 and published a report on her visit in November 2019.  In her report the rapporteur pointed to a lack of a dedicated and integrated strategy to respond to sexual violence against children.  She further noted gaps in data gathering, barriers within the criminal justice system and the need for care and recovery services to be bolstered around the country in order that services available to child victims are timely and continuous.  IHREC recommends that the State works with the Central Statistics Office to develop a methodology for collecting uniform and reliable data on the scale and different forms of sexual abuse and exploitation of children, in line with the recent recommendations of the UN special rapporteur's report on the sale and sexual exploitation of children.  Perhaps we could get the Minister for Justice to come before the House for a debate on this very serious concern.  It is awful to think that 34 children in our country have been trafficked since 2013.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#T00300"><p>I congratulate my colleagues on Dublin City Council who approved the scheme to build 853 homes on the Oscar Traynor site.  It includes 40% cost-rental, 40% social and 20% affordable housing and is a physical manifestation of the legislation that was passed in these Houses, so we should congratulate the Minister on that.  It is a hugely welcome development but there are other really important developments around the city, such as St. Michael's Estate, where I would like to see a scheme approved.  I raised this last week and the Minister has agreed to meet the community behind the cost-rental model in St. Michael's Estate.  I would like to see more fresh impetus behind that scheme.</p> <p>I am disappointed that the Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, has sought to exclude from the redress scheme those who were in mother and baby homes for less than six months.  I know other people have raised this.  I saw today that 30 clinicians have written to the Minister to say how damaging early childhood trauma can be and that it is shocking that these people have been excluded.  Whether you are one day or one year in such a place, it will have a really detrimental impact on you.  In the space of six months there is ample opportunity to be emotionally or physically abused.  Many children were boarded out, sometimes adopted out illegally or sent to industrial schools.  I would like to know the rationale for the exclusion of those who spent less than six months in these homes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#T00400"><p>This Friday is Black Friday, which promotes a huge amount of Christmas shopping, predominantly done online.  We see today promotions about buying on Black Friday and they will get greater and greater in number over the coming days.  It is the day on which you can get products cheapest, supposedly.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Garret Ahearn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=GarretAhearn&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If there was ever a year when we should try to promote local shopping, it is this year.  The Government has supported businesses throughout the pandemic, over the past 18 months and longer, but there is no greater support that an individual can give than to go into his or her local shop to buy a shirt or book because the money goes back into the community.  As attractive as some online offers seem to be in the context of people getting the best sale price they will ever get, much of the time this does not seem to be the case.  The prices are put up for a period in order that they can be dropped again for Black Friday.  The latter has become a phenomenon in America and there are major sales online in Ireland.  The Government needs to do as much as it can to support businesses in small towns such as the one I am from, Clonmel.  I accept, however, that Clonmel is actually a fine size.  If the Government or the Department of Enterprise, Trade and Employment could set up a campaign of some kind for businesses that greatly rely on support from their local communities, that would be great.  We should encourage people, this year above any other, to shop locally and support local businesses as much as possible and to spend their money in shops in Clonmel and other towns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#U00200"><p>Like others, I listened to Peter Tyndall, the Ombudsman, speaking this morning about his frustration regarding the abject failure of successive Governments to assist people with disabilities with transport schemes.  We know that two key schemes were scrapped in 2013, namely, the mobility transport grant and the mobility allowance.  These were grants which allowed people to purchase motorised vehicles or to access taxis to go to work, to shop and to take part in the life of their communities.  It is bad enough that they were scrapped in 2013, but the fact that there are still no schemes in place for these people eight years on is just unacceptable.  I cannot imagine what it must have been like for people with disabilities listening to the Ombudsman express his deep frustration as he leaves his role and stating that after eight years in the job he has made no progress and that there appears to be no one in government willing to listen and take action on this key issue.  We often talk now about previous Governments and what they should have done, but this Government is not delivering for these people and nor did that which preceded it.</p> <p>How can it be that we have a Government which appears to be happy to sit with its arms folded and continue to discriminate against people with disabilities eight years on?  There is absolutely no excuse for this.  The Ombudsman made the point very clearly that the reason there has not been any action is because the Government is not prepared to spend the money.  That is not my view; it is the view of the Ombudsman as he leaves his role.  I am asking for an urgent debate on this issue.  It is incumbent on all of us to ensure that this action is not delayed any further as eight years of failure are more than enough.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#U00300"><p>Today is 23 November.  It is almost exactly one month to Christmas.  I know that we all want to look forward to Christmas but all of the media talk and speculation is about lockdowns, shutdowns and circuit breakers.  It is three weeks since I contributed to the Order of Business because I was also hit with Covid-19.  Everybody is very alert to the infection rates and we are all frightened.  We have all been there and nobody wants to go back to the lockdowns.</p> <p>I do not believe that a lockdown is inevitable.  I listened to Dr. Tony Holohan.  He clearly stated that nobody has yet been infected, has been hospitalised or has, sadly, died in December.  With 80% of the population vaccinated and with more than 7.8 million vaccines administered, with the booster campaign already delivered to the most vulnerable who we are protecting, and with the Covid-19 certificate being more widely used and accepted, a lockdown is not inevitable.  We certainly have to increase, however, the public&rsquo;s ability to conduct their own screening such as people who are not symptomatic but who are engaged in education, entertainment, retail, in public transportation, all of whom are considered now to be high-risk activities which we need to recognise.</p> <p>The Government and the Cabinet are meeting this week and are considering all of the actions they can take to support businesses, the entertainment and hospitality sectors and all other sectors.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Fitzpatrick:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MaryFitzpatrick&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I urge the Leader to urge the Government to make antigen tests free and freely available instead of &euro;5 a test.  We want people to screen themselves two or three times a week, which is what people need to do when they are not symptomatic, to ensure they are safe and engaging in safe activities.  We need the Government to make antigen tests free.  I ask the Leader to write to the Taoiseach and the Cabinet subcommittee on Covid and urge them to make this tool available to the general public, who are reducing their contacts and increasing their social distancing.  They are doing everything they can to avoid a lockdown.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#V00200"><p>I want to raise the issue of the messaging through all sources of media on a lockdown in the middle of December.  It is having a serious effect, particularly on many people in the tourism and hospitality industry, including pubs and restaurants.  My party colleague, Councillor Colin Dalton, works for a local cash and carry that covers the midlands.  I spoke to him this morning.  Businesses are afraid to order in advance for Christmas based on what is in the media.  They are afraid of being left with out of date stock.  We need to come out quite clearly and state that we will not have a lockdown.  We need to push a new communication message to get more people to get vaccinated.  There is a responsibility on the 7% of people who have not been vaccinated to look at the effect they are having on our hospital service.  I spoke to a relative who works as a theatre nurse manager in one of the major hospitals in Dublin.  A significant number of theatre staff are not vaccinated.  Unvaccinated staff are not allowed to work in theatres so hospital management must try to get agency staff to cover theatres because of staff who have not been vaccinated.  There is a responsibility on people.  We need to reinforce this message ahead of Christmas.  It has to be our priority this year.  We do not need a lockdown.  Businesses have suffered enough.  We need to support them.</p> <p>David McRedmond, the chief executive of An Post, was on the radio this morning.  As everyone knows, I work with An Post.  There is a responsibility throughout the Government to support the network.  It is a very difficult period for An Post.  Our social welfare business dived dramatically during Covid.  It is reducing by 12% per year.  The long-term future not just of rural post offices but of the entire network including in cities is at a very difficult stage.  I urge colleagues from all parties to support the network throughout the country.  It has huge significance for all of our communities.  The local post office is about maintaining communities throughout the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#V00300"><p>I send my sympathies and best wishes to the Ceann Comhairle, who has Covid.  I hope he is not affected too badly by it.  I will continue on the theme Senators Conway, Carrigy, Fitzpatrick and others referenced on Covid and next month.  Here we are on 23 November and the month of December is traditionally the most important for the licensed trade and hospitality business, at between 2.5 and three times the normal month.  It is not like closing in March, November or October.  It is a significant month.  Of course we have to have balance and of course we have to make sure we are safe but it is so important that we encourage people.  We must look at the figures and try to make sure everybody knows the vaccination system is very safe.  I know we got a lot of emails in response to something I said to the Leader on another day.  They really work.  If we look at the figures that came out yesterday, the 54% in ICU who are unvaccinated are generally younger and extremely healthy before they get Covid but they end up in ICU.  They are healthy younger people who just did not think it would affect them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerry Horkan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2476"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2476&amp;amp;pid=GerryHorkan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Everybody who has been vaccinated and is in ICU has an underlying condition.  We wish them all well.  However, the point is that vaccines work.</p><p>As others have said, vaccine certificates should be required for entry into gyms and hairdressers.  Why not introduce such a requirement for supermarkets and public transport?  I know it is difficult to police some of these things, but really, if people want to participate in society, they need to be vaccinated.  If they do not want to participate in society, that is okay.  They can stay at home; that is their business.  However, unvaccinated people are putting themselves, their families, the rest of us and the economy at risk.  None of us wants a lockdown.  It is in all of our hands to behave as best we can.  We can socialise safely.  If people are vaccinated, it is unlikely to do them too much harm if they do not have a pre-existing condition.</p><p>I ask the Leader to organise a proper discussion of this issue.  New communities may not be as tuned into mainstream media, newspapers and radio.  Let us ensure all are aware of the benefits of vaccination.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#W00200"><p>Last Friday, Senator Ruane and I had the honour of participating in the launch of a short film called "Turning Down the Volume", which was produced by our respective drugs task forces.  Senator Ruane is the chair of the Canal Communities Local Drug and Alcohol Task Force and I am the chair of the D12 Local Drug and Alcohol Task force.  First, we must remind ourselves the drug task forces, as we all commonly refer to them, are actually drug and alcohol task forces.  We recognise, particularly following the entry into force of the Public Health (Alcohol) Act 2018, that alcohol is a problem.  It is a drug and it affects communities and people's health.  Three people die every day of alcohol-related illnesses in Ireland.</p> <p>The short film is extraordinary.  It has hand-drawn by Sadhbh Lawlor and Gary Gowran.  It shows and demonstrates the incredible increase in the supply of alcohol and in the number of outlets supplying it in our respective areas, between the canal communities and Dublin 12.  In the period between 1991 and 2018, the number of outlets supplying alcohol increased from 45 outlets to 125 in what is quite a small community.  If you live in that area, at any one moment, you are no more than 300 m away from an outlet that will sell you alcohol.  For those who are recovering in the community, coping with the aftermath and trying to hold it together, especially in Covid times when it has been especially difficult and stressful, a short walk brings them past probably four outlets that sell alcohol.  I wish to bring the film to the attention of Members.  It is coming everybody's way.  It is going to be used by the drug and alcohol task forces and youth groups throughout the country.  It is very powerful and impactful.</p> <p>I congratulate the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, on having the courage to bring forward the Commencement matter on the minimum unit pricing of alcohol in January.  That will make a huge difference.  The figures are such that for every citizen over the age of 15 in this country, 40 bottles of vodka are consumed per year.  It is an extraordinary consumption.  Indeed, consumption has increased by 425% over a very short period of time.  We need to take that very seriously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#W00300"><p>Today, we show yet again how the Seanad makes a difference.  On behalf of the Fine Gael group, the Leader of the House, Senator Doherty, together with Senator Robbie Gallagher, presented the cross-party Horticultural Peat (Temporary Measures) Bill 2021 today.  The Bill shows how we can deal with the practical impact of the lack of peat for the horticultural industry, and that industry only.  Currently, peat is being imported, which does not make sense.  The Bill shows how to deal with those practical impacts.  It is a temporary measure and will support growers.  Only 0.12% of the total of Irish peatland is required to deliver the measure.  As highlighted by Senator Doherty, importing peat involves high monetary and environmental costs.  It is practical temporary step we can put in place until there is a viable alternative.  Limiting the number of licences will also ensure it is used for the domestic market only.  It is a practical measure that will be in place only for a short time until we have practical alternatives.  It is a measure that will prevent the higher costs of importing peat into this country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aisling Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AislingDolan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I thank Senator Doherty for working on cross-party lines and for working with us as well to pass the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#X00200"><p>I second the proposed amendment, which is very important.</p> <p>I raise the issue of the high cost of road diesel.  Tomorrow, the Irish Road Haulage Association will hold a demonstration outside Leinster House and will probably bring the city and the country to their knees.  Many road hauliers' businesses are on the line.  It is difficult for them to keep going in light of the high cost of road diesel over recent months.  That is not taking into account the carbon tax increase that will be in place from next May.  I propose the Government examine this issue and provide some form of rebate for road hauliers.  The price of diesel affects everybody because it increases the cost of food and the cost of the transport of food, including in regard to exports.</p> <p>More than any other country, we need road hauliers.  Most of our exports and goods in general are trafficked by lorries and road haulage.  The industry is a must for this country and is very important.  Hauliers would not plan to demonstrate tomorrow were they not feeling the pinch.  I ask that the Government introduce some sort of rebate.  We did this before in regard to road tax on goods vehicles, which was reduced a number of years ago, and something similar should be done to resolve the predicament faced by these people, who give a great service to this country.</p> <p>Never before was the cost of transport so competitive.  It is a very competitive industry.  This will put some hauliers out of business and will, eventually, affect the competitiveness of the entire industry.  Will the Leader convey that message to the Government?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#X00300"><p>I echo the accolades expressed to our colleague and friend, Christy Kelly, who is retiring after 40 years' service.  He is a gentleman and a pleasure to work with.  I thank him most sincerely for his tenure in the Houses of the Oireachtas.</p> <p>I support Senator McGreehan and commend the Leader and Senator Gallagher on the horticultural Bill.  It is farcical that we are importing peat.</p> <p>I rise primarily to seek a debate on the future of sport, particularly boxing.  There seems to be an all-out civil war in Irish amateur boxing.  The representative association's annual general meeting, AGM, scheduled for next weekend, has been deferred.  Candidates have been put forward and then retracted and 25 members were expelled last week.  Members of the Dublin, Leinster and Connacht clubs have voted no confidence in the central council.  It is a great concern that people of the calibre of Andrew Duncan are being treated the way they are.  I know him well.  He is a person of value, substance and high integrity who puts the sport of boxing first, second and third.</p> <p>Our boxers should be revelling in the joy of last summer with the deeds of Kellie Harrington and others who have achieved Olympic success.  Instead, there has been an Oireachtas committee meeting on Irish amateur boxing and there will be an independent review.  Will the Minister of State with responsibility for sport, Deputy Chambers, come to the House for a debate on boxing?  Let us bring an end, once and for all, to this ongoing review that is damaging the sport of boxing from grassroots level to high performance.  The young boys and girls of our boxing clubs, and our young adults and potential and current Olympians, deserve boxing to be free from rancour.  Will the Leader invite the Minister of State to appear before the House for a debate on the future of sport, especially boxing, in our country?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Y00100"><p>There is a chill in the air as we approach winter.  We all feel it a little bit but the colder weather has not stopped the good people of D&uacute;n Laoghaire and south-east Dublin from swimming in the sea, despite the temperature having fallen so much.  We know the benefits of sea swimming and how good it is for the cardiovascular system and for building up the immune system.  There is no doubt about that.  The people who go swimming at Seapoint, the Forty Foot, Hawk Cliff and Sandycove are entitled to a minimum standard of water quality.  At the moment, they are not guaranteed it.  I go swimming less often than I would like.  The quality of the water varies greatly from one day to the next.  It is reasonable for people who swim in the sea to expect the water to be clean and hygienic and for it to be unlikely that they will pick up an infection, possibly bacterial, because the water being discharged from sewage plants is not properly filtered and cleaned.  UV treatment and ongoing monitoring of the water throughout the year, and not just in the summer, is needed.  People swim all year round and should be entitled to expect high-quality water all year round.  They should be given assurance by Irish Water, the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage and local authorities that the water is clean and free of bacteria that might make them sick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Y00200"><p>I could not agree more with Senator Ward, particularly since our swimming pools were closed for such a prolonged period.  Even people who are not as brave as some of those who have been doing it for years have taken to our seas.  I see it outside my office in Skerries all of the time.  It is just wonderful.  The very least people expect is for the water to be tested and for guarantees to be given.  I do not know if D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council, in the Senator's neck of the woods, continues to test, but Fingal County Council certainly does in ours.  I can write to Irish Water if that would be of any assistance to him.</p> <p>Senator Buttimer asked for a debate on sport.  I brought the issue of boxing, which Senator Carrigy raised last week, to the attention of Deputy Chambers.  I am very sorry to hear that the situation has deteriorated even further.  I can contact the Minister of State's office again today to see if we can schedule a debate not just on boxing, but on sport in general.  I will come back to the Senator on that.</p> <p>Senator Paddy Burke raised the issue of the impending protests, which we are aware are to take place tomorrow.  The increase in the price of fuel is driving an awful lot of the discontent in certain industries.  The haulage, taxi and transport industries expressed concerns over the weekend.  I will certainly bring the Senator's concerns to the Ministers for Transport and Finance and let them know what the feedback is.</p> <p>A number of colleagues raised the issue of the Horticultural Peat (Temporary Measures) Bill 2021.  I will be very pleased to accept the amendment to the Order of Business in that regard.  I thank colleagues for their help.  I will take this opportunity to thank all of my colleagues for their assistance and support.  I ask all of our Opposition colleagues to look favourably on the Bill after they have had an opportunity to look at it.  There is a briefing session tomorrow.  We hope to schedule debate on the Bill in the coming weeks.  There is a crisis in the industry that is not of the industry's own making.  I totally acknowledge that the Government should have addressed this issue before now but I hope it will now see our Bill in the spirit intended and understand its intent.  It aims to bring this issue to a conclusion by providing a derogation to the industry, which supports 17,000 jobs and, more importantly, produces food for every one of us, supplying the supermarkets and markets we go shopping in every week.  I thank Senator Dolan for raising the matter today.</p> <p>Senator Seery Kearney talked about the video, "Turning Down the Volume".  I wish her well.  She highlighted some shocking statistics.  I was sitting there and thinking that, because I do not drink vodka, it does not apply to me but that just means that somebody else is drinking a number of bottles on my behalf if the numbers are right.  I am sure that is true for many people in the country who do not drink spirits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Y00300"><p>That adds to the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Y00400"><p>That accentuates the problem and makes it even larger than it seems.  I will try to organise a debate on that level of consumption and the State's reaction to that growing issue.</p> <p>Senator Horkan and others raised an issue.  It is interesting to see that for every person who gives out about the fact that new restrictions may come in between now and Christmas, there is another who would very much welcome such restrictions.  That is not only the case in here, but in society.  Society is very divided at the moment.  People need to have the opportunity to earn a livelihood.  We have taken that away from too many people for too long.  We should do absolutely everything possible to keep businesses, venues and entertainment, including swimming pools, sporting venues, GAA clubs, restaurants and bars, open.  We need to keep society open.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We must do everything we can to ensure we keep it open.  The many people who are minded to be more cautious - last night the survey carried out by RT&Eacute; showed that many people would welcome restrictions - can certainly take care, mind themselves and change their behaviours, but we have to try to keep society functioning as much as possible, not least the schools.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Z00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Z00300"><p>However, I will certainly organise a debate.  There is one scheduled with the T&aacute;naiste on business supports in the next couple of weeks, but I have attempted to seek debates from a health perspective, a transport perspective and a business perspective and I will organise them as soon as I get dates.</p> <p>Senator Carrigy, among others, mentioned the lockdown issue.  I listened to Mr. David McRedmond on RT&Eacute; this morning and heard his welcome call seeking more business to be put through the An Post network of more than 900 post offices around the country.  I appreciate they are doing banking on behalf of some of the pillar banks that have pulled out of some towns, which is an awful pity, but there is a great deal more that the State can do and should be doing.  During my time in the Department of Social Protection they played a huge role in alleviating fraud in respect of the social welfare payments made through the system.  One of Mr. McRedmond's biggest criticisms this morning was the fact that the pandemic unemployment payment, PUP, was paid directly into people's bank or Revolut accounts.  I have to be honest with Senators.  Obviously, I was a Minister at the conception of the PUP.  It was done for speed.  Many people did not have post office accounts so we just had to do it.  However, we have managed to tweak and refine that payment over time and now it is being wound down, but we certainly should be looking towards increasing the social welfare payments through the post offices.  It was a vital flow of revenue for them, but it also ensured that we saved revenue because of the human interaction with payments.  It is something we should definitely return to.</p> <p>Senator Fitzpatrick mentioned lockdown and the media, and asked for antigen testing to be free.  That is something I concur with and I have been saying it until I have probably been blue in the face, but I believe we will get there eventually.  I am aware that the Minister, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, is bringing a memorandum to the Cabinet next week.</p> <p>Senator Gavan asked for a debate on the Ombudsman.  I have put in a request.  This morning's report is shocking and I am not taking away from it.  It is a sad reflection on the response of this Government and its predecessor to the shelving of the mobility grant scheme in 2013.  I acknowledge the Senator said that today.  I have a debate scheduled on the cost of disability report that I commissioned in 2019.  That might encompass both aspects because transport is obviously a huge cost for people who have different abilities or disabilities but if the Senator would like a separate debate, he might talk to me afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Z00400"><p>I thank the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#Z00500"><p>Senator Ahearn spoke about the need to shop local, particularly this year.  It is probably more important this year than it has ever been.  We will have campaigns in all our localities to try to support businesses on our high streets.  It is absolutely vital given how businesses have been afflicted in the last 18 months.</p> <p>Senators Ardagh and Boyhan mentioned the passing of permission last night for 853 homes to be built on Oscar Traynor Road.  That is very welcome.</p> <p>Senator Keogan spoke about violence against women and the 34 minors who were trafficked in Ireland in the last number of years.  The most shocking thing about that for me, if it was not shocking enough in itself, was the fact that it was two women who were trafficking those young girls in Ireland.  For the life of me I could not get my head around how a woman would use a young girl or woman in that industry.  However, the Senator asked for that debate and I will certainly organise it.  It will probably be in the new year, but I will do it as quickly as I can.</p> <p>Senator Joe O'Reilly had specific questions about the gambling control Bill and the CAMHS waiting lists.  I do not have an answer for the Senator, but I will make the request for the information today and refer back to him.</p> <p>Senator McGreehan spoke about the Ombudsman's report and referred to the provision of primary medical certificates.  She talked about valuable members of our community.  We all have them where we live.  There is a saying, if I do not get the words wrong, that the measure of any state is how it treats the most vulnerable.  We have left a lot to be desired, but we have an opportunity to raise this, supported by the Ombudsman's report, and to say that the time has come to stop talking.  We all acknowledge that it will cost money, but everything costs money.  It is about our choices, as Senator Gavan has said previously.  I thank the Senator for raising that.</p> <p>In response to what Senator Sherlock said, I cannot even fathom it.  First, I do not believe a woman should have to tell the Passport Office that she is breastfeeding just so she can get a passport to bring her small baby with her back to her country.  All of us have reflected in the last couple of months on the difficulties there have been in the Passport Office.  To be honest, it is infuriating to deal with it at present, and that is not to say that the officials are not trying their best.  They are lovely and helpful.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is dysfunctional at the moment.  The Senator has highlighted how dysfunctional, which is a real shame.</p><p>Senator Boylan talked about the Society of St. Vincent de Paul appeal that is being launched today, something it does every year.  We reflect on the fact that it is kind of sad that as a State we need to have these appeals every year.  We as a nation have hundreds of charities that do enormous and incredible work for different sections of society and different people who, at different times in their lives, need a little bit of a helping hand, although not necessarily consistently.  The Society of St. Vincent de Paul is one of the most loved and much lauded charitable organisations in the country.  I wish it success this year because it has extra families to help due to a number of reasons.  </p><p>I want to correct something that Senator Boylan said, namely that Sinn F&eacute;in had asked for discretionary funds to be made available for people.  They are already available, and have been available for probably 30 or 40 years, through the Department of Social Protection  They are called exceptional needs payments.  For the past number of years, the availability of those payments have become freer.  Some &euro;24 billion of taxpayers' money is now being spent through the Department.</p><p>Senator Garvey mentioned an event the Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney is going to, which she thinks it is inappropriate.  If it is okay with the Leas Cathaoirleach, I will get more details of the event because if, as alluded to, I would think it is probably not appropriate.  I do not have all the details so I will come back to the Senator.</p><p>Senator Boyhan spoke about the peat Bill, and I want to thank him and welcome his positive contribution.  He mentioned the fact that planning for 853 homes had been passed yesterday evening.  </p><p>Senator Conway expressed his concerns and wishes around expanding Covid certificates to other services.</p><p>Senator Fiona O'Loughlin, along with the Leas-Chathaoirleach, wished Christy Moore continued success.  He has entertained all of us.  I do not think we think we own him just because we are from Kildare.  We all think we own a little bit of him because he is such a legend and a fabulous musician.  </p><p>On a more serious note, Senator O'Loughlin mentioned that her cross-party committee on dementia had a significant presentation from Professor Sean Kennelly.  The advances that are being made are wonderful, in particular for dementia and Alzheimer's patients.  We can now know about it years before it is diagnosed.  It is to be hoped that in a lot of cases, people are diagnosed before it is too late and the advent or onset of dementia and Alzheimer's disease is slowed down.</p><p>Nobody referred to Amanda Brown, so I would like to mention her.  She was on RT&Eacute; radio this morning.  I do not know if anybody knows who she is.  She is the stepdaughter of the late David Tweed.  I want to put on the record that her bravery, courage and, in particular, her dignity this morning was humbling.  She is a powerful woman and the testimony she gave and the fight she has had over a number of years is genuinely humbling to observe.  She deserves and requires the support and respect of people who have made inappropriate comments on the passing of David Tweed over the past couple of months.  I want to put on the record of the House that I thought she was powerful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.85" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Senators" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#AA00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#AA00300"><p>Judging by the reaction, that has the endorsement of Senators across the Chamber.</p> <p>Senator McGreehan has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 22 be taken before No. 1."  The seconder was Senator Paddy Burke.  The Leader has indicated that she is prepared to accept this amendment.  Is the amendment agreed to?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.87" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.88" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#AA00500">Horticultural Peat (Temporary Measures) Bill 2021: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#AA00600"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the Planning and Development Acts 2000 to 2021 and the Environmental Protection Agency Acts 1992 to 2011 to make exceptional provision for peat extraction for the purpose of horticulture for a temporary period in the public interest in order to mitigate the adverse consequences resulting, or likely to result from an interruption to supply and to provide for a just transition.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.90" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#AA00800"><p>When it is proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#AA00900"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#AA01000"><p>Is that agreed to?  Agreed. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.94" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.10 p.m. and resumed at 2.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.95" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD00100">Planning and Development (Amendment) (Large-scale Residential Development) Bill 2021: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I wish to advise Members that this business will be concluded at 4.30 p.m.  I remind them that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage, with the exception of the proposer of the amendment, who may reply to discussion on the amendment.  On Report Stage, each non-Government amendment must be seconded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD00300"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 23, after &ldquo;other&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;higher&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD00400"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD00500"><p>This amendment seeks to stipulate that when the Minister designates an amount of large-scale residential development, LRD, floor space which must be used for housing, the figure may only be higher than the 70% figure in this Bill.  It is important that when we speak about LRD planning permission that it is used primarily to deliver housing and not for commercial interests.  I have further amendments in respect of this which I will speak to regarding what the remaining 30% of land should be used for to foster sustainable communities.  The crux of this amendment is what the Minister can stipulate in respect of that figure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD00600"><p>I thank Senator Ruane.  This is one that we discussed at length on Committee Stage.  My position has not changed.  It is considered that these amendments would be overly prescriptive.  We are changing it now to improve it from 15% to 30% but the intent is to allow the discretion with the local authority.  I do not have to advise Senators that we had an extensive debate on Committee Stage when there was lots of really good interaction.  This is about restoring planning to local authorities.  If we are restoring it to local authorities, we need to allow them and the planners to make those decisions.  I believe that up to 30% is the correct balance to strike.  We want brownfield development and mixed development, particularly within our cities where there has been a massive issue with regard to viability.  I thank the Senator for tabling the amendment but I have not changed my position and will not be accepting it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD00700"><p>I will press the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.102" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD00900"><p>Amendments Nos. 2 and 10 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD01000"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 25, after &ldquo;development&rdquo; to insert the following:  	&ldquo;with regard to the LRD floor space not used for the purposes of housing, a public consultation shall take place with individuals and community groups which the planning authority shall have due regard to in determinations of the granting of permissions for such floor space&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD01100"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD01200"><p>This amendment relates to public participation in the shaping of the new residential areas which will be built using LRD planning and permission.  With regard to LRD floor space not used for the purposes of housing, the amendment provides that there would be a public consultation for individuals and community groups which the planning authority would have regard to in the granting of permissions for that space.  The Government has spoken a lot about this legislation and new processes in the delivery of housing but it is essential that the process seeks to engage the public as much as possible in the creation of new communities.</p> <p>Amendment No. 10, similarly to amendment No. 9, will provide that with regard to student accommodation, the Minister shall provide for consultation with educational institutions, representative student bodies and elected members of the planning authority, who may in the course of such a consultation set out conditions in respect of student accommodation to which the planning authority must have due regard in rendering an opinion under section 32D.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#DD01300"><p>We do not want to be overly prescriptive with regard to what the planners do.  We need to ensure when we are bringing back planning to local government that we allow them to operate and make the decisions.  The amendment relates to the definitions section of the Bill.  I do not believe inserting an obligation on planning authorities in the definitions section is appropriate and the amendment does not provide for how and when such consultation would take place.</p> <p>In respect of amendment No. 10, educational facilities, developments and consultation with educational institutions, student bodies and elected members of the planning authority, again we discussed this in some detail the last time.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As part of a normal two-stage planning process, we believe that would be the time for submissions to be made where people are concerned by an application, or are positive or negative about it, and that they would do that by way of a submission.  Again, both of these were discussed at some length on Committee Stage.  I have not changed my view on them and I will oppose the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.109" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#EE00300"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 4, line 36, to delete &ldquo;academic term times&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;the academic year&rdquo;  </blockquote> <p>This amendment, which was raised with the Minister by my colleague, Senator Higgins, on Committee Stage, seeks to change the period in which student accommodation can be used for purposes other than housing for students, from outside of the academic term time to outside the academic year.  This is to address concerns that at Christmas, students who are revising for exams and students who may have to remain in student accommodation, in particular international students, do not have security of tenure in their accommodation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#EE00350"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#EE00400"><p>Again, this amendment has been re-tabled.  In fairness, Senator Higgins outlined her position on this and I explained why I did not believe it would be appropriate.  My primary concern regarding student complexes is that they should not be used as permanent residential accommodation or as a hotel or hostel.  I issued this circular a number of weeks ago.  They are dedicated student accommodation complexes and that is how it should be, particularly always having regard to the general shortage of student accommodation.  We are tackling the matter and intend for it to happen.  I am happy that this provision is appropriate and it strikes the right balance for considering whether student accommodation development goes through the LRDs process.  I cannot accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.113" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#EE00600"><p>Amendments Nos. 4, 5 and 20 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed to?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#EE00700"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 6, between lines 8 and 9, to insert the following:  	 <blockquote> 	&ldquo;(ea) details of the manner in which obligations under the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with a Disability, with due regard to the principle of universal design and regulations under Statutory Instrument Number 513 of 2010, have been reflected in the proposed development;&rdquo;.  </blockquote>  </blockquote> <p>On Committee Stage similar amendments to this were proposed to be included in information that the Minister may prescribe as a requirement for an LRD meeting.  This amendment is a requirement that information on how obligations under the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, UNCRPD, and Part M of the convention, have been reflected in the proposed development.  We must ensure that the rights of people with disabilities to accessibility under Article 9, and to independent living under Article 19 of the UNCRPD are upheld and vindicated by the State when it comes to housing.</p><p>Amendment No. 5 stipulates that a calculation of the expected greenhouse gas emissions, including emissions from embodied energy expected through construction or demolition in the proposed development, should be included in information submitted before an LRD meeting.  We need to take account of the impact of development on our emissions, to estimate those emissions, and to ensure that the most sustainable building practices are being used and are reflected in the law in Ireland.</p><p>Amendment No. 20 seeks to insert criteria into the determination of the application by the planning authority, particularly changes in building and planning guidelines, obligations under the UNCRPD, or other such issues that may have arisen as part of an area development planning process. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#EE00750"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#EE00800"><p>I thank Senator Ruane for these amendments.  Again, we went through these in great detail on Committee Stage.  I propose to address amendments Nos. 4 and 20 first.  These are matters far more appropriate for building control and are dealt with in our building control and standards legislation rather than planning legislation.  The area of the rights of persons with disabilities is one that we all espouse and we make sure that we do have universal design concepts in place too.  To have this in the Bill, however, would simply take one element of building control and planning design and put it into the Bill as opposed to all others.  We do not think it is appropriate to put these amendments into the Bill.</p> <p>On amendment No. 5 and climate emissions, I debated this at length with Senator Higgins.  The whole area of embodied carbon emissions is addressed in the climate action plan and construction products regulation.  It is not appropriate for inclusion in this legislation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I cannot accept any of the three amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF00200"><p>I completely agree with the Minister.  To express carbon emissions so thoroughly within a Bill is inappropriate.  However, it would be remiss of me, as a member of the Joint Committee on Disability Matters, not to highlight the fact that witnesses have come before the committee to report that building regulations are not centred on their needs.  Their ability to visit properties is catered for but their ability to stay over is not.  People can come and visit but there is no requirement for their needs to be catered for further.  It is fine if they are visiting the ground floor but there is no facility if they need to go upstairs.  When we come to building regulations and all those other aspects, we must ensure the voices of people with disabilities are included at the centre of the discussion and influence the outcome so that there is nothing about us without us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.120" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF00400"><p>I move amendment No. 5:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 6, between lines 8 and 9, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(ea) a calculation of the expected greenhouse gas emissions, including emissions from embodied energy, expected through construction or demolition in the proposed development;&rdquo;.   </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF00500"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.123" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 and 7 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF00800"><p>I move amendment No. 6:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 6, between lines 8 and 9, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(ea) details of the manner in which the local development plan or county development plan of the local authority in which the site is located is reflected in the proposed development;&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF00900"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF01000"><p>My amendment in this grouping would stipulate that the developer must provide details of how the local or county development plans have been reflected in their proposed development ahead of the LRD meeting.  It is welcome that we are returning to the two-stage planning process but we must ensure the voices of local government and local communities are enhanced in the planning process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF01100"><p>I wholly endorse this amendment.  Without rehashing and going over what we said last week, participative engagement by citizens and elected members of city and county councils is vitally important.  We need to see it in the context of a form of local government.  I posed a question here last week and thereafter received calls from three sitting councillors in Limerick.  I did not think too much about the issue until I received those phone calls yesterday.  If we are to have an elected mayor of Limerick, as we and others have been advocating, that mayor would have no function under the new legislation we are bringing in.  The mayor would be out of all of this.  We may change legislation in the future but we must strengthen the powers of our elected members in local authorities.  That engagement existed in the strategic housing development, SHD, process.  It is important that the LRD process will restore the previous two-stage planning process by returning the primary decision-making functions to the planning authority and the appeal mechanism to An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  As politicians, we sometimes get caught up in all the words and legislation but there must be three or four key measures, when one drills down into the matter.  In fairness, the Minister has said that repeatedly.  That is an important measure.  When I leave this Chamber, I like to think that I take away some concise messages and retain the full integrity of what they mean when I pass them on.  This is one of those key measures.  We are going away from the terrible SHD process.  We can forget about who was responsible and who prolonged that process.  That was yesterday and it is in the past.  Going forward, we will now have a two-stage process and I welcome that.  I support this amendment, in particular.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF01200"><p>I too welcome this amendment.  My colleagues and I were happy on Committee Stage when the Minister indicated a positive attitude towards this amendment.  I am aware that Senator Boyhan has worked with the Minister on this provision and I am glad that the role of the local authority members is being represented in this legislation.  The habit of SHD applications working outside the relevant county development plans has been a bone of contention for councillors for years.  I hope that our move towards this new LRD process will place a higher, more appropriate onus on the work of our local councillors in planning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#FF01300"><p>I thank the Senators for their contributions.  We have discussed these amendments and they have a great deal of merit.  The two amendments are similar.  I said on Committee Stage that we would work together to see how we can move the situation forward.  There is merit in such proposals although I did flag there may be issues around structure and wording.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I note that the Senators have come back with a revised wording for such a provision.  As I have said, amendments Nos. 6 and 7 are very similar but I am happy to accept an amendment in this regard.  Given that amendments Nos. 6 and 7 aim to provide for a broadly similar provision, we do not need both amendments.  I recognise that Senators Boyhan, Keogan, Higgins, Ruane, Craughwell and Black have all worked on similar amendments.  Therefore, I am accepting amendment No. 7 as the wording is consistent with the general wording of the Bill.  That is the amendment that Senators Boyhan and Keogan have just been talking about.  I would genuinely like to thank all Senators from both sides of the House for the constructive nature of the discussions around this provision.  To put it in context, Senator Boyhan is right when she says it is about bringing planning back to local government.  The SHD process review said it was good that councillors were involved in the submission stage, but it only went to the board then.  As we discussed on Second Stage and Committee Stage, we want to have both.  When every application is lodged, every local elected representative is going to know about it.  He or she must be informed about it.  It must not happen on an <i>ad hoc </i>basis and must not depend on which council is involved.  Every councillor will be advised when an LRD is applied for.  I thank the Senators for amendment No. 6 but I cannot accept it.  Amendment No. 7 is more precise and I am happy to accept it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#GG00200"><p>  Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#GG00300"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 6, between lines 13 and 14, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(ga) a statement setting out how the proposed LRD has had regard to the relevant objectives of the development plan or local area plan in whose area or areas the proposed LRD would be situated, and&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#GG00350"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#GG00400"><p>  Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#GG00500"><p>Amendments Nos. 8 and 9 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#GG00600"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 6, line 41, to delete &quot;development.&quot; and substitute &quot;development, including elected members of the local authority.&quot;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#GG00700"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#GG00800"><p>I am conscious that we are under time pressure.  We have discussed much of this before.  It is disappointing that the Minister has not accepted the amendments we discussed on Committee Stage, which would retain the right of the city and county council.  The Minister made his case with regard to it.  We had a vote on it as well, and clearly it was not supported by any of the Government parties in the House.</p> <p>It is important that city and county councils, given their collective views, their huge involvement locally and their huge knowledge of their communities, would be supported.  This is a reasonable amendment.  As I said before, it is important to value their contribution.  All this amendment would do is give discretion to the planning authority to engage with local councillors ahead of an LRD meeting to get their perspectives on matters of interest or concern to the community that should be taken into consideration.  After all, these people represent the community.  Rather than having a situation where planners say to councils that they cannot discuss applications with them because the legislation bars them from doing so, we are proposing to give them the right and the discretion to engage.  We must recognise that we are merely giving the planners some discretion.  I recognise the enormous and valuable work done by planners.  I want to put it on the record that they work hard, often under pressure in terms of resources, time and expertise.</p> <p>Planning has become a complicated issue.  I am saying it is important to send a clear message.  I took the trouble to look at the number of Government Ministers, Deputies and Senators who have engaged or made objections.  I remind the House that observations are not always negative.  As the Minister said earlier, it can be an observation.  We always talk in the negative.  People can make positive contributions and positive statements in regard to planning.  It does happen.  I have certainly done it.  I have sent in submissions of a positive nature.</p> <p>I want the message to go out loud and clear today that we will support city and county councils in their efforts with the planners to have an opportunity to share their local knowledge and their understanding of the community.  Ultimately, planners make decisions.  We are back to a two-stage process.  I reiterate that this proposal will not stop any individual councillor from sending in a submission in his or her own right.  There is something to be gained in terms of that shared engagement.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I like the idea that it is open and transparent.  It is not a matter of someone having a word with a planner in a room; it is a matter of a formal meeting at which concerns are shared.  Ultimately, it is an executive function of the planners to make the decision.  I hope the Minister can support and accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#HH00200"><p>I also call on the Minister to support and accept the amendment.  It is a simple amendment, not one that forces the hand of or constrains the planning authority in any way.  It simply adds an express reference to the elected members of the local authority where the legislation sets out that the planning authority may meet persons who have relevant information prior to the LRD meeting.</p> <p>When we think of relevant information when it comes to planning, our councillors should be at the forefront of our minds.  As Senator Boyhan pointed out, local ties, boots on the ground, the eyes and ears of the community and knowledge of the physical area and the social environment all serve to place our elected members in a prime position to contribute in an indispensable way to decisions made regarding planning in their areas.  I hope the Minister will consider accepting the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#HH00300"><p>I acknowledge the engagement the Minister had with Fianna F&aacute;il councillors and other councillors through Senators.  He fully understands the need for councillors to be able to engage.  That will happen but it is important to put on the record of the House that the Minister has engaged widely with councillors, certainly through our group.  He has attended meetings and explained his position to those in attendance.  That has to be acknowledged.  The Minister fully understands the importance of engagement with councillors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#HH00400"><p>Amendment No. 9 relates to the proposed development of student accommodation.  When such development is proposed through the LRD process, there should be consultation with "community groups, residents' groups from the affected areas, member groups of public participation networks, student unions, groups with relevant heritage or environmental expertise".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#HH00500"><p>I thank the Senators.  We accepted the previous amendment, but we cannot accept every amendment.  I will give the reasons we cannot accept those under discussion.  We have discussed this.  Let me return to the original point.  This is about restoring planning functions to local authorities, which is what the Government wants; however, it is also about restoring the primacy of the development plans.  We discussed this the other night.  I refer to the crucial matter of having boots on the ground whereby councillors have the reserve function to put together development plans because they know their areas.  It is from them that the plans emanate.  The purpose of the LRD arrangement is to have a return to the two-stage process.  The primacy of the development plans is restored, and this is also the case in respect of the local area plans and master plans.</p> <p>On consultation, let me refer again to the proposed section 32B(4).  It states: "The planning authority may, prior to the LRD meeting taking place, consult with any person who may, in the opinion of the planning authority, have information that is relevant for the purposes of the LRD meeting in relation to a proposed development."  This is very clear although I understand where Senators want to get to.  I outlined to Senator Higgins the last day my view on the idea of a local authority reaching out beyond the public consultation process and asking a myriad of groups what they think.  We are trying to streamline and improve the planning process while recognising that, in many areas of planning, there are roadblocks that inhibit the development of homes for students and others.  We need to make the system better while restoring local authority responsibility.  I am not accepting either amendment, but I thank the Senators for their contributions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#HH00600"><p>I am disappointed.  I will be pushing this to a vote, partly because I have given a commitment to the city and county councils that I will pursue it.  I went through the legislation line by line and thought really hard about this matter.  This is where I stitched it in the provision because, as the Minister has rightly said, it allows the planning authority to engage with a community.  All we are asking for is an explicit reference to elected members of local authorities.  It is very simple.  Instead of using the proposed mechanism, let us put a reference in primary legislation.  Do we believe in the city and county councils?  Do we really believe they have a role to play?  Do we really believe they will not interfere with, or undermine, the system?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Do we really believe they have a role to play?  Do we really believe they will not interfere with or undermine the system?  I believe in them.  More importantly, the AILG and LAMA came before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Planning and Local Government and made a very strong case for this.  They are on the record and on the report for that meeting as having done so.  I understand from talking to them as early as this morning that they were clear.  Their understanding is that the executive took a decision.  They submitted two papers to the committee and I gave a commitment at that committee that I would stand by them and support them.  Ultimately, Members make decisions.  I want to stand by the decision I made to them.  The AILG and LAMA sought this in their submissions.  They are representative bodies of the city and county councils.  It is a reasonable request to allow this additional line including elected local authority members.  I am somewhat surprised that we did not get that from the Minister, but that is his call.  I will push this amendment to a roll call vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#JJ00200"><p>I refer the Senators to section 34 of the principal Act which, as amended on Committee Stage, means that every councillor will know when every application is lodged under this process.  It states:</p> <blockquote> 	Where a planning authority receives an application for permission to which section 32A(1) applies it shall&mdash;  	(a) notify the elected members of the planning authority of the making of the application, of where the application is available for inspection, and of such other information as may be prescribed.  </blockquote> <p>That removes any discretion.  Planning lists were being issued on an <i>ad hoc</i>basis in certain local authorities.  I respect our councillors, as Senator Boyhan knows.  This Government, since taking office, has done work on councillors' terms and conditions, maternity leave, with the Minister of State, Deputy Burke, me and others, and restoring powers to local government.  We will continue to do that.</p><p>I understand the thrust of the Senators' amendments.  I do not think they are required.  They might in one respect be overly onerous for many in that they apply to every single application that is made.  I have already allowed for the fact that, and made sure that, the planning authority lets every elected member of that local authority be aware of this.  I thank the Senators for tabling their amendments but I will not accept them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.148/1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#JJ00300"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 7; Níl, 27.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Sharon Keogan and Victor Boyhan; Níl, Senators Jerry Buttimer and Robbie Gallagher.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.148/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2021-11-23" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#JJ00300">
            <divisioncount ayes="7" noes="27" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" vote="aye">Lynn Boylan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" vote="aye">Sharon Keogan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" vote="aye">Marie Sherlock</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" vote="no">Catherine Ardagh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" vote="no">Malcolm Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" vote="no">Miche&aacute;l Carrigy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" vote="no">Pat Casey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" vote="no">Shane Cassells</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" vote="no">Ollie Crowe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" vote="no">Regina Doherty</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" vote="no">Aisling Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" vote="no">Mary Fitzpatrick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" vote="no">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" vote="no">R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" vote="no">Pippa Hackett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" vote="no">Erin McGreehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" vote="no">Eugene Murphy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" vote="no">Fiona O'Loughlin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" vote="no">Mary Seery Kearney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" vote="no">Barry Ward</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.148/3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#JJ00300"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.149" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee has advised the Cathaoirleach that she has entered into a voting pairing arrangement with Senator Eileen Flynn for the duration of Senator Flynn&rsquo;s maternity leave and accordingly has not voted in this division.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#MM00100"><p>Amendment No. 9 has already been discussed with amendment No. 8.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN00100"><p>I move amendment No. 9:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 6, after line 41, to insert the following:  	 <blockquote> 	 <blockquote> 	&ldquo;(4A) Consultations referred to in subsection (4) may include, but is not limited to, community groups, residents&rsquo; groups from the affected areas, member groups of public participation networks, student unions, groups with relevant heritage or environmental expertise.&rdquo;. </blockquote> </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN00200"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.153" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN00400"><p>Senator Warfield will deal with the rest of our amendments on our behalf.  We emailed the Seanad Office to that effect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN00500"><p>I move amendment No. 10:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 7, between lines 5 and 6, to insert the following:  	 <blockquote> 	 <blockquote> 	&ldquo;(6) With respect to information provided under subsection (3)(a) with regard to student accommodation, the Minister shall provide for consultation with educational institutions, representative student bodies and elected members of the planning authority, who may in the course of such a consultation set out conditions in respect of student accommodation, which the planning authority must have due regard to in rendering an opinion under section 32D.&rdquo;. </blockquote> </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN00600"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN00700"><p>I am conscious that the amendment was discussed earlier.  It relates to consultation with educational institutions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.158" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN00900"><p>Amendments Nos. 11 and 12 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN01000"><p>I move amendment No. 11:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, between lines 7 and 8, to insert the following:  	 <blockquote> 	 <blockquote> 	&ldquo;(1A) The planning authority shall make the opinion available on its website, together with a copy of plans and other details discussed at the consultation meeting, upon lodgement of the LRD application.&rdquo;. </blockquote> </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN01100"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN01300"><p>These are the final two amendments in my name.  I will be withdrawing amendment No. 11 with the agreement of the House.</p><p>Amendment No. 12 states:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, between lines 17 and 18, to insert the following:  	 <blockquote> 	 <blockquote> 	&ldquo;(2A) The LRD opinion issued by a planning authority under subsection (1) shall be made public when a planning application in respect of the proposed development is made in accordance with section 34.&rdquo;. </blockquote> </blockquote>  </blockquote> <p>I thank the Minister and his officials for the engagement I have had with them.  One issue I had to return to, having thought about it, relates to the independent review body.  I am now satisfied, having had a detailed read of the body's report.  It noted the highly problematic matter of the deficit in community consultation in respect of SHDs.  It stated:</p> <blockquote> 	Although pre-application meetings with both the Planning Authority and the Board may take place over many months prior to a SHD application being lodged, the general public &ndash; and local residents in particular &ndash; have no knowledge about the proposal, and will have only 5 weeks to inform themselves about the application and (if they so wish) prepare a submission to the Board. With larger and more complex SHD applications, this can cause resentment and a perception of being excluded from the process.<br /><br />We consider that the making the Board's 'Opinion' available to the public following the submission of a SHD planning application, together with a copy of the plans and other details discussed at the tripartite consultation, would alert interested members of the public in relation to a prospective application. However, they would need to be informed about the availability of the Opinion, e.g. by means of the Planning Authority&rsquo;s weekly list of applications and decisions [or its website or whatever mechanism a planning authority would use, or may use, in future]. </blockquote> <p>The amendment will give effect to the review body's proposal in the cases of the LRDS.  While it will do little to address the democratic deficit this legislation retains or to remove it, it will ensure the community has the maximum information at its disposal at the point where it has to get to grips with what are very complex issues for many laypersons, such as the application itself and related issues.</p><p>I could go on but I think the Minister has got the gist of what I am seeking.  I can give more detail, depending on his response.  I hope he will accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN01400"><p>I, too, hope the Minister will accept the amendment.  It will allow for increased community consultation with regard to large-scale residential developments.  It will be a great improvement on what is quite often a deficit in communication with regard to SHDs.  Involving community stakeholders is a must in regard to developments of this size on account of the profound impacts they will have on areas and communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#NN01500"><p>The purpose of the legislation is to get communities involved.  Senator Boyhan quoted from the review committee's report, which relates to SHDs, but the SHDs will cease to exist on 17 December.  New applications will be through the LRD, with the exception of the transitionary arrangements that are in place.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I understand where the Senator is coming from with the two amendments.  We discussed the matter at length on Committee Stage.  The language in amendment No. 12 better reflects what we want done.  I want transparency within the process.  The Senator intends to withdraw amendment No. 11.  My officials worked directly with him on this.  I will accept amendment No. 12.  I believe it improves the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO00200"><p>I thank the Minister for that.  I appreciate his response and wish him well in continuing with this legislation.  I thank him for his time and thank his officials for their engagement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.167" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO00400"><p>I move amendment No. 12:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, between lines 17 and 18, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(2A) The LRD opinion issued by a planning authority under subsection (1) shall be made public when a planning application in respect of the proposed development is made in accordance with section 34.&rdquo;.   </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO00500"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.170" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 13 and 14 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO00800"><p>I move amendment No. 13:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, after line 44, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;<b>Insertion of section 32H into Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>32H. </b>Where new regulations with regard to planning, including regulation in respect of the environment and disability, supplementary documentation must be submitted to the planning authority by applicants who have received permission under section 32A(1), but where the development has not commenced, which demonstrate incorporation of any new regulations.&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO00850"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO00875"><p>This amendment would require that, in the case of new regulations with regard to planning, including regulations in respect of the environment and disability, supplementary documentation which demonstrates incorporation of any new regulations must be submitted to the planning authority by applicants who have received large-scale residential development, LRD, permission but whose development has not commenced.  I put that on the record on behalf of Senator Higgins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO00900"><p>I thank the Senator.  We covered these matters in great detail on Committee Stage.  I have nothing further to add.  I will not be accepting amendments Nos. 13 or 14.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.176" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO01100"><p>I move amendment No. 14:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, after line 44, to insert the following:  	<b>&ldquo;Insertion of section 32I into Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>32I.</b>(1) Where new European Union Directives are issued in respect of building standards or planning, applicants who have received LRD permission must provide supplementary documentation to the planning authority demonstrating how the applicant has incorporated the new Directives into their development.<br /><br />(2) Where a new LRD application must be made in respect of subsection (1) the State shall not be liable for any costs incurred by the applicant.&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO01200"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.179" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO01500"><p>Amendments Nos. 15 and 17 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO01600"><p>I move amendment No. 15:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, after line 44, to insert the following:  	<b>&ldquo;Insertion of section 32J into Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>32J</b>. Where an application for planning permission to which section 32A(1) applies has been granted but construction has not commenced on that site within a period of 36 months following the decision of the planning authority, such planning permission shall be revoked.&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO01700"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO01800"><p>This amendment relates to the "use it or lose it" clause.  I believe it is a good idea.  Where construction has not commenced within 36 months, the permission would be revoked.  It is a very good amendment but, on behalf of Senator Higgins, I will withdraw it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO01900"><p>Does the Minister wish to come in?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO02000"><p>I will not if it is being withdrawn.  The Senator is correct; we did debate the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.186" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO02200"><p>I move amendment No. 16:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, after line 44, to insert the following:  	<b>&ldquo;Insertion of section 32K into Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>32K.</b>Where an application for planning permission to which section 32A(1) applies has been the subject of more than five successful judicial reviews, the applicant shall not be eligible to apply for LRD planning permission for a period of two years.&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO02300"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.189" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO02500"><p>I move amendment No. 17:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 8, after line 44, to insert the following:  	<b>&ldquo;Insertion of section 32L into Principal Act</b><br /><br /><b>32L.</b>Where an applicant has received LRD planning permission and wishes to sell the site, the applicant shall not do so with the LRD planning permission attached to it. Thus, the LRD planning permission is revoked upon the sale of the site to another person.&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO02600"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.192" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO02800"><p>If amendment No. 18 is agreed to, amendment No. 19 cannot be moved.  Amendment No. 19 is a logical alternative to amendment No. 18.  Amendment Nos. 18 and 19 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO02900"><p>I move amendment No. 18:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 9, to delete lines 13 to 17 and substitute the following:  	&ldquo; &ldquo;(1B) Where a planning authority receives an application for permission to which section 32A(1) applies it shall&mdash; <blockquote> 	(a) notify the elected members of the planning authority of the making of the application, of where the application is available for inspection, and of such other information as may be prescribed, and<br /><br />(b) at the next meeting of each Area Committee concerned, or of the municipal district members for each municipal district concerned, as appropriate, inform the relevant elected members of&mdash; <blockquote> 	(i) the details of the application, and<br /><br />(ii) the consultations and meetings that have taken place in relation to the proposed development.&rdquo;,&rdquo;. </blockquote> </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO03000"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#OO03100"><p>The Minister spoke about bringing planning back to local government.  That is what we are trying to do.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Wall:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarkWall&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->He and other speakers have mentioned the importance of councillors in the planning function, and this is an attempt to do that with regard to notification of planning applications to be discussed.  That is why we are proposing it.  We discussed it on the previous occasion as well.  I look forward to hearing what the Minister has to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP00200"><p>I appreciate that we debated this at some length.  I want the involvement of elected councillors.  I reiterate that what the Government is doing, in fairness with the support of the Opposition heretofore, is restoring planning to the local authorities.  The primacy of the development plan is very important.  I have read into the record the two sections whereby councillors will be directly involved.  Every application lodged under this process will not just be copied to every councillor, but every councillor will be notified as a matter of course and not at the discretion of the local authority.  We want to ensure that while we are doing this, we are streamlining the planning process as well and making it more efficient and effective while giving people a chance to have their say.  The first observation period will be at the stage when an application is lodged, and rightly so.  Councillors will have the ability to make their views known for free at that stage.  Then, should somebody not be happy with the decision, it can go to An Bord Plean&aacute;la as was previously the case prior to SHDs for developments of more than 100 units.</p> <p>In this instance, I understand the purpose of both amendments being tabled.  I also discussed this with Senator Fitzpatrick.  We would like to have an opportunity to consider this in a little more detail in advance of the Bill going to the D&aacute;il.  There is something in them, but I do not want to create another step in the planning process.  I thank Senators Wall, Sherlock, Moynihan, Hoey, Fitzpatrick and Davitt for tabling these amendments.  I have had some discussion on them.  We will have a look at this in advance of going to the D&aacute;il and I will reference the Seanad, if that is okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP00300"><p>I wish to comment briefly on this.  If I do not do so now in respect of amendment No. 18, amendment No. 19 will have been discussed.  I will move amendment No. 19, but I will speak to it now.  The amendments are similar in nature and are grouped together.  I was a member of a local authority for 12 and a half years and many Members were members of local authorities for various periods of time.  It is vital that councillors have their say and an involvement, but I take on board that the Minister is going to reflect on this and, hopefully, bring the spirit of this into the legislation when it goes through the Lower House.  I will be happy to move and withdraw the amendment when we reach it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP00400"><p>I will not delay the debate, but I acknowledge the comments from Senator Wall and the Minister.  The amendments are quite similar, but the most important thing is that it clearly states that there will be this for councillors, because they will have to be notified.  That is important, and councillors have been telling us that.  I acknowledge the fact that the Minister will have a look at this and, hopefully, we will have a situation where councillors will have this notification put in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP00500"><p>I welcome the Minister's comments and I will withdraw the amendment on the basis that he will examine this for the next Stage.  I appreciate that and thank him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.202" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP00700"><p>I move amendment No. 19:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 9, to delete lines 13 to 17 and substitute the following:  	&ldquo; &ldquo;(1B) Where a planning authority receives an application for permission to which section 32A(1) applies it shall-- <blockquote> 	(a) notify the elected members of the planning authority of the making of the application, of where the application is available for inspection, and of such other information as may be prescribed, and<br /><br />(b) at the next meeting of each Area Committee concerned, or of the municipal district members for each municipal district concerned, as appropriate, inform the relevant elected members of the details of the application.&rdquo;,&rdquo;. </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP00800"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP00900"><p>I propose to withdraw the amendment based on the Minister's comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.206" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP01100"><p>I move amendment No. 20:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 9, line 28, after &ldquo;environment,&rdquo; to insert the following:  	&ldquo;changes in building and planning guidelines, obligations under the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with a Disability or other such issues that may have arisen as part of an area development planning process,&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP01200"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.209" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#PP01400"><p>I move amendment No. 21:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 10, between lines 3 and 4, to insert the following:  	<b>&ldquo;Limit of duration of permission</b><br /><br /><b>6. </b>Section 40 of the Principal Act is amended by the insertion of the following subsection after subsection (3): <blockquote> 	&ldquo;(4) Notwithstanding subsection (3), where a planning authority grants a permission to which section 32A(1) applies&mdash; <blockquote> 	(a) &lsquo;the appropriate period&rsquo; means the period of 12 months beginning on the date of the grant of permission, and<br /><br />(b) section 41 shall not apply in relation to the permission.&rdquo;.&rdquo;. </blockquote> </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ00100"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ00200"><p>This was discussed on Committee Stage.  I would like to hear the comments of the Minister again.  It about using or losing planning permission.  We are all aware of the problems with SHDs.  The Bill attempts to deal with that.  We all want something good to come out of this and to ensure that planning comes back to where we all want to be.  We have tabled this amendment because we do not want land held on an extended basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ00300"><p>I take this amendment in the spirit in which it has been tabled.  We discussed this issue in great detail on Committee Stage.  In terms of using it or losing it, I want permissions that have been granted to be activated.  We need to do that.  It is something that can be done through the introduction of the zoned land tax, land value sharing and other measures that we are bringing forward.  For large-scale developments, I genuinely think setting a 12-month timeframe would be really problematic.  There was a general understanding that good permissions that had been granted could not be activated if this clause was introduced.  I do not mean this in a condescending way.  I know the spirit in which the amendment has been tabled is well meaning.  We all want to make sure that permissions are activated.  Setting an arbitrary 12-month limit would cause a problem.  I have not changed my views since Committee Stage and I cannot accept amendment No. 21.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ00400"><p>Do any other Senators wish to speak?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ00500"><p>I accept what the Minister has said.  I still want to press the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.216" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ00900"><p>Amendment No. 22 in the names of Senators Warfield, Boylan, Gavan, &Oacute; Donnghaile, Higgins, and Black has been ruled out of order as it would involve a potential charge on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ01000"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ01100"><p>Unfortunately, I do not think we cannot take a point of order on this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ01200"><p>For the record, I am looking to keep things the same.  How could there be a cost on the Exchequer if there is no change being made?  I am seeking to delete the section, so there could not possibly be a cost or charge to the Exchequer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ01300"><p>If the Senator wishes, he can bring that up with the Seanad Office.  Unfortunately, the amendment is considered out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.222" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 22 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ01500"><p>Amendment No. 23 in the names of Senators Higgins, Ruane and Black has been ruled out of order as it would involve a potential charge on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.224" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 23 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ01700"><p>Amendment No. 24 is in the name of Senators Higgins, Ruane and Black.  It arises out of committee proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ01800"><p>I move amendment No. 24:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 10, line 27, to delete &ldquo;as expeditiously as possible&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;in an appropriate manner&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ01900"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ02000"><p>This amendment would require the Supreme Court to act as expeditiously as possible in determining a case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ02100"><p>We are not supporting the amendment.  We discussed this matter at length previously.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ02200"><p>Do any other Senators wish to speak to the amendment?  How stands the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ02300"><p>I will withdraw the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.232" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ02500"><p>Amendment No. 25 in the names of Senators Higgins, Ruane and Black arises out of committee proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ02600"><p>I move amendment No. 25:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 16, line 16, after &ldquo;may&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;not&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ02700"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ02800"><p>This is about providing a consultation in respect of the development under subsection (7), which currently provides that no consultation would be required where a planning authority receives received a request under this section.  I am happy to withdraw the amendment on behalf of Senator Higgins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.237" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#QQ03000"><p>Amendment No. 26 in the names of Senators Higgins, Ruane and Black arises out of committee proceedings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR00100"><p>I move amendment No. 26:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 16, between lines 27 and 28, to insert the following:  	<b>&ldquo;Insertion of section 247A into Principal Act</b> <b>16. </b>The Principal Act is amended by the insertion of the following section after section 247:  	 <blockquote> 	<b>&ldquo;247A.</b>With regard to a development to which section 32A(1) relates&mdash; <blockquote> 	(a) the planning authority shall convene a final consultation meeting within four weeks of receipt of the prospective applicant&rsquo;s request, to be attended by the planning authority, the prospective applicant or his/her representative, or both, and planning authority officials who have sufficient level of relevant knowledge and expertise in the matter concerned and members of the public, who may subsequently submit observations to the planning authority within two weeks,<br /><br />(b) the planning authority on receipt of the request, may issue the documentation received, or parts thereof, to any relevant prescribed bodies that in the opinion of the planning authority may have relevant observations in relation to the proposed development including relevant Community organisations,<br /><br />(c) the failure of a prescribed body to respond to a request under paragraph (b) shall not prevent the planning authority from proceeding under section 247A to deal with the request concerned,<br /><br />(d) the planning authority shall be required, within six weeks of the holding of the final consultation meeting, to form, and issue to the prospective applicant, and other relevant prescribed bodies, an opinion as to whether the documents submitted for the final consultation meeting constitute a reasonable basis for making an application for permission for the proposed development.&rdquo;. </blockquote> </blockquote>  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR00200"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR00300"><p>Senator Higgins has been contacted by several residents and groups seeking more input into the planning process in respect of LRD developments.  This would involve additional consultation in that regard and I would welcome a response from the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR00400"><p>We have discussed this point at some length.  I am opposing this amendment because it effectively adds an additional level of consultation to the LRD process and what we are doing, effectively, in this legislation is to allow for proper consultation.  Bringing planning back to local authorities means that residents or any interested groups will be able to make their observations at the first stage and will not have to wait until an application goes to An Bord Plean&aacute;la.  The current situation partially accounted for why we have seen an increase in judicial reviews, because groups and interested parties felt they did not have a say during the initial stage.  This proposed amendment seeks to add another layer to the consultation process, but we have greatly improved that aspect already in this legislation.  I am, therefore, opposing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR00500"><p>How stands the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR00600"><p>I am happy to withdraw it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.245" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR00800"><p>Amendment No. 27 in the names of Senators Warfield, Boylan, Gavan and &Oacute; Donnghaile arises out of committee proceedings.  Amendments Nos. 27 and 28 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR00900"><p>I move amendment No. 27:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 17, line 10, to delete &ldquo;16 weeks&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;8 weeks&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR01000"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR01100"><p>I thank Senator Wall.  The Minister is not accepting these amendments, but I appeal to him in this regard.  He said this SHD process was going to end in February, but it is not ending then and will continue into April for the first category of applicants and into June for the second category of applicants.  Neither I nor my party see any justification for giving a period of 16 weeks to those people who have got their pre-planning approval.  We propose to give them eight weeks instead.</p> <p>Regarding the second category, concerning those people putting their applications in now, we believe they should be rolled into the proposed new LRD process and not given access to the SHD process next year.  We must end this thing.  The Minister made a point regarding how we had opposed transitional arrangements in this context, but this is essentially an invitation for people to get their applications in.  The Minister has a terrible habit of saying he is going to do something, and then we get the longest goodbye possible, accompanied with an invitation for people to get their applications in.  We saw that happen with co-living and we see it here again.  Therefore, I am pressing my amendments and I will bring them to full votes, but I appeal to the Minister to accept them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#RR01200"><p>We have discussed this aspect already.  I welcome the Senators' engagement with this legislation and thank them for it.  I genuinely welcome that Members of all parties and none are supporting this legislation which will bring a significant change to the planning process.  It is required.  I also welcome Senator Warfield and his party coming around to accepting the need for a transitional arrangement, unlike on Second Stage, where they did not believe that transitional arrangements were needed at all.</p> <p>Passing this Bill would see the new LRD process start from 17 December, and that is what we are aiming for.  If applicants have engaged with the additional SHD process, through the formal pre-planning process, then it is not possible to move them out of that process and into another one.  It is not a long goodbye and we are not extending this situation.  It was the same with co-living, by the way, where we had to include screening for a month.  We did what we said we would do with co-living and this Government has ended that concept.  </p> <p>The reality, however, is that we must provide for a transition in this case, and we are doing that.  We have outlined the process and the timelines involved clearly.  Subject to the legislation being passed by the Oireachtas and signed into law, we aim to have the new LRD process commence from 17 December.  Therefore, I think we have moved as quickly as we can.  Most people will understand that applications in the current system must conclude under the planning system and law that pertained when they were submitted.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If we do not do that then we would be open to challenge of all types.  It is better to have a clean cut with this and that is what we are doing.</p><p>I understand that the Senator seeks to reduce the number of weeks from 16 to eight but I cannot accept either of the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#SS00200"><p>I wish to press the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.253/1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#SS00300"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 7; Níl, 29.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Fintan Warfield and Niall Ó Donnghaile; Níl, Senators Jerry Buttimer and Robbie Gallagher..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.253/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2021-11-23" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#SS00300">
            <divisioncount ayes="7" noes="29" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" vote="aye">Sharon Keogan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" vote="aye">Marie Sherlock</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" vote="no">Catherine Ardagh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1633" vote="no">Niall Blaney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" vote="no">Malcolm Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" vote="no">Miche&aacute;l Carrigy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" vote="no">Pat Casey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" vote="no">Ollie Crowe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" vote="no">Regina Doherty</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" vote="no">Aisling Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" vote="no">Timmy Dooley</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" vote="no">Mary Fitzpatrick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" vote="no">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" vote="no">R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" vote="no">Pippa Hackett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" vote="no">Erin McGreehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" vote="no">Eugene Murphy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" vote="no">Fiona O'Loughlin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" vote="no">Mary Seery Kearney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" vote="no">Barry Ward</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.253/3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#SS00300"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.254" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee has advised the Cathaoirleach that she has entered into a voting pairing arrangement with Senator Eileen Flynn for the duration of Senator Flynn&rsquo;s maternity leave and accordingly has not voted in this division.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#VV00100"><p>I move amendment No. 28:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 17, line 25, to delete &ldquo;16 weeks&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;8 weeks&rdquo;. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#VV00200"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.257/1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#VV00300"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 7; Níl, 29.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Fintan Warfield and Niall Ó Donnghaile; Níl, Senators Jerry Buttimer and Robbie Gallagher..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.257/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2021-11-23" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#VV00300">
            <divisioncount ayes="7" noes="29" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" vote="aye">Sharon Keogan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" vote="aye">Marie Sherlock</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1630" vote="no">Catherine Ardagh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1633" vote="no">Niall Blaney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" vote="no">Malcolm Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" vote="no">Miche&aacute;l Carrigy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" vote="no">Pat Casey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" vote="no">Ollie Crowe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" vote="no">Regina Doherty</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" vote="no">Aisling Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" vote="no">Timmy Dooley</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" vote="no">Mary Fitzpatrick</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" vote="no">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" vote="no">R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" vote="no">Pippa Hackett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" vote="no">Erin McGreehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" vote="no">Eugene Murphy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" vote="no">Fiona O'Loughlin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1694" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" vote="no">Mary Seery Kearney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" vote="no">Barry Ward</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.257/3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#VV00300"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.258" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee has advised the Cathaoirleach that she has entered into a voting pairing arrangement with Senator Eileen Flynn for the duration of Senator Flynn&rsquo;s maternity leave and accordingly has not voted in this division.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#XX00100"><p>I move amendment No. 29:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 17, after line 42, to insert the following:   	<b>&quot;Report on operation of Act </b><br /><br /><b>18.</b>The Minister shall, within 30 months of the passing of this Act, lay a report before the Joint Oireachtas Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage outlining&mdash;  <blockquote> 	(a) the proportion of sites, expressed as a percentage, which have been granted LRD planning permission where construction has not commenced, <br /><br />(b) the proportion of sites, expressed numerically and as a percentage, which have been granted LRD planning permission and have subsequently been sold, <br /><br />(c) the proportion of land, expressed in hectares, which is the subject of LRD planning permission and is owned by real estate investment trusts, and <br /><br />(d) the number of completed housing units under the LRD process which remain vacant.&quot;.  </blockquote>  </blockquote> <p>We need to know this process is delivering housing and is not being exploited for profit or dominated by the real estate investment trusts, REITs, which are not delivering the housing we need in the State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#XX00200"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#XX00300"><p>We discussed this on Committee Stage.  I thank the Senators for retabling the amendment.  I want the permissions to bring about homes for people.  That is what we earnestly want.  It means a big change in the process.  I say genuinely respectfully that this amendment, as written, would be absolutely unworkable.  I envisage the Oireachtas committee having a role in seeking information on what permissions have been granted and activated, but the amendment refers to "within 30 months of the passing of this Act".  The legislation will pass with the Senators' support and will be in effect from 17 December this year.  There is a lead-in period, which we have discussed, but new applications that have not been in the process will start to come in after 17 December.  Even though we are going to have very strict timeframes, we need to get the process up and running.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Darragh O'Brien:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2178"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2178&amp;amp;pid=DarraghOBrien&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=23"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We will have the pre-application stage, the application stage, the decision stage and the potential to go to the board.  For any applicant to say that he or she will be in a position to outline what is requested here - and I went through this with Senators Higgins and Black on Committee Stage - just would not be possible as outlined.  However, I can see the role of the joint committee and certainly at the local authority that people would be able to request information of others.  We will have a fully transparent process.  We want to make sure we have a process that is streamlined, that will deliver homes for people and that is not going to just deliver enhanced values on paper permissions.  That is what this Government wants to do.  That is why this legislation is so important and why, to be fair, the Seanad has enabled its swift passage and why I introduced it in this House - so we could tease through a lot of these issues.</p><p>Respectfully, I cannot accept amendment No. 29.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#YY00200"><p>Lots of legislation contains review clauses in it or calls for reports to either both Houses or the relevant committee.  I do not really understand why it is not workable.  Is it the timeframe?  Is it the 30 months?  Is there an alternative way that we can ensure we can report to both Houses on this information just in a different way?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#YY00300"><p>I have no difficulty at all looking at what we can do here by way of reporting.  The Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage, on which I served during the term of the previous Oireachtas, will regularly seek details overall.  We would have seen details on SHD.  Regarding even the division of the four different items, the Senator is being very prescriptive as to what is looked for, and I cannot give a guarantee that we will be able within the first 30 months to have those data.  Of course we will have data, and what we want to see is a throughput of applications that are granted permissions.  We are seeing activation of those permissions.  We can look at what we could do, maybe through the Oireachtas joint committee.  I will have a look at that between now and the Bill's passage through the D&aacute;il to see if there is another mechanism we can use.  All legislation is up for review at any stage.  It will be open to Senator Ruane, as a Senator and a legislator, be it D&aacute;il or Seanad legislation, to bring forward amending legislation that would mean that a Minister would have to come to the House if there were elements of the legislation with which she was not happy.  This is a big piece of legislation and a lot of work has gone into it that we know will improve the SHD process, replacing it, taking what was good out of it, including the pre-application process, but then restoring our planning to local government.</p> <p>I thank the Senator for the amendment.  I cannot accept it here today but we will certainly look at elements of it to see whether they are workable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.265" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.266" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Bill, as amended, received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#YY00550"><p>When is it proposed to take next Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#YY00575"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#YY00587"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.270" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill do now pass."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1561" speakername="Darragh O'Brien" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#YY00700"><p>I thank all Senators for their input and thank my officials.  It has been a very informative, useful and progressive debate as the Bill moved through Second Stage and on to Committee and Report Stages.  The House will have seen that where we have been able to accept amendments, we have done so and worked with Senators.  We will look at a couple of items between now and the debate in the D&aacute;il.  I thank the Cathaoirleach, the team in the Seanad and my officials for the efficient and expeditious way in which this legislation has moved through Seanad &Eacute;ireann over the past week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021112300002#YY00800"><p>I thank the Minister for his presence last Tuesday night into Wednesday morning.  I know that was not quite in his schedule, but we appreciate that he was here for the entire debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.273" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-11-23a.274" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.04 p.m. and resumed at 5 p.m.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>