<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#A00100">Teachtaireacht ó Chomhchoiste - Message from Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#A00200"><p>The Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage has completed its consideration of the Planning and Development Act (Exempted Development) Regulations 2022, laid before the Houses on 11 February 2022.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#B00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.8" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#B00200"><p>I welcome my friend and colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Colm Brophy, to the House.</p><p>I have received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Defence to make a statement on the report of the Commission on the Defence Forces </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the cancellation of major national road projects. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Seery Kearney of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for business, employment and retail to make a statement on progress on the employment regulation order to determine terms and conditions of employment for childcare workers. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the opening of B&oacute;thar Oirialla group home, Carrickmacross, County Monaghan. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on progress in the roll-out of the programme on women&rsquo;s health announced in budget 2022. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Erin McGreehan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on measures to reduce fuel poverty such as utilising surplus renewable energy on the grid. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Miche&aacute;l Carrigy of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the relocation of the Phoenix Centre in Longford. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media to make a statement on the introduction of a basic income scheme for artists. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Barry Ward of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to ensure the establishment of municipal and-or metropolitan districts in all local authority areas. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on fire services infrastructure in Galway city. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lynn Boylan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to provide an update on planning regulations to support the installation of solar panels on homes, schools and businesses. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on resourcing at the adult metabolic service in the Mater Hospital and resourcing for response testing to new innovative therapies for phenylketonuria, PKU, treatment. </blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, the Cathaoirleach has selected Senators O&rsquo;Loughlin, Boyhan, Seery Kearney and Gallagher and they will be taken now.  The Cathaoirleach regrets that he had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Boylan on the ground that it anticipates the Committee Stage debate of the Planning and Development (Solar Panels for Public Buildings, Schools, Homes and Other Premises) (Amendment) Bill 2021, which is scheduled to take place in the Seanad tomorrow, Wednesday, 16 February 2022.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#B00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.10" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#B00400">Defence Forces</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#B00500"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach, and I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Brophy, to the Seanad to discuss this very important issue.</p> <p>I welcome the report of the Commission on the Defence Forces.  There is no doubt that this will foster real debate and, indeed, has started to do that around the defence Ireland needs as a modern European country.  This is very welcome.  It is a substantial report running to 224 pages and making 69 recommendations.  I commend all of those involved in this very comprehensive report.</p> <p>There are many noteworthy recommendations within the report such as: a meaningful transformation in the military hierarchy; an increased focus on cybersecurity; new armed personnel carriers; a larger and more robust naval capacity; a larger aircraft fleet; and many others.  Of course, there was a huge emphasis on the people within the Defence Forces.  That is absolutely the greatest strength we have.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The recommendations for the regeneration plan for the Reserve are critical.  The proposal of regular potential officer courses, what we call the commissioning of the ranks, enables experienced non-commissioned officers to train to join the commissioned ranks.  They are recommendations that the former Minister for Defence, Deputy O'Dea, made in 2006.  In 2022 it is still a recommendation but nothing has happened in between, which is regrettable.  We have to recognise there has been a lost decade for the Defence Forces and that defence needs an increase in current funding and investment to undo the damage caused by neglect and return Defence Forces modernisation to the path originally charted in the 2000 White Paper.</p><p>I hail from Kildare and represented that area in the last D&aacute;il, where I advocated strongly on behalf of the defence community not just in Kildare but across the country.  I have continued to advocate strongly for it in this House.  While I am pleased to see the comprehensive report, I am concerned and slightly sceptical about the implementation process.  We need to see action now.  We have broken the trust of the defence community before by failing to act and this cannot be allowed happen again.  For far too long the Defence Forces have been under-resourced, ignored and not shown the respect they deserve.  This has to be a turning-point for the defence community in my area of south Kildare and across the country.  The days of reports and talking about reports must come to an end.  We need to come to the next phase if we are to revitalise our Defence Forces and if we are serious about attracting people to a career in our forces, which is hugely important.</p><p>In this House last week, I asked the Minister for Defence, Deputy Coveney, to prioritise the immediate establishment of a permanent pay review body in tandem with my party colleague, the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Michael McGrath.  Pay and conditions for Defence Forces personnel must improve and the establishment of this pay review body must be a priority.  I ask the Minister of State, Deputy Brophy, to outline when we will see a comprehensive implementation plan.  How long does the Minister of State estimate full implementation will take?  Will he on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Coveney, commit to prioritising the establishment of a permanent pay review body as a matter of urgency?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#C00200"><p>I welcome to the Visitors Gallery, Ms Nina O'Connor, who is a transition year student.  It is great to see young people interested in our proceedings.  She is the guest of our esteemed colleague and temporary Chair, Senator Horkan.  I invite the Minister of State to respond to the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1573" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#C00300"><p>I am taking this Commencement matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for Defence, Deputy Coveney.  The Minister welcomes the publication of the report of the Commission on the Defence Forces.  The establishment of the Commission on the Defence Forces was set out in the programme for Government and was a key priority for the Minister for Defence.  The publication of the report represents the culmination of the work carried out over the past 13 months and is testament to the considerable efforts of all who contributed to its completion.</p><p>The report is wide-ranging and comprehensive.  As Senator O'Loughlin mentioned, it contains 69 main recommendations and, together with sub-recommendations, there are 133 recommendations in total.  The report proposes significant changes for the Defence Forces, including to high-level command and control structures, and for the level of defence provision in Ireland.  It challenges the <i>status quo</i>across a range of areas and is forthright about the requirement for cultural change in the Defence Forces.  It proposes a range of measures to make the Defence Forces a more inclusive, diverse, equal and attractive workplace.  The importance of the Reserve is also clearly stated.</p><p>The report poses serious questions regarding defence provision that we as a society must carefully consider.  This includes the type of defence capabilities we should retain and the level of resourcing we are willing to commit to in order to equip and train our Defence Forces for the roles we require them to undertake.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Colm Brophy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2427"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2427&amp;amp;pid=ColmBrophy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister hopes that this report will foster real debate about the defence that we need as a modern neutral European country.</p><p>The report sets out three indicative levels of ambition, LOAs.  LOA 1 would encompass the current capability; LOA 2 would enhance our current capabilities and seek to address specific priority areas; and LOA 3 would look to develop full spectrum defence capabilities to protect Ireland and its people to an extent comparable to similar-sized countries in Europe.</p><p>The commission recommended a step to LOA 2 in the short term, pending more detailed policy debate and decision required for higher levels of ambition.  This step up to LOA 2 would require an additional &euro;500 million per annum.  LOA three would require expenditure of &euro;3 billion per annum.</p><p>Clearly, there are matters that require careful consideration and, in some critical aspects, interdepartmental discussion and agreement.  This includes the level of resourcing that may be allocated to defence and the governance framework that will be required to underpin the changes that the commission has recommended.  The Minister is also anxious to engage with key stakeholders in the Oireachtas.</p><p>There have been calls, obviously, for quick movement on the recommendations in the report and I understand that there may be an impatience to move on certain aspects of the report.  The Minister believes that a four- to five-month timeframe is necessary to bring a considered and comprehensive proposal back to Government to address the fundamental issues that the commission has set out.  The Minister intends to engage with key stakeholders in the intervening period.</p><p>Significant work is currently ongoing, which the commission has referred to in its report.  This includes key issues such as the development of a capability development planning process, the work of the independent review into dignity and equality issues, the ongoing procurement of equipment and infrastructure and direct entry competitions and the amendment of legislation relating to the working time directive.</p><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response on behalf of the Minister for Defence.  While I note the points that he made, to be perfectly honest, I cannot understand how the Minister needs five months to prepare his response.  Nothing in the commission's report can be a surprise to him or, indeed, to his officials because for the past ten years we have been listening to the issues, challenges and problems, particularly around recruitment and retention.</p> <p>While much of the public commentary has unsurprisingly been focused on the big ticket items, the real meat of the commission's recommendations relate to structural and system reforms that will go a long way to tackle the twin problems of poor morale and personnel retention.  These are the two biggest issues that we have.  </p> <p>I participated in a meeting of the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence along with the Leas-Cathaoirleach two weeks ago in the Curragh where we heard all of this first-hand.  It used be a situation where those who went into the Army certainly took great pride in their role and in their position.  While they still take great pride, there is certainly a huge lack of morale and that needs to be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1573" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#D00300"><p>As the Senator will be aware, I have outlined some of the key matters in the commission's report.  I will certainly take on board what she has said and the important points that she has raised and bring them to the Minister, in terms of following on from this.</p> <p>I reiterate that given the significant recommendations in the report, that period of consideration is required.  The report will require detailed consideration and interdepartmental consideration.  It is important that having done the work the commission has done, the Minister would get those views clearly from all the stakeholders.  In that context, four to five months is a reasonable timeframe.  The process will proceed from the engagement.  I thank the Senator again for raising the matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.18" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#E00200">Road Projects</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#E00250"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Troy, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#E00300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting this Commencement matter and welcome the Minister of State to the House.  The purpose of this Commencement matter is to highlight the concerns raised by councillors in counties Cork, Monaghan, Longford, Westmeath, Tipperary, Waterford, Offaly and Galway, from whom I have received representations.  I am asking the Minister for Transport to explain the rationale behind the decision to shelve certain major road projects scheduled for this year; and to make a statement on the matter.  The roads that I wish to single out for attention are the N25 from Carrigtwohill to Midleton in County Cork; the N2 from Clontibret to the Border in County Monaghan; the N4 from Mullingar to Longford in counties Westmeath and Longford; the N24 from Waterford to Cahir, County Tipperary; the N25 from Waterford to Glenmore, County Kilkenny; the N52 from Tullamore to Kilbeggan in counties Offaly and Westmeath; and the N59 from Clifden to Maam Cross.</p> <p>The councillors who raised the matter with me said that they were somewhat concerned by the official statement issued by the Department and the Minister, in which the Department of Transport confirmed that the projects had been stalled and would be considered for funding next year or possibly the year after.  An explanation of the rationale for the decision is required.  What is the logic for it?  There may be other valid reasons for the decision that people are simply not aware of.  Perhaps they have been missed.  However, I think there is, and was, an expectation among the Oireachtas Members in these areas and indeed, the citizens and people who travel on these roads and their local councillors, that these works would be done.  The projects are not new; they have long been thought-out.  They were part of the plan and the programme of national roads projects.  I know that the Minister of State is very familiar with these roads.  When people hear and read that local, and particularly important, road projects are shelved for an indefinite period, there is some concern.  It is happening at a time when I thought there was a substantial amount of money around for critical infrastructure, which these roads are.  We cannot argue with that.  It is important to have critical infrastructure for the travelling public but also for the commercial life and the economy of the country.  These are significant and important routes.  I would appreciate it if the Minister of State could shine a light on the issue and perhaps outline some of the rationale behind the decision and a possible timeline for the new dates on which these projects might commence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#E00400"><p>I thank Senator Boyhan for raising this important issue.  I am taking this matter on behalf of the Minister for Transport, who has responsibility for the overall policy and Exchequer funding for the national roads programme, which includes the motorway network along with national primary and secondary roads.</p> <p>As the Senator may be aware, once funding arrangements have been put in place with Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, under the Roads Acts 1993 to 2015, and in line with the national development plan, NDP, the planning, design, improvement and upgrading of individual national roads is a matter for TII, in conjunction with the local authorities concerned.  TII ultimately delivers the national roads programme in line with Project Ireland 2040, the national planning framework and the NDP.  In the new NDP, which was launched in October 2021, approximately &euro;5.1 billion is earmarked for new national road projects up to 2030.  This funding will enable improved regional accessibility across the country, as well as compact growth in our towns and villages, which are key national strategic outcomes.  The funding will provide for the development of numerous national road projects, including the completion of projects which are already at construction stage and those close to it, as well as the development of a number of others.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Robert Troy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2305"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2305&amp;amp;pid=RobertTroy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This year, approximately &euro;615 million of that &euro;5.1 billion of Exchequer capital funding has been provided for national road projects through TII to local authorities.  These allocations were announced on 17 December 2021 and details are available on the website.  Funding for regional and local roads was announced earlier today.  </p><p>I agree wholeheartedly with what Senator Boyhan said regarding the importance of the road projects he outlined.  I thank him for raising this issue on behalf of councillors in several counties.  My colleagues, Senators Paul Daly and Carrigy and Deputy Flaherty have also raised this issue, as I have, with the Minister for Transport.  When the roads projects office is undertaking its planning, it is important for it to have certainty regarding when these projects can progress.  </p><p>As I said, &euro;5.1 billion is earmarked in this regard up to 2030.  We need greater certainty, however, concerning when these roads projects, as outlined by Senator Boyhan, will be progressed.  I know the roads from Mullingar to Longford and Tullamore to Kilbeggan especially well.  In some cases, these projects only require a small amount of money to progress to the next stage.  As the Senator rightly said, the landowners on the routes also need certainty and clarification.  I have been consulting with the Minister for Transport in this regard.  He has assured me that he has brought my concerns to the attention of TII.  I assure the Senator that on foot of his strong contribution on behalf of the councillors in the respective counties that I will now go back to the Minister to ask him to engage with TII to bring certainty and clarity in respect of the road projects highlighted in the Senator's Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#F00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for that comprehensive response.  The disappointing aspect is that these road projects were announced, there was great excitement and press releases were issued.  Local politicians promoted and welcomed these projects, as did the Minister of State.  He travels these roads and two of them relate directly to his constituency.  Therefore, I have every confidence that he will make these projects happen and that he will pursue this matter.</p> <p>We need some sort of indication now that these projects will be back under way in 2023.  I say that because there is some disappointment in this regard and a suggestion that certain elements of the Government are not pro-roads to the same extent.  These projects, however, are critically important.  They concern rural connectivity, communities and the economy.  I thank the Minister of State again for his comprehensive response, and I will come back to him if I need further information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#F00300"><p>The Senator is right.  There has been disappointment.  Nobody likes to see a road project on schedule moving backwards.  We want to see these projects continue to move forwards.  Funding of &euro;5.1 billion has been allocated to the roads programme up to 2030, and in that context the bare minimum required is certainty regarding when these projects can move to the next stage.  The local authorities need to know, as do the impacted landowners and road users.</p> <p>Some of these roads are very dangerous.  They have a high frequency of accidents and require upgrading.  I have undertaken already, and I do so again now, to bring the Senator's concerns back to the Minister for Transport and to try to ascertain a clear timeframe for these projects.  I would like to see a clear timeframe for work to be undertaken on the road from Mullingar to Longford.  It is a busy road and one with a high frequency of accidents.  It went through various stages of work to 2010, and was then paused.  I do not want to see this project paused again.  I undertake to raise Senator Boyhan's concerns with the Minister for Transport and to ask him to respond directly to the Senator.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.25" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#F00400">Childcare Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#F00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for taking this Commencement matter and the Cathaoirleach for choosing it.  In the Programme for Government: Our Shared Future, we stated we would support the establishment of a joint labour committee, JLC, in the childcare sector and the drawing up of an employment regulation order, ERO, which would determine minimum rates of pay for childcare workers, as well as their terms and conditions of employment.  This subject has been particularly close to my heart.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I lobbied hard for this to be in the programme for Government because I have represented the childcare sector.  I have worked with childcare providers during the past ten years prior to becoming a Member of the Seanad and seen first-hand the difficulties they experience in retaining and recruiting staff from the point of view that, in many cases, highly qualified women with experience working in child care could not work in the sector because the cost of living was such that they lost too much by being in full-time employment in the sector and the rates of pay were not sufficient, and that was prior to more recent escalation in the cost of living</p><p>I want to say a big "Thank you" to those involved in the Big Start campaign.  They talked about pay and conditions in childcare.  For example, 66% of early years educators earn less than the living wage and 42% of managers stated they earned less than &euro;15 per hour.  These are the group of people who care for our children, who enable predominantly women to access the workforce and who are dedicated professionals in the creation of care of our children.  It is important they have a career in this sector and that money is red-circled for this sector to support childcare providers in meeting whatever pay and terms and conditions can be put in place by an ERO.  As a Government, we have red-circled money in the budget for later this year.  I am anxious we achieve a timeline on that, that the momentum continues and that by September this year we are in a place where we can be sure the people who are recruited into childcare will stay in the industry, will be able to build careers and grow in the industry, and will be encouraged to pursue higher level education in order that we have that level of expertise for children prior to their going to school. </p><p>I am anxious that we would know we have a constant momentum with respect to this sector.  At what time will we have a report and be in a position where we have an ERO that will apply to this industry?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#G00200"><p>I am responding on behalf of the Minister of State with responsibility for business, employment and retail, Deputy English, who sends his apologies for not being able to be here.  I thank the Senator for raising this important matter.  Everybody knows she is s a very strong advocate for this sector and has worked tirelessly in this area.  This debate gives us an opportunity to reaffirm to those working in early learning and childcare services the recognition they deserve for the very important work they do and the benefits their work brings for children, families and society.  The programme for Government makes extensive commitments to improve access and quality of childcare, and, crucially, we have begun work delivering on those commitments.</p> <p>In recognition of the importance of this sector and the Government&rsquo;s commitment to ensuring high-quality, affordable and accessible services, the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth,, Deputy O&rsquo;Gorman, announced major reform of funding for early learning and childcare following the report of an expert group last year.  Budget 2022 committed to a transformative and groundbreaking package of measures to begin to implement the vision set out in the report.  Some &euro;78 million is being made available to enable this in 2022, including &euro;69 million for a core funding stream, equivalent to &euro;207 million in a full year.  Furthermore, throughout the pandemic, substantial State supports, including the employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS, the temporary wage subsidy scheme, TWSS, and other sectoral specific supports such as the reopening funding package for childcare services have been provided to the sector, which have enabled services to operate safely and ensured the increased costs associated with public health requirements and with lower demand were not passed on to parents.</p> <p>However, on the topic for discussion today, I would like to clarify the Minister of State, Deputy English&rsquo;s, role regarding the ERO for childcare.  As the Senator will be aware, in line with his statutory obligations as set out in the Industrial Relations Act, he approved a recommendation of the Labour Court to establish a joint labour committee, JLC, for the early learning care and school age childcare sector in June 2021.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Robert Troy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2305"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2305&amp;amp;pid=RobertTroy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, policy responsibility for this sector sits outside his remit and is a matter for my colleague, Deputy O&rsquo;Gorman, as the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth.  I understand that the joint labour committee, JLC, for the early learning care and school age childcare sector, which is independently chaired, has met on a number of occasions to date and is progressing its work.</p><p>Proposals for an employment regulation order are formulated in the first instance by a JLC where it is satisfied that such proposals would promote harmonious relations between workers and employers.  The Labour Court then considers whether or not to adopt the proposals of a JLC.  If the Labour Court is satisfied that the proposals are in a suitable form for adoption, the Labour Court adopts the proposals and submits the issue to the Minister of State with responsibility for business, employment and retail.  If the Minister of State is satisfied that the relevant legislative requirements have been met and it is appropriate to make an order, he will give effect to the proposals through the making of an employment regulation order.  I am informed that the Minister of State, Deputy English, has not yet received any proposals from the Labour Court regarding an employment regulation order for the early learning care and school age childcare sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#H00200"><p>I appreciate that we are still in February and there is still much time.  My request is that the Minister of State is poised and ready to respond as soon as he receives that report, so that it can be implemented urgently.  Many contracts in this area run on a fixed-term basis.  It would be lovely to issue long-term contracts from September this year and for them to be at the new rates, which are appropriate for the retention of staff in this area.  This area is predominantly staffed by women.  The high cost of living has seen a loss of staff from this sector.  There is consequently a knock-on effect on the sustainability of services and the ability of parents who rely on those services to get back into the workplace as we return to a more normal, though hopefully hybrid, society.  I urge that we be ready for that report whenever it comes in.  If it is listening, the Labour Court should urgently move to ensure that we have this report as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1596" speakername="Robert Troy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#H00300"><p>As the Senator knows, the establishment of the JLC for the sector is fulfilling a programme for Government commitment.  It is a significant and welcome development.  It is an independent process and I encourage bodies representing both employers and employees to engage with the JLC process because it can yield significant positive benefits for both parties.</p> <p>An agreement on a new set of terms and conditions for employment will help to maintain and grow the talented pool of people working in the sector, as well as providing security and opportunity for career development in the early learning care and school age childcare sector, as the Senator alluded to.  I have no doubt that when a recommendation comes before our colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy English, he will not be found wanting.  The Government is committed.  We have proven through our actions and support for the sector in the last years that we want to support it, since it is crucial for our economy and society.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.32" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#H00350">Disability Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#H00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I thank her for taking time from her busy schedule to be here.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I would like to discuss the B&oacute;thar Oirialla group home in Carrickmacross.  I hope that with the arrival of the Minister of State to the House, she will have some good news for us regarding the opening of the facility which will provide a home and cater for up to five people in the Carrickmacross area who have physical and sensory disabilities.  The building has been lying idle for many years and families have been waiting for far too long for the facility to be opened.</p><p>I was delighted that with the change in Government some 18 months ago came a change in attitude and a sense of urgency that the project needed funding to get the facility open.  I thank the Minister of State because I know she took her portfolio, grasped this issue by the scruff of the neck and secured funding.  I am delighted things have moved on as far as they have.  They would not have without the work of the Minister of State.  It has been an issue for the people of Carrickmacross since the building was first initiated.  Local councillor P.J. O'Hanlon has worked tirelessly to try to open the facility.</p><p>The last time the Minister of State and I spoke, we were given a projected date of the last quarter of 2021.  She told me she had allocated some funding so that works could be done to the building.  Due to the fact it had lain idle for so long, some small remedial works were required so that the building could be opened.  I understand the works have been completed.  Now all we await is the good news I hope the Minister of State will have for us.  Families have been waiting a long time to get their local ones housed in the facility.  I hope we will finally have an opening date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#J00200"><p>I thank the Senator for giving me the opportunity to address this matter.  He has long advocated for the opening of the group home in Carrickmacross, and I thank him for the raising this important matter again today.</p> <p>As the Senator knows, there have been protracted negotiation between HSE community healthcare organisation, CHO, 1 disability services and the Respond housing agency regarding the lease agreement for the B&oacute;thar Oirialla group home in Carrickmacross.  I can inform the Senator that HSE estates confirmed it has received and has now forwarded the full suite of executed lease documentation to the HSE solicitors to support the final handover of the premises to HSE CHO 1 disability services.  The HSE solicitors will forward these documents to Resilience, the contracted service provider, once documentation is fully reviewed.</p> <p>HSE CHO 1 is awaiting contact from the approved housing body, Respond, to arrange handover of the premises and will then immediately complete the local licence arrangement with the service provider, Resilience.  Resilience met all residents at meetings during quarter 4 of 2021.  While the residential service is awaited, various supports and interventions are in place for residents, determined by the individuals&rsquo; needs.  The HSE advises that the full staffing complement has been recruited by the care provider and a person in charge of the unit has been identified.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, all designated centres for people with disabilities are required to register with the office of the chief inspector of HIQA.  Once the HSE is in receipt of the keys to hand over the premises to the contracted service provider, Resilience can lodge its registration application to HIQA.</p> <p>In some positive news for the Senator, the HSE has advised me today that the Carrickmacross group home should be open for residents to move in by the end of March.  I know the Senator and others in the community have been waiting a long time for this home to become a reality.  I am acutely aware there have been a number of delays over recent years, but I have kept a close eye on developments in Carrickmacross and it is welcome that we are now so close to this becoming a new home for five residents.  I am sure this will be a huge relief and an exciting update for families who need reassurance the facility will be open and running.</p> <p>My Department has provided the money and worked closely with the HSE to ensure that whatever obstacles were in the way since the matter was brought to my attention were addressed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Anne Rabbitte:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2436"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2436&amp;amp;pid=AnneRabbitte&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This has been done in conjunction with the requirements to ensure the building will meet inspection once the handover is complete.</p><p>We are not talking about having more of a protracted process.  This house is now available for residents to move into.  It did not open at the end of the fourth quarter of 2021 because it was around Christmas and a period of transition.  Some people did not want to make that full move; there was only one resident who was interested in the move at the time.  We are now doing it at the end of the first quarter of 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#K00200"><p>That is certainly very welcome news.  I have no doubt Senator Gallagher will have a positive response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#K00300"><p>Absolutely.  I thank the Minister of State most sincerely for giving us this excellent news.  People have waited years to hear that sentence and I am delighted, as the Minister of State has mentioned, that the facility will open in March.  On behalf of the community in Monaghan and particularly in Carrickmacross, I thank the Minister of State for her work and sense of urgency in securing the initial funding but also for driving this on so that today we have a date for the official opening, which is the end of March.  I am delighted with that.  It would give me great pleasure and it would only be right and fitting that someone who has done so much work in securing this facility would visit it and perhaps do an official opening, if that is in order.  I would be grateful if the Minister would do that and I look forward to her response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#K00400"><p>The Minister of State has the final word on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#K00500"><p>We are just between friends here and I do not mind sharing that in order for me to expedite this, I named the date I was coming to Carrickmacross, which was 28 March.  There is a little bit of pressure on everybody, whether it is HIQA, the HSE or the Department, to ensure the building is opening and fully functioning for those five residents.  I am coming that day to ensure it happens.  It is money I wanted spent in 2021 but it dragged into 2022.  I am nonetheless delighted the providers - the HSE and Resilience - have worked really hard for me to ensure we can have delivery.  I look forward to coming down on 28 March to see our new facility opened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#K00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.42" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ag 3.20 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ag 3.30 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.43" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#N00050">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#N00100"><p>Today's Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the approval of the appointment of a member of the Legal Services Regulatory Authority, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, motion regarding Planning and Development Act (Exempted Development) Regulations 2022, back from committee, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022 - Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m., with the opening contribution of the Minister not to exceed ten minutes, contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, with the Minister to be given not less than ten minutes to reply to the debate; and No. 4, motion regarding the report of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Environment and Climate Action on the carbon budget under the Climate Action and Low Carbon Development Acts 2015 to 2021, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 3 and to conclude after 60 minutes, if not previously concluded, with the opening contribution of the Minister not to exceed six minutes, contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed seven minutes and Senators may share time, with the Minister to be given not less than five minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#N00200"><p>I congratulate the Cathaoirleach and thank him for the lovely event this morning to mark Seanad 100.  It was very special to have Senator Norris and former Senator and former President Mary Robinson reflecting on the Seanad's role in society and politics and speaking about some of the issues that have been raised in the past and that we have to deal with now.  The one element that really stuck out for me was the word "passion".  Former President Robinson spoke about the need for passion when articulating the subjects we speak about.  She spoke about the importance of climate change and how we in the Seanad will need to be a very strong voice on this.</p> <p>On that note, with regard to the retrofitting grants which were announced two weeks ago and are incredibly welcome, I want to make several points.  If administered correctly, they could be transformative in respect of the energy we use and its cost.  With regard to the loans the Government has indicated it will give, I would like to see them rolled out through An Post.  There is a post office in practically every community.  We are looking at ways to make the post office continue to be a central space in every area.  It is important that the loans be administered through it.  We need to cut down on red tape and administration.  I know from those using the SEAI system they find it very difficult.  This is not what it should be.</p> <p>Over the weekend there was a debate about the National Women's Council's decision not to include women from Government parties at a rally outside Leinster House on 5 May to celebrate International Women's Day.  It is important to note that here.  The caucus has a good working relationship with the National Women's Council.  In any debate moderated by any group there should be a balance of female representation.  The journey to get here is hard enough.  I ask that women Oireachtas Members from non-Government parties support this also.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The last point I want to raise concerns the cost of living, including for students.  I heard contradictory remarks over the past week from the T&aacute;naiste and the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science on whether third-level fees would be reduced.  Let us be clear: they absolutely should be but not at the expense of the universities and other third-level colleges, which have been managing on a shoestring for the past decade.  The Cassells report was sent to the European Commission for an economic cost analysis of the three options put forward.  I understand the analysis has been submitted to the Department.  It is important that we have a debate on it and ensure that we do right by our universities and other third-level colleges.  Most important, we should do right by our students by ensuring they all have an opportunity to go to college.  I ask the Leader for a debate on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#O00200"><p>I thank the Chair for the great Seanad 100 event this morning.  It was absolutely wonderful to see former President, Mary Robinson and Senator David Norris in full flow.</p> <p>I welcome the extension of the consultation period requested regarding the flood relief measure planned for Ballinasloe.  It is excellent news that the OPW is going to co-ordinate an in-person public event.  This will be crucial in making sure communities in our area can engage on the huge development, which is to involve flood walls and embankments around the town.  It is really great news.</p> <p>I had the opportunity yesterday to meet the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, Deputy Simon Harris, who visited Galway, particularly Galway&ndash;Mayo Institute of Technology, GMIT, which on 1 April will become the brand new Atlantic Technological University.  Some &euro;430 million in Government funding was announced by the Minister yesterday.  There are four funding streams under that.  The funding will be divided between the traditional university sector and our brand-new technological universities.  There will be a specific fund for further and higher education, which is crucial.  Just as the Minister has expanded the CAO form to reflect further and higher learning and the apprenticeship programmes, we need to ensure our universities have the funding to match.  When we were in GMIT, we got to meet Dr. Orla Flynn, the institute's recently appointed president.  She was appointed just in the past two years.  We were brought on a tour of the various areas in the college and noted the investment that has taken place through Enterprise Ireland, particularly in respect of medical imaging.  There was a jobs announcement in Galway yesterday.  It is crucial to see how jobs announcements and investments are linked to investment in research, because the companies are working with all those involved in research and development in the universities.  It is important that we recognise that investment in third level results in jobs, income and a better standard of living for people in regional areas.  The technological universities appearing in the west and in regional towns across the rest of Ireland are crucial to our development.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#O00300"><p>I join other Senators in thanking the Chair, the Seanad Office, all the staff of the Communications Unit, particularly Mr. Mark Mulqueen and Ms Verona N&iacute; Bhroinn, and all others involved in organising the events of today.  It was a fabulous achievement.  We were asked to film a little bit afterwards and to give a sound bite, and I was particularly happy to be able to say both Ms Mary Robinson and Senator Norris have been two remarkable Senators.  Ms Robinson was an Independent Senator, just as Senator Norris is today.  It was interesting that Ms Robinson, having served three or four terms as an Independent Senator, became a Labour Party Senator.  David Norris has been a Senator continuously since he was first elected.  Ms Robinson was elected in 1969 and Senator Norris in 1987.  What a remarkable story.  I thank the Chair.  I hope we will have a really exciting year of celebration.  I know I speak for everyone in saying that there is not a day on which we come in here without being conscious of the enormous privilege it is to represent the people in the Houses of the Oireachtas, particularly the Seanad.</p> <p>There was to be a motion taken in the House this week on a Dublin citizens' assembly.  In fairness to the Leader, she contacted all of us to say it would be deferred for a week.  Between now and then, I do not want to talk about the motion or the substantive issue but to highlight two or three concerns.  We have 183 councillors in Dublin: 63 in Dublin City Council, 40 in Fingal County Council, 40 in South Dublin County Council, and 40 in D&uacute;n Laoghaire&ndash;Rathdown County Council.  It is important that we have a system.  The proposed amendment suggested 12 councillors.  How does one select 12 councillors from that total?  I simply do not know.  More important, I am anxious that we represent people across the board, of all parties and none.  Perhaps the D'Hondt system could be used, but that is a matter for councillors.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I am also concerned about gender.  If the Minister is suggesting there are only going to be 12 people out of 183, it is a bit silent about gender and how we are selecting them.  I think we should fight for a bigger majority.  Remember these sitting county councillors are politicians too and they are in the Minister's party and everyone else's parties or are Independent.  We need a better deal for them.  We want them at the heart of a citizens' assembly.  </p><p>The issue of a mayor is another one about which I am concerned.  I am not concerned about the mayor but the motion talks about having regard to an independent mayor.  The people of Dublin rejected a directly elected mayor among the four councils, although one or two of them accepted it.  It was scrapped so we need to be clear.  If we are having a citizens' assembly, we need an open debate and to let the assembly decide what it wants to do.  Let us not preordain the outcome.  Perhaps we might reflect on that in the next few days.  How will we get gender representation in this group and how will we have representation among city and county councillors?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1661" speakername="Pippa Hackett" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#P00200"><p>I reiterate my thanks to the Cathaoirleach and the team behind the event earlier today.  It was really lovely.</p> <p>We are good at labelling.  Of course, this applies to all walks of life but today, I want to challenge our understanding of two ways in which we label farmers.  One is loaded with positive assumptions, the other much less so.  One is the label "productive or commercial farmer" while the other is the somewhat belittling term "hobby farmer", which is often used to describe those who farm on a part-time basis.  Regarding the term "productive farmers", we are referring to farmers who farm full time to produce as much meat, milk or grain as possible.  Traditionally, that was seen as an undisputed positive but we now realise that some of that production has come at a cost and many such farms put significant pressure on our natural environment.  Take something as basic as hedges.  Data from Teagasc has indicated that a staggering 90% of hedges on intensive farms are classified as low quality exhibiting issues such as impoverished ground flora, low species diversity and gappiness.  Increasingly, there are other pressures on such farms.  Rising energy, fertiliser and feed costs have impacted on farmers across the country.  Our pig sector is in significant difficulty and our grassland farmers are facing very challenging decisions in terms of fertility inputs this year.  </p> <p>Perhaps we should not be quite so quick to consider the drive for more and more production as an unquestionable good, particularly now when we allow the term "hobby farmer" to be tossed around almost as an insult because most farmers in Ireland are in fact part time and there is nothing wrong with that.  They manage their land and farming enterprises like any other but they rely on off-farm income to survive and raise their families.  Of course, many of these farmers are not in receipt of the big EU direct payments.  Often this is because they were not farming in a particular way during the reference years at the start of this century when we decoupled payments from livestock numbers to land area-based payments.  Many of these farmers may then have been breeding and providing quality stock to other farmers who are in the position to bring the animals through to slaughter but it is the latter rather than the former who have largely benefitted from the past 20 years of payments.  </p> <p>However, with the levelling of EU direct payments in the form of convergence and other measures, it is quite likely that we will see more part-time farmers in the future.  Some bemoan that but I believe it should be welcomed and encouraged.  Some of the best farmers I know are part time.  They love what they do and because they are not wholly reliant on their farms for income, they can afford to be more flexible, experimental and innovative.  I do not think it is really important whether a farmer is full time or part time.  What matters is that farmers appreciate that their land must do more than just produce a profit at any cost.  Profit at the expense of the environment is just too costly for us all so let us stop praising it and start acknowledging those farmers who see themselves as true custodians of the land - as managers of enterprises, yes, but also as caretakers who are just passing through determined to leave to the next generation land that has been nurtured, regenerated and enriched.  Such farmers are engaging in real productive farming.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#P00300"><p>Before I came into the House, I had the misfortune to listen to the Joe Duffy show.  It is not something I do very often.  Comments were made about the Irish Women's Parliamentary Caucus.  As long as the caucus excludes parliamentary and secretarial assistants and all the other women who work in these Houses, it is exclusionary and, therefore, I will not participate in it.</p> <p>Monday was the anniversary of the Stardust fire 41 years ago.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There was a large gathering of relatives who met to commemorate their dead loved ones and also to call on this Government to stop putting obstacles in the way of their search for justice.  Over the last eight months, the State has put a series of obstacles in their way, the most recent one relating to jury selection.  There is an expert working group report on jury selection that is 20 years old.  Successive governments have done nothing to act on its recommendations.  One of the things the report says clearly is that the way juries are selected for inquests is deeply problematic.  We are now facing the largest inquest in the history of the State and are talking about the possibility of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na selecting the jury when it is itself a party to the inquest.  When the Taoiseach unveiled a bench at the INMO headquarters at the former Richmond hospital yesterday, he said he was listening to the families.  I hope he meant that and was not giving them false hope.  Under no circumstances will the families accept An Garda selecting the jury or accept the alternative the Taoiseach mentioned in the D&aacute;il two weeks ago, which would be to have a judge-led inquest with no jury at all.  Let us not forget that there have already been two judge-led inquiries into what happened in the Stardust nightclub and that both came out with deeply concerning findings.  One actually found that arson was probable and, although this finding was eventually reversed, it tarnished the entire community of north County Dublin and suggested that they were somehow responsible for what took place that night.  I really hope the Taoiseach was not speaking out of both sides of his mouth when he gave assurances to the families yesterday.<br/><br/>I would also like to raise a story covered in the <i>Irish Independent</i>today on the back of the reply I received to a freedom of information request.  It suggested that the Office of Public Works carried out works on Emo Court in Laois without the necessary derogation or licence, destroying a bat roost, before proceeding to try to cover it up and seek a licence for those works retrospectively.  When the National Parks and Wildlife Service investigated the matter, did it recommend prosecution?  That seemed to be the direction it was taking in the response to my freedom of information request.  It seems that someone intervened with the two agencies to ensure that investigation and prosecution did not proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#Q00200"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for organising the wonderful Seanad100 event today.  There was a real sense of pride and privilege in being able to listen to Senator Norris and the former Senator and President, Mary Robinson.  It was really heartening to see that the light is still shining very brightly for both of them with regard to their campaigning.</p> <p>I raise today the issue of the scheme to regularise the status of long-term undocumented migrants opened by the Government on 31 January.  For those of us who have been arguing in this House for justice for the undocumented in this country for a long time, this is a major breakthrough.  Like so many others, I want this scheme to succeed but I have serious concerns about the eligibility criteria.  It appears that some of those who were previously documented but who are now undocumented will be excluded from this new Government scheme.  We have to ask why that is the case.  The very nature of some of the employment schemes under which workers come here means that they are tied to their employers.  When such workers are injured or feel they have to leave their jobs because of harassment or appalling conditions, they not only leave their job but also lose their documented status.  I particularly wish to raise the plight of 200 ex-fishers who are currently not documented.  Because they were documented in the last four years, they cannot apply for the Government scheme announced on 31 January.  It is not right and it is not good enough.  If this groundbreaking regularisation scheme is to live up to its potential and if it is to afford a future to those who have come and made their lives here and who are working in the Irish economy or in the seas around this island, we cannot turn our backs on those workers.  I am conscious that an interdepartmental review group has been set up to look at the atypical permits scheme.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This scheme was developed in 2015 on the back of Trojan work by the International Transport Workers Federation, which effectively unmasked and uncovered the appalling exploitation of workers that is happening in Irish waters and on Irish vessels, with exploited fishers working in those vessels.  The review is likely to come out over the next weeks.  In that review we really need to see that the process by which undocumented fishers are documented and how they are documented is corrected, that it is not just left to the vessel owners to document the workers and, crucially, that fishers working on Irish registered vessels are no longer tethered to their employers.</p><p>There are two distinct but related issues here.  First, all workers who were previously documented and who fell out of documented status have to be eligible for the Government's new scheme.  Second, it is no longer acceptable that any work permit in the State would tether an employee to his or her employer.  They have to be free of their employer and free to be able to take up employment wherever else after a period of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RRRRR00200"><p>I commend the Cathaoirleach and all of the staff and others who were involved in today's launch of Seanad 100.  It is an exciting year ahead and it is interesting to be looking back at the past 100 years.  There have been some very strong contributions and inspiration from speeches from former Senator Mary Robinson and the current longest serving Senator, Senator David Norris.</p> <p>I rise to ask for an amendment to the Order of Business.  It has come to my attention that there are some significant concerns about the regulations.  I believe there is a proposal that there would be a motion to approve the draft Planning and Development Act (Exempted Development) Regulations 2022, without debate today.  Unfortunately, it has just come to my attention that there are some significant concerns regarding those regulations which may merit attention, debate and discussion.</p> <p>Specifically of concern are those regulations for a potential requirement of a two-year vacancy in the context of exempted developments.  Given the law of unforeseen consequences, we could actually see an incentive around vacancy if the promotion of vacancy was to allow, for example, exemption from planning.  We do not want to create that kind of perverse incentive.</p> <p>There are still concerns about some of the environmental factors around bats' routes and nesting birds.  Very importantly, and it may even be an inadvertent admission, it does seem that in the areas that are excluded from the exemption there is a concern that the subsection of Article 9.1 in our planning and development regulations, which is the piece specifically around protecting architectural conservation areas, they are not included in the areas excluded from the exemption.  There is a concern there.  I am sorry not to have raised this earlier with the Leader, but it has come to my attention since.  I am hoping that perhaps we might be able to table this item for another day.  We will be looking at planning issues on other days.  Perhaps we could at least have some debate or discussion of it, and perhaps some clarity from the Minister before we approve these regulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RRRRR00300"><p>Can I clarify if the proposal is that No. 2 not be taken today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RRRRR00400"><p>That it not be taken today or that it not be taken without debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RRRRR00500"><p>It must be one or the other.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RRRRR00600"><p>Apologies.  I ask that it would be postponed to another day, and not taken today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RRRRR00700"><p>That is fine.  I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RRRRR00800"><p>I am open to other suggestions from the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RRRRR00900"><p>The Leader may be aware that the week commencing 28 February to 6 March is to be Eating Disorder Week.  I raised this issue previously in the House, and I know that it is one the Leader is very familiar with.  Notwithstanding that the Government set aside significant amounts of money last year and this year, there is a considerable delay in rolling out appropriate services.  I believe there are only three centres in the State that deal with eating disorders and offer the kinds of therapy that people need.  There is one centre for adults and two for minors or those under the age of 18.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Timmy Dooley:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2015"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2015&amp;amp;pid=TimDooley&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is a huge issue which has grown in terms of numbers and impact on young people during the pandemic.  It would be appropriate if the Leader could schedule for the week commencing 28 February a debate in the House on eating disorders in general, look for a response from the Government and try to understand what more we can do to action those plans.</p><p>There are issues in recruitment across the HSE but it is not good enough to say moneys have been set aside and are in place, and then leave the operational piece to wither on the vine.  Reports this week from the Department of Health suggest targets are not being met in other areas of the health service.  This is an important issue.  There are wonderful interventions which can impact positively on the lives of those suffering from an eating disorder, get them back on track and allow them to live their lives, no different to other illnesses, particularly those with a mental illness dimension.  </p><p>It is an issue many people do not like or want to talk about, that is bedevilling our young people and that has grown through the pandemic for obvious reasons.  It is one we should grapple with in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#S00200"><p>I welcome the regulations before us on the exemption of commercial properties from the requirement to go through an often lengthy planning process to be converted into productive residential units for individuals and families.  I assure Senator Higgins that this got ample discussion at last Thursday's meeting of the Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage, where the Minister, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, was present and all members of the committee present contributed on it.</p> <p>I have campaigned for some time on the fact that vacant and derelict former public houses have been omitted from the original regulations introduced in 2018.  It is now being rectified.  We all know many such former pubs across the country in towns, villages and cities that are a blot on the landscape and could be put to far better use as residential units.  That is what we are doing by introducing these regulations.  It removes the red tape in order to bring them back into use.  Since the regulations were introduced in 2018, they have delivered 1,400 residential units, including 676 in the last 12 months.  We are making progress and those numbers of units should not be sniffed at.  By including vacant and derelict former pubs, we will see a far higher take-up. </p> <p>There are notifications regarding section 57 that have to be negotiated with the local authority in the event that a property is a protected structure or has architectural merit.  Those protections are inbuilt as is the necessity to be in accordance with existing regulations, be it fire or size requirements for units.</p> <p>This is a welcome move by the Government that has come from evidence on the ground of issues that have been fed up through the Oireachtas joint committee to the Minister.  Action has now been taken and it is a perfect example of how the system can and does work.  We often give out when it does not work but this is an example of the system working.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#S00300"><p>I join with Senator O'Loughlin.  I have called in this House before for a debate on the future funding of higher education.  We are no further along that track.  While the announcement is welcome that will result in the reduction of fees for students at third level, it cannot be at the expense of core funding for higher education institutions.  We need clarity on the future funding of those institutions.</p> <p>I raise the question of approximately 100 Tesco security workers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These are workers who are employed directly by Tesco.  Last Tuesday they were summoned into all of the stores throughout the country to be informed that a decision had been taken centrally to outsource their jobs to OCS security services.  In many cases, many of these workers, who are all around the country, have been working for decades with Tesco and frequently have to deal with much antisocial behaviour.  We know that, during the pandemic, retail workers and those working in our retail environments were front-line workers.  Some of these workers were attacked and experienced physical abuse.</p><p>For Tesco, which normally has a reputation of being a good employer, simply to call in the 100 workers around the country - the unions were not notified about this - and essentially tell them the jobs would be outsourced or Tesco may - the word used was "may" - be able to find them a job within the existing stores is the sharpest example I have come across in a long time of HR and industrial relations practice.  Tesco is a highly profitable store.  Tesco is making billions here in Ireland.  It generally has a reputation as a good employer.  I understand the unions, Mandate and SIPTU, were due to meet with Tesco management on Thursday.</p><p>We need to send out a very clear message that it is totally unacceptable that this sort of sharp industrial relations practice is being engaged in and that we, as public representatives, are hugely appreciative of the front-line retail workers and, particularly, those security workers in our supermarkets over the past two years, but indeed over many years.  I would hope that, in raising this issue here, it would communicate our anger and annoyance at the approach of Tesco management.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#T00200"><p>I wish to raise a couple of issues.  Senator Byrne mentioned Tesco, but the Irish Farmers Association, IFA, and all involved in the horticultural sector have been looking to engage with Dunnes Stores with regard to prices, especially the price of vegetables.  We have seen over the past 24 hours the IFA holding a dispute at two Dunnes Stores centres.  I call on Dunnes Stores to engage with the IFA and discuss these issues.  We have seen, particularly in the pig industry and, as I said, the horticultural industry, that these are extremely challenging times, and it is only right farmers get a fair price for what is an excellent product.  That needs to be highlighted today.  Dunnes Stores is an Irish company and prides itself on being an Irish company.  We need to talk to the local farmers who produce for the company.</p> <p>I also wish to raise a housing issue.  It would have been on "Drivetime" a number of days ago.  There was a discussion with residents in Colmcille Terrace in Granard in north Longford.  Four years ago, I brought the Minister at the time, Eoghan Murphy, to Granard, where funding had been sought for a long number of years to upgrade a significant number of derelict houses in that area.  We secured funding, met with the residents and a process started between Longford County Council and Tuath.  It started in early 2019, we are now at February 2022 and not a stick of work has been done.  There are boarded up houses with dampness coming through the walls to where people are living.  There are rats and cats.  It is not acceptable in 2022 that this happens and people are living in these conditions.</p> <p>I ask the Leader to write to the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to get me an update on when in 2022 the works will start on this project, when it will be completed and when the residents can live in what should be up to standard housing.  This is not acceptable at this day and age.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#T00300"><p>It was International Epilepsy Day yesterday.  I have soft spot for it because I know so many people with this condition.  Epilepsy Ireland had a very catchy campaign saying to time the seizure, keep them safe and stay with them.  Therefore, it is "Time, Safe, Stay".  We are all about to be empowered to know how to look after a person who is having a seizure.  There are 40,000 people in Ireland who have epilepsy, so the chances are we could come across someone going through a seizure.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Erin McGreehan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=ErinMcGreehan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is most important that we all empower ourselves to look after people with epilepsy, to be aware of the signs and to make sure that they feel safe in society.  I call on the Department of Social Protection to amend the requirements for free travel and to build some flexibility into free travel schemes.  If a person with epilepsy has a seizure, they are not permitted to drive for six months.  That has a huge impact on many people's lives.  It often puts them out of education and work because they cannot afford the cost of travel.  It would be a good way to empower people to allow them to continue their day-to-day normal life as they would have done prior to having a seizure.  For many reasons, it would be really beneficial for the Department of Social Protection to look at introducing flexibility into the free travel scheme.  As the Leader is aware, the scheme is very rigid.  I ask for the introduction of built-in flexibility and for allowances to be made to make it reasonable in certain cases, such as epilepsy.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#U00200"><p>Today, I want to suggest a measure to ease the cost of living for families in a small but significant way.  One of the hardest things about living on a tight budget is that you do not have room for the unexpected or out-of-the-ordinary costs.  That can drive families to make impossible choices.  We need to stop those scenarios from arising where we can.  I am of the belief that the &euro;75 levy for attending children's urgent care centres should not be there in the first place.  There is one such centre in Blanchardstown that opened a few years ago.  It is part of Children's Health Ireland, CHI.  A new centre opened recently in Tallaght.  These state-of-the-art centres are run by CHI and its paediatric emergency medicine teams.  Urgent care centres treat conditions such as sprains, strains, broken bones, vomiting and diarrhoea, minor burns and scalds, fever in babies older than 12 weeks and small cuts and injuries.  Of course, the levy is there to try to prevent people from abusing the system, but the centres are there for parents who are worried about their children.  If they are worried, they should be seen without the imposition of a levy.  Cost should never be a barrier to urgent healthcare for children and families.  There are some exemptions from the levy, including medical card holders, members of the Defence Force and their families and people receiving services in respect of prescribed infectious diseases.  Children can be referred to these centres by their GPs.  Why should they have to go through their GP in order to be referred to an urgent care centre?  That just puts even more pressure on GPs.  We are already extending free GP care to those aged seven and under.  We need to do it for children of all ages attending these centres.  One final point that I wish to make is that the opening hours of the centres are 9 a.m. to 5 p.m., Monday to Friday.  The hours need to be extended.  I know that there are reasons for the current hours, including resources.  I have some suggestions on how we can help with that.  However, in general, the model was supposed to provide services seven days a week.  That is what we should be working towards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#U00300"><p>Hyperemesis gravidarum is a condition that around 10% of women suffer from during pregnancy.  Most people who have never been through it call it morning sickness.  It is nothing like morning sickness.  It is a severe illness that women have for nine months of their pregnancy.  It probably became well known because Kate Middleton had it the first time she had a child.  Currently, there are three drugs available in the market to treat people who suffer from the condition.  Two of them are not available in Ireland.  One of the drugs, Cariban, is available in Ireland, but it is unlicensed.  At the moment, people have to purchase this drug.  It costs them about &euro;45 a week.  For some people, the cost over the term of a full pregnancy is around &euro;3,000.  It is a severe cost for those going through pregnancies.  The cost of it actually impacts the decisions of women on whether to have a child.  For those who cannot afford the drug, going through pregnancy without it is totally and utterly unbearable.  I raised the issue nine months ago, ironically, and nothing has really changed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Garret Ahearn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=GarretAhearn&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Will the Leader ask the Minister for Health to commit to making this drug available to women going through this in Ireland?  It is a horrendous condition for the women who have to suffer through it for nine months.  The argument always made is that Cariban is unlicensed.  The State has put provisions in place to support people in the context of other unlicensed drugs.  It must be possible to find a way for the Department of Health and the Minister to make an exception for the small number of women who go through these very difficult pregnancies.  The condition can be alleviated through the use of this drug, but the associated cost is a heavy one for people to bear.  In fairness, we would in turn save on the cost of women having to go to hospital as a result of suffering from this condition.  Many women cannot work because it is so difficult.  The least we can do is to support women when they are going through pregnancy to bring new life into the world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#V00200"><p>Today is a happy day.  Two children were born in Kyiv.  Their Irish parents travelled there in recent days for the birth of their much-longed for babies.  Other babies will be born later this week.  They have been born into a context where our Government has advised people not to travel due to the impending possibilities that could occur in Kyiv.  Often in this House we get up and give out about officials, the Government and Ministers, and we hustle and hustle.  Throughout the increasing tensions in Ukraine, though, I have been incredibly proud of our Department of Foreign Affairs.  It has been extraordinary.  Its staff have been in daily contact with all the parents registered with the Department.  Those parents have been provided with support and welfare support.  The Department has helped in every possible way and it is trying to move mountains to ensure the parents are reassured as they go to Ukraine to try to bring home their much-longed for babies.  Many of these women have come through cancer.  Some of them were part of the 221+ cervical cancer group.  These are people who have had an arduous journey to get to this stage.  That they are arriving in a place where their baby is going to be born and terrified that it is going to be a conflict zone is unbelievably upsetting for them.</p> <p>I pay tribute to the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, and to all the officials in the Department of Foreign Affairs because they are full of compassion.  For people in that position, officials can hold such power over lives.  The Department's officials are going to extraordinary lengths to demonstrate how much they are on the side of Irish people.  It is a tremendous tribute to the Minister and the Department.  I just want to acknowledge that here and to congratulate those who are mammies and daddies today.  How exciting this is, and we look forward to welcoming them home at Dublin Airport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#V00300"><p>The Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, has responsibility for local government.  I commend the Leader for withdrawing the motion on the creation and establishment of the two citizens' assemblies that were to be on the Order Paper for Thursday.  I ask that, in the interim, we have a debate on citizens' assemblies.  I was a proud member of the Constitutional Convention and I never missed a meeting.  The concept is an important part of our participative democracy.  The motion on citizens' assemblies, however, if it had been brought to the House on Thursday, was one that would have done a great disservice to our local government representatives.</p> <p>In the context of the contribution of Senator Boyhan this morning, I ask that we have a real debate about local government and the role of councillors.  Regarding the remarks of former President Robinson today concerning climate change, it has forced significant change on all of us, but particularly on local government and how it delivers.  I refer to aspects such as sustainable development, modal shift and active travel.  It is appalling, however, that the Government would shoehorn the role of local government in Ireland generally into a motion on a citizens' assembly for a directly-elected mayor of Dublin.  That does a huge disservice to our local government members and to local government.</p> <p>I do not dispute the need to have proportionality in representation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->With all due respect to my Dublin colleagues, there should be a representative from all regions of the country when discussing the future of local government.  I repeat we cannot and should not shoehorn the future of local government into a motion on a directly-elected major for Dublin when we should be having a specific citizens' assembly on the future of local government.  Given that the Taoiseach was such a fan and played such a significant active role in the plebiscite that took place in Cork, I ask that he consider the role of a directly-elected mayor for Cork city in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#W00200"><p>I draw the attention of the House to a report launched yesterday by Women's Aid, which documents the findings of a survey it conducted with the support of Red C Research and Marketing into relationship abuse, specifically relationship abuse among young people aged 18 to 25 in Ireland.  The research was done over the course of two years and the findings are stark.  It has prompted Women's Aid to launch a campaign entitled "Too Into You".</p> <p>The findings tell us that more than half of our young people have experienced or known someone who has experienced intimate relationship abuse.  One in five young women and one in 11 young men in Ireland have suffered intimate relationship abuse.  In all cases where women were subjected to intimate relationship abuse, their abuse was perpetrated by someone who was very close to them, a former or existing intimate partner.  For young women, the abuse lasted longer than one year, almost one and a half years.  One in six young women and one in 13 young men have been subjected to coercive control by a partner or an ex-partner.  What coercive control means is a persistent, insidious controlling pattern of behaviour that intrudes on the person's independent sense of self and self-security.  The findings are stark.  Of the young women affected, 51% first experienced the abuse before they were 18 years of age.  That robbed those young women and girls of their childhood.</p> <p>Copies of the report have been circulated to all Members of the Oireachtas.  It is incumbent on all of us to draw public attention to the findings of this report, raise awareness about what constitutes abuse, support victims of abuse and let them know it is okay to speak out and that help is available, and for us all to respond to them.  I commend Women's Aid on the report and also the campaign it is launching and I encourage every Member of the House to support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#W00300"><p>I commend Women's Aid on the phenomenal work it has done.  I totally agree with my previous colleague on the impact coercive control has and how it can be devastating for any young woman or man who is living in such a situation.  I commend Women's Aid on the great work it does.</p> <p>I am here today to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#W00400"><p>Formally second my amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1632" speakername="Frances Black" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#W00500"><p>I formally second the amendment to the Order of Business proposed by my colleague, Senator Higgins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#W00600"><p>The Senator did her job with aplomb.  I call the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#W00700"><p>While Senator Black did not raise the issue this afternoon, I have the date she sought.  It is in the diary with a date in the next couple of weeks.</p> <p>I thank Senator Black for seconding the amendment to the Order of Business.  Unfortunately, I will not be in a position to accept it as the recommendations have to go through today.</p> <p>Both Senators Black and Fitzpatrick raised the Women&rsquo;s Aid report issued yesterday.  Its findings are shocking when we think about our young women and men who were canvassed for their information and experiences.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have a long way to go to mind people and to change the culture in this country and every country, because it is not unique to Ireland.  The campaign is worthy of support from all of us.  I look forward to it.</p><p>I concur with Senator Buttimer's thoughts.  It probably got through the initial schedule last week because I did not read to the end to see that it was about far more than just establishing a citizens' assembly regarding a mayor for Dublin city.  There is absolutely no way that we will have just an hour-long debate on the future of local government.  It is far more complex than that and should not be determined for the entire country by 100 citizens and politicians from Dublin.  That is going back to the drawing board.  Once it is reworded, I will come back and offer it to everybody again.  We will agree on exactly how long is required for it.</p><p>Senator Seery Kearney, with such a beautiful smile, talked about the two babies who have been born and the babies waiting to be born in Kyiv.  I commend the Senator for her leadership in the last week.  I know that she knows this system inside-out.  She also knows the experiences that people are going through.  The empathy and leadership that the Senator showed during the week are a credit to her and the community she represents.  It is a small but growing community.  It is certainly worthy of the Senator's membership.  I congratulate her.</p><p>As he has on many occasions, Senator Ahearn raised hyperemesis and the drug in Ireland which is prescribed, bought and paid for by families, Cariban.  It is unlicensed, which has meant historically that the reimbursement scheme has not been able to reimburse families.  I am pleased to announce that last week, following suggestions from both female and male Senators, the Minister for Health set up a working group to try to find a way around the fact that it is unlicensed so that we can reimburse women.  I am sure that where there is a will, there is a way.</p><p>Senator Currie said that the cost of living for families can be directly impacted by the &euro;75 charge when people need to bring their children to an urgent care centre where she lives, in Dublin 15.  It seems like a lot of money to have to pay to attend an emergency care centre in the first place.  I will bring it to the Minister's attention.</p><p>Senator McGreehan talked about International Epilepsy Day, which was yesterday.  Coincidentally, I had the privilege of meeting Epilepsy Ireland on Friday with regard to a new planned project that it has in Fingal.  I was shocked to hear that there are 67,000 people in Ireland who are currently managing epilepsy, with just three doctors.  The dearth is staggering.  People have raised the lack of neurological nurses in the past.  We cannot monitor some of these patients more than once a year because we have no nurses and only three doctors.  We have a long way to go to look after the 67,000 people and their families, who rely on their good health.</p><p>Senator Carrigy spoke about the impasse between Dunnes Stores and the productive farmers in our pig and horticultural industries.  I am not sure that we really get that five entities in this country determine what we eat and what is on our supermarket shelves week-in, week-out, and what they pay to the producers.  If they do not like the prices that the producers offer, they just go to different countries and get cheaper products.  We row into Dunnes, Tesco, Lidl, Aldi and SuperValu weekly, thinking that we are buying an Irish product that is produced by our farmers and that they are making money from it.  They are not.  They are hanging on by their fingernails.  I commend Senator Carrigy for raising that issue.</p><p>As a former Minister for Social Protection and Employment Affairs, I am gobsmacked by the matter that Senator Malcolm Byrne raised.  He is right to call it sharp practice.  Tesco is a worthy employer.  It is sharp practice for it to try to downgrade and outsource the 100 security guards who have worked for and served it incredibly well, for many years in some cases.  I will contact SIPTU and Mandate after the Order of Business to offer our support and see if we can do anything to help them.  There is no way that those people should be made redundant, which is presumably what will happen.  Outsourcing those jobs has to be illegal.</p><p>Senator Cummins raised the building regulations and highlighted the lengthy debate that happened on the committee report last Thursday.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->On Senator Dooley's contribution, I will gladly organise a debate for the week beginning 28 February for eating disorder week.  It is a silent issue, probably because many families do not want their children to be known as victims.  One of the most prolific ways in which women in this country self-harm is by controlling their eating.  It is very harmful but somewhat hidden.  A wonderful book, <i>The Raggy Dolls: Stories of Survival from Anorexia Nervosa</i>, was written by a psychologist who specialises in this area.  He produces very good podcasts.  We need a Government response and action plan, and I will happily organise that debate.<br/><br/>Senator Higgins and others spoke about Seanad 100 today.  It was a wonderful event and I pay particular credit to all of the officials who supported the Seanad and the Seanad 100 centenary celebrations.  A lot of effort went into it and it will be a wonderful celebration of the diverse and sometimes diverging views we share.  It highlighted the amount of work and thoughtful co-operation that happens in this Chamber, something that does not happen elsewhere to the same extent.<br/><br/>Senator Sherlock spoke about the regularisation of the migrant scheme and her concerns about the eligibility criteria.  I will pass those concerns on to the Minister.<br/><br/>Senator Boylan spoke about the expert group on jury selection today and the response to a freedom of information request she received with regard to the Office of Public Works, OPW.  I will bring that to the attention of the Minister so that the Senator can get a direct response.<br/><br/>The Minister of State, Senator Hackett, spoke about hobby farmers.  I have to be honest.  I am not sure I would 100% agree with her contribution because to my mind the reason most people are part-time farmers in this country is because they cannot earn a living from being full-time farmers and have children, wives and homes to support.  We have a long way to go to be competitive and not pitch farmers against each other and multiples, and definitely not farmers against the State and the Government that supports them.<br/><br/>Senator Boyhan spoke about Seanad 100 and the Dublin citizens' assembly.  He expressed his concerns about the amendment that has been withdrawn.<br/><br/>Senator Dolan spoke about Seanad 100 and her joy at watching Mary Robinson and Senator Norris, and the passion they displayed when they spoke so eloquently earlier today.  She spoke about her visit to GMIT.<br/><br/>Senator O'Loughlin, Seanad leader for Fianna F&aacute;il, spoke about how the Seanad can show its leadership on climate change, retrofitting grants and having daily and weekly conversations about how Government actions have an impact and can change people's lives.  She also spoke about the National Women's Council of Ireland, NWCI, rally on 5 March.  I thank her for raising the issue.  I also thank Joe Duffy for talking about this on the radio today.  Women work supremely well when we work together in unison.  That does not necessarily mean we all have to have exactly the same political or ideological views.  Our power is when we come together and fight and campaign for something.  It is ironic Senator Boylan said she will not participate in the women's caucus in Leinster House because it is exclusionary but is quite happy to participate in the NWCI rally in a couple of weeks even though it is exclusionary.  This is a State-funded body that is supposed to represent all women in Ireland, not just a select few with some select views.  I have to be very honest: this is not the first time I have genuinely felt it does not represent me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#Y00200"><p>Senator Higgins has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 2 not be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#Y00300"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.86" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.87" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.88" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#Z00100">Legal Services Regulatory Authority: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#Z00200"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann, noting that the Government agreed on 7th December, 2021, to propose, for the approval of Seanad &Eacute;ireann, S&iacute;ona Ryan to be a member of the Legal Services Regulatory Authority on the nomination of the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission, and pursuant to section 9 of the Legal Services Regulation Act 2015, approves the appointment by the Government of S&iacute;ona Ryan to be a member of the Legal Services Regulatory Authority to fill a casual vacancy pursuant to Section 10(9) of the said Act of 2015.&quot; </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.90" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.91" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#Z00400">Planning and Development Act (Exempted Development) Regulations 2022: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#Z00500"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:  	Planning and Development Act (Exempted Development) Regulations 2022, a revised copy of which has been laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 11th February, 2022.&rdquo; </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.93" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.94" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ag 4.32 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ag 4.50 p.m.

Sitting suspended at 4.32 p.m. and resumed at 4.50 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.95" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#DD00100">Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.96" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#DD00300"><p>I am very glad to be here to introduce this Bill.  It is an important part of the Government's response to the recent increase in the cost of living due to high electricity and gas prices.  It is in this regard that we produced the Bill.  I am glad to be opening the debate today and to be able to set the context for the action to be taken on foot of this Bill.  I will describe the sections of the Bill and, having regard to its main provisions, set out some background as to why they are needed for the operation of the scheme.  My overarching message is that while the scheme this Bill will establish is just one of a package of measures, it is critical to put it into place within this quarter.  I seek permission to achieve that.  First, I will outline the main factors affecting electricity prices in Ireland.  Second, I will outline the Government's response to rising electricity and gas prices.  Third, I will reaffirm the Government's conviction that the best long-term approach to insulating consumers from volatility in international fossil fuel markets is to decarbonise our energy system and radically improve the energy efficiency of our housing stock.</p> <p>I will now turn to the first point, namely factors affecting Irish electricity prices.  Senators will appreciate that we face additional costs due to our geographical location, fossil fuel dependency, the small scale of the Irish market, our low population density and exchange rate fluctuations.  However, the most immediate factor affecting electricity prices in Ireland has been the unprecedented upward trend in international gas prices since 2020.  Indications are now that these higher prices will remain significantly higher for the immediate future.  This feeds directly through to retail electricity prices because gas is used for electricity generation.  It is a matter of serious concern to the Government that energy price increases caused by these international conditions are putting increasing pressure on consumers, particularly the most vulnerable.  These price increases are not caused by the Government or regulatory decisions.  Suppliers compete with one another on price and set their own prices, as expected in a competitive commercial liberalised market.  The Commission for Regulation of Utilities, CRU, indicated that customers could save &euro;300 by switching their electricity or gas supplier every year.</p> <p>It is important to state that all European markets are experiencing these same price increase.  Other member states have taken various actions, including suspending tariffs for networks, suspending tariffs for green energy subsidies, reducing VAT and introducing or increasing payments to low-income households.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Eamon Ryan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2028"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2028&amp;amp;pid=EamonRyanGP&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Since Ireland's announcement of a credit to each domestic electricity household, Belgium has followed suit announcing that it will introduce &euro;100 credit for households.  </p><p>I will now turn to the Government's response to the rise in prices.  On 10 February, a suite of Government policy measures was announced by the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform designed to further support households.  These new measures included an increase in the energy credit in this Bill to &euro;200, including VAT.  This will necessitate a change to the text of the Bill that specifies both the upward limit on funding for the scheme it establishes and the amount of the individual payment to be made to each domestic electricity account.  I will bring forward the necessary amendments on Committee Stage in this House.  </p><p>A temporary 20% reduction in public transport fares will apply from April until the end of the year.  A further lump sum payment of &euro;125 on the fuel allowance will be paid in early March to some 390,000 recipients.  In addition, there are reduced caps for multiple children on school transport fees to &euro;500 per family post primary and &euro;150 for primary school children.  There will be a reduction in the drug payment scheme from &euro;144 to &euro;80, which will benefit approximately 70,000 residents.  The working family payment budget increase announced on budget day will be brought forward from 1 June to 1 April.  </p><p>All of these measures are on top of the existing measures taken in budget 2022 to support households.  Budget 2022 increased the weekly rate of the fuel allowance by &euro;5 to &euro;33 a week so that &euro;924 will be paid to eligible households over the course of this winter.  The fuel allowance is one of a range of income supports paid by the Department of Social Protection, which also includes general social welfare schemes, living alone increases to support those living alone and at a higher risk of poverty, and the household benefits package.  Targeted supports are also provided under the supplementary welfare allowance scheme, exceptional needs payments and urgent needs payments while under the supplementary welfare allowance scheme, a special heating supplement may be paid to assist people with special heating needs, for example, in the case of ill health.</p><p>Looking to the future and the urgent need to decarbonise, I will now outline the long-term approach for Ireland and in that context, the Government's urgent focus on energy efficiency.  Energy efficiency is central to addressing the root causes of energy poverty and improving health and social inclusion outcomes while at the same time, contributing to decarbonisation.  On 8 February, the Government announced unprecedented grant supports for home energy upgrades and increased numbers of free energy upgrades for those at risk of energy poverty.  A new national home energy upgrade scheme providing increased grant levels of up to 50% of the cost of a typical B2 home energy upgrade with a heat pump - up from 30% to 35% currently - with a one-stop-shop providing an end-to-end service for homeowners.  We are also introducing higher grants for cavity wall and attic insulation, which will more than triple to cover approximately 80% of the typical cost of these measures and will be available to all homeowners.  For instance, in the case of a semi-detached home, the attic insulation grant will increase from &euro;400 to &euro;1,300.  It is expected that these works will pay back in one to two years in most houses.</p><p>A total of &euro;267 million has been allocated for SEA's residential and community retrofit schemes in 2022.  This investment will support almost 27,000 home energy upgrades, including upgrading over 8,600 homes to a BER of B2, which is a near doubling of B2 output over 2021, and 4,800 free energy upgrades for households at risk of energy poverty.  In addition, &euro;85 million in funding has been provided by the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage for the local authority energy efficiency retrofit programme.  Making our homes energy efficient not only means they are warmer, healthier and cheaper to run but also means we are taking concrete action on social deprivation, including energy poverty, that is sustainable and enduring.  </p><p>I will now devote my remaining remarks to the Bill's subject matter.  The Bill will establish a scheme through which the electricity cost emergency benefit can be paid in 2022.  The Commission for Regulation of Utilities, CRU, as an independent energy regulator, will provide oversight of the scheme, which will be operated by the electricity distribution system operator ESB Networks.  I will provide, under regulations, for a date on which the distribution system operator will calculate the total number of domestic electricity accounts in the State on the basis of meter point registration numbers, MPRNs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Eamon Ryan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2028"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2028&amp;amp;pid=EamonRyanGP&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> ESB Networks will notify me of the number of MPRNs and that will allow for the calculation of the allocation of moneys for the scheme.  On the effective date, which will also be set out by me in regulations, ESB Networks will notify electricity suppliers of the assigned MPRN for each domestic electricity account supplied and of the amount of money that will transfer to them for the purposes of the scheme.  I will set out in regulations the period within which ESB Networks will transfer the funds to suppliers for the sole purpose of making the payments.  Following receipt of these funds, suppliers will then, within the period to be prescribed by me under regulations, credit each domestic electricity account held with them on the effective date with the payment.  </p><p>I will now provide a section-by-section summary of the Bill.  Section 1 provides for definitions.  Section 2 provides for the establishment of the scheme, to be operated on a once-off basis.  It provides the basis for the estimation of the amount required and for the upper limit on total funding to be allocated by me, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p><p>Section 3 provides for the transfer of the moneys to each domestic electricity account in the State for the operation of the scheme by me with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, to the distribution system operator, DSO.  Sections 4 and 5 provide for the functions of the DSO and suppliers, respectively, for the purposes of the operation of the scheme.</p><p>Section 6 provides for the amendment of section 9 of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999 to create functions for the CRU, including oversight of the functions of the distribution system operator and suppliers, to ensure that the administrative and operational arrangements necessary for the scheme are in place.</p><p>Section 7 deals with an amendment to the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997.  This amendment is to exempt the electricity costs emergency benefit payment from income tax.  Section 8 provides for me to make regulations, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, to set out the dates and periods for the operation of the scheme, as well as to provide for additional functions of the distribution system operator, electricity suppliers and such administrative and operational matters as may be required.</p><p>Section 9 provides that the DSO and electricity suppliers shall bear their own expenses.  Section 10 contains the Short Title and commencement of the Act.</p><p>I have outlined the main provisions of this Bill and provided additional detail on the sections.  I hope this will assist Senators and I look forward to a meaningful debate with Members from all sides of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#FF00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and I thank him for setting out the ten sections in this Bill and the rationale behind the legislation.  I recognise this comes as a Government response to the rising costs of energy.  Unfortunately, some would say it is not enough, while others would say it is not specifically targeted.  Indeed, I find myself wondering why I am getting a payment when I am well paid, have a good job and do not need it.  I do not wish to be flippant about this, but I do want to be honest.  Frankly, I do not know why any Oireachtas Member should benefit from a &euro;200 package.  It is not targeted and it is not the right thing.  That is a criticism of the system, and not of the Minister.</p> <p>I understand that the Government wishes to roll this out fast and that it must be simple and simple to administer.  Given our incomes, however, I have a serious issue, frankly, with the elected Members of the Houses of the Oireachtas benefiting from &euro;200.  That is one of my concerns about this measure.  I do not have the option to pass it on, other than writing a cheque and passing that on to a charity or to someone who needs it.  I must say that, because I am uncomfortable that I, as an representative in the Oireachtas, am getting some sort of subsidy when, quite frankly, I do not need it.  I suggest many other people do not need it either, but that is not for me to say because people have different circumstances.  That is my concern.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for setting out the context of this legislation and its provisions.  I acknowledge that the package of measures is clearly an attempt to sort out the issue of rising costs.  The Government has said that it is committed to protecting the most vulnerable.  I know where it is coming from in that regard.  Too many of the people in the squeezed middle, however, are telling me they have difficulties paying their rent or mortgage; it is a question of affording food or heat or the rent or mortgage.  These are tough times, and the Minister accepts and understands this.  </p> <p>The Bill establishes a scheme to make the electricity cost emergency benefit payment of &euro;200 in 2022.  I also understand, and this point has been raised with me by people who are tenants, that there are approximately 300,000 tenancies registered with the Residential Tenancies Board, RTB.  The Minister will be familiar with the work of that organisation.  Most of these tenants either hold their own electricity accounts or pay their landlords for the cost of their electricity based on a bill.  There are questions concerning who can receive this electricity cost emergency benefit payment.  It is clearly intended for the consumers of electricity in a residence and not the landlord.  This initiative, though, must be administered and I do not know if thought has been given to this aspect.  I ask the Minister to elaborate on this aspect of the scheme.</p> <p>I have several concerns regarding this Bill and I will flag them now.  We are talking about the need and importance of insulating customers from further electricity price rises.  It will be a long-term process, while this is a short-term measure.  In his contribution, the Minister stated, "The fuel allowance is one of a range of income supports paid by the Department of Social Protection, which also includes general social welfare schemes".  Not everyone receives those payments.  There are people on low incomes not receiving some of these payments.  </p> <p>The Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, indicated that there are plans to invest &euro;85 million as part of the local authorities' retrofitting programme for 2022.  I welcome that as a positive initiative.  These things take a long time to come through.  I am not sure if the Minister is that familiar with the detail of the scheme, but he might share what information he may have with us.  These are positive things that are happening and I welcome them.  In theory, this funding would allow for the retrofitting of more than 2,000 local authority homes and increase their energy ratings, and that is a plus.  Ideally, we should have a rolling programme to set this initiative in motion.  </p> <p>The Minister understands, as I do, that alleviating energy poverty must be a key consideration in any successful national retrofitting plan.  This is the problem.  The programme must be cost effective, but the current loan structure is unaffordable for many people.  This is the reality of the situation.  I asked a woman recently whether she would apply for this scheme and her reply was that she would get a lot of electricity for &euro;27,000.  I suppose she had a point.  The cost of retrofitting is prohibitive for many people on limited incomes.  </p> <p>I understand what the Minister is doing and I am supportive of what is being done.  It is a short-term undertaking.  There is a bigger strategic plan for the long term and we must go in that direction.  We have people who are cold in their homes, as I said, and who simply cannot afford to pay their bills.  Many of those people are working and on low incomes.  We must acknowledge that important point.  I spoke to a woman from County Galway and she told me she was thinking about removing her landline telephone connection because she can no longer afford it.  A landline is critical in rural Ireland, especially if there is a power cut and it is not possible to charge a mobile phone.  Taking out her landline will result in that woman becoming more isolated.  That is just an example of one personal experience.  I also received a letter recently, as many of us did, from the Irish Senior Citizens Parliament, a voice of older people.  The letter crystallises what I am trying to say to the Minister.  It refers to retrofitting being worthwhile and beneficial, but also states that the scheme excludes many older people who do have the savings base to secure a loan to do the work.  This point was made by an important and active organisation representing Irish senior citizens.  </p> <p>I am not going to dwell on this.  I am of course going to support this legislation.  I understand where the Government is coming from and what it is attempting to do, but we have a real energy cost crisis.  I would particularly like to hear about the Government's plans for retrofitting our social housing stock.  It is one area where we know people are suffering disadvantage.  Many of them are on low incomes, and that is why many of those people are in social housing.  It is a target area we could focus on.  If we are going to support people, let us target those supports to the really vulnerable people in need.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#FF00300"><p>I am thankful for the opportunity to contribute after Senator Boyhan.  The Minister is very welcome.  We all receive letters and go to people's doors, and we know we are in crisis.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pauline O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=PaulineOreilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are in the midst of two crises, a climate crisis and a cost-of-living crisis.  As has been said, this legislation is one small part of a set of measures.  This Bill came before the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Climate Action and many of us are members of that committee.  We all agreed to waive pre-legislatiive scrutiny of the Bill.  That was when the benefit payment proposed was &euro;100 less then what is proposed in Bill.  That showed we all understood the crisis, the emergency and that time was against us.  While I take on board the issues with the fact that the payment is not targeted, we also know that we must act fast.  The provisions are not in place to target this payment but many other measures are also being introduced.  It is important to reach everyone because everyone is impacted.  What people choose to do with this money is up to themselves but some people will rely on it heavily and need it urgently.  Other measures the Minister outlined include a 20% reduction in public transport fees, a fuel allowance lump sum payment of &euro;125, a reduction in the caps on school transport fees, a reduction in the drugs payment scheme monthly threshold from &euro;144 to &euro;80, which will impact on many people I know, and the front-loading of the working family payment.  </p><p>I hope Senator McGahon will speak about a flexible public transport ticket, which he has raised previously.  We need to address the issue of public transport.  I acknowledge the Minister is not present in his role as Minister for Transport but it is an important issue.  Important considerations are what plans the National Transport Authority has and how quickly it can implement those plans to ensure their roll-out.  Some 70% of 15-minute journeys are made by car.  We must address the fact that a modal shift is not taking place.  </p><p>A total of 14 councillors on Galway City Council voted against a proposed temporary cycle lane last night, bearing in mind that with respect to 15-minute journeys, only 1.6% of people cycle them.  We need to urgently address these matters.  Part of that is to ensure we have the necessary public transport and that it is available.  We are coming to that point now with Connecting Ireland and so on.  Part of that is also a responsibility on local authorities and local councillors and that means every party playing its part.  Only two political parties voted in favour last night, not of retaining the temporary cycle lane in Salthill as it had not been put in place but of keeping to what had been their previous message, namely, that they were in favour of the putting in place of a temporary cycle lane.  Everybody must play his or her part and not only the Minister but the local authorities.  Under the Climate Action and Low Carbon Development (Amendment) Act 2021, relevant bodies also have obligations.  That must include local authorities but they are not stepping up to the mark.  Time and again we have put forward funding to introduce such measures, which are low-hanging fruit when it comes to climate action, and councillors have voted against them and executives have not put them forward.  We have a climate crisis but also a crisis when it comes to local authorities and local democracy.  Every day people contact me who desperately want action to be taken to ensure their children do not have to get into a car to go to school.  I live five minutes from the promenade in Salthill and I certainly would not cycle with my children along that road.  I would cycle it but one has to dodge in and out as car doors are opened and closed all along the promenade.  It is simply not safe for even the hardiest of cyclists.  Therefore, there is an obligation on everyone, not only on the Minister.  </p><p>I would like to address the fact that some parties are against a carbon tax.  Sinn F&eacute;in is one of the very few parties, internationally, against a carbon tax; that is a fact. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#GG00200"><p>A minority of countries enforce it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#GG00300"><p>It is important to point out that many of these measures, including this one and the retrofitting measures, are all paid for from carbon tax revenue.  When I hear the narrative about the hike in the fuel prices, it is often blamed on carbon tax, but we must be honest with people.  That is not the case.  A very small percentage of that is carbon tax.  It is required to ensure we use a carrot to ensure we shift people into thinking a different way.  For instance, only 2.5 cent of the 35 cent increase on a litre of motor fuel is accounted for by the carbon tax.  The most responsible thing to do is to be honest about it to ensure we continue to address the climate crisis but also address, in a substantial way, and this Bill is a part of that, the cost-of-living crisis.  Those two elements can go hand in hand, which is what we have seen with the national retrofitting plan and the increase in the fuel allowance.  Is it not enough?  It is not because there is an international crisis.  We are reliant on a fossil fuel industry and on prices from other countries.  Therefore, we must increasingly invest in retrofitting and renewable energy.  Currently, wind energy accounts for 40% of our renewable energy and we need to reach the target 80% in eight years.  That will take investment but also people in local authorities, the national Government and national parties supporting us all in order that we can all move forward together.</p> <p>Many of us were at the lunch with Mary Robinson earlier and her big message was that the Seanad should be used to substantially address the issue of climate and to make it real for people.  These are measures that make it real for people.  Let us not play politics with it.  Let us all get on board with being honest about what carbon tax means and what measures are in this Bill, that they are a small part of what is required but that we are trying to do something positive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#GG00400"><p>I welcome the Minister.  Like many others, I welcome the Government intervention in assisting people with the significant cost-of-living increase, particularly concentrated in the energy sector.  The &euro;200 benefit payment and &euro;125 lump sum payment on the fuel allowance will not solve all the losses people for sure, particularly those on low pay and in receipt of social welfare, will have suffered as a result of this.  I need to speak out against the people who say it will make no difference.  For those people I deal with who are living on the edge, &euro;325 will mean an awful lot to them.  Those who would cast it aside and say it means nothing are people who are reasonably wealthy and are making a judgment.  The fact of the matter is that this intervention is significant and it will help.  It does not go all the way and, like Senator Boyhan and others, I would have liked a more targeted approach taken.  I would like to have seen a greater quantum of money given to people on lower incomes but I recognise that if we are to act quickly and try to address the problem, developing a means-tested targeted approach would disenfranchise people in the short to medium term and it would take too long.  It is always the case that wherever a threshold is set, there is a hardship case on the other side of that.  This is an appropriate response.  In an ideal world we would be able to do it differently.  Sadly, we do not live in an ideal world.</p> <p>In parallel, we need to increase our ambition for the retrofitting programme and the development of renewable energy sources, and the Minister is addressing that.  That is the future.  That is the best way we will address price certainty and energy security into the future.  We see what is paying out on the Russian-Ukraine border.  Obviously, that is creating international uncertainty.  It is allowing for gain for those who buy and sell the litre of oil a multiplicity of times before it ever gets to be utilised here at the end of a very long journey.  We have access to that area.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Timmy Dooley:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2015"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2015&amp;amp;pid=TimDooley&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister and I have had numerous conversations about our ambition regarding floating offshore wind turbines and a corresponding hydrogen strategy.  I just hope that the Government, over the coming years, will be able to advance these ahead of the ESB's ambition, which involves a timeline of eight to ten years.  We have got to realise our ambitions much more quickly.</p><p>At best, we hope that the very significant increase in oil and gas prices will be somewhat temporary.  Depending on who you listen to or read, the instability could be for the next 12 to 18 months, but it could be for longer.  The Government will have to intervene if it goes, or is likely to go, beyond that.  With the cost of diesel having risen by 35 cent to 40 cent in a relatively short period, people will just not be able to manage economically or take on the intolerable burden.</p><p>People have bought into the carbon tax.  I agree with my colleague in this regard.  The vast majority of people I know recognise there had to be a signal to the marketplace, investors and the fuel sector that fossil fuels would cost more in the future.  We agreed on this at the committee meeting, with the exception of one party and a number of Independents, whom I accept disagreed for their own reasons.  The reality, however, is that we had shown the trajectory and people had bought into it.  It pales into insignificance, however, when you consider the uncertainty the market has foisted on us.</p><p>We have to move towards more active travel.  We are getting there through our investment, but if the massive spike in the cost of diesel and petrol is to continue beyond a year or year and a half, the Government will have to do something to moderate it.  There are rebate systems.  There would be a very significant impact on the agricultural community, which we are trying to bring with us on this green journey.  From discussions the Minister had with some farmers in Clare last Friday, he will know they are up for that.  Not all of them are, but the majority are.  Increases will have an impact on the cost of goods and an effect on the supply chain.  Therefore, while I understand where the Government is at the minute, I am firmly of the view that if a price spike becomes a plateau, there will have to be a significant intervention.  I hope that can take place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#HH00200"><p>The electricity costs emergency benefit scheme we are talking about forms part of a package of budget interventions put forward in October 2021 by the European Union, including the Commission's toolbox of interventions that allow member states to go about tackling rising energy costs.  I ask everyone to read the supporting documentation today.  It is really interesting.  The tools will serve as an important part of our arsenal, not just in the next 18 months but also over the next eight years as we move towards our target of having 70% of our energy generated from renewables.</p> <p>Some of the price hikes that are due to be implemented in April are quite worrying.  I can see why they are so worrying for consumers but that is why it is so important to expand on the emergency measures the Government is taking to allay their concerns.  SSE Airtricity's electricity price is to rise by 6.2% and its gas price is to rise by 4.5%, effective from 1 April.  Energia announced an electricity price increase of 8.6% and a 5.7% in gas prices, effective from 5 April.  Panda Energy announced an electricity price increase of 7.5%, effective on 8 April.  Flogas announced an electricity price increase of 8.5% and a gas price increase of 6.5%, effective on 12 April.  We are not facing these increases only in Ireland but also right across the European Union.  The reason is the increase in global demand as we exit the pandemic.  However, it is important to remember that, as Senators have said, markets are expected to stabilise at some stage, possibly early this year.  </p> <p>While the instability exists, it is important to be able to introduce emergency measures such as the one under discussion.  As Senator O'Reilly said, we decided not to go ahead with pre-legislative scrutiny to allow us to introduce it across the board very quickly.  That is what is really important about it.  There could be further instability between now and 2023.  It will then be really important for the Government to rely on the European toolbox of measures.  It could be really useful.  There are many decent suggestions in it.  We are going with the main suggestion, which involves member states making payments to those most at risk in paying their energy bills.  This is being financed through the EU emissions trading system.  Along with implementing such measures, it is important that we consider introducing safeguards to make sure energy companies cannot disconnect people's energy supply.  This would be useful if people were to fall into arrears and things got worse. </p> <p>There are many other measures we could introduce.  The measure being introduced is just one of a suite of measures.  If things get worse, we can introduce an energy taxation directive whereby we can temporarily exempt vulnerable households from tax, or apply a reduced tax rate, directly in respect of electricity, natural gas, coal and solid fuel.  We could also do a lot to empower and protect consumers here in Ireland.  We could provide people right across the country with quality information and options regarding how they can participate in the energy market.  Making the switching of suppliers faster and easier is one way we can go about this.  We can further boost the role of consumers in the market.  We plan to do this by giving people the ability to generate their own electricity.  They will be able to use it themselves or sell it back to the grid.  I am trying to talk about a range of measures we can implement as a Government if we come across further price instability in electricity markets.</p> <p>On the point on selling energy back to the grid, creating our own energy and having energy communities, I want to make a small diversion into the topic of solar energy.  Both solar and wind energy will play such an important role in hitting our targets by 2030 and reducing our reliance on fossil fuels.  By reducing our reliance on fossil fuels, we will decrease the possibility of price instability.  I raised with the Minister at a committee meeting a couple of months ago the impact of capital acquisitions tax on the agricultural community and renewable energy sector.  The current rules for the tax state those who inherit agricultural land can get a relief of 90% on the market value of the asset, but this is contingent on the total amount of land being utilised for solar panels constituting less than 50% of the total landholding.  This threshold of 50% needs to be removed because the point is that we will not be able to incentivise people in the agricultural community to move into full-blown solar farming if their capital acquisitions tax is to be impacted if they wish to inherit a farm.  We want people to be able to fill a large field fully with solar panels, not 49.5% or something like that.  We should remove a barrier that exists in the agricultural community.  The Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, will have to examine this.  I spoke to him about it before.  I would appreciate it if the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications and I could meet briefly to discuss it.  He could pass on my concerns to the Minister for Finance.  Addressing the capital acquisitions tax issue would be a simple way to remove a barrier that exists, making sure people who want to get into solar energy can do so as easily as possible.</p> <p>Former President Mary Robinson mentioned earlier that people can be scared by the science and nuance of the climate action debate.  I found this myself when I first got involved as a climate action spokesperson 18 months ago.  Trying to get involved in the climate action debate can be intimidating when you are up against people like the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, and others who have been involved in it for decades.  What we need to do is make it as simple as possible for the average Irish person to engage in the debate.  We can do so by making measures financially viable for people.  We are doing this through the retrofit programme, the introduction of so many electric-vehicle charging points and making so many grants available.  We are making it financially simple for people who want to live a green and sustainable lifestyle.  We are making it financially possible but also as hassle-free and easy as possible.  An example of where we are doing this relates to the concept of the one-stop shops for the retrofit programme, whereby someone will project-manage the whole thing.</p> <p>I went off on a slight tangent but my point relates to solar energy.  If we want people in the agricultural community to engage in solar farming on a wide scale, we really need to remove the 50% barrier.  I am interested in hearing the Minister's thoughts on that.</p> <p>While we move towards renewable energy, we should note that it promises much lower prices in the long term.  Over the short to medium term, consumers may have to deal with the price instability we are seeing, but the whole point of the legislation we are introducing today and the suite of measures the European Union has said we could introduce, including the toolkit, is to address this instability.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John McGahon:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=JohnMcGahon&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While we are making the transition to a renewable energy economy and working hard over the next eight years to get to the 70% target for wind and solar energy, we must be able to introduce emergency measures or at least have fallback plans or measures that can be introduced, as we are doing now, to protect the Irish consumer against instability in energy prices.  This is a good example of one way of doing that, but it is just one of many other tools in the armoury that will be open not only to this Government but to all member states in the European Union.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#JJ00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  Before giving my substantive contribution, I must address some of the commentary here today.  I accept that people have differences of opinion on how to tackle climate change but I will not accept people dismissing the fact that others have done their research on this.  I have worked in the area of environmental issues and climate change for years and my research on the carbon tax, which is backed up by a meta-analysis carried out in 2021 and empirical <i>ex post</i>evidence from January and February 2021, shows that the reductions in carbon are minimal, at between 0% and 2% per year, and that it is highly damaging to the public buy-in to the transition.  I also wish to point out that in 2018 it was exposed by an eminent academic, who has exposed all the work ExxonMobil has done in damaging the arguments about climate change and undermining climate change evidence, that ExxonMobil pledged $1 million to support a carbon tax advocacy group and the head of that group was a former PR executive adviser for ExxonMobil.  We can disagree on this, but I will not have people saying that this is something that has just been jumped on as a populist measure.  This is a position that has been researched and which I will stand over.</p><p>We are talking today about energy poverty and people facing hardship.  It is worth pointing out that over a year ago, not long after I was elected, I was raising this issue with the Minister.  I conducted a study on energy poverty.  The responses received then were harrowing, even before all the hikes in energy prices.  People were huddling in one room and choosing between heating their homes or putting food on the table.  The dogs in the street knew back then that they were struggling.  However, whenever I ask Ministers about the level of energy poverty they are unable to give me an answer because we do not have a clear definition of what constitutes energy poverty.  It was clear from budget 2022 that the Government did not have a handle on the scale of the problem because it did not go far enough in that budget to protect people.  Then there was this announcement last week to make up for that, with the Government referring to if it had known then what it knows now.  The truth is, however, that many of us were highlighting this a year ago and saying there were massive issues with energy poverty.</p><p>In our alternative budget, Sinn F&eacute;in proposed enhanced payments in social welfare and fuel allowance.  Deputy Kerrane put forward the idea of a discretionary fund.  The T&aacute;naiste said he would consider it, but the Government failed to heed any of that.  If we do not know what the definition of energy poverty is and if we do not measure it, we cannot address it.  I have spoken numerous times, like a broken record, about the energy poverty strategy.  That strategy lapsed in 2019 and there is no new energy poverty strategy.  We were promised a review of the implementation of the previous strategy last year, but last week, in a response to a Commencement matter, the Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Ossian Smyth, promised that we will have it in the first quarter of next year.  We have also been promised Central Statistics Office, CSO, metric indicators around making sure that the retrofitting programme can be held up for its social impact assessment.  We are also told that the Economic and Social Research Institute, ESRI, is working on the metrics but, again, there is no timeframe for that.</p><p>It is unfortunate that Senator Pauline O'Reilly was not at the meeting today of the Joint Committee on Environment and Climate Action when the energy regulator, the Commission for Regulation of Utilities, CRU, was there for three hours to answer questions from those of us who are concerned about what the regulator is doing to help people with their energy costs.  It was deeply concerning to hear the regulator take a very hands-off approach to what it can do.  It refuses to intervene directly in the market and to regulate when 70% of what is in a customer's bill are costs that are directly regulated by the CRU.  I was dumbfounded to hear the regulator say that the markets will fix this and that it is just an international problem of costs when we know that the wholesale costs across the EU are lower than they are here.</p><p>The regulator refused a cap on affordable tariffs, as happens in Britain.  The pay-as-you-go tariff will not be capped and the default tariff will not be capped.  The regulator ruled it out, saying it did not have the evidence to show that it would work.  The regulator refused to curtail network and wholesale costs.  Some 38.1% of customers' bills will go on network costs and the regulator did not question that.  It was the same with its challenge of EirGrid and the ESB.  The regulator has spent 25% of its budget on private consultants, yet it has never challenged the ESB.  It does not have the resources to challenge the likes of the ESB and ask if all the costs are necessary.  The CRU was asked about public service obligation, PSO, reform.  Up the road in the North the PSO is designed in a way whereby households pay less PSO to businesses.  The regulator ruled that out as an option as well.</p><p>We are here to discuss the &euro;100 rebate measure, which forms part of the EU toolbox to address the energy price crisis.  People say it is not targeted and that it is too little, too late.  I have concerns.  We looked at what is suggested in the EU toolbox.  It says that social payments should be targeted.  The EU also suggested using the revenue from the EU emissions trading scheme to fund it.  Again, however, Ireland does not do that properly.  According to the European Court of Auditors and the Comptroller and Auditor General, the Government does not ring-fence the funds from the emissions trading scheme for climate measures.  We talk about the carbon tax but how about ring-fencing the money from the emissions trading scheme that is coming in every year for climate measures, as every other EU country does?  That would make energy-intensive companies pay for the transition instead of households.</p><p>I made a freedom of information, FOI, request regarding the &euro;100 rebate and it appears that funds to fund this &euro;100 or &euro;200 rebate are coming from energy poverty alleviation programmes, retrofitting and rural broadband.  The Department of Public Expenditure and Reform said in the FOI that it was concerned that helping people in this way would set a precedent and that the Minister should avoid going into details about where the funding was coming from because it was underspend from the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications.  The EU also suggested applying a reduced rate of tax on a temporary basis.  Again, the FOI showed that this was not considered.  It was ruled out of the question.  The EU suggested taking measures to help all energy consumers and to direct support for a defined minimum consumption per household or inhabitant.  While the Government's plan supports all energy consumers, it is blind to the minimum consumption necessary.  Everyone gets &euro;100 regardless of whether one lives in a G-rated rental or an A1-rated new build.  The EU suggests stepping up investments in renewable energy, renovations and energy efficiency, but the Government decided to do the opposite and take the money from that fund to fund the &euro;100 measure.</p><p>I am running out of time so I will not get to all the issues I wished to raise.  People at home might have been hoping that the energy regulator would do its job and regulate the energy companies when they are making profits.  I believe the profit for the ESB last year was &euro;74 million.  If we were banking on the energy regulator to stand up for ordinary people and households, it certainly made it clear today that this would not be the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#JJ00300"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House.  He spoke about his commitment to protecting the most vulnerable.  We all share the view that it is vital that something is done to address the cost-of-living crisis in this country, but how to fix it is another question.  Vulnerability comes in a number of forms.  There is vulnerability with regard to housing security and rising rents and vulnerability with regard to the prospect of some working parents thinking about leaving a job because there is no affordable childcare available.  The real regret and disappointment for me last week was that nothing was done with regard to what I consider to be the permanent cost-of-living crisis in this country.  There was no rent freeze and nothing for families who are reliant on or seeking affordable childcare.  Some childcare providers are saying that they will be forced to increase their rates over the coming months because of the tapering off of the employment wage subsidy scheme, EWSS.</p> <p>There was nothing for people who have to drive and do not have the alternative of access to public transport.  We want to shift people away from cars and into public transport, but the Minister knows as well as I do that the reality in large parts of this country is that there are no bus or rail networks.  Nothing was done to help them in view of the 32% increase in the price of diesel and petrol.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For those who are vulnerable and at risk of fuel poverty, there was also a huge disappointment.  There was an abject failure to amend and improve the fuel allowance scheme, which was put in place to deal with those who experience fuel poverty.  Other than the &euro;125 that they will get, nothing was done with regard to eligibility for the fuel allowance.  That 20,000 applications for fuel allowance were rejected last year, along with a further 3,000 in the first five weeks of this year, tells us something about the desperation that many households are in with regard to their rising energy costs.  There was a missed opportunity in the context of amending the eligibility and entitlement rules.  As the Minister knows, if everyone in a household does not qualify, nobody qualifies for the fuel allowance and that has to be changed from here on out.</p><p>We are here today to debate the Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill 2022, which provides for a universal untargeted payment of &euro;200 to all electricity account holders.  There are a number of key concerns with regard to the Bill.  First, the payment will be to electricity account holders.  There is a significant difference between the definition of an account holder and a household, particularly when it comes to utility payments.  For the less than 70% of households that are in owner-occupier houses that have a mortgage, it is relatively straightforward in that we know the &euro;200 will go directly to them.  However, for the more than 30% that are in rented accommodation, there are a whole raft of issues, some of which Senator Boyhan raised earlier.  For those who are renting accommodation where utility costs are part of the rent, we need to be clear on how we ensure the benefit of the &euro;200 payment goes to that household in part or in full and is not retained by the landlord.  We in the Labour Party will table amendments on that precise issue.  For those in shared accommodation, we need to be clear on how the payment will benefit everybody in the household and not just the person whose name the bill is in.  There is a glaring need to ensure those in rented accommodation get the full benefit.  Due to the way the Bill has been set out, there is a real risk that large pockets of people will fall through the net.  There are other issues with pay-as-you-go or prepay customers, which we know amount to 12% of all households in this country.  It is an increasing number and that reflects the hardship households are facing with regard to utility bills.  However, we have no detail on how they will benefit from this payment.</p><p>Overall, there is a serious question about the conversation the Government has had or will have with the energy suppliers in this country.  As Senator Boylan more eloquently expressed than I ever could, there has been a failure by the Commission for Regulation of Utilities to engage seriously with the issue of how energy suppliers can also contribute to supporting households.  Senator Boylan talked about how the profits of ESB Networks increased by &euro;74 million last year.  Energia's post-tax profit surged by 50% last year to almost &euro;29 million.  Bord G&aacute;is Energy again saw an increase in its profitability last year.  The question has to be asked: what are we asking of them?  Tariffs are tightly regulated in this country, but there must be scope within that system to ensure additional supports are provided during this fuel crisis.  The burden of responsibility must be shared between the Government and those energy suppliers.  There is an opportunity cost of using that &euro;215 million to support all households instead of supporting the worst-off households.</p><p>The Minister has said that energy efficiency is key in addressing the root causes of energy poverty, and I do not doubt his passion and sincerity in that regard.  We have heard him say that many times.  Last week's retrofitting announcements were very important and a significant step.  However, at the heart of what was announced last week there was a very basic inequality.  Households that can afford a deep retrofit, afford to stump up the 50% and afford to borrow or have the savings for the &euro;25,000 plus can reap greater benefits than a household that can only insulate its attic or do more minor works.  This is a serious problem.  The Minister knows, as do the Senators in the Chamber, that the gap in the energy bill for a house that has a rating of G or F relative to a house that has a B2 rating is in the region of &euro;3,500 per year, and I am sure that figure is growing.  We need to better support those households that do not have the savings or can never afford to borrow.</p><p>There is an irony here.  We are talking about a cost-of-living crisis.  The Government has decided to make a universal untargeted payment to everybody, in effect recognising that everybody is affected by the energy crisis.  As we introduce the retrofitting measures that are crucial to ensuring we take households permanently out of fuel poverty, as opposed to the temporary measure before us today, we need to ensure the money goes to all low-income households and not just those dependent on social welfare or in social housing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#KK00200"><p>I welcome the fact that we are taking action by way of an intervention in terms of electricity.  I understand the case the Minister made in that this is a measure he wants to move on speedily and the logic that was presented.  I have no doubt it will make a big difference to many households.  I would not diminish the impact it may have but I would point out, whatever about the speed that is needed in terms of this &euro;200 measure, having been &euro;100, there is a crisis which we have known has been coming for a while.  We also know, as does the Green Party Minister, that energy bill costs will go up because the costs of energy, particularly the cost of carbon energy, are so high.  We knew that was happening.  I am not blaming the carbon tax for the increase in prices; many factors are driving it.  The direction of travel, ultimately, is that fossil fuels will continue to create a high cost, with either society carrying that cost, the environment carrying that cost or citizens carrying that cost.  That is a fundamental piece about the direction of travel on this issue.  Therefore, we should have been planning in advance for the fact and likelihood of energy poverty and we need to do better planning for the next measures we bring in.</p> <p>We are in a climate crisis.  The cost-of-living crisis has received a huge amount of attention in recent weeks.  It has been felt by people for a long time.  The most fundamental distortion in most households' costs is housing but we will put that aside for now.  When we talk about the cost-of-living crisis, I sometimes wonder if we are deflecting from the housing crisis, which has increasingly claimed a greater proportion of every household's income for the past couple of years.  I do not know why the measures regarding the cost-of-living crisis suggested by the Minister in his speech would be temporary.  They have to be permanent.  I refer to measures such as a temporary 20% reduction in public transport fares.  In what world of a climate crisis could we imagine putting public transport fares back up again next year?  Clearly, that would be irresponsible in the context of the climate crisis we face.  I refer to the idea of reducing fee caps for children on school transport.  I believe an opportunity was missed in not removing some of the caps on school transport fees.  When people went back last September after the pandemic, everybody should have gone back with the option of free public transport that was fully subsidised.  It would have made a big difference.  It would have made people plan their lives and their families' lives differently.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->How could we, in a climate crisis, conceivably plan to change that cap again?  We need to be honest that we are in an extraordinary time of flux and change.  We are in a period of climate crisis and the cost-of-living crisis sits with within that.  We are also facing many political and geopolitical crises.  We need to start talking about radical measures as a reality.  In every month of the next 18 months, or every six-month period, we will need to be taking measures like this.</p><p>In that regard, the inequity that exists in a blanket and universal measure like the &euro;200 payment certainly should not be replicated.  There is no excuse for it to be replicated with retrofitting.  There is a concern there.  There is no excuse for having a measure and a retrofitting plan that is designed predominantly towards homeowners rather than those who are most vulnerable.  In the retrofitting plan we are told that the plan is for 50,000 houses per year.  There was a suggestion that it might be difficult to achieve the 50,000 because of building demand this year.  Yet, the plan only allows for 36,000 social houses to be retrofitted across a decade.  Why would we not front-load the social housing, given that in many cases the people living in such housing are also impacted by the high fuel prices?  Why would we not front-load that within this year or the next 18 months?  This is something that we can do.  The reason we are not doing it is a dynamic that I am very concerned about.  If we continue with this logic and dynamic, it will stop us tackling the climate crisis.  The logic seems to be that we want to create market dynamics.  Market dynamics in housing have failed us.  The market absolutely has a role, but when it comes to climate and energy security, one cannot take gambles on the market.  For example, we are hoping there will be demand in relation to retrofitting, and we will do things to encourage that.  That is fine.  In the next 18 months, however, we should really be trying to retrofit every house that we can and take that as direct action from the State, rather than this hands-off and market encouragement approach that we overly rely on.</p><p>Like others, I was at today's committee session with the Commission for Regulation of Utilities.  Frankly, I am extremely concerned because, while I do not put this on the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, much of its narrative was very close to the line "shop around".  That is very much the framing.  It is the idea that individuals, families and households will make all of these very complex decisions, that they will maximise, that they will save &euro;50 here or &euro;100 there, and that this will create the pressure on the market and then the market will suddenly start producing green energy at an affordable price.  In fact, the State has tools such as the regulator to try to address energy costs strongly.  There is, however, a reluctance to use this.  Again, it was the same language of market encouragement, consumer pressure and customer pressure.  Many people are not in that position.  It is the same when we are talking about this particular Bill, which relates to electricity costs, and it is the same again with the retrofitting scheme, unfortunately.</p><p>Renters are a big gap here.  How will renters be supported and how will this benefit them?  Much as with the retrofitting scheme, there was opportunity to put in security of tenure for renters and harder pressure for landlords with the stick and not just the carrot.  That is important.  The opportunity has not yet been taken in terms of retrofitting.</p><p>Another cohort that is very vulnerable are those on meters.  It is a concern if 12% of households, including some of the most vulnerable people in our society, are not going to be able to benefit from this scheme in the same way.</p><p>Another piece that is regrettable is one that the Minister had signalled.  Perhaps he has pressed for it.  I hope he would continue to press for it.  I refer to the expansion of eligibility for fuel allowance.  This is something that many of us expected.  Again, however, it has been disappointing that we have not seen more of a press on the fuel allowance, which is a targeted tool that we have, and the attachment and extension of it as widely as possible to those who are receiving social welfare allowances.  Maybe there could be an examination of those households - I believe it was 20,000 last year and 3,000 so far this year - that have been rejected for the fuel allowance, so that we can see the basis for them being rejected.  Obviously they are households that feel that they are vulnerable and need this support.  How can we adjust the criteria so that fewer of them fall out of the fuel allowance net?  I hope we can address this before September.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#LL00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, into the House.  I agree with Senator Higgins with regard to the public transport provisions.  I am aware of the measure introduced by the Minister for reduced fares for younger people, which is very welcome, but it should go further.  It represents a good start.  I agree with Senator Higgins that if we introduce a 20% reduction in the cost of public transport, we should keep that reduction.  I am not an expert on inflation, but if we reduce it by 20% now and then choose to increase it in January, a 20% increase - or as it would then be a 16.7% increase - will actually contribute towards inflation in January.  I would like to see this be allowed to continue.</p> <p>I certainly agree with some other points.  The fuel allowance is a targeted measure, and the measures in the budget also must be welcomed.  The lump sum in March has to be welcomed.  I agree with a lot of the comments made by colleagues but maybe we could broaden some of the debate.  We are going to see a lot of price volatility around electricity over the coming years.  It is not just because of some of the geopolitical concerns, but also because we will see a rise in electricity demand.  If we are to see the electrification of transport, which is something I support, this will lead to a rise in demand.  If we are going to look at green hydrogen, which we must focus on, this will also require through electrolysis renewable electricity to be used.   We are going to see a move out of fossil fuels, which is welcome, but this too will present some of its own challenges around demand.  Ireland must ensure it has the necessary supply as a result.</p> <p>There are a couple of questions that need to be asked.  One is around the planning process.  It takes far too long from the inception of some wind energy and solar energy projects to get them up and running.  I am thinking in particular of offshore projects.  I worry that some of the measures being announced are welcome in the short term but we need to start to think about long-term electricity demand and how we can ensure the supply is there, or else we will be constantly dealing with issues around energy prices.</p> <p>The Minister might be able to answer another concern I have with regard to reviews at European level of the EU wholesale energy and power market.  I am aware that Spain has been expressing concern, as a member state, that essentially we are selling cheap renewable energies on that market at roughly the same price as, or in some cases even costlier than, fossil fuel-produced markets.  I struggle to understand why Ireland is not as supportive as it could be in that regard.  There was evidence last October of Ireland opposing some of the electricity market reforms.  It would be welcome if we could look at the European energy market to see how we can ensure there is an incentive for that renewable energy to be produced.</p> <p>My final point is slightly tangential, but it is relevant because it is around the research into renewable energies, how we reduce some of these costs in the long run and Ireland's membership of CERN.  Ireland is one of only three European countries that does not have any real relationship with the world's leading physics research laboratory, which is looking at all of these areas of new and renewable energies.  If there is one thing we should have learned from the global pandemic it is that to get us out of some of these challenges, we must co-operate with other countries.  Similarly, when it comes to ensuring we tackle the climate crisis, while at the same time ensuring we continue to have a reliable supply of good renewable and clean energy, we must co-operate at a global level.  This has been spoken about for far too long but I believe that as a measure to ensure we play our part in global research into cheaper but more environmentally friendly energy, it is essential that the Government indicates very clearly that Ireland will join CERN.  I support the measures announced today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#LL00300"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, to the Chamber.  I welcome the Bill before us, which relates to the cost of living and energy costs for Irish householders.  It will have a hugely beneficial and real immediate impact once it can be processed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The electricity cost emergency benefit scheme is welcome.  A sum of &euro;100 was announced before Christmas, which is to be amended to &euro;200 in recognition of the price increase for wholesale gas.  I also welcome the Government response, with the cost-of-living measures that were agreed last week.  It is a realistic, targeted package, which will have an immediate positive impact by putting money back in people's pockets by quickly deploying cash to all households.  That package of &euro;505 million encompasses a range of measures to mitigate the cost of living, including a &euro;125 fuel allowance lump payment, the energy credit of &euro;100 excluding VAT, which we are dealing with in this Bill, an increase in the weekly income threshold for the working family payment, a reduction in the drugs payment scheme threshold, and a maximum annual charge of &euro;150 per family at primary level and &euro;100 per family at post primary for the next academic year for school and public transport fare reduction.  Those are all positives.  They are targeted and reduce costs for families.  I welcome all of that.</p><p>There was a debate about the carbon tax.  The beauty of the carbon tax is that it is ring-fenced.  People know that the money being collected for carbon tax goes to the retrofitting of homes.  The Minister, Deputy Ryan, announced a scheme last week which has been very beneficial.  If climate change did not exist, which of course it does, retrofitting homes and reducing costs would still be beneficial.  The carbon tax is targeted and important.  There is a scheme relating to the carbon tax for farmers, which will be rolled out under the new Common Agricultural Policy in 2023.  That is an area where the carbon tax is being used for environmental gain.</p><p>Some people have spoken about the cost of Government subsidies for fuel, diesel and petrol.  There is a high cost, but it also goes into general taxation, which pays for all the services that are provided across the country, in urban and rural areas.  I have heard people say, quite dismissively, that tax collected in rural Ireland is all spent in Dublin.  That is ridiculous.  Plenty of taxes and services are provided and spent in rural communities.  Every public official, teacher, garda, nurse, public servant and special needs assistant as well as our health services are paid for from general taxation and they provide the services that people avail of.  We also welcome the &euro;597 million in roads funding that has been announced.  There is some &euro;37.6 million for Galway County Council, which is beneficial.</p><p>I also welcome the Government investment of &euro;25 million announced some weeks ago for Rossaveal fishery harbour.  This will be potentially used in the building, maintenance and servicing of wind farms off the west coast.  A project by Macquarie's Green Investment Group at Sceirde Rocks off the west coast received relevant status from the Department in the first half of 2020.  This important project can progress through the planning permission process, subject to the Maritime Area Planning Act, which was recently passed by the Houses.  That is positive and has potential to harness offshore and renewable energy to allow us to become a country that exports energy.  That will help to reduce the costs of fuel and our reliance on fossil fuels.  Fossil fuels and gas will play a part over the coming decades, which is acknowledged.  The potential of offshore energy is substantial.  I welcome this Bill as a positive step to assist families with the cost of living.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#MM00200"><p>I had not intended to speak on this Bill.  I welcome the Minister to the House.  There are two or three provisions in this legislation that are reasonably good.  For many years, I have listened to people outside talking about us living in a bubble in here, totally removed from real society.  How many people sitting round the Cabinet table or in this House have ever experienced real poverty?  I mean people who could not even put a slice of bread on the table.  I remember one time in my life having three beetroots and a sliced pan for dinner for me, my wife and my two kids.  I cannot begin to express the anger I feel at throwing out &euro;200 to every electricity account in Ireland, including holiday homes, the rich, or people like me who are on a good income and do not need it.  I will not take it.  I am not saying that from a populist point of view but because I meet people who are struggling to live.</p> <p>I speak frequently in this House about members of the Defence Forces and how tough they have it.  A sum of &euro;200 would make a huge difference to these people.  I appreciate that the effort here was to get the payment to the public quickly, but what will we do if oil prices hit $150 per barrel by the end of the month?  How will we meet the demand or the cost increase if this goes on?  How will we address that?  We are using borrowed money to make sure people who can well afford to pay their ESB bill get &euro;200 from the Exchequer.  There were matrices that the Government could have used to make sure the payment was targeted.  We could have sent it to those who receive the working family payment, rather than every citizen in the country.</p> <p>There are good things in this legislation, but there are others that are difficult to understand.  There is a 20% reduction in the cost of public transport.  What about those who cannot avail of public transport because there is no public transport service close to them?  It is good to see the caps on school transport costs and the change to the drugs payment scheme, but I cannot get away from the &euro;200 payment.  I walk around south Dublin, where I live, and see some houses which cost &euro;7 million or &euro;8 million, knowing that the owners are getting &euro;200 off their ESB bill.  I ask myself how any of us in this House can justify that.  It is totally unacceptable.  It is the crudest measure the Government could have used.  How will we pay for this?  How will we continue to support people who find themselves in an energy crisis as energy costs go through the roof?  The way things are at the moment on the geopolitical stage, we could find oil prices hitting $150 per barrel by the end of this month and gas supplies being reduced around Europe.</p> <p>One of my colleagues mentioned landlords.  A number of landlords rent out properties and control every aspect of those properties.  They will get &euro;200.</p> <p>I appreciate what the Minister is trying to do, but the methodology being used is utterly wrong.  I will table an amendment on Committee Stage proposing to remove the &euro;200 payment.  I know people watching this debate will say "To hell with him, I want my &euro;200."  We would all take &euro;200 if it was thrown at us but at the end of the day, this is not the way to go.  We in this House are capable of providing a much better service to the public than introducing a measure as crude as this.  I regret I will not be present to hear the Minister's reply because I have another meeting to attend, but I will read his reply.  I am happy to meet him at any stage to discuss this matter with him.  I know he is a decent guy, but this is all wrong and I believe he is being badly advised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#MM00300"><p>I welcome the Bill and the opportunity to speak on it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister is very welcome to the Seanad.  </p><p>I want to echo the comments and sentiments expressed by other Senators in terms of having a preference for more targeted measures.  I accept the limitations of our ability to do that within a short period of time.  It is important that measures are rolled out quickly to show the understanding of the impact of the rise in the cost of living on people.  People are really struggling and the cost of living crisis has crept up on us.  This time last year, or even six or three months ago, it was all about the pandemic and Covid, and how we could deal with that.  Prior to that, it was all about Brexit.  Now the real crisis we all have to deal with on a daily basis is the cost of living which is impacting on everybody in communities and society.  </p><p>We know the current average domestic customer bill is approximately &euro;1,715, comprising &euro;976 for electricity and &euro;739 for heating.  Several reports estimate an overall increase of another &euro;500, a rise of approximately 29%.  That is colossal.  We need to make sure that we are doing everything we can to alleviate the pressure on household incomes, and such measures are welcome.  The &euro;200 electricity credit will make a difference.  I ask those who feel they do not need it ensure they give it to a local St. Vincent de Paul service or other such organisations that help those who could do with more than &euro;200.  </p><p>The lump sum payment of &euro;125 in the fuel allowance will be paid in early March to 390,000 recipients.  There is no doubt that will make a difference, but we need to widen the eligibility threshold for the fuel allowance.  I ask the Minister to consider that as a matter of urgency.  These measures will not cover the impact of the increased cost of fuel and electricity, but they will make a difference.  To say they will make no difference is simply untrue.</p><p>We also need to be clear that the increases we are all seeing in fuel and electricity costs are based on international factors.  Certain political groupings which are trying to paint the imposition of carbon taxes as the root cause of our issues are being completely disingenuous.  They are damaging our collective efforts to encourage people to shoulder the responsibility of reducing carbon emissions.  </p><p>I want to acknowledge that the Government has been to the fore in tackling climate change and there is no doubt that we have seen a distinct focus on climate mitigation measures.  The recent retrofitting announcement is important in this regard and is something that we need to replicate.  New grant levels have been announced.  They will cover up to half of the cost of a deep retrofit and up to 80% of the cost of doing simpler work, which is important.  Such work could knock about 20% off the cost of annual heating bills.</p><p>I have two pleas for the Minister.  One is regarding the loans that will be made available for those who need to draw them down.  I ask that the Minister consider the possibility of rolling out those loans through the post office network.  Practically every rural community has a post office.  We have a dedicated group of people who are very committed to their communities.  It would be a good way of rolling out loans.  I also ask the Minister to make sure that the red tape and bureaucracy around the administration of the loans be minimised because that is one complaint about the current SEAI scheme.</p><p>I want to mention the 20% reduction in fares on public transport, which is very welcome.  I would like to once again advocate for a medium hop zone for the south Kildare area.  As we know, people are travelling from Portarlington, Kildare and Newbridge to Sallins because it is within a short hop zone.  They are staying on the roads and driving due to the difference in fare price, when they could access trains in their towns.  The price in Sallins is one third of the price of the journey from Newbridge, which is 6 km away.  That has to be examined.  Some cannot access public transport because there is simply no public transport for them in rural Ireland.  I speak for rural Kildare.  We need to have a bigger investment in our local link service which would be able to bring people to hop zones.  </p><p>Overall, this is a positive Bill which goes some way towards tackling the spike in prices.  We need to keep the pressure up to ensure that additional supports are put in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#NN00200"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  We are discussing the Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures Bill.  The Minister is fully aware that we are in the middle of a global energy crisis and that the impact of inflation in the eurozone is nearly 7%, never mind what is happening in the United States.</p> <p>The Minister mentioned the short, medium and long term.  In the short term we need to take action right now.  That is the &euro;200 that will be put into over 2 million household accounts by April.  That is immediate action to deal with an issue that is facing us right now.  The Minister also mentioned the fuel allowance.  I agree that we need to review the eligibility criteria, but it will benefit up to 70,000 households.  </p> <p>When it comes to the medium term, there is investment in the retrofitting scheme which is important.  Last week, 100% funding was announced for those who are most vulnerable, 80% for wall and attic insulation and up to &euro;25,000 for a full energy home upgrade.  The Minister, Deputy Harris, referred to the centres of excellence that have been rolled out for the retrofit scheme.  There are now four across the country.  We need to upskill people and get them up to speed in their trades so they are able to roll this scheme out.  I do not know if the Minister can speak about the plans he has in place to manage the waiting times around that.</p> <p>Yesterday, &euro;430 million in funding was announced for the third level sector.  Half of that will go to technological universities.  There will be four funding streams, one of which will be around apprenticeships.  Technological universities will have the capacity to develop more and more students coming through to do apprenticeships linked with employers.  That is crucial.  </p> <p>The Minister also spoke about the long term, which comes back to renewable energy measures, in particular offshore wind farms.  I am curious about how the micro electricity scheme has progressed since the announcement in December.  Does the Minister have any update on that?  It would be very interesting to hear about that.  It has huge potential in terms of our farms and schools being able to have solar panels which generate their own electricity while also paying back into the grid under the export certificate scheme.</p> <p>The Minister knows I am from Ballinasloe and he knows Ahascragh pretty well.  East Galway and Roscommon are quite regional areas.  The Minister is very aware of the transport challenges we face.  I was involved in the Connecting Ireland scheme during the public campaign.  I did two campaigns, one in Roscommon and a second in east Galway, to promote transport and how we want to connect our universities and hospitals, such as TUS in Athlone and GMIT in Galway.  There is no real connectivity between key institutions, amenities and hospitals in our area, such as Portiuncula Hospital and Roscommon University Hospital.</p> <p>What is the outcome of the Connecting Ireland rural mobility plan?  Is there a timeline for when there will be an outcome?  A number of different routes were suggested.  In the past week a reduction of 20% in fares on public transport was announced and the cap on school transport costs at &euro;500 for a family with secondary school children is welcome.  </p> <p>However, an awful lot of people in my area are annoyed because that is of no benefit to them.  Such measures are brilliant if people are living in city or town centres.  The fare scheme for students aged 19 to 23 was introduced in the budget, which involves half-price travel.  It should be implemented as soon as possible, along with the working family payment.  </p> <p>What about the Connecting Ireland scheme?  When will we get the feedback from that?  When will there be more transport between our smaller villages and towns?  When will there be basic bus stops with a cover on them?  It sounds like we are asking for the sun, moon and stars, but when I was a councillor I invested in one bus shelter.  We could only have one on one side of the road in Ballinasloe because of the width of the footpath.  There is no cover for people waiting at bus stops.  The bus stops at the hospital are covered, but older people, those with disabilities and those with families, including children in prams, are being asked to wait on the side of a road.  It is crucial that we have quality of life because people now demand more than they did 20 or 30 years ago.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aisling Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AislingDolan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->People now demand more than 20 or 30 years ago.  There are people who are taking taxis right now and how does this funding of a 20% decrease in public transport fees benefit them?  I know it is hard for the Minister to provide answers immediately and I very much appreciate the short-term and immediate measures that the Government has taken straight away.  In the medium and long term, how will we get back inputs from the measures being put in place over the past few months?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#OO00200"><p>The Minister is very welcome and I am delighted to get the opportunity to speak to the Bill at a time when people are facing real hardship in their lives with inflation and rising energy costs.  These costs have led to many families spending a higher proportion of their income on food and fuel.  Electricity prices have increased by 22%, gas prices have increased by 28% and the price of home heating oil has gone up by a massive amount in excess of 50%.  I have a small business that includes a fuel court and we can see when every delivery comes in there is a 5 cent or 10 cent increase.  That has happened over the past ten months or so, leaving many families with the painful decision between heating their house or feeding themselves.  The rising cost of electricity is a global trend and it is causing cost-of-living issues all around the world.  Here in Ireland it is affecting pensioners and families whose income is not rising enough to keep up with increasing energy costs.</p> <p>I welcome this measure and the Bill that has been brought forward by the Minister as part of the Government, and it will put &euro;200 towards every household electricity bill.  It may not be enough for some families and we must put in place an extra fund for those who may continue to find themselves in hardship.  I am in favour of perhaps having a smaller grant for all account holders while giving additional funding to others, as has been done through the fuel allowance, or increasing the credit in the household scheme, particularly for the likes of older people and carers, to give a larger number of free electricity units.  It would be a more targeted approach.</p> <p>I have a few queries.  We have heard mentioned the question of holiday homes and where landlords have kept the electricity accounts in their own names but customers are using prepaid credit purchased in various shops.  We must also consider the development of long-term and sustainable options to make electricity more affordable.  There is much potential in this country to deliver wind energy offshore on a massive scale.  This would create jobs in our towns and villages along our coastline and it would be capable of being our biggest contributor to the effort to reduce carbon emissions.  We must tap into that resource.</p> <p>I welcome the recent enactment of the Maritime Area Planning Bill 2021, which will help us achieve our renewable energy targets and regulate planning for offshore wind.  There is a major opportunity to develop solar panels on various schools and community centres, as well as on agricultural sheds throughout the country, and this would cut costs while also providing income.  I know there is a Private Members' Bill from the Minister's colleagues in the Green Party being discussed here tomorrow related to that and I will support it fully.  I am involved with my local community centre and we recently installed solar panels.  We had to go through the expense of having to get full planning permission to do that.  I welcome any change in that regard.</p> <p>I also welcome the national home energy upgrade scheme, which will provide up to &euro;8 billion to 2030 for the retrofitting of houses.  We can think back to when the Green Party was previously part of a Fianna F&aacute;il Government at the time of the crash, and although these types of schemes were suggested, the funding was a problem.  If we had funding at the time to retrofit more houses, we would not have as many issues as we do today.  This scheme will address a major challenge for households, as the question was being asked as to whether it made financial sense to spend money on such work.  A constituent of mine who had a detached house built in the 1940s with solid stone walls got a quote of &euro;26,500 to do an external retrofit, with a grant set at &euro;6,500.  That person decided it did not make financial sense to invest the difference in the work as it would take perhaps 40 years to claw back that investment.  I welcome this scheme, which makes it more realistic for people to spend money on such work and get benefits from it.</p> <p>I support the comments of Senator O'Loughlin about a loan scheme.  The Minister may know I also work for An Post and there would be a great opportunity to work with that company, which has previously set up the Green Hub scheme.  I would like to see the Department working with An Post to roll out that loan scheme.  It is important for us as public representatives to promote this scheme in all our local areas and ensure people avail of it.</p> <p>I will digress slightly to the matter of roads.  I spoke to the Minister when he came before the transport committee a number of weeks ago about the N4 in particular and how a preferred route has not been identified.  Funding has not been put in place for the consultation process to continue and we were only a number of weeks away from identifying an initial preferred route before we could have further consultation.  I ask the Minister to comment or is Transport Infrastructure Ireland in a position to provide that funding to ensure the scheme could continue?  This would enable us to have a nailed-down preferred route rather than having hundreds of families left affected by the ten identified routes.  They cannot get planning permission as a result.  Will the Minister comment on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#OO00300"><p>That concludes the contributions from Senators so I invite the Minister to respond to the debate.  I ask him to do his best to do it within ten minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#OO00400"><p>It will not be a problem for him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#OO00500"><p>I thank all the Senators who contributed to what has been a very useful and interesting debate.  I very much appreciate the thought and time they have given to their contributions.  I will not address every matter raised but I will try to cover as many as I can.</p> <p>I will start with Senator Boyhan, as some of the points he raised were also mentioned by a number of other people.  There is the question of everybody getting this credit.  We must look at this and recognise that this is not the only measure that the Government is applying to address energy poverty.  The primary means or mechanism for doing this is the budget.  The measure before us is unusual or exceptional and I do not believe it will be repeated.  We are in unprecedented times.  The majority of the measures to address energy poverty were contained in the budget.</p> <p>What Senator Boyhan said is true because we have been watching these gas prices rise for almost a year now with increasing concern.  The increases arise because of factors that include a rise in demand in Asia and very low stocks in Europe.  Even last summer there was a very low incidence of wind across north-west Europe, leading to gas demand increasing.  The increasing price of carbon shut coal plants, leading to more gas plants being used.  There is an incredibly complex range of factors that caused the particular spike in gas prices at the centre of this energy price spike that we have seen.  This is why the Government in its budget introduced significant measures for social welfare, including increases in household allowances, the qualified child allowance, the working family payments and the fuel allowance.</p> <p>It recognised that we must target and try to prevent fuel poverty in everything we do.  I attended the European Council of energy ministers and environment ministers in the autumn and it was indicated that we had to go further across the board in countries across Europe.  This was because we were not seeing prices come down as quickly as we expected them to.  We still expect them to come down, although again not as quickly as expected.  The European Commission's expectations for inflation in our country next year will be between 2% or 3%, I believe.  The expectation is that inflation in gas prices will come down, although not as quickly as we would like.  The rate is far higher than historical precedent suggests.  The European Commission indicated in the autumn that we should start looking at other measures for further support.</p> <p>Included in that toolbox were direct payments.  We might have looked at mechanisms including reducing VAT or taking from the emissions trading system, as mentioned by Senator Boyhan.  With this measure we have taken from an underspend in the previous year and provisions from the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform in contingency funding in order to make a direct payment to everyone.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Eamon Ryan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2028"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2028&amp;amp;pid=EamonRyanGP&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If it is seen just in isolation people think we are looking after everyone in the same way.  We are not.  There is a range and sequence of other measures.  Included in this is the money for retrofitting.  There is &euro;267 million from the Department and &euro;85 million from the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage.  Senator Higgins and others said it is not targeted.  It is targeted.  The majority of money is targeted at those on low incomes.  Out of the &euro;267 million approximately &euro;118 million-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00200"><p>For clarity-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00300"><p>The Minister without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00400"><p>I said the overall retrofitting scheme did not do enough to target those on lower incomes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00500"><p>I thank the Senator.  The Minister without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00600"><p>It is useful debate.  The warmer homes scheme, which is 100% State support for those at most risk of fuel poverty, gets &euro;118 million out of the total, and rightly so.</p> <p>I do not have the full details on how the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage is progressing on it but it is getting stuck in.  It is learning.  It is deeply committed.  The Government is committed to tackling three issues with all of our heart.  These are: tackling the health crisis of Covid and reforming the health system; addressing the housing crisis, which is particularly profound in our areas of the country; and the climate crisis.  The climate crisis requires an all-of-government effort and not just from the Department with responsibility for climate action.  The &euro;85 million, which is not a small contribution and which will scale up as the Department learns, is targeting those on the lowest incomes.  I can understand asking why we are giving something to everyone but we are not.  We are targeting it.</p> <p>The payment was deliberately designed so it could be done quickly.  These are the months we need the support.  We do not want people out there saying they will turn off their heating now.  It will be cold next week and bad weather is forecast.  We do not want people who might be at risk of fuel poverty saying they will live in the cold.  This is one of the biggest health risks we have.  Having it payable now in the teeth of the highest spikes in prices is the right thing to do.  Doing it directly through the bill and through the networks means it is a rebate straight back.  We looked at a range of issues.  Senator Boylan asked about EU emissions trading system funding.  We looked at this.  The funding would not have covered the amount of money we need.  This way is quick and something we could do in an effective low-cost way.  It was designed to leave no one behind.</p> <p>To answer the question about those in the rental sector, the Bill has been specifically designed so that the vast majority will be recipients of the direct credit as they get the bill.  In instances where people do not get the bill, there is clear provision for the Residential Tenancies Board to be able to act as a mediator should a landlord not pass on the benefit.  This has been designed to protect those in vulnerable positions.  Tenants are just as important as the owner of a household.</p> <p>I am very conscious I am constrained by time.  I have probably almost busted my ten minutes.  I want to mention a couple of other points.  Senators Dolan, Carrigy and others mentioned the transport provisions.  The heat of the price crisis at present is in energy and transport because of oil and gas.  Gas is increasing electricity bills as well as heating bills because our electricity bills are set by the price of gas.  Transport is also a significant cost and it has seen increases.  We have to be careful in fighting inflation.  If we just pump money into the economy to fuel inflation it could be very counterproductive.  We want to give a clear signal to people with regard to their everyday real lives and the bills they have to pay, such as prescriptions and bus or Luas fares.  Bringing these down helps, particularly for those struggling to meet day-to-day costs.  The reduction in transport costs was also needed.</p> <p>The measure on transport is also needed because our public transport is slow to come back after Covid.  Average patronage is approximately 60% of pre-Covid numbers.  It varies.  In the regional cities it has taken off.  In Limerick I understand it is back to almost 100%.  We have introduced new services, such as in Navan and Louth, where we have redirected bus services and these have gone above what we expected.  We will have to get more buses and drivers into some of these areas.  The new services have taken off.</p> <p>To respond to Senator Dolan, I do not have the full details on the consultation process with the NTA on Connecting Ireland but I believe it is one of the most important investments in public transport we have made.  It has the potential to be creative and efficient whereby, in just the way Senator Dolan has spoken about, we connect our public transport and local link services with local health services, social welfare service and schools.  This is an opportunity.</p> <p>We will have to do this well because there is not an endless pot of money.  It is the public's money we are redistributing.  It is the tax we pay.  Only a government can do this in a clever and intelligent way to do things that only the public service can do, such as a public transport system or protecting social welfare for those who do not have a safety net.  Tax is not a bad word from my perspective coming from the left because it gives us the ability to protect or to invest in a way that as a private citizen we can never do.  We can never get the security from our neighbours, which is part of our security, if we do not have the tax revenue.</p> <p>We are going to have to be efficient and clever.  We have put a lot of money into these measures because it was important to have a response immediately but the State also needs to get good value from the money we spend coming out of Covid.  We must be very clever and smart in how we spend it.  I will finish with this thought.  I was worried about being a bit inflationary until I heard the Opposition the day after we announced the &euro;500 million calling for spending of &euro;1.5 billion and &euro;2 billion.  I will raise them &euro;3 billion.  Let us make it &euro;4 billion.  We have to be careful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.132" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00750"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00775"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00787"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.136" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 22 February 2022.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.137" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP00900">Report of Joint Committee on the Carbon Budget: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP01000"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann shall take note of the Report of the Joint Committee on Environment and Climate Action laid before the Houses of the Oireachtas on 7th February, 2022, pursuant to section 6B(2) of the Climate Action and Low Carbon Development Acts 2015-2021 regarding the carbon budget, which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 6th December, 2021, pursuant to section 6B(1)(a) of the Acts. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#PP01100"><p>I thank the Seanad for inviting me to discuss the carbon budget programme and the recently published report of the Oireachtas joint committee on the proposed carbon budgets.  I welcome the committee's recommendation for the carbon budgets to be adopted and I greatly appreciate the approach taken by its members.  A number of Senators were centrally involved in some of the work of the committee in the production of its report as they engaged with numerous stakeholders and experts and sought to achieve political consensus on the need for robust climate action.  As I told the committee in November after returning from COP26 in Glasgow, I witnessed there the powerful testimony of many international leaders from climate vulnerable nations who painted a stark picture of the impact climate change is having on their nations.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Eamon Ryan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2028"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2028&amp;amp;pid=EamonRyanGP&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The latest Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, IPCC, report, Climate Change 2021: The Physical Science Basis, establishes incontrovertibly that the negative effects of climate change are already being experienced globally and will continue to increase exponentially in magnitude and volatility along with global temperatures.</p><p>We made some progress towards this goal in Glasgow.  Ireland had a significant presence there and undertook extensive engagement on a number of key areas that will feed into the global decarbonisation efforts.  The Glasgow Climate Pact, which is an overarching agreement, keeps alive the ambition of restricting global temperature rise to 1.5&deg;C.  It strikes a balance between increasing climate ambition and delivering on calls for increased climate finance and adaptation supports.  It provides a way for new dialogue on loss and damage, critical to supporting climate justice for those most exposed to climate change.</p><p>Last year saw a step change in our approach to climate action with the signing into law of the Climate Action and Low Carbon Development (Amendment) Act 2021 and our new climate action plan.  The plan establishes our climate objectives in law and will underpin national climate action in the medium and long term.  On 25 October last, the Climate Change Advisory Council submitted the first carbon budget programme under the Act.  This programme comprised three consecutive five-year carbon budgets, bringing us to 2035.  The first two budgets in the programme provided for a 51% reduction in greenhouse gas emissions by 2030 relative to 2018, as set out in the Act.  The third budget is provisional and is consistent with the 2050 national climate objective.</p><p>Last December I caused a copy of this proposed carbon budget programme to be laid before both Houses of the Oireachtas.  The D&aacute;il referred the programme to the Joint Committee on Environment and Climate Action for its consideration.  On 1 February the committee voted to support the proposed carbon budgets and on 7 February it published its report recommending that the budgets be adopted by both Houses of the Oireachtas.</p><p>In parallel and in accordance with the climate Act, a public consultation on the carbon budgets concluded last week and the submissions received are being reviewed by my officials.  As part of the process to consider the proposed carbon budgets, I have consulted the relevant Ministers.  Following consideration of the public consultation, the recommendation of the joint committee's report and input from Government colleagues, I will take the proposed carbon budget programme to Government for approval and a motion will be considered on the Government's proposed carbon budgets taking effect.  Once these economy-wide carbon budgets are adapted, the Government will divide the budgets into sectoral emissions ceilings.  Such ceilings will establish how each sector must contribute to meeting the target through further established sectoral decarbonisation targets.</p><p>It is crucial we prepare our carbon budgets and sectoral emissions ceiling and that delivery of climate action continues at pace.  The climate action plan that I launched on 4 November with the Taoiseach and T&aacute;naiste provides a detailed roadmap for meeting our climate ambition under the Act.  The 2021 plan sets out indicative ranges of emissions reductions for each sector of the economy.  Following the legal adoption of carbon budgets and sectoral emission ceilings, these ranges will be finalised and reflected in the 2022 climate action plan.</p><p>The Government has published an accompanying annex of actions to support the delivery of the climate action plan.  The annex sets out the detailed actions and measures with timelines that are required to drive delivery and ensure our emissions fall.  It also identifies the key Departments, State bodies and other key stakeholders that will oversee and implement the actions.  The Government will support the changes through major public investment announced recently in the &euro;165 billion national development plan, including increased funding for retrofitting our homes, building new public transport, reskilling workers and supporting a just transition.</p><p>While climate action plan for 2021 builds on the ambitious targets of the 2019 plan, it represents a significant step up in ambition and implementation.  I will highlight a number of the most significant measures in the plan.  It commits to increasing the proportion of renewable electricity to 80% by 2030, including an increasing target of 5 GW of offshore wind energy, and to a significant reduction in transport emissions by 2030, which will be achieved by enabling 500,000 extra walking, cycling and public transport journeys per day by 2030 and supporting the take-up of 1 million electric vehicles by 2030.  It includes the implementation of a new national retrofit plan, which we discussed in the previous debate.  It commits to a faster uptake of carbon neutral heating in our enterprise sector, increased electrification of high temperature heating and the phasing out of F-gases with high global warming potential.  It includes reducing emissions associated with agriculture and provides a pathway to doing so while supporting world-class food production through innovation.  There will be a reduction in chemical nitrogen.  There will be more targeted use and a fall in the use of fertiliser, while maintaining our position as global leader in healthy, pastoral family farming systems.  Reducing emissions for land use and moving it from being a source of emissions to a store will involve huge amounts of bog rehabilitation, significantly increased afforestation and the rewetting of peat organic soils.  A new forestry programme will be prepared for launch in 2023.</p><p>The plan places a just transition at the core, setting out four principles that will guide our policymaking and implementation over the coming years to ensure we effectively monitor and manage our transition and that our responses remain flexible so we can respond to future transition challenges and target the areas in need of support.  Each Minister as well as the Government as a whole will be expected to consider these principles as we develop and implement our climate policies.  We have committed in the plan to establishing a just transition commission, which will make periodic recommendations to Government, building on research, engagement through the national dialogue on climate action and the annual review from the Climate Change Advisory Council, on how Government policy can further the just transition.</p><p>In delivering this ambitious climate action plan, we must ensure we bring people with us and the transition is fair.  The national dialogue on climate action, launched in March 2021, will facilitate public engagement, participation, community action, networking and capacity-building activities, giving everyone in society the opportunity to play their part.  Last November, I announced &euro;60 million in funding from the climate action fund for community climate action projects to support and empower communities to shape and build low carbon sustainable communities in a coherent way.</p><p>The proposed carbon budget programme provides Ireland with a strong and deliverable framework for meeting our national climate objectives and our international obligations on climate action and emission reductions.  It will require a considerable level of co-ordination and co-operation to ensure we meet these budgets.  The processes undertaken to consider the proposed budgets highlights how to build political consensus towards robust and impactful climate action.  It will take similar levels of engagement to achieve the delivery of the budgets.</p><p>The transition to a climate neutral economy will provide significant opportunities to foster innovation, create new jobs and grow businesses in areas like offshore wind, cutting-edge sustainable agriculture and low carbon building.  While we must all act together towards our climate objective, I realise the cost of climate action will be more acutely felt by some than others.  As a Government, we are committed to protecting those most vulnerable and ensuring a just transition to a low carbon economy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#QQ00200"><p>I thank the Minister for that comprehensive introduction.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#QQ00300"><p>The Minister is welcome again.  Many of us in the House were on the Joint Committee on Environment and Climate Action that has put this report together.  It is appropriate, therefore, that we are discussing it in the Seanad.</p> <p>We are in a climate emergency.  I know we say that a lot but time is upon us.  Particularly in relation to these carbon budgets, there is a statutory time laid down by which they have to come before the Oireachtas.  We had that in mind.  It is important to go back to the climate Act and look at the fact we strengthened the council that came up with the recommendations put before us.  On the basis of its evidence before us and the extremely ambitious targets in the carbon budget, the committee decided to agree with its proposals.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pauline O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=PaulineOreilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We put forward several other recommendations that I hope the Minister will consider, particularly in respect of peatland.  I know Senator Higgins put forward a recommendation relating to peatlands that I was certainly happy to support because it is something we could start doing immediately.  I know the Government has been doing that immediately.  It is also a crucial part of a just transition.</p><p>My core point is that these budgets are very ambitious.  That is overwhelmingly what all of those who came before the committee stated.  To be fair, three members of the committee did not agree with the proposal and believed it should go further.  However, if we are looking at a just transition and are faced with incredibly onerous and ambitious targets, those who are seeking something that goes beyond that have to point to how we can go beyond that and still bring everyone with us and ensure we are meeting our targets.  I am not sure that is possible based on the evidence that was presented to the committee.</p><p>The members of the Climate Change Advisory Council who spoke to the committee stated there were certain issues in respect of modelling, particularly when it comes to social justice.  The reason for that is that we just have not been doing these budgets.  That is something in which we need to invest in the coming years.  There could be an ongoing process with the Department to bring scientists and departmental officials together on an ongoing basis to consider how we can model each individual decision that comes before us, because that is ultimately what these carbon budgets are going to come down to.  We have a detailed climate action plan and in the annexe of actions there are hundreds of pages on what we have to do in each quarter of each year.  In order to make those decisions, we need to do more than set carbon budgets.  We probably need to do more than come back on it every year; we actually need to look at the individual actions.</p><p>That is substantially what I wish to add to the discussion.  The committee was presented with good evidence, which the Minister has before him in the report.  The difference of opinion substantially comes down to the issue of whether it is ambitious enough.  I, and the majority of committee members, believed it was and that there was no convincing evidence that we could effectively go beyond that.  I point to the remarks of Ois&iacute;n Coghlan of Friends of the Earth Ireland.  I will not quote his exact comments but all of the witnesses who contributed on the day he appeared before the committee were specifically asked if they agreed with the carbon budget and they confirmed they did.  I know witnesses who appeared on another day went beyond that but what those people who have been dealing with politics for a long time feel quite strongly, as do I as somewhat of a newbie, is that we have to be realistic and ambitious and ensure we are doing something that is socially just but will, at the end of the day, get the job done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" speakername="John McGahon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RR00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his attendance and for taking two debates one after the other.  I pay tribute to Deputy Leddin.  As Chairman of the Oireachtas committee for the past 18 months, he has done a tremendous job of steering landmark legislation through the Oireachtas.  Senators Higgins and Pauline O'Reilly and other committee members will agree that at all times Deputy Leddin has tried to do so in a very collegial and consensus-based manner.  We do not agree all of the time.  That is the way politics and the world of debate are and that is absolutely fine.  I pay tribute to Deputy Leddin and his stellar leadership of the committee in getting us to where we are today.</p> <p>In my simplistic view, carbon budgets set out a clearly defined roadmap we need to follow to achieve the targets we want to hit in 2030 and 2050.  As the Minister stated, that roadmap includes the sectoral targets.  I refer to how expansive those sectoral targets are, whether in agriculture, changing land use, active travel, transport or what we want to do with electric vehicles or getting people back on public transport.  The targets are so vast and widespread that it is so important we have carbon budgets to provide that significant roadmap for people in a wide variety of sectors to be able to follow.  I have no doubt that the introduction of carbon budgets will help us to get to a climate-resilient and, most important, a climate-neutral economy by 2050.</p> <p>The public consultation was really important and there are many good views for the Minister and his officials to consider.  What is impressive about the climate action committee is that it is able to draw on such a wide variety of people from academia, NGOs and a whole sector of society to get expert advice that we, as Oireachtas Members, can take back and put into a report and recommendations for the Minister to consider.</p> <p>To add to the point made by Senator Pauline O'Reilly, while we have to be ambitious about this because that is what the climate crisis demands, it is also about doing it in a structured way so that we can bring people along with us.  We have to accept that it is going to be more difficult to bring some people along with us than others.  It is about convincing those people and being able to bring them on board in a simple manner that will help all of us get to the points we want to achieve.  That is why it is important to be ambitious, but also to realise that we need to bring people along with us on this whole journey.  There are many people in society who have been major advocates on climate justice and climate action politics for many years but the vast majority of the public have only got on board with it in the past four, five or six years.  It is the average person on the street who we need to really convince about why we have to do this.  That is exactly the type of person we need to bring along.  We need to be ambitious but it is also very important to be cognisant of that fact.</p> <p>I pay tribute to colleagues on the committee, particularly Senator Higgins, who is an excellent voice and brings a lot of experience, and Senator Pauline O'Reilly.  I commend Deputy Leddin on doing an excellent job of steering such landmark legislation through the Oireachtas in the past 18 months.  I cannot speak for everyone, but I think the committee would be lost without him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RR00300"><p>To clarify for colleagues, it is just party spokespersons who may contribute on this occasion, according to the order of the House agreed earlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#RR00400"><p>To clarify, I am representing Senator Dooley, who is the Fianna F&aacute;il spokesperson and a member of the committee.  Unfortunately, he had other urgent business to attend to, so I am here on his behalf and that of the party.  I thank all those involved on the committee for the tremendous work they did.  I echo the support expressed for the committee Chairman, who did an excellent job of steering the committee.  I am sure it was not always easy.</p> <p>As all present are aware, the science is indisputable.  The effects of climate change are already clear.  We know we have to act.  By acting now, we can build a cleaner and greener economy and society that create opportunities for all.  The Climate Action Plan 2021 provides a detailed plan for taking decisive action to achieve a 51% reduction in overall greenhouse gas emissions by 2030.  That is important.  It is why Fianna F&aacute;il is very supportive of the motion before the House.  Following discussion with my colleague, Senator Dooley, I acknowledge that while there were some differences in opinion among the stakeholder submissions to the committee and, no doubt, among the membership as well regarding the proposed carbon budgets and whether they should be more ambitious, it was certainly made abundantly clear that the committee should approve the budgets without delay in order to move the implementation of policy forward.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is notable that the committee agreed, in spite of some differing opinions, that stakeholders share the one main climate ambition, that is, recognising the need for immediate and significant change to make the transition to a carbon-neutral economy.  I think we all will acknowledge, as the report does, that the task ahead will be extremely challenging and that very difficult decisions will have to be made in the D&aacute;il and in this House.  Given the time lag between policy implementation and emissions reductions, substantial interventions are most definitely needed immediately in all sectors of the economy, with several stakeholders cautioning that 2022 is the second year of the first carbon budget.</p><p>I wish to comment briefly on the need for the Government to prepare measures immediately, which I know that the Minister has been working on, to ensure a just transition in all sectors of society, ensuring that those who have benefited most from and are most responsible for emissions bear the greatest burden.  I speak as somebody from County Kildare, where, particularly in north-west Kildare, many communities have been very dependent on Bord na M&oacute;na, not just for employment; where they can, people still go out and cut turf for their own homes.  They are greatly impacted by the transition.  The communities in the smaller villages of Coill Dubh, Allenwood, Carbury, Derrinturn and Rathangan and of Kilberry and Athy developed from the employment provided by Bord na M&oacute;na.  It is good to see just transition funding going to the Allenwood Community Development Association, ACDAL, in the Michael Fitzpatrick Centre.  It has received sizeable funding to provide a hub for alternative employment.  We are now looking at the Bord na M&oacute;na headquarters in Newbridge.  Circumstances are changing for Bord na M&oacute;na as it diversifies.  It has a sizeable site in the centre of Newbridge.  Councillor Noel Heavey and myself are working on a proposal to try to ensure we have some kind of further education institution there that could do work similar to what An Foras Tal&uacute;ntais did in Lullymore on experimentation and a hub for employment measures, whereby people could start a small enterprise related to agriculture or climate change and could be given opportunities there.  There is no doubt that we have to consider very positive measures like that.  Of course, there will be a lot of emerging technologies and changing scientific consensus all the time.  Because of that, the climate action plan needs to be updated annually.  While we must have the roadmap of actions put in place, they will change as we go forward, learn more and see more developments in technology and research.</p><p>I wish to take this opportunity to endorse the report and to commend all the committee members and the Chairman of the committee on his leadership in bringing forward all these recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#SS00200"><p>There will be a change of Ministers now.  I thank the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, for his engagement, and welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#SS00300"><p>I see that the Minister is staying.  I thank him for doing so.</p> <p>We have all been waiting a long time for the national carbon budgets.  Like everybody else, I am very keen to see them implemented and to see a new, harder, firmer structure to our climate ambition.  We have a duty, however, to make sure we get the budgets right, and we need to be very clear that getting them right does not delay the process.  The process is under way.  We on the climate committee are not tasked with simply approving or disapproving the budgets but with scrutinising them and advising the Minister before the draft carbon budgets are finalised.  Again, improving or changing those budgets does not delay the process.  The Minister mentioned there has been a public consultation, so we are not simply looking back on the carbon budgets.  I am sure he will be back here engaging with us again when he brings his final carbon budgets forward to us.  I hope that when he does so, those budgets will have been improved in a few crucial ways.</p> <p>I hope he will bring forward carbon budgets that will, at a minimum, deliver the 7% average emissions reduction rate per annum promised in the programme for Government.  In fact, I hope he will do better and deliver the 7.6% average emissions cut the UN has said we need.  A 7% cut would mean a cut of 27 Mt in the budgets, and a 7.6% cut would mean a cut of 41 megatonnes.  I sat with the Minister on a previous climate committee where we discussed exactly why those targets really matter and why those levels of cuts matter.  We are talking about real emissions and the very hard target of 1.5&deg;C, which, if we go above it, will tilt our world into unlivability.  I hope the Minister will reflect that in the final budgets.</p> <p>I also hope he will accompany the final budgets with two hard guarantees: first, climate justice and real funding - that is, additional funding - for where we fall short on climate justice, and, second, that there will no accountancy tricks.  I will be frank; I am deeply concerned by suggestions of forward-counting, for example, which would go against the science and the reality and undermine the entire credibility of the carbon budget process if that were to happen.  I say that to give the Minister a few key points to consider.</p> <p>In the report there are many very good recommendations.  I was very happy that my colleagues accepted a number of my recommendations, including on peatlands, as has been mentioned, on a potential limitation on demolition and, crucially, that in the second carbon budget there can be no carryover after 2030 because of that hard target of a 51% reduction in emissions.  We need to publish the roadmap for an exit from the &euro;2.4 billion in fossil fuel subsidies a lot earlier than 2024.  They are important recommendations.  I am concerned, however, that Government members voted against my recommendation that the megatonnage in each carbon budget should relate to removals and omissions measurable within the period of that budget and that no projected emissions reductions or removals that would occur beyond the timeframe of that budget should be included when calculating or assessing the budget.  It is really important that the carbon budgets are the carbon budgets.  We may need incentives in forestry and so on but we cannot play with the facts regarding incentives.  If we start to do that, the credibility of the entire carbon budget process will be undermined.  We, therefore, need a guarantee on that.  The Minister knows there has been kite-flying on forward-counting, and simply saying we will count cuts later does not cut it.  The carbon budgets are real and we need to treat them as such.  They are based on the physical reality of emissions.</p> <p>I come to the reason I, for the first time in six years on five committees, was not able to support this report.  It was because it was not ambitious enough and did not reflect the science and, sadly, did not reflect the scientists in the body of the report.  Some of the scientists who gave us hard, stark, important, challenging, detailed information, such as Professor Kevin Anderson, Professor Barry McMullin and Dr. Andrew Jackson, are listed in the appendices but not included in the body of the report.  We cannot afford to look away or down when we hear important scientific testimony.  As Professor Anderson said, the reason we face challenges with these carbon budgets is that we have had 33 years of not listening to scientific advice.  Some of the most crucial scientific advice we heard came from Professor Barry McMullin, who made it clear that the carbon budgets as currently proposed will amount to a reduction of less than 6% per year.  That was later confirmed by representatives of the Climate Change Advisory Council who told us that the carbon budgets as proposed amount to only a 5.7% reduction per year on average over the ten years to 2030.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->To put that in context, the programme for Government committed to a 7% average reduction in overall greenhouse gases from 2021 to 2030.  Even more important, the UN environmental programme stated we need a global average reduction of 7.6% every year if we want to stay below 1.5&deg;C of heating.  Over 1.5&deg;C of heating, this world becomes unliveable, an actual hell for many across the planet.  As a wealthy country, we should be doing much better than that average of 7.6&deg;C.  How can we conceivably justify the idea that we would be doing less than the average?  Who should take up our slack because we find it so difficult to do these things?  Are we asking countries like Malawi, where emissions for an average person are 100 times less than those of an average person in Ireland, to do more because we do not want to achieve even the average that is needed?</p><p>It is colonialism.  That was put to us as a committee and Ireland needs to reflect on it.  As one of the witnesses put it, we took their people, we took their minerals and now we want to take their carbon budget space.  Our carbon budget is not something that sits within the Irish economy.  It sits within the global carbon budget which sits within a planetary reality of the amount of emissions we can produce.  If we produce more than our share, we are taking from others.  We are directly taking from the poorest and from future generations and the space they need.  We need to be honest about this.  We talk about being real.  That is the hard reality.</p><p>I urge the Minister to strengthen the carbon budgets and let Ireland show leadership.  Professor Barry McMullin said it is no longer enough to do our best; we must do what is necessary.  Sadly, this report does not demand enough.  The carbon budgets as currently proposed do not deliver enough, certainly not for climate justice or for our planetary survival on this very beautiful planet in this opportunity we have right now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1465" speakername="Eamon Ryan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#TT00200"><p>I am glad to follow Senator Higgins.  We have soldiered together on that Oireachtas committee.  She is right.  The analyses of the likes of Barry McMullin, Kevin Anderson and others have been presented and we cannot deny the science.  It is clear and presents a completely scary reality that we are heading towards, seemingly inexorably.  We have known the science since Dr. James Hansen testified before a US Senate committee back in 1988  The science has not changed that much.  We know the risks, downsides and potential disaster that could unfold if we allow our climate that has been balanced and stable for 10,000 years to tip into runaway dangerous climate change.  No one can deny that.  That is the climate science.</p> <p>What we need to work out as well is the political science to raise the level of urgency and response that is commensurate with the climate science.  We have to admit that is difficult.  The House is not full for this debate, for example, with no criticism of anyone.  It is indicative of the need for change.  How do we inspire in people a sense of urgency and a sense we can make the leap?  It is a leap, given the scale of change.  Whether it is 7% or higher, it is a leap.  No one and no country has done anything like it and no example can be shown for that scale or speed of change.  I believe we can and will do it.  There will be various things encouraging us to make the leap.  We need to be honest and upfront with people about the science.  However, if it is just that story, we might get frozen in fear.  A lot of people are frozen in fear.  We need also to inspire people to make the leap out of love of home and love of each other.</p> <p>It is appropriate to point out that making the leap, as well as protecting against the potential for runaway catastrophic climate change, can and will be good for us.  It will be good for social justice; I am convinced of that.  I have seen when campaigning on things like active travel or public transport that it is about recognising it is a more socially just system.  Senator Kyne will know small farmers out in Connemara and those areas.  That is where the money is going to go.  It is going to create an income stream for many of the farmers who get the least out of the existing system.  It will redistribute money to the north and west of the country because that is where we can do some of the nature-based solutions.  We have to do it everywhere but certainly it will help those in parts of the country with poorer land who have been getting the least because by definition they are not as successful in this intensive agricultural system we have created.  It will also be healthier.  There is nothing to beat clean air for people's health.  There is nothing to beat clean water.  We have to address the biodiversity crisis as well as the climate crisis, and that means cleaner water.  It means the farming has to change as we pay them more to help with those solutions.  That is our health in a natural environment, with healthier food.  A low carbon diet is a healthier diet.</p> <p>It is also an economic opportunity for our country.  It is an economic opportunity for every country because the nature of this renewable energy system we are going to switch to is that it is distributed.  It is not as energy dense as oil, gas or nuclear but it is everywhere.  It belongs to everyone.  We will never hold someone to ransom over a solar panel.  For us it is a massive economic opportunity.  We can and will be good at this balancing act of electrifying everything and the dance between variable supply and variable demand.  It is no harm for us to tell that story as well as the scientific story of real fear.</p> <p>We have real potential because in Irish politics we have been working together in those Oireachtas committees and in previous governments.  Deputy Richard Bruton's original plan in 2019 was really good and we are following it, just ramping up the level of ambition.  We have achieved a broad consensus.  That Oireachtas joint committee report in 2018 influenced what Deputy Bruton did in 2019, which in turn has influenced what we are doing now.  Even though the committee may have been divided in terms of whether there needs to be further ambition, I do not think it is fundamentally divided on that sense that there is an opportunity for us to gain by taking this leap together.  The vast majority in the Seanad, D&aacute;il and local authorities throughout the country and the vast majority of the people are starting to believe that in their hearts and in their heads.</p> <p>We are also fortunate to have a very good Climate Change Advisory Council which is really experienced.  It produces the statistics and carries out oversight and reviewing, keeping an eye on Government.  The council members came up with a lot of the proposals in terms of how we account for things.  Professor Peter Thorne, who was formerly adviser to the joint committee, is on the Climate Change Advisory Council.  I would trust Peter when it comes to managing this incredibly complex issue of land use, land use change and forestry, LULUCF, leading into the agriculture, forestry and other land use, AFOLU, accounting regulations.  Peter is as good as it gets.  He was one of the leading authors of the latest IPCC report, as I understand.  That is backed up by those whom we got in from the IPCC to speak to the previous Oireachtas committee.  We follow the science.</p> <p>I will conclude on something from Senator Higgins's home turf.  How do we make that work in Galway, which is in the news at the moment?  I was in County Clare last week and met the council.  It was very interesting.  They are well up for this and open to it.  They know their local area well.  We need that local knowledge.  We cannot push people into this, beat them into it with a stick, shame them into it or make them feel guilty.  It has to come from the local.  As we can see, that is difficult.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Eamon Ryan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2028"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2028&amp;amp;pid=EamonRyanGP&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=02&amp;amp;day=15"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It was not about a lack of money or a lack of ideas in the end, but a fear as to whether this leap could be made.  What we in politics do on this issue now is important.  We need to listen and ask people to help.  We should not necessarily tell them what to do in a top-down way that suggests we know best.  We should inspire people that this can be done.  </p><p>We have a tough budget.  The budgets are real and tight.  They will be harsh because if Ministers are not meeting their budgets, they will have to change their policies.  I hope they will be held to account by Oireachtas committees and the Climate Change Advisory Council.  Reference was made earlier to budgets in respect of the financing aspects earlier but these budgets must be more significant if they are to have meaning, which I believe they will.  We have a strong Act and good constitutional protection and provision to back it up.  We in Irish politics are not the worst in how we are approaching this.  We can learn by doing, by listening to each other and by getting down to delivering.  This Government has three years to go.  It is about delivery, delivery and delivery.  I am looking forward to the meeting of the Cabinet subcommittee on environment and climate change next week.  I will be going with ideas as to how to deliver quickly in the areas of sustainable mobility, offshore wind, retrofitting, just transition, land-use planning and climate communications, which is the most important matter.  Very few emissions will be saved by anything we say here today but, if we do not get the story right and inspire our people to believe that we are going to be good at this, we will not meet our budgets.  However, if we do, we will.  That is why I am keen to work with the Seanad and councils across this country in the coming three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#UU00200"><p>I thank the Minister for that very motivational and inspirational address.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.154" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#UU00400"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022021500002#UU00500"><p>Tomorrow morning at 10.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-02-15a.157" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ag 7.22 p.m. go dt&iacute; 10.30 a.m., D&eacute; C&eacute;adaoin, an 16 Feabhra 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 7.22 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 16 February 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>