<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.1" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.2" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 12:00:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.3" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.4" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.5" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Fiona O'Loughlin that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Defence to provide an update on the implementation of the recommendations of the report of the Commission on the Defence Forces.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Marie Sherlock of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth to make a statement on the potential loss of early childhood care and education, ECCE, places due to the establishment of autism spectrum disorder, ASD, units within primary schools where ECCE providers are also located. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for special education and inclusion to set up a scheme to allow school principals apply to upgrade their special educational needs classrooms. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Malcolm Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Justice to make a statement on her Department&rsquo;s role in determining criteria for health insurance for international students. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Fitzpatrick of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Finance to make a statement on plans to introduce a vacant property tax in budget 2023. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aisling Dolan of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for heritage and electoral reform to provide an update on the conservation status of 45 special areas of conservation turloughs, in particular, the restoration of habitats and protection of wildlife in the Lough Funshinagh area. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Social Protection to make a statement on the current youth unemployment rate and steps being taken to help young people into the workforce. </blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Sharon Keogan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for planning and local government to make a statement on the allocation of funding for the provision of a dedicated EU affairs officer and a strategic policy committee in each local authority area. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the roll-out of eight 24-hour bus routes in Dublin, as recommended by the night-time economy task force. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and Marine to make a statement on plans to review the aquaculture licence application process to improve processing timeframes. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Emer Currie of the following matter:</p><blockquote>	The need for the Minister for Education to make a statement on the DEIS status of St. Luke&rsquo;s National School, Tyrrelstown, Dublin 15. </blockquote><p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected the matters of Senators O&rsquo;Loughlin, Sherlock, Ahearn, Malcolm Byrne, Fitzpatrick and Dolan, and they will be taken now.  I regret I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Warfield on the ground that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.8" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#B00125">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.9" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#B00150">Defence Forces</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#B00175"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Smyth, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#B00200"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for choosing this important subject as one of today's Commencement matters.  I also welcome the young people who are coming into the Gallery.  It is always good to have the opportunity to see young people coming into the Chamber, listening and engaging with our process.  I also thank the Minister of State for being here.</p> <p>This issue I wish to raise relates to the Defence Forces and the Commission on the Defence Forces, which is important not just to me but also to the defence community in south Kildare and throughout the country.  As the Minister of State will be aware, the Curragh Camp is the main training centre and more than 2,000 personnel are based there.  There are many military families in County Kildare, and many retired personnel have made their homes there.  I am only too acutely aware of the difficulties that exist for people who are serving in the Defence Forces.</p> <p>I note there was a recruitment and rebrand launch in early June 2022 to communicate that a career in the Defence Forces will give a person skills for life.  That campaign was run to inspire and motivate potential soldiers.  I have no doubt a career in the Defence Forces would give a person skills for life.  However, it is premature to say we want to inspire and motivate potential recruits while we are still in pure limbo in the context of the commission.</p> <p>When the Commission on the Defence Forces report was published in February, I stood where I am now and said it must be a turning point for the defence community in my area of south Kildare and throughout the country.  The days of reports and talking about reports must come to an end.  We need to come to the next phase if we are to revitalise our Defence Forces and if we are serious about both retaining and attracting people into our Defence Forces.  That is important and I stand by the remarks I made.</p> <p>I must say I was incredibly concerned last week when I heard there are already potential delays just five months after the commission's report was published.  We were given an absolute commitment that, within six months, the Minister for Defence would come back with costed recommendations and, more importantly, an action plan.  The action plan on the implementation of the recommendations was due to be brought before Cabinet at the start of the month.  However, that has now been thrown into doubt amid media reports of internal friction on the issue of costs.</p> <p>The sticking point that has always held back our Defence Forces is a lack of money.  Our Defence Forces, as the Minister of State knows well, go over and above in the service of this State.  They work for low pay and in poor conditions, and battle every day to carry out their duties on a shoestring budget.  That is something to which they have become accustomed.  We owe them more than that.  We owe them respect, honesty, investment and appreciation.  That is what I hope the Commission on the Defence Forces delivers.  It must deliver change, respect and transformation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Prior to Covid I had a number of public meetings with personnel from the Defence Forces.  I can honestly say they love their job and serving their country but we hear more than 20% of them have to rely on family income support to be able to meet their bills.  I met a young family where the dad has had to serve four overseas missions back to back to help pay the rent and has no chance of being able to buy a house.  </p><p>I appreciate the Minister of State, Deputy Smyth, is representing the Minister, Deputy Coveney.  Can he confirm a memorandum will be brought to Cabinet in advance of the summer recess and that the action plan will be brought forward to deliver on the ambition of the commission's report?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  The Minister for Defence welcomed the publication of the report of the Commission on the Defence Forces in February of this year.  The establishment of a commission on the Defence Forces was set out in the programme for Government and was a key priority for the Minister, Deputy Coveney.  The members of the commission were drawn from a wide range of national and international experts.  The publication of the report represents the culmination of 13 months of work and is testament to the considerable efforts of all those who contributed to it.</p><p>The report is wide-ranging and comprehensive.  It contains 69 recommendations and together with sub-recommendations, there are 130 recommendations in total.  The report proposes significant changes for the Defence Forces, including significant cultural changes and changes to human resources, HR, practices.  It also includes proposals on high-level command and control structures and for the level of defence provision in Ireland.  It challenges the <i>status quo</i>across a range of areas and is forthright about a requirement for cultural changes in the Defence Forces.  It proposes a range of measures to make the Defence Forces a more inclusive, diverse, equal and attractive workplace.  The importance of the Reserve Defence Force is clearly stated, as is the immediate action required there.</p><p>The report poses serious questions regarding defence provision that we, as a society, must carefully consider.  This includes the types of defence capabilities we should retain and the level of resourcing we are willing to commit to equip and train our Defence Forces for the roles we require them to undertake.  The Minister hopes this report will provide the platform for real debate about the defence we need as a modern neutral European country.</p><p>The report sets out three indicative levels of ambition, or LOAs, namely, LOA 1, LOA 2 and LOA 3.  LOA 1 would encompass current capability, LOA 2 would enhance our current capabilities and seek to address specific priority areas and LOA 3 would look to develop full spectrum defence capabilities to protect Ireland and its people to an extent comparable with similar-sized countries in Europe.  The commission recommends a step up to LOA 2 in the short term, pending more detailed policy debate and decision required for higher levels of ambition.  This step up to LOA 2 would require an additional &euro;500 million per annum.  LOA 3 would require expenditure of &euro;3 billion per annum.</p><p>Clearly, there are matters that require careful consideration and, in some critical aspects, interdepartmental discussion and agreement.  This includes the level of resourcing that may be allocated to defence and the governance framework that will be required to underpin the changes the commission has recommended.</p><p>Since the report was published the Minister for Defence has engaged in extensive consultation with ministerial colleagues and a range of other stakeholders, including the representative associations.  This is a complex and technical piece of work on which the Department of Defence and the Defence Forces have been collaborating with a range of stakeholders, including other Departments.  This has included detailed and very constructive discussions with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  The Minister for Defence will shortly revert to Government with a proposed response to the commission's recommendations and a high-level action plan.  The implementation process will follow Cabinet agreement on the recommendations to Government.</p><p>There is significant work ongoing in the Department of Defence and Defence Forces, which the commission referred to in its report.  This includes key issues such as the development of a capability development planning process, the work of the independent review into dignity and equality issues in the Defence Forces, ongoing procurement of equipment and infrastructure, direct entry competitions and the amendment of legislation relating to the working time directive.</p><p>I thank the Deputy for the opportunity to appear and for her interest in such an important matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#C00300"><p>I acknowledge that the report of the Commission on the Defence Forces is a substantial one, running to 224 pages and containing 69 recommendations.  It is a colossal piece of work.  I appreciate the complexity and the technical nature of devising an action plan to implement these findings.  However, we cannot fall at the first hurdle.  There must be a time-bound element to it.</p> <p>The report calls for a major investment in the three arms of the Defence Forces, the Air Corps, Naval Service and Army.  We must deliver the funding required for the people serving our country in order for them to be able to live a decent life and have a decent lifestyle for themselves and their families.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have no doubt there is a time element but the Oireachtas and the Cabinet, as bodies, have a responsibility to play a part in advancing the agenda.  The request is very clear from the perspective of the Commission on the Defence Forces and Defence Forces personnel.  They want a well-funded multi-annual plan that will transform the operations of our Defence Forces, as well as providing a viable and sustainable career path for Defence Forces personnel.  I have no doubt in the Department's ability to deliver that but must be prioritised.</p><p>The Minister of State indicated in his response to me that the Minister for Defence will respond shortly.  Will the Minister of State absolutely guarantee this will be done before the summer recess because that is what is required?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#D00200"><p>The first question is whether the Minister for Defence will come back on this before the summer recess.  The Minister, Deputy Coveney, has said he will shortly revert to the Government and I cannot go beyond that.  That is his guarantee.  He has said he will respond to the report but he will also bring an action plan to the Government.  That deals with the Senator's other question.</p> <p>The Senator mentioned that the Army, the Naval Service and the Air Corps are the three branches of the Defence Forces but we must also think about cyber defences, which will also need attention.  That is referenced in the report.</p> <p>The budget is coming up and, as the Senator knows, the summer economic statement was published yesterday, although that does not provide any detail about the different Departments and who is getting what.  The Department of Defence is liaising with my Department of Public Expenditure and Reform to work out what level of funding is required for this year's budget.  I cannot say any more than that.  I am here on behalf of the Minister and that is all the information I can give the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#D00300"><p>I have just read through the notes and there is mention that it will happen before the summer recess.  That is in the statement that was circulated.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.18" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#D00400">Early Childhood Care and Education</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#D00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Anne Rabbitte, to the Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#D00600"><p>I warmly welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, to the House and thank her for taking the time to be here today.  I had hoped the Minister for Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth would have been here but I understand there are other commitments.  I acknowledge efforts he made in response to matters we raised with him last year.  I want to be fair to him about those efforts with the national childcare scheme and in particular the eligibility for after-school hours.</p> <p>Today's question relates to the alarming loss of early childhood care and education, ECCE, places this September.  In one area in Stoneybatter, an urban village in Dublin 7, there will be a loss of 55 ECCE places this September.  This is across two services, the Donard/Glen community play group and Creative Kids &amp;amp; Co.  It is an enormous loss to any community, particularly when we know there is massive demand for ECCE places right across the country and in Dublin at this point.</p> <p>Both closures relate to changes happening within the primary schools in which they are located, and these are good changes.  That is to be welcomed.  It is important to say we accept that those who run preschools located in primary schools know there is uncertainty hanging over them every year.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The licence is renewed every September on a ten-month basis.  Nonetheless there are very serious questions now about forward planning and co-ordination between the Department of Education and the Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth when changes are made with regard to school buildings.</p><p>To be frank, the Department of Education has made decisions on ASD units without really looking at what is happening within those school buildings.  We have to ask if the Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth is going to stand by and see the loss of 55 ECCE places within one very small area of Dublin.  I have no doubt that is replicated right across the country.  Creative Kids &amp;amp; Co. was informed at the start of the year that it would potentially not have its licence renewed.  It started the search process then.  The person who runs that service runs two others so she knows what she is doing.  She cannot find anywhere for love nor money in terms of trying to locate her ECCE service in another part of Dublin 7.  Cost does not even come into it.  It is about finding an appropriate place.  Because we rightfully have these services so highly regulated, it makes it all the harder to find an appropriate location.  There is an onus and responsibility on the Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth to ensure that appropriate locations are made available.</p><p>The Donard community play group was told that its licence would end in December 2022 and it would be extended on a monthly rolling basis.  Because of changes by the Department of Education the group was told only last week that it will have nowhere as of this September.  The heartbreaking thing about this is that there are a number of kids in both services who have additional needs.  The irony for these children, who were due to go into their second year of ECCE, is that when they get to primary school in September 2023 they will have fantastic services in place but they will have nothing in the 12 months between September 2022 and September 2023.  Weeks and months matter in children's lives, particularly those children who have additional needs.  There are serious questions here for the Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth about what it is going to do to put in place secure, sustainable locations for ECCE schemes that effectively have to close overnight.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#E00200"><p>I want to begin by apologising on behalf of the Minister, Deputy O'Gorman, who would have liked to have been here but he is delayed.  I am going to read his script but I have taken a note of what the Senator mentioned in respect of Donard community play group and Creative Kids &amp;amp; Co.</p> <p>I thank Senator Sherlock for raising this issue and for offering the opportunity to respond.  I regret to hear that early learning and childcare services are being displaced from school premises although I can appreciate the position of the schools in needing to prioritise the establishment of early intervention classes.  The Department of Education guidelines on the use of school buildings outside of school hours guides schools in the use of school facilities for other services, including early learning and childcare services.  The guidelines are clear that the issue is a matter for the property owners, taking into consideration the needs of the school staff and students.  The guidelines also require that any licence should include a term that the use of the facility or portion of the site covered by the licence must cease should it be required for school provision.</p> <p>Government is aware of the challenges that can face an early learning and childcare service if it unexpectedly loses its premises.  The Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth has an effective process in place to support providers in such circumstances.  The Department provides the majority of funding to the early learning and childcare sector, primarily to the ECCE programme and the national childcare scheme and, from September, through a core funding scheme.  However, it does not directly operate or manage early learning or childcare services.</p> <p>These services are provided as for-profit or non-profit services and are either privately owned or operated by community organisations.  While decisions about the day-to-day running of such services, including choice of location, any contracts or leases for premises and any decision to close is ultimately a matter for the provider, the Department can provide support in a number of ways to services that face losing their premises.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Anne Rabbitte:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2436"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2436&amp;amp;pid=AnneRabbitte&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Support to find alternative accommodation is available to all services, both private and community, from the local city and county childcare committee, CCC.  The CCCs have engaged with services that were losing their premises and have provided assistance to identify alternative premises.  The local CCC should be the first point of contact for any service seeking support.</p><p>Parents whose children are attending a service that may be due to close can contact their CCC for assistance in locating an alternative early learning and childcare place for their child.  A recent survey of early learning and childcare services showed significant unused capacity for early childhood care and education, ECCE, places.  CCCs can share this information with parents.</p><p>The Department oversees a case management process through its city and childcare committees and Pobal, which work together to provide support to early learning and childcare services experiencing difficulties.  Case management assistance can include specialist advice and support appropriate to individual circumstances.  Financial support may also be accessed through the case management process following a financial assessment.  This support is currently available to community services to assist with operational costs associated with a sudden need to move premises.</p><p>From autumn, a new strand of the sustainability fund connected with core funding will operate.  It will be open to both private and community providers that are in contract for core funding.  As with previous strands of the sustainability fund, it will focus on operational and financial supports to assist services manage their immediate difficulties and transition to sustainability.  Any early learning and childcare services that are at risk of losing their premises in a school or elsewhere are encouraged to contact the local city or county childcare committee as soon as possible.</p><p>I know what I have just said is of little comfort to the Senator because, at the end of the day, there are 55 spaces in a particular area that will not be available on 1 September unless the service finds a premises.  It is incumbent on the city and county childcare committee to assist both providers to find alternative accommodation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#F00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for reading that reply.  The statement of the Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth that it has an effective process in place to support providers is simply not true.  To say that the buck should be passed to the city and county childcare committees is simply unacceptable.  The question here is not about the day-to-day costs; it is about undertaking a lease in a new facility.  The providers to which I refer, one of which is a community provider, do not have a hope of finding an alternative location.  I would say to the Department there is a real issue here because we are depending on people setting up a preschool out of the goodness of their hearts, either as a community facility or a for-profit facility.  If there is an issue with the lease, that service disappears overnight.  That is not good enough in 21st century Ireland.  I know the Minister of State will relay that message back to the Department.  The detail we have here is not good enough in terms of ensuring we have secure and sustainable locations for preschool education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#F00300"><p>I appreciate the pressing need for schools to ensure there is sufficient accommodation for children with additional needs.  I also appreciate the importance of early intervention.  Indeed, substantial and significant developments have been made in the early learning and childcare sector to ensure children with additional needs have full access to the ECCE programme through the access and inclusion model, AIM.  The Senator has unearthed a serious issue that requires the Department of Education and the Department of Children, Equality, Disability, Integration and Youth to sit down in conjunction with the city and county childcare committees to identify alternative locations to support both providers, be they private or community.  Those families need that support and the reassurance the service will be available in their area in September.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.26" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#G00050">Special Educational Needs</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#G00100"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the Chamber today and in particular for all the work she is doing and the commitment she has made in the past two years in regard to special education and inclusion.  It is hugely significant.  The impact is evident from the numbers of people working in the sector such as special needs assistants, SNAs, and the number of new classrooms being opened.  Another 315 new classrooms are being opened in September.  The impact of that in recent years is visible in any school or constituency in the country.  The Department of Education is spending &euro;2 billion on special education, which is more than at any time in the past.  That is significant and represents about one quarter of the total budget of the Department.</p> <p>Every couple of weeks, we see new school buildings or extensions being built in County Tipperary.  A large new school has just been built and opened in Cahir in the past two weeks.  In recent year, the Government has provided massive financial support for upgrading and extending school buildings and for new schools.  Part of this has been for classrooms for special needs education, which is a requirement for all new buildings and extensions.  This is really important.  I see the need for those classrooms in Tipperary.  When new classrooms are opened there is an influx of people who want to use them, and a waiting list as well.  The demand is there.</p> <p>In my parish of Ardfinnan I have spoken to the principal of the national school, Ms Br&iacute;d Quinlivan, a number of times.  The school has had an occupational therapy room for more than ten years and it now needs upgrading, improvement and extra equipment.  As Members know, all schools can apply under different schemes for funding for extra equipment and upgrading schools.  However, due to the number of special educational classrooms and occupational therapy rooms in schools, it would be beneficial for the Department to provide for these rooms and classrooms separately in schemes.  Ardfinnan National School was one of the first national schools to open an occupational therapy room.  It accommodates about 32 pupils, which is about 10% of the total.  The Department should have a scheme focused on upgrading facilities and equipment in special educational classrooms and occupational therapy rooms, rather than addressing this as part of a general scheme for upgrading classrooms.  It would place a priority on principals and schools to identify the need to do this.  The Department and the Minister of State have viewed this issue as a priority in the past two years.  We support schools always, and the Minister of State in particular has done so in the past two years.  However, a focused scheme would make it simpler for principals to identify what they can do in terms of upgrading and facilitating special education classrooms.  As well as the principal, I spoke to a teacher in Ardfinnan National School, Monica Griffin.  They are both very passionate about the work they do.  All they want is the best for the kids who are with them every day.  They love their jobs but it is about having the best equipment possible to serve the children in the school.  I thank the Minister of State for coming in and for the support she has given this sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#G00200"><p>I thank Senator Ahearn for raising this matter.  My role as Minister of State with responsibility for special education and inclusion is to make sure we have sufficient special school places and, specifically pertinent to the Senator's question, to have special classes throughout the country and sufficient places for children with additional needs.  There is no point having these classrooms unless they are properly kitted out and properly resourced and funded.  That also applies to ancillary special education rooms such as occupational therapy rooms which the Senator mentioned.  I am open to looking at a scheme to upgrade occupational therapy rooms.  The Department tries to fast-track applications from schools that relate to trying to reconfigure existing accommodation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Josepha Madigan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2424"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2424&amp;amp;pid=JosephaMadigan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A minor works grant is available.  It is &euro;5,500, plus &euro;18 per mainstream student and &euro;74 per student per special class.  That might be of assistance.</p><p>Once the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, sanctions a class, a school can apply to the Department for capital funding to reconfigure its existing spaces.  The Senator will also be aware of the additional accommodation scheme to construct additional accommodation where it is needed.  Interim accommodation can also be provided if no space is available pending the delivery of a new building.  The Department works closely with schools, as I said, to fast-track any applications in this regard, although this involves a workload for staff.  The Department funds external stakeholders engaged in the devolved delivery of building projects for individual schools.  I am sure the same also applies in respect of rooms.  </p><p>Senator Ahearn also mentioned equipment.  His question was not specifically on this topic but it is important that he is aware of the grants available for special classes.  There is a start-up grant of &euro;6,500, an ICT grant of &euro;6,700, a grant for a sensory room of &euro;7,000 and a furniture grant of &euro;2,500.  Additionally, if special equipment is recommended by an occupational therapist, such as specialist chairs, tables, desks, changing benches or tables, hoists, etc., the NCSE and the Department can sanction grants for all those items.</p><p>Our school building programme has many different projects under way.  Overall, some 1,300 school building projects are at various stages of design and planning and we are ramping up our efforts to provide additional places for children with special educational needs.  When there are rooms, as I said, it is important that they can be reconfigured, reconstructed or re-equipped if necessary for the purposes that may be required in this context, particularly for the work of occupational therapists and speech and language therapists.  If we are to move towards the school inclusion model in the future, we will need more capacity for occupational therapists, speech and language therapists and other therapists to provide their services to these children who require them so badly.  Therefore, what the Senator is saying has merit and I am certainly open to exploring a separate scheme, perhaps, for therapy rooms, as distinct from special educational classrooms.  I thank the Senator for raising this issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response and I am grateful that she will examine this issue.  The problem will become more serious as time passes because of the amount of money the Minister of State has allocated to special classrooms and occupational therapy classrooms.  If the Minister of State were open to this suggestion, it would be important for her to visit Ardfinnan National School.  She has family connections in Kilcash.  In her role as the Minister of State with special responsibility for special education and inclusion, it would be well worthwhile for her to visit Tipperary.  I will bring her to Ardfinnan National School.  She has already met one of the school's students, Cara Darmody.  We have more than 300 other fantastic students who would also be grateful to meet the Minister of State and show her the facilities.  It is a great school and is led by a fantastic principal, Ms Br&iacute;d Quinlivan.  It would be a good opportunity to see where other schools will be in a few years' time if we do not put something in place to support them now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#H00300"><p>The Minister of State and I must have a chat about Kilcash sometime because my grandparents were from there.  They were the principals of the boys and girls national schools, respectively.  What is now the community centre in Kilcash was then their home.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#H00400"><p>Senator Ahearn will need a bus to bring all the people to visit the school.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#H00500"><p>My mother was from Clonmel in County Tipperary.  I am delighted to accept Senator Ahearn's invitation to come down to Tipperary and particularly to visit Ardfinnan National School.  I have met the wonderful Cara Doherty.  I am sure she did incredibly well in her junior certificate mathematics examinations.  The school is to be commended.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Josepha Madigan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2424"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2424&amp;amp;pid=JosephaMadigan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It sounds like a role model in that regard.  I would be absolutely delighted to come down, see the room and perhaps discuss how we can assist the school into the future, and any other schools in the environs as well.  It is always very helpful to me to visit not just mainstream schools, but also schools with special classes and special schools, of course, as well, to get that feedback and listen to what the people have to say.  The people on the ground everyday working with children with additional needs know what is required to sort of make sure the students have as independent a life as they possibly can into the future.  They need the wraparound supports in order to do that.  </p><p>The school inclusion model trialled in February 2019 was interrupted because of Covid.  It is back now on a trial under community healthcare organisation, CHO, 7.  I hope it is something we can bring forward in the future, which will assist Ardfinnan National School also.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.35" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#J00150">International Students</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#J00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth, back to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#J00300"><p>The Minister of State may not be aware of the full history of this particular issue, but it is a problem for international students coming to Ireland and a requirement by the Department of Justice that they must have health insurance.  This has been a long-running sore and to say it has been a difficulty is an understatement.</p> <p>I raised the matter not long after my election to this House and subsequently raised it with the Ministers, Deputies Harris and Stephen Donnelly, including in this House on 24 September 2020 when the Minister, Deputy Harris, assured me that there would be progress on the issue.</p> <p>On 5 March 2021, I introduced the Health Insurance (International Students) Amendment Bill with the specific purpose of trying to address this problem for our international students coming here.  On the basis that there was a Government commitment that it would be addressed, I chose not to seek to amend the Health Insurance (Amendment) Act that December, because the Minister of State, Deputy Butler, told me that this issue would be resolved in a matter of months.  Indeed, I tabled this as a Commencement matter with the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, on 9 December 2021.  He assured me that it was not a policy matter for the Department of Health, but that this would be resolved, hopefully, within the following two months.</p> <p>On Wednesday, 22 June, the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, was back answering this very same Commencement matter.  I had tabled it at the time to the Department of Justice, which kicked it over to the Department of Health.  I appreciate it is not specifically the remit of the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth, but this is why the question is tabled to the Department of Justice.</p> <p>I have quickly determined that the worst phrase one can hear in these Houses is that a matter falls between a number of Departments.  However, what is very clear from the responses that I received from the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science and the Department of Health, including from the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, just two weeks ago, is that this is now strictly within the remit of the Department of Justice.</p> <p>Even though there are negotiations going on within the Departments, the other Departments said this is a matter for the Department of Justice to make a determination on.  I am hoping that finally, after more than two years of raising this, and particularly where concerns have been expressed by the universities, the institutes of higher education, the Irish Council for Overseas Students, the Alliance for Insurance Reform, the Union of Students in Ireland &ndash; a whole range of players &ndash; but more particularly, the concern that this is for international students and international students who want to come here, that we can finally have an effective system that can be put in place that will allow them to have access to affordable insurance.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Malcolm Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=1111"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1111&amp;amp;pid=MalcolmByrne&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I get that there are broader implications.  For the most part, we are talking about students who are healthy and who are only going to be here for a specified period.  However, if we are not clarifying this, it is a significant problem in respect of our wish to attract international students into Ireland.  I hope that, today, the Minister of State will finally be able to give us some progress on it, particularly as the various Departments have all been promising that a resolution is imminent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#K00200"><p>I am here on behalf of the Minister for Justice, Deputy Helen McEntee, and her Department.  I thank the Senator for raising this important matter.  The Minister is aware that this is an issue on which he is engaged.  She, too, is keen to see a resolution to the matter as soon as possible.</p> <p>By way of background, the Senator will be aware that many immigration permissions include the condition that the permission holder must have private health insurance; this does not just apply to international students.  The rationale for this is that the permission holder must be able to support themselves while living in the State without recourse to State services such as public healthcare. </p> <p>A 2018 Court of Appeal judgment found that students who are here for a course of study for more than one year are deemed to be ordinarily resident for the purposes of health insurance legislation, meaning that, if required to have private health insurance, that insurance must meet the conditions that apply to private health insurance generally.  This means that health insurance policies sold internationally to international students would need to be community rated, provide minimum cover and comply with other requirements set out under law, potentially resulting in a higher cost to the student.</p> <p>Ireland benefits from its international student population and our policy, led by the Department of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, is to encourage more international students to come to study in the State.  We do not want to create impediments to this but we must also be cautious that any policy changes implemented do not have unintended consequences with implications for the delivery of State services.  That is why the Department of Justice has been working closely with the Departments of Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science, and Health to examine the implications of this ruling and to put in place an appropriate solution.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, students already have travel insurance that covers their medical needs for their first year in the State.  Discussions are, therefore, ongoing between the three Departments as to whether it would be appropriate to drop the requirement for health insurance under the student scheme, starting from year two.  The removal of this requirement could impact public health services and, therefore, the views of the Department of Health are crucial to guiding any decision in this regard.  The Minister, Deputy McEntee's office has been engaging directly with the Minister, Deputy Donnelly's office and, as I said at the outset, she is keen to see a resolution to this issue as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#K00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I am afraid my response is to tell us something that we do not know.  The difficulty, as he rightly outlined, is that this has been an issue since the 2018 Court of Appeal judgment.  Discussions have been ongoing since that time between the Departments so I do not accept there is any urgency among them about trying to resolve this.  The issue had always been around those students who were studying in the State for more than one year.  It would surely be reasonably easy for the Department of Health to quantify how many &ldquo;students&rdquo; potentially impose a burden on our health service of those who are spending more than one year studying here.  On the assumption that a significant number of them are younger, they are likely to be healthier and the number is probably fairly small but, in any event, one would imagine that in a four-year period that could have been quantified.  I appreciate the Minister of State is only delivering the response but I really do not believe that, after four years some sort of innovative solution could not be found to address what is a relatively simple matter,.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#K00400"><p>On the question of quantification, I believe 30,000 international students would be affected by this, so that is the number being looked at.  There is a concern in the Department of Health that this could lead to calls from other groups for similar arrangements on the basis of fairness and, therefore, it would go beyond students and other people on international visas would request the same treatment, which could lead to a higher cost or higher burden on the State through the Department.</p> <p>The Minister for Justice said it is clear that the insurance policy that was previously available to students in the State is no longer available for them to purchase as it does not comply with relevant legislation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->To avoid a problem for the students and the colleges they attend, the Ministers are committed to addressing the issue at the earliest opportunity they can.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.43" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#L00150">Tax Code</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#L00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending the House to respond my Commencement matter calling for a vacant property tax.  No more than anybody else I do not like taxes.  We must accept, as everybody does, the housing emergency gripping our State.  The Government has provided unprecedented funding and made changes to housing policy since taking office.  A glaringly obvious waste of built properties is documented in the recent Central Statistic Office census.  Anybody would objectively say it is morally wrong to see such vacancy when there is such enormous housing need.</p> <p>We recognise that more than 10,000 people are homeless.  More than 38,000 Ukrainians have arrived in our country since the start of the war and more than 6,000 people are living in direct provision.  None of these numbers capture the tens of thousands of people who want to buy their own homes or are stuck in inadequate accommodation.  I commend the Minister of State and the Government on the &euro;20 billion commitment they have made under Housing for All to deliver 300,000 homes.  I also commend the changes they have made to use State-owned land to deliver social and affordable homes and empower local authorities and housing charities to do this.  The Government has committed to ending direct provision.  It has banned co-living.  It has returned power to local authorities so they can reserve new developments for home owner-occupiers.  It has reinstated Part V to ensure a minimum of 10% social housing and a minimum of 10% affordable housing, with a total of 20% in every new private development.</p> <p>All of this is very welcome, as is protection for renters through capping rents and increasing the notice periods, but we are treading water.  It is like we are on a sinking ship bailing out the water as it is coming in when we look at all of the vacancy.  The CSO numbers state more than 160,000 properties are vacant nationally.  There are more than 30,000 of them in Dublin alone.  Every vacant property has its own complex issues and mini-drama as to who owns it and the circumstances of ownership.  Housing for All includes many financial supports under the lease and repair, buy and renew and living city schemes.  There are also other supports to help property owners to restore them.  We are doing this because the fastest and most sustainable way to increase our housing stock is to reuse the buildings already on roads with public lighting, sewerage and public transport and that are near schools.  Not only would this increase housing stock and affordability, it would reinvigorate and regenerate communities.</p> <p>I asked the Minister for Finance to come to the House because I have raised this issue in the House and at the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage.  The committee produced a report that calls for a vacant property tax.  The reason it specifically did so is taxes are in place.  A debate goes on about dereliction and vacancy.  Under either of the two charges, the State is failing miserably.  Under the derelict sites tax, &euro;300,000 was collected.  It sounds like a lot of money.  Guess how much should have been collected?  It was &euro;5 million in 2020 alone.  There is another local authority tax for vacancy.  In 2020, local authorities collected &euro;21,000 out of a target of &euro;21 million.  That is less than 1%.  The levies are not being collected.  They are not effective.  They are not tackling the vacancy.  It is morally, economically, environmentally and socially wrong for vacancy to be allowed to persist at a time of such huge housing emergency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#M00100"><p>I thank the Senator.</p> <p>Addressing vacancy and dereliction, and maximising the use of the existing housing stock, is a priority objective of the Government.  Housing For All outlines a suite of measures aimed at addressing vacancy in a co-ordinated and robust manner, and specifically includes an action for the Department of Finance to collect data on vacancy with a view to introducing a vacant property tax.</p> <p>In considering the case for such a tax, it is important to have a sound understanding of the quantity, locations and characteristics of long-term vacant properties.  It is also essential to identify the reasons for vacancy, and whether these are long or short-term in nature.  There may be genuine and acceptable reasons for vacancy such as refurbishment work, the temporary absence of the owner for medical reasons or pending the grant of probate for a deceased person's estate.</p> <p>The Finance (Local Property Tax) (Amendment) Act 2021 enabled Revenue to collect certain information on the occupancy status of residential properties in the local property tax, LPT, return forms submitted by residential property owners in respect of the new LPT valuation period, 2022-2025.</p> <p>Regarding vacant properties, the LPT returns requested information such as whether a property is vacant, the reasons for the vacancy, and whether the period of vacancy is 12 months or more.  The return data provide a snapshot of vacant properties in Ireland as at the valuation date of 1 November 2021.</p> <p>Revenue has completed a preliminary analysis of the LPT returns received to date which has been shared with the Department of Finance.  The results of the preliminary analysis suggest that levels of vacancy are low across all counties.</p> <p>The Revenue analysis provides a basis for the Department of Finance to assess the merits and impact of introducing a vacant property tax, and how best such a tax might be designed.  This work is under way.</p> <p>I will comment briefly on the recent publication of preliminary census data.  According to the preliminary figures released two weeks ago, 166,752 vacant dwellings were recorded giving a rate of 7.8%.  This is a decrease compared to 2016.  It is an even further decrease - a reduction of 12% - compared to 2011, when 230,056 vacant dwellings were recorded.</p> <p>It is important to note that the CSO highlights that this is a point in time measure of vacancy relating to the weeks either side of census night.  The figures are not intended to be a measure of long-term vacancy, and do not suggest these properties are available for reuse.  These homes may well have been occupied again a few weeks after census night.</p> <p>Indeed, on the figures for Dublin mentioned by the Senator, it is relevant that of that vacancy figure of 30,000, 4,000 properties were up for sale, 5,000 were being renovated, 3,000 were vacant because the resident was in hospital or care, a further 3,000 were vacant because the resident was recently deceased, and, finally, 1,000 were new builds awaiting their first occupation.</p> <p>The Minister for Finance is considering this issue in consultation with colleagues before reverting to Government with proposals on the appropriate response.  I understand Revenue intends to publish a profile of the occupancy data from the LPT returns shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#M00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the response.</p> <p>We all believe in reasonableness and fairness and we can all accept that properties can be from time to time vacant.  Nobody has any argument with that.  In fact, the joint Oireachtas committee states that reasonableness must be applied.</p> <p>I welcome the fact that the Department has made progress with the report and on its summary.  I urge it to publish that report without any further delay.</p> <p>I take the point about the 30,000 properties in Dublin.  What they are saying essentially is that there are explanations for 16,000 of the 30,000.  That is fine, but that means there are 14,000 without explanation that could house 30,000, 40,000 or 50,000 people.  We are in an emergency and it is incumbent on the Department to publish the report as soon as possible and to bring forward recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#M00300"><p>I thank the Senator.</p> <p>The report will be published as soon as possible.  She has a point that there are still a significant number of vacant properties in Dublin and that the Department is doing the groundwork for introducing a vacant property tax.</p> <p>With regard to dereliction, I am advised that the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage continues to liaise with local authorities on the implementation of the Derelict Sites Act 1990 with a view to improving its effectiveness.  The Department initiated a review of the Act in November 2021 to identify potential improvements with local authorities and it will engage with local authorities on this matter during the year.</p> <p>Regarding a tax on vacant residential property, the Minister for Finance is considering this issue in consultation with colleagues and will revert to Government with proposals on the appropriate response.  The Minister for Finance will take the points that were raised by the Senator today on board when considering the matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.48" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#N00100">Special Areas of Conservation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#N00200"><p>This Commencement matter was intended for the Minister of State with responsibility for heritage and electoral reform, Deputy Noonan.  I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth, for being here.  I ask him to provide an update from the National Parks and Wildlife Service, NPWS, on the conservation status of 45 special areas of conservation, SAC, Irish turloughs and objectives to restore habitats and protect the local community in the Lough Funshinagh area.</p> <p>There were hundreds of people at a public meeting in Lecarrow, County Roscommon, last night.  They were there to talk about the severe flooding and loss of homes, farms and access at Lough Funshinagh.  There were families young and old, farmers and residents of Ballagh, Rahara, Lisfelim and Ardmullen.  They came out to support action and to find solutions and a way forward.  I thank the organisers for bringing people and public representatives together and giving a presentation on events since 2016.</p> <p>Lough Funshinagh, the lake of the ash tree, is classified as a turlough and designated a SAC.  However, it has not drained in 26 years, with the last time it did being in 1996.  In 1997, it was designated a SAC.  It is an area of beauty but is now one of devastation too.  In 2016, the lake doubled its surface area.  It forced families from homes.  Acres of farmland were lost.  This disappearing lake does not disappear.  Instead the waters rise year on year.  People are in distress.  There is pure mental anguish and people just wait to see when the next flood will be.</p> <p>The impact on wildlife and vegetation is clear for all to see, with trees standing as white sculptures within the lake.  They have no leaves and are all dead and rotting away.  High floods and waves from the lake in the wintertime wash away the vegetation and all the soil to leave only stones.  Land is crumbling away and the SAC itself has been listed with the poor condition status.  An urgent engineering solution by Roscommon County Council and the Office of Public Works, OPW, was halted in the courts and yes, environmental assessments are required.</p> <p>I understand a turlough, listed as code 3180, is an annex I habitat and there are 75 designated turloughs in the Natura 2000 network.  Most, if not all of them are in the west, across Roscommon, Galway, Mayo and Clare.  I understand the west of Ireland contains close to all of the Irish SACs, that is 45, or 60%, of all listed turloughs, according to the Natura 2000 network.  Therefore, Ireland can, as a member state, take a lead in how we manage and bring our turloughs back to a favourable condition and how we work with vital farming communities in that region.  Along with the habitats directive we have the floods directive and the water directive.  The objective of the floods directive is to establish a framework for the assessment and management of flood risks, and to reduce the negative consequences of flooding on human health, economic activities, the environment and cultural heritage in the EU.</p> <p>I thank some Irish researchers for their paper entitled "Groundwater flood hazards and mechanisms in lowland karst terrains".  That is what we have in the west; it is a karst limestone landscape.  It can be seen that "... backwater flooding of sinks, high water levels in ... flooded basins (turloughs), overtopping of depressions, and discharges from springs and resurgences" lead to flooding, especially in karst areas.  How then are we going to protect our cultural heritage in the west of Ireland, where we have the majority of turloughs for the whole of the EU and also manage the flooding to ensure we are also protecting those communities?</p> <p>Positive farming practices such as grazing turloughs are crucial.  They assist in the maintenance of these turloughs.  Last night we heard of studies on the lough.  We have the floods directive to protect people and the habitats directive to protect habitats, species and wildlife, yet there is rotting vegetation, trees in the lake, the growth of algae and probably no oxygen.  Whether fish are dying or not we do not know.  We have the birds directive and the soil has washed away, as have the food plants and vegetation that is one of the qualifying criteria.  There is anecdotal evidence the whooper swans are not there and neither are the curlews.  There is the water directive and yet our rivers do not meet the criteria.</p> <p>How do we work together with Departments, the NPWS and the OPW?  How do we ensure the qualifying criteria and conservation objectives for Lough Funshinagh?  How do we update designations for the SAC?  What is the active management plan?  What is the timeline for this type of review?  How do we fund and increase the expertise level so local authorities in the west can have ecologists and hydrologists, as we are supposed to be the ones maintaining this environment for the whole of the EU?  How can Ireland take a lead at the EU level within the Directorate-General for the Environment?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aisling Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AislingDolan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The birds have flown away, the trees are dead and we are left with families in despair.  We have to find a way forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#O00200"><p>I thank Senator Dolan for raising this matter.  I will answer on behalf of the Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, to whom the NPWS reports.</p> <p>Special areas of conservation, SACs, are prime wildlife conservation areas in the country that are considered to be important on a European level as well as an Irish level.  The legal basis on which SACs are selected and designated is the EU habitats directive, which was transposed into Irish law by SI 477 of 2011, as amended.</p> <p>Turloughs are semi-natural habitats that are virtually unique to Ireland.  They generally flood in winter and dry out in summer, but there may be other sporadic rises in response to high rainfall.  Turloughs are considered to be of high conservation value for their plant, invertebrate - both terrestrial and aquatic - and bird communities and are an annex I habitat.</p> <p>Under Article 11 of the directive, each member state is obliged to undertake surveillance of the conservation status of the natural habitats and species in the annexes and, under Article 17, to report to the European Commission every six years on their status and the implementation of the measures taken under the directive.  In April 2019, Ireland submitted the third assessment of conservation status for 59 habitats and 60 species.  The overall status of the 45 sites designated for the annex I habitat turloughs, because of ongoing pressures related to drainage, groundwater pollution and ecologically unsuitable grazing, has been assessed as inadequate and stable.</p> <p>The National Parks and Wildlife Service of the Department of the Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, has published site-specific conservation objective documents for all the SACs that have been selected for the priority Annex I habitat turloughs, along with a supporting document called Conservation Objectives Supporting Document: Turloughs and Rivers with Muddy Banks with Chenopodion Rubri p.p. and Bidention p.p. Vegetation.  That document is available on the NPWS website.</p> <p>Lough Funshinagh was selected as a special area of conservation taking account of the more drawn out pattern of drainage than the typical annual rise and fall of other turlough lakes.  The typical species of turloughs, including those found at Lough Funshinagh, are those that occur underwater as well as those typical of the water's edge.  Lough Funshinagh SAC, however, is also selected for the EU habitats directive Annex I habitat rivers with muddy banks with chenopodion rubri p.p. and bidention p.p. vegetation.</p> <p>Geological Survey Ireland, GSI, has been monitoring water levels on Lough Funshinagh since 2016 and has indicated that the levels are due to rainfall rather than blockage or change in the natural draining system.  GSI has found that the rate of drainage during dry periods has been consistent and that the problem is that the drainage rate in general is unusually slow for a turlough of Lough Funshinagh's size.  While most turloughs empty each summer, Lough Funshinagh is slow to drain, typically every four to five years.  It is evident that Funshinagh does not get a chance to reset, as it is called, its flood pattern each year.  As a consequence, Lough Funshinagh has not drained since before the 2016 flood.  This issue has been further exacerbated by the heavy rainfall of recent years.</p> <p>I assure the Senator the Government is acutely aware of the difficulties faced by landowners and householders in the local area in respect of the threat of flooding.  However, a change to the designation of Lough Funshinagh SAC, or to any Natura 2000 site, is not a national policy decision in isolation but would require ratification by the Directorate General for Environment of the European Commission and would always be based on scientific grounds.  The current advice from the National Parks and Wildlife Service is that there is not a compelling scientific case to go to the European Commission seeking to remove Lough Funshinagh from the SAC list.</p> <p>Policy relating to flood risk management and its implementation are primarily the responsibility of the Office of Public Works and the local authority, which also have a role in ensuring adherence to EU nature legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#O00300"><p>From what I understand, then, the Geological Survey of Ireland, GSI, is stating Lough Funshinagh is still a turlough.  Is that correct?  From what I understand and from what the Minister of State has told me, he is stating that the last time Lough Funshinagh was cleared was in 2016, whereas Roscommon County Council has stated the last time it was fully drained was in 1996.  In other words, Lough Funshinagh is not operating as turloughs normally would.</p> <p>The Minister of State has stated that every six years an update is provided to the European Union, on the conservation objectives.  When was the last update given to the European Union?  All the sites in Ireland, from what I understand, are assessed as inadequate and stable.  Does that mean they will continue as inadequate?  As for the conservation objectives, I know that within the NPWS there has been funding for a conservation implementation section, which will look at the conservation measures.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aisling Dolan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AislingDolan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We need to know what the plan ahead is.  Conservation measures need to be put in place or else we will lose the habitat that we want to protect in Lough Funshinagh.  We cannot proceed unless we know, from the NPWS, the measures that will be put in place to protect the habitat, vegetation and all other qualifying criteria under the EU habitats directive annex I designation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#P00200"><p>Geological Survey Ireland has stated that the problem at Lough Funshinagh is caused by rainfall and poor drainage, and that the recent problems were caused by increases in rainfall.  I understand that there are strong feelings locally and I am aware the Senator attended a meeting with other representatives to which a large number of people turned out.  I know as a politician that this is significant and means there is considerable concern about the issue.  I will seek to arrange a meeting between the Senator and the Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, to discuss this in order to find a way forward within the law.  Naturally, we must abide by not just Irish law but European law regarding special areas of conservation.  In whatever way we manage a balance between staying within the law, protecting the environment, as well as protecting the livelihood and lives of those who live around Lough Funshinagh, I will do whatever I can to help.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#P00300"><p>That would strike a balance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.56" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 1.12 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 1.30 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 1.12 p.m. and resumed at 1.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.57" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#T00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#T00200"><p>Before I call the Leader on the Order of Business, I welcome to the Distinguished Visitors Gallery, Ms Cara Hunter, MLA, who is most welcome.  I congratulate her on her election to Stormont and I thank her for being in Seanad &Eacute;ireann today.  I now call on the Leader for the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#T00300"><p>I thank the Chair.  I also congratulate Ms Hunter and wish her the best of luck.</p> <p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding membership of the Joint Committee on Standing Orders relative to private business, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business without debate; No. 2, motion regarding the 16th report of the Seanad Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight, to be taken on conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, Sick Leave Bill 2022 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken at 2.45 p.m. and the proceedings thereon shall, if not previously concluded, be brought to a conclusion at 4.45 p.m. by the putting of one question from the Chair, which shall in relation to amendments include only those set down or accepted by the Government; No. 4, motion regarding EU directive on protecting persons who engage in public participation from manifestly unfounded or abusive court proceedings known as strategic law suits against public participation, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. or on conclusion of No. 3, whichever is the earlier, and to conclude after 45 minutes, if not previously concluded, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister not to exceed five minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given no less than five minutes to reply to the debate; No. 5, EirGrid, Electricity and Turf (Amendment) Bill 2022 - all Stages, to be taken at 5.30 p.m. or on conclusion of No. 4, whichever is the earlier, with the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister on Second Stage not to exceed ten minutes, group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given no less than ten minutes to reply to the debate, and Committee and Remaining Stages to be taken immediately thereafter; and No. 6, motion regarding earlier signature of the EirGrid, Electricity and Turf (Amendment) Bill 2022, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 5, without debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1642" speakername="Lisa Chambers" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#U00200"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  Last night I attended a meeting of about 450 people in the TF Royal Hotel and Theatre in Castlebar organised by representatives of RSS and T&uacute;s and also attended by SIPTU.  As anyone working in public life knows, a meeting of that scale takes a lot of organising so there was an impressive crowd there last night.  It took place on foot of the campaign that has been ongoing for many years to improve the operation of T&uacute;s and the RSS, the rural social scheme, in terms of how they operate, the eligibility criteria applied, the top-up payment and the flexibility around the schemes, while also acknowledging their huge importance in many rural communities right across the country.</p> <p>The schemes, as people will know, were originally set up by Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, and have been going strong ever since.  There was acknowledgement at the meeting last night that some of the changes made, in particular the removal of the six-year rule, were really welcome and will be of help but that there is still more work to be done.  The schemes are finding it very difficult to get people to come onto the schemes and there are vacant places.</p> <p>The RSS and T&uacute;s schemes do everyday jobs like keeping the local football pitch mown and ready for all the sports clubs - be it the under fives all the way up the senior team, keeping the parish hall or the community centre clean, tidy and operational, and keeping the door open and closed at certain times.  As the saying goes, "You don't know what you've got until it's gone" and it is only when people like that are not in the community and the work is not being done, that the true value is realised.</p> <p>It may come as a shock to many people that people on those schemes only get &euro;22.50 as a top-up to their farm assist or social welfare payments.  This is certainly value for money embodied and then some.  What the RSS and T&uacute;s representatives were looking for last night was greater flexibility in how they operate those schemes, so that they can try to get people into those schemes through direct referrals, and also by expanding the eligibility criteria.</p> <p>For example, only one person can join under each herd number and that prevents a nephew or niece working on the farm, from participating in a local scheme.  That makes no sense to me.  Greater flexibility will mean these schemes are viable.  They started off as a stopgap for job activation, as a way of getting people back into the workforce but also dealing with rural isolation and allowing people to connect with and contribute to their local communities.  Very importantly, they also top-up farm incomes by allowing people working on farms and in fishing villages to do some extra hours on a scheme on top of the hours they do on their farm.  The schemes are really important for increasing people's income, but also connecting them with their local community.  The schemes have evolved since that point in time and they are now part of the very fabric of rural life.  Many communities would not get certain jobs done if it was not for these schemes.  They do work that the local authorities simply do not have the manpower, womanpower or resources to get done.  </p> <p>I request that the Seanad have a debate at the earliest opportunity to try to get some further engagement with the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, around these outstanding issues that need to be resolved.  I appreciate it will probably be in the autumn session.  We should also look at how these schemes can be protected into the future and how to ensure their sustainability and viability for the years and decades to come.  They are now part and parcel of how business is run in rural areas and are vitally important.  </p> <p>I thank the RSS and T&uacute;s representatives who organised that meeting last night.  It was a fantastic meeting and they certainly rallied the troops.  We were all sent away from the table with orders to try and advance these issues right across both Houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#U00400"><p>Go raibh maith agat, a Chathaoirligh.  I join in welcoming Ms Cara Hunter, MLA, to the House and I commend her on her courage and bravery not just in her political life but in her personal life.  Cuirim m&iacute;le f&aacute;ilte roimpi inniu chuig Seanad &Eacute;ireann.</p> <p>I rise today predominantly to ask for the Minister of State with responsibility for disability to come to the House to discuss the lack of a service level agreement between ChildVision and the HSE in CHO 4 in Cork.  It is alarming that an organisation such as ChildVision, based on the Model Farm Road in Cork, providing a tremendously important service for children with sight loss and additional disabilities in particular at preschool time, should have no service level agreement.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It provides a tremendously important service for children with sight loss and additional disabilities, particularly at preschool level, where there is no service level agreement.</p><p>Last Saturday, Deputy Colm Burke and I met ChildVision chief executive officer, Mr. Brian Allen, and a group of parents to discuss the unique organisation that is ChildVision and preschool visual impairment early intervention for young children.  It is extraordinary that at a time when we are told the HSE has a huge amount of money at its disposal, for the sum of a ballpark figure of &euro;144,000 there cannot be a service level agreement signed between the HSE and ChildVision.</p><p>To be fair, the Leader knows Mr. Brian Allen does tremendous work as chief executive, as does the entire organisation.  These young children are benefitting and progressing rather than regressing.  It is incumbent on us to see that what Dublin has, Cork should have when it comes to this type of service provision.  It is about a world-class intervention and services for children.  It is happening in Cork since approximately 2010 with this organisation on the grounds of Model Farm Road with the Irish Guide Dogs for the Blind.</p><p>It is important now for the Minister to come to the House and hold the HSE accountable for the lack of a service level agreement that would give certainty and clarity to the young children and, equally important, to their families.  This is about parity of service and ensuring the service level agreement is signed so we can allow for these young children to be given the service, care and attention they need so their lives may evolve in a positive way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#V00200"><p>I welcome Ms Cara Hunter, MLA, and Dr. James Wilson to the House.  It is great to see them here.  I congratulate Ms Hunter on her election and Dr. Wilson on his support for that election.</p> <p>Last week we had the Air Navigation and Transport Bill 2020 before the House.  I do not wish to rehash the debate but on 29 June, the Department of Transport issued a tender seeking an aviation consultancy service relating to the competition for the provision of an Irish Coast Guard aviation service.  Are we really going to appoint an agent for our next search and rescue service?  I have been harping on about this for two years, if not more.  It is absolutely diabolical to think we are about to engage in another search and rescue contract when four people lost their lives because of the lack of oversight of the previous contract.  We are about to go to tender on this.</p> <p>I understand that in contempt of the Oireachtas committee a tender has already gone out and the Secretary General of the Department has refused on four occasions to come before the committee to discuss the process that has brought us to the point we are at.  It is simply unacceptable behaviour.  I wonder, at this stage, to whom the Civil Service is answerable.  Have we in the Oireachtas a role at all or are we just here to rubber-stamp whatever comes our way?  It is diabolical that the Department of Transport is engaging in anything to do with aviation when it has no expertise to support it in the area.</p> <p>On a related matter of aviation, my colleague, Deputy Cathal Berry, has made the point that soldiers are being brought from Donegal to Dublin to assist Dublin Airport Authority.  They should at the very least be paid &euro;10.50 per hour for every hour they are on the road.  If it is a 24-hour duty, they should be paid &euro;10.50 per hour on top of their salaries.  What is being done here is an insult to anybody who ever wore a uniform.</p> <p>Dublin Airport Authority has the support of this State and the State supported businesses through Covid-19 like no other state in Europe.  Dublin Airport Authority took an opportune moment to get rid of a load of people and I have heard its representatives on radio talking about the difficulty they have in recruiting people.  It is absolutely unacceptable.  Today we heard on Claire Byrne's radio show that it will take two hours for passengers on any flight coming in to recover their bags, if they are lucky.  They will be two hours waiting in the arrivals hall to get a bag.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is totally unacceptable.  For once we actually have to stand up for the Government on this one.  The Government put the supports in place for all of these companies and the Dublin Airport Authority threw it back in the face of the Government and took the opportunity to get rid of the cheapest labour it has.  Now it wants to use the Defence Forces for a job.  It should hire private security companies and see what they will charge.  Using soldiers for this kind of work is totally unacceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#W00200"><p>I extend a warm welcome to Ms Cara Hunter MLA and Dr. James Wilson.  It is great to see them here today.  There is a strike happening today on behalf of the Irish Wheelchair Association in 50 centres throughout the State.  The workers are personal assistants who carry out very important work in terms of personal care, hygiene and the social outlets they create for their clients.  As one client says in a video on the SIPTU website, if it was not for this person they would not get out of their house.  That is too often the case.  They create an incredibly valuable contribution to the quality of life of people with disabilities.</p> <p>The Government response to the strike today is to the effect that the Irish Wheelchair Association is a private company and the Government does not get involved with setting rates of pay.  The Irish Wheelchair Association has made it very clear it fully sympathises with its workers on strike today and states that it needs an increase in the HSE grant.  A Chathaoirligh, if you want to know why the Government is so unpopular, it is because of glib statements like its response I mentioned.  These workers have not had a pay rise in 14 years and are now in the midst of the worst cost-of-living crisis in decades.  The Government's response is there is nothing to see here and it is nothing to do with it.  These people have been forced to go to the picket line.  It is an absolute disgrace.</p> <p>Tomorrow, workers from a host of community sector organisations will go on strike for the very same reason.  People from Rehab Group, Western Care Association, Pieta House, local employment services, Ability West, Inclusion Ireland, jobs clubs, LEADER projects and more are going on strike for the same reason, that for 14 years Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael governments - it makes no difference - have ignored them.</p> <p>I presume tomorrow the Government will come out with another glib statement saying it has nothing to do with it.  The only way these workers can get a pay rise is for the Government to engage with their employers, release the funds and make it happen.  For too long we have had platitudes about these workers.  They are front-line workers who do incredible work in the community sector, bringing people back from addiction and exclusion, getting them into work, society and third level education, and getting them back on the road to having a decent life.  For 14 years governments have ignored the staff who provide these services.  Are they going to have to go on strike again after today and tomorrow?  Will the Government continue to put its head in the sand and pretend it has nothing to do with it?  Will someone on the Government benches today acknowledge that a great wrong has been done to these workers?  We need to see the Government engage collectively with these workers and deliver the pay rise they so fully deserve.  I hope for a positive response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#W00300"><p>I want to raise some concerns about the ordering of business this week and last week.  I refer to the Circular Economy, Waste Management (Amendment) and Minerals Development (Amendment) Bill 2022.  We have the Higher Education Authority Bill 2022 coming up this week as well as the Electoral Reform Bill 2022.  Those two Bills are once in a lifetime pieces of legislation in their importance, their reach and potential for change in a number of sectors.  Our group is concerned about the Electoral Reform Bill this week.  It provides for how we do electoral politics but we undermine that by skipping processes in how we do business and scrutinise legislation as Seanad &Eacute;ireann.  We know it is urgent and fundamental legislation.  I and others take our role extremely seriously in how much effort and time we put into scrutinising every line of legislation, as we have with the Electoral Reform Bill.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Ruane:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2481"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2481&amp;amp;pid=LynnRuane&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Obviously, the Bill has been in flow for two years but has now been rushed through in the past two weeks.  That does not give the House time to do what it is mandated to do and what Senators are elected to do.  I note a change to the Order of Business on Thursday in respect of the Electoral Reform Bill.  It was initially scheduled to take Report Stage but then it changed to Committee Stage (resumed) and Report and Final Stages.  Is the intention to attempt to guillotine that debate?  We strongly oppose any such proposal and will seek to put any guillotine on the Bill to a vote.</p><p>We have raised previously, in the context of other legislation, our concerns in respect of the taking of all Stages at once, especially when it is legislation in which there is significant interest and input and with a large number of amendments.  We are seeking to clarify whether the Order of Business on Thursday will be amended to remove Report Stage from the timing so that Senators have a chance to table amendments on Report Stage.  To take the Stages together is just telling us that what will happen in here on Thursday is theatre.  We will come in but have no room to table more amendments and the Minister will not accept any amendments anyway.  That does not do the House any service and it definitely does not do the legislation any service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#X00200"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" speakername="Malcolm Byrne" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#X00300"><p>I, too, welcome Cara Hunter to the Gallery.  Yesterday, she spoke profoundly on RT&Eacute; radio in respect of her experience of online abuse during an election campaign.  In these Houses last week we launched a report in respect of the abuse of referees, match officials and others involved in sport.  Yesterday, Ursula Jacob who, as Members will be aware, is an All-Ireland camogie medal winner for Wexford, a commentator and a person with great experience of sport, became the latest person in the public eye to have to speak out against the online abuse, anonymous and otherwise, she has experienced.  I am conscious that the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill will be back before the House next week.  There are measures that need to be taken in that context but this House needs to discuss calling on the social media platforms to do a lot more.  Not enough is being done to tackle online abuse.  It should not be the case that, every week, individuals in the public eye and, in many cases, people who are not in the public eye, have to suffer levels of online abuse.  We will certainly show our continued solidarity with Ursula Jacob and all other victims of anonymous online abuse.</p> <p>I regularly raise in the House the issue of foreign births registration.  There have been ongoing problems relating to the Passport Office.  The problem with foreign birth registrations, however, is not improving.  The Department of Foreign Affairs has now reached applications that were submitted in January 2020.  A person applying now for a foreign birth registration will have to wait more than 30 months before his or her application is considered.  That is not acceptable.  I again ask that we have a specific debate on the issue of foreign birth registrations and that the Leader write to the Minister on behalf of Senators to express our concern.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#X00400"><p>The recent announcement by the US Supreme Court in the Dobbs <i>v</i>. Jackson Women's Health Organization case is a positive one as it finally ends the wrong-headed Roe <i>v</i>. Wade judgment of 1973 which inferred a constitutional right to abortion under the heading of a right to privacy.  That was a legal aberration from the beginning, one that had an extremely negative impact on human rights and unborn life for 50 years.  It must be borne in mind that approximately 21,000 Irish unborn babies have had their lives prematurely ended by abortion in the first three years of Ireland's abortion regime.  The sky-rocketing human life impact of the abortion law here must prompt serious reflection.  There has been a serious failure to provide alternatives to abortion or to find a way to reduce these startling abortion rates.  The Government has buried its head in the sand on this issue.  For more than a year, it has outsourced any issues that have arisen since the introduction of legal abortion to the chimeric promise of a three-year review.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The review has since commenced and is in fact uninterested in addressing serious issues.  Instead, its brief has been to concentrate on expanding abortion to the detriment of grasping the nettle and seeking to curb the worst excesses of Irish abortion laws.  Saturday's Rally for Life saw thousand of people march from Parnell Square, down O'Connell Street and onto Custom House Quay welcoming the US judgment and asking our politicians to thoroughly re-examine the protection that we offer to life in Ireland.  Unfortunately, a lot of the rhetoric reacting to the decision has been extremely unhelpful and alarmist.  The Taoiseach talked about the appointment of far right justices to the Supreme Court and warned of a politicisation of the court.  This is an unfounded insinuation and suggests his characterisation of politicisation only works in one direction.  <br/><br/>In the Dobbs <i>v</i>. Jackson ruling, the Supreme Court returned the issue of deciding abortion policy to the people through their elected representatives at state and federal level.  It strongly echoes the 2018 referendum outcomes that empowered the Oireachtas alone to decide Ireland's abortion policy.  The Government should objectively look at the situation for what it is and not try to stoke up culture war arguments.  The global narrative is clearly shifting and I hope the impact of the recent decision in the US will produce further, greater efforts to protect human life in Ireland and elsewhere.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#Y00200"><p>I welcome our friends in the Visitors Gallery, Ms Cara Hunter, and Dr. James Wilson, but they have left.  I did not fully hear Senator Chambers when she was speaking first but I think she was calling for a debate on issues with social employment schemes and T&uacute;s workers.  I certainly support that because while there has been some movement from the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, which I welcome that, there are one or two issues that, if they were they sorted out, would ensure such schemes would retain their importance for not only rural communities, but urban communities as well.  They are very important in different areas of life.</p> <p>I wish to return to the matter of Lough Funshinagh that I brought up last Thursday.  Last night, more than 300 people attended a meeting in Lecarrow, County Roscommon.  This is where there has been a major flooding issue due to a turlough that is no longer draining.  This has been an issue for a number of years.  The local authority, Roscommon County Council, with the support of the Minister and the Government provided funding for an overlay pipe to take the excess water.  Unfortunately, the Friends of the Irish Environment objected to that, took the local authority to court and won its case.  That annoyed people but the reality is we now have a court judgment and we have to deal with that.  In fairness to the Minister of State at the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy O'Donovan, he is trying to address this issue.  A number of other Ministers, including the Taoiseach, are concerned about it.  We must try to get heads together on this matter because it is an injustice.  It is unjust to people whose homes, which were never flooded, will now be flooded and will have to relocate.  Something has gone wrong in the area.  Nobody can put a finger on what has gone wrong but we have to take those people out of their misery.  It may be a bad summer but rainfall is below previous levels.  In that area we are lucky there has not been excess rain despite the poor weather.  If the weather turns bad for three or four weeks when we go into the winter, there will be stories to be told in that area.  We need to put our heads together, write to the Minister and push this on as quickly as we can to get something done to ensure those people will not suffer any longer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#Y00300"><p>I wish to make Members aware of an event that will take place in Liberty Hall on 11 August.  It is the concert to save Moore Street.  As Members know, the Moore Street Preservation Trust, which is made up of families of the signatories to the 1916 Proclamation, have been campaigning for a considerable time to save, preserve and develop the Moore Street battlefield site on behalf of the city and, indeed, on behalf of the nation and all her people.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The families have described the latest planning permission granted for further demolition of buildings in the Moore Street Quarter as deplorable.  Speaking on behalf of the families, James Connolly Heron said:</p><blockquote>	This is a deplorable decision, with Dublin City Planners now having granted permission to all three of Hammerson&rsquo;s applications for Moore Street.  The City Planners have now given the green light to the development of a six-storey office block that would totally dominate the historic 1916 terrace and turn O&rsquo;Rahilly Parade into a cavern between two towering buildings.  They have yet again ignored the wish of Councillors to add the Moore Street terrace to the list of protected structures and survey reports that confirm the existence of 1916 buildings structures and elements throughout this area described by The National Museum as 'the most important historic site in modern Irish history'. </blockquote><p>Therefore, there is a battle now to save Moore Street.I do not know of any other government, state or society around the world that would allow an area which has been described as the most important in a country&rsquo;s modern history to be overrun with more glass boxes, characterless and soulless buildings, when the Moore Street Quarter has so much potential, so much history, so much built heritage and so much potential for the future of our capital city in the context of sharing in the learning of the 1916 Rising.  Probably more important, however, is the potential to share, develop and grow in that vision.  In that context, I hope the Leader will be able to facilitate, as early as possible, statements from the Minister on saving Moore Street, because we all have a stake in this battle and we must all play our part in ensuring that Moore Street is saved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#Z00200"><p>I raise the issue of the smart villages and rural towns meeting being held in Mountbellew this evening.  The venue has been selected by Galway Rural Development, GRD, to receive this type of funding.  I encourage people in the local area to come along.  The meeting begins at 7.30 p.m. this evening and it will be great to be able to see the opportunities for funding.  Mountbellew is now one of the campuses of the Atlantic Technological University, ATU.  An agricultural college is also based there and people will know of Mountbellew very well from that context.  Now, however, the town is also a new campus for the ATU.  Equally, consideration is being given to developing the town in other ways.</p><p>We also need to see more rural transport links.  In the context of the Connecting Ireland plan for transport, one example of what is needed is that there is no bus link to bring people from Mountbellew to the train station in Ballinasloe, for example, or to Portiuncula Hospital, or <i>vice versa</i>.  Equally, it is difficult for students to get to the campus.  It is important therefore when we are looking at our smart villages and rural towns initiative that we also examine how we can get funding for rural transport links.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#Z00300"><p>I also express my support for all those employed by the Irish Wheelchair Association, IWA, who took the decision to go on strike today.  Those people last saw a pay increase in 2008.  I stood with those workers this morning in Clontarf and, believe you me, they do not want to be out on strike.</p> <p>It is important to say that minimum levels of care continue to be provided, so people are being looked after today.  These workers, however, have been forced to go on strike because they feel they have no other option and that nobody is listening to them.  Talking to one of those workers today, Jacinta, I was struck by her talking about the frustration of doing one of the most important jobs, of undertaking a caring role, and yet feeling so disrespected because of the rate of pay that she gets for that work.  She cannot even afford to buy a car and spends hours on buses travelling across the city every day trying to get to the people she looks after.  The front-line worker payment of &euro;1,000 has not been given to these people, although they were going into houses day in and day out during the height of the pandemic, with the attendant risk to themselves and their families.  To add insult to injury, there has also been no progress regarding their long-standing pay claim.</p> <p>A woman who is a wheelchair user came out on the protest today.  She talked about her frustration in this regard, and she fully supports the strike.  From talking to other wheelchair users as well, I know they fully support what the workers in the IWA are doing today.  Those service users see the frustration in this context and they want the people taking care of them to be better respected and supported.  I refer to the failure by the Government, to date, in the context of section 39 organisations.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Of course, the IWA is just one section 39 organisation.  Not to put in place a proper system of pay is simply shameful.  At the moment, the HSE is obviously giving money to the likes of the IWA and other services and yet it is poaching workers from many of those organisations and taking them into the HSE.  As Jacinta said to me today, she wants to work with wheelchair users and the IWA.  However, life has been made very difficult for her at the moment.</p><p>I plead for the Taoiseach to intervene personally.  It is no longer about calling on the Minister for Health.  Rather, it is about the Taoiseach intervening personally to ensure those who provide a very important role in our society are properly respected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#AA00200"><p>I have just come from an excellent briefing in the audiovisual room.  I appreciate those who are here did not have the opportunity to go to it.  It was from the Ukraine Civil Society Forum and about 65 different organisations that together are responding to the Ukrainian crisis within our country.  We must acknowledge that, since 24 February, when Putin&rsquo;s war of aggression started, the Irish people and, indeed, the Irish Government have been wonderful in terms of their humanitarian response.  Little did we think, or perhaps some did, that almost five months later we would still be seeing horrific scenes coming from Ukraine.</p> <p>We all know families and communities that have opened their hearts and homes to the refugees who have come to this country.  There are many in congregated settings and some who have been able to find accommodation.  We are at a pinch point now.  We recognise the war will not finish any time soon and there will be another accommodation crisis during the summer and in September when students are back.</p> <p>The group made a number of recommendations.  The key ones, which I would absolutely support and agree with, are, first, that there should be a national lead appointed to drive planning, co-ordination and implementation.  That is very important.  Another main recommendation, and this related to the White Paper on ending direct provision, was that a refugee agency would be established.  Even taking those two key recommendations would be beneficial.  We have only one more chance to try to get this right.  It will be for the medium and long term.  It will be important that message would go to the Taoiseach and the relevant Ministers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#AA00300"><p>I thank my colleagues for their contributions.</p> <p>I thank Senator O&rsquo;Loughlin for describing the recommendations made by the Ukraine Civil Society Forum.  Given the announcement of the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, yesterday, that we are putting aside &euro;2 billion next year to look after the guests we have in Ireland, it is a very logical request to have a refugee agency and a national lead who represents the Government.  I will certainly pass on the Senator's messages.</p> <p>Senator Sherlock and Senator Gavan raised the issue of what I can only describe as a very unfortunate strike.  Obviously, however, after 14 years, people felt they had absolutely no choice but to go on strike today.  I am mindful about section 38 and 39 organisations.  The reason we have them is because the State does not provide certain services for the people in need.  It is disingenuous on behalf of the State to say it is not its responsibility to set pay policy when Government policy is to outsource these services to the people and organisations we all recognise as being valuable and, indeed, as Senator Sherlock said, the workers themselves whom we also recognise as being valuable.  I find myself probably not being on the side of the Government&rsquo;s response the morning because I think it is time for Government to intervene and take responsibility for those workers who may not be direct employees of the State but who are actually providing services in lieu of the State.  I very much concur with both Senators&rsquo; remarks and I will pass them on.</p> <p>Senator Dolan spoke about a meeting tonight in Mountbellew on the smart villages initiative and rural transport funding.  I acknowledge that she is inviting everybody to come along.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile talked about a concert in Liberty Hall that is happening on 11 August to raise money for the Save Moore Street campaign, and I acknowledge that.</p> <p>Senator Murphy and the Fianna F&aacute;il group leader raised the issue of the meeting on and the support for further changes to T&uacute;s and the rural support scheme, RSS, that were announced by the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, last week.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We did see some welcome changes.  I can only say this from the experience of being in the Department, but we need to be mindful that the schemes in the Department are considered employment and activation schemes.  At a time when we have nearly full employment, it is hard to find people to fill those schemes.  The reality is a lot of them are income supports and community facilitation for work and organisational support in local communities that would not otherwise be supported by the State if we did not have them.  There is a real need for some flexibility.  I will try to arrange a debate in the autumn with the Minister, as requested.<br/><br/>Senator Murphy also referred to a very large meeting in Roscommon last night on an issue he and Senator Aisling Dolan raised last week with regard to the special area of conservation, SAC, at Lough Funshinagh.  Again, I wish the Senators continued success in the deliberations with the Minister of State, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan, in trying to find a resolution.<br/><br/>Senator Keogan brought up the recent Roe <i>v</i>. Wade decision in the United States and the debate that has been struck, not just in America, but internationally arising from that.  We have our own three-year review of the abortion legislation that was passed arising from the repeal of the eighth amendment a number of years ago.  As I had committed to beforehand, I will certainly organise a debate on that review once it is released by the Minister.<br/><br/>Senator Malcolm Byrne, not for the first time, brought up foreign births registration.  I am flabbergasted by the example he gave and I will certainly bring it to the Minister's attention because it is not acceptable.<br/><br/>The other point raised by the Senator this morning is that we will hopefully be finishing the Online Safety and Media Regulation Bill in the Seanad next week.  What I can tell him personally is that from the interactions we have had with social media companies, they are certainly not happy.  They are not happy that we intend to issue the regulations immediately but they have done absolutely nothing to crown themselves in glory with regard to how they treat people whom we will call them victims.  I am sure there are a few of them in this room, but there are certainly plenty of people we know, many of them far too young to be resilient enough to be able to deal with the harassment and negativity they receive on social media platforms.  The companies have done little or nothing to try to protect people.  It is certainly time the State took the bull by the horns and started to regulate that industry.  I thank the Senator for raising the matter.<br/><br/>In response to Senator Ruane, I am between a rock and a hard place at the moment.  I totally recognise the Senator&rsquo;s concerns and I hear her loud and clear.  The position I am in is that we have two weeks left and we have an awful lot of work to do.  I have tried to facilitate in particular the Electoral Reform Bill because some colleagues were not here last week.  Ideally, we should have finished Committee Stage last week and then we would only have Report Stage this week, and we would have had plenty of time to put in the amendments.  Given that some colleagues were not here last week, I extended Committee Stage to have it this week and to allow that debate, but it meant I had to put Committee Stage and Report Stage together, which I know is not acceptable to the Senator.  There may be one or two options I can take to swap things around, if I can talk to the Senator afterwards.  I know it does not affect today's order because that is as it is.  I had asked last week if we could do all Stages of the EirGrid, Electricity and Turf (Amendment) Bill in the Chamber on Thursday.  There may be a way I can swap the Institutional Burials Bill to the evening and then try to split Committee Stage and Report Stage, but I can only do that if I have the acquiescence of the Cathaoirleach because to turn around the Report Stage amendments between Wednesday and Thursday would require an exception.  The Bills Office and our colleagues who work to support us are under pressure at this time of year, as they always are.  I will try, and I will see if I can come up with some sort of flexibility.<br/><br/>To be honest, I do not like using guillotines and I do not like closing off debate.  However, if we do not close off some debates this week, then we are pretending we are going to take amendments because I can bring them in next week, but there will be no D&aacute;il to take the amendments.  The Higher Education Authority Bill and the Electoral Reform Bill are time-sensitive.  We need to establish the electoral commission and the boards of our universities are changing during the summer, so the legislation needs to be passed before then.  I find I am between a rock and a hard place.  As the Senator is aware, even though the Electoral Reform Bill has been around a long time, we only got it relatively recently, and the HEA Bill was only published last week, so we could not have taken it any earlier.  I will do my best to try to juggle things around.  I will liaise directly with the Senator after the Order of Business, once we speak to the Bills Office and the Cathaoirleach.  I hear the Senator&rsquo;s concerns and I totally understand them.<br/><br/>Senator Gavan spoke of the Irish Wheelchair Association.  He also brought up the Air Navigation and Transport Bill from last week.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A tender for external expertise has been issued by the Minister for Transport to advise him on the search and rescue contract because the Department does not have expertise.  The Cathaoirleach is well aware that I have strong personal views on this.  Recommendations Nos. 29 and 31 of the Air Accident Investigation Unit arising from the loss of life on Rescue 116 specifically targeted the lack of expertise in the Department.  The Department still does not seem to see fit to put expertise on its own staff.  It is not something I can commend.</p><p>Deputy Berry made a statement recently and Senator Craughwell has made a call today for Army members to be paid &euro;10.50 per hour for any hours they are asked to work for the DAA.  I will certainly pass that on to the Minister.  The Minister is right, and it would be remiss of me not to stick up for the Government occasionally, that we borrowed &euro;36 billion in the two years we supported our people and businesses during Covid.  It is an enormous amount of money but it was the right thing to do.  It was a time for us to be generous.  We have to wonder with the amount of money we used to support people why companies still took the opportunity to let go some of their most expensive and valuable staff.</p><p>Deputy Buttimer spoke about ChildVision and the HSE's CHO 4 in Cork.  ChildVision has been providing a wonderful service not only in Cork but in other parts of the country.  It is unfathomable that the HSE would not give ChildVision a service level agreement.  What is wrong is that the HSE does not pay for services already in existence.  It only pays for new services.  There would be an outcry if the service was not available.  For the HSE not to provide the miserable sum of &euro;144,000 for a service for 80 children and their families would be a crying shame.  I will certainly raise the mater with the Minister for Health on behalf of Senator Buttimer and Mr. Brian Allen.</p><p>Senator Chambers opened proceedings seeking a debate on T&uacute;s and the rural social scheme, including a top-up and the need for greater flexibility in recruitment.  I will organise such a debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.82" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.83" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#CC00300">Joint Committee on Standing Orders Relative to Private Business: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#CC00400"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That, notwithstanding anything in the Standing Orders of the D&aacute;il and Seanad relative to Private Business, in relation to the membership of the Joint Committee on Standing Orders (Private Business), a maximum of four members of the D&aacute;il and four members of the Seanad may be members of the Committee. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.85" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.86" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#CC00600">Report of Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#CC00700"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That the Sixteenth Report of the Committee on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight on the amendment of Standing Orders 47, 49A, 72, 85, 98, 99, 107, 108, 110, 113 and 176 be adopted, laid before the House and printed. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.88" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.89" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 2.18 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 2.45 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 2.18 p.m. and resumed at 2.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.90" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#KK00050">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#KK00100"><p>No. 3 is the Sick Leave Bill 2022, Report and Final Stages.  Before I call the Leader, I welcome to the Public Gallery Councillor Damien O'Reilly and Councillor Robert McDermott, his daughter, Ms Ellen McDermott, and brother, Mr. Andrew McDermott, and Andrew's daughter.  You are all very welcome to Leinster House.  I hope you have a lovely day here.</p> <p>I also welcome another group, Mr. Gavin McGowan, Ms Susan Meehan and Mr. Liam McBride, who are visiting Leinster House from Donegal.  You are all very welcome.  I hope you enjoy your day in Leinster House.</p> <p>I call the Leader to announce a small change to the business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#KK00400"><p>I propose, notwithstanding anything in Standing Orders, that the sitting be suspended until 3.05 p.m. when the Minister of State, Deputy English, will be able to come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#KK00500"><p>As the Minister of State has been delayed by a vote in the D&aacute;il, it is proposed to suspend until 3.05 p.m.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.94" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 2.55 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 3.05 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 2.55 p.m. and resumed at 3.05 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.95" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#NN00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#NN00200"><p>We are due to resume item No. 3 but the D&aacute;il is still in the middle of a vote.  I understand the Leader wishes to make a proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#NN00300"><p>I propose, notwithstanding anything in Standing Orders, the House suspend for another ten minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#NN00400"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.99" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 3.06 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 3.15 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 3.06 p.m. and resumed at 3.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.100" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00100">Sick Leave Bill 2022: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy English, to the House finally, following the D&aacute;il votes.</p> <p>Before we commence, I remind Senators that a Member may speak only once on Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment, who may reply to discussion on the amendment and each non-Government amendment must be seconded. </p> <p>Amendment No. 1 arises out of committee proceedings.  Is there someone who will second Senator Gavan&rsquo;s amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00300"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00400"><p>Amendment No. 1 then falls.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.104" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 1 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00600"><p>Amendment No. 2 arises out of committee proceedings.  Amendments Nos. 2, 7 and 8 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  Senator Sherlock is not here, so amendment No. 2 will fall as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.106" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 2 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00675"><p>Amendments Nos. 3 to 5, inclusive, are ruled out of order.  They have previously been rejected by a committee of the whole Seanad.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.108" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 3 to 5, inclusive, not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00693"><p>Amendment No. 6 is ruled out of order as a potential charge on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.110" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 6 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00698"><p>Amendment No. 7 arises out of committee proceedings.  It has been grouped with amendment No. 2.  Senator Sherlock is not here, so it falls.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.112" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 7 not moved.</p><p>Amendment No. 8 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00774"><p>Amendment No. 9 arises out of committee proceedings, but Senator Sherlock is not here, so it falls.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.114" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment No. 9 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00793"><p>Amendments Nos. 10 to 14, inclusive, are ruled out of order.  They have previously been rejected by a committee of the whole Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.116" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 10 to 14, inclusive, not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00798"><p>Amendments Nos. 15 and 16 are ruled out of order as potential charges on the Revenue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.118" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendments Nos. 15 and 16 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.119" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be received for final consideration."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ00900"><p>May I speak?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ01000"><p>The Senator cannot speak to the amendment because it is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ01100"><p>My understanding is that we could speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ01200"><p>The Senator cannot speak to the amendment because it is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ01300"><p>I will speak to the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ01400"><p>The Senator can speak to the Bill.  He may go ahead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#QQ01500"><p>I just want to make a couple of valid points.  Naturally, I thank the Minister of State for his continuous presence here over the past number of evenings.</p> <p>As the Acting Chair outlined, I want to speak to the Bill and Senator Casey will speak as well.  Many Senators have outlined that throughout the progress of the Bill we have expressed concerns about the impact this will have on small businesses, particularly those in hospitality and customer-facing sectors.  Hospitality and retail are the most obvious examples where anyone out due to illness will need to be replaced so that the other staff are not under enormous pressure.  As a representative of the Licensed Vintners Association, LVA, the Acting Chairman is well familiar with that.  In hospitality, if an employer is suddenly looking for a staff member to work at the weekends and replace someone who is ill, the reality is they will probably have to offer time and a half or double time.  Between that and paying the ill employee, naturally enough, employers are impacting on their overheads.  </p> <p>As I outlined previously, I support the Bill, which I believe all Members do, despite some differing views on how it should be implemented.  My concern is that small businesses are still seeking to recover from the Covid pandemic in challenging circumstances.  They are dealing with a range of challenges in addition to this, particularly with regard to inflation and supply chain issues. </p> <p>Following on from that, a number of SMEs have contacted me expressing concern about the additional costs their businesses will face under this legislation.  As I said previously, these are good, honest and decent employers who want to do the right thing by their staff.  However, between the number of issues I have outlined, they are under significant pressure to keep their businesses going.  I have seen it suggested that this legislation will add 1% or 2% to their payroll bill.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ollie Crowe:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OllieCrowe&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->While 1% or 2% may sound a small amount, for many SMEs that might have seven or eight staff, bar restaurants or shops, that is potentially thousands of euro per year.  SMEs tell me it is money they simply do not have in the current climate.</p><p>With the Minister of State, Deputy English, present, I again want to outline that I am supporting the Bill but I urge the Government to get ahead and to address this issue before it becomes a major problem.  I welcome the comments from the Minister of State, Deputy English, last week in the House that it should and could happen, but I would prefer something more certain.  As we are all aware, SMEs are the backbone of the Irish economy and there is an onus on all of us, in particular the Government, to ensure their sustainability is at the heart of this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#RR00200"><p>I appreciate that we are where we are with the Bill and if I was sitting where the Senator is sitting, I would probably be echoing the same points.  However, from the Chair, I have to be neutral and I must point out that, at this stage, where the Bill has been received for final consideration, only very brief comments can be made.  I invite Senators Ahearn and Casey to make brief points.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#RR00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I welcome the Bill and it is not before time that it has been brought through.  I recognise the amendments have been ruled out of order due to the potential cost to the Exchequer but, to be fair to small businesses, this is in recognition of the fear they have of the cost element of this measure coming through.</p> <p>To be fair to the T&aacute;naiste, when he was here on Second Stage he recognised that and he has not ruled out some sort of rebate being brought in at a later stage.  Obviously, the businesses themselves would like that to be done now and put in as part of this legislation, and we put this amendment forward to support them.</p> <p>In the grand scheme of things, the Bill is very positive and is more than welcome.  However, there is an element for small businesses that have been under severe pressure in the last year or two due to Covid and now the cost of living.  I ask that this be taken into account.  They want to work with the Government on this and they understand why this is being brought forward.  We need to ensure that this group, which is essential to our economy, is protected and is not adversely affected in a significant away by this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#RR00400"><p>I have no problem with the Bill in regard to the sick pay aspect.  However, when we are drafting legislation, we should honestly and clearly identify that there is a significant difference in sick pay for a large company when compared with a small company, or for a small SME when compared with a large SME.  Tied into all of that equation, when calculating this we have to take into account industries that have high labour costs as a percentage of turnover, because it is a double-whammy for them, as opposed to industries that have a very low percentage of labour costs to turnover.  This has a significant impact on the viability of these industries, whether in terms of the type of the industry or the size of the industry.</p> <p>My two colleagues have spoken on this and I know we are not in a position to move this specific amendment.  However, under the legislation, there is a report to be generated within the next 18 months.  During that period, I ask the Minister of State to commit to looking at this more closely in regard to the small SME sector to see how we can help it get through this and give its employees the very same opportunity as large-scale employers.  That is all I am asking.  Given that a report has to be drafted under the legislation, I am asking that, as part of that report, we focus in on the impact this is having on the small SME sector and how it might affect its viability into the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#RR00500"><p>I have had representations made to me on the same note.  Again, while I have to be completely impartial in the Chair, those points have been very well made by all of the Senators.  I call the Minister of State to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1505" speakername="Damien English" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#RR00600"><p>I thank the House for facilitating this discussion.  We were anxious to get this legislation through before the summer break of the Houses, so that is important.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I thank everybody for their help and for all their work.  I thank the officials.  Ms Wendy Gray who put a lot of work into this legislation over a long period of time could not be with us today.  I want to give her a shout-out because she put a lot of work into this important Bill that both Houses wanted.  Approximately a year and a half ago the T&aacute;naiste committed that we would bring it forward.</p><p>We are conscious this will mean extra costs for employers.  Senator Casey clarified the difference between larger businesses and smaller and medium enterprises.  Senators Crowe and Ahearn mentioned customer-facing roles.  Certainly when it comes to retail and hospitality there is a lot of pressure on the system.  Many businesses tell us their concern is not so much about the beginning of the sick leave scheme but about when employees increase their number of days.  It is something the T&aacute;naiste, departmental officials and I have committed to keeping an eye on and reviewing.  We will do this as part of our ongoing review of legislation.  Some of the amendments proposed a rebate.  There should be some supports for businesses and this is something we will analyse.  On Committee Stage I said we could look at other supports through a development agency, perhaps the local employment offices.  We are aware and conscious of it.</p><p>This is important legislation.  Everybody wanted it.  We are one of the few countries in Europe that does not have a statutory sick pay scheme.  We are conscious that it will put extra pressure on employers.  We want to continue with a very strong jobs-led recovery but we cannot take it for granted.  We are conscious that any increase in costs can jeopardise jobs.  We will keep an eye on it and we are prepared to step in if needs be.  We have to keep our cost base in order.  We are conscious that it will be more difficult for some sectors.</p><p>With regard to legislation generally, we try to find the sweet spot to be able to assist small businesses.  It can be difficult because a small business can have a large turnover.  It is not always easy to find the spot to kick in.  We will track and monitor this and we will respond if needs be.  I am conscious we had a similar conversation with Senator Gavan on the cost of medical bills and certification costs.  It is outside the scope of the Bill but it is something we are working on to be able to assist overall.  It is a positive measure and it will be important legislation for employees.  It will also strengthen Ireland's hand in attracting talent and staff.  We have a difficulty with sourcing the talent we need from the European employee market.  I hope we will be able to build on this and become a more attractive place for employees.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#SS00200"><p>I thank Senators Ahearn, Casey, Crowe and Gavan for their co-operation.  I thank the Minister of State, Deputy English.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.135" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#SS00400"><p>When is it proposed to take Fifth Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" speakername="Ollie Crowe" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#SS00500"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#SS00550"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.139" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question, "That the Bill do now pass", put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.140" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#UU00100">European Directive on Strategic Lawsuits against Public Participation: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" speakername="Pat Casey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#UU00200"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:  	Proposal for a Directive of the European Parliament and of the Council on protecting persons who engage in public participation from manifestly unfounded or abusive court proceedings (&lsquo;Strategic lawsuits against public participation&rsquo;), a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 30th May, 2022. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#UU00300"><p>On behalf of the Minister for Justice, Deputy McEntee, I thank the Cathaoirleach for facilitating this motion.</p> <p>Senators will be aware the prior approval of the Oireachtas is required, under Article 29.4.7&deg; of the Constitution, if Ireland wishes to take part in an EU measure whose legal base falls under Part 3, Title V of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, TFEU.  The proposed measure before members today has its legal base under Title V and therefore requires such approval.</p> <p>The proposal is for an EU directive on minimum common measures in member states to protect individuals and bodies, especially journalists and human rights defenders, against a type of manifestly unfounded or abusive court proceedings commonly known as SLAPPs, which is short for strategic lawsuits against public participation.  The proposal, which was first presented by the European Commission on 27 April 2022, forms part of a number of initiatives by the European Commission to reinforce the application of the Charter of Fundamental Rights of the European Union and to strengthen protection for democracy and the rule of law at EU level.  It responds to increasing concerns expressed by the Council of Europe, the European Parliament, the European Commission and NGOs across Europe concerned with press freedom and the protection of human rights about the increase in threats to democracy and human rights and, in particular, in physical and legal threats to media freedom and the safety of journalists.</p> <p>A particular concern has been these so-called SLAPP actions.  The proposal defines SLAPPs as manifestly unfounded or abusive court proceedings brought against those engaged in "public participation on matters of public interest" to deter them from such participation.  The objective is less to reach a determination of the main proceedings than to threaten, exhaust and silence the defendant by using procedural strategies such as artificially inflating legal costs, maximising delays, threatening the defendant with exorbitant penalties, making unfounded accusations, or issuing multiple proceedings in different jurisdictions.</p> <p>The proposal explains the characteristic purpose of a SLAPP proceedings is not to seek access to justice but rather to close down freedom of expression and information that is essential in a democracy.  SLAPP actions are therefore seen as not only a threat to the defendants themselves, but also an abuse of court time and resources and a potential threat to democracy, fundamental rights and the public interest.  Obviously, the proposed directive will need to strike a careful balance between the right of freedom of expression and information in the public interest, on the one hand, and, on the other, the rights of access to justice and to an effective remedy.  It is important to underline that, under the proposal, whether a particular set of proceedings amounts to a SLAPP would remain a decision for the national court.  The purpose of the proposed directive is rather to ensure every member state provides a minimum common toolbox of procedural safeguards to their judges and tribunals to protect defendants across the EU against SLAPP actions and to prevent these abusive actions from developing and proliferating.</p> <p>I will outline the main minimum procedural safeguards proposed.  The first safeguard is provision for SLAPP defendants to seek early dismissal of proceedings as "manifestly unfounded".  In that application, the burden of proof falls on the SLAPP plaintiff to show his or her action is not manifestly unfounded.  If the defendant seeks early dismissal, the main proceedings must be stayed until a final decision is made on the early dismissal application, which must be treated as an accelerated procedure.</p> <p>The second safeguard is provision for SLAPP defendants to seek a court order that the SLAPP plaintiff provides advance security for the defendant&rsquo;s costs, for example, that the plaintiff lodges money in court, if the court considers that appropriate due to "elements indicating abusive proceedings".</p> <p>The third safeguard is provision that courts may accept third party intervention in SLAPP proceedings by specialised NGOs on behalf of defendants.  The role of the NGO may be either to provide support to the defendant or to provide relevant information to the court.</p> <p>The fourth safeguard is, if the court or tribunal concludes that the proceedings are "abusive", it must have power to impose "effective, proportionate and dissuasive" penalties on the SLAPP plaintiff and to order the SLAPP plaintiff to bear the full costs of the proceedings.  These should include the full costs of legal representation incurred by the SLAPP defendant, unless such costs are excessive.</p> <p>The fifth safeguard is that any SLAPP defendant who has suffered harm as a result of the SLAPP proceedings must be able to claim and obtain full compensation for that harm.</p> <p>Under the sixth safeguard it is proposed that courts and tribunals in any member state would also have power to refuse to recognise or enforce a judgment of a non-EU state if it arises in proceedings which, under the law of the member state, would have been considered a SLAPP.  Member states are also required to ensure that if an abusive SLAPP action is brought in a non-EU country against a defendant domiciled in a member state, that defendant may seek compensation in their member state of domicile for damages and costs incurred in the third country proceedings, irrespective of the SLAPP plaintiff&rsquo;s country of domicile.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Many of these procedural safeguards are already available, to a greater or lesser extent, in our legal system.</p><p>It is important to note that the proposed directive is limited to matters of a civil or commercial nature; it does not cover any criminal proceedings.  In addition, for the proposed directive to apply, the proceedings, in accordance with the treaty legal base, must have "cross-border implications".  Under the proposal, such implications are taken to exist where either or both of the parties is not domiciled in the same member state as the court seized of the proceedings; the "act of public participation" against which the court proceedings have been taken "is relevant to more than one Member State" - for example, statements or activities in respect of cross-border pollution, or allegations of cross-border money-laundering; or the plaintiff, or connected entities, has initiated concurrent or previous proceedings against the same or associated defendants in another member state.</p><p>Finally, it is useful to mention how some key terms are defined in the proposed directive.</p><p>"Public participation" is defined as any statement or activity "expressed or carried out in the exercise of the right to freedom of expression and information on a matter of public interest", along with preparatory, supporting or assisting activities.</p><p>A "matter of public interest" is defined as any matter which affects the public to such an extent that it may legitimately take an interest in it, in areas such as public health, safety, the environment, climate or enjoyment of fundamental rights; activities of a person or entity in the public eye or of public interest, which does not extend to satisfying curiosity about a person's private life; allegations of corruption, fraud or criminality; activities aiming to fight disinformation; and matters under public consideration or review by a legislative, executive or judicial body, or any other public official proceedings.</p><p>"Manifestly unfounded" proceedings are not defined by the proposal.  The Commission considers this as a term that is recognised in member states' legal systems and can be interpreted and applied by national judges at their discretion.</p><p>"Abusive proceedings", in this context, are defined as proceedings that are "fully or partially unfounded and have as their main purpose to prevent, restrict or penalize public participation".  According to the proposal, such proceedings typically involve litigation tactics used in bad faith, such as delaying proceedings, causing disproportionate costs to the defendant in the proceedings or forum shopping, and are often combined with threats, intimidation or harassment.</p><p>In Ireland the issue of SLAPPs has already been considered in the Report of the Review of the Defamation Act 2009, which the Government approved for publication on 1 March of this year.  That report noted that while the term "SLAPPs" was not explicitly used in submissions to the public consultation on reform of the Defamation Act 2009, a number of submissions from journalists' representative bodies and from the print and broadcast media raised fears and concerns that echo those typical of SLAPP cases.  One of the key recommendations of the report was to introduce "a new 'anti-SLAPP' mechanism, to allow a person to apply to court for summary dismissal of ... proceedings that he/she believes are a SLAPP".  The Minister for Justice has indicated that she is preparing an amending defamation Bill to give effect to the recommendations of the report.  The proposal for a directive, however, applies both more widely, in referring to all civil proceedings and not only defamation law, and more narrowly, in referring only to proceedings that have "cross-border implications".</p><p>This is clearly an important proposal.  Subject to approval by the Seanad and the D&aacute;il, it appears desirable for Ireland to opt into the proposal at this stage, before its adoption, in order to ensure that we can participate fully in the Council's deliberations and that the final text of the directive takes full account of our own legal systems.  I therefore recommend the motion to the House and ask that Senators support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1696" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#VV00200"><p>I was where the Cathaoirleach is now when the Minister of State arrived.  Our business had gone a bit ahead of schedule.</p> <p>This is a very important proposed EU directive and Government motion and, on behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party, I support it.  The Minister of State is here on behalf of the Minister, Deputy McEntee, and the Minister of State, Deputy James Browne.  The directive is being brought through the Houses, as the Minister of State outlined, because motions on directives brought forward need the approval of the Oireachtas.</p> <p>The Minister of State has given a comprehensive speech, and there would be no necessity or value to my repeating or adding to everything he said.  I have 12 pages of briefing notes; he probably read out about ten of them.  It is an important directive the purpose of which is to protect individuals and bodies and, as the Minister of State highlighted, journalists and human rights defenders in their work.  It seeks to stop people throwing money at lawsuits and so on in order to silence genuine, valid concerns people may have when dealing with legislation or proposals in public participation on matters of public interest.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerry Horkan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2476"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2476&amp;amp;pid=GerryHorkan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->On behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il group, I support the proposed EU directive.  The Minister of State has comprehensively outlined what needs to be done.  I support the motion and urge other Senators to do the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#WW00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  On behalf of the Fine Gael Party, I concur wholeheartedly with Senator Horkan's remarks.  It is critically important that we send a message from the House that we support this important legislation.  It is extraordinary that it has to be introduced in the context of what is happening in many parts of the world.  It is about safeguarding the rights of journalists as well as safeguarding those who promote and work for human rights.  In a wider context, there is an absolute need to rebut the argument being peddled by some people that we have too many NGOs in this country.  A democracy must always have voices that promote and advocate on behalf of different people, groups and organisations whatever their point of view may be.  Some say that we have too many NGOs and people promoting X over Y.  When one sees basic freedoms being curbed or curtailed across the world, there is a need for us in this Parliament and democracy to stand up and be that voice.</p> <p>As Senator Horkan said, the Minister of State has given a clear explanation of what is required of us, thus I will not delay the House any further.  It is important for us in this House, the European Union and beyond to send a collective, collaborative message.  It is about ensuring the rights that we have won and achieved in the western world are made clear to other parts of the world and that we do not regress and go backwards.  I support the proposed directive.</p> <p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the Chamber.  He said that the Minister is looking at amending the defamation Bill, a subject about which we can debate another time.  However, today is an important day and I am happy to support the motion on behalf of the Fine Gael group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#WW00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it agus gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis as an &oacute;r&aacute;id chuimsitheach a thug s&eacute; don Seanad.  Taca&iacute;m leis an r&uacute;n at&aacute; os &aacute;r gcomhair.  I welcome the Minister of State to the House and, like my colleagues have done, thank him for the comprehensive speech he delivered.  There is not a great deal more that I could add in acknowledging the importance and, indeed, necessity for this motion to be agreed by both Houses.</p> <p>Senator Buttimer touched on the misuse of SLAPP in some instances not just against organisations but individuals who take a principled stand for human rights, equality and justice issues.  Not only does that place a huge financial burden on individuals in certain circumstances, but it also has the potential to create a chilling effect for people who want to continue in their campaigning and activism.  That is why I support the motion as others have.</p> <p>I know that some of my colleagues in the Lower House have a broader view on the directive.  They equally support it and will, no doubt, outline those considerations to the Minister of State when the motion comes before the D&aacute;il.  I thank him for being in the Chamber and I welcome and support the motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#WW00400"><p>The Minister of State is welcome to the Chamber.  The points have been well covered by my fellow Senators.  I note the Minister of State said that he would monitor the situation to ensure there is no unintended consequence of this initiative.  It is not so much a question of whether to SLAPP or not to SLAPP; it is a question of what a SLAPP is and could it ever be used in a situation that may be inappropriate.  On the balance of advantages versus disadvantages, I believe the motivation behind this directive is well intended.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is to protect people who may not have a bottomless pit of funds so that their voices can be heard in court.  It is to protect those who may not be able to withstand a deliberate assault - metaphorically speaking - causing a chilling effect.  While I am happy to support the motion, it is something we should continue to monitor on a regular basis.  There are mechanisms in place in our courts.  If there is a particular serial litigant we can seek an Isaac Wunder order.  There is a long-established right to go to court on notice to the other side with an application that it is bound to fail if a matter is vexatious with no grounds whatsoever.  The motion is something I will keep an open mind on.  I believe the intention is good.  The remarks of the Minister of State on behalf of the Minister for Justice were well made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#XX00200"><p>I thank the Senators.  I listened carefully to their comments.  I thank them very much considering what we are doing.  We are trying to prevent people abusing the law to intimidate or bully individuals who engage in public participation.  If we have a public consultation or a forum open to the public they should not be threatened with defamation actions, the power of expensive lawyers or threats of being made insolvent.  This is so that we can have a fair procedure.  As one Senator pointed out, if this type of situation arises it could have a chilling effect and a situation where people did not want to go ahead or participate in a particular forum for fear of being sued in return.</p> <p>I take on board the comments of Senator Martin that we need to be careful there are no unintended consequences and that a genuine contribution from somebody in a public consultation is not judged to be a SLAPP or used in the opposite way to which it was intended.  One of the reasons we propose that Ireland opts-in at an earlier stage to this Commission proposal is that we can bring along our own body of law and negotiate and make sure our own Defamation Act fits in with what is happening rather than waiting for it to pass through the Council and the European Parliament and opting in at the very last stage.  This is the intention.  As Senator Martin said, we have options in Irish law, such as an Isaac Wunder order which is for vexatious litigation.  We want to see how this fits in with what is being proposed in the EU.  Not everybody has the same common or civil law jurisdiction or system.  I thank the Senators very much and the Cathaoirleach for facilitating the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.151" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.152" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 3.58 p.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 4.19 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 3.58 p.m. and resumed at 4.19 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.153" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#BBB00100">EirGrid, Electricity and Turf (Amendment) Bill 2022: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.154" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#BBB00300"><p>I am very glad to be here to introduce this Bill.  It is an important part of the</p><p>Government's response to increasing concerns with regard to security of electricity supply, with particular regard to the identified generation capacity gap over the coming winters.  It is in this regard that we produced the Bill.  I am glad to be opening the debate today and to be able to set the context for the actions to be taken on foot of this Bill.  I will describe the sections of the Bill and, having regard to its main provisions, set out some background as to why they are urgently needed.  My overarching message is that while the provisions outlined in this Bill are part of a broader package of measures, it is critical to put the Bill and its measures into place before summer recess. I seek permission to achieve that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I will discuss the generation capacity gap that the provisions in this Bill seek to address, along with outlining how the measures in it will support our security of supply as we transition to up to 80% renewable electricity by 2030.  I will reaffirm the urgency of the Bill to maintain a secure electricity supply for customers.  I will also outline its necessity in helping to protect customers against increasing electricity costs through the establishment of a process to allow for the public service obligation, PSO, to be credited as a benefit to electricity customers when the Commission for Regulation of Utilities, CRU, calculates a negative PSO. </p><p>On the factors affecting security of electricity supply, Senators will appreciate that we in Ireland face additional pressures due to our geographical location, low levels of interconnection with other countries, fossil fuel dependency and the smaller scale of the Irish market compared to many other European countries.  However, the most immediate factor affecting security of electricity supply in Ireland over the coming years is a potential generation capacity shortfall that was identified in EirGrid's all-island generation capacity statement published in September 2021.  This potential capacity shortfall arises in periods of peak demand when there are low levels of wind generation and interconnection available to the system.  The shortfall has arisen largely due to non-delivery of previously contracted capacity, increasing electricity demand and the increasing unreliability of existing plant.  The CRU has statutory responsibility to monitor and take measures necessary to ensure the security of electricity supply.  It is assisted in this role by EirGrid, Ireland's electricity transmission system operator.</p><p>On 7 June 2022, the CRU directed EirGrid to procure, using the most expeditious means available, approximately 450 MW of additional generation capacity from the winter of 2023-24 to the winter of 2025-26 to ensure a secure electricity supply for that period.  This temporary generation capacity will be in place until more enduring capacity can be delivered through regular market auctions.  The specific nature of this CRU direction requires the legislation before the House to ensure EirGrid can fulfil the direction as required.  This legislation includes supporting provisions for EirGrid in its role of securing the temporary generation units with equipment manufacturers and contracting for its deployment and operation by electricity generators and ensures the necessary financial support can be given to EirGrid to achieve the objective.  In this regard, I will bring a Supplementary Estimate next week to provide for the capital funding for EirGrid to place orders on the generation units required. </p><p>While this legislation facilitates security of supply through the provision of temporary generation, which ensures there is sufficient reserve capacity on the system to enable security of supply in peak periods when there is low wind generation and interconnection available, it is important to note that this will not impede any of our plans for renewables, interconnection, batteries, demand side response or energy efficiency.  Having this reserve capacity available allows EirGrid to have more confidence in scheduling network outages for new connections to the grid such as new wind and solar farms from the recently announced renewable electricity support scheme 2, RESS 2, list of projects, without jeopardising security of electricity supply.  This is very much in keeping with Government policy of delivering up to 80% renewable electricity by 2030. </p><p>Further to this, the Bill also provides for an increased borrowing limit for both EirGrid and Bord na M&oacute;na.  This will enable EirGrid to invest in the Celtic interconnector with France and other necessary investments to ensure our grid can accommodate up to 80% renewables by 2030.  The Bill also enables Bord na M&oacute;na to further develop its brown to green strategy and deliver new </p><p>investments to former peat harvesting regions. </p><p>To ensure the security of our electricity supply over the coming years, it is vital that the legislation be passed prior to the D&aring;il rising in order to make sure certain measures can be initiated in time, in particular that EirGrid from July 2022 can acquire electricity generation, sell and transfer the electricity generation plant to electricity generators and enter into agreements with electricity generators for the operation of the electricity generation plant.  I emphasise the urgent nature of this situation and reiterate that it is of paramount importance that the legislation be passed immediately. </p><p>Crucially, as well as providing for the provision of temporary generation capacity for the coming years, the Bill establishes a process to allow for the PSO to be credited as a benefit to electricity customers when the CRU calculates a negative PSO.  This provision will enable the delivery of savings to electricity customers.  Under current legislation, the PSO levy is charged to all final electricity customers to fund renewable electricity generation schemes in support of national policy objectives.  The RESS has introduced a two-way floating premium, which means if the wholesale market price is higher than their bid price the supplier pays moneys back to the customers through the PSO mechanism.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The existing legislation, however, does not provide for crediting a negative PSO levy.</p><p>In recognition of the rising cost of living and of the impact on households and businesses of increasing energy bills, the Government approved, on 14 June 2022, legislative amendments to enable PSO payments to be credited as a benefit to electricity customers when the Commission for the Regulation of Utilities, CRU, calculates a negative PSO.  This legislation is required in order for the CRU to be able to direct that the PSO can be credited to customers over the period from quarter 4 of 2022 to quarter 3 of 2023.  This credit has been provisionally calculated by the CRU to be in the order of &euro;75 for the average domestic customer.  The CRU is expected to make its final decision on the credit amounts later in July.  It is vitally important in these times of rapidly rising energy costs that we allow passage of this Bill to deliver this saving to households and businesses and, in particular, financially vulnerable residential consumers. </p><p>I will devote my remaining remarks to the subject matter of the Bill.  It is designed to enable EirGrid to take certain emergency measures, including acquiring electricity generation plant and entering into agreements with electricity generators regarding electricity generation plant, for the purpose of ensuring and protecting security of supply, pursuant to a direction of the CRU.  For that purpose, the Bill provides for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to give financial support to enable EirGrid to take certain measures.  The Bill also increases the borrowing limit of EirGrid through an amendment of the Electricity Regulation (Amendment) (EirGrid) Act 2008.  The Bill includes an amendment of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999 to provide for payments to final customers of certain benefits relating to compliance with a public service obligation.  The Bill also increases the borrowing limit of Bord na M&oacute;na, through an amendment of the Turf Development Act 1998. </p><p>I will provide a section-by-section summary of the Bill.  There are 14 sections.  Section 1 is a standard provision which provides for definitions.  Section 2 sets out that expenses incurred by the Minister in the administration of the Act are to be paid out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas, to the extent sanctioned by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p><p>Section 3 provides that EirGrid shall take urgent measures, as required, under a direction from the CRU to ensure security of electricity supply, including acquiring electricity generation plants, selling and transferring such plant to an electricity generator, and entering into an agreement with an electricity generator to operate the electricity generator plant.  It provides for the operation of generation plant in line with the CRU direction and for operations to cease upon the fulfilment of the direction or 31 March 2027, whichever is earlier.</p><p>Section 4 prevents EirGrid from operating a generation plant acquired by it pursuant to a direction from the CRU and provides for it to enter an agreement with an electricity generator to sell the emergency generation plant and undertake its operation.  This section also ensures that the electricity generator may only receive reimbursement of reasonable costs and a reasonable return as may be approved by the CRU for undertaking this activity, and that upon termination of the agreement, the electricity generator shall dispose of the electricity generation plant in an arm's length transaction in accordance with any direction of the commission.  This section includes a provision that in all circumstances EirGrid shall be paid the full price of the electricity generating plant and any profit received on a sale of the plant by the electricity generator. </p><p>Section 5 provides for obligations on EirGrid to take measures, as required, under a direction from the CRU to ensure security of electricity supply and ensures that EirGrid obtains no benefit other than reimbursement of reasonable costs and a reasonable return as may be approved by the CRU. </p><p>Section 6 ensures that all functions performed under this Act shall be in compliance with laws and treaties of Ireland and the European Union.</p><p>Section 7 provides for the Minister to provide financial support to EirGrid in an agreed form and manner, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  It obliges EirGrid to use financial support for the purposes of complying with a direction of the CRU only, and that the use of any income or revenue received in connection with the agreement with electricity generators shall only be used for the purpose provided or the purpose of making distributions to its shareholders as determined by the directors of EirGrid.</p><p>Section 8 provides for a quarterly report by EirGrid to the CRU.  </p><p>Section 9 provides for the CRU to make further directions to EirGrid, the public electricity supplier or an electricity generator to address the temporary electricity emergency, and where such a direction is not complied with, to apply to the High Court to make such order as it thinks fit.</p><p>Section 10 provides for the CRU to report upon progress to the Minister no later than 31 October 2026 and for the Minister to make an order to extend the period for which the emergency generation can be operated by one year, upon approval by both Houses of the Oireachtas.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ossian Smyth:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=OssianSmyth&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Section 11 provides for an increased borrowing limit for EirGrid of up to &euro;3 billion.</p><p>Section 12 provides for the amendment of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999 to allow for PSO payments to be credited as a benefit to electricity customers.  Calculation of the annual PSO levy is a matter for the CRU.  On 14 June, the CRU issued a draft determination that gives the potential for a refund of about &euro;75 for the average domestic customer with the passage of this enabling amendment.</p><p>Section 13 provides for the amendment of the Turf Development Act 1998 to increase Bord na M&oacute;na's borrowing limit to &euro;650 million.</p><p>Section 14 provides for the Short Title and commencement of the Act.</p><p>I have outlined the main provisions of this emergency measures Bill and provided additional detail on the sections.  I hope this will be of assistance to Senators.  I look forward to an informed and meaningful debate and to working constructively with Senators on all sides of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#EEE00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  He could nearly take up full-time residence in the House.  This is the third or fourth time I have met him in the House today.  Fianna F&aacute;il welcomes this legislation, which will help protect the security of Ireland's electricity supply.  As the Minister of State outlined, the purpose of the Bill is to provide for emergency measures to ensure and protect the security of the supply of electricity, and for the giving of financial support by the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to EirGrid to enable it to take certain measures.  The Minister of State may have outlined some of those.  They include acquiring electricity generation plant, to provide for EirGrid entering into agreements with electricity generators regarding electricity generation plant, and to increase the amount of money EirGrid and Bord na M&oacute;na may borrow, which, as the Minister of State mentioned, is &euro;3 billion and &euro;650 million, respectively.  That is very important.</p> <p>We have had the closure of Shannonbridge and Lanesborough power stations in my part of the country.  We have accepted the change and know it has to happen.  We want the pace of that change to increase in our area.  I do not know what the intention is with regard to those power stations but I believe they will be dismantled.  We need to put some other structure in place there.  It might not provide as much employment.  We are going from a brown to green economy there.  That is acceptable.  Whatever structure is put in place, it must take account of the needs of the local communities.</p> <p>This legislation provides for payments to customers of certain benefits relating to the public service obligation levy and other related matters, including a requirement that EirGrid shall provide a report to the CRU every quarter, or more frequently as the CRU may require.  The measures in the Bill were announced in mid-June as part of a wider package of measures to help mitigate rising household electricity bills.</p> <p>It is appropriate we are discussing this Bill at this time.  In recent years the public and industry have been looking over their shoulders in terms of having enough electricity supply to bring us over the winter period.  That concern still exists although, in fairness to the Government and the Minister, that has calmed down a bit.  It is a concern for people in that, unless we rectify the position and get the situation under control, we could be in trouble.  Nobody wants to see lights or power having to be switched off.  We must avoid that at all costs.</p> <p>There is great opportunity for wind and solar energy development if we handle this properly.  I meet farmers every week at my constituency clinic and they all want to get involved in solar panel development.  They are willing to do that.  That is good for climate change.  It is one sector where farmers will play their part.  Farmers are becoming involved in it.  In some cases there might be more controversy about wind turbines.  When they were first put up in my part of the country, there was all hell to pay, but that seems to have calmed down because of the community involvement, which involved Coillte at the time.  It is now Bord na M&oacute;na and the ESB, and that system is working out well.  There are many farmers in rural areas who would like to get involved in solar panel development and that has to be good.</p> <p>Section 3 provides that EirGrid shall take urgent measures, as required, under direction from the CRU, to ensure security of electricity supply, including acquiring electricity generation plants, selling and transferring such plants to an electricity generator, and entering into an agreement with an electricity generator to operate the electricity generator plant.  It provides for the operation of the generation plant in line with CRU direction and for operation to cease upon the fulfilment of the direction or 31 March 2027, whichever is the earlier.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Eugene Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2444"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2444&amp;amp;pid=EugeneMurphy&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Section 4 prevents EirGrid from operating generation plants acquired by it pursuant to a direction from the CRU, and provides for it to enter into an agreement with an electricity generator to sell the emergency generation plant and undertake its operation.</p><p>Fianna F&aacute;il welcomes this legislation.  We will support it.  What we do with decommissioned power stations, from an economic perspective, has been a major issue in my part of the country.  We all know we have to change, however.  Security of supply will be the issue we need to sort out.  Rather than have people worry about whether they will have electricity supply in the months ahead, the Government, which is in control, must ensure this is properly done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#FFF00200"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome to the debate on this very important legislation.  As my colleague, Senator Murphy, has said, the issue of energy security and supply is one that will be critical.  The backdrop to this debate is the words and comments of the European Commissioner, Ms Mair&eacute;ad McGuinness, who raised the prospect and possibility of fuel rationing in the winter.  Regardless of whether she is right, there is an obligation and need to have that discussion to assure people in Ireland of our energy security.</p> <p>Senator Murphy correctly said there is a balance to be achieved in terms of the move from dependency on fossil fuels to a new type of energy security and supply.  We have to be conscious that the majority of our gas supply is coming via a pipeline from the UK and mindful that we do not, as far as I know, have any gas storage facilities or a LNG terminal in this country.  This potentiality raises all sorts of outcomes of which we must be cognisant.  The publication date of the report on energy security supply is imminent or may be due.  CEPA was commissioned to do that report and to be fair to the Minister of State, the Minister, Deputy Ryan, and other Ministers, it is a priority for Government.  I accept and appreciate that.</p> <p>I will raise the issue of the Barryroe field, which was raised at the annual general meeting of Providence Resources last week.  The company may submit an application to drill a new well off the Cork coast.  Providence is telling us this could assist with our energy security.  I hope the Department will engage with Providence on the Barryroe field.  I have no vested interest in this matter, other than wanting to ensure a continuity of supply.  We benefited greatly in Cork, during what I accept was a different time, from the Kinsale field.  Natural gas from Kinsale benefited the modernisation of our country in the context of energy supply and security.</p> <p>It would be remiss of me not to refer to the decision of Electric Ireland to raise prices for the fourth time in a year.  The ESB has increased the price of electricity by 11% and the price of gas by 29%.  This is the second time the company has raised prices in 2022.  There is a question mark around whether the ESB will increase prices again.  What is its rationale beyond what the company has already done?  Why are price increases being countenanced given that we are in an energy crisis?  I ask Electric Ireland and the ESB to explain the reasoning for these increases to the people of Ireland.  I say that in the context of the measures taken by the Government to mitigate the higher costs of energy being incurred by people.</p> <p>The retrofitting scheme is not necessarily part of this debate but it is important that we look at how it is working.  We also need to look at public transport fares.  I listened to the discussion on "The Late Debate" the other night when the eminent commentator, Mr. Gerard Howlin, spoke about the Green Party in Government having a clear focus and clear policy objectives.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->All of us, in the context of the modal shift in the car which has been assisted, unfortunately, by the war in Ukraine and the energy crisis, are looking to public transport.  We all accept that public fare reductions should be extended.  We all welcome the commitment of the Government to the BusConnects programme, whether it is Dublin or Cork.</p><p>There are contentious issues around that which we accept and we can park that for a moment, but it is important that every effort be made to have public transport fares as low as possible.  I know the Minister of State, Deputy Smyth, is very committed to that.  In Cork, we now have a new 24-hour bus service which is changing behaviour more than one could ever imagine.  I am fortunate to be on a 24-hour bus route which is absolutely brilliant.  I have spoken to people in the last week or so, when I have been out doing leaflet drops and meeting people, who are making decisions about what journeys they will take, how they will take them and where they will go.  That has a potential knock-on effect in a social aspect as well.</p><p>We are coming to the end of the leaving certificate and heading into the issue of school holidays and third level holidays.  I hope that as part of the budgetary process and academic term, we try to make the fare reduction in terms of Dublin Bus, Bus &Eacute;ireann, Luas, Go-Ahead Ireland, Iarnr&oacute;d &Eacute;ireann, Commuter and DART journeys as great as possible or to make fares free.</p><p>We spoke about university education being monumental in terms of the Niamh Bhreathnach-John Bruton Government or Donogh O'Malley with free education at second level.  The potential legacy this Government will leave is in terms of assisting passengers, not just with the cost burden in the short to immediate term of the energy crisis and inflation, but in that modal shift.  If we want to be serious about incentivising people to move from the car to public transport, Government must be proactive and encourage and assist people, be it with the Leap card or the issue of scheduling and availability of buses or light rail.  I am very optimistic about the future of public transport from a Cork perspective with BusConnects, notwithstanding some of the potential issues we will have in the future in terms of land and bus lanes and so on.  It is about ensuring that we give people the opportunity to make that conscious decision to move away from dependency on fossil fuels.</p><p>The issue of energy security and supply is concerning people.  When one hears someone such as Commissioner McGuinness making that comment, it forces people to sit up and think.  I commend the Minister of State for the work he is doing in his Department, along with other Ministers.  Measures are being taken by the Government which are helping and we should continue to take them.  I look forward to and hope that we can have a debate before the summer recess on the budgetary process, because it is critical.  The Government has differing views on a myriad of issues but, in particular, on our own energy security.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#GGG00200"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  It would be remiss of me not to point out the rushed manner in which this Bill is being brought before us.  The Department sought for the pre-legislative scrutiny to be waived.  No general scheme of the Bill was published.  There was no regulatory impact assessment.  It was rushed through the D&aacute;il in two sittings and today it will be rushed through this House in one sitting.  We are being asked to grant a waiver to the constitutional provisions against rushed legislation, to allow for an earlier signature by the President.  On top of all of that, we had the issue last week where the Government used a procedural loophole to pass related legislation by amending the Circular Economy, Waste Management (Amendment) and Minerals Development (Amendment) Bill 2022.  I must register my concern that this is not the way in which we should be passing legislation.</p> <p>I listened with interest to Senator Buttimer talk about the need for a LNG terminal.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have to be honest about why we are passing this legislation.  It is an emergency measure.  No one wants the lights to go off in the winter.  However, the main aim of the Bill is to allow EirGrid to procure 450 MW of backup electricity generation capacity to ensure we have enough electricity to meet demand over the coming years.  This mismatch in electricity supply and demand is a direct result of the failed, incoherent policies of Governments, of which Fine Gael has been a part, for the past ten years.  It is staggering that we are in a situation where emergency legislation is being passed in 2022 because we are at risk of the lights going out.  We all know the elephant in the room is that rising demand for electricity continues to outstrip the pace of generation and the extra demand is coming from data centres, whose demand increased by 144% between 2015 and 2020.  The insatiable demand is, of course, the natural outworking of Fine Gael policy.  For years, Fine Gael was open about encouraging data centres to set up in Ireland and rolled out the red carpet for them.  That is why it is disappointing that, having followed the debate in the D&aacute;il, it seems the Green Party is refusing to accept that fact.  It is not the Green Party's legacy.  It is a Fine Gael Legacy that the Green Party has unfortunately inherited.  We have to accept that the reason we have to pass emergency legislation is that demand from data centres is outstripping the pace of generation.</p><p>The other factor that has led to this legislation is the failure of the CRU to procure generation capacity.  The commission has serious questions to answer in that regard.  Every time Members table parliamentary questions to the Minister about the CRU, they are reminded that the CRU is an independent regulator.  The CRU must be held accountable and to that end, I welcome that the Joint Committee on Environment and Climate Action has agreed to my recommendation that the CRU be brought before the committee on a quarterly basis.  The CRU is accountable to the committee and has serious questions to answer in regard to the procurement of 200 MW of generation capacity.</p><p>The Bill prioritises the CRU in directing EirGrid to facilitate gas-powered generation.  Where is the priority for a demand-side strategy?  According to the response to a Commencement matter, we will see it by the end of this year, which means it will not come into effect until 2023.  A demand-side strategy would allow households to be rewarded for reducing their electricity demand.</p><p>Where is the biomethane strategy whereby we could use waste to generate gas fuels instead of bringing in fossil fuel gas?  Where is the EirGrid software update that would recognise battery storage?  Across the water, multi-hour and multi-day battery storage is displacing gas-powered generators, whereas our grid does not even recognise battery storage.  Prioritising gas-powered generation to meet the demand of the energy shortfall skews our priorities.</p><p>Major questions need to be answered about the impact on households.  We are halfway through 2022 and there is still no energy poverty strategy.  I encourage everyone to come to the briefing in the audiovisual room at 10 a.m. tomorrow to hear about the impact of energy poverty across the whole of society.  The last energy poverty strategy lapsed in 2019.  The Bill shifts more costs on to households, although by how much is unclear.  The Minister outlined in the D&aacute;il how the full cost for households will not be known until the contracts are finally worked out.  A figure of &euro;40 per household, per annum was put to him.  Will that figure be confirmed today?  We were told it would be less than &euro;40 but can that be guaranteed, so that we are not adding to people's household bills?  With this legislation, is the Minister asking households to write a blank cheque?  What protections are in place to prevent costs being borne by the most vulnerable consumers?</p><p>The Minister also outlined in the D&aacute;il that &euro;350 million is to be transferred to EirGrid from Vote 29 - Environment, Climate and Communications, by means of a Supplementary Estimate.  Will the Minister of State outline the exact budget lines he proposes to take from to fund this transfer to EirGrid?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Lynn Boylan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=LynnBoylan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The last time we had such a situation with a Vote was regarding the underspend on retrofits.  Is the underspend in the Department coming from broadband, cybersecurity or An Post?</p><p>The Bill will amend the Turf Development Act 1998 to increase Bord na M&oacute;na&rsquo;s borrowing capacity to &euro;650 million, which we are told will help it fund its expansion into renewable energy.  This is welcome given the urgent climate crisis.  We want to see the State, particularly through semi-State bodies, lead the way on investment in renewable energy to ensure the State retains as much ownership as possible of our energy production capacity.  I have concerns about this section and will return to them on Committee Stage.  I also express my concerns about how Bord na M&oacute;na is treating the communities of the area in which the mid-Shannon wilderness park is proposed to go ahead.  The company gave a commitment to those communities that it would create a wilderness park when it had stopped harvesting the turf.  It now seems to be going back on that commitment, which does not bode well for a just transition.</p><p>I raise once again my concerns about the sort of risk assessment that has been done in terms of procuring gas-fired generators, the Energy Charter Treaty and the possible exposure of the State if it decides to fast-track the running down of these gas generators.  If we get renewables on stream quick enough, and with demand reduction and battery storage, we may not need gas-fired generators as much as we think we will.  Will we be liable to foot the bill of what the companies think their future profits will be?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" speakername="Annie Hoey" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#JJJ00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House.  I echo previous speakers' statements that it is frustrating that, as per usual ever summer, there is a rushing through of all Stages of Bills.  I do not know why that seems to be necessary.  The debate on the Bill could have been done over two separate sessions.  To hear all Stages in one or two hours is poor practice, especially when no pre-legislative scrutiny is provided for this legislation.</p> <p>The main purpose of the Bill is to ensure we have sufficient electricity generation in place from winter 2022 through to 2026.  We understand EirGrid will then sell and transfer that capacity to an electricity generator and enter into an operating agreement.  This emergency legislation is supposed to last for only three years, but we are investing an enormous sum of money in the building and preparation of something that is for three years.  Is it reasonable to think that after three years we will say that is enough of that and we will have figured the whole situation out, or is it a Trojan horse in that we will have to rely on these beyond the three-year agreement?</p> <p>It certainly raises questions as to how we have found ourselves so exposed to supply shortages and why this legislation has only been brought forward now.  My colleague, Deputy Bacik, raised this and other such matters during the Order of Business in the other House.  She raised the fact it is not good legislative practice to see legislation being rushed through.</p> <p>It is often said the current crisis is because of the war in Ukraine, but we cannot wholly blame Ukraine or the rapid increase of gas prices.  Clearly the war has exacerbated energy security and supply issues internationally, but the current crises in this country is as a result of a failure to plan long term for the transition to renewable energy sources.  Throughout last summer and autumn, the pressure on the electricity supply grew due to the growing demands from data centres, which the Houses have debated, as well as the transition from dirtier fuels such as coal, and balancing the needs to support the generation of wind power.  All of this happened before the war in Ukraine, so it is not feasible to say it is the only reason this is happening.</p> <p>The CRU stated in its announcement that these emergency measures were needed due to the increased risk of older generators becoming unavailable and ageing out.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Annie Hoey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AnnieHoey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Obviously, the older generators are not as efficient as the newer ones and have higher carbon emissions.  We in the Labour Party, however, are concerned that the measures will lock in new fossil fuel generation capacity.  I know this is an emergency but gas is a fossil fuel and when we are supposed to be transitioning away from fossil fuels, I am concerned, and my colleagues in the Lower House have expressed this concern, about this potentially locking us into new fossil fuel generation capacity.  Once we go down the route of getting the transitional system operating to source emergency extra capacity, there is the potential it will become the default option if the electricity generation market does not operate properly.<br/><br/>The central question about these generators is what fuel they will run on.  As I said, there is a concern about enhancing our fossil fuel dependency.  Will EirGrid be told what it has to procure?<br/><br/>Another question is what the cost to the State of developing and running such generators will be.  I know others have stated, and reports have indicated, that the costs will be recouped from customers over a three-year period, but is the State putting up the capital spend in the first place?  The Minister of State might clarify where the &euro;350 million in capital funding for these generators is coming from.  A figure of &euro;400 million has been thrown around as being what is left in the annual budget.  If the &euro;350 million is coming from that, it is a fairly sizeable amount.<br/><br/>It is prudent to point out that this is happening at a time when energy companies are making extraordinary and unexpected profits due to the soaring prices of fossil fuels.  The Labour Party has called for a windfall tax on excessive profits as a measure that could and should be included in budget 2023.  We think the revenue raised could be used to fund additional climate mitigation and energy efficiency measures that would reduce our reliance on energy imports at a time when we see unprecedented insecurity of supply.  I recognise that is largely due to the war in Ukraine.<br/><br/>While we rush through this law in order that these new gas generators can be put in place this summer, it has not been adequately explained why the ESB, a publicly owned company, has previously pulled out of contracts to build a number of gas power plants.  There was extensive coverage of this in the <i>Business Post</i>, and the matter was raised in the D&aacute;il as well.  I do not know if the Minister of State has any comment to make as to why the ESB did that.  Now we find ourselves in an emergency, whereas the ESB potentially could have acted earlier.  The question remains as to whether that contributed to the supply crisis that underpins this legislation.  It is one of the reasons for the legislation and an expectation that we would have additional capacity for power generation but we can no longer rely on it.  Is it likely that the ESB will be one of the electricity generators contracted to operate this emergency supply?<br/><br/>Data centres were mentioned.  Is this new extra capacity really to allow for the development and operation of data centres?  There is no question about the gobbling up of our energy supplies that they are doing and will do into the future.  Many questions have been asked about data centres and their feasibility at a time when we are under enormous pressure not only on the grid but also to meet crucial emissions reduction targets.  Friends of the Earth has asked a number of important questions about what alternative measures have been considered such as demand-side management.<br/><br/>Another provision in the Bill is to increase the borrowing capacity of Bord na M&oacute;na to &euro;650 million to support its brown-to-green transition.  That is a really important programme.  As a previous speaker noted, the reference to turf in the Bill is unfortunate.  It puts the Bill into a different frame.  When I first saw the Title I was surprised to see the word &quot;turf&quot;.  We might all agree, especially considering that the aim of Bord na M&oacute;na is to move away from peat extraction, a move that is very much welcomed, that it would be useful if the Minister of State could outline what projects or investments this borrowing will support and if he could give a commitment that a strategy for Bord na M&oacute;na will be presented, maybe to the relevant Oireachtas committee.  My colleague, Deputy Bacik, has also made that request.  We have had an opportunity in Bord na M&oacute;na to build out a national wind energy and retrofitting company.  It is to be hoped that this will be State-led and could secure an energy transition to underpin a just transition.<br/><br/>We need to accelerate our delivery of onshore wind and solar energy.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Annie Hoey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=AnnieHoey&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Offshore wind energy will be the cornerstone of our future zero carbon electricity system.  I do not know if the Minister of State has any thoughts on how these two sources will align.  We need to accelerate the move to reduce our reliance on fossil fuels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#LLL00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I am grateful for the opportunity to say a few words on this important Bill.</p> <p>I, too, would like to voice my opinion on the rushing of this legislation.  It happens every summer and at Christmas time and I often wonder why.</p> <p>In relation to data centres, the biggest companies in the world are employing thousands of people in this country and the vast majority of them are producing data.  Why should we not have our fair share of the data centres producing data?  There is an onus on us in that regard.  Do we want all the Third World countries to have all the data centres?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#LLL00400"><p>We are a complete outlier.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#LLL00500"><p>We may well be but we have an obligation to have data centres here, particularly given the employment being generated in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#LLL00600"><p>Senator Burke does not need points of information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#LLL00700"><p>It is unbelievable that the Derrybrien wind farm is being dismantled.  The Minister should seek a derogation from the European Union in relation to the current fines until we reach maximum energy production in this country.  At a time when we are not self-sufficient in energy, it is daft that we are about to dismantle a wind farm at great cost and replace it with gas generation.  The Minister should, therefore, seek a derogation from the European Commission in relation to the fines.</p> <p>The Bill does not provide for joint ventures.  The Minister of State might be able to enlighten us on that.  There could be joint ventures between electricity generation companies all over Europe and the ESB is probably one of the best in the world.  These companies have a great deal of expertise.  Financial houses may also be interested in joint ventures at this point.  We have fallen behind, particularly along the west coast.  The opportunities that exist along the west coast are very slow to take hold.  There is something wrong when we only have one offshore wind energy plant in the country, which is on the east coast.  There is something  wrong in the Department with responsibility for energy that we have not made more ground, especially given the connections to the grid along the Shannon Estuary.  We do not have wave or wind energy installations along the west coast.  While it is probably difficult to do  this work along the west coast because of wind speeds and the depth of the Atlantic, drastic measures are needed.  I would like to see emergency legislation introduced in this area.  Most people would back emergency legislation to get that into production because it could be our oil for the future.  Similar to the Saudis who produce and export oil, given the assets we have along the west coast and on the mainland, we could generate electricity through wind and Atlantic waves.  That potential should be looked at in the shortest possible time.</p> <p>Much has been said about solar energy production for domestic purposes.  It has been championed by many people but there is an enormous difference between a fine sunny day and a cloudy day.  On a bad day, solar could generate only 20% of requirements.  Solar panel production should be supplemented with small wind turbines.  This area should be looked for domestic use.  The wind blows at night as well as during the day.  People have to switch on their lights at 4.30 p.m. in the wintertime here.  We could get into the manufacturing of small wind turbines.  In recent years, we have excelled in engineering.  We have McHale Farm Machinery and Malone Engineering in Mayo and a whole host of other engineering companies the length and breadth of the country.  If the Government sent a signal on energy-generating products, they would take off and be used.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#LLL00800"><p>I will respond to some of the interesting, insightful and valuable comments of Senators, for which I thank them.</p> <p>Senator Murphy referred to Shannonbridge and Lanesborough and stressed the importance of taking local communities into account.  One aspect of those locations is that they have very valuable grid connections, which could be used for renewable energy connections, storage or other energy infrastructure.  There has been a history of jobs in energy, whether in Bord na M&oacute;na or the ESB, in the midlands.  I hope the just transition funding will help.</p> <p>I am happy to hear that farmers are showing enthusiasm for solar energy.  It can be deployed quickly and helps with our energy resilience.  We do not have all our eggs in one basket when it comes to electricity.  The price of one fuel, whether gas or oil, can go up or there could be a day with no wind or sun, so we want a combination of energy sources.  We are heavily tilted towards wind and gas and we need more sources.  The more solar we can generate, the better.  Senator Burke referred to domestic solar energy, which is something we may be able to rapidly deploy.</p> <p>Senator Burke asked whether we can delay the dismantling of the Derrybrien wind farm or get it turned on again.  As the Senator will be aware, the matter was the subject of a legal decision which makes it difficult to do anything with it.  There is a fundamental problem with building wind farms on active bogs, as was done early on.  If there is any way we could do something with Derrybrien, I would be delighted rather than having to take the wind farm apart.</p> <p>The Senator also asked about the possibility of having small wind turbines along with domestic solar energy.  The orthodox view, certainly a few years ago, is that small wind turbines were too inefficient and it is always better to have larger wind turbines.  I am happy to look at this again to see if there has been any improvement in the technology.  It is another example of the need to have both sources, so that if one of them is not working, the other can be used.</p> <p>Senator Buttimer asked that every effort be made to ensure that public transport fares are as low as possible.  Our cuts to public transport fares were a cost-of-living measure.  They are also a positive measure.  Often, when trying to bring in climate action measures, they can be seen as negative if they are taxes or levies or ban certain things.  Having positive strong attractive measures helps people to get on board and can be the difference between deciding to use a bus or not.  I certainly see that with young people.  People under 24 are seeing that their public transport fares dropped dramatically and they are now making many journeys they otherwise would not have taken.  We need to look at that in the budget.  As the Senator said, there will be many voices seeking to have the public transport fare cuts, which were a temporary cost-of-living measure, maintained.</p> <p>Senator Boylan asked about a demand-side study.  I will find out if there are demand-side studies under way.  Anything that reduces demand is even better than something that generates renewable energy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM00100"><p>It is the demand-side strategy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM00200"><p>Yes, it is the demand-side strategy.  We have smart meters being rolled out around the country and that is part of demand-side strategy but I will see if there is a specific document on that.</p> <p>The Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine is working with my Department and the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications on a biomethane strategy at the moment and the green hydrogen strategy is due to be published very soon.</p> <p>Senator Boylan asked about the source of funds for voted expenditure additions this year to pay for the generators.  Approximately &euro;200 million is planned to be voted through, of which &euro;90 million comes from savings in the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications and the other &euro;110 million is from Exchequer funds, given we have buoyant tax returns this year.</p> <p>The PSO, levy was designed to subsidise wind farms and renewable energy.  The idea was that this renewable energy would impose an extra cost on the grid and this cost could be paid for by applying a small charge on everybody&rsquo;s bill.  Last year it was approximately &euro;50.  What was not envisaged was that renewable energy might save a person money in the future.  One of the problems sometimes when people are framing climate action or changes relating to the environment is that it is assumed that they are going to have a cost and that they are going to be negative.  As it turns out it is saving us money because oil and gas are so expensive.  There was no mechanism within the law and it had never been foreseen that the PSO levy could be negative.  It will be a negative amount of &euro;75 this year.  Everybody is going to be credited with &euro;75 on their bill.  One of the reasons to put this through as emergency legislation is so that money can be applied to people&rsquo;s bills as soon as possible.</p> <p>The Senator also asked whether the Energy Charter Treaty could prevent us from shutting down gas power and whether a risk analysis had been done on that.  I will have to come back to her with an answer to that question but it is a good one.</p> <p>Senator Hoey asked what happens to these generators after they are decommissioned.  The Bill provides that they will be sold after they are decommissioned.  I was also asked if this new capacity will lock in our dependence on these generators and what other fuel these generators use.  There will either be using natural gas or liquid distillate.  They are there to be used in emergencies; they are peaking power plants and are not to be used all of the time.  The idea is that if a number of other generators fail on the grid at the same time, we have that backup and do not have a blackout.  The entire purpose of this Bill is to prevent blackouts in the winter, particularly in the winter of 2023-24.  </p> <p>I was also asked whether the ESB could win the contracts to be the generator and whether it is likely to win it.  I do not know if it is likely but it can certainly apply like any other generator. </p> <p>There was a question about what way the Bill relates to turf.  It increases the borrowing capacity for Bord na M&oacute;na to get away from turf.  I take the point on that.  The fact is that it amends the Turf Development Act 1998 and that is the reason turf is in the Title.</p> <p>I was also asked whether this was being done for data centres.  Part of the reason for having to bring the Bill forward is increased demand from large electricity users, many of which are data centres, but many generators have also been failing and much of our generating capacity has had unexpected outages in the past.  With that, as they have become more unreliable, we need to cover for them.</p> <p>We have many of data centres but they are generating approximately 2% of our emissions and we have to take this in context.  It would not be a smart idea to double our data centre capacity or to throw in huge quantities of them when we are trying to do everything to ensure that we have good security of supply.  That is why the CRU issued its new guidance on data centres and said they should not be connected to the grid if there is any chance that they are going to impair our security of supply.  That applies, in particular, to Dublin.  EirGrid and ESB Networks are the bodies that grant access for a new data centre.  The centre must have planning permission first but it also needs a grid connection.  Those grid connections will not come about if there is any chance that they are going to impair the security of supply.</p> <p>As was pointed out by Senator Burke, this is a large area of the economy.  I believe there are 200,000 people employed in the pharma and tech sector.  Part of the infrastructure of those companies is data centres.  There is a significant number of people working in that area, which generated &euro;15 billion in corporate taxes last year.  This paid for a large portion of Government expenditure and it generated less than 2% of emissions.  While we need to ensure they do not expand quickly and put our grid at risk, because none of these companies would like it if there were blackouts and would like that even less than if we were not to give them data centres, we have to be realistic about this.  It is not the case that we can just say that all of our problems are about data centres and that if we get rid of data centres we would not have to engage in any climate action.  It is something that we need to watch carefully and to constrain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.177" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM00400"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM00500"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM00600"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.181" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM00700">EirGrid, Electricity and Turf (Amendment) Bill 2022: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.182" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sections 1 to 6, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.183" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>SECTION 7</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.184" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That section 7 stand part of the Bill."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM01000"><p>On the PSO levy being returned, could the levy be used so that people might be able to get a loan to put in solar panels?  Equally, could this money be offset by some of the electricity or generation companies so that this levy could go towards a loan to put in solar panels or some other form of green energy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM01100"><p>The Bill proposes to send the PSO levy directly into the utility accounts of the people and on to the bill as a credit of the electricity customers so they can use it for the whatever they want.  It will not be the case that the Government will take the PSO levy money and use it as a loan.  There will be a low-cost loan scheme for renewable energy, including solar panels and so on, later this year and that will be available to people who normally cannot get credit.  That is in the works.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM01200"><p>Why is this money going to be taken out if it is going to be put back into people's account?  Is that the way or how is it going to operate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM01300"><p>The PSO levy will come from the State and go on to the electricity bills of customers as a credit and they can use the money for whatever they want.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM01400"><p>How will the low-cost energy scheme operate on the ground?  Where does someone go and who will provide those low-cost loans?  Will this come from the generation or who will do it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM01500"><p>I understand that the loans are backed by the European Investment Bank and by the Ireland Strategic Investment Fund, which is the State bank.  The loans will be provided, presumably, through credit institutions, will be set at a low rate, of approximately 3% I believe, and these loans will be available to people who would not normally be able to get credit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM01600"><p>Would people be able to go to their local credit union and get the loan there?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#MMM01700"><p>Yes, and the purpose of the loan is to cover the portion of the retrofit that they cannot afford or get a grant for.  If a person has a retrofit job that costs &euro;20,000 and receives a grant of &euro;10,000, the other &euro;10,000 can be borrowed at a low rate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.193" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.194" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sections 8 to 12, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.195" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>SECTION 13</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#NNN00300"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 11, line 30, after &quot;&euro;650,000,000&quot; to insert the following:  	&ldquo;and such borrowings shall be used in line with principles of and for the purpose of facilitating a just transition&rdquo;.   </blockquote> <p>Senator Higgins sends her apologies as unfortunately she cannot be here today.  The amendment is quite simple.  We are increasing the borrowing limits given to Bord na M&oacute;na quite significantly.  This should be the case as we are in a climate emergency and in a cost-of-living crisis in which the price of energy is a real challenge for people.  This amendment is saying that the money that can be borrowed should be used for just transition measures.  We have heard many times in recent months that accelerating the development of renewable energy is key to reducing the cost of living.  We heard from the Minister that since the cost of oil and gas is so expensive, the cost of renewables has come down, which means they are paying back into the PSO, which sees households getting a rebate on that element of it.</p><p>However, we have not seen that acceleration or move towards a just transition in reality, and for ordinary people the crisis is getting worse.  For our planet the emergency is deepening every day.  In Ireland and throughout the world, energy companies are making huge profits at the moment on the backs of workers and the horrific war in Ukraine.  As a separate point, we should be taxing the windfall those companies are receiving and investing those revenues in a just transition for workers and communities.  We talk all the time now about how we are experiencing an unprecedented crisis when it comes to energy but the reality is it is not unprecedented; it is expected.  The tide is turning on fossil fuels but it needs to turn faster.  The Ukraine war has certainly brought it into focus and those who may have defended the use of fossil fuels as bridging fuels can no longer make those arguments.  They are not sustainable and do not belong in conversations about the future of energy supply.  This amendment places a clear obligation on Bord na M&oacute;na to use the money borrowed under this provision for just transition measures.  It is the direction we need to be moving towards, and indeed steps like this represent the ambition we need to end both the cost of living and the climate crises.</p><p>Those of us who sat in on the pre-legislative scrutiny on the climate Bill at the time were concerned that a just transition did not feature once in any reference in the Bill.  Eventually we got a small reference to it included.  In regard to just transition and its principles, the amendment we call for is to mirror Scotland where principles are enshrined in its climate Act.  The reality is that just transition and climate justice have to be factored into everything we are doing.  That is why with the stuff around the data centres, we have to put the facts on the record: 15% of electricity demand in Ireland is from data centres.  That figure is 1% in Germany, 6% in the Netherlands which is the closest to us.  We are a complete outlier.  When we talk about just transition and just transition principles, it makes it much harder for us to meet our climate targets but it is also putting a cost on the State to provide emergency generation to feed that insatiable demand.  It is important.  It might be 2% of our emissions but we are in the process of trying to bring down our emissions by 4% per year, so 2% is actually quite a large amount of our emissions.</p><p>The amendment is from Senator Higgins.  I would like to hear the Minister of State's response to it because it is a very simple amendment that says that if we are increasing the borrowing limits given to Bord na M&oacute;na, we should at least ensure that just transition is at the heart of borrowing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#NNN00400"><p>It is not proposed to specify in this legislation what the companies can use the increased borrowing limits for.  A borrowing limit increase for Bord na M&oacute;na will underpin the company's brown-to-green transition.  The company has ceased its peat harvesting activities and is accelerating the deployment of renewable energy, particularly in these former peat harvesting regions.  Just transition is already a part of Bord na M&oacute;na's brown-to-green strategy and is being implemented, as seen with the peatlands climate action project, which forms a crucial part of the Government's and Bord na M&oacute;na's just transition plans, securing employment for the 350 employees previously engaged in peat harvesting activities.</p> <p>Bord na M&oacute;na has commenced the enhanced decommissioning, rehabilitation and restoration scheme, the EDRRS programme.  The EDRRS will deliver a range of climate action benefits from greenhouse gas mitigation through reduced carbon emissions, carbon storage and accelerated carbon sequestration.  The scheme is expected to be completed by the end of 2025 and is expected to protect the storage of millions of tonnes of CO2 emissions, enhance biodiversity and provide employment opportunities as part of a just transition in the midlands.</p> <p>Bord na M&oacute;na is one of five partners in the LIFE IP Peatlands and People project with an overarching aim to be a climate action catalyst, connecting Ireland&rsquo;s peatlands, policies and people to support the realisation of a carbon neutral, low emission, climate resilient and environmentally sustainable society and economy by 2050, thereby playing a significant role in achieving Ireland&rsquo;s climate action plan targets, CAP 2019.  One of the pillars to the project is the just transition accelerator, which is an accelerator programme for systemic innovation focused on low carbon and circular economies.  Furthermore the shareholder letter of expectations, SLOE, for Bord na M&oacute;na is being updated to reflect its repositioning as a climate solutions company and the continued importance of a just transition.  On this basis I propose to reject the Senator&rsquo;s amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#NNN00500"><p>In the context of what Senator Burke said about access to revenue and funding, when it comes to retrofitting, we must make it simpler and more straightforward for people to fit solar panels to their family homes and businesses.  If we do that, it will be a bit like the comment on the issue of public transport in that we will get buy-in from people and people will move towards retrofitting and putting solar panels on the roofs of their houses if we make it easier.  There is a fear among people that the grant only covers a certain amount and they cannot get to the required amount.  That lacuna needs to be addressed.</p> <p>Senator Boylan referred to data centres.  My information is that data centres are not the source of the issue.  They did not use three quarters of the energy that was available to them.  Only 25% was used.  It is important we have that debate.  However, on the point Senator Boylan makes on the profits of the oil companies, and I think she will find a bit of agreement from me on this, President Biden in the US recently called on big oil in America to have less profit and more production.  There is a need for the oil companies to be honest in terms of what they supply and the prices they charge.  The issue of profits is one thing, but the oil companies have a moral duty to respond to the distribution of profits and the impact of the higher oil prices on people's pockets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1636" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#NNN00600"><p>Planning permission has held up many projects on account of various issues.  Nearly 40 years ago the Naas dual carriageway was held up because of a snail.  A wind farm near where I live was held up because of objections to the planning permission due to concerns that the red grouse would become extinct.  Objections to a bridge over the River Moy on the grounds of the freshwater pearl mussel caused a road connecting Ballina and Castlebar to be held up for years.  In the case of the wind farm where the red grouse was the problem, that wind farm went ahead.  The red grouse nest under the wind turbines.  Some sort of investigation, survey or report should be carried out in regard to the displacement of those species to see what has happened.  Have they come back because of infrastructure taking place?  Have those species that were supposed to be displaced come back?  I have asked for this on numerous occasions and have never got a response from any Department.  I believe they come back.  The freshwater pearl mussel is found in nearly every river now and many projects were held up over it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paddy Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1866"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1866&amp;amp;pid=PaddyBurke&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As I said, the red grouse has come back under the windmills when it was thought to have been displaced.  I am sure there are many other examples.  This is the responsibility of the National Parks and Wildlife Service.  It is important for an independent report to be carried out on all of those areas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO00200"><p>I call Senator Murphy.  We will move on after that because it is almost as if we have gone back to Second Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO00300"><p>I will keep my contribution brief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO00400"><p>May I come back in?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO00500"><p>Of course.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO00600"><p>Senator Boylan made comments about Senator Higgins's amendment.  Obviously if the amendment is pushed to a vote, I will be supporting the Government but I agree with some of the sentiments that have been expressed.</p> <p>It is important that we spend money to facilitate proper just transition, as was promised.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach will probably know because of his connection to Roscommon and the midlands that some of the semi-State bodies have removed themselves from promises that have been given.  The wilderness park is one example but there other projects to which I could refer.</p> <p>I am sorry for being a bit parochial but those of us in that area have suffered a lot.  We accepted change.  I am talking about a rural area and farmers will accept solar panelling and other types of change.  However, we cannot have moneys withdrawn or reneging by semi-State bodies.  I am thinking about the communities around Lanesborough and Longford.  I often draw attention to north-east Roscommon, an area the Leas-Chathaoirleach knows well.  That area is not spoken about often.  We suffered more than most counties from a loss of employment because of the requirements for the ESB and Bord na M&oacute;na to change and move from brown to green.  I stress again that we are in favour of change but just transition must be just transition as it was outlined.</p> <p>In fairness to the Minister of State, he acknowledged that here today and the Minister has done so in the past.  We need to ensure that those projects which were promised funding are going to get it.  We need to have no hold-ups in the system in that regard.  I do not make any apology for fighting for that part of the country on that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO00700"><p>I thank Senator Murphy.  Senator Boylan wants to say a last word on her own amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO00800"><p>It might not be the last word.  This is Committee Stage so I can say a few words.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO00900"><p>The Senator will say a last few words.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO01000"><p>We are rushing enough as it is.  The Mid Shannon Wilderness Park is a perfect example of where we are not seeing a just transition by Bord na M&oacute;na.  There are concerns in that regard and that was why I was happy to move Senator Higgins's amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO01100"><p>Where is the Senator talking about?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO01200"><p>The Mid Shannon Wilderness Park in the midlands.  Bord na M&oacute;na gave a commitment to the community.  The community was asked what it would like to see happen in the area and the people in the area were given a commitment for a wilderness park.  It was endorsed by the county manager at the time.  Bord na M&oacute;na then went ahead and put in a planning application for a wind farm on the site.  We know that wind farms on peatland, particularly if the peat can be rehabilitated, is going to cause emissions as opposed to what it could be, that is, a carbon sink.  Bord na M&oacute;na went back on that.</p> <p>The planning application was withdrawn because Bord na M&oacute;na believed it was going to lose in the courts.  We now hear it will put forward another application.  The community bought into the idea of a wilderness park.  There is fantastic wildlife in the area.  As soon as the pumps were turned off, wildlife returned to the area.  That includes nesting waders.  Bord na M&oacute;na is continuing to pump water off that peatland, which uses energy at a time we are all trying to conserve it.  It is pumping water off the peatland which has resulted in the awful sight of those nesting birds wandering around wondering where the water source they landed on has gone.</p> <p>I do not think the commitment in Bord na M&oacute;na's blue-green strategy holds water when what it is doing in action is completely contrary to it.  It is riding roughshod over what communities in that area want.  The community was given a commitment that once the extraction of peat ended, there would be engagement over a just transition process.  Senator Higgins has her reasons for submitting the amendment but I support it because I do not see Bord na M&oacute;na demonstrating a commitment to a just transition and certainly not with regard to the Mid Shannon Wilderness Park.  Bord na M&oacute;na's proposition for that site is in contradiction with the Government's peatland strategy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#OOO01300"><p>Senator Burke raised an interesting idea.  When infrastructure is built, there is an assessment of its negative effect on the environment but there is not often an assessment of the benefits.  We have seen surprising benefits to the environment from many infrastructure projects.  There is a bird sanctuary in Booterstown in my constituency which was the result of a railway built across the bay 150 years ago.  That development trapped some water and a bird sanctuary that was not there before has been the result.  Fish are breeding at the base of offshore wind turbines because they are protected because people do not fish near the base.  That is also the case at the base of the pillars of the bridge that runs between Denmark and Sweden where there are areas of wildlife sanctuary.  Projects can have a net effect on the environment whereby they create habitats.  It is sometimes hard to predict beforehand but there is a real question in that regard.</p> <p>There is a tension when one is trying to deliver an environmental project and at the same time is being delayed by environmental legislation.  I am well used to that challenge.  I would like to see, as the Senator said, more research into the habitats that can be created and an examination of the net effects.</p> <p>Senator Higgins's amendment is all about the just transition.  Such a transition is vital.  In order to get buy-in from the public and in order to be able to carry out climate action, a transition must be, and must be seen to be, fair.  The midlands in particular have been hit much worse than the rest of the country.  The decision was made to target funding towards those areas.  I must give some credit to Deputy Cowen for his work in that area.  A large quantity of money has at this stage been directed to those areas, as Senators will acknowledge.</p> <p>Many of the projects are at an early stage and cannot come soon enough.  People want to see the benefits of them faster, which is fair.  There are projects in the area of ecotourism, including greenways, boardwalks and so on.  There are bog re-wetting and renewable energy projects.  I will speak to the Minister of State, Deputy Noonan, about the Mid Shannon Wilderness Park to see if he can carry out an assessment from a biodiversity point of view to see what is going on in that regard.  I am in contact with the midlands just transition commissioner and I can ask him what is going on in respect of that project.  If the Senator has specific questions about it, she can send me a message.  I am happy to investigate and see what is happening.  Those are my comments on the contributions of Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.213" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.214" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Sections 13 agreed to.</p><p>Section 14 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.215" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Title agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.216" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Bill reported without amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#PPP00100"><p>When is it proposed to take Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#PPP00200"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#PPP00300"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.220" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Bill received for final consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#PPP00500"><p>When is it proposed to take Fifth Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#PPP00600"><p>Now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#PPP00700"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.224" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question, "That the Bill do now pass", put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.225" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#PPP00900">EirGrid, Electricity and Turf (Amendment) Bill 2022: Motion for Earlier Signature</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022070500002#PPP01000"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That, pursuant to subsection 2&deg; of section 2 of Article 25 of the Constitution, Seanad &Eacute;ireann concurs with the Government in a request to the President to sign the EirGrid, Electricity and Turf (Amendment) Bill 2022 on a date which is earlier than the fifth day after the date on which the Bill shall have been presented to him. </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.227" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-07-05a.228" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ar 5.41 p.m. go dt&iacute; 10 a.m., D&eacute; C&eacute;adaoin, an 6 I&uacute;il 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 5.41 p.m. until 10 a.m. on Wednesday, 6 July 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>