<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#A00200"><p>I have notice from Senator Colm Burke that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><p>The need for the Minister for Health to put in place adequate funding to assist junior doctors involved in medical training.</p><p>I have also received notice from Senator Colette Kelleher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to provide an update on the review of funding for traveller-specific accommodation and the implementation of the<br /><br />traveller accommodation programmes.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to urgently introduce a redress scheme for families in counties Donegal and Mayo affected by defective concrete<br /><br />blocks in their homes following the publication of the report of the expert panel in July.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senators Aidan Davitt and Robbie Gallagher, sharing time, of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to provide an update on its intention to improve the terms and conditions for councillors; to outline when the increased &euro;1,000 representational allowance will commence; to provide clarity on the new increased vouched expenses scheme and options for councillors; and if he will address the current financial anomaly with city councillors in Dublin, Galway and Cork.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Neale Richmond of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to outline the current status, ownership and future plans for the Central Mental Hospital in Dundrum.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to publish planning guidelines for regulation of solar farms.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as being suitable for discussion.  I have selected Senators Colm Burke, Kelleher, Mac Lochlainn, Davitt and Gallagher and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#A00400">Traveller Accommodation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#A00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending today.</p><p>I welcome the commissioning of the review by the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government into funding for Traveller-specific accommodation and the implementation of the Traveller accommodation programmes.  It followed a very useful meeting that we had, and I thank the Minister for acting upon that.  I understand that the housing agency report has been complete since July but it remains unpublished, and I rely on leaked information from <i>The</i><i>Irish Times </i>article published on 14 September which reported that Traveller accommodation targets have not been fully met at any point since they were made mandatory on local authorities 18 years ago.  The article in <i>The</i><i>Irish Times </i>goes on to say that the leaked report concludes that anti-Traveller prejudice at local authority level may be hampering progress.  If the intention of Government policy and the current legislation is that targets for Traveller accommodation would be met in full and that things would improve it is clearly failing.  It is failing Traveller women, children and men.  The report commissioned by the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government finds that more than &euro;55 million provided for Traveller housing remains unspent since 2000, and just 68% of promised Traveller accommodation units have been provided.  All the while, Travellers continue to live in shocking conditions, which I have seen myself at first hand.  </p><p>There is unacceptable overcrowding on halting sites.  Figures from the Department show that the number of Traveller families in need of accommodation since 2000 has more than doubled.  In this new leaked report, local authorities agreed that overcrowding was an issue, leading to health and safety concerns.  All stakeholder groups agreed that the future assessment of the needs for Traveller families was unfit for purpose.  The second anniversary of those who died in the Carrickmines fire is coming up.  More people will die in tragedies if these concerns are not addressed.  People will continue to live shorter lives and suffer from housing related ill-health.  I ask the Minister of State what will be done about all of that.</p><p>According to the 2016 census, the Traveller homelessness rate is 11 times higher than the general population.  In the last five years the rate of Traveller homelessness has tripled.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colette Kelleher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2484"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2484&amp;amp;pid=ColetteKelleher&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The leaked report also finds that the private rented accommodation provisions are extremely difficult for Traveller families to access.  Often discrimination and prejudice are getting in the way.  People are rejected based on their names alone.  It is a landlord's market, as the Minister of State knows, yet some local authorities use private rented accommodation as the alternative to staying on waiting list for Travellers seeking access to Traveller-specific accommodation.  Figures show a rise from 162 families in 2002 to 2,222 in 2016.  This has rendered increasing numbers of families homeless, further fuelling the crisis.  Most Traveller-specific housing and social housing in general is provided by local authorities using the Part VIII planning process but the leaked report further found that the most significant obstacle to the delivery of Traveller accommodation is the planning process itself, particularly objections from settled residents and elected representatives, as the Minister of State well knows.</p><p>I note and welcome the Minister's decision to review the Housing (Traveller Accommodation) Act 1998.  However, there must also be a review of legislation that affects Travellers in order to alleviate the crisis.  For example, the recent amendment to the Planning and Development (Housing) and Residential Tenancies Act 2016, which facilitated developments of more 100 accommodation units being dealt with directly by An Bord Plean&aacute;la without going through local planning processes, could also include Traveller accommodation.  Legislation should be introduced immediately to implement this change and decisions to approve specific proposals for Traveller-specific accommodation should be taken away from the local political system and invested in An Bord Plean&aacute;la.</p><p>There is, at best, systemic apathy and, at worst, prejudice in terms of meeting the accommodation of Travellers.  An indication of the apathy towards Travellers and their accommodation is reflected in the participation in this leaked review, as the Minister of State knows, where only 26 out of the 31 local authorities responded to the survey and only 22 submitted with sufficient detail across all questions.  Significant gaps were found in local authority reporting and inadequate data-keeping.  In some cases, there were no standardised recording, reporting and monitoring mechanisms.  Indeed the deadline for reporting to the Housing Agency, which the Minister commissioned, was extended twice to facilitate poor responses.  Will the Minister of State tell us when the Housing Agency review will be published and his plans to address the issue raised in the report and the major crisis for Travellers and their housing needs?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B00200"><p>I thank Senator Kelleher for providing me with the opportunity to update the House on the Traveller accommodation programme, TAP, review which was recently completed and provided to the national Traveller accommodation committee, NTACC.  A Programme for a Partnership Government commits to establishing a special working group to audit the current delivery and implementation of local authorities' Traveller accommodation plans and consult stakeholders on key areas of concern.  This commitment was underpinned in Rebuilding Ireland - Action Plan for Housing and Homelessness which provided for the commissioning by the Housing Agency, on behalf of the Department, of an expert, independent review of expenditure on and delivery of Traveller accommodation to underpin the work of the special working group.</p> <p>In 2016, the Housing Agency commissioned the review, which examined capital and current funding for Traveller-specific accommodation for the period 2000 to date, having regard to the targets contained in the local authority TAPs and actual units delivered.  It also examined the current status of the accommodation funded and the funding provided for accommodation maintenance and other supports.  Where targets in the TAPs have not been met, the review included an analysis of the underlying reasons to identify the particular challenges that need to be addressed to underpin future progress.</p> <p>The final report was completed and submitted to the Housing Agency in June and it, in turn, submitted the final report to my Department in July.  It was circulated to the NTACC members, considered by a subgroup of the NTACC and discussed at the most recent meeting of the NTACC on 28 August.  At this meeting, the NTACC agreed to advise me to establish an expert group to examine and make recommendations on issues regarding Traveller accommodation policy, strategy and implementation.  This is in keeping with the commitment in A Programme for a Partnership Government, and I have agreed to proceed with the establishment of this expert group.  I have also agreed that a review of the Housing (Traveller Accommodation) Act 1998 should be part of the work of the expert group.  The composition and terms of reference and methodology of this expert group are being formulated with a view to it being in place as soon as possible.  My Department is making arrangements for the recently completed review to be made available on the Department's website within the next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B00300"><p>I have two questions.  One of them was answered by the Minister of State, namely, when the report be published.  It will be published within the next week.  I will monitor that and look forward to seeing that report.  I welcome the expert group.  While the expert group is welcome, it cannot be a delaying tactic or a way of kicking this urgent issue to touch.  Over the past 18 years since the legislation was introduced, the targets have never been fully met.  Local authorities are sending money back.  They are not even making their returns to the review.  I would like to hear more specifics from the Minister of State, and not simply the date when the review will be published, which is welcome, and the establishment of an expert group.  I would like to know some specifics in terms of what the Minister of State is going to do about this urgent issue for Traveller families, an issue that is a matter of life and death for families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B00400"><p>I assure the Senator that it is not a delaying tactic.  I only inherited this role a few months ago.  There is no agreement on the best way to spend this money.  I am not happy in the same way as the Senator is not happy that the money is not being spent where it should be.  There are accommodation issues.  The budget has increased over the past year.  We made sure of that as well.  My job as Minister of State is to make sure it is spent.</p> <p>I will not comment on the review because it is not published yet.  I will have no problem commenting on it when it is published next week but, as a habit, I do not comment on leaked documents.  We can discuss it in greater detail when it is published next week.  Again, it highlights many of the issues that need to be addressed.  We must find ways of spending this money.  When the committee agrees who will be on the expert commission, I hope it involve some international experts to find ways of making sure we honour our commitments because it is a priority for Government.  We are putting the money back in where it should be.  I agree with the Senator that if one analyses many of the local authority waiting lists, one sees there is a difficulty for people from Traveller backgrounds, so we need to address that.  Likewise, they have different issues as well.  Some of them want to live in different places, so we need to accommodate that as best we can.  There is no excuse for money not being spent.  Along with the review and the report of the commission, I will try to engage with local authorities to make sure the money is spent this year and the year ahead.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B00500">Building Regulations</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B00600"><p>With the Leas-Chathaoirleach's assistance, my colleague, Senator Conway-Walsh, will take the supplementary question because, obviously, it pertains to Donegal and Mayo.  Is that agreeable?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B00700"><p>Senator Mac Lochlainn is starting but the brief supplementary will come from Senator Conway-Walsh?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B00800"><p>Yes.  Is that okay?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B00900"><p>Perfect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#B01000"><p>I appreciate that.  The Minister of State is very familiar with this issue.  I know he has visited Donegal a number of times and met affected families.  He knows it very well at this stage.  Even though it had limited terms of reference, the expert panel report, which was published almost four months ago, clearly demonstrated that there was a profound failure in State oversight of the manufacturing of concrete blocks.  There was also a failure in building control regulations.  Looking at the eight recommendations, it can be seen that they clearly point to a failure in State oversight.  What does that mean?  According to this report, and based on my own evidence in Donegal, it means that thousands of families in Donegal were profoundly failed by the State.  The biggest investment a family will make is, of course, the purchase and securing of the family home through a mortgage or loan.  It is a huge investment.  They have been left not just with unsafe homes but also with this financial distress.  It is deeply distressing for the families.  This expert panel report was delayed by one year.  This is another year of distress, worry and not knowing what is going to happen.  We are now a further four months down the line.  All I am asking for is that the families affected in Donegal and Mayo receive the same support from this State as did families in Dublin and north Leinster who were affected by pyrite.  We are just asking for equality of treatment and equality of support from the State.</p> <p>There is no more time for dragging heels.  The Minister of State knows what needs to be done.  We need a redress scheme in order that families can make their homes safe.  I have spoken to families in Donegal who are worried that the bison concrete slabs between their floors could come down on top of them.  They are worried that their gable could collapse.  The Minister has heard these stories as well.  We must do something about this.  There must be financial supports for families who are already paying a mortgage.  They have seen their houses devalued profoundly, so in the vast majority of cases they do not have the financial capacity to do it themselves.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2321"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2321&amp;amp;pid=PadraigMacLochlainn&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The State needs to step up here.  It failed in its responsibilities.  The concrete block is the core component of the family home in Ireland.  Not ensuring those blocks were manufactured to a proper safe standard and that building control measures were right and proper was a huge failure.  It is a collective failure of our State and we need see collective responsibility being taken.  Now, four months after the publication of this report, I urge the Minister of State, please, to put in place a redress scheme for the families in Donegal and Mayo who desperately need the Government's help.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C00200"><p>I thank both Senators for raising this important issue.  It is one that affects many people and one that has been raised weekly by colleagues from all parties.  I reiterate that it is important we all realise it is an issue on which we must all work together to resolve as best we can.</p> <p>I acknowledge the very difficult and distressing situation that certain home owners in Donegal and Mayo face on account of damage to the structural integrity of their homes.  I have seen some of these damaged homes first-hand and have met home owners in both Donegal and Mayo and understand what they are going through.  The will is there to try to help people through this difficult phase.</p> <p>I understand clearly the difficulties they face.  I firmly believe the parties responsible for poor workmanship and the supply of defective materials should face up to their responsibilities and take appropriate actions to provide remedies to affected home owners.  The Senators may reread the report and see what it says exactly because it does refer to defective materials.  That is the root cause of this problem.  The expert panel on concrete blocks was established by my Department in April 2016 to investigate problems that have emerged in the concrete block work of certain dwellings in counties Donegal and Mayo.  I will not go through the panel's terms of reference again but it was about trying to establish the number of houses in question.  We now know roughly the breakdown in Mayo and Donegal.  Much good work has been done in gathering that information by the different action groups and sharing it with the expert panel.  I ask people to continue to do that and to identify themselves if they have properties in which they believe mica or pyrite is present, because that helps us formulate our plans.  A major part of the work of the expert panel and the reason it took time was to work out a process on how best to address these houses and remedy the problems, including the technical solutions involved, which is the key part.  Most of the residents who have engaged with it understand the process.  We are all annoyed that it took longer than we had hoped, but we understand the processes we had to go through. The Senator referred to other schemes, and similarly there were formulas used there.</p> <p>I received the report of the expert panel in June 2017.  It is comprehensive and addresses all areas of the terms of reference.  On 13 June 2017, I published the report.  It has eight recommendations.  My Department has already taken action to implement recommendations 1 and 2 as priorities.  Having spoken to the residents of affected houses, they understand the process and that recommendations 1 and 2 are key to their situation.  The others apply more to the future but are not the main issues for the residents currently affected.  We had to prioritise recommendations 1 and 2, so that is what we are doing.</p> <p>With regard to recommendation 1, the testing and categorisation protocol, the National Standards Authority of Ireland, NSAI, technical committee, established to scope and fast-track the development of a standardised protocol, held its inaugural meeting on 11 September 2017 and has scheduled several further meetings for the coming weeks.  I am pleased to hear its work is progressing well.</p> <p>With regard to recommendation 2, the competent professional oversight, my Department has been in contact with Engineers Ireland about the establishment of a register of competent engineers for home owners' or affected parties&rsquo; reference.  Engineers Ireland provided assurance that it will collaborate with the Department, the NSAI and others on measures to establish such a register.</p> <p>On 19 July 2017, I visited Donegal and met key stakeholders.  Many public representatives from all parties attended that meeting.  I met affected home owners and members of groups working with them and other interested parties.  We discussed the publication of the report and its recommendations.  I explained the importance for me as a Minister in this area of the priority in implementing recommendations 1 and 2.  Regardless of how these solutions will be funded or who will step up, and I referred from the start to the many stakeholders involved in this, we must establish the protocols to do this properly.  That is the number one issue.  The residents understood that, as did the local councillors.  We are doing this as quickly as possible.  I also visited Mayo some weeks later and had similar discussions with stakeholders there and urged all the various groups to come forward with their plans in order that we can identify the numbers.</p> <p>I fully appreciate and understand the urgency of this matter.  I understand that some people have suffered a lot in recent years and that they want solutions, but I want to be clear that as a Department, we are on this matter.  We are implementing recommendations 1 and 2 and will then consider how best we can drive this on and solve the matter.  The first thing is to identify the technical solutions and the process.  I cannot emphasise this enough.  I will not jeopardise this by making a commitment that they will be finished in a week when it will take a few months but the expert panel is there from the NSAI and there are good people with experience on this matter dealing with it.  I am happy we will move this on quite soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C00300"><p>Senator Conway-Walsh has one minute in which to ask a brief supplementary question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to Mayo.  I speak on behalf of the action group there.  I was very disappointed, as was the action group, that I was not invited to attend that meeting and was excluded from it.  As the Minister of State knows, I and Senator Mac Lochlainn have been working on this matter for several years.  However, it is not about us.  It is about the home owners.</p> <p>Did the Minister of State ask the Minister for Finance for a line in the budget to provide for these homes?  I fully understand that the Minister of State cannot yet quantify the amount that may be necessary, but while he says the home owners understand the delays, they do not.  What they do understand is that if the Minister of State has requested a line in the budget to provide for the homes affected by pyrite, they do not expect him to have a whole figure.  That said, they want a gesture of an amount that would show his and the Government's solid intention to address this in an equitable way, as it was on the eastern side of the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C00500"><p>I recognise the involvement of many people across all parties and at all levels of public representation, at local level and council level.  I am surprised that Senator Conway-Walsh was not at the meeting.  I do not know why she was not invited.  Her Sinn F&eacute;in colleague was there so there is no issue of that.  She would have been very welcome there because it was cross-party, which we proved in Donegal.  I am not making this issue political.  I want it resolved and am committed to doing that.</p> <p>I disagree with the Senator that people do not understand.  The home owners I met who are affected by this understand that I have to go through a process.  I explained to them that if I do not follow that process indicated in the recommendations, it could jeopardise any funding to resolve the matter.  There has to be a logical way to address this with technical solutions, and then the money can be put behind it.  I will repeat what I said again.  There are many stakeholders involved in the process.  There were defective materials and the matter needs to be addressed.  My job is to ensure we find a solution for the residents.  That is my commitment and I will continue to work towards that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C00600"><p>Will the Minister of State guarantee -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C00700"><p>I cannot allow the Senator again under the rules.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C00800"><p>When the report was published-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C00900"><p>Unfortunately, I am not allowed to let Senator Mac Lochlainn in again under the rules, I am sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01000"><p>There was a very different -----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01100"><p>We are moving on.  I thank the Minister of State and the Senators.  I see the Minister of State, Deputy John Paul Phelan, is present.  We will take the item to which he is responding next as the Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, is not here yet.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.31" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01125">Local Authority Members' Remuneration</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01150"><p>With the House's permission, we move to Senators Aidan Davitt and Robbie Gallagher who are sharing their time and have two minutes each.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01200"><p>We are splitting the time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01300"><p>The Senators have two minutes each.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01400"><p>It is two and a half minutes.  We have five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01500"><p>No, the Senators only have four.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01600"><p>Five.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01700"><p>If the Senators agree not to make a supplementary contribution, they can have two and a half minutes each.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#C01800"><p>No, we will take two minutes each or as near we can.  I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  On behalf of the Fianna F&aacute;il Senators and councillors, it is with a heavy heart we meet.  There was a time that when Ministers gave a commitment, it meant something.  Unfortunately, the Minister of State now presides over what is now the Department of broken promises.  During the Fine Gael leadership campaign, the then Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government, Deputy Simon Coveney, sat where the Minister of State sits now and promised councillors &euro;5,000 in expenses annually and a pay increase of &euro;1,000 starting on 1 July.  He was adamant about the time.  We were told it was written into legislation.  The Minister of State will be aware this has not happened.</p> <p>I appreciate that the Minister of State has only got his feet under the desk and we wish him the best in his role.  I am aware of his previous work and I know he is a hard worker and comes with that reputation.  I have great hopes.  I implore him to give me a date for when the pay increase will start.  That is the simple question he is here to answer today.  When will the expenses kick in and will there be back pay to the date from which the increases were promised?</p> <p>We are haemorrhaging talent from councils.  In the Minister of State's electoral area, a Fianna F&aacute;il councillor was replaced in recent days.  In my own county of Westmeath, there was a Fianna F&aacute;il co-option in the previous week.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aidan Davitt:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2475"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2475&amp;amp;pid=AidanDavitt&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The week before that there was a Fianna F&aacute;il co-option in Offaly.  Those are only three of which I am aware.  I am sure it has happened in other parties too.  I implore the Minister of State to take a stand on this issue in his new Department.  I ask that he would hold his head high when he leaves office and say he did the right thing by councillors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D00200"><p>I, too, welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  It is disappointing in many ways that we are back here discussing this same issue despite, as my colleague, Senator Davitt, outlined, the promise that was made about its resolution.  I am sure the Minister of State will agree we are fortunate to have so many hard-working local authority members throughout the country.  The problem is due to changes made by Mr. Phil Hogan when he was a Minister.  The workload of county councillors and the geographic area which they have to cover is now, despite their best efforts, nearly impossible.  In my constituency of Cavan and Monaghan, in the past 18 months to two years we have had a turnover of three or four councillors.  All of them cite the same reason, which is that they simply cannot do the work of a local authority member properly and hold down a job at the same time.  I am sure this does not come as a foreign language to the Minister of State.  I am sure he has the finger on the pulse himself and that he knows what I am saying is correct.</p> <p>We are less than 18 months away from the next local elections.  I believe I speak on behalf of all local authority members and Senators when I plead that the issues alluded to by my colleague, Senator Davitt, should be grappled with once and for all.  Otherwise we will continue to lose good people.  As a former local authority member, I am convinced there is no element of democracy closer to the public than the county councillor.  Unless we do something to address the issue, we will lose more people.  I spoke to many county councillors who are seriously considering their position because they cannot afford to do the work and travel to regional and local meetings while holding down a job at the same time.  I therefore request earnestly that the Minister of State grasp the issue and address it once and for all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D00300"><p>This is a good opportunity to outline the current position with regard to councillors' pay and conditions.  I thank Senators Davitt and Gallagher for raising it.  I think Senator Davitt was a little melodramatic in calling the Department the Department of broken promises.  A commitment was given and it is still intended that it would be honoured.  There was a time not that long ago when the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government, as it is now called, would be able to make the decision itself, but now it requires joint approval with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  That is where the issue rests at the moment.  In terms of dates and times, it is my intention that it would be finalised before Hallowe'en and that it will be backdated to when it was originally due to be implemented.</p> <p>The Senators are correct in terms of councillors leaving office.  I have come across it myself.  It is occurring much more regularly in recent years.  The major contributor is the workload involved while trying to continue with a full-time job or rearing a family.  These are huge issues.  I recently met Women for Election with a view to looking at some of the examples that were mentioned, and I also met some councillors in my constituency.  Senator Davitt mentioned the retirement of Councillor Anne Ahern in Carlow, who received a significant promotion.  I am not sure she would have been able to continue anyway.  However, I acknowledge her work in Carlow County Council over many years.  She was a very effective councillor.</p> <p>Senator Gallagher raised the anomaly between city councillors and county councillors.  It is proposed that the city councillors will get the same increase as county councillors.</p> <p>Effective local government structures are an essential part of our democracy.  I was a child councillor myself 20 years ago.  In turn, effective local government cannot be achieved without the heard work and commitment of elected members in service of their communities.  A range of financial supports are in place to assist councillors in their work.  These include the representational payment, fixed annual expenses, a travel and subsistence allowance, a mobile phone allowance, a retirement gratuity and conference and training provision.  A Programme for a Partnership Government includes a commitment to review the supports provided to councillors in consultation with representative bodies.  The former Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney, met representatives of the Association of Irish Local Government, AILG, and the Local Authority Members Association to discuss the view of their members that positive consideration should be given to improving the range of supports available.</p> <p>In January this year, taking account of the considerable additional workload councillors have experienced since 2014 and the reforms of local government, the former Minister announced two important changes to support councillors in their role as public representatives.  First, a new allowance of &euro;1,000 per annum is to be introduced in recognition of the work councillors undertake in carrying out their reserved functions at municipal district level, and second, a new vouched annual expenses allowance of up to a maximum of &euro;5,000 is to be introduced, which councillors may choose to opt for in place of the existing unvouched rate of approximately &euro;2,500.  It is proposed that the allowable expenditure categories and documentation requirements of this new vouched system would be aligned, as appropriate, with the arrangements in place for Oireachtas Members.  While it was intended that these new measures would be implemented with effect from 1 July, the Association of Irish Local Government requested that further consideration be given to the terms and conditions that would apply.  I subsequently met a delegation from the AILG shortly after I assumed office myself to understand its views on the matter.  A particular concern raised, which I acknowledged, was to ensure appropriate recognition of the workload of all councillors at sub-county level throughout the country.</p> <p>As Senators will appreciate, the introduction of measures of this kind requires the amendment of regulations made under section 142 of the Local Government Act 2001, which requires the consent of the Minister for Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform.  Draft amending regulations have been prepared and are under consideration between the two Departments.  While the matter is taking longer than intended, it is important that the measures are implemented from the outset in a manner that is fair to all councillors.</p> <p>I thank the Senators for raising this matter and ask for their continued patience while procedural matters associated with the measures outlined are finalised.  I reiterate the intention that this will be resolved before Hallowe'en.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D00400"><p>I will speak on my own behalf and on behalf of other Senators, including Senator Mark Daly who got tied up on the way to the meeting here.  I was only talking to him a few moments ago.  He just could not make it here today.  I appreciate the Minister of State's answer and his honesty.  He has given us a timeframe, which we did not have before now.  We were in the dark.  I know the Minister of State met representatives from the AILG and that they found the meeting quite productive.  We welcome the commitment to introduce it by Hallowe'en.  It would be great if it happened.  We certainly would welcome it.  We are delighted to hear about the backpay as well and that expenses will be examined.  Will the anomaly between county councillors and city councillors be sorted out in the same timeframe?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D00500"><p>Yes, that is the intention.  It is part of the reason for the delay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D00600"><p>I appreciate that.  I know that this is also close to the heart of the Leas-Chathaoirleach, a man who has worked hard on it over the years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D00700"><p>Had the Senator another question?  The clock is running.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D00800"><p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach will not be harsh on one of his own.  I appreciate the Minister of State's clarification on that point.  I was concerned about reports in the media about the councillor who was on maternity leave.  I am sure the Minister of State saw it.  Has he any thoughts on it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D00900"><p>I will not comment on individual cases.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D01000"><p>I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D01100"><p>I think it is a broader question about how we pay local government members and ensure the same benefits that accrue to other workers accrue to them.  Following on from this decision, there will be some consideration as to further reforms for members in local authorities to bring them in line with every other public servant, which is effectively what they are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D01200"><p>I thank the Minister of State and the Senators.  We all appreciate that it is an important issue.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.52" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D01300">Non-Consultant Hospital Doctors</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D01400"><p>The Minister of State, Deputy Jim Daly, has arrived.  It is a long way from Skibbereen but the good man is here.  I call Senator Colm Burke.  The floor is his.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#D01500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending to deal with this matter.  I have raised this issue with regard to junior doctors consistently over the past four to five years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In 2012, I conducted a survey of people doing their final medical examinations in Irish universities.  It indicated that more than 60% of them did not intend to work in Ireland once they had finished their internship.  A survey published in recent days indicates this number may very well have increased to 80%.  While we have had various reports going back to 2003, including the MacCraith report and the second MacCraith report, which dealt with training for junior doctors, we do not seem to be making any progress.</p><p>I had to leave a meeting of the health committee with the Minister, Deputy Harris, to come here.  The committee received a report on training and development in the HSE for the first six months of 2017, which showed we are underspending by approximately 36% on training and development.  This concerns me because we want to retain junior doctors and we do not seem to be proactive in dealing with this.  I made the point at the committee that the HSE has recruited more than 2,000 administrative and managerial staff in two years.  We now have 17,000 managers and administrators in the HSE but, at the same time, we seem to have done nothing for the people working at the coal face, namely, junior doctors.  We have a major problem with smaller hospitals, which are finding it extremely difficult to recruit senior house officers, registrars and senior registrars, particularly in places such as Letterkenny, Sligo, Castlebar, Clonmel, Waterford, Tralee and even Limerick.  We need to address this issue, and it is for this reason I have tabled this question.  We need major reform in how we provide for this category of personnel in the HSE at front-line level.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator who has been very consistent, dedicated and committed to this cause.  I commend this and I thank him for raising this important issue.  As a country, we invest considerable resources in training our non-consultant hospital doctors, NCHDs.  As recently as Tuesday this week, a report published by the RCSI highlighted that more than 80% of trainee doctors have said that working conditions, training opportunities, and work-life balance are factors that would influence their decision to leave Ireland.  Last Saturday, the Minister, Deputy Harris, attended for the second time the annual medical careers day, where he was struck by the enthusiasm of the students.  It is vital that we continue to foster a positive attitude and support these medical students during their time in training.</p> <p>National Doctors Training and Planning, NDTP, in the HSE funds postgraduate training for trainees through service level agreements with each individual training body for the various specialties.  It also provides financial supports to NCHDs through two separate funding schemes for the costs involved in undertaking exams and courses.  The first of these is the clinical course and exam refund scheme.  NDTP provides funding of &euro;450 for mandatory courses or exams undertaken in Ireland and &euro;650 towards exams taken outside of Ireland.  It is recognised though that sometimes the costs of courses or exams will exceed this amount.  The second scheme is the higher specialist fund.  This fund is available to higher specialist trainees, including GP registrars.  In total there are approximately 1,500 of these trainees.  Trainees are entitled to &euro;500 per year of higher specialist training.  This equates to &euro;2,500 for those on a five year training programme.  The total number of trainees is now more than 3,700 and this number has grown in recent years.  In addition, the number of NCHDs who do not occupy training posts is growing.  The total number of NCHDs has increased by more than 1,000, to approximately 6,000 in the past three years.  While this increase is welcome, it must be recognised that the budget available to NDTP has to cover more trainees than previously.</p> <p>The strategic review of medical training and career structure working group, chaired by Professor Brian MacCraith, published three reports in 2013 and 2014, and made 25 recommendations.  The need to support NCHD training was highlighted by the group.  I will mention some particular successes already achieved in implementing the MacCraith group&rsquo;s recommendations, including the appointment of lead NCHDs.  This role involves representing all NCHDs in their dealings with clinical directorates and hospital management.  There is also the improvement of the work-life situation of NCHDs.  The HSE has agreed to double the number of family-friendly training places over a three-year period, and the recruitment of additional NCHDs has meant significant reductions in working hours.  The Department remains committed to the full implementation of the recommendations of the group.  This includes recommendations relating directly to NCHD training needs and assisting in the recruitment and retention of key medical staff.  On this basis, it was agreed earlier this year that management and the Irish Medical Organisation would undertake a review of the continuing education requirements of NCHDs.  This review is due to commence in the near future and will be undertaken under the auspices of the Workplace Relations Commission.  It is important that we continue to improve the working conditions of NCHDs and support their training needs to the maximum extent possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I fully accept a serious effort has been made with the MacCraith report, but I am very concerned that while the report set out a huge number of recommendations, it is not clarified how many of the 25 recommendations have been implemented.  Perhaps we could get answers to this.  I thought the MacCraith report would resolve many of the issues, but we are not resolving them and, in fact, we are going backwards.  I am extremely concerned.</p> <p>Another issue which has arisen to cause further problems is the number of doctors coming from abroad is not as plentiful as what it used to be because Ireland is no longer seen as an attractive training location for junior doctors from abroad.  They have other choices such as Australia, Canada and New Zealand and we are not competing for them.  We have a major challenge.  If we want to reduce hospital waiting lists we need to have enough people at the front line to be able to do so.  We have a problem with junior doctors, and because we have a problem with them we now also have a problem with recruiting consultants.  This is something that needs to be given priority by the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1261" speakername="Jim Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#E00400"><p>I undertake to get the Senator an update on the recommendations of the MacCraith report from the Department and furnish the Senator with a detailed update on how many recommendations were made, what actions have been taken, how many have been implemented and what steps have been taken to ensure the full enactment of all of the recommendations.  I will do this without delay.  I thank the Senator for his continued interest and help in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.59" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.20 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.60" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, statements on the mid-term review of the capital plan and next steps, to be taken at 2 p.m. and conclude after 90 minutes, with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes each and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes each and the Minister to be given five minutes in which to reply to the debate; No. 2, Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Bill 2016 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 3.30 p.m., adjourned at 5 p.m., if not previously concluded, and resumed at the conclusion of Private Member's business; No. 3, Private Member's business, An Bille um &Uacute;dar&aacute;s na Gaeltachta (Leas&uacute;) 2017 - Second Stage, to be taken at 5 p.m., with the time allocated for the debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#G00300"><p>I refer to cancer services.  Cancer Week 2017 runs from 25 September until 1 October.  Since 1996, when the first cancer strategy was launched, Ireland has prided itself on providing a world-class cancer service which adheres to international guidelines and best practice.  However, we are hearing reports of a deterioration in the service, with delays in the commencement of chemotherapy programmes, at a time when we know that time is of the essence for oncology patients.  I have also learned of shortages of radiographers in St. James's Hospital which are resulting in surveillance scans such as MRI or PET scans to monitor the progression of cancer patients not being performed.  The scans were previously conducted on cancer patients on a quarterly basis to determine whether their treatment was working and whether they should continue with their chemotherapy programmes.  As such programmes are very tough on the body, this situation is both infuriating and stressful for families.  Many of the issues arise from staff shortages in the public sector, a matter I have raised in the House previously.  There are staff shortages in the armed forces, mental health services and so on.  The Public Sector Pay Commission recommended that an expert be appointed to address the shortages, but, to date, no one has been put in place and no solutions have been offered to the problem of staff shortages in the public sector.  Will the Leader ask the Minister of Health why this has not happened and to clarify whether targets for cancer patients are being met.</p> <p>Another issue which comes up time and again is the unfair income thresholds for receipt of the fuel allowance.  Many constituents presented at my office during the summer who were above the threshold by as little as &euro;1 or &euro;2.  Some suffer from health issues such as COPD or emphysema.  The home of one man is not insulated.  He suffers from COPD and can barely breathe during the winter because of the cold.  As he is above the income threshold by &euro;6, he is not entitled to receive the fuel allowance or any of the ancillary benefits that accrue to those in receipt of it, including the opportunity in some areas to have one's home insulated.  The weather is turning and, given increases in the price of fuel and electricity, I ask the Minister for Finance to consider increasing the threshold for receipt of the fuel allowance or inserting into the legislation a special stipulation in order that the Department can exercise discretion in certain circumstances.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#G00400"><p>I do not have a specific request for the Leader, but I wish to refer to a very important news item.  Ireland has been named as the country with the most secure food in the world.  This was announced yesterday at the launch of the sixth annual global food security index and is a remarkable achievement.  The news was published in the newspapers yesterday and again today.  The index measures improvements in food affordability, availability, quality and safety.  Ireland finished with a score of 79 out of 100, just ahead of Austria which had a score of 77.  The United States of America which had previously topped the list finished fourth.  France and Germany came third and fifth, respectively.  This remarkable story must be acknowledged.  The detailed reports contain a very interesting analysis and emphasise that Government support for agricultural research weighed heavily in Ireland's favour.  In that context, I refer to Bord Bia's food strategy, Making a World of Difference.  Bord Bia does great work and its strategy is outlined in a booklet which was published in 2016.  I am delighted to say it is also included in the programme for Government.  A lot of emphasis in placed in Origin Green on food security and organic production in the meat sector, as well as the vegetable and horticulture sectors.  We must acknowledge and celebrate this great achievement, particularly in the context of Brexit, as well as the great opportunities it presents on the island of Ireland, North and South.  We must harness the opportunities for major expansion in organic production in the Republic of Ireland and across the island.  I ask the Leader to pass on the good wishes of the House to the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and those involved in rolling out the strategy, particularly in Bord Bia.  They are on the right track.  It constitutes international validation of what they are doing and should be acknowledged.  I say, "Well done," to all involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#G00500"><p>I have just come from the launch of part of Sinn F&eacute;in's pre-budget submission on tackling the health crisis which lays particular emphasis on the need to invest in home help and home care packages.  The inhumane cuts to the numbers of home help hours and home care packages initiated by Fianna F&aacute;il and continued by Fine Gael have left the service in crisis which is not just manifest in rural Ireland but also in urban Ireland.  The nonsensical Fianna F&aacute;il policy of allocating just 30 or 45 minutes to households and elderly vulnerable persons and the drive towards privatisation mean that there are swathes of rural Ireland without a service.  In some cases, home help packages are being allocated, but the necessary personnel are not available to provide the service because it has been privatised.  This is an essential service, as acknowledged in many Government policy documents.  Home care packages need to be delivered in the home and the community.  In the forthcoming budget Sinn F&eacute;in proposes an increase in the number of home help hours by 20%, which would result in an additional 2.1 million home help hours being made available.  We are keenly aware that families have a variety of needs and that the provision of home care packages is essential.  In that context, we propose an increase in the number of home care packages by 15%, or 2,485.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These measures would constitute an investment of &euro;72.65 million in older people and would go some way toward delivering for them and their families and ensuring they can live with the dignity and respect they have earned and deserve.  Not only are the measures the fair and decent thing to do, they also make sense financially as well as having the knock-on effect of alleviating pressure on acute hospital services through beds being freed up and thus the reduction of the trolley and waiting list crises.  Older people deserve such measures and Sinn F&eacute;in is on their side and is making it a priority for budget 2018.  I would like the Minister to come to the House to deal with some of the issues in relation to home care, home care packages, these not being a Government priority and there not being the personnel in many parishes in rural Ireland to deliver services to ensure elderly and vulnerable persons have the choice of living in their own homes.  It makes social and economic sense to deal with these issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H00200"><p>It is a pleasure to be back in the House after a busy and productive recess.  I add my voice to those of fellow Senators on the transformation of the Chamber.  I say well done to all involved and I thank the National Museum for hosting us.  However, I echo another sentiment aired yesterday by Senators Alice-Mary Higgins and McDowell.  This day next week will be the fourth anniversary of the referendum on the abolition of the Seanad.  My party and I opposed that abolition and the referendum was defeated by Irish citizens who looked to the Government to provide meaningful reform of this institution, whether it wished to do so or not.  Since then, a Seanad reform Bill was introduced and passed Second Stage almost immediately, followed by a Government commitment to convene a committee on Seanad reform.  Nothing has since been done.  In spite of numerous calls for it to meet, the committee has not been convened, the Seanad Reform Bill has not been advanced to the next Stage and-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H00300"><p>Very defective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H00400"><p>The Senator is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H00500"><p>-----there is continued resentment of the Seanad's lack of democratic input.  The old Seanad Chamber might be undergoing renewal but there is absolutely no sign of a similar renewal for this institution.  Senator McDowell's Seanad reform Bill which I was proud to co-sign would invigorate future Seanaid by giving them the democratic mandate and expertise the institution was always meant to embody.  It would guarantee one person, one vote for the election of the majority of Senators and thus end the injustice of some people having as many as seven votes while the majority have none.  It would ensure the Chamber would be made up of real experts in their fields and provide a clear line of difference between this House and the Lower House and would give representation to the thousands of Irish abroad who are denied representation in either their new or original homes, in contravention of international democratic norms.</p> <p>I ask the Leader for clarification on several points regarding this issue.  When will the Government convene the committee on Seanad reform?  What will its remit be?  What will be the timeline for its work?  How will it be resourced?  Who will be the Chair of the committee?  Will the Government agree to engage with the committee in the spirit of reform and constructive engagement engendered by the result of the referendum four years ago?  Will the Government specifically focus on the Seanad reform Bill that remains on the Order Paper or a wider remit?  Is it the Government's intention to slow the process yet again and wait it out until the next election and the convening of yet another report to tell us what we already know?  I ask the Leader to indicate which Minister is responsible for the Bill and if that Minister will come before this House as soon as possible to tell Senators of the process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H00600"><p>I rise to raise a very sensitive issue and one which all Members should be in a position to support, which is cardiac care in Ireland and how children are dealt with.  I request that we facilitate a debate in the House on this issue.  I had a discussion with the parent of a child who passed away last February.  The boy's name was Gavin Coyne and his mother's name is Maria.  Gavin suffered from a condition known as dilated cardiomyopathy.  His mother has concerns about his treatment in Crumlin children's hospital and in the Mater hospital and also the treatment of her family when they relocated to Newcastle for further treatment.  She is not asking for anything for her family now as nothing can be done for Gavin, he having passed away at ten years of age.  He leaves behind a grieving family, classmates and friends.  However, his mother has questions in relation to how the entirety of care for children with such illnesses is handled in Ireland.  I ask the Leader to facilitate a debate in the House on cardiac care for children.  I ask that the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, come to the House to speak not just to this issue and case but the general issue of the service that is available for such children.  I will write to ask the Minister to meet with the family but in the House it is more appropriate to address the general issue.  A young child has died and possibly unnecessarily so.  This case leads me to believe that further investigation is needed into how we care for children who suffer from these serious ailments and I make that request of the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H00700"><p>A very important issue for Cork currently is that of local government structures.  An ongoing debate has been taking place in Cork city and county in recent years if not decades regarding whether there will be an extension to the boundary.  The issue has rumbled on over the past four or five years and there have been three or four reports expressing different views.  There have been many columns on the issue in newspapers over the past few months.  It has been very unhelpful to Cork and its development.  The issue needs to be sorted out and a conclusion reached one way or anther because, unfortunately, the continuous debate and commentary on whether there should be one local authority, whether it should be a large city or what is to happen to the region of Cork has taken away from its development.  We need to move forward and have clarity.  The Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Murphy, needs to move swiftly to ensure that whatever decision he makes is made in the next few weeks.  We cannot have another situation where councils write letters and send section 29s to each other or that mayors continue to have public spats.  It is not good for the region, the local authorities or the image of local government in Cork.</p> <p>I hope that the Minister or the Minister of State, Deputy Phelan, can come to the Chamber as soon as possible to bring the needed clarity to the issue.  A decision is needed.  We do not want more debate or reports.  We want the Minister to come forward with a conclusion so that we can move forward because at this stage it is stalemate in Cork.  The region is not developing because all we are really doing is tearing each other apart and the knock-on effect is that the communities we serve are not being served because it is a power game at the moment.  That is not good for the locality.  I suggest to the Leader that the Minister come to the House to bring clarity to this issue.  It is the biggest issue in Cork at the moment and needs to be sorted out once and for all for the second city and its region.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H00800"><p>I offer my congratulations to the Cathaoirleach on his presiding over the new Seanad.  It is nice that Senator Norris, the longest-serving Member of the Seanad, is here.  I will not go into the details but I congratulate all involved, including the Clerk of the Seanad, the Clerk-Assistant of the Seanad and, in particular, the Office of Public Works.  It deserves great credit for the quality of work and the design and craftsmanship of the men and women who put this together.  It is well deserved.  It is an excellent Chamber and will hopefully add to the quality of debates here over the next few years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H00900"><p>I doubt it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#H01000"><p>The acoustics are better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00100"><p>I regret that I was not here yesterday.  I was a member of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly committee on Brexit, led by Andrew Rosindell, MP, joint chair of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly and also chair of that committee.  We spent a number of days in Brussels.  We are preparing a report for the October session of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, which is being held in Liverpool.  We have representatives of the D&aacute;il, Seanad, the House of Commons, the House of Lords, the Scottish Parliament, Welsh Assembly and the Northern Ireland Assembly.  We were there to try to ensure the best arrangement we could to influence negotiations between the European Union and UK.</p> <p>One thing is missing.  We have no democratically elected Executive in Northern Ireland.  It is vital that the Executive is formed to represent the people of Northern Ireland in Brexit negotiations.  I appeal to the Democratic Unionist Party and Sinn F&eacute;in.  I see the Democratic Unionist Party would prefer to run the show from London.  It has a &pound;10 billion fund to distribute and divvy out.  That is the way that I see things going.  The DUP is also going to have influence on the final negotiated settlement.  We discussed whether there is to be a border or customs border of any sort, whether electronic or otherwise.  Is it the 500 km Border or is it a border in Larne and Belfast on the Irish Sea?  This is the point that comes across clearly at the moment.  The European Union is not that helpful.  It says that it is not its problem but that it is the UK's problem because it has decided to leave.  We in the Republic will be the ones who will experience collateral damage because we are not at the negotiating table.  We have no direct representative.  We are represented by one of the 27.  The point is that Britain is represented by the British Government and the Democratic Unionist Party has a say in that Government.  Bear that in mind.  I ask the Leader if he will arrange an update on the position and enable discussion of these matters among a very representative Seanad, representing all the parties and Independents, to update people on what is happening in Brussels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00200"><p>We should all welcome the decision by Saudi Arabia to allow women to drive.  We could see it as a small step for man, perhaps, but a giant leap for womenkind.  We should not speak too soon, however.  I recall the late Libyan dictator, Muammar Gaddafi, when he arrived in Italy some years ago, seeing himself as a self-styled emancipator of women, with an all-female bodyguard.  He asked to meet about a thousand Italian women leaders in the world of culture and politics.  When he was asked about the ban on women driving in Islamic states, he got polite applause for asking why these women should have to apply to the head of state for the right to drive a car.  Then he went and ruined it all by saying that it was a matter for women's husbands or brothers to decide.  We will just have to wait and see what happens in Saudi Arabia.</p><p>A more credible voice for human rights and equality is John Pittock, the former chairman of Deloitte, who has resigned his membership of the audit committee of the Department of Children and Youth Affairs.  He has done so because he does not want to be associated with the contradiction of having a Minister for Children and Youth Affairs who is radically in favour of repealing the eighth amendment.  He said</p><blockquote>The tiny baby girl or boy needs to be protected by our laws just like every other member of society.  Unborn children should not be discriminated against and suffer child abuse but should be given the choice of a happy life.  In England and Wales, where they brought in the killing of unborn babies, which was legalised in 1967, supposedly on restricted grounds, we now have a situation where one in every five unborn babies is killed.</blockquote> <p>The eighth amendment protects the lives of pregnant women and allows our doctors to perform all necessary life-saving care.  John Pittock said it was a disgrace that the person to whom the Government had bizarrely given responsibility for safeguarding and protecting children should promote the killing of unborn babies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00300"><p>Ridiculous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00400"><p>He is blunt but he is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00500"><p>It is rubbish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00600"><p>The contradiction is both bizarre and disturbing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00700"><p>I would not say it is rubbish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00800"><p>There has been very little in the media about it.  Ms Zappone's views on this issue, while she is a fine politician in many respects-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J00900"><p>Dr. Zappone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J01000"><p>Dr. Zappone's views are much more serious and disturbing than anything said by George Hook in recent times, but got much less commentary.  We should have a debate on it even while we are discussing this issue at the committee.  Such a default by a member of the Executive in the area of authentic human rights and the protection of all people in our society should not go unremarked on in these Houses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J01100"><p>Women can be in charge of cars but not their own bodies, then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J01200"><p>I call Senator Neale Richmond.  We are not having a debate now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J01300"><p>I rise briefly today to discuss, once again, another European issue.  Every time we talk about Europe at the moment, it relates to Brexit, and rightly so.  While the negotiations are ongoing and the British prepare to leave the European Union, Europe itself is preparing to change.  We need to discuss it in much greater detail and depth and be aware of it because if we start to take our eye off the ball, we could pay a price in years to come.  Last night, the French President, Emmanuel Macron, gave a lengthy two-hour address laying out his vision for the future of Europe in response to the European Commission White Paper.  He raised many sensible suggestions but also suggestions that might be in the interests of Europe and of Ireland as a whole, such as tax harmonisation, a European military and a European border force.  I call on the Leader to call in the Minister of State, Deputy Helen McEntee, to have a detailed, lengthy debate on the future of Europe in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J01400"><p>On the debate on Brexit, I want to note that the British Labour Party's shadow Secretary of State yesterday endorsed the view that special European status should be given to the North.  That is in line with the findings of Oireachtas reports and a vote in the D&aacute;il.  I would like our Government to put that proposition much more firmly in future.  It is clearly a common sense proposition that is gaining ground.  I note that very welcome development from the potential next British Government and potential next Secretary of State in making that declaration yesterday.</p> <p>On Seanad reform, we have a lovely new room for now but we need a lovely new Seanad.  We have legislation from the Manning report.  Those involved were kind enough to draft the legislation.  It does not require a constitutional referendum.  It is not all that Sinn F&eacute;in would seek but we see it as a massive step forward in winning the hearts and minds of Irish people, including not just those living on this island but also those living abroad.  I cannot understand why that legislation is not being progressed by Government.  I hope that we will see it advance in this term and made law so the next time Members of the Seanad are being elected, the people will vote for them directly and we will have a truly representative Seanad.  Hopefully, we can achieve that.</p> <p>My final comment today is on the issue of flooding in Inishowen.  I ask the Leader to note this.  My hometown is Buncrana.  Two issues there have really devastated and will continue to devastate our community.  We have lost our key community amenity, called Swan Park.  It was a beautiful riverside walk but it has been destroyed.  The estimated cost to restore it is &euro;1 million to &euro;2 million.  It will be closed for the foreseeable future.  It is a huge loss to my community.  Cockhill Celtic is a major junior football club in Donegal.  Over 300 people of various ages utilise its various facilities.  It has eight teams.  Two of its three pitches have been utterly destroyed and cannot be played on.  Hundreds of thousands of euro worth of damage has been done.  In those two instances, we have not got clarity from Government on the financial relief that is going to be required.  I urge the Leader to raise these issues with his colleague, the Minister of State with responsibility for sport, and indeed, the Minister, Deputy Michael Ring.  We need clarification from Government that those two key amenities will be restored.  I appeal to the Leader to get that clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#J01500"><p>I refer to an article about the business of this House that appeared in <i>The Sun </i>newspaper.  It is grossly inaccurate and misleading, and it is under the headline &quot;'Special' allowance call.  Taxpayer faces &euro;1m bill after David Norris get initial green light for Senators to blitz college graduates with leaflets.&quot;  It continues in the usual media fashion of fake arithmetic.  It says that there is going to be a bill of &euro;1 million after I requested money to cover postage so that we could send newsletters to 161,000 former students.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->With stamps now &euro;1, the newspaper multiplied the number of leaflets by that cost and said that it will cost &euro;300,000 a year and &euro;960,000 for the National University of Ireland.  It is absolute total rubbish.  It will cost the taxpayer nothing at all.  I was making an argument about the allowances we are given, which are now monitored, taxed and have to be vouched and so forth.  The major allowance is restricted to hiring public relations firms, expense account lunches and things like that.  It is complete nonsense.  We used to be able to send out newsletters because we got an allowance, in the beginning, of nearly 3,000 envelopes, which is now down to a couple of hundred a month.  It simply cannot accommodate the sending of newsletters.  The situation is that I am just seeking that the allowances which are already granted by the Oireachtas, which would not cover a mass newsletter, be allowed to do so.  I am just suggesting that the allowances we already have, which the taxpayer has accounted for, should be allowed to be used for that purpose.  <br/><br/>One other amusing thing it said was that I was elected with an insignificant vote of in the region of 4,700.  That is approximately what a Senator receives.  One would be damn lucky to get that many first preferences in a D&aacute;il election.  Anyway, <i>The Sun</i>is not noted for accuracy, although regrettably it does come up every day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#K00200"><p>I will call on Senator Paul Coghlan.  The matter of envelopes and so on is a matter for a Houses of the Oireachtas Commission, but the Leader may respond anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#K00300"><p>I would like to briefly refer to the Valentia Island ferry.  This is something which has been there for the last 21 years.  Five families are involved in it.  As we know it links the Victorian capital of Knightstown with the mainland.  It is a five minute crossing.  It is very important for tourism in the south west and, indeed, the local economy.  In 2016 the ferry handled 250,000 passengers and 100,000 cars.  The traffic handled by the 15-car capacity ferry has now reached a stage where more capacity is needed.  The demand is huge.  This is an old vessel.  It is nearly 50 years old.  It needs a modern, efficient replacement which will be able to take coaches.</p> <p>Some research has been done on this issue.  The new vessel would cost &euro;2.83 million.  It was thought it could be financed by a F&aacute;ilte Ireland grant but, unfortunately, EU state aid rules would not deem assistance to this ferry allowable.  I know the Minister, Deputy Ross, met with the directors some time back.  In view of its importance, the directors are prepared to raise &euro;1 million locally to surpass this roadblock.  In the overall scheme of things the balance is not huge.  As it is such an important proposal for tourism and the south west, I urge the Government and the Minister to bridge the gap, so to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#K00400"><p>I am glad to see the Senator moving beyond Killarney.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#K00500"><p>We know how important Killarney is but we must think of the entire south west of this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#K00600"><p>I would like to raise the issue of the report from the review group set up to examine the issues around granting access to the Workplace Relations Commission and the Labour Court to representative bodies of members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na - both the Garda Representative Association, GRA, and the Association of Garda Sergeants and Inspectors, AGSI.  I echo their calls this morning outlining their disappointment at the fact that they will be excluded from both bodies, which is a very retrograde step.  We saw what happened last year when we were held almost at gunpoint, one could say, when garda&iacute; threatened industrial action.  All of a sudden, all the industrial relations mechanisms available to the State were rolled out in order to address that impasse.  We certainly do not want that situation to arise again and it is something that needs to be grasped.</p> <p>If one looks at how members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na are treated, one would be even more disappointed if one looked to members of the Defence Forces.  They were not even granted access to this review group, which is very disappointing and highlights a total lack of respect for members of the Defence Forces and for their representative bodies, the Permanent Defence Force Other Ranks Representative Association, PDFORRA and the Representative Association of Commissioned Officers, RACO.  I ask the Leader to invite both Ministers to the House so that they can outline how issues affecting the welfare of members of both organisations, who serve this State so well and who deserve special recognition for the work which they do, are going to be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#K00700"><p>I had to attend a meeting of the Joint Committee on Education and Skills yesterday during the Order of Business, so I would just like to congratulate Birdhill on winning the Tidy Towns competition and Limerick on receiving its first bronze medal.  It is a big boost to all the volunteers who are out weekly cleaning the streets and so on.</p> <p>The main issue I want to raise today is the overcrowding at University Hospital Limerick.  I know we are having a debate in the afternoon on the mid-term capital review, but I think it is time we called in the Minister for Health because, not only is this issue affecting Limerick, but it is affecting the mid-west region as well.  The highest amount of overcrowding is in University Hospital Limerick.  The new accident and emergency department only opened in May of 2017 and yet there were 22 people waiting for admission to beds in wards and almost 40 people on trolleys who were treated in the new accident and emergency department.  There are so many people dependant on this hospital.  It is time that the beds which are so necessary to expand services for the region be put in place as a matter of urgency, both in University Hospital Limerick and in St. John's Hospital, Limerick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#K00800"><p>I echo the inquiries made of the Leader by Senators Grace O'Sullivan and Padraig Mac Lochlainn in respect of the Seanad reform process.  We need some clarity on this issue.</p> <p>The main thing I want to say is that I echo what Senator Neale Richmond had to say about the need for this House to have a really good debate on Ireland's approach to the future of Europe.  When one looks at Emmanuel Macron and his words yesterday, most of what he is proposing is deeply hostile to Ireland's interests.  It is about time people started saying so in public.  There are such-and-such class battleships and such-and-such class destroyers.  I refer to him and some other Heads of State as Bambi-class politicians.  They are photogenic and seem to be cleaner than clean, but they come from nowhere.  He is an accident of the French political system.  Were it not for the fact that the front runner for the Republicans in France made an absolute mess of his campaign, Emmanuel Macron would never have surfaced.  When push came to shove, his views on Europe were a minority view in France.  Some 80% of the votes cast in the primaries for the French presidential election were cast for people who radically disagreed with his agenda for Europe - the extreme left candidate and the two other candidates, including Marine Le Pen.  </p> <p>It is about time that we stand up to the European federalists who are trying to push Europe down the road to a united states of Europe.  Guy Verhofstadt has written a book which says that we need to create a united states of Europe with a single army and a single this and a single that.  The great majority of Irish people are wholly opposed to these kinds of proposals.  Our Constitution prohibits us from participating, for instance, in European defence.  Let us get real for a change.  Let us have a real debate in this House, not a Punch and Judy show where those who are totally against Europe and those who are totally for a federalist Europe knock holes in each other, but a debate for the great majority of decent, sensible people who realise that Europe should continue as an intergovernmental partnership of nation states and who realise that is the model we want.  Let us have an opportunity for Members on every side of this House to express their views honestly on these issues rather than keeping ourselves, through some process of self-censorship, enthralled to people who have extremist views of a federalist kind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#L00100"><p>I have just come from the Youth Work Changes Lives showcase in the Mansion House where the Minister, Deputy Zappone, addressed the crowd.  The Minister concluded her remarks referencing how proud the First D&aacute;il would be of the young people in Ireland today.  The youth population is growing and their needs and aspirations are changing.  They have expectations in areas such as equality, social justice, the rights of women and on the abortion issue.  GCN conducted a poll of 565 young people between the ages of 13 and 24 and 85% of individuals stated they wanted to repeal the eighth amendment, 10% did not know and 5% would vote "No".  Some change is inevitable.  I wonder, however, can Ireland move to a place of economic equality that supports our young people to prosper to achieve their full potential.  Employment, education, social protection supports, housing and mental health are all issues raised by organisations under the umbrella of the National Youth Council of Ireland today.  Their message, in the Mansion House this morning, was invest in our youth population and value their place in society.</p> <p>Eleven thousand young people are long-term unemployed.  Mental health waiting lists are up 40% on last summer.  The poverty rate among young people is double the overall rate and 800 of those who are homeless are between the ages of 18 and 24.  We have to move to a place where young people have housing as of right, and have to respond to that right.</p> <p>In the NYCI pre-budget submission, the total investment requested was &euro;153 million, all aimed at enhancing youth work services, halving long-term youth unemployment, equality for young jobseekers, tackling youth homelessness and greater investment in mental health supports.  The youth population will increase by 11.6% by 2025.  Investment in young people would not only make a difference now but would generate a social and economic dividend in the coming decade.  One million young people will live in this State come 2025.</p> <p>I would encourage all Senators to visit the Mansion House.  The atmosphere is electric and young people are there to tell their own stories.  I would encourage all Senators to attend.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#L00200"><p>I would like the Minister for local government to come to the House.  I spoke at length recently about paid parking in towns and villages, out-of-town shopping centres, and giving planning permission for out-of-town shopping centres and filling stations.  As far as I can see, it is unfair competition for those who are trying to run their businesses in the centre of towns and it is to the detriment of the centre of towns.  As I stated previously, they made the same mistake in England 15 or 20 years ago where it ruined the inner cities of Manchester and London.  We are putting shopping centres on the outskirts of big towns and villages and I have no problem with these coming along.  I note Aldi and Lidl are planning extensions.  I have no problem with them, but we have to think of the traders in the middle of these towns and villages who have customers coming to their shops who have to pay anything from &euro;1 to &euro;2 for the privilege.  Then these traders are paying high rates.  I have a simple way of solving this problem.  If the local authority gives planning permission for out-of-town shopping centres or out-of-town filling stations, they should scrap the parking charges - it is unfair competition - and let the multiple that is coming in subsidise the paid parking in the middle of the town.  That is the way they do it in England.  We need a debate on this issue or we will close down rural Ireland and the centre of small towns and villages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#L00300"><p>We will not have it in the winter.  We are very enlightened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#L00400"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#L00500"><p>I support Senators Richmond and McDowell in their call for a debate soon on the future of Europe and our part in that future.  I say to Senator McDowell one need not go to mainland Europe to come across Bambi-class leaders.  We ourselves have one of them in this country where the colour of his socks seems more important to him than policies and improving the well-being of the community that he is supposed to be leading.</p> <p>I would welcome a debate on Seanad reform.  We have before us a number of proposals, including, at Second Stage, those of Senator McDowell and his colleagues.  However, we need to do this in a reasoned manner.  Just to put it on record here, every one of us in this Chamber is democratically elected under the Constitution.  While we agree there is need for reform, that reform should be meaningful, and if it requires constitutional change then I suggest we should take our time and do it properly.</p> <p>Finally, there is a joint Oireachtas committee established to look at proposals regarding the eighth amendment that came from the Citizens' Assembly.  However, I note already, in this House and in the Lower House, conditioning from one side seems to be going on.  Let us leave the committee to do its business or let us have a full debate here on the eighth amendment and get all the views of this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#L00600"><p>I thank the 18 Members for their contributions to the Order of Business.</p> <p>I will begin with Senator Ardagh.  I join with the Senator and all Senators in collectively working to ensure that we reduce the incidence of cancer among citizens, friends and family members.  It is important that we work together in the national strategy.  Whether it is breast cancer, cervical cancer or colorectal cancer, survival rates are improving.  I would ask all Members to look at the national healthcare quality reporting system survey for this year which points to the improvement.  There have been significant improvements in cancer screening and treatment services.  However, I agree with the Senator that we cannot be complacent.  If there are gaps or deficiencies then we must immediately fill those posts.</p> <p>Senator Ardagh makes reference to public service appointments.  As the Senator spoke, the Minister of State at the Department of Defence, Deputy Kehoe, was announcing permanent recruitment in the Defence Forces.  The previous Government ended the moratorium on employment in the public service.  The Government is employing people.  We have reopened Templemore.  We are hiring more garda&iacute;, doctors, nurses and special assistants.  There is a need to do a lot more, obviously, but it is important that we continue.</p> <p>Regarding the fuel allowance, Senator Ardagh makes a good point.  I would hope that in the budget in a couple of weeks' time we will see an increase in the fuel allowance.  Senator Ardagh is correct that it is a 26-week payment to some of the most vulnerable in society who require to have their houses heated and who want, even in the month of July or August, to have heating on.  The Minister, Deputy Regina Doherty, has made changes to the fuel allowance where one can have it paid in two lump sums.  There are 410,000 people in receipt of the fuel allowance at a cost of &euro;229 million per year.  It is a matter on which we need to see further changes.  I am sure the Senator will join with me in welcoming the changes made by the Minister in regard to the fuel allowance.</p> <p>Senator Boyhan complimented Bord Bia on its food strategy.  The remarks the Senator made show that the country, when it is focused, determined and committed, can do quite well.  Ireland had a score of 79 out of 100.  Bord Bia deserves to be complimented and praised for its work on global food security.  I would be happy to have the Minister, Deputy Creed, come to the House in regard to the matter the Senator raised.</p> <p>Senator Conway-Walsh made reference to the need for more home care packages.  The Senator will find agreement from all sides of the House that there must be investment in home care packages, whether it is home help hours or a combination of what the Senator spoke about.  All of us in politics recognise the importance of keeping people in their homes in their community and being treated at home, and the Senator will find no opposition from this side of the House in that regard.  None of us, certainly on this side of the House, wants to see a privatisation of the service.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As our spokesperson on social protection, Senator Butler has been very strong in advocating on behalf of us with the Minister.  The point Senator Conway-Walsh makes is a valid one and I would be happy to support her in that regard.  </p><p>Senators Grace O'Sullivan, Michael McDowell, Diarmuid Wilson and P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn referred to Seanad reform.  I discussed it yesterday.  There is no ambiguity regarding the Government position.  The former Taoiseach set up the implementation group.  There has been an acceptance by the Government of the need for Seanad reform.  There is a school of thought that, as eminent as Senator McDowell is, his Bill is flawed.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M00200"><p>That was Senator Manning's Bill.  I did not write it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M00300"><p>Senator Mac Lochlainn used the words "kind enough." Well Senator McDowell jumped on the horse.  As I said yesterday, his very fine newsletter, which is being circulated to the Members in Dublin Bay South, speaks about what we can do regarding Seanad reform.  I am very committed to bringing about Seanad reform.  What Members with different viewpoints must recognise is that we live in a democracy and we are democratically elected - regardless of whether Members opposite like it or not.  The question of whether we broaden the franchise from the NUI and Trinity College is a matter on which Senator Mullen and Senator McDowell might have different views.  Senator Norris has a different view from that held by Senator McDowell but I am happy to have the debate on Seanad reform.  I have not blocked Senator McDowell in any way, shape or form.  As I said yesterday, the Taoiseach will be in contact with group leaders.  He has committed to coming to the House to have a discussion on it and I very much welcome that.  I will not be found wanting in that regard.  I think Senator McDowell should recognise that this is not about one person's view or one person having an opinion; it is about the country having an opinion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M00400"><p>On a point of order, I am sorry to interrupt the Leader but I want to make it clear that I have no opposition to the broadening of the franchise.  I may have appeared to the Leader to have winced but that was something else entirely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M00500"><p>He did wince.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M00600"><p>Senator Mullen is a long time in this House; it is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M00700"><p>It should be clear that this is the Government's policy on the Manning report, not mine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M00800"><p>All I am saying is that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M00900"><p>The debate will held another day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01000"><p>Absolutely, but Senator McDowell, as eminently qualified as he is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01100"><p>It is in the programme for Government-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01200"><p>Methinks the Senator protests too much.  I cannot wait to read the <i>Sunday Business Post</i>next Sunday to see his reply.</p><p>I thank Senator Grace O'Sullivan in her absence, for which she apologised as she had to leave, for her very nice postcard over the summer to all Members of the House.  I thought it was a very personal touch and assured us even in a small way the importance of the post office and the stamp.  </p><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in raised the very sensitive and tragic issue of the sad passing of Gavin Coyne and the issue of cardiac care of children.  I would be happy to have that debate in the House.  I sympathise with the family and I am sure we will all join in the debate so that we can improve the services and situation regarding young children in particular.  </p><p>Senator Lombard raised the issue of the structure of local government in Cork.  All of us from Cork recognise the importance of the Mackinnon report.  I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House.  Where we all find agreement is on the need to have the Mackinnon report acted upon, to reach an agreement on what is best for the city and county of Cork and to progress the structure of local government in a way that is beneficial to the development of Cork city and county.  Nobody wants to see an escalation or continuation of the debate.  What we need now is pragmatic compromise and discussion in a meaningful, polite and respectful manner whereby we can put aside our individual or personal differences and recognise the importance of Cork for its people and as a region of growth, employment, tourism and business.  I hope we can do that in a sensible and very formal way.  </p><p>Senator Leyden raised the very important issue of Brexit and the Northern Ireland Executive.  I would be very happy to have that debate.  Regarding the Senator's point about the Executive, I certainly hope the DUP and Sinn F&eacute;in can agree on going back into government.  We have been without an Executive for too long.  I very much hope that Deputy Adams's remarks at the weekend where he said that Sinn F&eacute;in are open to going back into government were not just rhetoric but were meaningful and that we can get both sides, who have been engaged in talks in the background, to come to the table with a final result because it is important.  As Senator Leyden rightly noted, now that we are entering into the critical part of Brexit talks, it is vital that the voice of people in Northern Ireland is heard by democratically elected politicians.  I know Senator Conway-Walsh will bring those remarks back.  </p><p>Senator Mullen referred to Saudi Arabia.  We all welcome the movement towards equality in all parts of the world and I am glad that the Senator is now very able to articulate the views of women in Saudi Arabia.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01300"><p>I hope they do not have to wait as long as people do for Irish driver tests.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01400"><p>As Senator McDowell knows, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport from the Independent Alliance was a member of the Independent grouping here.  I am sure the Senator can have a word with him regarding that but the issue of driver tests is one that we all want to see solved with testing expedited because it is unfair on the many thousands of motorists and young motorists in particular who are waiting to be tested.</p> <p>Senator Mullen raised the resignation of John Pittock from the audit committee of the Department of Children and Youth Affairs.  It goes back to Senator Wilson's point.  Can we stop introducing red herrings in the debate?  Senator Mullen knows that I am on the Joint Committee on the Eighth Amendment of the Constitution, as is he, and he recognises that I am reasonably open-minded and fair and want to see a balanced debate referred to Senator Wilson.  There is conditioning on both sides, regardless of whether or not the Senator likes it.  Each side is particularly good at whipping up levels of activity and rhetoric.  Regarding the resignation of Mr. Pittock, the audit committee has no relationship with the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs.  It has no function regarding Government policy or the views of the Minister so if we could-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.118" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01600"><p>I did not interrupt the Senator and I accept his right to make the comment but we should go down the road of tangential commentary.  This is a very sensitive matter-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01700"><p>It is important.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01800"><p>I am entitled to my view.  Let us have that debate in a respectful manner.  I would be very happy to have the debate because it is one we need to have in a respectful and tolerant manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M01900"><p>Is the Leader promising a debate on that because I raised an important point about the inappropriateness of a member of the Executive having those views given that she is responsible for children?  It is a simple point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02000"><p>The Senator is doing it again.  He did it in the past and is trying to do it again.  I ask him not to do it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02100"><p>That is just a rhetorical device.  It is a serious point about human rights and human rights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02200"><p>I am too.  This is about an issue - a constitutional matter - not about a personal view of a Minister or an individual Member of any House of the Oireachtas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02300"><p>The Minister has very radical views.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02400"><p>The Minister is entitled to her opinion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02500"><p>Through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02600"><p>It has not impacted on her doing her work.  She is a very fine Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02700"><p>In other ways, yes, but in this way, sadly, it is a disgrace.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#M02800"><p>Senators Richmond, Wilson and McDowell also raised the issue of the future of Europe.  I would be very happy to have that debate and it is important that we have that debate.  I agree wholeheartedly with Senator McDowell in the context of some of the "Johnny come latelies" and the movement towards federalism.  The Senator is right.  The remarks of President Macron on Monday were very hostile to what we stand for and what we want to see in this country in terms of the EU.  I agree with the Senator on a personal level.  I very much want to have that debate.  I think Senators Wilson and Richmond are right.  I would be very happy to invite the Minister of State, Deputy McEntee, to come to the House to discuss that issue separately from the issue of Brexit.  It is a debate that we should have in the short term.</p> <p>Senator Mac Lochlainn raised the issue of flooding in Donegal.  I again thank the emergency services, the first responders and the local communities in Donegal for their response and their work regarding the desperate plight of many residents in Donegal.  Of course, things can be done better, as the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, said in the D&aacute;il last night but the Government responded and was very proactive regarding the issue of flooding.  I would be very happy to take Senator Mac Lochlainn's comments back but I reiterate that there are schemes available for home owners, community groups and sporting and voluntary organisations.  The closing date for applications for funding is 30 September.  The point made by the Senator is that irrespective of politics, we need to see how we can respond better in all situations to tragedies.</p> <p>Senator Norris referred to the issue of entitlements, expenses, letters and envelopes.  This is an issue for the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission and the Seanad CPP, so I will leave it at that.  </p> <p>Senator Coghlan raised the issue of the Valentia Island ferry.  He might be best placed to raise it as a Commencement matter but I would be happy to allow for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to come to the House.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Senator Gallagher raised the issue of the report of the review group on industrial relations structures in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, which was presented to the Government this week.  The Government has considered the report and has approved the drafting of legislation that will, when internal industrial relations mechanisms are in place, give the Garda Association access, by right, to the Workplace Relations Commission and the Labour Court.  It will be a priority for the Government.  The issue of Garda strikes is a contentious and sensitive one.  My personal view is that garda&iacute; should not be allowed to go on strike; they are defenders of the State.  I would, however, be happy to have the Minister for Justice and Equality to come to the House to discuss the legislation when it is ready.  I commend the working group chaired by Mr. John Murphy, which made a number of recommendations on the future of industrial relations for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  </p><p>Senator Maria Byrne congratulated Birdhill on its success in the all-Ireland TidyTowns competition.  We all join her in congratulating Birdhill.  I congratulate Carrigaline and Douglas on their final results in the competition and I commend all who were involved in it.  It is volunteers who go out on many a wet and horrible morning cleaning, planting and tending to local public spaces.  I commend them on that.</p><p>I would be happy to have the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, come to the House regarding University Hospital Limerick, which has grown exponentially.  Senator Maria Byrne has raised this on many occasions here.</p><p>Senator Warfield asked for a debate on youth and their future role in our country.  I would be happy to have that.  I commend all those who work with youth groups.  Unfortunately, we could not get to the Mansion House this morning to the showcase on youth work.  The Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Katherine Zappone, was in attendance.  I commend all who were involved and thank them for their work.</p><p>Senator Butler raised the very important issue of the growth of shopping centres and white goods stores on the peripheries of towns and urban areas, including Cork city.  The Senator has made a very good point in that we need to incentivise people to come into our large towns and cities, such as Cork city.  Cork City Council has incentivised parking for the period up to Christmas, whereby we will see free car parking in certain cark parks in the morning and also late at night.  There will also be a park-and-ride facility for six weeks.  Senator Butler is correct that there needs to be a progressive campaign to attract people back into our large towns, which were the heartbeat and hub of rural Ireland.  Unfortunately, in some cases, because of planning, we have allowed shopping centres to emerge on the peripheries.  I would be happy to have the debate.</p><p>I thank the Senators for their contributions.  We have many requests for debates and we will endeavour, in the coming weeks, to have them put on the cl&aacute;r.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.133" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.134" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.35 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.135" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#W00100">Mid-Term Review of Capital Plan: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#W00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#W00300"><p>I welcome the opportunity to address the Seanad in its new surroundings.  Now that Senators are here, possession is nine tenths of the law.  In fairness, it is a beautiful room and I compliment whoever organised it during the summer and everybody who worked on it.  However long or short it is intended that the Seanad will located be here, I wish Senators the best of luck.</p> <p>Included in A Programme for a Partnership Government is a commitment to increase public capital investment in the remaining period of the capital plan to 2021, to be allocated on the basis of the outcome of a review of the capital plan.  In my contribution I will outline the process that has taken place as part of the mid-term review, the main themes and findings the analysis has produced and the next steps in developing a longer term ten-year national investment plan.  I would also like to discuss the efficiency of capital investment in Ireland and how we can ensure value for money will be achieved from the investments made.  This is an issue that is all too often forgotten but which is of critical importance in delivering the infrastructure our society and economy so badly needs.</p> <p>The mid-term review of the capital plan was launched in January and conducted over the course of the year.  Its objective was to provide a robust evidence base that would guide and inform the decisions made on capital allocations at budget time in October.  It will also be an important input to the long-term ten-year national investment plan which will be finalised before the end of the year.  It has now been published and provides a detailed evidence base for the allocation of the &euro;4.1 billion of additional funding available in the period to 2021 and subsequently the new ten-year national investment plan in the light of the infrastructural deficits identified through the analysis undertaken in the review.</p> <p>The evidence base for the review includes detailed submissions by Departments and offices, an extensive public consultation process and an infrastructure capacity and demand analysis completed by the Irish Government Economic and Evaluation Service, IGEES, in the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  It is important to note that in terms of the conduct of the review, it was a matter, in the first instance, for each Department to identify its sectoral priorities and specific projects.  Departmental submissions were received by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform earlier this year and these recommendations will play an important role in ensuring the additional funding will be aligned with the relevant sectoral priorities.  The review examines a number of key issues relating to public capital investment in Ireland such as the rationale and objectives of public capital investment, the efficiency of public capital investment and steady State funding and the sustainability of increased public capital investment.</p> <p>Based on all of the evidence and analysis, the review of the capital plan identified a number of key sectoral infrastructural priorities, including, in transport, the maintenance and upgrading of the road network, as well as public transport; in education, higher education and the schools building programme; in health, subject to further analysis, the totality of health capacity and infrastructure; and, in housing, on the basis of the review of the action plan for housing and homelessness.  The Government will make final decisions on the allocation of the additional capital resources in advance of publication of the Estimates for 2018.</p> <p>Following the allocation of funding for increased capital investment in the 2018 Estimates, a new ten-year national investment plan will be published before the end of the year for the period 2018 to 2027.  The key priority for the ten-year plan will be to secure the coherence of long-term and strategic sectoral objectives with the planned new spatial configuration in the national planning framework.  Drawing on key strategic sectoral objectives outlined by Departments and in line with international precedents, the longer term focus of over five years will be largely thematic.  The ten-year national investment plan will also include proposals for structural reform of public investment in the planning, selection and delivery of capital projects.  It will be informed by the public investment management assessment, PIMA, undertaken by the International Monetary Fund, IMF, in July 2017.  An IMF PIMA evaluates the design and effectiveness of the institutions that shape decision-making at the three key stages of the public investment cycle - planning investment, allocating investment to the right sectors and implementing investment.  All of this work being carried out by the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform will ensure the additional capital resources available will be targeted at the priority public capital infrastructure required to support Ireland&rsquo;s medium-term growth potential and underpin social cohesion.</p> <p>Based on previous discussions, I expect all those present to agree that increasing capital investment in public infrastructure in the coming years is crucial for Ireland&rsquo;s future development.  It is, therefore, a moot point to a certain extent.  However, simply increasing capital expenditure will not, in and of itself, result in all of the infrastructure deficits being addressed in the short term.  Clearly, there are constraints on the economy&rsquo;s capacity to deliver capital  infrastructure in a given year.  Increasing the efficiency of public investment will allow us to deliver greater levels of infrastructure.  It is critical that we plan and prioritise our investment in a sustainable manner based on robust research and evidence, something that has not always happened in the past.  In the period to 2008, capital investment was ramped up to unprecedented levels.  Research from the ESRI has called into question the efficiency of the investment in that period and whether value for money was achieved, given the overheating and price inflation in the construction sector.  Since that time the Office for Government Procurement has been established, the Government&rsquo;s economic and evaluation service has been established and the public spending code has been developed.  The recent publication of a capital projects tracker on the website of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, alongside the capital review, will also help to bring to the public greater transparency and certainty on the major projects planned for delivery.  Furthermore, the Government&rsquo;s intention to develop a long-term approach to capital investment will provide clarity, confidence and certainty for the construction sector to plan for providing the capacity and capability required to deliver the infrastructure on a value for money basis in the coming years.</p> <p>It is very important in examining capital investment that we shift the debate away from an exclusive focus on individual projects.  To make better use of the resources available for public capital investment we must support the continued development of a culture of evaluation in which projects will be subject to a full  project appraisal consistent with the requirements outlined in the public spending code.  This was a key theme in the submission made by the Committee on Budgetary Oversight on the capital review.  The mid-term review of the capital plan was a detailed and comprehensive process.  It provides us with an evidence base to debate and, I hope, come to some conclusions on what sectors of investment merit prioritisation in allocating the additional funding available.</p> <p>The review of the capital plan also highlights some key themes that will closely inform and be incorporated into the analysis leading to the finalisation of the new ten-year national investment plan.  A discussion of these themes may also be beneficial.  They include confirmation of the central role of public capital investment in underpinning the economy&rsquo;s long-term growth potential and addressing overheating risks, as well as supporting social progress; the need to align public capital investment priorities with the changing demographic profile; the critical importance of public capital infrastructure in meeting the essential  requirement for balanced regional growth and promoting the societal transformation required to achieve climate action objectives; the mechanisms through which public investment can strengthen the economy&rsquo;s resilience to major risks such as Brexit; the central importance of robust mechanisms to support the efficiency public capital investment to ensure the public infrastructure and services delivered through capital expenditure will be secured on a value for money basis; and the strong business case for ensuring public capital spending will be balanced between new projects and maintaining the quality and capacity of existing public capital infrastructure.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Patrick O'Donovan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2316"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2316&amp;amp;pid=PatrickODonovan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->As a Government, we are very interested in listening to the perspective of all Senators here today about these critically important issues.  I look forward to a constructive session ahead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#X00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  He is very welcome to our new Chamber.  It is my first time speaking in it.  A fine body of work has been done.  I would not mention too much about possession being nine tenths of the law.  The Minister might frighten a few people.  Those were his words and not mine.  I am sure we will be looking forward to going back to our new Chamber-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#X00300"><p>The Senators are in now anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#X00400"><p>-----as soon as possible.  I welcome the opportunity to speak on the mid-term review of the plan.  It was announced with much fanfare in 2015 about the period from 2016 to 2021.  We are only one year into it.  It is probably not really a mid-term review, but a review of the early part of the term.  Unfortunately, the announcement in 2015 did not say much.  There was much fanfare but unfortunately the substance has not yet been delivered.  The Government would like us to believe that it is the saviour of capital investment but, unfortunately, nothing could be further from the truth.  The Government has much spin and so on involved, but we need to look at what is happening on the ground.</p> <p>Capital expenditure has suffered extensively from austerity, as we know.  It was only last year that capital expenditure exceeded the level of 2000 and 2001.  Meanwhile, our secondary and minor road network are at breaking point, our national broadband roll-out is faltering and we have a crippling housing crisis.  A whooping &euro;4.5 billion in capital, to be fair, has been allocated to housing, yet very little has happened and very little has been delivered.  It is true to say that units do not appear overnight and we all understand that, but we need to address it in a speedier fashion.  The Government needs to return to building social and affordable housing as it has over many generations, including in many times in the past when we did not have many resources.</p> <p>There is hardly a debate in this Chamber that does not involve the mention of Brexit.  Brexit is certainly very important to be considered in the context of the mid-term capital review.  It is one of the most significant geopolitical challenges that we have ever faced.  Rural areas, particularly in the Border and midland regions, face very real threats as a result of a potential hard Brexit.  While we all wish for there to not be a hard Brexit, it is very hard to reconcile the idea of not being in the customs union and yet wanting to have no border.  Everybody says that they want no border, but I think it would be very difficult for us to have no hard border while simultaneously having the UK leave the customs union.</p> <p>It is fair to say that we have had a two-tier recovery in Ireland and that parts of the country have done better in the last number of years than others.  It is vital that both the national planning framework and the capital plan reflect this and help to drive development in the regions.  As somebody based in Dublin who was a councillor for many years in Dublin but who has four country grandparents, it is not in Dublin's interests for everything to happen in Dublin.  It adds to further congestion and pressure on prices of housing and services generally, including schools, green areas, sports clubs and so on.  As many other speakers will allude to better than me, rural areas simultaneously face population decline and it is difficult to maintain services, schools and roads with a falling population.</p> <p>Capital investment since 2008 has been abysmal and it has not met demographic needs or demands.  Over the next decades, Ireland&rsquo;s population is expected to reach unprecedented levels with some predicting a population of over 8 million by 2040.  Fianna F&aacute;il believes that the national planning framework and the capital plan should be integrated better to meet the needs of the country.  The Government plans to release the national planning framework and the capital review at the same time.  We believe that the national planning framework should provide the overarching objectives for the country and the capital plan should feed into those objectives.  Further, we believe there should be a national infrastructure commission that would prioritise major capital investment in the context of the objectives outlined in the national planning framework.  This would ensure that all aspects of Government policy go in the same direction.  Both the national planning framework and the capital plan must have a balanced regional perspective.  This means spreading economic development throughout the country.  It is fair to give credit today when the M18 is opening and acknowledge that work is being done.  We are more than willing to acknowledge the work that is being done when it is being done but we also point out that we need more.</p> <p>In Ireland, we have had a two-tier recovery.  It is not good for urban areas and it is very poor for rural areas.  Rural areas are crying out for fear of their population and it is important that we try to give those areas a lift and to give them the advantages that they need to compete for investment.  Of course, one is not necessarily going to get Google, Facebook or eBay in a small rural town, but we need to try to get more employment opportunities outside the greater Dublin area, as well as ensuring that we strengthen Dublin, which I will address in a moment.  Commuting and travel times represent one of the most practical and quantifiable measures under which the greater Dublin area can improve its international offering.  To reduce congestion in Dublin, metro north and DART underground need to be advanced and prioritised.  A brand new town in Clonburris is proposed.  It is going through planning at the moment.  It is near Clondalkin.  Equally, Cherrywood strategic development zone, SDZ, in my former county council area of D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown is progressing but major infrastructure is needed to accommodate 8,000 homes, with almost 20,000 people living in both areas.  They need to be given the quality of life that they deserve for the 21st century town that we are building.  It is a great opportunity but we need to ensure that the required capital investment is there.  I mentioned before to the Minister that the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan, formerly worked with, Deputy Shane Ross, that the Luas green line is fairly full most of the time at Cherrywood already, and that we are going to put 20,000 people at the end of it.  When he was last in here, the Minister said that it could be addressed, but there is nothing concrete.</p> <p>Page 63 of the capital plan review addresses the Minister of State's former Department.  I am not saying this because of Deputy O'Donovan; it is really in reference to the Minister, Deputy Shane Ross.  The part on transport, tourism and sport is full of vague aspirations.  There is nothing concrete or solid in it.  There is about half a page on page 63 about an overall package of measures, "which focuses on areas that are supported by direct Exchequer investment", but nothing concrete about what we are doing or how.  We need to face up to the challenges of congestion, not just with regard to quality of life, but the fact that we need to be able to get people to move around efficiently.  The Dublin Chamber of Commerce made a very detailed and comprehensive submission to the mid-term review of the capital investment plan.  It is over 18 pages.  I am sure the Minister of State has had a chance to study it.  It talks about a new approach to capital expenditure and Ireland's long-term needs, both for urban and rural Ireland, the short-term investment priorities and so on.  I am sure it will be taken into account in the overall production of the mid-term review, but there is a lot of very good stuff in it and I think we need to make sure that we include many of its points because they are very well made.</p> <p>I saw that Senator O'Donnell was here earlier and he never misses a change to mention the M20 and the proposal for it.  I am sure he will mention it if he is back later.  It is very important that we connect our second and third largest cities with a quality road network.  Broadband is also a huge issue.  It is a much bigger issue for areas outside of Dublin than it is in Dublin.  The recent withdrawal of SIRO from the tender process further undermines whatever planning we had for the roll-out of broadband.</p> <p>We should also mention public private partnerships, PPPs.  We had Andrew McDowell at the finance committee.  He is somebody the Minister of State would be very familiar with.  He is the vice-president of the European Investment Bank.  He talked about how it had money there, ready to go, but that we had limits on how many PPPs we could have.  That is restricting the amount of money available for investment.  We need to have more projects.  We can look at whether PPPs work.  Some work and some did not work so well but the concept should not be thrown out entirely.  We must make sure that we have more growth and more ambition.  The 10% rule makes it very difficult.  Conor O&rsquo;KeIly of the National Treasury Management Agency, NTMA, indicated that the use of public private partnerships can lock in exceptionally low interest rates for a long period of time.  We also need to look at the Juncker plan and the European Investment Bank, as I mentioned.  It is available and willing.  Its representatives came into our Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach and said that the funds are there and that we just need to harness them at relatively modest interest rates.</p> <p>We also have Ireland Strategic Investment Fund, ISIF, with over &euro;6 billion in foreign investments.  Perhaps we could divest ourselves of some of those foreign investments and redirect that money into our own economy.  We could then have further improvements in our infrastructure.</p> <p>There are other issues that we could cover and I am conscious of the time.  We need to make sure that the European fiscal rules are adjusted.  We should say that productive capital investment is not the same as giving everyone revenue bonuses and so on with regard to current spending.  We need to tackle the infrastructure crisis.  We need to make sure that we deliver on behalf of all of our citizens and that our country is ready for the population growth we have, for the fact that people are living longer and that our population is growing very significantly.  There are difficulties in schools, roads and so on.  I welcome the review today.  It is timely that we are here.  Some progress has been made but we have a lot more to do.  We wish the Minister of State the best with it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerry Horkan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2476"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2476&amp;amp;pid=GerryHorkan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The regions and Dublin need very significant investment in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Y00200"><p>Before I call Senator Mulherin, I welcome to the Distinguished Visitors' Gallery our former colleague, Senator Michael Mullins, from County Galway.  Michael is very welcome.  He was a most productive Member of the Seanad over five years.  I know he is only taking temporary respite from the House and he will be back.  He is very welcome and it is good to see him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Y00300"><p>I am standing in for my colleague, Senator Paddy Burke, who will be here later.  I also recognise Senator Michael Mullins in the Chamber.</p><p>The Minister of State has outlined the capital review and the next steps.  We are down to kernel of the matter, namely, what our priorities will be for the &euro;4.1 billion additional investment in capital spending which will be available between 2018 and 2021 and what the focus will be for the next ten years under the capital investment plan.  It is about priorities.  It exists in tandem with the new national planning framework which is still in draft form but we expect will come into existence by the end of the year.</p><p>I will outline an approach I believe would be helpful to simplify and achieve the Government's objectives outlined by the Minister for Finance in his introductory statement to the mid-term capital review.  In his address he referred to balanced regional development and said this mid-term capital review was essential.  Thanks to policies pursued by the Government, we are in a totally different economic space.  There is the issue of responding to demographic change and why the population is declining in certain areas.  Much of the elbow power which the Government has is in its capital expenditure along with other policies such as the Action Plan for Jobs, agencies and so on.  The most significant way of shaping the country comes from the capital investment programme.</p><p>All things are not equal in the country.  I agree there has been a two-tier recovery.  Looking back to the last national spatial strategy, it had some good objectives and it identified some good things.  Among many areas which are quite far behind, it is not the case that they have been left behind or have not experienced the recovery.  We have seen a significant drop in unemployment, but these groups did not experience any investment under the national spatial strategy which was at least 15 years ago.  They have been coming from behind and this is compounded because some areas which had capital investment in roads, broadband and so on, can now rise more easily and are more able to attract private and public investment.  </p><p>As priorities are being considered for 2021, and in ten years' time, these areas which did not experience delivery should be on the top of that list.  These are predominantly rural areas.  The west and north west is a unique region - I understand there may be areas of Kerry and west Cork whose experience may be similar - where there is no major interurban routes, no high-speed trains and no major ports in the north-north west.  It has not had the delivery.  </p><p>The report highlights historic investment.  Can we have figures for historic capital investment in the regions, not only under the current and previous Governments but the one before?  Based on looking at things on the ground, I am sure there is an anomaly and there has not been balanced regional development.  We will not achieve our objectives for rural Ireland, with all the fine plans, such as the action plan for rural Ireland, the regional action plan for jobs, unless at a strategic level we invest in this infrastructure.  It is not all equal on the table.  There are figures, and I am asking the Minister of State for them.  It cannot be like before when one project is cherry-picked and another is not.  There is a case to be made and I am asking for the data for previous levels of capital investment.  The national primary roads into these areas should be invested in.</p><p>On the objective of renewing rural Ireland, the current economic model from which we work will continue to work against rural Ireland unless we change it.  That is reflected in the national planning framework which has been published.  It clearly envisages growth in cities.  We recognise that but that is happening everywhere, it is in Ireland, the UK, Europe and around the world.  People are drawn to the cities for work.  Let us say there are two reasons someone would choose to work in an area, because it is an attractive area and there is work available.  Rural Ireland is a fantastic place to live, I live there.  There has been massive investment by the Government, including the sports capital grant administered by the Minister of State in his previous role from which we see the finest sports facilities around.  We see great community effort and great clean places to live which are aesthetically pleasing.  We have schools and empty houses.  We have schools that need more pupils or will lose a teacher, yet there is the opposite problem in the cities where they are seriously congested.  We must take a holistic look at the problem.  The economic model we have where we identify something that is needed in an area is just a short-term response.  There is rural decline.  Populations have declined in Donegal and Mayo in the last census.  It is the young people who have gone to the cities.  These people are looking for housing in the cities.  They want their children to go to school and cannot get places for them and the list of problems goes on.  The challenge is for us to encourage the idea that rural areas are areas to invest in and then there will be more work.  </p><p>The report refers to rates of return economically and socially.  This argument that there will not be critical mass is one I often here from Dublin economists, but there will not be critical mass in rural Ireland because people cannot live on fresh air.  It is beautiful but one cannot live on that, especially when one is a young person.  We all know about the problems of young people being unemployed and it is the same where the Leas-Chathaoirleach is from.  The north-north west is in a difficult situation unless something radical is done.  I am glad that my fellow county man, Deputy Michael Ring, has been appointed the new Minister for Rural and Community Development and I do not doubt his intention to get something done, but he cannot do it by himself.  There has to be fresh thinking.  I agree that we need to see research and evidence but I ask the Minister of State to tell us the historic investment in the region.  What is the <i>per capita</i>investment compared with that of the tax take of the region.  I believe there is proportionately less investment compared with the taxes paid in the north-north west.  We need data on this.  I have not been able to get data.</p><p>An organisation that has been identified as being in a position to advise the Government on policy is the Western Development Commission.  It is on the ground supporting businesses and doing great work but it does not have the wherewithal to come up with its own data, do economic analysis and give a perspective on economics that is not Dublin-centric.  That is what is going on.  I ask that it be charged with doing this and feeding in information and data such as how much investment the region is getting compared with tax paid, how much capital investment it has enjoyed, and then we can put all this information into the mix.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->At the moment, we need this sort of arm.  As well as having the Minister and our action plan for rural Ireland, we need an overarching input and a change from the mindset which is prevalent and which I have encountered on panel discussions.  It is a mindset that says "sure, we haven't got the population in rural Ireland.  What are you doing that for?" and then they all come to the cities.  Are we really going to change it or is just tourism?  I believe there is great potential, including on the IT and life sciences side.  I know the Minister will be familiar with them but there needs to be some further measure or what is happening at the moment will continue, which is migration to the cities and an undermining of rural Ireland.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for being here.  The last input was extremely interesting.  It outlines what we have received in 100 years of Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael in the regions and the desperate state the regions are in, particularly-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z00300"><p>The Senator might want to check her history.  She used the term "100 years".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z00400"><p>Well, almost 100 years but we will not split hairs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z00500"><p>I know that some people like to rewrite it but writing it before it exists is a different matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z00600"><p>The Senator gets what I mean.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z00700"><p>I am trying to be helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z00800"><p>The Senator is always trying to be helpful.  It is very interesting when a Government colleague stands up and tells the Minister of State straight that what the Government is doing is not working, that what it has done previously has not worked, that rural Ireland is left behind and that this capital review needs to do something drastic and needs a new approach.  I certainly agree with that.  In fact, I think it needs a new Government to deliver it but that is for another day, hopefully, not before too long.</p><p>Every single expert who has expressed a view has said that the State is in need of a massive capital investment programme.  We are coming from a very low base so the Government should ensure that whatever fiscal space that might exist is not frittered away on tax cuts but put to good long-term use in extra capital spend.  Unfortunately, the stated position of those in power is that rather than invest, they think we can spare a good chunk of the fiscal space towards tax cuts.</p><p>When the Minister was appointed, he received a brief from Department officials which stated clearly with regard to the capital plan:</p><blockquote>Many commentators criticised what they saw as an insufficiently ambitious programme.  If the economy grows continuously over the next several years, pressure on economic infrastructure will increase and there may be merit in reviewing these plans.  The overall housing supply challenge is certain to lead to demands for increased levels of capital and current expenditure investment in social housing.  We would support additional resources for housing and housing related infrastructure.  </blockquote> <p>The same year, the global competitiveness report ranked inadequate supply of infrastructure as the most problematic factor for doing business in Ireland.  That was the challenge put before the Minister and the Government but they have not risen to it.  The Minister can spin figures all he likes but the fact remains that this Government is putting tax cuts above the long-term investment the country requires.  Its policies are precisely the type of short-term thinking that will lead to another mess.  Both the Seanad and the D&aacute;il debate Brexit a lot.  The one thing that is completely within our control in order to fend off the challenge of Brexit is to invest - that is the one tool we have - yet it is bottom of the list.  Long-term economic visions do not win votes.  This is the blunt and short-sighted calculation being made by this Government.  </p><p>The Government's capital investment plan puts capital investment at just 2.16% of GNP for 2018, which is a shockingly low level of capital investment and both reckless and unsustainable.  It will also ensure that our capital investment remains one of the lowest in the EU.  The Government will spin that this new programme will move us up that list.  Well, this is exactly where we need to be anyway; we have a younger demographic profile than many other countries.  The lack of ambition in the capital plan programme is a lack of ambition for the country.  It is literally putting a cap on how much growth we can achieve.</p><p>I welcome the review of the capital programme.  Sinn F&eacute;in's manifesto represented a substantial plan for the coming years.  I accept some more money is going to go into capital but we must remember that the interpretation of the fiscal rules allows for smoothing of some capital spend over four years.  That is all the more important in a tight year for fiscal space like this one.  When the Minister stands before us in October and announces tax cuts, we must recall that every euro in tax cuts he announces amounts to &euro;4 that could be spent next year on our schools, hospitals or roads.  That is the Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il choice and it is the wrong one.  The fiscal rules are a bad idea and are now, as Sinn F&eacute;in said they would, preventing necessary investment in our country.  Has the Minister even raised the need for an exemption for Ireland for at least capital spending over the coming years, including the repayment of the &euro;64 billion that was taken to fund the banks?  This should be argued for anyway but especially so in light of Brexit.  However, how we argue for that in Brussels when it sees the Government giving out tax cuts when it could be spending four times that amount on investment?</p><p>The Government plans to spend &euro;70 million on flood defences next year increasing to &euro;100 million by 2021.  Is this the type of thing that can wait?  The pre-fab replacement scheme could be accelerated so that our children are not taught in rundown schools.  I could go on.  Regional imbalance must be addressed.  In the past number of weeks, we saw the example of the regional hospital in Galway and the department where all procedures had to be cancelled because a roof fell in.  Anyone who has visited the regional hospital in Galway knows that staff are doing Trojan work but the infrastructure is falling around them and is not fit for purpose.  Again, we see the opportunities relating to Ireland West Airport Knock that are lost without proper investment in the airport.  Broadband is another example.  We can see the jobs and opportunities for the west of Ireland that are lost.  Roads are a further example.  I know there was an announcement of more LIS funding for roads at the National Ploughing Championships but when one breaks that down, it breaks down to about two roads for every councillor in a 100-mile radius.  The extension of the greenways is another example.  Capital investment is needed in all these areas to generate jobs and regenerate our rural economy.  The negative consequences of the &quot;start-stop&quot; approach to many infrastructure projects are not the way forward - things being announced, re-announced and re-announced.  The people in rural Ireland and Ireland as a whole are fed up waiting for vital infrastructure.  It should be provided for under this plan. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z00900"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I regard this as a very important and critical debate.  We have come out of a period of great difficulty where our country was bankrupt and where we were effectively borrowing to keep the lights on.  We have now reached a stage where we are returning to full employment.  We must get back to what would be the normal levers of Government, one of those being putting capital projects in place.  I have a small bit of housekeeping first.  In his speech, the Minister of State said that a new ten-year national plan for 2018 to 2027 will be published before the end of the year.  Could he indicate when he expects that to happen?  Will it be part of the budgetary process to be announced on budget day?  Alternatively, will it be a separate announcement?  When will that take place?</p> <p>I will speak about local issues in the area I represent in Limerick in the limited time I have.  People will know of my personal interest in the M20 Limerick to Cork motorway.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.154" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z01100"><p>Senator O'Donnell, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#Z01200"><p>All help would be welcomed.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kieran O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2207"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2207&amp;amp;pid=KieranODonnell&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I looked at the submissions made in the context of the mid-term review and a substantial proportion of them referenced the M20 project.  Coming from Limerick, the Minister of State will know just how important that road project is in having an Atlantic corridor which links Cork, through Limerick, with Galway as a counterpoint to Dublin.  The new Tuam-Gort bypass is being opened today, which is very welcome.  We see it as another link.  It should be possible to travel from Cork to Limerick in an hour and also from Limerick to Galway in an hour.  Therefore, the journey from Cork to Galway should take no longer than two hours.  A substantial part of the planning process was completed by November 2011 and preliminary work by Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, is ongoing, which will allow the project to advance.  I hope that in the new plan to be announced following the mid-term capital review the M20 project will be a priority.  The work could be done on a staged basis.  In 2011 the preferred route was via Croom, Charleville, Buttevant and Mallow.  The section from Limerick to Mallow is key and should be stage one.  The M20 project is critical from the point of view of connectivity.  It is also critical from a safety perspective because there are fatalities on the N20 far too regularly.  If we are to speak meaningfully about the need for balanced regional development, we cannot do so without the M20 being in place.  </p><p>While the new emergency department in University Hospital Limerick is very welcome, there is a hospital beds capacity issue.  When the reconfiguration took place, the emergency departments in Ennis, Nenagh and St. John's hospitals were closed, which meant that 50 beds were taken out of the system.  As part of the reconfiguration, a new 138-bed unit was to be built via a public private partnership on the grounds of University Hospital Limerick, but it never came to pass.  We have secured funding through the HSE to progress the design phase for a 90-bed acute unit alongside the emergency department.  I would like to see that unit progressed under the capital plan.  I would also like to see the maternity hospital moved from the existing site to the grounds of University Hospital Limerick.  </p><p>I would like to see the three projects mentioned - the M20, the 90-bed acute unit in University Hospital Limerick and the relocation of the maternity unit to the site of University Hospital Limerick to improve the cohesiveness of the care provided - included in the new national plan.  When is it expected that announcements will be made on the new capital plan?  Will they form part of the budget day announcements?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#AA00200"><p>Does Senator P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh wish to contribute?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#AA00500"><p>I had not planned to do so, but I would be delighted to do so.  </p> <p>I welcome the Minister of State.  T&aacute; f&aacute;ilte roimhe.  Labhr&oacute;idh m&eacute; i mB&eacute;arla c&eacute; go bhfuil m&eacute; n&iacute;os comporda&iacute;, b'fh&eacute;idir, ag labhairt i nGaeilge.  </p> <p>First, we must look at where we have come from, as Senator Kieran O'Donnell said.  We have come from a situation where a few years ago we had a 14.5% unemployment rate.  It now stands at around 6%, which represents a very significant improvement.  We are, therefore, very close to full employment.  It is said an unemployment rate of around 4% or thereabouts represents full employment.  </p> <p>The books are reasonably well balanced again.  Therefore, where do we go from here?  The economic reports I have read and the economists to whom I listen, although sometimes we should not listen to as many as we do, are urging caution.  We, therefore, need to be careful and must be prudent about capital expenditure, to which there are two parts - revenue and capital.  During my time as Chairman of the Oireachtas Committee on the Future Funding of Domestic Water Services the big issue was on and off-balance sheet expenditure.  I learned an awful lot about the public finances, although I would have known a little about private investment and business.  Off-balance sheet expenditure is really important and very significant.  If we can create a situation where a lot of our capital expenditure is paid for or supported by off-balance sheet funding, it will support a lot of the capital expenditure about which my colleagues have spoken on hospitals in Galway and the Limerick to Cork and Limerick to Galway roads, projects I strongly support.  As capital expenditure is a long-term investment, I urge prudence in that regard.</p> <p>Another important factor to bear in mind is that EU regulations stipulate the degree of flexibility we have in any budget which is based on income.  It is a multiple of the revenue the Exchequer receives.  I ask the Minister of State to correct me if I am wrong, but I understand the position in 2018 will be pretty tight from a budgetary perspective.  Things will loosen again in 2019 because we will be working with a greater revenue cash flow from the Exchequer's perspective.  Again, I caution the Government not to spend money we do not have and not to spend money that will be on-balance sheet.  We should try to work off-balance sheet to a proper ratio or degree.</p> <p>In the context of the mid-term capital review, I live in Spiddal in Connemara.  It can take me an hour and a half to travel about five miles from Spiddal to Galway racecourse, from where I can get to the M50 in the same amount of time.  The roads in Galway are absolutely killing the people and the local economy.  If we had a good hospital, that would be fine, but we cannot get to it on time.  A very good friend of mine from Oranmore died recently of a heart attack.  If it had happened at 4 p.m. rather than at 4 a.m., it would have taken an hour and a half to get him to the hospital.  Access is absolutely critical.  I, therefore, urge the Minister of State to look at providing an outer bypass in Galway and to do whatever he can to get that project moving.  It would also support Senator Kieran O'Donnell's very well made point about the western corridor to join Cork, Limerick and Galway and, I hope, places further north such as Ballina and Sligo.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#AA00600"><p>I welcome this timely debate on the national capital expenditure plan.  We need to debate the issue in the context of where the country is at and from where it has come in recent years.  We must acknowledge that there were serious reductions in capital expenditure and infrastructural investment owing to the state of the economy from 2007 until recently.  However, I must give the last Government credit for continuing to invest in schools, in building new schools, continuing the prefab replacement scheme and building school extensions all over the country.  We have almost eradicated the use of prefabs, although there is still some work to be done in that regard.</p> <p>In 2015 a new capital plan was announced in which housing was prioritised, an in which I had a role.  Over &euro;4 billion was provided for various schemes throughout the country.  That sum has been expanded since, with &euro;5.5 billion being provided for housing.  It is no good, however, just having the money in place.  We need to get building under way.  With the restoration of our economic fortunes, the country can once again provide for capital investment.  However, as the Minister of State outlined, we need to undertake such investment in a coherent, logistical and transparent way.  </p> <p>I was somewhat bemused to hear a Sinn F&eacute;in representative criticise the Government when members of that party speak out of both sides of their mouths.  In Northern Ireland Sinn F&eacute;in will not take responsibility to govern.  In most local authorities the party will not take responsibility for voting on a budget, but its members still look for all services.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paudie Coffey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2237"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2237&amp;amp;pid=PaudieCoffey&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Even recently, in the Joint Committee on the Future Funding of Domestic Water Services of which I was a member, where investment is critically needed in water infrastructure, they did all in their political power to undermine capital investment by the populist stances that they take.  That is typical of Sinn F&eacute;in.</p><p>We in government focus on the positive ways in which the economy can provide for the communities into the future and that is why a new national development plan 2040 is due to be announced shortly.  It is vital that the capital plan is linked intrinsically and strongly to that new national development plan 2040 because that will outline the vision for economic growth in this country and it is critical that investment is made in tandem with that.</p><p>At present, Dublin is a vortex of economic activity.  It is overheating.  However, we have cities around the country that are capable of providing for the economy and driving the regions in which they are.  The national spatial strategy was a good strategy at the time but it failed miserable.  It failed because cities, such as Waterford, the area that I come from, did not have the capital investment infrastructure that it required and that went with the status that it was given.  Now we have a unique opportunity to put that right with the new national development plan and the new capital investment plan.</p><p>Using Waterford and the south east as an example, where it is envisaged that we want to grow that city to almost double in population terms, it is critical that we invest in essential infrastructure.  The north quays in Waterford are similar to a mini-docklands and there is huge potential for the city to grow in that area.  There is interest in investing over &euro;300 million of private investment to provide housing, commercial activity, tourism-related activity and a strong retail offering for a city that should be attracting people from around the entire south-east region.  This development will require substantial Government investment that can return to the Exchequer solid taxes and income.  It will require in the order of &euro;60 million of investment.  I have already spoken to the Minister for Finance and Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe, regarding the critical need for this investment and I am certainly hopeful it will be a strong part of the announcements of the capital plan over the coming months.</p><p>Other areas that require investment in the region are regional infrastructure such as University Hospital Waterford, which is a level 4 acute hospital.  It is getting a new palliative care unit with a five-storey building that will certainly help in regards to beds but there is a strong need for a &euro;3 million investment in a regional emergency cardiac care service to bring it up to a 24-7 service.  I will continue to voice that need for my region here in the national Parliament.</p><p>I am not being parochial here.  These are all regional needs I am outlining.  If we are going to have a strong country, we must have strong regions.  We need a technological university for the south east.  I am glad to report that WIT and Carlow IT are now working together.  For that to progress, it will require capital investment.</p><p>Senators spoke about the roads and road safety.  That is an area that fell behind considerably during the dark days of the recession.  The rural and regional roads need investment.  The road between my city and the Minister of State's, the N24 from Limerick to Waterford, is probably the worst national road in the country.  I would urge the National Transport Authority and everybody involved in policy making on roads to look at that road with regard to an upgrade.  If we must have strong regions and inter-connectivity between the cities, that is one road that needs work.</p><p>I could go on forever on areas such as broadband and next generation investments in information technology.  Climate change will be a significant challenge for this country and we will need investments in renewable energies.  All of the regions can contribute positively in that respect and that is why we need a coherent vision for this country with the plans and the infrastructure, and the expenditure, to make it happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#BB00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy O'Donovan.  It is my first opportunity to congratulate him in public on his appointment as Minister of State.  Knowing Deputy O'Donovan, as I do, over a number of years, he brings great ability and energy, and high principle to the office and I wish him well in it.</p> <p>Through a lot of hard work, great effort and great courage on the part of the previous Government and this one, we have come to the point that we can have this discussion, that we can have a balanced budget, that we are significantly reducing national debt and that we are now in position where we have credibility from a borrowing perspective to get attractive interest rates, and that we are now in a position to engage strategically in capital investment.  I suppose there are a couple of big objectives that we need to achieve through the capital investment.  The Minister of State, as a former teacher like myself, will be familiar with long-term and short-term objectives in teaching plans.  The biggest long-term objective we have is to maintain sustainable populations in rural Ireland and maintain a balance, to deal with what Senator Coffey aptly describes as the "vortex" that is Dublin at present and to get a level a decentralisation in terms of population and sustainable communities throughout the country.  With that in mind, the commitment to road infrastructure and transport infrastructure is a vital one, both in terms of achieving inward investment in rural Ireland and in terms of its development and quality of life, and attractiveness to live there.</p> <p>In the county that I and the distinguished Acting Chairman, Senator Wilson, come from, we do not have railways.  We do not have immediate access to local airports, etc., and we depend on the road infrastructure in a big way.  For that reason, the road infrastructure is vital.  In that context, I would commend two projects in County Cavan to the Minister of State that are relevant to both Cavan and Monaghan.  The first is the east-west link, linking Dundalk to Sligo.  That goes through the critical towns of Shercock, Cootehill and Carrickmacross throughout my constituency.  That project is so important because we have the large employer, Carton, in Shercock, employing 600 to 800 local people in a place one would not necessarily have food processing where one would not readily attract alternative employment, and Abbott in Cootehill.  That east-west link is critical.  I commend that project to the Minister of State.  It will stand up to any analysis and any objective scrutiny.  I would also commend the extension of the M3, with the bypassing of Virginia to Cavan town as a critical piece of infrastructure for that region.  I would appeal to the Minister of State to look seriously at those in the context of transport.</p> <p>The Minister of State has a commitment professionally, as I and virtually all of us in the House have, to the regionalisation of education.  Indeed, I note the Acting Chairman is highly involved in that project at home too.  We are committed to getting the new third level campus, the post leaving certificate college, to Cavan.  It is committed to in the capital plan.  In his response, I would like the Minister of State to restate his public commitment to it.  It would mean so much to people.  It is a vital, long awaited project up there.  That is a necessary exercise, if we have any genuine commitment to regionalisation and to maintaining sustainable communities outside of Dublin.</p> <p>I agree with all the points the Minister of State makes in his address around structural reform, planning, procurement and good value for money.  That is prudent and right.  What people want with their hard-earned success is that it would not be squandered.  Of course, I agree with those and I will not labour them, but the Minister of State would be the first to agree that we need inward investment in rural areas.  I cannot go about attracting inward investment to, and we cannot have successful trade mission for, a place such as Cavan until one gets the infrastructure.  Crucial to that infrastructure are the roadways, the college and, as referenced by Senator Coffey, broadband.  Broadband is most crucial.  I accept it is a different debate in the sense it is the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Denis Naughten's, specific responsibility, but it is enormously vital.</p> <p>My colleague, Senator Mulherin, opened with the contention that we have to achieve with this capital plan viable communities around this country, particularly in the disadvantaged areas of the Border region and the mid-west that have suffered hugely.  The Border region, in my area, has suffered enormously down the years.  We have to right that wrong and correct that imbalance.  I appeal to the Minister of State to see that happens.  It is a great and exciting opportunity for the Minister of State and for all of us to put something right here, to make it likely that people will want to live in counties such as Cavan and Monaghan and right through the west of Ireland, and that we will get those in the aptly described "vortex" or population centre that is Dublin to choose other centres.</p> <p>Of course, there must be a match between the capital plan and the spatial strategy into the future.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I contend that the projects that I have mentioned will so do. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#CC00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I thank him for his speech that outlined his thoughts and plans.</p><p>The regions have been spoken about an awful lot and my colleague, Senator Kieran O'Donnell, referred to the M20, which is very important.  I shall return to what Senator Coffey said in terms of regional development.  I, too, would like to support the M20 and the connection with Waterford.  I know the Government has a big commitment to the area outside of Dublin and job creation.  A commitment has been given to create over 60% of jobs, etc., outside of Dublin.  I agree that the Government must focus on and develop the regions.  Senator Coffey is right that there is a big connection between the different cities and towns located in the regions.  Limerick is very lucky to have Shannon Airport on its doorstep because many companies have located their businesses in the region thus leading to job creation.  Education has also been included and highlighted in the Minister of State's report.  We must invest in education in the regions in order to assist businesses to grow.  I shall refer to the Minister of State's <i>alma mater</i>.  Mary Immaculate College has a library facility for 700 students but in actual fact it has close to 5,000 students attending the college.  Therefore, students lose out in terms of access to the library and research facilities.</p><p>Recently I visited the Monaleen national school that is comprised of eight classrooms and 16 prefabs.  The school has been in the building programme for a  long number of years.  There must be investment in local schools and colleges.  Such investment is an investment in our future and that leads to job creation in the regions. </p><p>This morning on the Order of Business I mentioned the overcrowding at University Hospital Limerick.  I know that Senator Kieran O'Donnell referred to the matter earlier.  I believe that there must be investment in extra beds at both University Hospital Limerick and St. John's Hospital.  They are not just hospitals for Limerick city; they are hospitals for the region.  University Hospital Limerick has the highest level of overcrowding in the region.  The figures have been consistent for quite a while in terms of the highest level in Ireland.  For an initiative to work and have a positive effect on the region there must be investment in both hospitals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#CC00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I also welcome the opportunity to say a few works on the mid-term review of the capital plan 2016-2021.  First, I wish to compliment everybody involved in getting this Chamber to its current state when it was opened yesterday.  I can remember well two years ago, as Cathaoirleach of the Seanad, when I visited this room.  I can assure Members that it was not in the same state that it is in today.  The room looked as if a reception had taken place a number of nights beforehand and quite a number of wine and champagne glasses were strewn around the room.  In the far corner was the Sam Maguire Cup.  I did not think it would hang around the capital ever since.  I compliment everybody, including the Ceann Comhairle, and everybody involved in the project.</p> <p>I shall make a few points about the mid-term review of the capital plan.  I am delighted that the Minister of State has given us an overview of where things are at the moment and where we can reach.  Every area has a project.  Like everybody else, there are quite a number projects in the west and the north west.  During the Celtic tiger years the region did not get its fair share of capital spending and, thus, fell very much behind other regions.  That fact can be seen quite effectively.  The last census shows that a declining population exists in counties Mayo and Donegal.  I ask that the Minister of State takes a serious look at the population census for 2016.  I ask him to take the data into account when allocating funding to projects throughout the country.</p> <p>I shall name a few projects.  Ireland West Airport Knock is central to the prosperity of the region as it is an international airport.  I ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport and the Minister for Finance and the Taoiseach to take a close look at the airport as it needs capital investment and hangarage.  The airport is a vital piece of infrastructure for the western and north-western region.  People from the region can now commute to London on a weekly basis.  In fact, people who work in London during the week can fly home and arrive in the western area quicker than if they travelled by car from Dublin.  The airport also allows people to travel to the Algarve, Spain and Germany.  The airport is a vital infrastructure that allows people who invest in the region, and to move in and out of the region.  The airport is also very important from a tourism point of view as tourists from Germany and various parts of Europe can travel to the region.</p> <p>The N5 and N26 roads were neglected during the Celtic tiger years.  I ask that the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport fast forward capital for the N5.  All of the planning stages have gone through and the fencing has been completed.  The N5 project is ready for completion and ready to go to tender.  I ask that the N5 project is placed high on the agenda when deciding terms and projects for the capital plan 2016-2021.  There are a number of projects in the western region.  In Mayo, in particular, there is the N5, N26 and the Ireland West Airport Knock and I ask that the Minister of State prioritises these projects.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#CC00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House for this important discussion.  I say so not least because, as he said in his speech and rightly so, that we consider the capital plan in the context of individual projects and how best to grow and develop all regions of this country.  We must also be mindful that we draw a line beyond the M50 and Red Cow roundabout so that we can ensure that priority is given to the regions, that there is investment and that capital infrastructure takes place.</p> <p>We all have a list of individual projects that we want to see prioritised and completed.  As the Minister of State said in his speech, the Government does not have an infinite amount of money to spend on a wish list.  He comes from County Limerick so he will recognise that the Cork-Limerick motorway can act as a catalyst for change and investment in the Cork-Limerick region.  It is important that we learn from the debacle that was the decentralisation policy by a past Government.  We must ensure that we give autonomy to the regions and that we allow for a strategy that will empower the regions to grow.</p> <p>I was very much struck by the joint presentation that we received from Cork County Council and Cork City Council about Cork 2050.  The presentation recognised and emphasised what the region needs to reach its full potential.  Whether one comes from north, south, east or west it is critical, in whatever decision is made by Government, that there is a process that allows for the country as a whole to benefit.  That is why this debate is important.  We can all produce a wish list.  I could talk about Cork-Limerick, the M28 and the need for a second hospital in Cork.  I could list a whole plethora of projects that are important for the Cork area.  What is important is that the allocation of money is done in a way that promotes investment, secure jobs and retains jobs.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It would ensure that Ireland, which will be the only English-speaking nation left in the European Union, will be open for business, which it is.</p><p>In a recovering economy the key factors, as mentioned by the Minister of State, are transport, education, health and housing.  The kernel of what we must do is recognise the need for investment in capital infrastructure such as the pressing and urgent need for housing and the provision of schools, hospitals and roads and balance that against the services people require in their day-to-day lives such as care for the elderly or disabled and the recruitment of more garda&iacute;, nurses or teachers.  We must try to balance those needs.  Those in Opposition who come out with grandiose plans must recognise that this must be about how the people and the country can benefit.  It is not just about making connections locally and internationally but also ensuring an opportunity for the country.  The Government and Fine Gael have always focussed on the country and the people.  For the five years during which some Members of the Opposition could not decide to cross the road, the Government took decisions to ensure the country recovered and that we are on the cusp of a funding model that will ensure a benefit.  The Government has much interaction with the European Investment Bank in terms of the provision of moneys.  It is important that we invest in infrastructure.</p><p>The situation post-Brexit will be challenging for many parts of the economy.  Senator Paddy Burke referenced the issue of air travel.  The issue of tourism, for which Minister of State had a very strong and supportive role in his previous Ministry, must be addressed to determine how the regions can counteract Brexit.  The southern region has experienced a sharp decline in visitors from the United Kingdom since the Brexit vote although that has been mitigated by direct flights from Cork Airport to Providence which have led to an increase in North American visitors.  The balance has to be gotten right for the way forward.</p><p>The national planning framework, Ireland 2040, is due to be published soon.  It explores how we can plan for the future in the context of expanding cities and counties.  Cork city and county local governance structures were discussed during the Order of Business.  That needs to be gotten right and resolved in order that we ensure that Cork city and county prosper and develop.</p><p>I thank the Minister of State for his attendance.  It is important that we get this right and have investment but it is also about people and being able to attract investment and retain jobs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#DD00200"><p>I thank the Senators who have attended this important debate.  One would have imagined there would be a bigger interest, in particular from some Opposition groups.  I am very disappointed by the attendance.  I do not know if another event is taking place.  I was looking forward to contributions from both sides of the House.  The Senators who attended made some interesting contributions, much of which I agree with and much of which I do not.  One would imagine there is no more important issue than the preparation and planning for the future development of Ireland, the children yet to be born, the roads yet to be driven and the schools yet to be attended.  We cannot live in the past but must try to plan for the future.  I thank Senators who turned up and showed an interest in such an important issue.</p><p>Senator Horkan is correct that a lot of catching up needs to be done.  He identified a number of issues and I will not get into the specifics of all those projects as that would not be appropriate because there is a fairly large shopping list from the Seanad.  The Senator failed to mention that the State was banjaxed in 2011 and was a borrower of last resort, that the economy had no money and was running on empty and the Government did not know if it would be able to keep the doors of the country open.  It needs to be said on the record that the transformation of the Irish economy in a short period of time on the back of the efforts of the Irish people has been enormous.  There are commentators who said a second bailout would be needed, that the State would have to go cap in hand to look for it and that all the policies pursued by the Government were wrong.</p><p>One political party opposed everything the Government did during the previous D&aacute;il just for the sake of it.  Its deputy leader said of its leader that anyone could fumble a figure.  It was not the first time that Deputy Adams fumbled a figure in the hundreds of millions.  I take particular issue with Sinn F&eacute;in's record on economic policy and where they were and are <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>the economic collapse.  First, it has absented itself from any decision making on the island of Ireland and, secondly, it has decided to oppose for opposition's sake anything done by either the previous Fianna F&aacute;il or Fine Gael-Labour Governments or the current Fine Gael-Independent minority Government supported by Fianna F&aacute;il.  If everything we did was wrong, we would not be in the position four years later of having a balanced budget and being able to talk about fiscal spending space.  If we did as Deputy Adams suggested and told the European Union to take its money and g, and one must remember Sinn F&eacute;in has opposed every EU treaty since 1973 for the sake of it, where would we be?  Where would we now be if we had taken the advice of Sinn F&eacute;in in 2011?  We would be on a one-way ticket to the stone age and would not have to worry about class sizes, roads or the future development of the hospital network.  The country would be akin to a modern-day basket case.  Rather than saying everything the Government did was wrong or coming forward, as it did last year, with proposals that would have meant that every single person who avails of a tax credit they pay into a pension would see a cut of &euro;800 in his or her annual take-home pay, it would be nice to see costed proposals from a party that just opposes everything.</p><p>That is the type of make it up as you go along economics of which I am tired.  I admire Opposition politicians such as Senators &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh and Horkan who make proposals based on circumstances that bear some resemblance to the economic reality of the State.  However, that is not the case for a party that continues to have no regard to either the past or the present in relation to where the economy was, where it went or the policies pursued by successive Governments to do what we believed was right and resulted in us being on a trajectory to virtual full employment from an unemployment rate of 16%.  We are on the way to a balanced economic budget and do not need to worry about a lender of last resort.  We are on the way to being able to look after our citizens as any sovereign government should without going cap in hand to anybody.  Where would we be if we followed the alternative?  All Members know where we would be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#DD00300"><p>Parts of Mayo have an unemployment rate of 31%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#DD00400"><p>I did not interrupt the Senator.  This is proof of what I said.  The truth hurts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#DD00500"><p>The Minister of State should deal with the 31% unemployment rate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#DD00600"><p>We will shout them down.  During the summer some councillors went on the national airwaves to identify how they were treated by party members who have very little regard for differences of opinion, more of which has been seen here today.  I did not shout down the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#DD00700"><p>Speakers should stick to the subject.  The Minister of State to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#DD00800"><p>I am doing so.  Many worthy projects were identified by Senators, some of which are in my own region.  The projects include the M29, Limerick Regional Hospital, Ireland West Airport Knock, the Luas cross-city which will soon be opened and the Newlands Cross flyover which was built at a time of economic collapse.  All of those things can only be done if there are the building blocks of a sound economy.  One cannot have such building blocks if one makes it up as one goes along in some sort of <i>Alice in Wonderland</i>-type fairy tale.  He might not be great at the figures.  We know he is not great at the figures and he should stay away from them.  It is no wonder that a party that can try and suggest that the country can somehow just decide it is going to run around on empty, tell the EU, IMF and the troika to get out, vote against every EU treaty and pretend it is going to be all right on the night does not want to be in government in Northern Ireland, take its seats in Westminster, be in government in this jurisdiction nor be in power in any local authority in the country because that would involve making a decision.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Patrick O'Donovan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2316"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2316&amp;amp;pid=PatrickODonovan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=27"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have done the right thing by this country since 1922 and we will continue to do so.  The main opposition party has, by and large, always done what it believes is right.  We might disagree with it politically, as we might with the Labour Party, the Green Party and the Independents who come from a variety of backgrounds, but I will not sit here and listen to this type of thing we must also listen to in the other House, where a Senator can stand up and say it is time we rise to the challenge.  Why is her party not rising to the challenge?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE00200"><p>Is that a direct question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE00300"><p>Where is Sinn F&eacute;in when it comes to taking responsibility for the democratic mandate given in another part of this country?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE00400"><p>I will not sit here and listen to this rant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE00500"><p>It is time all politicians rose to the challenge.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE00600"><p>That is why we made a fully costed pre-budget submission.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE00700"><p>We all know the fully costed versions that have been brought into this House and the other House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE00800"><p>Through the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE00900"><p>It is time Members spoke honestly to the people in this country.  We cannot turn on some type of magic printing press for money or dip into the wishing well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01000"><p>What about the &euro;13 billion to Apple and the &euro;340 million to vulture funds?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01100"><p>How can any party suggest the people who get up in the morning do not deserve some tax break or relief on their income?  They are the people who pay for everything, and without the 2 million people at work in this country where would we be?  We would be in the same economic basket case I referred to earlier had we followed the economic policies of the party that told the EU to hump off and that wanted us to be out of the EU at every single referendum held.  This is the reality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01200"><p>You are obviously rattled.  Get back in your pram.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01300"><p>It is nice to see people arriving.  I welcome the opportunity to listen to the constructive comments of Senators who have projects all over the country.  Every one of them will be taken into consideration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01400"><p>Except those of Sinn F&eacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01500"><p>To answer Senator O'Donnell, it will be published in December.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01600"><p>The Minister of State's party colleague told him he made an absolute mess.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01700"><p>Oh dear, I turn my back and a row breaks out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#EE01800"><p>Before I move on, I acknowledge the presence in the House of former Senator, Mary Jackman, and her husband Nick.  I had the pleasure of serving with her and we shared a corridor in the Engineering Block.  She is very welcome and I hope she enjoys her visit.  We will suspend until 3.30 p.m.  Everyone needs to draw their breath.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.193" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.25 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.194" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00100">Visit of Czech Delegation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00200"><p>I am sure Members wish to join me in welcoming a parliamentary delegation from the Czech Republic led by Mr. Jaroslav Kubera, Vice President of the Czech Senate.  He, his ambassador and the rest of the team are very welcome.  On my behalf and that of all my colleagues in Seanad &Eacute;ireann, I extend a very warm welcome to them and good wishes for a very successful visit to Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00400"><p>I hope my pronunciation was not too bad.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.198" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00500">Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Bill 2016: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, to our new Chamber.  I welcome all Members as it is my first time in the Chair in the new Chamber.  I hope we will get through the 43 amendments relatively briefly.  Is Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell having a difficulty?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00700"><p>The acoustics are problematic.  Most of us wish to hear the Acting Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00800"><p>I will try to project a little more.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF00900"><p>I think there is an electronic problem as well.  Perhaps we need to settle as it is very difficult to hear speakers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF01000"><p>I noticed that myself.  I do not know if it comes down to acoustics or that we are a little further away from each other than we might have been previously.  I will do my best to try to project my voice and I hope we can get through this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF01100"><p>There does not seem to be any heating.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF01200"><p>I am well insulated enough but maybe some other Members are not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF01300"><p>As somebody with a vision impairment, this Chamber is far superior to the last one.  That is in terms of getting around and brightness and so forth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF01400"><p>We are only on our second day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.208" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.209" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF01700"><p>This amendment makes a change to the commencement provisions of the Bill to allow that certain provisions, particularly provisions relating to the use of screens in courtrooms to prevent a victim from having visual contact with the accused person, may be commenced for different courts or areas at different times.  The purpose of the amendment is to allow for a phased roll-out of the provisions on the use of screens over time as necessary equipment becomes available in different courts.  It mirrors existing commencement provisions in the Criminal Evidence Act 1992 that applied to other special measures for the protection of vulnerable witnesses under that Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF01800"><p>I have no difficulty whatever with this and it seems to be a reasonable provision from the Government.  It is interesting that nearly 40 of the amendments come from the Government.  It has happened before.  It is happening that there are more and more Government amendments.  This raises a little warning in my mind about the preparation of legislation.  It comes to the House in a rather unfinished manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF01900"><p>The Senator is correct and we are proposing 30 amendments today.  The majority of these are technical amendments, updating the Bill for criminal evidence provisions introduced by the Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Act 2017.  We passed another Bill recently and we are just updating the Bill to take account of that.  We are doing much stuff at the same time.  A small number of other amendments provide additional rights for victims giving victim impact statements and during bail hearings.  We are trying to keep it updated as best we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF02000"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his explanation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.214" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.

Section 1, as amended, agreed to.

SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF02200"><p>Amendments Nos. 2 and 3 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF02300"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 6, after line 37, to insert the following:&ldquo; &ldquo;investigating authority&rdquo; shall include any body which has the responsibility and/or the statutory power to investigate and/or prosecute a criminal offence;&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>I wish to be brief so I will not go on at any great length on the Bill noting its current state.  I will take Members through the rationale behind the proposal.  Article 4 of the victims' directive, the right to information, provides that all victims of crime have a right to certain information on first contact with the competent authority.  The competent authority is not defined by the directive but the European Commission justice guidelines give an indication as to who should fall within this definition.  The Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Bill 2016 only applies to the investigations conducted by the Garda or Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission.  Such a restriction prevents victims from accessing information in any other form of prosecution or investigation.  Any statutory authority with the potential power to prosecute a criminal offence would fall under the remit of Article 4 of the directive, the right to information.</p><p>There is a significant list of bodies falling within the remit, including but not limited to the Health and Safety Authority, HIQA, Tusla, the Health Service Executive and ComReg.  These bodies have the power to investigate and prosecute criminal offences.  Victims who are natural persons should be provided with information from these prosecuting authorities in accordance with Article 4 of the directive.  Similarly, where a competent authority is investigating or prosecuting an offence, it should be obliged to provide all the necessary information, support and protection that would otherwise be provided by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na if it prosecuted.  That is the rationale and I would like to hear the Minister of State's comments.  I hope we can have some support for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF02400"><p>I second the amendment, which has been covered comprehensively.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF02500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and the opportunity to be here to debate on Committee Stage of the Criminal Justice (Victims of Crime) Bill.  I thank all the non-governmental organisations that have engaged with us, the Minister of State and his officials in the time between Second and Committee Stages.  I support what Senator Boyhan said and my amendment No. 3 seeks to do something similar.  It is a matter I raised on Second Stage and I am grateful to the Victims' Rights Alliance and others for raising this issue with me and others.  We were concerned the Bill did not cover other prosecuting authorities or persons with functions related to the investigation or bringing of the prosecution of an offence conferred by enactments.  That would include, for example, the Health and Safety Authority and other bodies.  I know the Victims' Rights Alliance shares our view that victims of crime may be victims of offences prosecutable by other entities and agencies.  They should not be excluded from the remit of the Bill.  That is the intention behind the amendment and I ask the Minister of State to consider it.  As it was raised on Second Stage, I hope the Minister of State has had the chance to consider the matter at least.  I look forward to his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017092700002#FF02600"><p>I support the amendments.  It seems that the Bill should not be restricted to the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, particularly when there are other agencies, such as Tusla and the Health and Safety Authority etc., which can be involved in these prosecutions.  It seems clear these provisions should extend to them.  There is also the matter of the right to information.  It is very important for the proper conduct of any kind of trial or legal process that the parties involved should have the maximum possible information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-09-27a.220" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>