<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#B00100"><p>I have received notice from Senator Maria Byrne that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the appointment of a neurology clinical nurse specialist for the University Limerick hospital group.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to give details of the targets set for local authorities in 2019 in relation to the delivery of affordable homes to purchase and rent.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Ian Marshall of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to give an update on the publication of legislation to provide for enhanced co-operation with legacy inquests in Northern Ireland.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform to make a statement on the assessment criteria, policy and procedures in the awarding of State contracts to successful tenderers from outside the State</blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#B00200">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#B00250">Health Services Staff Recruitment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#B00275"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#B00300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  The Minister of State is very welcome.  I rise today to ask about the recruitment of a specialist MS nurse for the mid-west region.  In a report that was commissioned, it was recommended that three to four nurses were necessary for the region but at the moment we have none and one would be a bonus.  When I last raised the issue, I was told, as were the people involved in the MS society, that someone would be in place in the second quarter of 2019, but as of yet there has been no advertisement for the position, and there seems to be no movement in filling the position.  A recruitment ban was announced recently by the Minister, and people are very afraid that this position will not be filled.  Perhaps the Minister of State will give an update on the situation.  People who suffer from MS have to go to Cork and different places around the country to access the services of a specialised nurse, so if there were one in the region, it would be of great benefit to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#B00400"><p>I thank Senator Byrne for raising this very important issue.  I welcome the opportunity to address the House on this matter on behalf of the Minister for Health, and to provide an update on progress made on the proposal to recruit a clinical nurse specialist in neurology at University Hospital Limerick, UHL.  I am advised that the UL Hospitals Group recognises the need for a clinical nurse specialist in neurology and it has been deemed a priority post for the hospital group.  In that regard, I am pleased to inform the House that the UL Hospitals Group has made the funding available for this post, and it is anticipated that the post will be filled by the third quarter of this year.  The UL Hospitals Group is engaging with the HSE recruitment service in relation to this post.  I have also been informed that the recruitment campaign for the clinical nurse specialist post in neurology is progressing, and I have been advised by the UL Hospitals Group that the advertisement for this position is pending.  It is envisioned that the post will be advertised in May 2019 and filled by the third quarter of this year.</p> <p>The national clinical programme for neurology has developed and published a model of care for neurology services.  This model of care provides a framework for neurology services to be delivered with an integrated service approach, which is in line with international best practice.  Implementation of the new model of care will see an increase in the number of consultant neurologists and nurse specialists, including clinical nurse specialists, in neurology and other healthcare professions, and this will address waiting times.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The new model of care will see an increase in the number of consultant neurologists, nurse specialists, including clinical nurse specialists in neurology and other healthcare professionals and this will address waiting times.  The purpose of the clinical nurse specialist post is to improve and enhance the care of patients and their families by developing services, and to assist overall in optimising quality and continuity of care.  The clinical nurse specialist is required to work as a key member of the multidisciplinary team in the hospital providing physical, psychological and emotional support to neurology patients and their families.  They act as a liaison between community services, primary care teams and other agencies.  The national clinical programme for neurology proposes implementation of the new model of care over a period of five years.  This will significantly improve access for all neurology patients in the mid-west.  The implementation of the new model of care is a work in progress.  I can confirm that the University Limerick hospital group has recognised the need for this specialist nursing post and is treating the recruitment for this post as a priority.</p><p>In addition, looking to the future, the national clinical programme for neurology has developed a new model of care for neurology, the implementation of which will improve service provision incrementally over the next few years not only in the mid-west but nationally.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#C00200"><p>I welcome the fact that it is at last being advertised.  Twelve months ago I was told it was going to be advertised.  That is why I raised the matter again today but I am glad that it will be advertised by May.  It will be disappointing for some people that it will be quarter 3 before somebody comes in but now they know that it is a priority for the university hospital and it is recognised that a nurse has to be put in place.  Perhaps it is time that I started lobbying for a second one because it has taken so long to fill the post.  I know it is not the Minister of State's fault but it is disappointing that it has taken so long for the recruitment process to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#C00300"><p>The bottom line is that it is a priority and it will be delivered and it is being advertised in May.  The UL hospital group has recognised the need for recruitment of a clinical nurse specialist in neurology and funding has been provided for the post.  I am confident that the new clinical nurse specialist post will help improve and enhance the care provided to neurology patients and their families.  It is a priority for me.  I will give this my utmost support because I am a strong supporter of this clinical nurse specialist service.  It will be developed, not just in the mid-west but it will be rolled out nationally.  The post is being advertised and it will be delivered shortly.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#C00400">Social and Affordable Housing Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#C00500"><p>Will the Minister of State with responsibility for local government confirm the details that have been set by the Department of Housing, Planning and Local Government in consultation with the chief executives of all 41 local authorities in respect of the delivery of affordable housing?  We know, and it has been a major plank of the Rebuilding Ireland policy, that the Government would envisage the roll-out of a national affordable housing scheme and it is disappointing to say that, despite being three years on from that, we do not have a national affordable housing scheme in place.  There are several reasons for that but they are not all the Minister of State's fault.  We need to keep the focus on and deliver affordable housing, more purchase, and affordable homes for renting, particularly in the cities and the Dublin area.  People know there are great difficulties in just renting a home at an affordable and sustainable price.  There is a national problem that needs to be addressed.</p> <p>It came to my attention recently that there was a draft affordable scheme of priorities proposed and brought by the management in D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I understand it was rejected across the political lines, including by councillors from the Minister of State's own party and those from other parties and none, because they had what they described as major difficulties with the flexibility of the scheme.  I am talking about the draft affordable scheme of priorities for affordable housing.  The argument, apparently, is that there is not sufficient flexibility locally in terms of the charges and other issues around all of that.  I think we have a difficulty and I ask the Department to look specifically at this local authority.  It is the one I know best, the one I live in and the council on which I served.  This is only a very recent development and I know the Minister is aware of it.  We need to look at the pitfalls and concerns expressed by elected members of this council.  I understand it was unanimous across the board.  They raised concerns.  I do not know the legitimacy of those concerns or the detailed reasoning behind them.  I understand that the director of housing on this council sent the draft report with comments back to the Minister, and that the Minister will have to come back to the council at some point.</p><p>I am mindful that in most local authorities there will only be one more council meeting before the local elections.  Some councillors will not be re-elected and some will; there will be substantial changes across the 31 local authorities, no doubt.  The key, substantive issue is that of affordability.  What specific targets has the Government set?  We have to talk about targets and keep monitoring them, otherwise we are not going to see the delivery of affordable homes to purchase and rent.   Perhaps the Minister of State will enlighten me further.  I ask him to relay to the Minister that we might look at D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown specifically because it is the only one I know that has been sent back to the Minister at this point.  Perhaps there are lessons to be learned from it and perhaps there are not but we should look at it.  If everybody is rejecting a scheme of priorities and holding up an affordable scheme in a local authority, it has to be an issue of concern both to the Government and to the local authority in question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#D00200"><p>I thank the Senator.  I am taking this matter on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy.  Having read through the response that is provided by the Department, I am not sure it will deal with some of the issues that Senator Boyhan has raised.</p> <p>One of the Government&rsquo;s key priorities is to address issues of housing affordability.  To this end, a multi-stranded approach is being taken to support those low to middle-income households in achieving home ownership.  In terms of affordable purchase, last year, my colleague, the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, commenced the relevant provisions of Part 5 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009.  This provided a statutory basis for the delivery of the affordable housing purchase scheme.  The Minister also made regulations last month, on foot of which local authorities are now moving ahead to develop their schemes of priority, which they will use to manage the allocation of affordable housing that becomes available in their local areas.</p> <p>The &euro;310 million serviced site fund, SSF, was announced in the last budget, with the core objective of achieving significant delivery of affordable housing.  Under the serviced site fund, at least 6,200 affordable homes will be facilitated over the next three years.  As part of the first tranche of this funding, in December 2018, ten projects were approved for &euro;43 million of funding under the serviced site fund&rsquo;s first call for proposals.  This will result in the delivery of over 1,400 homes in urban centres with clear affordability challenges in locations across Cork and Dublin.  Details of these schemes and their locations are available on the Rebuilding Ireland website and it is expected that the first tranche of affordable homes will come on-stream next year.  A second call for further applications under this fund was issued last week.  As a result of this, 19 local authorities which carried out economic assessments to identify affordability issues in their areas will be in a position to make applications for funding support for a further bundle of projects to deliver affordable homes to purchase or rent.  Furthermore, some 2,350 affordable homes are in the process of being delivered on mainly publicly-owned lands supported through the local infrastructure housing activation fund, LIHAF.  An additional 5,600 homes will benefit from a LIHAF-related cost reduction, some of which are already coming to market.  Again, details of these schemes and their locations are available on the Rebuilding Ireland website.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy John Paul Phelan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2004"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2004&amp;amp;pid=JohnPaulPhelan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Aside from affordable housing purchase options, the Government has also committed to supporting a new cost rental model.  Under the heading of cost rental, the provider supplies accommodation and charges rents sufficient to cover the capital costs associated with delivery, with the ongoing commitments related to the management and maintenance of the development.  Cost rental is a model that is delivered at scale in a number of European countries and which in the long term has been shown to help stabilise rent cost fluctuations and deliver security of tenure.  To drive delivery, a number of important cost rental pilot projects are being advanced.  They include the Enniskerry Road site in D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown and the site of the former St. Michael's estate in Inchicore, where 50 and 330 homes, respectively, are to be developed.  The contract for the work on the Enniskerry Road site is expected to be awarded later in quarter two of this year.  </p><p>Separately, the Department is engaging with the National Development Finance Agency, the European Investment Bank and the Land Development Agency on the issue of cost rental, with a view to examining the optimum funding and delivery options and establishing a consistent national approach to support delivery at scale in Dublin and other urban areas.  The work of the Land Development Agency will also be of crucial importance in delivering more affordable and cost rental housing.  The initial portfolio of sites to which the agency has access has the potential in the short to medium term to deliver 3,000 affordable homes in line with the Government's policy of achieving 30% affordable housing on State lands generally.  </p><p>In parallel, the Dublin local authorities continue to progress a number of other significant housing projects on publicly owned lands, including the redevelopment of O&rsquo;Devaney Gardens and a site on Oscar Traynor Road in Dublin city, yielding approximately 280 affordable homes.  Taken together, programmes are in place, under which nearly 18,000 affordable homes or homes with a LIHAF-related reduction will be delivered.  In addition, it is important to note that, in terms of affordability, over 11,200 households have been supported through the Rebuilding Ireland home loan and the help-to buy-scheme, demonstrating the Government&rsquo;s commitment to using a range of mechanisms and initiatives to support households in addressing the affordability challenges they face.</p><p>On the specific issue raised by the Senator in D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown, I do not have the full facts, but it appears remarkable, in the absence of some glaring omission, that a council would vote not to approve an affordable housing scheme in its area, particularly when D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown is one of the areas facing major affordability issues.  I will endeavour to get the Minister to respond directly to the Senator on the question of what will happens next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#E00200"><p>The real concern is those two pages do not address the question of targets, the principal question I asked.  I use the term "targets" because I read a circular on the RT&Eacute; news website recently in which the Taoiseach was quoted directly as saying it was important that targets be set for the 31 local authorities.  Nowhere in this response which was drawn up by a civil servant are targets mentioned.  We can keep admitting that we have problems, but if we do not set targets for delivery across the 31 local authorities, how can improvements be measured?</p> <p>I am reminded by my colleague, the former Minister for Justice and Equality, Senator McDowell, that 14 years ago Shanganagh Castle was sold to the local authority for the delivery of housing.  The site has been sat on it ever since and nothing has been done about it.  There a major affordability crisis in the area.  We also have the Central Mental Hospital in Dundrum where approximately 36 acres of State lands are being sat on.  I have singled out two State sites, for neither of which are there major plans for the delivery of affordable housing.  The clock is ticking; we have to deliver affordable houses, for both purchase and rental.  </p> <p>I thank the Minister of State and ask him to convey to the necessary authorities in the Customs House the need to respond to me this week with some explanation or rationale as to why D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown could not accept or agree to some compromise for an affordable housing priority draft scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#E00300"><p>I do not have much of a response, other than to say I will relay the Senator's comments to the Minister.  The Senator was a member of D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County council until four years ago.  The Shanganagh Castle site-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#E00400"><p>I know that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00100"><p>Ultimately, in the delivery of local authority housing it is the local authority that is supposed to be the primary driver, though sometimes that is not the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00200"><p>I agree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00300"><p>The Shanganagh site may have the potential for 540 homes overall and D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown County Council is required to carry out a cost-benefit analysis and financial modelling exercise under the public spending code, which sounds like the language of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00400"><p>The delay charter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1265" speakername="John Paul Phelan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00500"><p>I accept the point about a site being owned for 14 years but I will ask the Minister, when he is dealing with D&uacute;n Laoghaire-Rathdown in his response, to see where Shanganagh fits in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.29" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00700">Northern Ireland</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00750"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#F00800"><p>I thank the Minister for Justice and Equality for his attendance in the House.  I ask him to provide an update on the publication of the proposed Bill to provide for enhanced co-operation with legacy inquests in Northern Ireland.  The Kingsmill massacre was a heinous crime.  It was an affront to humanity and an attack on all the good people who lived and worked in the small sleepy townland of Kingsmill near Whitecross in south Armagh.  I remember the atrocity vividly as an eight year old boy growing up a few miles from where the carnage took place.  It was described as one of the deadliest mass shootings of the Troubles in a vicious parade of tit-for-tat murders in a small geographical area where the scale of the loss of human life was unimaginable.</p><p>On 5 January 1976, on a dark, cold winter's evening, a minibus with workmen travelling home after a day's work was stopped on the side of a lonely country road by armed gunmen.  The workmen were ordered out and lined up against the minibus.  The one Catholic on the minibus was ordered to run away and the 11 remaining passengers were faced with summary execution and slaughtered in cold blood.  There was no self defence and no chance.  One man, Alan Black, survived despite having been shot 18 times and he has survived to this day, no doubt reliving the horror many times over on a daily basis.  The local community was in a state of shock.</p><p>Last week in Belfast, Judge Brian Sherrard heard representations from stakeholders on the ongoing debate on whether the inquest into Kingsmill should name the two deceased suspects in the case.  These were two individuals who were in receipt of on-the-run comfort letters.  Judge Sherrard also made reference to the Birmingham bombings inquest, in respect of which senior IRA figures in Dublin had authorised the naming of four deceased suspects, names which the inquest subsequently published.  He appealed for anyone with information on Kingsmill to release this to the families or the authorities and to give answers to some of the questions that have tormented the families for over four generations.</p><p>During the hearing, counsel for the coroner, Sean Doran QC, noted that the Dublin authorities gave assurances that a Bill allowing the coroner to travel south to question Garda officers would be progressed in September 2018 but unfortunately, there appears to be little or no advancement of this.  Alan Kane QC, counsel for some of the families, made the point that families had lost hope, partly as a result of the apparent lack of appetite in Dublin to move on this, but also because of concerns that any further written questions regarding the massacre to the Dublin authorities would be a distraction from the lack of progress on the Bill.</p><p>When this was reported last week in the <i>Belfast Newsletter</i>, Philip Bradfield noted that the newspaper had contacted the Irish Department of Justice and Equality, which had responded that the drafting of the Bill was &quot;at an advanced stage&quot; and would be published very soon.  Criticism was also levelled at the Northern Ireland Office for a failure to present a witness to provide evidence on the on-the-run scheme, even though contact had been made as far back as February.</p><p>This atrocity goes down as one of the darkest episodes in the Troubles across the province.  Families, torn apart with grief and loss, have felt abandoned by the State on both sides of the Border.  These families, as passive onlookers to other inquests and inquiries, namely, the Bloody Sunday inquiry, Ballymurphy, the Birmingham pub bombings and, as recently as yesterday, the developments in the Daniel Hegarty case, feel completely abandoned and left behind with a sense of unfairness and a feeling that there is absolutely no regard for their redress, for closure for them, for answers to their questions or an opportunity to get whatever small degree of comfort or closure they rightly deserve, 43 years later.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ian Marshall:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2486"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2486&amp;amp;pid=IanMarshall&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These people are living this horror on a daily basis.  It never goes away and it never will go away.  The wrongs cannot be righted nor their loved ones returned but what can be done is to hasten the progress of this Bill to assist with answers to questions, to assist with the legal process and to demonstrate to these families that there is no hierarchy of loss, pain or suffering, that there is no hierarchy of victims and that all victims' families deserve answers and closure.</p><p>What is the status of the Bill?  What is the reason for the delay and when can the House expect to see the advancement of the Bill?  Could the Minister give assurances to the families of the Kingsmill massacre victims that no stone will be left unturned to answer their questions and to facilitate the coroner in his attempt to fill the information gaps in the 43-year struggle fighting for answers.  Furthermore, I appeal to the Kingsmill massacre inquest in Belfast to release the names of the suspects in this case.</p><p>If there is any degree of humanity or compassion in those responsible for this atrocity, they should see fit to authorise the release of the suspects' names.  The release of names in the Birmingham inquest has set a precedent, not only to identify those responsible but to take the suspicion and stigma away from those in the locality mistakenly labelled as perpetrators.  There is no doubt this one act was a defining moment in the history of south Armagh and it drove a wedge of mistrust between communities that would take decades to heal.  This Bill will not bring back the deceased, but it will go some way to reassure the families that they are as important as others and like others, they too deserve answers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#G00200"><p>I thank Senator Marshall for raising this important matter, which I understand refers to the criminal justice (international co-operation) Bill.  I acknowledge his work on these issues.  His membership of this House is important.  He provides an invaluable perspective on many issues, not least those concerning the legacy of the dark days of horrific violence on our island.  I thank him for giving me the opportunity to update the House on an issue he and I have discussed many times.  I had the opportunity of visiting the site of the Kingsmill massacre on a country road, as Senator Marshall outlined and to reflect also on the poignant monument near Whitecross.  I acknowledge the Senator's deeply personal recollection of the horrors of the atrocity at Kingsmill, and I assure him of my sincere personal commitment to ensuring the Irish Government plays its part in implementing the commitments of the Stormont House Agreement, the negotiation of which I was closely involved in, in my then role of Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade.</p> <p>I published the general scheme of the criminal justice (international co-operation) Bill in December 2017, following approval by the Government.  This proposed new legislation is an important further step in the Government's ongoing commitment to implement measures to address the legacy of the Troubles on this island and to support the victims of the Troubles and their families.  In addition to enhancing the co-operation provided to coroners' inquests in Northern Ireland into historical Troubles-related deaths, these proposals will further underpin the Government's commitment to full co-operation with the framework of measures set out in the 2014 Stormont House Agreement.  The proposed legislation will provide for a mechanism for coroners in Northern Ireland who are conducting inquests into Troubles-related deaths to hear testimony from Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na witnesses under existing Irish law.  The Bill will also extend the provisions of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 to allow the Garda Commissioner to enter into co-operation agreements with non-police law enforcement bodies outside the State.  That will be an important element in our co-operation with the legacy institutions to be established under the Stormont House Agreement, namely, the historical investigations unit and the independent commission on information retrieval.</p> <p>I must emphasise that this legislation is seeking to enhance further co-operation in addition to the considerable assistance which has already been facilitated by the Government and the Garda authorities.  In respect of the ongoing inquest into the horrific Kingsmill murders, the Government, in June 2015, approved specific legal arrangements to enable the transfer of material to the Northern Ireland coroner.  These specific legal measures were made in response to the absence of an existing formal, legal mechanism that would have allowed the Garda authorities to transfer relevant material outside the jurisdiction.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In accordance with those legal arrangements, the Garda authorities have provided the Northern Ireland coroner with all relevant documents in their possession and have responded to his follow up queries.</p><p>I strongly agree with Senator Marshall when he speaks about their being no hierarchy of victims.  He is right, and I agree with that fully.  The Bill is now at an advanced stage of drafting.  A considerable amount of legal work has been undertaken to ensure that, once enacted, this legislation will deliver on the Irish Government&rsquo;s commitment to fully co-operate with legacy inquests in Northern Ireland.  I expect to publish the Bill before the summer recess.  On the basis of previous experience with North-South related legislation I would expect broad support from all Members of the House.  I am confident that the Bill will progress swiftly through the legislative process and I will be seeking the co-operation of Senators at that point before we embark on the summer vacation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming into the House and for his response, which I fully accept.  I understand there is movement on this issue.  As I said, there is no hierarchy of victims but for any parent in Northern Ireland who buried a child or any child who buried a parent as a consequence of the Troubles, it is an unthinkable situation.  No one can bring back the victims or rewind the clock but if we are serious about reconciliation and an agreed future we must get answers to questions and some degree of closure for the families, irrespective of their background or political persuasion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#H00300"><p>Dealing with the legacy of the Troubles on this island is a difficult task.  There are no easy solutions.  I want to emphasise, however, that the Government is and always has been fully committed to the provisions of the Stormont House Agreement on addressing the history of the violent conflict in Northern Ireland.  It is a matter of regret that the political impasse in Northern Ireland has somewhat delayed the establishment of the framework of measures as set out in the Stormont House Agreement.  However, the Government remains fully committed to their implementation.  We are continuing to work with the British Government and the parties in Northern Ireland to give effect to these measures.</p><p>I agree with what Senator Marshall said about families and the need to address these issues.  At the outset of his contribution, he indicated that families were losing hope.  I want to say here in the Seanad this afternoon that families should not lose hope.  Families need answers.  Families need our help.  I am very hopeful that once the measures provided for in the Stormont House Agreement have been put in place they will provide an opportunity for the families of the many persons killed during the Troubles to access further information about those deaths where they wish to do so.  The Criminal Justice (International Co-operation) Bill will be an important element of the Irish Government's commitment to this process.  I look forward to bringing this legislation into this House before the summer and continuing to work with Senator Marshall and colleagues across the aisle in the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#H00400"><p>As there is a vote in the D&aacute;il, I ask the Acting Leader to suspend the House until 3.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#H00500"><p>I so propose.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.39" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.09 p.m. and resumed at 3.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.40" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#K00100">Public Procurement Regulations</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#K00150"><p>The Minister of State is welcome to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#K00200"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome.  Four State contracts are under way in Monaghan town at present, all of which have been secured by contractors from outside the State.  I understand the requirements of the State tendering process but is there a need for a review of that process to ensure absolute fairness?  Local people in Monaghan naturally are asking questions about the process that resulted in this happening and whether it is truly fair and just.  They are asking whether it is not strange that in awarding four State contracts, not a single contractor from Monaghan was successful.  After all, they employ local people, buy their materials from local suppliers and pay rates.  People need assurance that the current system of assessment is truly effective.  They need to be assured that the same criteria are used fairly for all tenders.  There needs to be absolute assurance that there are no loopholes, that is, that the current criteria of the tendering process do not give contractors from outside the State any unfair advantage.  Are there adequate inspections during and at the end of such contracts to ensure the criteria have been adhered to by the successful contractors?  People must be assured that there is a level playing pitch and that the Department is doing all it can to ensure this is the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#K00300"><p>I am taking this matter on behalf of the Minister for Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe.  Public procurement is a key part of the Government's overall reform agenda.  The public procurement process is governed by EU legislation and national rules and guidelines.  The aim of these rules is to promote an open, competitive and non-discriminatory public procurement regime that delivers best value for money.  It is important to point out that this regime also works to the benefit of Irish suppliers wishing to supply goods, service or works in other EU member states.  When carrying out procurement procedures, contracting authorities require suppliers to comply with a wide variety of legislation in areas that would include taxation, social policy, the environment and employment law.  Compliance with the legislation covering these areas is rightly a matter for the relevant Departments or agencies or both involved in the particular procurement process.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ciar&aacute;n Cannon:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2253"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2253&amp;amp;pid=CiaranCannon&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Public procurement regulations require applicants to meet certain standards when applying for public contracts.  That applies across the board.</p><p>The criteria upon which contracting authorities may exclude applicants from the award procedure of public contracts are set out in the European Union (Award of Public Authority Contracts) Regulations and the EU public procurement directives of 2014.  Before an applicant is excluded for certain breaches, the applicant may make a case and provide supporting evidence as to why it should not be excluded.  The contracting authority must consider this evidence before deciding whether to exclude or include an applicant.  In addition, the qualifying tenderer must submit signed declarations stating that none of the circumstances, for example, participation in a criminal organisation, corruption, terrorist offences etc. outlined in Article 57 of the procurement directive apply.  Contracting authorities may also require applicants for public contracts to declare that they have not breached their obligations in the fields of environmental, social and labour law established by European Union law, national law, and collective agreements or by the international environmental, social and labour law provisions listed in annexe X of the procurement directive.  These requirements are set out in the template documents used in tendering for goods and services, which have been developed by the Office of Government Procurement in conjunction with the Office of the Attorney General and the Office of the Chief State Solicitor.</p><p>A comprehensive interpretation of the public procurement directives, Public Procurement Guidelines for Goods and Services, has been developed to improve consistency and promote best practice in the application of the public procurement rules.  In addition to developing guidance and providing advice to contracting authorities, the Office of Government Procurement has responsibility for developing and setting out the overarching policy framework for public procurement in Ireland.  In this regard, the Office of Government Procurement has developed the national public procurement policy framework which consists of five strands, including legislation; Government policy; the capital works management framework for public works; general procurement guidelines for goods and services; and more detailed technical guidelines, template documentation and information notes, as issued periodically by the Office of Government Procurement.  This framework enables a more consistent approach to public procurement across the public sector by setting out the procurement procedures to be followed by public bodies.  The framework supports contracting authorities, including the four key sectors, namely, health, education, local government and defence, individual Departments, offices, commercial and non-commercial State bodies, and entities which are subsidised at a rate of 50% or more by a public body, when awarding contracts for works, goods and services.  It enables public bodies to adopt procedures to meet their public procurement requirements and facilitates compliance with EU and national procurement rules.  While the Office of Government Procurement guidelines facilitates and enables compliance with public procurement rules, it is the responsibility of each contracting authority to ensure that they adhere to these rules.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#L00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his response.  As I am sure he can appreciate, it is very frustrating for a local contractor who does not see one, two or three but four contracts going to contractors from outside the State, bearing in mind that these jobs are not that big to start with.  It is frustrating for people who are left wondering why their tender was not successful.  I understand what the Minister of State has said but it is important that the rules and guidelines that are in place for the awarding of these contracts are adhered to.  The Minister of State stated in conclusion that "it is the responsibility of each contracting authority to ensure that they adhere to these rules".  I seek an assurance from the Minister of State that there are adequate checks and balances in place to ensure the contracting authority is doing what it is meant to be doing, which is to ensure that the people who are successful in these contracts, to whom I wish good luck, adopt the same rules and regulations as others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1241" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Cannon" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#L00300"><p>I agree wholeheartedly with the Senator about requiring that every single contractor tendering for a project in Ireland, irrespective of from where the contractor emanates, is subject to the same set of terms and conditions and is required to comply with all of the regulatory regime underpinning the contracting process here in Ireland.  The Senator referred to oversight.  The Department of Public Expenditure and Reform requires those charged with the delivery of public works to comply with the public spending code and the capital works management framework.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ciar&aacute;n Cannon:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2253"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2253&amp;amp;pid=CiaranCannon&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That sets out the high-level principles that apply to project governance, in particular the procedures that must be followed by bodies with delegated sanction for capital expenditure - those being the awarding bodies I mentioned earlier.  All projects are required to complete the review stages set out in the code before sanction is given to go to tender.  That process is undertaken between the sponsoring agency and the sanctioning authority.</p><p>This is topical and a timely intervention on the part of the Department.  A review of the public spending code is under way in the Department.  As elements of the review are completed the associated updated guidance will be published.  Work is ongoing on updating the requirements for the various stages required in the process of selection, appraisal, approval and delivery of capital investment projects.  That review of the public spending code will be completed in the first quarter of this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.48" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.25 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.49" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#N00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re arrangements for the sitting of the House on Wednesday, 17 April 2019 and Thursday, 18 April 2019, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, Gaming and Lotteries (Amendment) Bill 2019 &ndash; Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to adjourn at 6.30  p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes; and No. 3, Aircraft Noise (Dublin Airport) Bill 2018 &ndash; Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 6.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#N00300"><p>First, I would like to extend my sympathy and that of the Fianna F&aacute;il group to the residents of Paris and the people of France on the burning of Notre Dame cathedral last night.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I presume most of us have spent some time in Paris and photographed the cathedral which is one of the most iconic churches in the world.  It is a real shame that it has burned down.  I hope it will be rebuilt at speed.</p><p>I would like to comment on the announcement made by VHI that it will cover the cost of some high-tech drugs for its private cancer care patients.  However, some of the drugs will not be available to cancer patients being treated in the public healthcare system.  As someone whose family was struck by cancer, the announcement is sickening.  It is unfair to think patients who are members of VHI will receive a different level of treatment.  We have always held ourselves up as having one of the best cancer strategies and there was fairness when it came to cancer care.  Oncologists are telling us that, from tomorrow, for patients suffering from the same illness, some will receive high-tech drugs, while others will not.  That is hugely unfair.  I ask the Minister for Health to comment on the matter as it is a source of huge concern. </p><p>I wish to discuss the issue of corporate governance.  Obviously, we have all been fascinated by the goings on in the Football Association of Ireland, FAI.  We learned that its own auditors had reported it to the Companies Registration Office, CRO, for breaches of accountancy reporting standards.  The Office of the Director of Corporate Enforcement, ODCE, probably will come on board.  For other organisations, we must ensure the ODCE is properly resourced to deal with these issues when it comes to investigating individuals in the context of corporate governance.  The spotlight is on the FAI, but there many organisations of this type in the country.  The ODCE has a long list of cases to deal with, but it is incumbent on us to ensure it is properly resourced to deal with the fallout from the discrepancies in corporate governance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#O00200"><p>I have a problem with the Order of Business in the time allocated for the Taoiseach's visit on Thursday.  The nature of my problem is that an hour and a half has been allocated.  Presumably, the Taoiseach will have the bones of half an hour to address us and a quarter of an hour at the end, with the remaining time to be divided between the spokespersons for the six groups represented in this House, who will have eight minutes each, leaving a pitiful amount of time for other Members of the House in which to contribute.  I note that the schedule, as proposed, states Members may share time.  How exactly can one share three minutes?  I do not know.  Even in being very economical in making speeches, it is not really dignified to expect Members of a House of Parliament to make a point in 90 seconds.  I, therefore, object to the allocation of time proposed.</p> <p>The other day I heard a member of the Government say on radio that the judicial council legislation and the capping of damages were being held up in this House in considering the Judicial Appointments Commission Bill.  That is simply false.  The Judicial Appointments Commission Bill has passed through Committee Stage and the only thing holding it back is the Government's consideration of Report Stage amendments.  The Bill has had a fair wind in this House.  It is completely false to give the public the impression that consideration of the question of civil liability and damages is being held up because of the length of time it is taking to consider the judicial appointments commission legislation.  The time allocated to debate the Bill is a matter for the Government, as is the order of priority of legislation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The third point I wish to make is that this House is now more than halfway through its expected term and we have made very little progress on its reform.  The people of Ireland voted to retain this House and they were told by the then Taoiseach, Deputy Enda Kenny, that he would embark on a programme of reform.  It was included in the programme for Government that he negotiated.  That was nearly the end of the story because nothing was done about it until the Taoiseach established a group chaired by me, despite the opposition of the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross.  The group produced a report.  Appended to the report was legislation, drafted by a draftsman paid for by the Department of the Taoiseach, to implement the reform on a phased basis, with nothing rushed.  Nobody in the House was likely to be affected by it for a term and a half at least.  Most Members, if they are re-elected, are assured of two further terms in the House if they play their cards correctly.</p><p>In those circumstances we have surely reached a stage now where something should be done about this.  It is cynical to the greatest extent to see this simply left aside and put on a shelf.  It is about time we confronted the issue.  I must now make it a public issue.  I have been reluctant to do so but the only way to get action on it is to bring it to the attention of the public, which I intend to do.  I have limited powers of attracting publicity but I will deploy such powers as I have in that respect to ensure some progress is made, one way or the other, with that legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#P00200"><p>Your powers to attract public attention have not diminished much in the last 20 years, Senator.  I call Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#P00300"><p>You stole my line, a Chathaoirligh.  That is what I had intended to say.  I would not describe them as limited.</p><p>On behalf of the Sinn F&eacute;in team I send solidarity to the citizens of France on the destruction of Notre Dame cathedral.  Everybody watched what was happening there last night with sadness.</p><p>I wish to propose a change to the Order of Business with regard to the Aircraft Noise (Dublin Airport) Bill 2018.  This Bill is far too serious to be pushed through Committee and Remaining Stages.  I propose that we take Committee Stage this evening and I ask Fianna F&aacute;il, in particular, to support the Sinn F&eacute;in amendments.  We should not proceed beyond Committee Stage of the Bill this evening due to its importance and the impact it will have on the lives of people who are living around Dublin Airport.</p><p>I also wish to commend the community employment, CE, supervisors who have once again gathered outside these Houses to put their case forward.  Their case, which was agreed at the Labour Court ten years ago and in a cross-party motion last year, is to give simple pension entitlements to CE supervisors and workers.  It is no more complicated than that.  These are workers who have not had a wage increase for the last ten years.  It is scandalous that they have to come here to protest for workers' rights.  I am fearful of the impact that the threatened five-day strike which they feel compelled to carry out will have on communities throughout the country in the future.</p><p>I wish to speak on broadband and the betrayal of rural Ireland.  It is an absolute betrayal, but it is not a betrayal that occurred today or yesterday.  It is a betrayal of rural Ireland and everything to do with it by this Government, the last Government and the Fianna F&aacute;il Government before that.  I have said several times in the House that Fianna F&aacute;il sold our main telecommunications company, leaving us at the mercy of French and Australian multimillionaires.  The centralisation and privatisation policies of both Governments have betrayed rural Ireland for decades.  It must stop.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We only have to look at the western rail corridor development, which is badly needed.  My colleague, Matt Carthy, MEP, had secured the backing of the European Parliament to have the western rail corridor as a priority in the report for consideration.  It then went into secret talks and the bureaucracy of the European Commission where it was blocked.  Had the Irish Government wanted it, it could have ensured that the western rail corridor development remained on the table for the funding.  When the questions were put to the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Sport, Deputy Ross, as to why the western rail corridor was removed, he cited confidentiality clauses.  We see this time and time again, hiding behind supposed confidentiality clauses.  Only last week, the Government was criticising a prominent public figure for not answering serious questions in front of the committee but when it comes to rural Ireland, the same behaviour is acceptable.  MEPs from many other European countries saw the urgent need for the rail transport development in the west and voted in favour of it.  Then behind closed doors and in full view of the Fine Gael-led Government, it disappeared.  </p><p>I ask the people in the west to ask the candidates from Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael what exactly happened to the bid to have the rail corridor included in that round of funding.  What is going on in respect of rural Ireland is disgraceful.  It has to stop.  Nice words do not cook the goose.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q00200"><p>By way of clarification, is Senator Conway-Walsh proposing a formal amendment to No. 3 on the Order of Business that only Committee Stage of the Aircraft Noise (Dublin Airport) Regulation Bill 2018 be taken today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q00300"><p>That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q00400"><p>That clarifies that.  Next, I call Senator Norris.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q00500"><p>If my Sinn F&eacute;in colleague, Senator Conway-Walsh would like it, I will very happily second her proposal, if I am not usurping Sinn F&eacute;in's place.</p> <p>I wish to express my great sadness at the partial destruction of Notre Dame cathedral, one of the saddest aspects of which is the very large destruction of medieval glass in the rose windows.  These can never be replaced and it is really sad.  I know that some people have said there are plenty of poor people in Ireland and we should look after them but we should remember it is a monument to European spirituality - I am not Roman Catholic but it is part of my heritage - and we should all be proud to help in the restoration process.  </p> <p>I wish to refer briefly to the question of what is going on in the Joint Committee on Tourism, Transport and Sport.  I understand that today, Deloitte &amp;amp; Touche has suddenly realised the FAI have broken sections 281 and 282 of the Companies Act 2014.  Where was it when all of this was going on?  The situation in the FAI was catastrophic.  Where were these auditors, what were they doing and were they asleep on the job?  Why did they not alert somebody to it?  Why have they now just discovered that they cannot sign off because there are irregularities?  This happened in 2017.  We already know that the FAI treasurer thought there was only one bank account.  There were 24 bank accounts.  How could one possibly have anything other than completely chaotic financial reporting in those circumstances?  I would like to ask the Deloitte people whether they were the crowd who were involved in auditing the banks just before the bank crash.  I think somebody should audit Deloitte &amp;amp; Touche and see whether that firm is worth a damn, because it looks to me as if it is not and I do not think we should be employing that firm in the light of its appalling track record. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q00600"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q00700"><p>I thank Senator Norris for his brevity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q00800"><p>Before I raise the issue I wish to speak on, may I say that I am sick, sore and tired of Sinn F&eacute;in Members standing up with their mantra that rural Ireland is forgotten.  Sinn F&eacute;in believes that if its Members say something often enough, it actually becomes true.  That is not the case.  Rural Ireland is not dead and gone but is very much alive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q00900"><p>The Senator's party closed the post offices.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q01000"><p>What rural Ireland needs is strong representation to continue the progress that has been made thus far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q01100"><p>The Garda stations were closed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#Q01200"><p>When Deputy Varadkar was elected Taoiseach, the first thing he did was create a Ministry and appointed a Minister with responsibility for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Ring.  There is nobody better to shout for rural Ireland.  I think that Sinn F&eacute;in Members think if they keep saying the same thing over and over, it will actually become true.  That is not the case.</p> <p>I wish to raise the one-day strike in February by community employment supervisors and assistant supervisors.  This action was taken by them because of a ten-year dispute over their pensions.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gabrielle McFadden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2399"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2399&amp;amp;pid=GabrielleMcFadden&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are 1,250 community employment, CE, supervisors, with no access to any occupational pension scheme, despite a 2008 Labour Court recommendation in their favour.  Before the strike in February, SIPTU wrote to the Minister asking him if he would meet with it to discuss the implementation of the Labour Court recommendation.  Thus far, it has not received a reply so I ask the Deputy Leader to use the good office of the Leader to request that the Minister reply, perhaps meet these supervisors and find a way of fixing this for them.  We all know about the wonderful work that is done in communities around the country, including in rural Ireland, by these supervisors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R00200"><p>There are 950 CE schemes around the country, 22,000 trainees and 1,250 supervisors who have been treated in the most appalling way.  In 2005, there was an enhanced redundancy deal offered and accepted through a Labour Court agreement, which would have given the retiring supervisors statutory redundancy plus 3.35 weeks.  What have we done with it?  Nothing.  Where are we with them?  Nowhere.  It is somewhat ironic to hear the Government side talk about the irony of what is going on here with the supervisors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R00300"><p>The Senator does not have a monopoly on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R00400"><p>The Minister should meet these people.  The Minister-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R00500"><p>Senator McFadden is very obstreperous today.  Relax.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R00600"><p>I am irritated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R00700"><p>She is normally very calm.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R00800"><p>She is a gentle soul.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R00900"><p>The Minister is obliged to meet these people and fobbing them off is simply not good enough.  There is a forum in place under the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, there is a chairman to that forum and that chairman should at least be available to them.  I ask the Deputy Leader to ensure that the chairman contacts the union responsible for the CE supervisors to ensure that a meeting takes place.</p> <p>I often speak on the Defence Forces.  Some &euro;92 million was returned to the Exchequer while soldiers cannot live.  Next week we will see soldiers parade in O'Connell Street and we will all talk of our pride in our Defence Forces.  Pride?  We could not care less about them.  We are allowing them to live in poverty so there is no pride in our Defence Forces and there is no respect for our Defence Forces.  Giving back money at a time when people cannot afford to live on the miserable pittance they are paid is no respect for anybody in uniform.  I wonder how we would feel if we finish up having to protect our borders again in this country?  I wonder how we feel every time one of our soldiers, airmen or naval personnel is killed while serving overseas?  The Irish Defence Forces have given an honourable and distinguished service to this country and what do we give them in return?  Nothing.  The Public Service Pay Commission is soon due to report and I sincerely hope it gives the Defence Forces the respect that countless Governments have failed to give it.</p> <p>I would love somebody to explain to me what it means when a chief executive officer, CEO, or a vice president or whatever name was given to the man in the FAI stepped aside last night.  What does that mean precisely?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R01000"><p>Stepaside Garda station.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R01100"><p>Hear, hear.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, is at it again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R01200"><p>What exactly does it mean?  Will he step back in?  Is this like Lanigan's ball and he will step out for a little while until all the dust settles and then he will step back in again?  At the end of the day, somebody might explain it to me because God help me, I am a little bit slow and I do not understand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R01300"><p>I might ask the Senator to give way or step aside for the next speaker.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R01400"><p>I will give way at this stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#R01500"><p>I am glad that the protest at lunchtime today was raised.  I have a particular personal interest in this because it was the first campaign I worked on as a SIPTU trade union official.  It frankly beggars belief that 11 years on, successive Governments have ignored the recommendations from their own Labour Court, the highest industrial court in the country.  This Government is very happy to lecture people for ignoring Labour Court recommendations.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Gavan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2469"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2469&amp;amp;pid=PaulGavan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It lectured the nurses on that for months.  Despite this, it has ignored this Labour Court recommendation for eight years.  Before that, Fianna F&aacute;il ignored it for three years.</p><p>Here is the thing.  These people are not well-paid.  When they retire, they have nothing to fall back on.  Having spoken to the workers outside the gates of this building, I cannot underestimate their anger.  They know, unfortunately, it is a fact that under this Government, this place is a cold house for working people and trade unions.  They cannot even get a meeting with the Minister.  The Minister for Finance did not even have the decency to reply or acknowledge that they have asked for a meeting after 11 years.  They are absolutely right to go on strike.  They have no choice.  They have tried every method.  They have tried everything.  A high-level forum was set up under the Lansdowne Road agreement to deal with this but this Government immediately ignored the agreement and has ignored it consistently since.</p><p>The Leader is not here today but, unfortunately, when I raised this issue back in February, he said that we cannot implement the recommendation because it would have financial implications that would be disastrous for the country.  This is the view from the Government that spent billions on the children's hospital, so it is nonsense.  It goes to reinforce that this Government in particular has contempt for working people and trade unions.  They are left outside the doors.  They cannot even get an acknowledgement from the Minister on this issue.  I am calling on the Government to act immediately, bring those decent people from the union, SIPTU, into this building, and treat them with respect for the first time in 11 years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#S00200"><p>The first thing I would like to do is send out some kind of energy, even from a small space, to France and the beautiful Notre-Dame de Paris, which was up in flames last night.  It reminded me of the great line by Milton from "Paradise Lost", because if I ever witnessed awe in my life, I witnessed it in Notre-Dame.  I also witnessed reverence.  I witnessed reverence from all walks of life and all peoples, colours, creeds and religions.  I know the French are a great race and they will rebuild it.  I think we should all help them, because if we want an example of elevation, magnificence, what it is to see magnificence and maybe have it in our lives, then it is Notre Dame.</p> <p>I want to talk about something else this afternoon: the new cultural body of the banks.  When I read this great article by Michelle Hennessy, I thought I was going to pass out.  I was seriously going to pass out.  The banks are now going to have a new body to improve their culture.  The new body comprises themselves, including KBC, Ulster Bank, financial advisers, Permanent TSB, AIB, Bank of Ireland and representatives from financial services.  There are many young people in the Public Gallery today.  I do not see any young people in their 20s or 30s who cannot afford a tree house or a barn or who cannot afford to live under the stairs and yet who have studied and have jobs.  I do not see any of them on the great board, which will be the new cultural way forward for our banks.  I do not see any artists on this new great cultural board that is made up of the banks themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#S00300"><p>They are con artists.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#S00400"><p>They are not going to restore trust in me, although I do not know about the young people.  They are a joke.  They brought us into the red even though they are now back in the black.  There is no one there.  I was in a bank yesterday but I had to talk to machines.  If they are going to restore my faith in machines, it is not going to happen.</p> <p>I very much believe the people have to stand up against the banks once and for all.  People should take all their money out of the bank, bar their salary, and put it in the post office, a plastic bag or maybe in a biscuit tin, because it is likely to be there when they go looking for it in several years.  They beggared us and we are paying for the beggaring.  We are choked every day by their inadequacies and profits.  Someone needs to start taking this seriously and stand up to them.  Also, we might question how much they paid for their awful building down on the docks.  To me, the idea of the banks having a cultural committee to change the sense of their own profiteering energy is simply the joke of jokes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#S00500"><p>I think we have collectively dismissed the idea of using a single-use plastic bag for our money.  A biscuit tin is a far better idea than a plastic bag.  I am keen to put that on the record in terms of climate action.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2301"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2301&amp;amp;pid=AodhanORiordan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I support Senator Gavan in what he said about CE supervisors.  </p><p>If it has not already been seconded, I second the proposal that we do not take Committee and Remaining Stages of the Aircraft Noise (Dublin Airport) Regulation Bill 2018 today.  It is not necessary to ram through the legislation this evening.  It is not fair; not right and not good parliamentary procedure, as the legislation needs to be teased out over a prolonged period.  </p><p>When we talk about politics in this House, football may not be regarded as very important, but it does touch the lives of many people.  I have just come from a briefing I hosted with Niall Quinn and others from the football family.  One of the statistics that jumped out at me was that 30% of players in the League of Ireland had no qualifications beyond the junior certificate.  That brought home to me why football was perhaps not powerful politically because the people who played the game were not powerful politically.  They do not have a high level of education, as shown by the statistic I have given, and do not have many friends in the Houses.  Other sports are more powerful politically as seen, for example, in the guaranteed and ring-fenced &euro;55 million a year for the horse and greyhound sector.  I think it received &euro;89 million last year.  While we argue over Sport Ireland's withdrawal of &euro;2.7 million, it is nothing when compared with the millions and billions funnelled through Departments and these Houses.  Once the circus moves on from the controversy over the Football Association of Ireland, FAI, its board and its former chief executive officer who is in the spotlight, politically we need to mind this sport because it is not being minded by those who are entrusted with the task of minding it.  It needs many more political friends.  Those who play the game generally come from disadvantaged communities and are more vulnerable; they are people whom politics does not necessarily reach or touch or represent, as well as others.  While today's news about the board is welcome, we need to take a new direction to have a fresh start for a sport that is so important to so many in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#T00200"><p>I am concerned about the charges imposed by local authorities on voluntary organisations, especially sports clubs, in developing new facilities.  Where a club seeks planning permission for the development of playing pitches or a clubhouse, charges are imposed on it.  Local authorities now seem to be requiring sports clubs to complete roadworks on the public road.  In a pre-planning meeting one club recently had with a local authority it was told that it would have to complete the footpath from the village to the sports facility.  The estimated cost of the work is &euro;100,000.  I am shocked that local authorities are collecting charges from developers to provide backup supports which include playing and recreational facilities.  It is wrong that money raised by a sports club from the local community is being used to put in place infrastructure the local authority should be putting in place.  We need to consider this issue and change the legislation to the effect that if a voluntary organisation, whether it be a GAA club or a soccer club, is providing facilities for a community, it should not have to pay planning charges as now required.  The local authority is requiring such organisations to carry out infrastructural works which is its responsibility.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am asking that this matter be debated and that the Minister would come here.  I was recently at a playground opening where the local community put in &euro;100,000, a lot of it raised voluntarily, and a lot of it through the LEADER programme.  The total sum paid by the local authority for that playground facility was &euro;8,000 out of &euro;100,000.  I do not think that is good enough.  It is wrong that facilities like this are being built 15 or 20 years after the housing development rather than at the same time, and then the local authorities are penalising the people who work voluntarily to provide these facilities.  We should have a debate on this matter in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#U00200"><p>I commend Deputy Hildegarde Naughton and the Joint Committee on Climate Action.  They published a very robust response and a report in respect of the Citizens' Assembly and climate change.  It is a very effective report which shows that the Oireachtas is listening to the many young people who have protested in recent times about climate change.  This has been an ongoing issue.  The Oireachtas has responded to that.  As an Oireachtas, we can collaborate well and prove to the citizens that we are responsive and we do listen.  This committee has done amazing work and needs to be congratulated across the board.  I particularly acknowledge the work in chapter 8, which deals with agriculture, forestry and the peatlands.  It makes some very strong recommendations, especially on the issue of incentivising farmers, who are in the main custodians of our environment, through financial incentives under the Common Agricultural Policy.  That is a very welcome move.  I ask every Senator to pick up a copy of the report.  I was there at the launch.</p> <p>I wish to raise the issue of the Taoiseach coming to the House this Thursday.  I welcome him and respect that he is the Taoiseach and Leader of the Government.  It is always a good opportunity to listen to what he has to say.  Having done some preparatory work in anticipation of his visit, I want to address a number of the issues he touched on and the commitments and promises he made to this House.  It appears that there will be a shortage of time in terms of the allocation for Members to speak.  People can share but it is very tight.  The motion proposes that the Taoiseach will address the House, as is right and proper.  It also proposes that he will have 15 minutes to conclude.  One does not need to be a mathematician to deduce the time remaining for a 60 Member Seanad.  It is important that we have an opportunity to listen to what the Taoiseach has to say, but I also know him to be a man who likes to listen and hear back.  We may be constrained in this House today by Standing Orders, and I respect those too.  I appeal to the Taoiseach that he may listen in and he himself may use an opportunity to seek to extend his period of engagement on Thursday.  It is my intention this afternoon, as leader of the Independent Seanad group, to write to him to this effect.  I respectfully ask the Deputy Leader to use her good office to have discussions with the Taoiseach's office to see if it is practically possible to extend his engagement by one hour.  That is a matter for him, the Deputy Leader and the House, and I respect that.  It is also a matter for the Clerk of the Seanad.  It is important that we have a positive engagement with the Taoiseach and that he is open and receptive to listening to and engaging with us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#U00300"><p>Last week, to mark World Parkinson's Day, a demonstration was held outside the gates of Leinster House.  The people there were calling for more support and a right to access specialist care.  Research clearly shows that there should be one Parkinson's nurse specialist for every 300 patients, yet in Ireland in 2019, there are only five specialist nurses for 12,000 people.  Parkinson's patients are expected to travel abroad for deep brain stimulation surgery, a life-changing procedure that should be available in this country but, sadly, is not.  Despite the fact that there is no cure for these people, they are not automatically eligible for the long-term illness scheme.  The association itself is not in receipt of any core funding from the State.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It shows that more needs to be done to assist these people suffering from this life-changing disease.  The Minister for Health should be asked to look at this issue so that funding can be provided for these people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#V00200"><p>I support the amendment to the Order of Business.  As Easter is almost upon us I wish everyone here a happy Easter.  I will be here for the next two days but may not be able to be at the Order of Business.  Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in spoke about nurses.  The deal that has been done is being put before the nurses by the Irish Nurses and Midwives Organisation, INMO, and the Psychiatric Nurses Association, PNA, to see whether it will be accepted and whether they will agree to call off the industrial action they are entitled to take.</p> <p>Easter is almost here, and I pay tribute to nurse Margaret Keogh, who was the first casualty of the 1916 Rising in the South Dublin union, now St. James' Hospital.  I will also pay tribute, as I do every year, to nurse Elizabeth O'Farrell, who surrendered on behalf of the Irish Citizen Army on Moore Street.  It is important to recognise the rebel nurses we have had and still have in the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#V00300"><p>Except that they were rebels and traitors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#V00400"><p>Before I call the Leader to respond, I would like to be associated with the expressions of sympathy and remorse in terms of the terrible fire that took place in Paris late yesterday evening and this morning.  As Cathaoirleach I met Ms H&eacute;l&egrave;ne Conway-Mouret, who is Vice President of the French Senate, and expressed on behalf of all Senators here the concern of this State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#V00500"><p>Well done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#V00600"><p>As has been said, this is not just a loss to France but a loss for the whole of Europe and the entire world.  More than 800 years of history has gone up in flames, and it is very sad.  As Senator Norris said, some of the medieval architecture-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#V00700"><p>I referred to the medieval glass.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#V00800"><p>-----can never be replaced.  I want to put that on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#V00900"><p>I join the Cathaoirleach in expressing my sadness at events in Notre-Dame.  What we saw last night in Paris was surreal.  There was some talk about how good it was that nobody died, but to me the 800 years of history and beauty and the sheer human skill that went into creating that iconic beauty means that this is a very sad event for Paris, and for anyone who has been lucky enough to be in Paris to visit what was and will be again a very beautiful cultural institution.  Senator Ardagh, among others, raised that issue.</p> <p>The VHI and the cancer drug issue is certainly of concern, but it is important to point out that when it comes to the availability and the use of medicines in public hospitals, there is no distinction between public and private patients.  The system in operation in public hospitals run by the HSE ensures that a situation can never arise where a private patient gets a drug that a public patient would not get.  This has come about as a result of the VHI's policy on private patients, which is small comfort to those who would like access to the drug, or indeed those whose lives depend on receiving that drug.  I assume that the system, which I believe is flawed in many ways in terms of how it reviews drugs to be funded, will review this drug for public patients.  I am very strongly of the view that if a drug is available that can improve the lives of cancer patients, then it should be made available to all patients.</p> <p>Many Senators raised the issue of the FAI and the fallout there has been in terms of corporate governance.  As a lawyer it seems to me that there are very serious allegations about breaches of the Companies Act.  Breaches of this kind occur very rarely.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I imagine there will be continuing fallout from this.  As Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in said, one would be concerned about the effect on the ordinary player and it must be very disillusioning for small clubs around the country to watch this unfold.  A natural progression would be a renewed focus on improving the game, from the point of view of funding and from a structural point of view in terms of how it is managed.  Some questions Senators have raised are being answered.  Senator Craughwell asked what stepping aside would mean.  New terms are being brought into use each day regarding this fiasco.  We need to watch and wait and ensure this does not happen again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W00200"><p>What about the accountants?  Are they any use?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W00300"><p>I cannot comment on Deloitte, Touche or any other accountants.  I imagine that any accountants would have been able to spot these glaring inadequacies in the structure.  It seems unorthodox, to say the least, that there were 24 bank accounts but I cannot comment because I do not know the full details.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W00400"><p>What is the difference between stepping aside and side-stepping?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W00500"><p>We could have a debate all day on that.  Senator McDowell asked about the time allocated for the Taoiseach's address on Thursday.  That has been a long-standing arrangement and the Taoiseach's diary is arranged well in advance.  I can understand why Senators might like to make a contribution but the Leader's office has been in touch and it is not possible to have an extension to the meeting on Thursday.  We will seek another opportunity to interact with the Taoiseach in early course and whenever he can make himself available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W00600"><p>Perhaps Government Senators could desist from speaking, leaving time for others.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W00700"><p>Please allow the Acting Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W00800"><p>Perhaps Senators could talk to one another about how to get succinct questions across.  As Senator Boyhan pointed out, the Taoiseach is a very listening person and if people do not make lots of statements and avoid repetition, it could be possible to get more time.  I have the impression that we generally want to say what we have to say here.  The Taoiseach could come back to us if he does not have enough time, as Ministers do on a regular basis.  It is not possible to extend the time on Thursday but I imagine it will be quite adequate to get through a good number of issues.</p> <p>The point on the Judicial Council Bill was well made.  There will be an opportunity to speak to the boss man about Seanad reform on Thursday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W00900"><p>Loud laughter ensues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01000"><p>Senator Conway-Walsh moved an amendment to the Order of Business regarding Committee Stage of the Aircraft Noise (Dublin Airport) Bill 2018.  There is no end time on the Bill this evening and we can continue speaking as long as Members wish.  There is no suggestion of guillotining it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01100"><p>What about amendments for Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01200"><p>We need time to submit amendments on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01300"><p>I am not willing to accept the amendment.  I understand the point about amendments on Report Stage but the order of the House which I have moved envisages us sitting until whatever time we wish this evening for Committee and Remaining Stages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01400"><p>It is highly undemocratic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01500"><p>Will there be provision for a break to allow us to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01600"><p>The Leader can come in and arrange for a break for Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01700"><p>It is a typical Ross mess.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01800"><p>It does a terrible disservice to the people living in the proximity of the airport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W01900"><p>The Acting Leader has outlined the position and if Senators are not happy, they can vote on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#W02000"><p>This is my position.  There is no wish on the part of the Government to stymie any debate on it.  If Senators wish to stay here until 12 midnight, that can be facilitated.</p> <p>Senator Conway-Walsh, along with other Senators, raised the issue with CE supervisors.  I will relay the comments of Senators to the Minister on that.  There should be interaction between the Minister and those workers and, as Senator McFadden said, it would be reasonable to meet at least, to allow a discussion to be had.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=04&amp;amp;day=16"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I do not think a reply has been received regarding meeting with the Minister, which is something that should happen.  I will pass on the Senator's comments in that regard to the Minister.</p><p>Senator Norris also raised Notre Dame.  We are all very sad about that.  He also raised the FAI.  I responded to his comments about the accountants that were in place since 2017, and I understand the reason for those remarks.</p><p>Senator McFadden also raised the CE supervisors issue on which she has been working.  I made my response to that.  Senator Craughwell also raised the CE schemes and the Defence Forces, as he does regularly in the House.  He indicated that the Public Service Pay Commission is due to report.  Senator McFadden has been in touch with the Taoiseach whom she has asked to speed up the process so that the report would come sooner rather than later.  We will have to await the outcome of that.</p><p>Senator Gavan also raised the CE supervisors, an issue to which I have responded.  Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell also eloquently expressed her sadness on Notre Dame.  I understand her frustration when speaking about the banks.  One needs to pick a particular bank to be able to interact with a person.  That is very frustrating.  Perhaps there is something positive in the fact that the banks have recognised they have problems that they need to address but who knows if they will improve their behaviour towards people who use their services.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#X00200"><p>I am finding it difficult to hear the Acting Leader.  Radio Luxembourg seems to be butting in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#X00300"><p>Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in also referred to the CE supervisors and the Aircraft Noise (Dublin Airport) Regulation Bill.  I referred to the valid points he made about the FAI, ordinary soccer players and the funding that should rightly be improved.</p> <p>Senator Colm Burke raised an interesting point about voluntary organisations being charged large fees, up to &euro;100,000, for carrying out works on a public road.  That would be useful legislation for him to introduce in consultation with the Department.  It is an important issue to highlight and it is one we could also debate in the House.</p> <p>Senator Boyhan complimented the Joint Committee on Climate Action.  We compliment all colleagues, especially those in this House, who partook in that very useful and worthwhile committee.  It shows the effect of cross-party committees in these Houses.  We have much work to do and the committee highlights a roadmap for that.  He also expressed his dissatisfaction with the length of the Taoiseach's visit on Thursday, which I addressed.</p> <p>Senator Gallagher raised World Parkinson's Day.  Until last week I did not realise one could not access brain stimulation therapy in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#X00400"><p>No, one cannot.  One has to go to Bristol.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#X00500"><p>It is shocking.  That is something we should debate in this House with the Minister, following on from the protests of the Parkinson's organisations last week.  Senator Devine, as a nurse, rightly wants to pay tribute to Margaret Keogh and others who were trailblazers in their field.  I bid her a happy Easter now in case I do not get to say it to her in advance of Easter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#X00600"><p>Senator Conway-Walsh has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, which was seconded by Senator Norris: "That Committee Stage only of the Aircraft Noise (Dublin Airport) Regulation Bill 2018 be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#X00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.130" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.131" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#AA00100"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(b) I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.133/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#AA00200"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 14; Níl, 22.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Máire Devine and Paul Gavan; Níl, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and John O'Mahony.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.133/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2019-04-16" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#AA00200">
            <divisioncount ayes="14" noes="22" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="aye">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="aye">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="aye">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" vote="aye">Ian Marshall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" vote="aye">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" vote="aye">Gerald Nash</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" vote="aye">Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" vote="no">Catherine Ardagh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="no">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="no">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="no">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" vote="no">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" vote="no">Frank Feighan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="no">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="no">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="no">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="no">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="no">James Reilly</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.133/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#AA00200"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#CC00100"><p>Is the Order of Business agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#CC00200"><p>Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#CC00300"><p>No. 1 is a motion regarding arrangements-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#CC00400"><p>The Order of Business is not agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#CC00500"><p>I thought it was agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#CC00600"><p>There is too much noise in the Senate.  If people want to chat they should move out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.140" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question, "That the Order of Business be agreed to", put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.141" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#DD00100"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(b) I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.143/1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#DD00200"><p>Question again put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: Tá, 19; Níl, 16.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and James Reilly; Níl, Senators Victor Boyhan and Michael McDowell.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.143/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2019-04-16" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#DD00200">
            <divisioncount ayes="19" noes="16" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" vote="aye">Catherine Ardagh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="aye">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="aye">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="aye">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="aye">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="aye">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" vote="aye">Paul Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1383" vote="aye">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="aye">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="aye">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="aye">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="aye">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="aye">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="aye">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" vote="no">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" vote="no">Rose Conway Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="no">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="no">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1428" vote="no">Joan Freeman</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="no">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="no">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" vote="no">Ian Marshall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" vote="no">Michael McDowell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="no">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" vote="no">P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="no">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" vote="no">Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" vote="no">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.143/3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019041600002#DD00200"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-04-16a.144" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>