<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#A00100">Business of Seanad.</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Jim Walsh that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to outline if the Government is refusing to support growing international calls describing the systematic murder, rape, slavery and persecution of Christians in the Middle East as &ldquo;genocide&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Pat O'Neill of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to state whether he feels the proposed takeover of Slaney Meats by ABP Group will have a positive or negative effect for the future of agriculture in Ireland, and if this takeover goes ahead whether the Minister will be making a submission to the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to allocate funds for house adaptation work to local authorities and that, when these funds are allocated, the local authority would have absolute discretion over the amounts allocated for local authority housing and private housing.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Bradford of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to outline the current position regarding the promised review of the 2014 local government arrangements.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by the Senators as suitable for discussion and they will be taken now.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#A00350">Foreign Conflicts</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#A00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Dara Murphy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#A00500"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  In putting this Commencement matter to the Minister I wish to emphasise, and the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade has acknowledged this, the terrible persecution of Christians in the Middle East and Africa by Boko Haram, Daesh and various other bodies.  There is a growing awareness that this is a systematic killing of minorities such as Yazidis and Christians, and Coptic Christians in the case of Libya.  There is a need for the international community to do more than it is doing at present.  Rhetoric is fine, but it must be backed by more concrete action which will hopefully, in the first instance, make the perpetrators of these atrocities begin to think that they will be held accountable.  Many politicians in the US and Britain have been calling for this to be recognised for what it is, genocide.</p> <p>The Minister of State might be aware that shortly before Christmas a group of 75 British politicians sent a letter to the Prime Minister to express their concern about the genocide being perpetrated by Daesh against various communities, including Iraqi and Syrian Christians, Yazidis and other vulnerable groups.  They pointed out that there is clear evidence that genocide is occurring, including the assassination of church leaders which we have seen, mass murders, torture, kidnapping for ransom in the Christian communities in Iraq and Syria, sexual enslavement, which is very common, the systematic rape of Christian girls and women, forcible conversion to Islam, destruction of churches, monasteries, cemeteries and Christian artifacts, and the theft of lands and wealth from Christian clergy and laity.  Daesh has made statements taking credit for the mass murder of Christians, so it is not as if these things are happening unknown to the world.  Daesh has put these statements on the media.</p> <p>One incident is an example of what is happening.  Last December, Daesh tortured a young child along with two other Christians and crucified them to death.  In an attempt to force the child's father to convert to Islam from Christianity the boy's fingertips were cut off.  The bodies were left hanging on crosses for two days under signs reading "infidels".  That is a clear indication that what is happening is tantamount to genocide.  Genocide as defined by the 1948 Convention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Genocide makes it clear that genocide is not simply random killing of individuals but the systematic killing or serious harming of people because they are part of a recognisable group, which may be national, ethnic, racial or religious.  The convention identifies it as acts committed with the intent to destroy the group in whole or in part.</p> <p>The purpose of this Commencement matter is to call on the Minister and the Government to use all the influence at their disposal, at both the United Nations and the European Union, to obtain an agreement that the word "genocide" be used.  That will have two main benefits.  It will send a clear message to those who are organising and undertaking the slaughter that at some point in the future they will be held accountable for their actions by the international community and that they will be caught, tried and punished.  It will also act as an incentive and encouragement to the other 127 nations that are signatories to the convention to face up to their duty of responsibility in this regard.  It would be a sad reflection on Europe, which has a strong Judeo-Christian tradition, if it fails when our Christrian brethren are being slaughtered to such an extent across the Middle East and parts of north Africa.  The time has come for governments and Ministers to step up on this issue.  I hope that ideological groups within the public service in the EU and the United Nations will not thwart this because of their antipathy to some Christian religions.  It would be a sad day if that happened.</p> <p>This is an appalling episode in our midst.  I hope the Minister will give a strong reply and that the Government will deny some of the reports that this Government is reluctant to classify it as genocide.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#A00600"><p>I thank Senator Walsh for his concern and the efforts he has made consistently to highlight the plight of the Christian minority in the Middle East and in other parts of the world.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Dara Murphy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2320"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2320&amp;amp;pid=DaraMurphy&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Government is in no doubt that Christian communities in many parts of the Middle East, especially in areas facing the rise of extremist groups such as Daesh, have been the victims, as the Senator said, of appalling crimes, including murder, sexual violence, enslavement and forced conversions.  The Government has repeatedly condemned crimes that have been committed against many religious minority communities, including Christians.</p><p>Ireland, in conjunction with 57 other states, sponsored a resolution calling for the UN Security Council to refer the situation in Syria to the International Criminal Court in 2014, as I am sure the Deputy is aware.  Unfortunately, the resolution was vetoed by two permanent members of the Security Council, namely, China and Russia.</p><p>Ireland has provided over &euro;43 million in recent years in humanitarian support for the victims of the Syrian and Iraqi crises and will make a further significant contribution at the forthcoming London conference on the Syrian crisis, which takes place in two weeks' time.  We have also accepted over 200 refugees from the Syrian conflict through our resettlement programme and, together with the UN, have also volunteered to take in, as the Senator will be aware, a further 4,000.</p><p>In line with international law on refugees, we do not discriminate between refugees on the basis of their ethnicity or religion.  Furthermore, we do not believe that the solution to persecution is to remove Christian communities from the Middle East, as this would effectively mark the destruction of Christian heritage at the very place of its birth.  The only means of securing the protection of Christian communities and other minorities across the Middle East is through the promotion of sustainable political solutions to the conflicts which have for so long destabilised the region and have been the key factor in the promotion of radical and extremist ideologies.  Ireland has been a key supporter of the UN's efforts to achieve an end to the conflict in Syria and Libya and for a unified Iraq free from the threat of Daesh crimes.</p><p>The Government has no doubt that horrific atrocities amounting to grave war crimes have been committed in the Middle East, including those, as the Senator noted, that have deliberately targeted Christian communities.  The crime of genocide is, however, specific and unique.  In order to not to undermine the status of this crime nor weaken its definitional elements, very careful consideration is required before making a determination that genocide has been committed.  This should include an assessment of the evidence supporting such claims.  Ireland fully endorses the views of the UN High Commissioner for Human Rights that, subject to a determination by an independent and competent court, ISIS may have committed war crimes against humanity and genocide.</p><p>I note that the largest number of victims of jihadist terrorists and terrorism attacks have, in fact, been Muslims whom Daesh and other terrorist groups have murdered for their lack of religious observance, their homosexuality or their commission of petty crimes.  As the Senator is aware, Ireland's capacity to obtain direct information from the areas in which the crimes are taking place is limited.  It is considered appropriate, therefore, that the matter is properly investigated by an independent and competent court or tribunal.  It is a determination resulting from such an investigatory and adjudicative process that is likely to assist in bringing these crimes to an end.  It is for this reason that Ireland has, for example, called for the situation in Syria to be referred to the International Criminal Court, the role of which in respect of the investigation and the prosecution of international crimes we have consistently supported.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#B00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his fairly comprehensive reply.  He dealt with the issue of genocide which, as he went on, I thought he would not.  We need to be careful.  There are radical ideological groups within the UN, in particular.  It is not an organisation that is as kosher as it would like to pretend.  If our blood brothers and sisters were being taken, raped, forced to convert and forced into sexual slavery and if elderly people were being killed, we would cry out to the high heavens about it.  These people are our brothers and sisters in Christ.  Therefore, our concern should be equally strong.  </p> <p>There is evidence for genocide in all of the reports that have been published.  The killing of Coptic Christians in Libya and what has happened in Syria has been put on video.  It is pretty clear that there is an attempt to wipe out the Christian community.  I have views about whether we should be selective about immigrants but that is a separate issue. </p> <p>I agree with the Minister of State.  It is important that we not do not denude the Middle East of its Christian community.  The Patriarch of Antioch has made a statement in that regard and has appealed to Christians to remain there.  I urge the Minister of State to ensure that the Government takes a much stronger position than it has done in this regard and to press for the latter to be defined.  Most objective people would agree that what has happened is tantamount to genocide.  The definition may have to be met but it should not be allowed to be blocked by one or two countries.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#B00300"><p>As I have said, the Government believes the UN and the Security Council, in particular, have not fulfilled their obligations to uphold the UN charter or international law in Syria to date.  Genocide is defined under international law as the intent to destroy, in whole or in part, a national ethnic, radical or religious group, as the Senator said.  However, proving the crime of genocide requires a comprehensive investigation of the evidence and having that established by a competent international court.  We, along with other members, have been strong on this, and we believe that, ultimately, this proof from a competent court will provide what we all want to see, namely, an end to the terrible violence, not just against Christians but also against Muslims and others as well.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#B00350">Beef Industry</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#B00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh.  I am disappointed that the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Coveney, is not present.  I mean no disrespect to the Minister of State in saying that and I am aware that the Minister is currently speaking in the D&aacute;il, perhaps on the same matter.</p> <p>I tabled this matter because there is a great deal of concern in the agricultural industry, especially among farmers, who are the primary producers, about the proposed takeover of Slaney Meats by ABP Food Group.  Such a development would place the latter in a dominant position in the market and that could be to the detriment of farmers.  My matter I tabled asks the Minister whether he feels it would have a positive or negative effect on the future of agriculture in this country and whether he would make a submission to the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission.  The commission has been in correspondence with the Joint Oireachtas Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, of which I am a member, on this matter.  It said it cannot make a comment until the takeover goes ahead.  I am concerned about the timing of the takeover.  If it takes place within the next couple of weeks, during a general election, no Oireachtas committee will be able to deal with it.  The current Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine will be operating in an acting capacity.  The takeover may, therefore, proceed without due scrutiny.</p> <p>In the past couple of years, there have been many problems in the beef industry.  Rules on full beef, steer beef, specs and weights were imposed by factories and retailers and these worked to the detriment of the farming community.  The Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine had to intervene in the sector at different stages because beef was in crisis.  He established the beef forum - whether it is working is another question, but at least it was established and it is trying to solve our problems in the beef industry.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pat O'Neill:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2364"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2364&amp;amp;pid=PatONeill&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The beef and sheep sectors, including the export of live cattle and meat, employ nearly 280,000 people in this country.  It is important that these sectors have the support of the Minister and the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission so that something like this does not happen.</p><p>If the ABP group takes over Slaney Meats, it will have 29% of the beef kill, 40% of the lamb kill and 50% of the rendering plants in the country.  A big problem on the previous occasion was the rendering plants because rendering is a by-process which must be done.  If the ABP group has 50%, it could lead to a lack of competition.</p><p>Following the past year, the price gap between our beef and beef in Britain is now &euro;293 per head.  It was &euro;97 per head on average over the past ten years.  This is because the factories and the retailers have now applied specifications that live Irish exports cannot be killed and put on the shelves in Britain as British beef.  That is why it is important that the Minister intervene to sort out the problem with Northern Ireland at present.  We have a big problem in that our beef cannot be sent across the Border to Northern Ireland to be slaughtered and get the Red Tractor standard.</p><p>The reason I have raised this matter is that I am worried this will have a detrimental effect.  I note the Minister is dealing with it in the D&aacute;il and I am interested to hear his reply.  The takeover could be timed to occur when this House, the D&aacute;il and the Oireachtas joint committee are at their least effective.  It is important that we keep an eye on it and that the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission intervenes to ensure that agriculture is not ignored.  Livelihoods are at stake here if this goes ahead and is not dealt with properly.</p><p>I am interested to hear the Minister of State's reply.  I know he will pass on what I have said to the Minister, who, I suppose, can also see it in the Official Report.  I note the Minister is dealing with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#C00200"><p>I thank Senator O'Neill for raising this matter.  It shows that the Senator's ear is to the ground because in my constituency in Donegal it is very much a concern in the farming community, not only regarding this proposed takeover, but in general regarding the price of beef in the factories.  When Senator O'Neill's colleague beside him, Senator Comiskey, and I meet, we talk about that significant challenge in relation to price.</p> <p>The Minister apologises that he cannot be here.  Not alone will this go into the Official Report, but the Ministers and the officials will be listening to the Senator's contribution.</p> <p>With regard to the proposed takeover raised by the Senator, there is a well established independent regulatory process involved in the assessment of such takeovers.  This is to ensure that consumers, other businesses or, indeed, agriculture in Ireland does not suffer or that the proposed takeover does not lead to a reduction in competition in any individual sector.  As the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, has stated, neither he nor any other Minister has any function in the process of assessing company mergers in Ireland.</p> <p>The State, through the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission, has an existing and well established infrastructure for the assessment of mergers and acquisitions of business organisations generally.  As part of this assessment, the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission examines any proposed merger or acquisition involving business organisations to ensure there is no substantial lessening of competition.</p> <p>However, in situations where a proposed merger or acquisition breaches certain thresholds, the matter must be notified directly to the EU Commission.  In such situations, my understanding is that the EU Commission itself may investigate the takeover or refer the matter back to the Irish authorities depending on the circumstances of the situation.  As part of this process, the investigation of the proposed takeover will involve either a one or two stage investigation by the relevant authorities.  At the end of the process, a number of outcomes are possible, including that the authorities may unconditionally clear the merger, approve the merger subject to remedies or prohibit the merger if no adequate remedies to the competition concerns have been proposed by the merging parties.</p> <p>The structure of the Irish beef processing sector has been the subject of much discussion over the years and one of the recurring themes has been the question of rationalisation in the processing industry to improve its efficiency.  However, it is clear that any such rationalisation must avoid distorting competition within the sector.  That is why the process of examining this particular proposed takeover is of utmost importance.  The process of the investigation by the relevant authorities is a detailed and robust one.  Furthermore, the process is a transparent one, with, if this matter is notified to the EU Commission, details of any new notifications being published on the Commission's competition website.  This will allow any interested parties to contact the Commission and to submit comments on the merger.  There are also timelines laid down for the completion of the different stages of the investigation to ensure that the investigation is completed in as timely a manner as possible for the sake of all parties.</p> <p>The Minister is very conscious of the need for competition in the beef sector and other sectors in Ireland.  I also emphasise that in addition to the number of meat processors, competition in the marketplace is dependent on a number of factors, including the number of markets available for sellers of Irish beef to place their product on and, of course, as Senator O'Neill said, a vibrant live export trade.</p> <p>Live exports are an important means of providing alternative market outlets for cattle farmers in Ireland, thereby increasing the level of competition surrounding the purchasing of cattle.  While 2015 was challenging in terms of live exports due to, for example, political difficulties in North Africa and new veterinary requirements regarding IBR in Belgium, it should be noted that increased domestic prices also contributed to a reduction in live exports for the year to 180,000 head, which was down from 2014.</p> <p>It is expected that 2016 will see an increase in the export of live cattle due to the improving economic situations in other countries, such as Italy and Spain, which have traditionally provided an outlet for the export of Irish cattle.  Additionally, there are currently three dedicated and three roll-on-roll off vessels approved for the carriage of livestock by sea from Irish ports and three more vessels are currently at various stages of the process for similar approval.</p> <p>On a more general note, and entirely independently of this proposed merger, it is widely accepted that there are imbalances in the relative power of primary producers compared to other operators along the supply chain.  With this in mind, the Minister is finalising regulations for the recognition of producer groups in the beef sector in order to permit farmers to benefit from the advantage of scale when it comes to selling their produce or purchasing inputs.  I am sure this proposal had its genesis within the beef discussion group which Senator O'Neill mentioned earlier.</p> <p>It is in the interest of all stakeholders in the Irish beef industry that there is healthy competition at all stages of production to ensure that the future of Irish agriculture is a positive one which allows the industry and the Irish beef sector to continue to grow in a sustainable manner.  I am satisfied that the regulatory process for the assessment of mergers are in place and will ensure a thorough and independent assessment of the impact of the proposed takeover, having regard to the requirements of competition law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#C00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy McHugh, for the reply on behalf of the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine.</p> <p>The Minister of State mentioned that live exports are down this year, which is not a good development, and he predicts that they will be up next year.  One must bear in mind that over 50% of the live exports from this country are female dairy exports which does not help the beef sector, for example, the steers, because that is what one needs to get out.  I encourage the Minister and other Departments, for example, the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, to continue liaising with the countries, such as Turkey and Libya, so that we can try to export live cattle because it is important that there is competition in the market.</p> <p>The Minister of State said that mergers go through the relevant bodies, such as the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission and also the European Commission, but it is important that the Minister shows a lead here because he represents the primary producer.  He is not here to represent the meat factories or those involved in the meat industry.  He is here to represent over 140,000 farmers, 100,000 of whom are involved in beef production.  It is important that whoever is the Minister in the next Government, whether it is the Minister, Deputy Coveney, or someone else, makes a submission to the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission and to the Commission.  If there is the weight of a Minister behind one, it adds credence to the worries of people.  It is important no matter what.  Regardless of whether the Minister thinks he can, it is important that he does so because the weight of a Minister on such a submission will help to ensure that the farmers of this country are not be ripped off by somebody getting a dominant share in the market.</p> <p>Before I conclude, I forgot to welcome Mr. John Bambrick, who is chairman of Kilkenny IFA.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Pat O'Neill:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2364"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2364&amp;amp;pid=PatONeill&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I thank him for coming to the House to take this debate.  He is a former neighbour of mine.  We used to live on the same road until he got a bit richer and moved on.  He is very welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/997" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#D00200"><p>It is good that the Senator is raising this matter today, particularly as he is articulating grave concerns.  There was a lobbying session by the IFA a couple of weeks ago and the matter is very much on its radar.  The Minister cannot refer anything to the Commission until the merger happens.  Prior to the latter taking place, the Senator is raising the matter publicly, creating awareness and notifying the Minister.  There is a robust process to go through if there are concerns.  It is obviously that the Senator has concerns at this early stage.  If the merger were to happen, there are mechanisms in place, through both the Competition and Consumer Protection Commission and the European Commission.  That is a mechanism that is open to the Minister.  It is important that the matter is raised.  Every farmer who is involved in the beef industry has grave concerns in respect of this matter.  They are articulating that and the Senator has added value by raising the issue publicly today.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.22" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#D00300">Housing Adaptation Grant</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#D00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Ann Phelan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#D00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  The issue I am raising relates to the allocation of funding to local authorities for house adaptation work.  One local authority with which I am dealing was allocated something in the region of &euro;1.9 million last year and that money was allocated to people who owned their own houses to do adaptation work on them.  The same local authority received only &euro;560,000 for carrying out adaptation work on local authority houses.  I am raising this issue because there is a huge backlog in respect of adaptation work required in respect of local authority houses.</p> <p>One case with which I am dealing involves a family where the child has serious intellectual and physical disabilities.  In July 2008, the family was advised that the house needed to be adapted because the child has to be lifted out of bed every morning, washed, and tube fed.  There is a great deal of work involved in that.  The house in which the family lives is not adequate for their needs.  In fairness, after seven and a half years and as a result of pressure from me - which the media highlighted - the local authority has responded and the work is now being done.  However, seven and a half years is a significant period to wait for work to be done.  There is a now a waiting list with Cork City Council of between seven and eight years for adaptation work in respect of local authority houses.  I am asking that for this year - I am not asking for every year, just this year - local authorities would be entitled to use the money allocated to them in whatever way they can in order to reduce the waiting time to get adaptation work done on local authority houses.  It is in that context that I am raising this matter.  Local authorities need to deal with the backlog.  The only way this can be done is by giving priority to local authority housing for one year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/964" speakername="Ann Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#D00600"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter.  I know it is an extremely important issue, particularly for the people on those lists who are waiting for work to be done to their homes in order that they can alleviate the impact of some of the situations to which the Senator referred.</p><p>The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government provides funding to local authorities under housing adaptation grants for older people and people with disabilities in respect of private homes and, separately, funds adaptations and extensions to social housing stock in order to address serious overcrowding and, in certain cases, to meet the needs of tenants with a disability.  The suite of grants available to private homeowners is 80% funded by the Department, with a 20% contribution from the resources of each local authority.  Three distinct grant types are available.  The housing adaptation grant for people with disabilities assists those with a disability to have necessary adaptations, repairs or improvement works carried out in order to make their accommodation more suitable for their needs.  The mobility aids grant is available to fast-track funding to cover a basic suite of works to address the mobility problems of a member of a household.  Qualifying works include the provision of stair lifts, level access showers, access ramps, grab rails and other minor adaptation works.  Finally, the housing aid for older people provides grants to assist older people living in poor housing conditions to have necessary repairs or improvements carried out.  Grant-eligible works include structural repairs or improvements, rewiring, repairs to or replacement of windows and doors, provision of water supply and sanitary facilities, provision of heating, cleaning, painting, etc.  Over 7,600 households benefited under these schemes in 2015.  It is expected that approximately 8,500 grants will be provided in 2016, which will assist with adaptation works to enable older people and those with disabilities to remain living independently in their own homes for longer.  In 2015, &euro;40.4 million in Exchequer support was made available countrywide for these supports and this has been increased by 10% for 2016.  At local level, the detailed administration of these schemes, including the assessment, approval and payment of individual grants to applicants, is the responsibility of the relevant local authority.</p><p>Separately, my Department provides a range of supports to local authorities to upgrade, maintain and adapt social housing to meet tenants&rsquo; needs.  This includes works to improve energy efficiency, provide extensions to deal with overcrowding and facilitate adaptations for people with disabilities.  As funding to local authorities for adaptations to social housing is part of a broader range of improvement funding for the authorities' own stock, it is budgeted for separately from the funding provided for private houses.  Adaptations to council houses are funded to the value of 90% by the Department, with local authorities providing the remaining 10%.  The implementation of works under these supports for local authority tenants is a matter for the authorities themselves.  It is for them to determine, in the first instance, if the works are needed in order to make the accommodation more suitable for the tenant and to prioritise the use of available resources.  In recent years, a concerted effort has been made to protect expenditure in respect of extensions and adaptations to local authority homes.  In 2015, funding nationally for this area was approximately &euro;11 million and it is expected that the funding for 2016 will at least be maintained at this level.</p><p>While local authorities do not have the discretion to reassign funding intended for private house grants to grants for the improvement of local authority stock or <i>vice versa</i>, my Department is responsive to the needs of individual local authorities in respect of the two separate schemes.  Local authorities are asked to submit details of the works proposed under both schemes, including identifying priority cases.  Where, for example, a local authority has less need for one stream of funding over another, a rebalancing of the budgets will be provided in line with the overall national availability of funding.  My Department is very much aware of the social benefit accruing from these schemes in terms of facilitating the continued independent occupancy of their own homes by older people and those with disabilities and also in the facilitation of early return from hospital stays.  The Department will, therefore, continue to work constructively with local authorities to meet priority needs for adaptations, whether to private houses or to the local authority housing stock.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#D00700"><p>The answer is what I expected but the problem is that both Cork city and county councils have waiting lists of seven years duration in respect of adaptation works.  The reply I have received is not going to do anything about that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For instance, in two cases the family has gone to the Ombudsman for Children.  I have one family which has been waiting more than six years.  The child has Canavan disease, which is related to cystic fibrosis.  The parent has to lift the child up and down the stairs every day to go to the bathroom because there is no downstairs bathroom.  The child is now seven.  It is more difficult every day to lift the child because the child is getting bigger.  I have a number of other cases like this.  That case has gone to the ombudsman's office, which is dealing with the local authority directly.</p><p>There is another problem with house adaption work in that no rating is given to the seriousness of the disability.  Once someone is deemed to require adaption work, he or she is just a number on a list and there is no priority list whereby, for example, the most serious case is five and the least serious is one.  That is another issue local authorities must deal with.</p><p>I have people waiting seven years on Cork City Council and the response I have received has done nothing to help me to resolve their problems.  The solution I have come up with is to deal with this backlog over one year to make serious inroads, and this should be taken on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/964" speakername="Ann Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#E00200"><p>I understand there are complexities and I acknowledge the level of priority the Senator is talking about.  If he will forward the list of the most urgent cases he is dealing with, I will undertake to bring them to the Minister's attention to see if we can examine them in that way.  Now that the Department is aware of the position in Cork, I will undertake to look into this to see if we can move on that list and see what needs to be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#E00300"><p>I appreciate that and I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.30" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#E00400">Local Government Reform</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#E00500"><p>I am grateful for the opportunity to ask the Minister of State to outline the current position regarding the promised review of the 2014 local authority boundaries, workload and ancillary matters.  The reform of local government in 2014, which resulted in the abolition of town councils and the creation of municipal districts, was a sea change in local government.  In retrospect, many people have come to the conclusion that some of the changes have had a negative impact.  In particular, there is a growing view that local government structures at town and community level must be reviewed again.  I am sure many municipal districts are working effectively, but some of them are large.  For example, a number in County Cork are 18 miles long.  Once a municipal district is of that scale, the word "local" is removed from the concept of local government and local democracy.  We are more than three years away from the next local government elections.  Unfortunately, these elections are held on a fixed five-year basis, but we have time to plan ahead.</p> <p>In the immediate aftermath of the changes, a number of senior and junior Ministers, led by the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, stated that they felt a review was required and consideration should be given to a town council structure in particular.  If there is a willingness to do that, we must look beyond the traditional town councils.  Many large towns and urban areas never had a town council, and I hope that a review would consider areas where new structures are required.  What is the current status of the operational review?  Where is it heading from the point of view of its thinking and philosophy on local government reform and local structures?  We still complain in this country about top-down decision-making in Brussels and about centralised thinking and political decision-making, but that is what have begun to do at local government level.  If we want to empower and engage citizens and if we want communities to work with and on behalf of each other, driving local services, newer and small local government structures will be required.</p> <p>I hope all of this is being considered in the review.  I am simply seeking an update.  Will the Minister of State put on the agenda the possibility of returning to sub-county structures by way of town and community or district councils?  We are beginning to learn that removing councillors from communities was a retrograde step.  Town councils and town councillors did not have all the answers, but they were a visible form of local government and local decision-making and people could engage almost on a daily basis with at least one of their town councillors.  This brought local government and politics closer to people, which is where it should be.  Smaller councils should have a role to play in the fruits of any review.  I am seeking an update on the review and on the Minister of State's thinking.  She served on a council in Kilkenny and she will be aware of the fantastic work that can be done in a non-political, non-partisan way at local government level.  This was done on a daily basis without any fanfare and I would like to return to that place.  I would like the Minister of State's views and observations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/964" speakername="Ann Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#E00600"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue, as it gives me an opportunity to update the House on the matter on behalf of my colleague, the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government.  The majority of the policy decisions, first announced in the action programme for effective local government, Putting People First, and subsequently given statutory effect under the Local Government Reform Act 2014, came into effect on 1 June 2014.  Those changes include enhanced roles for local authorities in economic development and local and community development; the dissolution of local authorities in Limerick, Tipperary and Waterford and the establishment of new merged entities in their place; the replacement of town councils by municipal districts; and provision for the reconfiguration of regional structures.  There were also a series of new governance arrangements, such as provision for an enhanced policy making role for elected members; new citizen participation measures; local authority service delivery plans; the redesignation of the position of manager to chief executive; stronger oversight powers for the elected council in the implementation of policy; and increased obligations on the executive in respect of the elected council.</p> <p>The new structures and reform measures are still at an early  stage of implementation, and it is likely to take a full five-year period of operation before a definitive assessment can be made.  It is important, none the less, to ensure that the reformed system is operating effectively and as intended.  To this end, the Minister initiated an operational review of new arrangements in 2015 involving an advisory group, on which both elected members and local authority chief executives are represented together with a local  government forum for engagement with the Association of Local Government in Ireland.   The feedback to date from these groups suggests that the revised structures are generally operating quite well but will need more time to bed down fully.  The discussions at the forum indicate that there is no significant demand for any reversion to the pre-reform structures, and the Minister has indicated that this is not an option.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Ann Phelan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=2293"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2293&amp;amp;pid=AnnPhelan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, if any adjustments to the operation of the system are needed, these can be considered.</p><p>One aspect on which concern has been raised is the pressure on councillors due to increased demands, and the Senator spoke of the size of the districts which a councillor now has to represent.  This is partly a result of the increased governance, oversight and policy responsibilities of elected councils, which are positive developments in themselves.  It also reflects issues that can be addressed in the future, such as the size of local electoral areas.  There may also be issues around how council business is organised and the need to take account of the fact that local authority membership is not a full-time occupation for most councillors.  I also stress the need for the executive to provide maximum support and appropriate facilities to enable the members to perform their new roles effectively.  Already, some adjustments to the local authority budgetary process have been implemented arising mainly from the work of the advisory group.  The next stage of the review process involves surveys of elected members and the executive in relation to the operation of the new structures and related matters.  This process is well advanced and the results should be useful in helping the advisory group to report on how the system is operating and whether any adjustments might be warranted.</p><p>In conclusion, the Government&rsquo;s intention in this area is that local government will act as the main vehicle of governance and public service at local level, with the potential for improved subsidiarity, coherence and efficiency resulting in better value for money and, ultimately, improved service delivery for citizens.  The review that is now under way will provide a sound evidence base upon which to consider the operation of the new structures and arrangements generally and whether any further changes to local government and local democracy, structural or otherwise, are warranted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#F00200"><p>Would the Minister of State agree that if the advisory group is made up of representatives of local authority chief executives etc., as we have learned here, and if, as we are being advised by the Minister, there is no going back to pre-reform days, then the people most affected by the changed structures, the people who would have represented town councils which have now disappeared, are not in a position to input into this dialogue?  This is the converted speaking to themselves but the group needs to stretch beyond the comfort zone of the representatives of the current system.  My argument, which I will keep pressing as strongly as I can, is that we need to look at the fact that local government is no longer local, given the size of our municipal districts and towns.  Town councils and, in previous eras, town commissions and other such structures gave a very strong democratic imprint to their communities and people.  While we are nationally demanding subsidiarity from Brussels and talking about the power of communities and local people, we are actually stripping away that power in the name of local government reform.  I am disappointed that the Minister has indicated that a return is not an option.  Clearly he is at odds with some of his party and Cabinet colleagues who have spoken in a different vein.  I hope all possible structures of local government are being considered and not simply how to slightly improve the <i>status quo</i>.</p><p>The good news is that there is a three-year window until the next local elections and I am the first to concede that it is not the biggest issue on the doorstep but the concept of local government, local democracy and local representation at the lowest and most local level feasible is very important and we have to have a very open mind on the work of this advisory group.  I would be very disappointed if its hands were already tied behind its back by what the Minister is saying is not on the table for discussion.  I ask the Minister of State to pass my comments on to the Minister, Deputy Kelly.  I am sure he is aware of the town councils in Templemore, Thurles, Nenagh and Cashel, all of which worked very effectively and gave us low-cost democracy in this country.  I would like them not to be permanently consigned to the scrapheap.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/964" speakername="Ann Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#F00300"><p>I take the Senator's points on board and, perhaps at some point in the future, they will deserve to be debated.  However, the process with the advisory group is well advanced and, because the process has begun, it is prudent to hear what the group has to say before we begin to make more changes and to see how the changes are bedding in before we try to undo the the process.  I draw the Senator's attention to the fact that the Association of Local Government in Ireland could raise this issue and would do so in a very forceful way if it was a burning issue.  The association represents the elected members and it is well able to do that.  I have an open mind myself on this issue and if it is a burning issue then, after the general election, we can return to it, with the help of God.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.36" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.25 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.37" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re the Twelfth Report of the Seanad Committee on Procedure and Privileges, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; No. 2, motion re Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(3)) (Variation of title: Optician) Regulations 2016, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1, without debate; No. 3, motion re Planning and Development (Amendment) Regulations 2016, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 2, without debate; No. 4, motion re Companies Act 2014 (Section 1313) Regulations 2016, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 3, without debate; and No. 5, Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Bill 2015 - Report and Final Stages, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 4 and to conclude no later than 5.30 p.m. by the putting of one question from the Chair which shall, in relation to amendments, include only those set down by the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#G00300"><p>A guillotine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#G00400"><p>Political reform?  Absolutely.</p> <p>Rural Ireland has been abandoned by the Government.  Some 20 general practitioner, GP, posts have remained vacant for more than three years.  According to the Irish Medical Organisation, IMO, 20% of GP posts will be vacant within five years.  The Government has no plan to fill those posts.  The epitome of the Government's abandonment of rural Ireland can be found in its initial response to Mr. Pat Spillane's report on the matter.  I refer to the fact that it allocated the same amount of money to fulfilling the report's objectives as it gave to the care of horses in urban Ireland.  Imagine that.  I reiterate, for the benefit of Members opposite, that the initial response of the Government to saving rural Ireland was to allocate the same amount of money to fulfilling the objectives in Mr. Spillane's report as it gave to the care of horses in urban areas.  If anyone wants more proof than this, please give me a call.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mark Daly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->According to the UN Human Development Index, Ireland is currently ranked the seventh best place in the world in which to live, which ranking is equal to that of Germany and above that of Canada and the United States.  This is a matter of which everybody should be proud.  It is the achievement of generations since the establishment of the first D&aacute;il 98 years ago.  Today, we celebrate the first meeting of D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann on 21 January 1919.  D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann was established on the principles of the 1916 Proclamation.  In essence, we are all guardians of the values of the 1916 Proclamation.  Its aims and objectives are timeless and universal.  It should be remembered that what we will be celebrating this year is that which others sought to achieve in 1916.  It is not about those against whom we struggled to achieve our full potential as a nation.  P&aacute;draig Pearse and his fellow signatories to the Proclamation sought to set out ideals and principles to guide us when faced with problems that they could not even imagine.  As we celebrate all those involved, we should remember the words of John F. Kennedy when he said: "A nation reveals itself not only by the men it produces but the men it honors, the men it remembers."  I hope that our celebrations this year of 1916 will honour the men and women of our greatest generation.  We must never stop trying to achieve the standards they set us regardless of how difficult the challenges.</p><p>My colleagues on this side of the House and I propose to bring the National Anthem Protection Bill 2016 before the House next week.  The Minister for Finance, Deputy Noonan, has said that he proposes to bring forth legislation to protect the national anthem, in respect of which copyright ran out in 2012.  I note opposite an Olympian who stood for the national anthem following his great achievement on the international stage, which brought great pride to this country.  The national anthem for which he stood needs to be protected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H00300"><p>I hope that he will discuss the Bill, which is only one page long, with the Government Whips over the next few days.  A great deal of legislation is being passed by this House without debate.  We now have an opportunity in the dying days of this Government to protect the national anthem, which I believe would be befitting of the memory of the men and women of 1916.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H00400"><p>I call Senator Conway and congratulate him on his new role.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H00500"><p>Five years into my time as a Member of this House, I am being asked to fill in.  I am always happy to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H00600"><p>He will be back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H00700"><p>The Bill referred to by Senator Daly is an interesting one.  I did not realise that the copyright had run out on our national anthem.  I was not even aware copyright was applicable to national anthems.  The Bill is worthy of discussion by the Whips and I propose to suggest same to Senator Paul Coghlan.</p> <p>I would also welcome a debate in this House on tourism, preferably before the end of term of this Seanad.  We are all aware of the significant achievements over the past five years of this Administration and the people of Ireland in terms of tourism, including the development of the Irish inter-county marketing strategy and allied to that, The Gathering, which was remarkably successful and probably set the tone in terms of how we should market Ireland into the future.  I ask the Deputy Leader to request the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Donohoe, to come to this House for a debate on tourism and in that context the development of a further Gathering, perhaps, in 2018.  The Gathering was followed up with the Wild Atlantic Way, which has also been hugely successful.  When one hears the people of Donegal speak of the benefit of the Wild Atlantic Way in a similar vein to that of people of west Cork and all counties in between Donegal and Cork there is no doubt but that it has driven tourism, enterprise and job creation in this country.  This issue is worthy of debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H00800"><p>The Senator's time has expired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H00900"><p>I thought when I took up this position that my allocated speaking time would be longer.</p> <p>There has been much discussion on the UK's plan for its future in Europe, a referendum on which will be held next year or the year after.  We have an important role to play in that discussion with our nearest and dearest neighbour.  A debate in this House with the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Flanagan, or Minister of State, Deputy Murphy -  I would prefer if the Minister, Deputy Flanagan, or even the Taoiseach, came to the House for the debate - on the pivotal role we can play in terms of encouraging our fellow neighbours in the UK to remain within the European project would be worthy and useful before the end of term of this Seanad.  I understand that the Taoiseach is meeting the Prime Minister, David Cameron in 10 Downing Street in the not too distant future to discuss this matter.  We need to assist at European level the UK in terms of its requirements-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H01000"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate on the matter?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H01100"><p>-----for a new direction for Europe.  We need to engage at senior level in that debate.  This House equally has a role to play in that discourse and deliberation and in that regard I suggest that a debate in this House would be timely and prudent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H01200"><p>Before I call on Senator Norris, I am sure Members of the House will join with me in welcoming Councillor Marcia D'Alton from Cork County Council to the Public Gallery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#H01300"><p>I join in the Cathaoirleach's welcome to the distinguished councillor.  Earlier this morning some of my colleagues and I had a meeting with representatives of the Cork Institute of Technology, which is concerned about the Government's proposals for legislation in this area.</p><p>I am concerned that today there are three items to be taken without debate, two of which are regulations.  I suppose the case can be argued that two of those items should be taken without debate.  On, No. 1, which is a report from the Committee on Procedure and Privileges on the amendment of Standing Orders for this House, surely amendment of Standing Orders of this House is a matter that should be discussed by all Members of this House and not only by the Committee on Procedure and Privileges, of which I have the honour to be a member.  I believe this is a matter in which every Member of this House should have a say.  I am seeking an amendment of the Order of Business to the effect that No. 1 be taken with discussion, which discussion should commence with a statement from the Government side on what is involved in terms of the proposed changes to procedures and privileges.  Also, while we will probably get through the Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Bill 2015 by 5.30 p.m. I find the proposed guillotine on that Bill, outlined on the Order of Business, distasteful and I object to it.  </p><p>Whatever the views of the Deputy Leader in terms of the first two issues I have raised, I am sure she will agree with my position in regard to the axing of the &quot;Gloria&quot; programme, which airs on Sundays.  I take the liberty of saying that I believe she will agree with me on this because I have been contacted by a Professor David McConnell, fellow emeritus Trinity College, who is greatly concerned about the axing of this programme and mentioned to me that Senator Bacik might also have an interest in it.  I regularly listen to &quot;Gloria&quot;.It is a wonderful programme presented by Tim Thurston, a gentleman with a lovely broadcasting voice and an extensive knowledge of remote areas of religious music.  Professor McConnell, who I think is publicly acknowledged as quite the campaigning atheist, pointed out in his letter to me that &quot;Gloria&quot; is a celebration of the sacred music of Europe, the origin of all classical music in our tradition, which is interesting.  He also states in his letter that it is one of the finest programmes he has ever had to pleasure to listen to.  I agree with him.  The presenter, Tim Thurston, plays music by people such as Hildegard von Bingen, which many listeners might previously have not heard.  He has introduced me to a range of music from the medieval to baroque and classical music.  Some 4,000 people have signed a petition to have Lyric reverse its decision to axe the programme.  Attached to Professor McConnell's letter to me was a letter was from a Mr. Keogan to <i>The Irish Times, </i>from which I would like to quote one paragraph:  It states:</p><blockquote><i>Gloria</i>is, however, about much more than just choral music; it is about excellence in broadcasting; about challenging the listener to expand his or her interest to far beyond the popular classics; in short, it is what public service broadcasting should be.  Is this the issue?</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> If it is a question of popularity, I think there is a wide audience for "Gloria".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J00200"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate on it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J00300"><p>Yes I am, if that is the only way I can get it onto the record of the House.  However, I am not expecting a debate on it.  In terms of popularity, a large number of people listen to this programme on Sunday mornings, unlike the programme about modern music, which is an hour or two of unmerciful, thumps, bangs, whistles, squelches, belches and God Almighty knows what.  I switch it off every time it comes to this thing about modern music.  Let us have some respect for the graceful traditions of Christian Europe.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J00400"><p>I welcome the announcement by the Insolvency Service of Ireland of the increase of 70% in 2015 in the number of people achieving permanent solutions to their insolvency problems.  This has been welcomed by New Beginnings and Fianna F&aacute;il.  A number of people have credited the improvement in those achieving permanent solutions as per the Insolvency Service of Ireland to the removal of the bank veto and the change in the term of bankruptcy to a one-year term.  It seems to be quite obvious that it softened the cough, to some extent, of financial institutions.  They seem to be prepared to accept solutions now that they rejected in the past.</p> <p>I take on board the criticisms of the Irish Mortgage Holders Organisation.  The organisation has said that the numbers actually achieving settlement through the Insolvency Service of Ireland is far too low.  In the region of 1,700 people have had their issues resolved.  When we compare that figure with the numbers of people in severe debt, it represents something in the region of 1.2%, which is far too low.  Part of the reason is that it has been said that people do not understand the Insolvency Service of Ireland and what it has to offer nor do they understand personal insolvency arrangements or the issues around bankruptcy.  Therefore, they are not coming forward to use the service.</p> <p>I am calling on the Insolvency Service of Ireland to take this on board.  I call on representatives of the service to explain to people in their communities, where they will have an opportunity to engage with them, what the issues are and how the service can be of assistance.  I acknowledge that they have begun to do that.  I know that towards the end of last year they announced publicly that they would go to the courts and approach borrowers personally who had cases coming before the Circuit Court.  That is a positive development but one that represents the tip of the iceberg.  No community or community organisation of any description in the country should be overlooked.  Where people are in trouble, they should be reached out to by the Insolvency Service of Ireland and resources should be made available to ensure that happens.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J00500"><p>I echo the comments that have been made by my friend and colleague, Senator Daly, about the Government's neglect of rural Ireland.  The people who live in rural Ireland - I happen to live in County Leitrim but this is mirrored throughout the country - can see at first hand the impact Government policies have had, including the closure of Garda stations and the threat to post offices.  I hope the Bobby Kerr report will awaken someone in government to take positive initiatives to ensure the rural post office network is maintained.</p> <p>Another aspect of my contribution in respect of the neglect of rural Ireland comes with the damning report from the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport on the lack of funding for the maintenance of our road network.  On many occasions in this House in recent years I have railed against what I saw as underinvestment.  It has been brought home to me repeatedly as a member of the Joint Committee on Transport and Communications.  Committee members have heard first-hand from the various stakeholders involved in maintaining our road network that there has been underfunding for years.  Let us put that against the Government spin to the effect that the economy is rapidly recovering and there is now money available.  We need only look at the auction politics being engaged in by the Labour Party and Fine Gael.  The latest from those in the Labour Party is that they are going to reduce college fees by &euro;500.  Who is going to believe them?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J00600"><p>Are they going to sign a pledge on that one?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J00700"><p>Exactly.  Who is going to believe those in the Labour Party who say they are going to reduce university fees by &euro;500?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J00800"><p>It is "Alice in Wonderland".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J00900"><p>It is "Ripley's Believe It or Not!"</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J01000"><p>The idea of trying to buy the public when, at the same time, our road network is crumbling at our feet is baffling.  Representatives from the National Transport Authority told members at a meeting of the Committee on Transport and Communications in the past 12 months that the authority needs &euro;300 million per year simply to maintain the network.  Despite this, the figures that have come out in the report from the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport suggest there has been a rapid decline in investment in our road network at national primary level and at national secondary load level, which is perhaps more insidious.  This means there are roads in my county and other counties in rural Ireland that are beginning to crumble, especially given the rainfall of the past two months.</p> <p>Many of us are old enough to remember the men who used to be out on the roads with a shovel.  People used to wonder what they were doing.  What they were doing, until the service was withdrawn as a result of lack of Government investment, was clearing drains and gullies on roadways to ensure the surfaces were maintained.</p> <p>I wish we had enough time to bring in the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to answer these questions.  These are important questions that are impacting, as we speak, on people living in small communities.  I do not believe the Government has either the heart or soul to commit to making their lives better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" speakername="Michael Mullins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J01100"><p>I support Senator Conway's call for a debate before we end this term with the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport on all the positive things that have happened in tourism in recent years.  When the Government took over in 2011, it rightly identified the significant contribution tourism could make to the economic recovery.  The Government set about investing and marketing Ireland as a tourist destination.  We have seen record numbers of tourists in recent years.  The outlook for 2016 looks particularly promising.</p> <p>One significant measure taken was the introduction of the 9% VAT rate for tourism related activity and the hospitality sector.  That made a major contribution to making Ireland attractive.  However, we need to reiterate the warning to those in the hotel sector in particular that they need to continue to keep their end of the bargain.  The Minister for Finance made some noises recently putting them on notice that the 9% VAT rate may not remain indefinitely.  There is evidence, especially in the capital and in some of the larger centres of population, that the hotel sector is hiking prices, in particular when significant events are taking place in cities and major towns.  If those in the hospitality sector wish to retain the 9% rate, they need to look at themselves and keep their prices in check.</p> <p>Senator Mooney referred to the publication yesterday of the final report on the post office network.  We all want to see a strengthened post office network in our communities, a network that can provide the type of service that people require.  I very much welcome that a post office renewal process, as recommended in the report, will be established immediately and will conclude its work within six months.  In particular, I welcome the Minister announcing that the Government has agreed to support the introduction of an electronic payment account in 2016.  If the post office network is to survive, it must be able to provide a range of electronic transactions.  I certainly hope the work being done in the coming six months will ensure and secure what remains of the post office network throughout rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#J01200"><p>I second Senator Norris's motion.  Truthfully, every time I read "without debate", I shiver.  What are we doing here if we are going to have things without debate?  I can understand the need for it sometimes when certain regulations are coming through.  However, in this case it is a motion on the report of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges on the amendment of Standing Orders 90 and 105 and the adoption of new Standing Orders 108A to 108E, inclusive, and a Schedule to Standing Orders.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Feargal Quinn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=1972"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1972&amp;amp;pid=FergalQuinn&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That seems to relate to this House and is the sort of issue that we should be debating.  I urge the Deputy Leader to accept Senator Norris's proposal that we debate it today.</p><p>One of our concerns down the years has been the length of time that it takes for regulations to be implemented on legislation that we pass.  The Seanad passed the Construction Contracts Act 2013 just ten hours before the new Government took office five years ago.  Although I will not say that nothing has happened, the Act has not been commenced since then.  Yesterday, I learned that it would be commenced within the coming months.  At least we are getting somewhere with it, but I cannot get over how long it takes to get things done.</p><p>I wish to address Senator Daly's concerns about rural Ireland and Senator Mullins's reference to post offices.  There are measures that we can take to ensure that rural Ireland survives.  Not all of them will cost money, but some will.  If rural Ireland is to survive and thrive in the years ahead, we must do something.  We have the answer.</p><p>I wish to raise an issue that I mentioned previously.  It concerns legislation that is being introduced across Europe to tackle ISIS killers who are returning to Europe after slaughtering people in Syria.  They were welcomed into a number of countries, but most European nations have now introduced legislation to ensure that judges can debar such persons and remove their citizenships.  We do not have that ability, but we should.  Austria and Italy have strong legislation.  If we are not careful, we will almost end up welcoming people who are returning to, or coming to, Europe having killed for ISIS.  We can do something about this.  We should at least give judges the right to remove people's passports, which we have been generous with in the past.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1208" speakername="M&aacute;ir&iacute;a Cahill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#K00200"><p>I welcome yesterday's publication of the Second National Strategy on Domestic, Sexual and Gender-based Violence 2016-21.  I commend the Minster for Justice and Equality, Deputy Fitzgerald, on her efforts in this regard and, in particular, on giving political priority to an issue that will always to be the fore of society.  Abuse permeates every section of society.  Importantly, the strategy is victim centred and highlights the devastating impact that such violence can have on victims.  A wide range of supports, such as counselling, information services and emotional supports, will be available to victims.  The strategy also recognises that victims can sometimes be placed through secondary victimisation by the criminal justice system.</p> <p>With this in mind, some Senators may know that Sir Keir Starmer, a world-renowned human rights lawyer, identified a number of failings in my cases and made a number of recommendations that could help future sexual abuse victims coming through the criminal justice system in the North.  In this regard, I am pleased to say that I will meet the North's Director of Public Prosecutions, Mr. Barra McGrory, on Monday when he will update me on those recommendations that he has implemented and those that he will implement in future.</p> <p>To put it on Senators' radar, the Rape Crisis Network Ireland, One in Four, Women's Aid and I will host an event next Wednesday at 1 p.m. in Buswell's Hotel to update those politicians who are going forward for election to this and the Lower House.  They are strongly calling for funds to be made available for a SAVI II report, as SAVI I has been such a long time in the offing that we do not have an up-to-date picture of sexual violence.  I ask all Senators who can make themselves available to listen to that presentation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#K00300"><p>Fad is at&aacute;imid in&aacute;r su&iacute; anseo ar maidin, t&aacute; naon&uacute;r teaghlaigh de chuid an Lucht Si&uacute;il ag dul isteach chuig Comhairle Cathrach na Gaillimhe ag r&aacute; go bhfuil siad gan d&iacute;dean.</p> <p>As we sit here, nine Traveller families from Galway who have been living at a dump for the past six months and face eviction tomorrow must declare themselves homeless to Galway City Council because of a failure by local authorities in the west to deal with the crisis in Traveller accommodation.  They were in an inappropriate place, which we highlighted previously, with the site's owner left no option but to have them evicted.  Responsibility for Traveller accommodation lies with local authorities and the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government.  Will the Deputy Leader implore her colleague, the Department's Minister, to enter into negotiations immediately with the Galway city manager to find a temporary resolution for these families?  They will be declared homeless and end up on the State's books anyway unless something is done.  They have found themselves in a diabolical situation.</p> <p>I wish to highlight an issue that has arisen in my travels around rural Galway.  The home care system has been privatised and the number of home helpers employed by the HSE has dwindled.  The race to the bottom in the sector is a major issue.  The rates paid to people to work in the companies running the services are too low and finding workers is proving difficult.  That people must travel between houses for appointments without being paid travel expenses or for the time they spend travelling means that the work is not worth their while.  The fallout has seen older people left in hospitals when they would be able to return home were home care available.  People who work in the west's health services tell me that this situation is chronic.  It shows the failure of the system's privatisation.  There is a myriad of crises in the health sector, but this one needs to be addressed.  I call for a debate with the Minister for Health on it.  If that is not possible, the concerns that we are raising could at least be raised with him in order to see what might be done in the short term.  Some patients in Galway's hospital system cannot return home because home care is not available following the failed privatisation initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#K00400"><p>I wish to raise the issue of drugs and criminality.  Senators heard about the terrible incident in Cork this week involving six people who were left in hospital by the drug 2C-B.  They were so psychotic that they were naked, the walls were covered in blood and they did not even realise that one of them was having a heart attack on the floor.</p> <p>This morning's "Today with Sean O'Rourke" on RTE ran a sad segment about children in Limerick city who were on Valium, Xanax, benzo, spice and TC, which are synthetic drugs.  Cannabis and cocaine cost &euro;50 per bag, but a child with lunch money can afford these tablets.  A drug dealer in Limerick might be a boy in a nice track suit with a packet of new fags in his pocket because he can afford to buy these drugs and sell them for &euro;10 at &euro;2 per tablet.  One will be out of it for the day and end up being sick psychotically.</p> <p>An articulate 20 year old who is now out of that scene was interviewed.  He stated that there was no hope for young people, including his friends.  They take these drugs to stay out of it and remain numb because they do not believe that there is any hope.  This is our country.</p> <p>In the UK, the Psychoactive Substances Bill will go through Parliament.  It seeks to alter the situation by applying a blanket ban on anything that might be conceived as a mood-altering substance.  Possession for personal use will not be an offence, but those found guilty of making or supplying the substances could face up to seven years in prison.  The net of the new law is cast deliberately wide and applies to any substance intended for human consumption that is capable of producing a psychoactive effect.  This excludes nicotine, food, caffeine, alcohol and medical products.</p> <p>Two new substances appear on the European market every week.  Beautiful, clean laboratories in China are making these drugs everyday.  Much of this drug making is funding terrorism.  The Minister for Justice and Equality must attend the House to debate this issue and the next Government's term.  Something must be done for our youth because "Love/Hate" is here in reality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#K00500"><p>I support Senators Norris and Quinn.  It is appalling that we would allow changes to the privileges and practices of this House without a debate.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have spoken many times on the issue of speaking time for people, such as myself, who are not members of groups or the way the House divides on party political grounds rather than on vocational panels which is what we are elected to.  It would be healthy to discuss these issues in the open.  </p><p>I rise this morning to speak on teachers, lecturers, institutes of technology and technological universities.  We are about to have a teachers' strike and nobody is saying a word about it because we are heading towards an election and nobody wants to speak about things that are nasty.  We need to have engagement with teachers.  The system is crumbling.  We need engagement and discussions with them.  In the rush for technological universities I ask the Leader to confirm that the Technological Universities Bill 2015 will not come before the House before the general election.  We cannot rush a Bill of that magnitude through this House in a matter of a couple of days purely to satisfy the electoral ambitions of somebody or other on the other side of the House.  It is simply outrageous.  At the Joint Committee on Education and Social Protection yesterday some very distinguished academics appeared before it who all agreed that the move towards technological universities was ill-advised in the way in which it is going forward.  One point made by Dr. Greg Foley from DCU was that we will finish up with 16 universities in this country and no alternative pathway.  The focus is on level 8 qualifications and we are pushing people through universities, towards a level 8 qualification, who are not sufficiently able to reach that level.  The focus on level 6 and level 7 qualifications has gone.  We no longer have that focus.  I accept the Government has done much to assist apprenticeships but we need to broaden the vocational base of education in Ireland and I think the Technological Universities Bill 2015 needs to be set aside until the next Government is in place.  We have in the Visitors Gallery a number of people from Cork Institute of Technology who would like to meet Members of both Houses to outline some of their concerns.  I ask Members that if they meet them during the course of the day to give them a few moments of their time. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L00200"><p>I thought I had better stand up and rebut some of the comments made here.  First, Senator Paschal Mooney referred to rural Ireland being forgotten about by the Government.  The fact is Fianna F&aacute;il closed more Garda stations and more post offices than the current Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L00300"><p>Would the Senator agree that the Government accelerated it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L00400"><p>In the past four-and-a-half to five years employment has gone way up and unemployment has come down to below 9%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L00500"><p>What about emigration?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L00600"><p>Senator Coghlan to continue, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L00700"><p>Recent statistics show that rural Ireland stands up as much as urban Ireland with job creation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L00800"><p>Not in its job creation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L00900"><p>The 2012 Action Plan for Jobs created 60% more jobs in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01000"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01100"><p>I just want to point out the facts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01200"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01300"><p>It is all about keeping the recovery going.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01400"><p>I hope the Senator sends out that story to rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01500"><p>Senator Daly's comments-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01600"><p>Senator Coghlan to continue, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01700"><p>That is going down well in rural Ireland.  The Senator is losing votes by the second.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01800"><p>Senator Coghlan to continue, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L01900"><p>Coming from a Dublin-based Senator, that is going down a storm in rural Ireland.  The Senator should keep saying it and he will-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02000"><p>Does Senator Coghlan have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02100"><p>The Senator should keep it going.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02200"><p>Has the Senator a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02300"><p>I would like to refer to the Soldier's Song like Senator Daly-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02400"><p>On a point of information, is there an election in the offing by any chance?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02500"><p>Does the Senator have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02600"><p>I did not get to speak yet.  I only wanted to pass a comment on Senator Paschal Mooney's comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02700"><p>The Senator is almost out of time.  Does he have a question for the Leader?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02800"><p>Yes, I have.  In reference to Senator Mark Daly's comments on Amhr&aacute;n na bhFiann, the Soldier's Song - this will be a little longwinded because the Cathaoirleach would not let me in due to all the interruptions - I was surprised to hear that the copyright was not protected.  He referred to me standing and listening to Amhr&aacute;n na bhFiann at a time in one's life when hearing it is the most exhilarating, thrilling, pride-filled feeling.  It is a signification of some kind of coronation or achievement when one hears the national anthem so I am surprised copyright has not been protected.  When I thought about it, I was saying to myself that people will not know who wrote this song.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L02900"><p>The Senator is way over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03000"><p>Peadar Kearney wrote it in 1907 and in 1923 Liam &Oacute; Riain gave the Irish rendition but it is correct that we need to copyright the national anthem.  I support this in every way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03100"><p>I call Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03200"><p>The Government bought it in 1933 for &pound;1,000 and, unfortunately, that copyright has gone, 40 years after Peadar had passed away.  I call for a debate on how we can protect Amhr&aacute;n na bhFiann, the national anthem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03300"><p>I refer briefly to my colleague, Senator Eamonn Coghlan, who is living in the suburban reality of Dublin.  It is not the same in Donegal or in the west.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03400"><p>The Senator came to Dublin and look at all the jobs that are-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03500"><p>The jobs are not being created.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03600"><p>Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill to continue, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03700"><p>The reality is that 30% of the 18 to 30 year age group in my county have emigrated since 2011.  The opportunities they are obtaining are not in this jurisdiction, they are overseas.  We cannot say that is a good statistic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" speakername="Eamonn Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03800"><p>That was then; this is now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L03900"><p>That is only one county.  Those figures come from the CSO.  It is not a good statistic.  I am not making a political point but I am expressing the reality.  Rural Ireland is struggling.  The economic recovery that we see is predominantly in the capital and in the interurban areas.  The focus of the IDA and Enterprise Ireland has been job creation in urban areas, not in rural areas.  Yes, there have been opportunities and jobs have been created in rural areas but they have been created because people have been willing to take a risk themselves, not through the intervention of any Government policy.</p> <p>The issue of the insolvency legislation was raised by Senator Aideen Hayden who said it is not working.  The reason it is not working is that the banks have a veto over the insolvency legislation because the banks through rent seeking behaviour were allowed to write the insolvency legislation which was supported by Government in these Houses.  It is not protecting the ordinary consumer who is in debt, negative equity or personal debt.  </p> <p>The other issue that is emerging and was debated in the other House last night is that of State board appointments.  It is not unique to Labour Party leaders that they are being appointed or reappointed to State boards.  State boards are being stuffed in the last days of this Government with people who are aligned to Government parties.  That is wrong.  Yes, it happened under Fianna F&aacute;il.  It was wrong then and it is wrong now because State boards should be filled with people who have some level of expertise in corporate governance.  I refer in particular to one State board, the Irish Greyhound Board, which is in receipt of almost &euro;15 million from the State, or &euro;285,000 per year.  Its corporate governance failings have been highlighted in an Indecon report published by the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  One of the recommendations in that report was that those who serve on the board should not do so for any more than two terms.  The Minister of State at the Department, Deputy Tom Hayes, has reappointed a crony for a third term on that board who does not have the expertise set out in the Indecon report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L04000"><p>Is the Senator seeking a debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L04100"><p>That is wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#L04200"><p>I support the call by my colleagues for a debate on tourism.  I acknowledge the achievements of tourism and the number of jobs created.  In doing so I acknowledge the voluntary contribution of a total of 850 local communities, north, south, east and west, and the part they have played which at times is not recognised.  In making their own towns and villages better places in which to live and better places for visitors to visit and stay, they have created hundreds of jobs throughout the country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Brennan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2360"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2360&amp;amp;pid=TerryBrennan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I can instance my home town of Carlingford-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#M00200"><p>That is a village.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#M00300"><p>-----where in excess of 400 jobs have been created by voluntary organisations that have worked for the betterment of their community.  There would be great celebrations in any town or village on hearing an announcement of 400 jobs.  One of the Senators instanced his county of Clare and the Loop Head peninsula.  What that community has done has been recognised worldwide and the area has been listed as one of the top 100 green areas in this country.  The scheme was initiated by Gabriel Keating who is one of our county council colleagues in Clare.  He used his own initiative but he was helped by local communities in the region.  I cannot emphasise enough the valuable work done by voluntary organisations.  Some of them have worked for the entire winter to make their towns and villages beautiful, primarily for their own benefit but also to attract visitors.  I seek a debate on the voluntary sector where I again will acknowledge the contribution made by volunteers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" speakername="Paul Bradford" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#M00400"><p>I agree with Senator Craughwell on the question of debating the Technological Universities Bill.  It would be remiss in the long-term interests of the country's educational prospects if we were to rush to put in place structures about which there is great uncertainty.  I understand how the concept of technological universities can seem attractive, particularly from a political perspective.  In the interests of the long-term educational needs of our society, serious reflection must be given to the legislation.  There is a lot of academic research to indicate that it may well be an incorrect destination that we are attempting to take and, therefore, we should proceed slowly and carefully.  Over the past 40 or 50 years, great advances have been made in the Irish education system.  Now, with a worldwide comparison, worrying trends have emerged.  We must ensure every institute, college or university is worthy of its name and the highest academic standards must apply.  Undoubtedly, there is a place in society and the education system for every student but we must match each student's needs with the best courses on offer.  Just claiming that one can, willy-nilly, have colleges here, there and everywhere does not do anybody any favours, so we must proceed in a cautious fashion.</p> <p>I concur with the welcome extended to the Kerr report on the future of the rural post office network.  I hope its recommendations will be acted upon.  There is the broader issue of rural development.  The regeneration of the rural economy and rural Ireland is necessary.  There is an almost daily tour of Ministers at present and this has been the case in recent months.  I would call it an Action Plan for Jobs tour.  There is no doubt that worthy announcements have been made but they could have emanated from the Department.  I would like an action tour that focused on rural development where three or four Ministers visited the provinces, counties and regions and we could talk about putting in place a plan for regenerating rural Ireland.  We must accept that we cannot simply go back to some of the structures that existed previously.  If we want a balanced country then we must ensure towns and villages are supported.  A big national plan in this regard is necessary and I hope the next Government will take the issue on board.  There can be a future for rural Ireland and rural communities but only if it is planned, supported and funded using a proper structure.  I hope the matter will be taken very seriously by the next Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#M00500"><p>I join my party's acting leader, Senator Mark Daly, in acknowledging that today is the 97th anniversary of the first D&aacute;il, a body which embraced the Proclamation and the vision of our patriots of 1916.  I refer to one of his comments.  He said that Ireland is ranked the seventh best place to live according to the UN Human Development Index.  As he said, such ranking is welcome.  Ireland is one of the best places to live provided people are not unfortunate newly married couples who want to access shelter or they do not want to provide shelter either for themselves, their partners or their families.  Ireland is okay as long as a person is not looking for a house.  As I have said in the House before, if a person is on a low income, local authorities will not accept him or her as a qualifying applicant on the housing list even though that person has no hope of providing or securing a house for him or herself other than renting.  If a person is a mortgage holder who has had difficulty meeting repayments, the Government will throw him or her to the wolves of the financial sector and the Four Courts.  If a person is endeavouring to get together enough money to buy a house, he or she will be unable to secure a mortgage from most of the financial institutions.  Obviously if a person is sick or elderly, he or she will be unable to access the health services.  Ireland is grand if a person does not belong to any of the categories I have outlined.  Surely the vision of the Proclamation, the people of 1916 and the members of the first D&aacute;il, of whom we are their successors, is one we should be embracing, especially as we approach the centenary of the first D&aacute;il and commemorate the 1916 Easter Rising.</p> <p>I ask the Deputy Leader, and I have asked for it before, for a good, open-ended debate on housing.  I know the time is short and we may only have a week or two left but there is nothing stopping us from fitting in statements on housing.  A far greater commitment needs to be given than we have seen given by the Government over the past five years.  I do not view housing as a political issue but it is important to the people that together we articulate the needs they have in this regard.  Unfortunately, the housing problem has led to other issues regarding relationship difficulties simply because people cannot get proper accommodation.  I am not just talking about the RTE television programme that was broadcast the other night.  We did not need such a programme because anybody who works in their constituencies to deal with the average person who comes to them for representation knows exactly how bad the situation is and the extent to which it has been allowed to deteriorate.  I appeal to the Deputy Leader for a debate on housing.  I also appeal for good representation in the House to ensure some spark is set under the Government in its dying days and in order that the incoming Government will at least start with greater energy and determination to solve the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#M00600"><p>I was somewhat inspired when I heard the interplay between the Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael Senators on various issues, including the national anthem.  I kept thinking that perhaps we should entitle today's proceedings "Civil War: The Musical".</p> <p>On a very serious note, it is probably a well-known fact at this stage that I am unlikely to run for this House again.  In reflecting on the five years I have been a Member, the single, greatest and most colossal disappointment I have had, which in a five-year timeframe is a microcosm of the disappointment I have felt over the 22 years since I came back to Ireland, has been our complete failure to address the structural problems in the health service.  When one hears something like we have heard over the past 24 hours, that in the second largest city in the country, in what is either the largest or second largest acute hospital in the country, all elective surgery has been cancelled - I know I am speaking to an audience who, from the medical and health profession point of view, are largely a lay audience - this is an abnormal as abnormal gets.  This is unprecedented.  This is mad.  This is nuts.  This is crazy.  This is the greatest illustration one could possibly have of a system that has failed.  It is not a third world health system.  I will not use emotional language.  I have seen third world hospitals.  We do not have a third world health system.  We have a first world health system but one that is strictly third class and mediocre.  There has been a complete, absolute and utter failure of all attempts to reform it.</p> <p>I endorsed the Government, although I am sure my ringing endorsement had nothing to do with it being elected, and I endorsed the potential coalition partners over three consecutive elections because in each of them they stated they would reform the health service when my colleagues in Fianna F&aacute;il had a different plan and wanted to redevelop the existing structure, with which I respectfully disagreed because I thought plan B was much better - to break up the health service and start from scratch.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator John Crown:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2369"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2369&amp;amp;pid=JohnCrown&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There was colossal disappointment on hearing, about two thirds of the way through the current Oireachtas, that basically they had given up on that plan.</p><p>I apologise if I sound like a broken record, but people need to think about the sheer abnormality of having all the elective surgery in a major hospital cancelled.  It is crazy.  One can talk about the slippery roads in Cork last Friday and people falling on the Mardyke and all of that, but the system should be able to absorb that activity.  Other systems absorb occurrences of multi-vehicle car crashes and terrible epidemics.  The situation is simply wrong and it is not just in Cork.  It is very close to happening in other hospitals in the State.  I have walked through the accident and emergency department of St. Vincent's Hospital on a number of occasions over recent months and I sometimes wonder how it would pass a fire inspection never mind a health inspection.  One sees people having to move one trolley to go between them to get to the next patient.  I would ask that when all the Members are back in the House in the next term they would think about this situation.</p><p>Over the past five years a number of Bills have been advanced in this House and they have been allowed to remain on the Order Paper.  These are not Government sponsored Bills so they will die.  I feel strongly about this.  When people propose these Bills without pushing them, it becomes an optical exercise.  I ask the Deputy Leader to designate several hours some day next week - which may be our last sitting week - in order that we may at least go through the formality and, if the Government does not accept these Bills, reject them.  I ask the Deputy Leader to allow No. 55, the Longer Healthy Living Bill, which everyone I have spoken to thinks is a really progressive idea which could go some way towards fixing many problems in the health service and the wider public service, to proceed some time next week in order that it would get the opportunity to be accepted or rejected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#N00600"><p>The Senator is out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#N00700"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business that the Minister for Health would come to the House to discuss the emergency in Cork.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" speakername="Thomas Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#N01600"><p>I second that amendment.  Ireland is facing a major choice in the next few weeks and is currently facing a severe crisis.  We have a Government in place which seems more than happy to blame the previous Government for any problems that arise and which is more than happy to take credit for any good that comes.  However, what shocked people most this week was the callous response of Minister for Public Expenditure, Deputy Brendan Howlin when asked about Monday's television programme "My Homeless Family".  The Minister suggested this was a priority for the next Government.  The current Government does not care.  It is doing its very best to ride a wave of glory to seek a coronation and get into power the next time, but in reality it has achieved very little.  The Government has implemented a plan which was devised by the late Minister for Finance, Brian Lenihan.  At the time, the plan was bitterly opposed by the parties which form the current Government and they voted against it time and again, but they have performed a U-turn.</p> <p>It is heartbreaking for the majority of the nation to see the way the homeless crisis has developed and to see the lack of shame from the Government benches in the Seanad and the D&aacute;il on this matter.  Of course, people want low taxes and of course they want the recovery to continue but they want basic decency in our country.  They do not want people and families in hotels nor they do not want them in tents.  That is what has arisen in society.  People do not want crime running rampant.  The Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald said this morning that crime is a feature of modern life.  Crime and homelessness are not, however, an acceptable feature of modern life.</p> <p>Shame on the Minister, Deputy Howlin, and the Government for putting the problems of today into tomorrow while blaming the past for any of the issues that arise.  They are not fit for Government and they deserve to lose office.  I am confident that in the next few weeks the public will put the Government out of office and a new broom will be brought in.  There will be great responsibilities on the new Government to solve this homeless crisis.  If the current Government is not prepared to do it and is prepared to sit back and ignore what is going on, it should be aware that the people are not prepared to sit back and the next Government certainly will not sit back.  I wish it to be on the record of the House that Fianna F&aacute;il is leading the charge to be the alternative Government.  We are in business, we are back in the game, we want to be in Government and we have a programme to deliver, at the heart of which is decency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#N01800"><p>I will respond first to Senator Daly and the other Senators who raised the issue of rural Ireland, the rural GP practice scheme in particular.  The Government is committed to ensuring patients throughout the State continue to have access to GP services, especially in remote rural areas and also in certain urban areas.  The rural GP practice is top of the agenda as part of the discussions on the new GP contract under way with the Irish Medical Organisation, IMO.  In fact, Ireland has a very low rate of GP vacancies nationwide.  As of 1 January 2016, there were 15 GMS lists without a permanent GP in place out of a national total of more than 2,400, which is only 0.06%.  Of the 15 GP vacancies, only five are in rural areas.  Half the 15 vacancies are recent and have occurred in the past 12 months.  However, each of these lists has either a locum GP or a neighbouring GP who has taken over the list and who is providing the full range of GP services to patients.  Patients continue to have access to GP and primary care services.  I hope this allays concerns on that very specific issue the Senators raised.</p> <p>On the broader issue of jobs and unemployment in rural areas, the Government has consistently said that job creation has been a top priority since the Government took office in 2011 when the rate of unemployment was over 15%.  We have seen a dramatic drop in unemployment, which must be welcomed whichever side of the House we are on.  The launch this week of Action Plan for Jobs 2016 noted that the first plan was launched with a target of 100,000 extra jobs by 2016.  Many people, including some Members across the floor of the House, criticised the plan at the time as being unrealistic.  However, according to the independent Central Statistics Office figures, the target was hit 21 months early in 2015.  There are now more than 135,000 additional people at work today compared with when the first Action Plan for Jobs was launched.  That is a significant and remarkable achievement.  The 2016 plan has set a target of 50,000 extra jobs this year and outlines 304 actions.  These are particularly focused on regional jobs outside the Dublin area.  Following on from the successful roll-out of the regional jobs plans, further actions to support regional jobs growth will be supported by &euro;530 million in funding.  There is also a national cluster initiative focused on strengthening rural initiatives to ensure job creation.  We can see an impressive roll-out of rural jobs within the agrifood industry and the food and drink industry.</p> <p>Senator Daly acknowledged the UN Human Development Index which has produced a very welcome statistic that Ireland is the 7th best place in the world in which to live, which is great news for us all.  Senator Daly also spoke, with his customary eloquence, about 1916 and the commemorations this year, to which we all look forward, in particular the 97th - rather than the 98th - anniversary of the first D&aacute;il sitting in January 1919.  Colleagues will recall that in 2009 a significant commemoration was held in the Mansion House and I hope we will have a similarly significant commemoration in 2019 for the centenary of the first D&aacute;il sitting.</p> <p>The proposed national anthem protection Bill 2016 was referred to.  I have not seen the Bill but, as Senator Conway has said, it appears to be eminently worthy of discussion among the Whips and deserves support.  I disagree with Senator Crown when he said there was a civil war on this issue.  Any colleague who spoke on either side of the House was very much supportive of the principle of the Bill.  Senator Conway, speaking on that Bill, also called for a debate on tourism and pointed to the success of The Gathering, the need perhaps for another gathering, and the great success of the Wild Atlantic Way which has driven tourism, job creation and local enterprise across the west.  I agree with the Senator's calls for a debate on Brexit which is of huge significance for Ireland.  While we look to have debates on issues raised by colleagues, there is a full legislative schedule over the next two weeks.  It will be difficult to include any time for statements given the legislation before the House.</p> <p>A number of issues were raised by Senator Norris.  He referred to a meeting he had today with members of the TUI from Cork Institute of Technology and with whom I and other colleagues have also met.  I would like it put on the record that I have a very strong personal connection with Cork Institute of Technology.  It is a superb third level institution which offers a high quality of education.  It is eminently deserving of technological university status.  The Technological Universities Bill was raised by some colleagues.  The Government has been pushed over recent years to bring this Bill forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#N01900"><p>By whom?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#N02000"><p>By people from all corners but especially in the south east.  There has been massive momentum behind it but it is important that the terms of the Bill are right.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I understand that Senator Craughwell, among others, sought information on the timing.  I have looked for that and I am informed the Bill is due to complete its passage through the D&aacute;il next week but I am not certain we will have it here before the end of this Seanad term.  I am making inquiries but that is all I can say at present.  The TUI is engaged with the Minister and officials from the Department of Education and Skills met with delegates yesterday.  There are ongoing engagements on amendments that the TUI has sought in respect of the Bill, particularly on concerns it has raised with all of us about the terms and conditions of its members in the event of any merger.  I have engaged with the TUI on this matter, as have other colleagues.<br/><br/>The Senator also referred to No. 1 on the Order Paper, the motion regarding the Twelfth Report of the Seanad Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  The Senator is entitled to table an amendment in respect of that but the CPP meeting concerned House business and was not a matter for the Leader's office.  It deals with the conduct of the Seanad.  We had a full meeting yesterday, from which a number of people were unfortunately absent.  We received legal advice, examined the amendments which are proposed to Standing Orders 90 and 105 and considered the adoption of new Standing Orders 108A to 108E.  This is the subject matter of No. 1 on the Order Paper and I am very happy to inform the House that we were told the amendments propose changes which are technical in nature but which are important because they will provide protection for privilege for official Seanad documents and the personal papers of Senators.  They give Standing Order status to a rule that is already present in Article 15.10 of the Constitution which states, &quot;Each House shall make its own rules and standing orders ... to protect its official documents and the private papers of its members&quot;.  Despite that provision of the Constitution, neither D&aacute;il nor Seanad had Standing Orders dealing with privilege for private papers or official documents.  In the case of Howlin <i>v</i>. Morris, the High Court criticised both Houses their failure in this regard.  On foot of the requirement of the High Court as well as the relevant provision in the Constitution, these Standing Orders are being brought introduced in both the D&aacute;il and the Seanad in order to bolster, or confirm, the practice that already exists in the context of privilege for these documents.  There is nothing new in the new Standing Orders, which are available for all Members to see.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O00200"><p>That may be the case but the matter is eminently worthy of debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O00300"><p>We obtained legal advice on them.  In any event, I am not sure anyone could disagree with their contents.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O00400"><p>I do not say that but there is a historical context in which it could be placed and the Senator referred to a High Court case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O00500"><p>Howlin <i>v</i>. Morris.  They are straightforward in simply giving effect to the constitutional imperative under Article 15.10, so I cannot accept the amendment.</p><p>The Senator also referred to the axing of &quot;Gloria&quot;, the RTE programme on Lyric FM.  This matter was raised by our eminent colleague Professor David McConnell.  I agree with him that it is a matter of concern.  Perhaps we might look at raising the issue as a Commencement matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O00600"><p>Perhaps we could share a Commencement matter on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O00700"><p>We could.  Senator Hayden welcomed the increase in the take-up in respect of the Insolvency Service of Ireland and I agree with her on that.</p> <p>Senator Mooney raised the matter of rural Ireland and I think I have dealt with that in full.  He spoke about auction politics but that was political rhetoric, rather than something that requires a Leader's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O00800"><p>I was curious about the offer of &euro;500.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O00900"><p>Is Ruair&iacute; Quinn going to sign that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01000"><p>In the interests of unity, I am going to agree with the Senators.  I do not agree with auction politics and we are seeing it from all sorts of people at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01100"><p>I just feel there is no credibility surrounding that offer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01200"><p>Senator Mullins supported Senator Conway in calling for a debate on tourism and spoke of the need for value for money, with which I entirely agree.</p> <p>Senator Quinn seconded Senator Norris's amendment, which I have dealt with.  I hope I have given people a clear idea of what is in the CPP amendments.  Senator Quinn also spoke on the issue of rural Ireland.  Furthermore, he asked about people returning from engaging with ISIS, the so-called "Islamic State", and referred to the question of sanctions.  He raised the possibility of the removal of passports and he may know that at EU level new transnational offences are currently being drafted which would apply to the scenario the Senator describes where people have moved from EU member states out of the EU to fight for ISIS in Syria and commit atrocities there.  While it is being dealt with at EU level, I agree that it is also a matter for national states.  We heard about the issue at the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality yesterday.</p> <p>Senator Cahill welcomed the new national strategy from the Minister for Justice and Equality on domestic, sexual and gender-based violence.  I absolutely agree with her on that matter.  Today, when we debate the Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Bill 2015, we will discuss some very important supports that will be put in place for victims and complainants in sex offences cases.  I welcome the fact that Senator Cahill is meeting with the DPP for Northern Ireland and that she has called a meeting for next Wednesday at 1 p.m. in Buswells Hotel on the issue of supports for victims of sexual offences.  There has been a great deal of work done recently in Britain on the use of intermediaries for child witnesses in sex offence cases and that is something we need to consider in the context of future legislation in this jurisdiction.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh spoke on a specific and serious issue in Galway involving the eviction of a number of Traveller families and asked for the Minister, Deputy Kelly, to enter into negotiations with the Galway manager.  This is a matter the local authorities are dealing with and I ask the Senator to table it for debate on the Commencement.  Clearly, there is real concern among local authorities about conditions following the appalling tragedy of the fire in which so many children and others were killed last year.  The Senator also raised the issue of home helps and that is also a specific matter where individuals are in hospitals and unable to be sent home because of the lack of availability of home care help.  I ask him to consider putting that down as a Commencement matter for debate with the Minister for Health.</p> <p>Senator Mary Ann O'Brien raised the serious issue of drugs and criminality, noting the very tragic incident in Cork where a number of people are in hospital as a result of ingestion of a particular drug.  She referred to the UK law in this area and that jurisdiction's Psychoactive Substances Bill.  The Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality held hearings on drug policy and produced a report.  It took a similar approach in calling for an end to criminalisation for small amounts of possession, believing as we did that the criminal justice system may not be the most appropriate approach in that particular case.  It is currently under review by the Government and we can look at that further.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell asked about the Technological Universities Bill, which I have dealt with.</p> <p>Senator Eamonn Coghlan spoke about rural Ireland and helpfully rebutted some of the points made by other Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01300"><p>I hope he prints and circulates that to rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01400"><p>It will be a good news letter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01500"><p>All is alive and well in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01600"><p>I will deliver it to Finn Valley.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01700"><p>He also noted that Fianna F&aacute;il closed more Garda stations and rural post offices than this Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" speakername="Paschal Mooney" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01800"><p>It is nothing to do with Senator Bacik - she would not say something like that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#O01900"><p>Senator Eamonn Coghlan also expressed support for the protection of the national anthem.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill raised the issue of rural Ireland and I think I have dealt with that.  He referred to a specific matter relating to State board appointments which I think, again, is more appropriate to a Commencement matter debate.</p> <p>Senator Brennan spoke about tourism and called for a recognition of the role of voluntary activists and community workers in tourism, which is an important point.</p> <p>Senator Bradford asked about the Technological Universities Bill, with which I have dealt.</p> <p>Senator Walsh raised the anniversary of the first election and called for a debate on housing.  The Leader, Senator Cummins, gave a full response to a question earlier this week on housing, a number of us having looked for a debate on the subject.  There is a great deal of work going on at present to ensure we deal with the very serious crisis of homelessness.  In particular, the current funding allocation for emergency accommodation for homeless people was increased in budget 2016 by an additional &euro;17 million, bringing Exchequer support up to &euro;70 million, an increase of 56% since 2014.  Many initiatives have been taken.  In 2015, over 13,000 units were delivered across all social housing programmes, representing an 86% increase from 2014, and the target for 2016 is to deliver over 17,000 units.  A very ambitious social housing programme is in place but, as anyone who saw the television programme on Monday night will know, there is still a very serious problem and we need to move very swiftly on it.  I will look for that debate and Senator Cummins has already done so.</p> <p>Senator Crown referred to the failure to reform the health service as a disappointment.  He would acknowledge that there have been massive reforms, notwithstanding the failure to bring in the universal health insurance system that was hoped for.  There have been massive reforms in the provision of free GP care for children and the elderly, very significant changes in hospital governance and in primary care investment.  He also raised the issue of Private Members' Bills and we can look for time next week to bring forward any Private Members' Bills that are still on the Order Paper.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I urge the Senator not to lose heart.  In 2011, at the last election, I had a Private Member's Bill on the Order Paper, the Bill to prohibit female genital mutilation.  I am happy to say that it was restored to the Order Paper by the Government in 2011 and is now in force.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#P00200"><p>Senator Bacik was a Government Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#P00300"><p>I was not at the time the election was called.  There is hope for these Bills.  Senator Byrne spoke about homelessness, which I think I have dealt with.</p> <p>I cannot accept the amendment Senator Crown put forward.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#P00400"><p>Senator David Norris has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 1 be taken with debate".  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#P00500"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.150" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.151" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Q00100"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(b) I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.153/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Q00200"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 16; Nl, 24.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Gerard P. Craughwell and David Norris; Nl, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.153/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2016-01-21" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Q00200">
            <divisioncount ayes="16" noes="24" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1208" vote="no">M&aacute;ir&iacute;a Cahill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.153/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Q00200"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#R00100"><p>Senator Crown has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business: "That a debate with the Minister for Health on the cancellation of elective surgery in Cork University Hospital be taken today."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" speakername="John Crown" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#R00200"><p>T&aacute; s&eacute;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.156/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#R00300"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 16; Nl, 25.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Thomas Byrne and John Crown; Nl, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.156/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2016-01-21" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#R00300">
            <divisioncount ayes="16" noes="25" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="aye">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1205" vote="aye">Paul Bradford</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="aye">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1196" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="aye">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="aye">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="aye">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="aye">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" vote="aye">Feargal Quinn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1156" vote="aye">Mary White</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1208" vote="no">M&aacute;ir&iacute;a Cahill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="no">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="no">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="no">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1143" vote="no">John Whelan</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.156/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#R00300"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.157" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put: "That the Order of Business be agreed to."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.158" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad divided by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#T00100"><p>Under Standing Order 62(3)(b), I request that the division be taken again other than by electronic means.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.160/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#T00200"><p>Question put: "That the Order of Business be agreed to."</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 23; Nl, 11.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins; Nl, Senators Sean D. Barrett and David Norris..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.160/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2016-01-21" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#T00200">
            <divisioncount ayes="23" noes="11" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="aye">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="aye">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="aye">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1124" vote="aye">Michael Comiskey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1158" vote="aye">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="aye">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="aye">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="aye">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="aye">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="aye">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="aye">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1162" vote="aye">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="aye">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="aye">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="aye">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="aye">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="aye">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="aye">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="aye">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" vote="aye">Susan O'Keeffe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="aye">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="aye">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1157" vote="no">Sean Barrett</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1116" vote="no">Thomas Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1147" vote="no">John Crown</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1159" vote="no">Mark Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="no">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="no">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="no">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" vote="no">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1123" vote="no">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1142" vote="no">Ned O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.160/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#T00200"><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.161" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U00100">Standing Orders: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U00200"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the report of the Committee on Procedure and Privileges on the amendment of Standing Orders 90 and 105 and the adoption of new Standing Orders 108A to 108E, inclusive, and a Schedule to Standing Orders be adopted, laid before the House and printed.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.163" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.164" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Senators" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U00400"><p>V&oacute;t&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U00500"><p>Will the Senators claiming a division please rise?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.166" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Senators David Norris, Paschal Mooney and Terry Leyden rose.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1120" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U00700"><p>As fewer than five Members have risen I declare the question carried.  In accordance with Standing Order 61 the names of the Senators dissenting will be recorded in the Journal of the Proceedings of the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.168" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question declared carried.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.169" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U00900">Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 Regulations: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U01000"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(3)) (Variation of title: Optician) Regulations 2016,copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 18th January, 2016 be referred to the Joint Committee on Health and Children, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3)(<i>j</i>), which, not later than 28th January, 2016, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 73, and Standing Order 75(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.171" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.172" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U01200">Planning and Development (Amendment) Regulations 2016: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U01300"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:Planning and Development (Amendment) Regulations 2016,copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 20th January, 2016 be referred to the Joint Committee on the Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3)(<i>j</i>), which, not later than 28th January, 2016, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 73, and Standing Order 75(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.174" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.175" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U01500">Companies Act 2014 (Section 1313) Regulations 2016: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" speakername="Maurice Cummins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U01600"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:Companies Act 2014 (Section 1313) Regulations 2016,copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 19th January, 2016 be referred to the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, in accordance with Standing Order 70A(3)(<i>j</i>), which, not later than 28th January, 2016, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 73, and Standing Order 75(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.177" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.178" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U01800">Criminal Law (Sexual Offences) Bill 2015: Report and Final Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U01900"><p>I welcome the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Fitzgerald, to the House.  Before we continue, I wish to remind Senators that a Senator may speak only once on Report Stage, except the proposer of an amendment, who may reply to the discussion on the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U02000"><p>On a point of order, in the case of someone who opposes a section, can that person speak twice?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U02100"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U02200"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U02300"><p>No sections are being discussed.  We are discussing amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.184" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#U02500"><p>The term "image" arises in section 6(1)(b) in the context of the offence of causing a child to watch sexual activity.  Section 8(4) sets out the definition of "sexually explicit material".  The section sets out how it is an offence to send such material to a child by means of information and communications technology.  For the purposes of clarity, it is proposed to define the word "image" to ensure it clearly encompasses still and moving images and any other type of image that may be produced.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frances Fitzgerald:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=401"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=401&amp;amp;pid=FrancesFitzgerald&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The wording used in the definition is similar to that used in the definition of "visual representation" in the context of child pornography, as it appears in the Child Trafficking and Pornography Act 1998.  An additional phrase, "or any other form of visual representation," has been included to ensure that any images produced by new technologies are automatically covered by the definition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#V00200"><p>It is important that definitions are as clear as possible.  As this amendment appears, in my opinion, to achieve that, I am happy to support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.188" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#V00400"><p>Amendments Nos. 2, 3, 5 to 22, inclusive, 27 and 44 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#V00500"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote>In page 6, line 14, to delete &quot;child pornography&quot; and substitute &quot;child sexual abuse material&quot;.</blockquote> <p>These amendments were also tabled on Committee Stage.  As I have already articulated my views on this issue on Committee and Second Stage, I do not intend to be repetitive today.  I appreciate that the amendments as drafted technically do not address everything that needs to be addressed, but I am strongly of the view that use of the phrase &quot;child pornography&quot; is abhorrent, and we need to be using it for the term that it is.  The word &quot;pornography&quot; in some way implies that there is some consent.  In the English dictionary in the mid-nineteenth century, the word was associated with terms such as &quot;taboo&quot; and &quot;secretive,&quot; but it has now become common parlance.  For me, the words &quot;child&quot; and &quot;pornography&quot; should never be used together.  We are clearly talking about child sexual abuse material relating to children who cannot and would not consent; they are victims of a crime.  The child abuse images are documented evidence of a crime in progress, a child being sexually abused.  </p><p>Similar to the amendments I tabled to the Criminal Law (Rape) (Amendment) Act 1990 in relation to assault, these amendments seek to positively change this legislation.  Similar amendments have been accepted.  Also, I note that the UK, through an amendment to its Serious Crime Act 2015, has amended its Sexual Offences Act 2003.  The term used in the UK for both child prostitution and child pornography is &quot;sexual exploitation of a child.&quot;  I want us to name this material for what it is.  What I am seeking from the Minister today is a commitment that her Department will seek to rectify this balance.</p><p>As I said, I do not propose to reiterate the arguments I put forward on Committee and Second Stages.  I believe that in Ireland we should have a system to filter all child abuse material, as happens in the UK and on our mobile phones, as mobile phone providers have signed up to an EU agreement in that regard.  We should be automatically doing this work.  I commend the work of the Internet Watch Foundation in the UK and hope we could have something similar here.  The purpose of these amendments is to name this material for what it is, namely, child sexual abuse material.  Interpol and Europol have asked us to call it what it is.  They have asked us not to use the term &quot;child pornography,&quot; because it in some way diminishes the act.  I ask that the Minister consider my proposals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#V00600"><p>I second the amendment.  This is an excellent amendment.  I am interested to learn that Interpol supports this proposal.  That is a very strong argument.  I hope that the Minister will see her way to accepting the amendment, particularly in light of the strong support for it from Interpol.  I may be an innocent, perhaps because of my age - I am almost 72 - but I have never seen child pornography.  I agree with Senator van Turnhout that it is doubtful that this material could be correctly termed pornography.  The word "pornography" comes from the Greek words "porne" and "graphein," and means the writings of prostitutes.  In common parlance it is taken to be erotic material to arouse the viewer.  I cannot imagine circumstances in which any normal adult would be aroused by the spectacle of children engaging in sexual activity, presumably, on many occasions, under compulsion.  Some of these children, I understand, are extremely young.  That is very worrying.  It seems to me that in every situation this is material that is an abuse of children.  It should not happen and it is a violation of children.  To my mind, the correct terminology is "child sexual abuse material."  The only reason I can think of for retention of the phrase "child pornography" is that it is a term that has registered in the public imagination and is the phrase used in the newspapers and so on.  I believe the Seanad has a role in educating the public, and should take the lead in that regard.  I ask that the Minister positively consider this amendment, acceptance of which will not result in any complications in terms of the passage of the Bill.  This is an aspect of the Bill about which I feel quite strongly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#V00700"><p>I thank the Senators for the amendments.  As stated by Senator van Turnhout, the effect of these amendments would be to substitute the term "child sexual abuse material" for "child pornography" throughout this Bill and the other Acts in which it appears.  The EU directive on child sexual exploitation and pornography uses the term that is used in this Bill.  However, I appreciate Senator van Turnhout's concerns and support her aim of ensuring that no one is in any doubt about what is meant when we speak of child sexual abuse material.  It is, as stated by the Senator, crime scene evidence of the most depraved and disgusting acts in relation to children.  A huge concern for criminal justice investigations across Europe and the world is the increasing evidence of abuse of children, most of whom, as stated by Senator Norris, are very young children.</p> <p>While I am not entirely convinced that the term "child pornography" fails to convey the true nature of this heinous material, I am, as I have stated previously, open to considering the change proposed by the Senator in a future review of child pornography legislation.  For technical reasons, and owing to the scale of the review involved, which I think the Senator will appreciate, I am unable to accept the amendments today.  The Minister of State outlined on Committee Stage the technical reasons to which I referred, and I would like to reiterate them for the benefit of the House.  The term "child pornography" appears in the Statute Book outside of the 1998 Act.  Any general amendment to that term throughout the Statute Book should be carefully made.  I am advised that a general amending provision such as that proposed by Senator van Turnhout in amendment No. 27 would not suffice.  Rather, apparently, each provision in the Statue Book containing the term that it is proposed to amend should be individually identified.  While it is not unusual to substitute one form of words with another, this is done through individual identification in each instance.  This is an important safeguard, particularly, of course, when it comes to criminal justice legislation.  </p> <p>The amendments proposed also raise technical issues, including, for example, the impact on the Short Title of the Child Trafficking and Pornography Act 1998.  I am advised that it is not appropriate to amend the Short Title to an existing Act by way of an amendment in subsequent legislation.  The Senator will appreciate that such amendment would need to be provided for by way of a different Bill.  The Act should be substituted and repealed.  I hope the Senator understands why I am unable to do that at this point.  However, I take the points made by the Senator and they will be taken into account in the context of any review of that legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" speakername="Jillian van Turnhout" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#V00800"><p>I thank the Minister for her reply.  I believe there are proposals at EU and Council of Europe level to look at this issue.  I hope that Ireland will be at the vanguard and lead any change in that regard.  I appreciate that the change cannot be made today, but I hope the Minister will accept the need for that change.  It is an issue I feel strongly about and that has the support, as I said, of Europol and Interpol.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jillian van Turnhout:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=24&amp;amp;MemberID=2391"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2391&amp;amp;pid=JillianVanTurnhout&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->An Irish garda working for Europol made a presentation to us here a few years ago and he was able to show us the types of material -  he did not show us images - the nature of the material and the depravity involved.  He talked of pictures of babies who still had umbilical cords on them.  There is no age too young for these horrendous and heinous images and it needs to be ensured our legislation reflects that.  I will not press the amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.195" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.196" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 3 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#W00400"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p><blockquote>In page 7, lines 12 and 13, to delete &quot;to a fine or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years, or both&quot; and substitute &quot;to imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years&quot;.</blockquote> <p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  The explanatory memorandum states that Part 2 &quot;contains provisions to enhance the protection of children from sexual exploitation, including exploitation through child prostitution and child pornography.  Provisions are also included to target acts of child sexual grooming.&quot;  It further states: &quot;A person found guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable on conviction on indictment to up to 10 years imprisonment.&quot;  On Committee Stage, the Minister of State took the Bill and he did not give a compelling reason as to why section 3 had been watered down.  Section 3(5)(b) states:&quot; A person guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable... on conviction on indictment, to a fine or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years, or both.&quot;  The Minister of State made this amendment on Committee Stage.</p><p>This begs the question: what offence would the person be guilty of that he or she could get by with a fine?  The section does not even specify what the fine should be, stating:</p><blockquote>3. (1) A person who for the purposes of the sexual exploitation of a child&mdash;<br /><br />(a) pays, gives, offers or promises to pay or give a child or another person money or any other form of remuneration or consideration,<br /><br />(b) provides or offers or offers or promises to provide, a child to another person, or<br /><br />(c) obtains a child for himself or herself or for another person,<br /><br />shall be guilty of an offence.</blockquote> <p>These are most serious offences.  The best the Minister of State could come up with on Committee Stage was that perhaps previously legislation reflected that judicial discretion would apply to conferring a fine or to imprisonment.  On summary conviction, it can be a fine or imprisonment and I do not challenge that, but if someone is charged on indictment, it means a more serious offence has occurred in the opinion of the DPP.  If the courts decide that the person is guilty, then he or she is guilty of a grievous crime against a child and it is unconscionable that we would send a signal that a fine is adequate sanction in that scenario.  Therefore, I hope the Minister will accept my amendment and revert to the original wording, which was drafted and approved by her and the Government.  Whatever lobbying went on to make her amend this should be set aside at this stage.  We should revert to sending a clear signal that paedophilia is not acceptable in the minds of Oireachtas Members and send a clear signal to the Judiciary that imposing a fine is not sufficient sanction when a person is found guilty on conviction on indictment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#W00500"><p>I second the amendment.  Senator Walsh has outlined clearly why the amendment has been tabled.  Somebody convicted on indictment of a serious sexual offence against one of the most vulnerable cohort of people in our society, namely, children, should face a term of imprisonment, not a fine.  To even provide for the option of a fine minimises the serious offence a person would be convicted of and there should be no leeway in this regard.  On conviction for a serious offence against a child, there should be a mandatory prison sentence up to a maximum of ten years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#W00600"><p>Virtually everyone would agree that sexual offences against a child are heinous but I have reservations about the amendment proposed by my Fianna F&aacute;il colleagues for a number of reasons.  First, Senator Walsh referred to conviction on indictment as if that was the only provision in the section but it is not.  Section 3(5)(a) states:</p><blockquote>&quot;(5) A person guilty of an offence under this section shall be liable - <br /><br />(a) on summary conviction, to a class A fine, or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 12 months.&quot;</blockquote> <p>Summary conviction is also considered, therefore, by the legislation.</p><p>The second reason is there is nothing here that says anything about the knowledge or the <i>mens rea</i>of the person committing the alleged offence.  One has to take into account the possibility that somebody might engage in sexual relations with somebody who appeared above the appropriate age.</p><p>With regard to the question of age, in this section and the following two sections, there are three different definitions of what a child is in terms of his or her years.  That suggests a certain confusion.  What is a child?  In one section, it is a person under the age of 18; in the next, it is a person under the age of 15; and in the next, it is a person under the age of 17.  That opens an area of ambiguity.  What about somebody, for example, who engaged in sexual congress with a person who was for the purposes of this section 17 years, 11 months and 28 days?  That seems to me to be a situation in which a fine would be perfectly well justified rather than a term of imprisonment of up to ten years.  I am afraid I cannot support my colleagues' amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#W00700"><p>I thank Senators Walsh and Wilson for the amendment.  The effect of the amendment would be to remove the possibility of imposing a fine as part of the penalty for an offence under section 3.  That includes the offences of obtaining or providing a child for the purposes of sexual exploitation and related offences.  The aim of the amendment is to ensure persons convicted of such appalling offences cannot escape with a fine instead of imprisonment.  While that is an understandable aim, it is, however, the norm, in particular for offences which may be motivated by, for example, financial gain, to include a fine in addition to a penalty of imprisonment.  The purpose of providing the options of a fine, a sentence of imprisonment or both is to ensure the court can determine the most appropriate sentence in all the circumstances of a particular offence and a particular offender.  It leaves this to the discretion of the court having regard to the particular offence, circumstances and so forth.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frances Fitzgerald:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=401"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=401&amp;amp;pid=FrancesFitzgerald&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Obviously these offences will vary and there is no question about that.  As we know, there are different levels of exploitation and the related offences as well.  </p><p>I want to highlight that section 3 contains a number of related offences.  It includes offences of paying for a child, providing a child and accepting a child for the purpose of sexual exploitation.  I have to agree that it is almost impossible to imagine any circumstances under which anything, other than a prison sentence, is an acceptable sentence for such offences.  It is also the case that a person who agrees to accept or give money to a child for the purposes of sexual exploitation but then thinks better of it, and does not proceed any further, is guilty of an offence under section 3.  That is one example of the kind of range that one could have.  I am not passing any judgment on that but making the point that one can have different types and levels of offences under section 3.  I mention that example not to suggest for a moment that any particular offence for which a fine alone may be appropriate, just to illustrate the range of offences and circumstances which are covered by section 3.</p><p>In other areas of law, for example in the case of a non-fatal assault, where in a similar discussion to what we are having here, one might say: "Well, of course, imprisonment is the option here."  In fact, we again leave it to the discretion of the court.  There is a possibility, in certain circumstances as we know, of a fine or a prison sentence or both.  It is leaving the discretion to the court, with the judge to decide having considered all of the evidence.  It is a recognition that the court is best placed to determine the appropriate sentence in a particular situation, taking into account all of the circumstances.  I think it is appropriate to provide in law a range of possible sentences, including under this section.  That is the usual practice.  Senator Walsh said that my colleague and the Minister of State, Deputy Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, referred to the fact that it is the norm to have that range of sentences so that the judge has the option, in terms of examining each case, to decide what is the most appropriate sentence.  As I have said, in other very serious offences, that is what we do in our law.  We give the range of sentences and then leave it to the courts to actually decide.  We are reflecting, in this legislation, the general approach in terms of the kind of discretion that we allow the courts to make so I cannot accept the amendment.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#X00200"><p>I thank the Minister for her response.  I have found her concluding remarks very unsatisfactory and I would like to deal with some of the points that the Minister and Senator Norris made in this regard.</p><p>Our knowledge now of paedophilia and of the effects it has on victims is far superior than it might have been some decades ago when some of this went on.  Therefore, it is important that we send the correct signals to society, perpetrators and the Judiciary as to where we rate this particular offence on the criminal code.  </p><p>Senator Norris pointed out, and I had already made reference to it, the phrase &quot;on summary conviction&quot;.  Is it not the case, Minister, that when the evidence is gathered, and when the Office of the Director of Public Prosecutions assesses that evidence, it will determine whether the charge will be made on summary conviction, on conviction on indictment or, if the case goes to a lower court, they might decide that it should be a conviction on indictment?  </p><p>With regard to what Senator Norris has said, <i>mens rea</i>is part of the defence, if it applies, that can be made in whichever court the case is in.  Also, <i>mens rea</i>forms part of the consideration before the judgment is determined.  That means there is nothing to prohibit the person before the courts, who is being charged, with being able to defend his or her position legally with the various arguments that his or her legal team can put forward in defence.  What we are talking about here is after all of that and when the particular judgment has been made.  We are talking about what the sentence should be and this is where I digress considerably with the Minister.  She talked about various levels of exploitation.  In the first instance, that will be taken into consideration, depending on whether the case goes forward on summary conviction or conviction on indictment.  Some evaluation will be made with regard to that and with regard to the levels.  </p><p>Section 3 clearly sets out that this is a deliberate attempt when somebody is found guilty for (a), (b) and (c).  Section 3(1) states:</p><blockquote>3. (1) A person who for the purposes of the sexual exploitation of a child&mdash;<br /><br />(a) pays, gives, offers or promises to pay or give a child or another person money or any other form of remuneration or consideration,<br /><br />(b) provides or offers or offers or promises to provide, a child to another person, or<br /><br />(c) obtains a child for himself or herself or for another person,<br /><br />shall be guilty of an offence.</blockquote> <p>Regardless of whether they were only the ones that got money from it, in my opinion they are as guilty as the people who sexually exploit the children.  This comes back to the best interests of the child.  I have to say that I was sceptical when I saw this Government put a referendum to the people about the best interests of the child.  There is no Government in the history of the State, and in my lifetime, where the child is more vulnerable because of the actions of this Government over the period.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#X00300"><p>That is rubbish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#X00400"><p>I could name many of them.  In this specific instance, the Minister has said that there is a range and that judicial discretion should be over a range of particular sanctions.  Depending on the gravity, on indictment, and on the assessment of the judge, when a person is found guilty the judge will still have a range because the amendment states clearly that it is "imprisonment for a term not exceeding 10 years."  That means there is a scale of sentencing ranging from a day, two days, a week or whatever up to ten years.  There is also the issue of suspending part of the sentence.</p> <p>I am clearly saying that we should not accept a situation where a person can get off by purely by paying a fine where he or she has been found guilty of an offence to exploit a child.  If the Minister has said that to me then I must clearly say to her and the Government that they have failed in their duty to the children and the constitutional amendment that they have brought forward.  It begs the question as to how sincere the Government was about that particular amendment to the Constitution.</p> <p>I am not a member of Government but I am a Member of this Oireachtas.  I do not want to be part of an Oireachtas which sends a signal to the Judiciary or society that a mere fine is sufficient where a person has been found guilty of an offence to exploit a child sexually, whether he or she is the direct exploiter or a participant.  I do not for a second understand, and the Minister has not explained, why the change in the amendment came forward from the Government on Committee Stage.  I am well aware that there are ideological groups globally that advocate all sorts of sexual freedoms, including pederasty and sex between children.  We have seen such groups.  A whole plethora of groups have argued the case.   </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#X00500"><p>I doubt there are very many.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#X00600"><p>I would hate to think that such ideologies are influencing or being reflected here.  I ask and appeal to the Minister to reflect upon what has been said and to put the best interests of the child in this legislation.  That means clearly signalling that such behaviours are unacceptable, and that if a person is found guilty of such acts then he or she will face a term of imprisonment.  The length of the sentence is at the discretion of the judge and depends on the gravity of the particular offence.  We must send the message that perpetrators will not get away, if they have deep pockets, with just paying money.  We have seen cases where this has happened with adults and money was paid.  There was a huge public outcry about money being paid and, subsequently, the decisions were appealed by the DPP.  I ask the Minister not to let that happen, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#X00700"><p>To suggest for a moment that the approach we are taking in this Bill is the result of lobbying is absolutely and totally incorrect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#X00800"><p>Why did it happen?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#X00900"><p>For the reasons I have outlined.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frances Fitzgerald:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=31&amp;amp;MemberID=401"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=401&amp;amp;pid=FrancesFitzgerald&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=01&amp;amp;day=21"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->To suggest that the Government or, indeed, anybody who would be working on this Bill or the approach we have taken in this Bill has any ambivalence whatsoever in relation to the offences that we are talking about is simply outrageous and untrue.  If we were to accept the amendment it would bring the penalty for this offence out of line with penalties for similar offences in other sections of the Bill.  A trial on indictment may indicate a more serious offence that still requires to be proven before a court-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y00200"><p>Yes, absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1009" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y00300"><p>-----but also a person tried summarily indicating a minor offence may elect a trial by jury which brings them into this penalty range.  That is an important point.  The reasons are as I have outlined.  To extrapolate from the approach we have taken in this part of the legislation and to suggest that the Government is not putting the best interests of the child first, in a week when the Child and Family Relationships Act has come into effect - where the best interests of the child have to be the paramount consideration when making decisions about guardianship, access, custody and maintenance - and given the work that has been done on the children's referendum, which gives the individual child rights and which protects children in long-term care so that better decisions are taken for them in terms of adoption, and given that we have passed the Marriage Equality Bill 2015 which protects children who are living with same sex couples, I certainly cannot accept what the Senator has had to say in regard to children and the approach of this Government to protecting children's rights.  I have given the reasons we are including a fine or imprisonment for this offence.  It is in line with the approach taken to all serious offences, apart from murder, where we leave it to the discretion of the court to examine individual cases and look at the individual circumstances.  To extrapolate beyond that and suggest that in some way there is an ambivalence about people who would exploit children is incorrect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y00400"><p>May I-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y00500"><p>No, I cannot allow the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y00600"><p>I am allowed.  Standing Orders-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y00700"><p>Standing Orders state that the proposer of an amendment may reply to a discussion on an amendment.  The Senator cannot speak twice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y00800"><p>So the Acting Chairman is silencing me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y00900"><p>I am not silencing the Senator.  These are the Standing Orders of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01000"><p>In that situation I find what the Minister has said is unacceptable.  I think it is a dereliction-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01100"><p>Sorry, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01200"><p>-----of fulfilling our constitutional responsibilities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01300"><p>The Senator knows the rules of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01400"><p>I am going to press the amendment and it will be up to the Members on the other side to decide if they agree with the Minister's weak response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" speakername="Pat O'Neill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01500"><p>Is the Senator pressing the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" speakername="Jim Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.226/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01700"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Seanad divided: T, 5; Nl, 21.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Jim Walsh and Diarmuid Wilson; Nl, Senators Aideen Hayden and Michael Mullins.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.226/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2016-01-21" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01700">
            <divisioncount ayes="5" noes="21" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1140" vote="aye">Terry Leyden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1128" vote="aye">Paschal Mooney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1115" vote="aye">Labhr&aacute;s &Oacute; Murch&uacute;</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1126" vote="aye">Jim Walsh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1164" vote="aye">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" vote="no">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" vote="no">Terry Brennan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1150" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1208" vote="no">M&aacute;ir&iacute;a Cahill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1165" vote="no">Eamonn Coghlan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1130" vote="no">Maurice Cummins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1117" vote="no">John Gilroy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" vote="no">Aideen Hayden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1152" vote="no">Imelda Henry</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" vote="no">Ca&iacute;t Keane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1161" vote="no">John Kelly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" vote="no">Marie Moloney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1174" vote="no">Mary Moran</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1134" vote="no">Tony Mulcahy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1118" vote="no">Michael Mullins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1136" vote="no">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" vote="no">Mary Ann O'Brien</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1170" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1125" vote="no">Pat O'Neill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1171" vote="no">Jillian van Turnhout</mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.226/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016012100002#Y01700"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-01-21a.227" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional text to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>