<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to clarify progress to date on the recruitment of an oncologist with a special interest in sarcoma, based at St. Vincent's University Hospital, Dublin.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Gabrielle McFadden of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality to review the current operation of the Garda vetting legislation, whereby an applicant approved by Garda vetting can have the clearance attached to the person for a fixed period of time, to avoid the need to make a number of applications for different organisations with which he or she may be involved.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Lorraine Clifford-Lee of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality to reopen Rush Garda station in County Dublin.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to make a statement regarding the status of the building projects at Ballinspittle national school, County Cork; and when is it proposed to make a site visit to progress this building schedule.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerard P. Craughwell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to make funding immediately available to ensure that local authorities in Border counties can establish European affairs strategic policy committees to address their unique Brexit issues.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide assurances that additional funding will be available, if needed, to retain all existing courses at the Castlebar campus of Galway-Mayo Institute of Technology.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to confirm that certain restrictive terms in a contract between Sic&iacute;n Co-operative Society and its growers are required by the Bord Bia quality assurance scheme and whether her Department will seek to mediate a dispute between a former chicken grower (details supplied) and Manor Farm-Carton Brothers Limited where that dispute has arisen from the refusal of the grower to take part in certain VAT-avoidance arrangements.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for mental health and older people to outline the timescale as to when works will start on a new 50-bed unit on the Sacred Heart home site in Roscommon town following the announcement of capital funding for the project last year.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to discuss what actions he is taking to address the serious and ongoing decline of health services in County Clare, with particular reference to the drastic curtailment of Shannondoc services throughout the county.</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by Senators Devine, McFadden, Clifford-Lee, Lombard, Craughwell, &Oacute; Domhnaill, Feighan and Gavan as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Devine, McFadden, Clifford-Lee and Lombard and they will be taken now.</p><p>I regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Mullen on the grounds that the Minister has no official responsibility in this matter.</p><p>Senators Craughwell, &Oacute; Domhnaill, Feighan and Gavan may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p><p>The speaking time for Members to put their case on the Commencement is four minutes and the Minister or Minister of State usually has four minutes to reply.  It is at my discretion to allow supplementary questions.  In recent times, the question and answer sometimes have taken 14 or 15 minutes, thereby putting pressure on others to comply.  I am not particularly warning anyone here but it is getting a bit out of hand.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#A00400">Hospital Staff Recruitment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#A00500"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.</p> <p>Senator Devine has four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#A00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her attendance.  I am not sure how well aware she is of Sarcoma Ireland, which formed last June or July owing to the lack of expert care in treating sarcoma here following the loss of a very experienced locum at the time.  After much toing and froing we met the Minister, Deputy Harris.  We asked him a series of five questions which have still not been answered.  In that meeting in July he agreed that filling that post was necessary and he committed to advertise that post as soon as possible.  This has been advertised and apparently the interviews took place last week.</p> <p>I welcome Susan and her sister Anna in the Gallery today.  There would be many more; nine have since passed away in the few months that they have been together as a group.  Those are only the people that we know of because of their protests.  The rest are ill and unable to attend.</p> <p>I have five questions I would like the Minister of State to answer today.  How many applications were received for this post?  How many of those applicants were deemed qualified and eligible for interview?  Who are the members of the interview panel?  What is the most likely date the appointee will start to work at the sarcoma clinic?  These are important questions and we need transparency in this appointment.  Several different meandering paths have been taken and we really have not got to the point whereby we will get the expertise these patients require.  We need a response from the Minister of State.  I might also ask for the Minister, Deputy Harris, to contact me by the end of the day.  The members of Sarcoma Ireland want five minutes with the Minister to discuss issues further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#A00700"><p>The Minister apologises that he cannot be here this morning.  On his behalf, I thank Senator Devine for raising the issue, which gives me an opportunity to update the House on the matter.  Sarcomas are rare cancers with about 220 cases occurring annually in Ireland.  Services for patients with sarcoma are currently provided in St. Vincent's University Hospital, Dublin and in Cork University Hospital.  Both hospitals are designated cancer centres and have an extensive range of multidisciplinary services and expert clinical advice available to them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2186"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2186&amp;amp;pid=CatherineByrne&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> A national clinical lead in soft tissue sarcomas is in place to oversee services for patients.  Patients have their cases presented and discussed at one of the two sarcoma multidisciplinary teams and members of these teams have links with European specialists in sarcoma.  The treatment of sarcomas requires integrated multidisciplinary care, with the involvement of many different clinicians.  St. Vincent&rsquo;s University Hospital has provided highly specialised and individualised treatment to sarcoma sufferers for a number of years.  St. Vincent&rsquo;s has access to all of the relevant specialties for treatment, including surgery, medical oncology, radiation oncology, radiology and pathology.  It is the largest provider of surgical procedures for soft tissue sarcomas in the country.</p><p>The Health Service Executive is committed lo providing a high quality, responsive and sustainable service for sarcoma patients.  To support the existing range of services for patients with sarcoma, an additional permanent post of consultant medical oncologist with a special interest in sarcoma has been approved for St. Vincent&rsquo;s.  The HSE has advised that interviews for this position took place last week and a successful candidate has been identified.</p><p>The Department is currently working on a new national cancer strategy for the next decade.  Services for rare cancers, such as sarcoma, have received considerable attention in developing the strategy.  The strategy will aim to meet the needs of patients in the treatment of cancer and in improving their quality of life.  Other areas of focus will include prevention, early diagnosis of cancer and facilitating patient input.  The Minister, Deputy Harris, intends to publish the new strategy in the coming weeks.  I would like to assure the Senator that high quality services will continue to be delivered by the multidisciplinary sarcoma teams, including the team at St. Vincent&rsquo;s University Hospital.</p><p>In response to the questions raised by the Senator, unfortunately, I do not have answers at present.  I will pass on her comments to the Minister and I will also inform him that Senator Devine would like him to contact her.  Although I do not know precisely where he is at present, I know the Senator is looking for some kind of a meeting, so I will pass on that request.  As I said, I do not have answers to the Senator's specific questions.  She has answered one of them herself in that somebody has been appointed and the starting date is due shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#B00200"><p>I think the most prudent way to proceed is if Senator Devine could get an assurance that the Minister, Deputy Harris, will meet her.  The Minister of State is not the line Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#B00300"><p>There are outstanding questions concerning how the applications were dealt with, how candidates were deemed qualified for interview and who were the members of the interview panel.  It is great that the Minister will launch the new strategy in the coming weeks and I hope this will facilitate patient input.  However, these people do not have that time.  They have lost several of their comrades in the last few months and more are very sick and unable to make it today.  Who is the new person who has been appointed?  Has the process followed the European Society for Medical Oncology guidelines and the protocol that should be followed in regard to this appointment?  How do I get the attention of the Minister, Deputy Harris?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#B00400"><p>I do not have that information to hand.  I will pass on Senator Devine's concerns to the Minister and inform him that she is seeking to meet him.  However, I cannot give her any commitment as to whether or not the Minister can meet her.  That is up to him, not me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#B00500"><p>I am sure the Senator will pursue it further if she does not get a response.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.17" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#B00550">Garda Vetting of Personnel</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#B00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for dealing with the matter.  The National Vetting Bureau (Children and Vulnerable Persons) Act 2012 makes it mandatory for people working with children or vulnerable adults to be screened by the Garda National Vetting Bureau.  This provision is necessary and prudent and is welcomed by all organisations working with the young and with vulnerable people.  It means that adults in roles such as teaching, youth work, sports coaching and nursing, those working in church organisations and many others are now obliged to have Garda clearance.  While this is positive, the fact an individual has to make a unique application for vetting clearance for each organisation seems an unnecessary duplication of effort and is an example of how the procedures are designed to suit the system rather than to accommodate the volunteer or the staff member.</p> <p>A young woman I know had to have Garda vetting for her college course.  She had to be vetted again because she is involved in a church group, vetted a third time because she is involved in the Irish Girl Guides, vetted a fourth time because she teaches English as a foreign language in her spare time and, would you believe, vetted a fifth time because her family keep Spanish students.  All of these accreditations are identical.  They all say that she has no criminal conviction and that there is no concern she will harm a child or put a child at risk.  They all say the exact same thing.  When she asked me why she cannot just have one card that proves she has been vetted and cleared, I could find no logical answer for her.  At the moment this woman, who has much to offer her local community and who understands and supports the need for vetting, is being asked, like many others, to jump through multiple hoops unnecessarily.</p> <p>This can be offputting and serve to discourage people from taking additional voluntary roles in the community.  I will agree that the application procedure has speeded up considerably in recent years, particularly with the introduction of online application vetting.  However, with 3,000 applications a month, I believe it makes more sense to have a single vetting card issued to an individual which would be valid for a fixed period of time and would be used in multiple contexts, as happens in other countries.</p> <p>There is an issue which is coming to a head at present involving 32,000 teachers who have worked in the same schools since before 2006, when vetting became compulsory.  They all now need to apply for vetting before the end of the month.  The Teaching Council is concerned that, based on current trends, as many as 600 teachers may lapse from its register and, therefore, face loss of salary.  Many of these 32,000 teachers already have Garda vetting clearance for other activities in which they are involved.  It seems ridiculous that this cannot be used for their teaching.</p> <p>Vetting is essential but unnecessary complication is not.  There are lots of excuses as to why a more streamlined vetting system cannot be put in place but there is no good reason.  I ask the Minister of State, the line Minister and the Department to review the current procedure without delay with a view to making it more user-friendly.  We need a system that not only protects children but one which removes unnecessary barriers for those wishing to help and support those same children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#B00700"><p>On behalf of the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality, I thank Senator McFadden for raising this issue in the House.  Unfortunately, she cannot be present and I am here in her place.</p> <p>As the House will appreciate, the primary purpose of Garda vetting is to seek to ensure the safety of children and vulnerable adults.  Every effort is made to make the system as efficient as possible but that cannot be at the expense of the core objective.  In accordance with the provisions of the National Vetting Bureau (Children and Vulnerable Persons) Acts 2012 to 2016, vetting is conducted by the Garda National Vetting Bureau in respect of a range of employments and services where persons would have substantial and unsupervised access to children and vulnerable adults.  It is necessary for the Garda National Vetting Bureau to conduct full vetting checks for each new vetting application received to ensure that the most recent data available is taken into account.  This is because once there has been any significant lapse of time between one employment and another, the original Garda vetting disclosure must be reviewed to take account of any changes in information, such as more recent criminal convictions.  Furthermore, under the Data Protection Acts, any sensitive personal data which employers use in regard to their employees must be current, accurate and up to date.</p> <p>I am pleased to inform the Senator that the vast majority of vetting applications are now submitted and processed via the eVetting system and that 80% of the applications are now being processed by the Garda National Vetting Bureau in five working days.  In circumstances where there is such a sustained reduction in processing times, the problems presented in individual cases of re-vetting or vetting transferability are very significantly reduced.  This sustained improvement in processing times has come about primarily as a result of significant investment by the Government in the Garda National Vetting Bureau and, in particular, following the launch in April this year of the new eVetting system.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2186"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2186&amp;amp;pid=CatherineByrne&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->All organisations are encouraged to avail of this service and indeed 85% of organisations registered for vetting are already using it.  Some individual cases will of their nature take longer than the average to complete when, for example, more extensive inquiries are required.  However, these cases are in the minority.  It is important to note also that the National Vetting Bureau (Children and Vulnerable Persons) Acts 2012 to 2016 provide for a degree of flexibility which may lessen the administrative burden in respect of vetting for the management of organisations that work with children and vulnerable adults.</p><p>Section 12 of the Acts makes provision for certain limited circumstances where organisations can share a single vetting disclosure in respect of an individual application where there is agreement with the vetting applicant.  This is a particularly important flexibility in respect of persons working, for example, in the health or education sectors as locums or substitute teachers.  Section 12 of the Acts also makes specific provision in respect of persons who may be employed on a recurring but non-continuous basis.  This could comprise persons who might provide services in a school or a number of schools on a regular basis.  The vetting obligations in respect of these persons shall be regarded as satisfied where the registered organisation received a vetting disclosure in respect of the individual for the initial engagement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#C00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State and I appreciate that this is not necessarily her portfolio.  It is absolutely vital that we and the public have confidence in the vetting process.  Nobody denies the absolute need for it, bearing in mind what we have been through in this country between the church and situations like &Aacute;ras Attracta in the past.  It is absolutely vital.  However, I believe that a passport type situation or a card valid for one year would make more sense.  The person I spoke to the Minister of State about had five different applications.  That is duplication of work.  One application could have looked after that situation for a whole year and reduced the work.  I think it would have been more cost effective for the State and much easier for people who want to start jobs but have to wait because of the Garda vetting.  It is duplication and a waste of money, but nobody denies the absolute need for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#C00300"><p>I will not read the concluding remarks because they have already been said in the initial response.  If Senator McFadden would like to give me the details of that particular applicant, I will make sure that the Minister has a look at it herself.  I will pass it on to her.  Regarding the other points the Senator raised, I will also bring those to the Minister's attention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#C00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State and Senator McFadden.  It is a very popular issue.  I have heard from many sources that it is a problem.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.24" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#C00500">Garda Stations</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#C00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House today to discuss this very important issue with regard to the reopening of Garda stations.  I particularly want to raise with her the issue of Rush Garda station, which is located in north County Dublin.  Rush Garda station closed down in 2012 under the last Government.  I call on the Minster of State to strongly consider Rush for inclusion in the pilot scheme to reopen six Garda stations, which is imminent.</p> <p>The closure has left a serious void in the policing of north County Dublin.  When it was closed in 2012, we were reassured that a 24-hour service would be provided in the nearby Lusk Garda station, but this never occurred.  In fact, the hours in Lusk Garda station have since been reduced.  As I said, this has left a very big void in the policing of north County Dublin.  Fingal is the fastest-growing county in Ireland.  The population of Rush itself is 10,000 and Lusk has almost 10,000.  We are being policed from Balbriggan Garda station, which is the nearest 24-hour Garda station.  That is over 14 km from Rush and has a population itself of 26,000.  That station is seriously overstretched and it is not able to provide an adequate service to the people in Rush in particular, as well as in nearby Lusk.</p> <p>Unfortunately, we have seen an escalation in both violent and serious crime in north County Dublin as well as anti-social behaviour, particularly in or around the Rush area.  I believe there is a strong correlation between the lack of a Garda service in the town and this increase in crime.  I come from a Garda family myself.  I am very well aware of the vital service community garda&iacute; provide to the community and the impact that visibility of garda&iacute; on the streets of a town can have on the level of both serious crime and anti-social behaviour in the area.</p> <p>As per the programme for Government, there is a commitment to review the Garda station closures, which occurred during the lifetime of the last Government.  More than 100 Garda stations were closed nationwide.  This review is currently being undertaken and is due to report in May.  As I mentioned, there was a commitment in the programme for Government that six Garda stations would be opened on a pilot scheme basis.  Recent media reports have suggested that the Minister, Deputy Shane Ross, has already secured the reopening of the Stepaside Garda station, which is in his own constituency.  According to media reports, he is so confident of this that he already has newsletters ready to be distributed around the constituency.</p> <p>I know that the Minister of State is not the direct line Minister of State but I appeal to her to pass on the message to the Minister for Justice and Equality to include Rush in this pilot scheme.  We do not have a senior Cabinet Minister or any Minister in north County Dublin.  I feel therefore that we are going to get left behind and that south County Dublin will benefit because it has a Minister.  I appeal to the Minister of State on the basis that Rush is a large and growing urban area with a surrounding rural hinterland.  As I said, it is among the fastest-growing areas within the fastest growing constituency and county in Ireland.  Therefore, we really need the reopening of Rush Garda station.  I appeal to the Minister of State to consider Rush Garda station in the pilot scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#C00700"><p>I thank Senator Clifford-Lee for raising this commencement matter.  The T&aacute;naiste unfortunately cannot be here and asked me to reply to the Senator.</p> <p>The Senator will appreciate that the Garda Commissioner is primarily responsible for the effective and efficient use of the resources available to her, including with regard to Garda stations.  As the Senator will be aware, the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na district and station rationalisation programme gave rise to the closure of some 139 Garda stations, including Rush Garda station, in 2012 and 2013, following the completion by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na of a comprehensive review of its district and station network.  The review was undertaken with the objective of identifying opportunities to introduce strategic reforms to enhance service delivery, increase effectiveness and streamline practices within the organisation.  The T&aacute;naiste has been informed by the Garda authorities that the closures have allowed front-line garda&iacute; to be managed and deployed with greater mobility, greater flexibility and in a more focused fashion, particularly with regard to targeted police operations.</p> <p>The programme for Government commits the Government to ensuring a strong and visible police presence throughout the country in order to maintain and strengthen community engagement, provide reassurance to citizens and to deter crime.  A cornerstone of this commitment is the Government plan to achieve an overall Garda workforce of 21,000 personnel by 2021 comprising 15,000 Garda members, 2,000 Reserve members and 4,000 civilians.</p> <p>Revisiting the decisions made to close Garda stations at the depths of the recession is also part of the commitment.  In this context, the T&aacute;naiste has requested the Garda Commissioner, while fully cognisant of her statutory functions, to identify six stations for reopening on a pilot basis to determine possible positive impacts that such openings will have on criminal activity, with special emphasis on burglaries, theft and public order.  The pilot will feed into the wider review being undertaken by the Garda Sioch&aacute;na inspectorate at the request of the Policing Authority of the use of resources available to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na in the delivery of policing services to local communities.  I understand that work is continuing in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to identify the six stations for inclusion in the pilot and that consultations have taken place with relevant stakeholders, including the Policing Authority.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2186"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2186&amp;amp;pid=CatherineByrne&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In this context, I am sure the Senator would agree that a comprehensive and evidence-based analysis should be carried out taking account of all the relevant factors before a final decision is made in respect of the stations to be reopened by the Commissioner.  I also understand that the T&aacute;naiste expects to receive a report from the Commissioner by the end of May in connection with the exercise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#D00200"><p>The redeployment of Garda resources is not being felt in the community.  I can give the Minister of State some real examples at a later stage.  It is really not being felt on the ground and the people of Rush have really felt the impact of not having a Garda station, even as a place to go to get their passport form signed or to get Garda vetting.  Not having a Garda station is very difficult for a community of 10,000 people.  The Minister of State referred to the increase in Garda numbers.  Garda numbers have dropped in the division that covers the area in question.  Fingal is the fastest growing county in Ireland and it is unacceptable that it is seeing a drop in Garda numbers.</p> <p>I understand that the report is being compiled by the Commissioner.  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport has secured the re-opening of Stepaside Garda station and it is a bit unbelievable for everybody else to believe that this is totally independent of Government.  I do not mean to labour the point but we do not have a Minister in north county Dublin and we urgently need the re-opening of Rush Garda station.  I appeal to the Minister of State to include it in the pilot scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#D00300"><p>The Senator made a very strong case.  Does the Minister of State have anything she wishes to add?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#D00400"><p>If the Senator wants to send me information relating to a Garda presence and the redeployment of garda&iacute; in the area to me, I will certainly raise it with the T&aacute;naiste.  I cannot comment on other Ministers having decided that Garda stations will be in the area because I am not assured of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#D00500"><p>The Minister of State is wise on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#D00600"><p>It probably will but I cannot comment on that.  I believe the Senator has raised a very significant point.  I have taken details of the points she raised and will bring them back to the T&aacute;naiste.  If the Senator sends me some of the data relating to crime, I will give them to the T&aacute;naiste.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.33" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#D00700">Schools Building Projects Status</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#D00800"><p>I wish to raise the status of the building project at Ballinspittle national school, which is a small school in a nice village in south County Cork.  The school has seen significant development, as has the village of Ballinspittle, over recent years.  The school was put on the six-year capital building programme in November 2015, which was a very positive step for Ballinspittle and the entire community.  In the original proposal, it was supposed to go to construction in 2017.  This is one of the key issues we are fighting for this morning.  We want to see this school progressing and we need the project to go to construction in 2017.  For the 2017 commitment to be met, it must go through detailed design, planning and tendering this year.  It is now March, time is ticking and the need for the school is very important.  The site is available.  There are at least three and a half acres around the school so there is no issue with the site itself.  Numbers in the school have increased.  By 2018, 230 pupils will be going to this school.  There are two autism spectrum disorder, ASD, classrooms that are a very important part of the school and its ethos.</p> <p>One of the key issues with the school building is that it is maximised at every level, be it a store room, the general purpose, GP room, the community hall or the hall itself.  The GP room is divided in two so there are two resource teachers in that room.  As the GP room is taken up with resource teachers, there is no drama or PE in the school.  A total of 19 children need sensory space, sensory time and sensory breaks, which are very important.  The only way they can get them is to get them in the hallway, which is not appropriate.  It is a big issue for the community, the principal and the parents of children in the school.  It is a thriving community that will do its utmost for its children.  It needs this project to be moved forward.  It is in the building programme but time is ticking.  It will need another teacher for the academic year starting in 2018.  There is no room at the moment for that teacher.  If the store room and GP room are being used and if there are children who need to use the hallway for sensory time, there is no capacity at any level to take another teacher in September 2018 so we need this project to be moved forward at pace.</p> <p>We need a site visit, the project to be progressed and the detailed design, tendering and planning to be done.  We need to get somebody on site in order that in the next year and a bit, this school will be completed.  In many ways, Ballinspittle national school is like many schools that need upgrades in a very short period because the community has grown rapidly.  The special needs aspect is probably the heartbreaking part.  We need to move urgently and the matter needs to be prioritised.  I realise that the Minister of State is not directly involved but she could give some hope to the community that this project will be progressed in the short term and completed by September 2018 because these are the very strict and tight deadlines that the community is unfortunately under.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#D00900"><p>I am taking this matter on behalf of the Minister for Education and Skills who is unavailable.  I thank the Senator for raising this matter as it provides me with the opportunity to clarify the Department's position regarding the provision of a major building project for Ballinspittle national school in County Cork.  The Senator will be aware of the demographic challenge facing the education system in the coming years, including in the Cork area.  In that regard, the six-year construction programme aims to prioritise new building projects and major extensions, including special schools, in areas where demographic need has been established.  In addition, the capital programme also provides for devolved funding for additional classrooms for schools, including special schools, where an immediate accommodation requirement has been identified.  In that regard, it is open to schools to apply for funding for additional classroom accommodation where required.</p> <p>The Senator will be aware that Ballinspittle national school is a co-educational Catholic ethos primary school catering for boys and girls from junior infants to sixth class.  In recent years, Ballinspittle national school has experienced significant growth in enrolments of almost 50%, with pupil numbers increasing from 145 pupils in 2010 to 214 pupils in 2016.  As a result, it requires a major extension to the existing school to meet current and anticipated future demand for school places.  In light of this increase in enrolments, it was agreed with the school that it would be allowed to grow from an eight-classroom to a 12-classroom school.  In addition, the Department has been in regular contact with the National Council for Special Education in respect of special education requirements in the Cork area, and provision will he made in the project brief for Ballinspittle national school for a three-class ASD unit.</p> <p>The Department is aware of the specific accommodation needs of the school, and in that regard, the building project for Ballinspittle national school is included in the Department's six-year construction programme.  In the context of progressing this project, the Department is undertaking an analysis of the school's architectural plans in advance of a technical site visit.  The Department will also be contacting the school shortly with a view to scheduling a date for the technical site visit after Easter.  I thank the Senator for raising this matter and confirm the Department's commitment to progressing the building project in the case of Ballinspittle national school.  I recently spoke to officials from the Department who are fully aware of the need to increase classroom space.  However, until the scheduled technical site visit takes place after Easter, they cannot provide any specific dates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#E00100"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response.  The key issue is the technical site visit which needs to be made as soon as possible.  We need to get the people on the ground to work out exactly what is required and where we can actually go.  As Easter is only a few weeks away, I hope that will happen in the next month.  If the technical site visit can be made, we can progress.  Perhaps the Minister of State might correspond with me on when exactly the site visit will be made.  Getting a date is very important for us.  If we can get one, we can reassure the community that progress is being made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#E00200"><p>I will speak to the Minister and ask him to correspond as soon as possible with the Senator on a date for the site visit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#E00300"><p>It might be appropriate for the Senator to also raise the matter at a parliamentary party meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.39" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.15 a.m. and resumed at 11.35 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.40" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Adoption (Information and Tracing) Bill 2016 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 12.45 p.m. and adjourn not later than 2.45 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes each and those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes each; No. 2, Sea-Fisheries (Amendment) Bill 2017 - Committee Stage, to be taken at 2.45 p.m. and to adjourn not later than 4.15 p.m., if not previously concluded; No. 3, Pensions (Equal Pension Treatment in Occupational Benefit Scheme) (Amendment) Bill 2016 &ndash; Second Stage, to be taken at 4.15 p.m. with the time allocated for this debate not to exceed two hours; and No. 4, statements on the report of the Joint Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform, and Taoiseach entitled, Report on the Rising Costs of Motor Insurance and the cost of insurance working group's report on the cost of motor insurance, to be taken at 6.15 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes each and the contributions of other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#G00300"><p>I rise to acknowledge the 60th anniversary of the Treaties of Rome.  The anniversary falls in a moment that is particularly complex in light of the internal and external challenges that face the European Union.</p> <p>The economic and social benefits generated by the membership of the EU have been incalculable for Ireland.  All we have to do is look at the visible investment that the EU has put into our roads network, the opportunities presented to small and medium-sized businesses in Ireland to access European markets, the explosion of European tourism due to low-cost travel and the common currency, the ease of mobility for our citizens to study and work across Europe and the list goes on.  We also cannot forget the fact that for the past 60 years there has been peace in Europe and that the concept and reality of war has been unknown for more than three generations.  For the past decade, however, the mood in Europe has changed with some countries feeling that the European Union has fallen below their expectations.  This has materialised in a Brexit referendum in the UK and next week, the British Prime Minister will trigger Article 50 in a planned exit from the European Union.</p> <p>The challenges that face the EU include globalisation, the technology revolution, the recent global economic crisis and the biggest political crisis, which has been generated by the vast migratory flows of people from neighbouring countries.  Millions of people have abandoned their countries of origin and fled to Europe to escape oppressive regimes, grave political strains, climate disasters and poor economic prospects.  They seek a brighter future in Europe.  Unfortunately, the inward migratory flow has engendered fear in many Europeans and been one of the main stimuli in the Brexit campaign.  I believe such a reaction was wrong and this is a view shared by many of my colleagues in this Chamber.  The real reason for the fear is a lack of knowledge and I believe that fear to be unwarranted.  </p> <p>As we all know, Europe is changing.  Ultimately the benefits of our EU membership massively outweigh any perceived concerns.  I look forward to participating in the Brexit debate in the Seanad Chamber and, over the course of the programme, examining the White Paper that has been prepared by the EU on the future of Europe.  I also look forward to debating our membership of the EU and how we can play an active role as a committed member.  </p> <p>The second issue that I wish to raise is legal aid.  The legal aid system in Ireland is known as free legal aid but in fact is not free because there is a small fee, starting at &euro;130, for those in receipt of standard social welfare payments.  Many women, especially those in violent situations, stay in their homes and do not seek the protection of the courts due to the fee being too high for anyone surviving on a low income.  </p> <p>The T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality attended a conference in Geneva the week after we passed domestic violence legislation.  One recommendation made at the conference was to grant an automatic waiver to anyone who finds himself or herself in a domestic violence situation.  I call on the T&aacute;naiste to initiate such a waiver programme, as it would allow women in domestic violence situations to seek the protection of the courts.  A waiver would remove a cost that acts as a barrier.  I ask the T&aacute;naiste to urgently implement the waiver as it will assist people in domestic violence situations. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#G00400"><p>Yesterday I advised that I might discuss issues relating to the Defence Forces here.  Thanks to the kindness of the Leader in offering a debate with the Minister of State responsible, I shall defer my comments until the Minister of State is here.</p> <p>Later on today we will discuss the insurance industry.  An issue that is of particular interest to anybody sitting in this House is the impact an accident may have on a county councillor who performs his or her duties.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Members will recall that some time ago in County Donegal first responders had their insurance cover loaded with additional costs.  We all know county councillors who drive hundreds of miles across their constituencies.  If they were to be involved in an accident while on council business, would they be covered?  I have not been able to get a definitive answer to this question.  Furthermore, if they were to be involved in an accident and injured in some way-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H00200"><p>I remind the Senator that there will be a debate on the subject of motor insurance later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H00300"><p>I understand that, but we will not be discussing this specific issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H00400"><p>I am saying it in the interests of avoiding repetition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H00500"><p>The other question is that if they were to suffer a personal injury, would they be covered?  This is something that is particularly-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H00600"><p>The Senator would be quite entitled to raise that issue during the debate on motor insurance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H00700"><p>The debate will be more general, but-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H00800"><p>No, I can assure the Senator that the Chair will allow him to raise the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H00900"><p>Thank you.</p> <p>I wish to make one final point on the issue of free legal aid.  I received a telephone call this morning to advise me that a person had been buried in a gold-plated coffin with a Rolex watch.  His partner is now looking for free legal aid, having been caught engaging in criminal activity.  Where are we going?  I fully appreciate the necessity to provide free legal aid for those who need it, but I would welcome a debate on the issue and whether the scheme is being abused.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H01000"><p>I send a message of solidarity to the families of Dara Fitzpatrick, Paul Ormbsby, Mark Duffy and Ciar&aacute;n Smith to let them know that they are in our thoughts and prayers.  I also commend the ongoing rescue effort off the coast in Blacksod Bay which is now entering its tenth day.  As each day passes, the stress on the families, as well as members of the Irish Coast Guard, the Naval Service, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, the RNLI, the Air Corps, the Commissioners of Irish Lights and other agencies, increases.  The massive collective effort is testament to their courage and professionalism.  I also thank local fishermen and the local community for all they are doing on a daily basis to help the families and assist in the efforts to recover the crew of R116.  I particularly thank commander of the <i>L&Eacute; Eithne, </i>Brian Fitzgerald, for his hospitality and all he and his crew are doing to enable the missing crew members of R116 to be reunited with their families.  I wish them well in their search again today.</p><p>My party colleague, Deputy Martin Ferris, asked by way of a parliamentary question, for a simple statutory instrument to be enacted by the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, to place the Irish Coast Guard which is leading the search on a statutory footing.  In his reply to the question the Minister states he is happy with the current legislative arrangements and that he sees no need for extra measures.  In that context, I ask the Minister if he has listened to the members of the Irish Coast Guard.  Has he heard the concerns they have voiced about helicopter provision and the security of sites around the country?  Is he aware of the need for the Irish Coast Guard facility in Belmullet to be upgraded?  I ask that he be invited back to the House, in the light of the recent tragedy, to discuss the urgency attached to dealing with all of these issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H01100"><p>It came to my attention approximately two weeks ago that Dublin Institute of Technology, DIT, intended to have all of its access programme students Garda vetted.  The programme aims to provide second-chance education, often for students from poor socio-economic backgrounds.  What is happening is alarming and discriminatory.  Dublin Institute of Technology is singling out a cohort of students and determining, for some reason, that they need to be Garda vetted.  I wrote to the president of the institute, Professor Brian Norton, whose response was unsatisfactory.  He admits that, in terms of the blanket collection of data, only 10% of the students will undertake restricted access courses.  They will be Garda vetted when they start their degree programmes.  Will the Leader invite the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Dara Murphy, who has responsibility for data protection to come to the House to discuss the issue because I believe Dublin Institute of Technology is in breach of data protection laws.  In the response I have received from Professor Norton he admits that the information is being collected on the basis that it "might" be relevant for a percentage of students in the future if they choose to continue their studies in the institute.  Under sections 2A and 2B of the Data Protection Act, sensitive personal data may only be collected where it is necessary for a particular purpose.  It is clear that Garda vetting in gaining access to education is not necessary for a particular purpose.  I have written to the Data Protection Commissioner to request that his office look into the matter.  I have also written to the Irish Human Rights and Equality Commission about it.  However, the Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy Richard Bruton, and the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Dara Murphy, both have a role to play, particularly given the promises made by the former to increase access to education for those from poorer socioeconomic backgrounds.  This measure is counterproductive in the context of the work the Minister is trying to do in this regard.  If I were telling the House that a group of Travellers or non-nationals had been singled out for Garda vetting, Members would be saying it was racist and discriminatory.  However, because this involves class discrimination, the matter is not receiving the attention it deserves.  It merits a conversation.  We should request that Dublin Institute of Technology reverse this decision and stop blocking young people from entering education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#H01200"><p>There is a real need to invite the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Denis Naughten, to come to the House to discuss what is happening in RTE.  I know that a briefing is to take place today and understand we could see up to 300 job losses at the State broadcaster.  Questions must be asked about the sustainability of the organisation and the investment needed.  I become very concerned when I hear of job losses of that level.  One must worry about the structures of the organisation in the context of the director general's remarks to the effect that the losses incurred last year were the result of the "unforeseen" general election.  It is my understanding general elections take place every five years.  The fact that Ms Forbes said the general election in 2016 was unforeseen leads one to question her capability.  We must also examine salary levels in RTE.  Approximately &euro;2.6 million is being spent on the top ten earners and we must ask if the money could be better spent.</p> <p>The Minister must also come to the House to discuss the issue in the context of the housing crisis, particularly in Dublin.  We cannot operate in silos.  The land at Montrose is State-owned.  There is talk of building 500 housing units on the 8.5 acres of land RTE is proposing to sell, but only 10% would be social housing units.  The State broadcaster certainly needs further investment, but the city also needs housing units.  We need social and affordable housing units, as well as affordable rental units.  On lands owned by Dublin City Council there is a 50:50 carve up, with 50% being market units and the other 50% split between social and affordable housing units and affordable rental units on a ratio of 3:2.  We need to look at a similar model for the site at Montrose.  We cannot have the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government operating in one silo and the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment operating in another.  We need an additional housing supply across the spectrum in Dublin city.  The Minister must come into the House to discuss the future sustainability of RTE and how it is financed, as well as the sale of State lands and how they should be used for the betterment of society in general.  The proceeds should not just be reinvested in the structures of RTE.  </p> <p>Concern has been expressed about the high avoidance rate of the television licence fee, which stands at over 13%.  Questions must be asked about An Post and whether it is actually doing its job in collecting licence fee income.  Will the Leader invite the Minister to come to the House as a matter of urgency to discuss all of these issues?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00100"><p>Yesterday in the Seanad I raised the issue of Indaver and the decision of An Bord Plean&aacute;la to adjourn its decision on Indaver, the toxic incinerator proposed for Cork Harbour.  It has now been adjourned four times.  I read today in the newspapers that it has been adjourned due to an issue or a query regarding the suitability of this site due to possible impact on the use of Haulbowline naval base by the Air Corps.  An Bord Plean&aacute;la said that it has looked for clarification because there is an issue regarding the aviation capabilities of helicopters landing in the site in Haulbowline if this incinerator is built.  If that is the reason we have seen it postponed for a fourth time, An Bord Plean&aacute;la should do the right thing and refuse this issue.  It is a very serious issue that there is a doubt over the safety of helicopters landing at the navy base in Haulbowline.  If there is any doubt over this, the project should be refused.  This information was not available yesterday.  It has been made available today.  Indaver is proposing to put an incinerator right on the edge of Cork Harbour.  The people in Haulbowline itself, their committed view and their experience tells us that it could be an issue regarding aviation safety.  That is an issue that Indaver needs to move on, a decision that An Bord Plean&aacute;la should not defer but should refuse straight away.</p> <p>This information was considered before the Rescue 116 tragedy in Mayo.  The tragedy in Mayo compounds the need to look at this situation again.  </p> <p>I hope that on the 15 May An Bord Plean&aacute;la will do what they should have done, which is to refuse this planning application.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00200"><p>On behalf of myself and Senator Conway-Walsh I would like to welcome pupils and parents from Corclough national school in Belmullet here today.</p> <p>Today we read in the newspapers that Ireland tops the list internationally for people drinking alcohol at home prior to going to the pub, with 85 % of people engaging in this practice.  Considering that one in three hospital admissions is a direct result of alcohol consumption, can I ask the Leader when is it proposed that the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill will come back to this House?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00300"><p>I wish to highlight that SIPTU is holding a protest at lunchtime today in regard to workers from the community sector.  It is a sector that is in crisis in terms of funding and job losses.  I would ask people from across the Chamber to come out and support our colleagues in SIPTU today.</p> <p>I wish to raise the issue of income equality and perhaps ask for the Minister for Finance to come to the House to debate this issue.  The ICTU has produced a wonderful document called "Because We Are Worth It".  It details the pay of top CEOs in our public companies.  Some of the figures are quite startling.  With the Cathaoirleach's permission, I will read out some of the figures.  The pay of the CEO of Grafton has gone up by a staggering 373 % in the past six years.  The CEO of C&amp;C has had an increase of 238 % over the same period, while Glanbia's CEO received an increase of 222 %.  The CEO of Ryanair received an increase of 203 %.  These are salaries in the region of &euro;1.8 million to &euro;2.4 million to &euro;3.7 million.  This is absolutely shocking.  It is telling when Dan O'Brien, an economist very much on the right, has called for this report to be read and acted on-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00500"><p>----- and in this report is a call to tax the wealth in this country that needs to be taxed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00600"><p>And we complain about Enda Kenny's money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00700"><p>Do not disrupt the Senator.  He is in good flow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00800"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach.  A TASC report, based on Government figures, shows that 10 % of the population now own 54 % of the wealth in this country, up from 44 %.  We have a crisis in income inequality.  It is something that we do not talk about enough.  These figures are scandalous.  They contrast with the ten cent increase in the minimum wage this year.  We need to have a debate about this.  Ultimately, it is an issue for Government policy in terms of how we redistribute and tax wealth.  I ask the Minister for Finance to come in and have a debate on that topic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J00900"><p>I want to raise the issue of the refugees coming to our town, Ballaghaderreen, yesterday.  More than 70 people travelled from Balseskin down to the emergency reception and orientation centre in Ballaghaderreen yesterday.  There was a hugely warm welcome for them.  They have been in the country for a number of weeks.  It was a real pleasure to be able to meet those people as they settled in.  The community in Ballaghaderreen intends to play its part.  We intend to support them as best we can.  A friends of the centre group led by a number of local volunteers has been set up.  The community have gifted both an indoor and an outdoor playground to the refugees, along with a lovely welcome wall.  That is very tangible evidence of the community in Ballaghaderreen wanting to support them on an ongoing basis through volunteerism.</p> <p>The most important thing now is that we get the education facilities up and running.  The Galway and Roscommon Education and Training Board has been very proactive in terms of recruitment of staff to support the centre.  There are well over 30 children in the group that came down yesterday.  It is important that primary and secondary education initially will be provided within the centre, along with adult education classes and a preschool.  </p> <p>There have been some difficulties with health funding.  Further funding was made available about two weeks ago.  I will be keeping a very close eye on it.  It is very important that additional health and education services in particular, along with interpretation services, are made available.  It cannot be from existing services because services in the area are already stretched.</p> <p>I want to emphasise the very positive welcome that the Syrian people received yesterday and we continue to want to support them as best we can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J01000"><p>A committee seems to have been established to regularise dress codes in the Oireachtas.  This is ridiculous.  I generally wear a suit out of respect for the dignity of the place.  I am not wearing one today because I have a broken arm.  However, if one looks at the other House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J01100"><p>It is a matter that the D&aacute;il is dealing with.  It has not come before the Seanad Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  It is with the D&aacute;il Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J01200"><p>Yes.  I am just commenting generally on the increasing bureaucracy that is around this place.  Whatever one thinks of Mick Wallace and Richard Boyd Barrett, they are among the most brilliant contributors to the Lower House.  There is a natural self-regulation.  People are not going to come in wearing a bikini.  If they did, they would be censured by the House and they would be expelled.  I remember Cicciolina in the Italian parliament.  There is far too much bureaucracy.  We should remember that we have the dignity and authority of having been elected.</p> <p>When I came in here about 30 years ago it was fairly amateur.  People drifted in and out.  It was very gentlemanly.  I got blamed for pushing it in the direction of a full-time professional job.  Now we have to fob in, but the Ministers who started this do not have to do so.  In an age when work can be done remotely, it is demeaning to be treated like cattle.  It is time we stood up against it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J01300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#J01400"><p>There are the ridiculous restrictions on allowances which were given to us to make up for the fact that we did not take pay rises.  People in the Civil Service who are our direct counterparts acknowledged this and got them streamed into their main pay but we did not.  There was also the abolition of the long service increment.  I do not know of another job in Ireland that does not get a long service increment.  I believe it was illegal to remove that.</p> <p>There is the question of sick notes.  I have just had a fair amount of illness.  Sick notes are averaged.  This comes from the Department of Finance.  It was not a ministerial thing at all.  Some faceless bureaucrat decided that sick notes had to be averaged.  They do not trust the doctors any more to say whether one is sick.  It is absolutely ridiculous.  It is time we stood up and asserted our dignity.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If we do not do our work effectively in Seanad &Eacute;ireann and D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann, the public will kick us out very soon.  We got &euro;311 in wage restitution - oh jolly, gee, wonderful, sucks, boo.  I hope we do not all spend it on the same big bash.  It is less than &euro;1 a day.  People are always criticising the Taoiseach for the amount of money he gets.  Like my colleague, Senator Gavan, I have received a couple of pages listing the earnings of chief executives.  Most of them get multiples of what the Taoiseach is paid.  Regardless of whether we agree with the decisions being made by the Taoiseach, we must accept that he is making them for the entire country.  The executives listed in the document mentioned by Senator Gavan are making decisions for one company.  It is time for us to stand up against the tide of populism by saying that as professionals, we deserve the money we get.  I suggest that the various allowances should be abolished.  We should be given the proper rate for the job so that we do not have to waste time and our secretaries do not have to turn into accountants.  When we send stuff off to the relevant personnel at the Standards in Public Office Commission, they come back to us with little niggly things.  It is utterly demeaning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K00200"><p>I suggest that Standing Orders should be suspended-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K00300"><p>It is time we demanded respect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K00400"><p>-----so that the Senator can be given more time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K00500"><p>He is well over his time already.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K00600"><p>I beg your pardon, a Chathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K00700"><p>If the Senator has issues with the increments, etc., he may consider writing to the commission and I am sure they will be dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K00800"><p>We will send them the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K00900"><p>I suggest that rather than bringing Ministers in, we could get Senator Norris to address the House because he makes a lot of sense, speaks from the heart and tells many home truths.  I fully concur with the sentiments he expressed.</p> <p>I would like to raise a much more mundane local issue that is quite serious.  Will the Leader raise with the relevant Department the fact that Edmonton national school in County Westmeath has been denied works and money under the summer school improvement scheme?  It received a menial amount of money in response to last summer's application.  It needs approximately &euro;40,000 of restoration works.  This is quite serious because teachers and pupils are being inconvenienced.  The toilets have not been upgraded since the school was built in 1965.  This is causing health and safety concerns.  These works should be done immediately.  I would appreciate it if the Leader could raise the case of Edmonton national school in County Westmeath with the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K01000"><p>I support Senator Norris in his suggestion that the body politic has damaged the careers of many politicians in economic terms over the years.  I do not think many of the populist moves that were made necessarily resonated with the public in the way that might have been expected.</p> <p>The World Health Organization, WHO, recently published a list of priority pathogens that are resistant to antibiotics.  The list, which comprises 12 families of bacteria that pose the greatest threat to human health, highlights extremely dangerous bacteria that have built-in abilities to resist treatment.  It is increasingly concerning that these bacteria can pass along genetic material that allow other bacteria to become resistant to drugs as well.  The introduction of penicillin in the 1940s heralded the antibiotic era.  We are now in the era of antibiotic resistance or antimicrobial resistance.  I was shocked to read that, according to a recent review on antimicrobial resistance commissioned by the UK Government, 700,000 people across the world die from antimicrobial resistance-related infections each year.  It is predicted that this death toll will reach 10 million by 2050, which would make antimicrobial resistance the world's largest cause of death, surpassing cancer.  In the case of a woman in the United States that was documented recently, none of the 26 available antibiotics worked on the incurable infection - the superbug - that eventually killed her.  We must address, as a matter of urgency, the fact that antibiotics will one day not work anymore.  A four-year project is currently probing the potential of coatings that might repel and eliminate micro-organisms that come into context with everyday hospital textiles such as bedsheets and gowns.  These antimicrobial coatings could also be used on solid surfaces like walls, floors, beds and tables.  Although this endeavour is not a silver bullet, I believe the HSE should do everything it can to support it, especially when it is investing in new hospitals.  I am calling on the Minister for Health to examine the list produced by the WHO and to allocate funding for research into the development of new antibiotics here in Ireland as a matter of priority.  If the Minister for Health is coming to this House in the near future, I will be very keen to raise this issue with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K01100"><p>T&aacute; m&eacute; tar &eacute;is ceisteanna a ard&uacute; maidir leis na h&uacute;dar&aacute;is &aacute;iti&uacute;la agus an cine&aacute;l maoirsi&uacute; a dh&eacute;antar orthu &oacute; thaobh na Roinne de.  I would like to raise the way the Department of Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government oversees local authorities.  Since we debated the Putting People First strategy, which proposed to give extensive new powers to the CEOs of local authorities, it has come to my attention that there are irregularities in Galway City Council regarding the income from parking meters.  I have been informed that the discrepancy could be to the tune of a couple of hundred thousand euro.  I am concerned that even though this was apparently brought to the attention of senior management in Galway City Council over three years ago, we did not find out about it until now.  Why has the whole thing been kept a secret?  I have also been told that all the machines in Galway are out of action, which means badly needed money is being lost to Galway City Council.  People constantly come to my office to say they have issues with housing and estate maintenance, etc., but when I contact Galway City Council, I am told no money is available for such matters.  The broader question of the level of oversight of local authorities that is in place within the Department of Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government arises in this context.  Is there is a flagging system that ensures the Minister and the Department, as the overseeing body through which the Government provides funding, are told when things like this are happening?  Is a criminal investigation pending in this scenario?  My understanding is that it involves a new parking system which was put in place a couple of years ago.  I think it is worth raising these issues with the Minister.  Perhaps that can be done in the context of the review of the implementation of the Putting People First strategy.</p> <p>I thank those who were able to attend the presentation on the International Protection Act 2015, which took place in the audiovisual room yesterday.  We were told that there are serious implementation issues with the 2015 Act.  Many speakers at the presentation said there are huge problems with the provision of legal support services to people who are applying for asylum as a result of the introduction of a complicated new 30-page questionnaire.  We were told that Google Translate has been used to translate the questionnaire in a manner that is nonsensical to native speakers of the various languages involved.  It appears that the only aspects of the McMahon report that are being implemented are the prosecutorial elements.  It seems that the positive elements of the report setting out the changes people need are not being implemented.  We need an urgent debate on this matter because these current issues need to be addressed quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K01200"><p>The Citizens Information Board's proposal to reorganise the Money Advice &amp;amp; Budgeting Service, MABS, at eight regional centres across the State is causing a great deal of concern.  As the Leader is probably aware, there are 51 MABS outlets throughout the country.  As everybody in this Chamber knows, MABS provides a great service to people who find themselves in financial difficulties such as mortgage arrears or debts of various kinds.  The local MABS offices constitute a vital link between the local community and the main MABS office.  If this proposal is to proceed - we certainly hope it does not - that link would be destroyed, which would be an awful pity.  Staff members are in limbo and are facing uncertainty because they do not know what the future holds for them.  I suggest that the proposed reconfiguration of MABS would be yet another attack on rural Ireland.  No part of the country would be more affected than rural Ireland by this negative proposal.  I plead with the Leader to ask the relevant Minister to ensure this proposal does not go ahead.  If it goes ahead, it will be an attack on rural Ireland and the individuals who live in rural Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#K01300"><p>I understand that when the Minister, Deputy Harris, announces his eight-point plan today, he will propose to scrap the HSE and start all over again.  I welcome this news because I think we could go back to the old health boards.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maria Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2465"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2465&amp;amp;pid=MariaByrne&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is his intention to scrap the HSE and devolve the powers to local hospital groups and community groups.  When we had the old health boards, there was a lot of accountability and people had local knowledge.  Currently, the way the HSE is run is that it is a centrally based committee that is not working, because people do not know the actual issues in the hospitals in the local areas.  I sat on one of those health committees for about a year when I was on the council.  There was accountability.  One could ask a question in advance and receive an answer that one could not question.  There is a lot of reform needed in this area.  The Minister is proposing to set up a much leaner national health agency.  I know that he has a number of points in the plan.  I think that having local groups responsible for their local hospitals and in return being responsible to a smaller and leaner committee will be the way for the future.  I know that will be a long-term plan.  The Minister is also proposing some changes to be brought to legislation as well to have more local accountability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L00200"><p>I know the matter has already been raised by my colleague, Senator Ruane, but I am extremely disappointed, to put it mildly, and quite upset about the decision of the Dublin Institute of Technology with regard to Garda clearance for students who are on access programmes.  Having said that, I have great regard for the institute.  I was a student of it nocturnally many years ago.  It has given a kick-start and an opportunity to so many people who otherwise would not have had it.  It is important to say that also.  I have had many years' experience working with disabled people and people with mental health needs in trying to get them started or back on the road to education and training.  That one needs to have a Garda clearance to go on these programmes is to start off with a stigma.  It is saying to people that they are different.  God knows a lot of them feel that enough already.</p> <p>There is also another issue which is that some of the students on these programmes are international students.  Are we going to need Garda clearance for people who are coming from the United Arab Emirates, Oman, Saudi Arabia, China, Brazil or wherever?  It is madness.  All of these students are interviewed before they come on these programmes.  Therefore, there are ways to tease out suitability and I am not talking about any particular backgrounds that they may have.  There needs to be an immediate halt to this approach and a rethink.  No other students in that institution or in any other third level institution are routinely Garda vetted before they commence.  It runs counter to the whole ethos of access.  It is wonderful to see students with disabilities and with a whole range of backgrounds getting a chance to let their wings fly and move.  We must value that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="Gerry Horkan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L00300"><p>I have a relatively brief point.  I ask the Leader to raise, with the Minister for Health, I presume, the issue of the disabled drivers' medical board of appeal.  If a person applies for disabled driver status and it is not granted automatically, there is an appeal mechanism in place.  I have a letter here from the secretary to the disabled drivers' medical board of appeal thanking me for my letter supporting somebody's appeal.  The person is appealing the process for not getting the status under the disabled drivers and disabled passengers tax concession scheme of 1994.  The response said that there are a large number of appellants on the waiting list and the waiting time is in the order of seven months.  Regardless of whether a person wins the appeal, I think "outrageous" is a reasonable word to use in terms of this wait for disabled drivers.</p> <p>The people applying for it are not doing so frivolously and genuinely believe they are entitled to it.  Under the regulations, perhaps some of them are not.  Regardless of whether they are, they should know within a period much shorter than seven months.  I am sure that Senator Dolan knows an awful lot more about this than I do, but I believe that seven months for any appeal process is wrong.  I would like the Minister for Health, or whoever the responsible Minister is, to come before the House, tackle the issue and point out to us how he is going to deal with it and reduce that seven months to a more appropriate period of a couple of weeks or whatever it should be.  If people are going to be granted the status and miss out on seven months, their quality of life is seriously affected.  If they are not going to get it, they should at least know that and not have to wait seven months for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L00400"><p>Before I call Senator Burke, I acknowledge the presence of two councillors, Tommy Cullen and Tom Fortune, and their respective partners to the House.  They are more than welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L00500"><p>On a good news point, it is interesting that the World Economic Forum now puts Ireland in the top seven countries for strongest democracies.  We are joint sixth with Canada after Norway, Iceland, Sweden, New Zealand and Denmark.  It is a credit to the political system in Ireland that we are now regarded as the joint seventh strongest democracy.</p> <p>Talking about democracy, my colleague, Senator Byrne, raised the issue of the HSE.  I have pulled figures from the HSE on what has occurred.  The Minister has announced an eight-point plan for slimming it down.  I have raised this point before, but I must say that the number of people employed in management and administration over the past two years has increased by the total sum of 1,789.  More than 700 of those have been in senior management.  For instance, the number of directors has gone from 201 to 272.  That is an increase of 71 directors, who are at the top end.  That is an increase of 35%.  The number of senior managers has gone up by 20.22%, which is an increase of 195 people.  We are now talking about slimming it down.  The HSE seems to be a juggernaut going down the road with no one in control.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L00600"><p>Who is in charge?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L00700"><p>I am really concerned about this matter.  I believe that if we are talking about an eight-point plan, we should have a debate in the House as regards how we restructure the HSE.  Someone should say to stop this juggernaut at this stage before we end up with 19,000 people.  We had 15,000 people in administration and management in December 2014.  We now have 16,901.  At the rate we are going, by the end of this year we will have more than 18,000.  I believe we need to have a serious debate on this issue when, in the same two-year period, an extra 39 public health nurses were employed, from 1,460 to 1,499.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L00800"><p>The Senator has made his point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L00900"><p>We need a serious debate on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01000"><p>At the beginning, I apologise to the House as I must make an amendment to the Order of Business.  The Minister, Deputy Zappone, has had to defer the Adoption (Information and Tracing) Bill 2016 today for a personal reason which I will explain later to Members.  I move to withdraw No. 1 and take the other items on the Order of Business as outlined.  We will suspend at the end of the Order of Business.  I apologise to Members-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01100"><p>Until when?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01200"><p>Until 2.45 p.m.  I will explain to Members later.  This has just come to me now.  My apologies for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01300"><p>On a point of order, is it not possible to take the other items immediately after the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01400"><p>No, on the basis of ministerial commitments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01500"><p>I understand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01600"><p>I thank the 18 Senators that have-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01700"><p>There seem to be very valid reasons the Minister, Deputy Zappone, cannot take that item today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01800"><p>I am not challenging that at all.  I completely understand and accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#L01900"><p>Senator Ardagh raised the very important and topical issue of the anniversary of the Treaties of Rome.  The summit in Rome this week is a very important one.  The Senator is correct and I hope we will have a debate on the future of the European Union, not just within the Brexit Seanad committee, but as a House.  Senator Ardagh is correct to raise the point that there is a mood change within Europe.  We need to reflect upon that and the many issues she raised.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The White Paper on the future of the European Union, along with the achievements of the past, offer an opportunity for us to reflect on what membership of the European Union means and what direction the Union should take.  The communiqu&eacute; regarding the White Paper raises the point of what future we want for ourselves, our children and the European Union.  In that context, given the triggering of Article 50 on 29 March next it is important that we continue to prioritise our position following Brexit in terms of trade, the economy, the peace process, the common travel area and our future within the European Union.  The summit in April will be important and I hope we will all wear the green jersey on that occasion.<br/><br/>The issue of insurance raised by Senator Craughwell will be discussed tonight.  Both Senator Ardagh and Senator Craughwell raised free legal aid.  I will be happy to invite the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality to the House to discuss that.<br/><br/>We join Senator Conway-Walsh in offering our compliments and thanks in respect of the community and voluntary effort being undertaken in Mayo.  It is a very difficult time for everybody involved and especially for the families.  We continue to pray that the three missing crew of helicopter R116 will be found and brought back to their families.  I join the Senator in commending Commander Brian Fitzgerald and the crew of <i>LE Eithne</i>on the work they are doing.  I am also happy to invite the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, to the House to discuss the issue the Senator raised regarding the statutory instrument and the Coast Guard.<br/><br/>Senators Ruane and Dolan raised the Garda vetting for students on DIT's Access programme.  I am not familiar with the situation.  It might be more appropriate to raise it as a Commencement matter.  The matters the two Senators raised are important because, as Senator Dolan noted, the Access programme has worked well.  It does not sit well that we are introducing vetting for some people and not for others.  The Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, was in the House earlier to discuss Garda vetting.  All of us wish to have proper vetting, protection of data and not to have people labelled or have a stigma attached to them.  We also acknowledge the importance of, and need for, Garda vetting but there must be flexibility in how it operates.  I cannot answer the Senators on the issue they raise but they should pursue it.  They will have the support of the House on the matter.  I can invite the Minister of State, Deputy Dara Murphy, to the House to discuss data protection in general.<br/><br/>Senator Humphreys raised the sale of RTE land valued at approximately &euro;75 million.  I agree with the Senator that the sale of State land should be carried out, because it is an asset.  However, where the proceeds go is a matter for discussion because it is a matter of public policy.  I understand from radio commentary and from the remarks of the director general who appeared before the Oireachtas committee recently that there is a need to return RTE to financial viability.  I also believe that we must have a public service broadcaster.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M00200"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M00300"><p>We can argue about its quality or lack of quality.  Yes, it is popular to knock the salaries of high earners - Senator Norris did a good job defending us here today - and it is necessary to examine how and what one pays people but we must have a public broadcaster that is independent and can produce not just news, sports and current affairs programming but also drama and coverage of arts, culture and all levels of Irish life.  We should congratulate RTE because it provides a good service in many areas, even if we might not agree with its editorial policy at times.  Senator Humphreys is correct that collection of the licence fee could be improved.  He said that 13% of it is not collected-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M00400"><p>It amounts to &euro;25 million per year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M00500"><p>That must be examined.  We all grew up watching the TV sponger advertisements on the television and the threat of the van outside one's door.  I remember those advertisements well.  It is an issue we must consider.  I agree that we should invite the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Naughten, to the House to discuss the matter.</p> <p>Senator Lombard raised incineration and the Indaver application.  During the oral hearing last year the Air Corps made a presentation on the flight path to Haulbowline and the location of this incinerator.  There is a huge need to allay the safety concerns that were expressed at that hearing.  In addition, if there is any doubt regarding the safety of Air Corps personnel or of any aircraft flying overhead, the application should be refused.  I hope An Bord Plean&aacute;la, which is diligent in its assessment of the information, will reject the application.</p> <p>To reply to Senator Swanick, I do not have a date for the sale of alcohol Bill.  My most recent information is that it is with the Office of the Attorney General where it is undergoing scrutiny.  However, I will refer back to the Senator on it.</p> <p>Senator Gavan spoke about ICTU and income inequality.  I accept that we need income equality and that we must raise people out of poverty.  However, 140,000 taxpayers are paying more than 45% of the income tax and USC yield.  That is &euro;9 billion in cash and 18% of all tax collected.  The top ten corporate taxpayers are paying &euro;3 billion.  As a nation, we are reliant on &euro;1 out of every &euro;4 collected in taxes.  I remind the Senator that the last Government and this Government increased the minimum wage and took many people out of the universal social charge net.  Now, people earning up &euro;13,000 are paying no universal social charge, a third of earners are paying no income tax and 30% are paying no income tax or universal social charge.  The most recent CSO figures show that annual disposable income increased by 6.2% in 2015 and that income is being more equally distributed in the country.  Finally, 920,700 people are exempt from paying income tax.  That includes the unemployed and pensioners.  The question we should debate, which some members of the Senator's party oppose, is how we can increase the tax base whereby we can pay for services. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M00600"><p>We are not opposed to that at all.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M00700"><p>The Senator's party is for high spending and high taxes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M00800"><p>Bring on the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M00900"><p>-----but it cannot live in that utopian bubble all the time.  One must live in the reality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01000"><p>You starve public services instead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01100"><p>Senators should address the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01200"><p>The Senator should read Cliff Taylor's article in <i>The Irish Times </i>and other commentary on our dependence on foreign direct investment.  If the Senator had his way, there would be no Apple in Cork, no manufacturing in the country-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01300"><p>That is nonsense.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01400"><p>-----and no pharmaceutical companies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01500"><p>That is not the point I was making.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01600"><p>The Senator cannot have it both ways.</p> <p>I join Senator Hopkins in welcoming new members to the community in Ballaghaderreen.  I thank the local people for the welcome they have afforded the new residents.  I agree with Senator Hopkins that the education piece must be put in place by the Roscommon and Galway ETB.  I will be happy to talk to the Minister about that.</p> <p>Senator Norris raised a number of issues in his fine contribution.  A dress code is not a matter for the Order of Business.  I disagree with the Senator on that as I believe we should have a dress code.  These are the Houses of Parliament and we are the people's representatives so we should be dressed accordingly.  I accept that people can make their contributions regardless of what way they dress, but a dress code would be fitting for the decorum of the House.  I agree wholeheartedly with the Senator on the pay and conditions of Members of all political persuasions.  There is a race to the bottom and populism in terms of cutting pay, not having a long service increment and having to fob in.  The Senator is correct about the new dispensation or new politics in the Lower House.  Given that the Members do not vote on Tuesdays or Wednesdays there is, perhaps, no need for a Member to be present.  I hope the Committee on Procedure and Privileges will examine this.  It is ridiculous that we must fob in every day we are here-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01700"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#M01800"><p>-----and I make no apology for saying that.  I have no difficulty with being here.  I had the highest voting record in the D&aacute;il in the last Oireachtas, but it counts for nothing in the overall scheme of things.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Our job is not just about being in Dublin, in Parliament, in the Chamber or committees, but about other parts of our work.  I know that some Senators claim we do not have a constituency, but I am sure for any Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N00200"><p>It is a potential constituency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N00300"><p>-----with the exception of the six university Senators, if we were to adopt the policy that we have no constituency, it would be a different story.  It is a point at which we need to look on a wider scale, given that we are Members of the Oireachtas and take our role seriously.  There is a multifaceted approach to our job; as such, it is ridiculous that members have to use a fob  I have said enough, but I agree with Senator David Norris.</p> <p>Senator Catherine Noone raised an important point about the World Health Organization on the issue of antibiotic resistance.  I will be happy for the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, to come to the House to discuss it.  </p> <p>I did not catch the name of the school mentioned by Senator Aidan Davitt in the context of the summer building programme.  He might raise the matter in the Commencement debate or e-mail me about it.  </p> <p>If I understood him correctly, Senator Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh referred to the oversight of local authorities.  It is an important matter.  I will be happy for the relevant Minister to come to the House to discuss it.  </p> <p>On the International Protection Act and the McMahon report on direct provision, the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy David Stanton, is working on the implementation of the report.  I was in a direct provision centre recently.  We need to do a lot more to improve the quality of life of people living in such centres.  We share a common approach to immigration, the way people are treated and in which applications are processed.  I will be happy for the Minister of State to come to the House to discuss the matter.</p> <p>Senator Robbie Gallagher raised an important issue in the context of MABS.  There was a committee hearing on the matter recently.  It is a worry because MABS provides a huge service in communities and any dilution of the service, forcing people to travel further, would be regressive.  I will be happy to have the relevant Minister come to the House to discuss the matter.  </p> <p>Senators Maria Byrne and Colm Burke referred to the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris, being before the Committee on the Future of Healthcare to discuss the eight point plan on the future of the HSE.  We all recognise the need for change and reform of the HSE.  In response to Senator Paul Gavan's prompting of Senator Colm Burke, the Minister is in charge and doing a job.  The HSE has been given the biggest Vote in the history of the State this year for the provision of health care facilities and services, but there is a need for accountability.  There is a need to have a management structure to get results for patients and staff.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N00400"><p>It has taken six years to recognise that the HSE has to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N00500"><p>In the recent Assembly elections I canvassed in the North and health was an issue for the people I met on the doorstep.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N00600"><p>I accept that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N00700"><p>I do not see Sinn F&eacute;in's health document being widely published at this stage.  It might publish and show it to us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N00800"><p>We have done that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N00900"><p>We will e-mail it to the Leader later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N01000"><p>I apologise to Senator Gerry Horkan.  I was taking note-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N01100"><p>There will be several debates on health in the next few months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N01200"><p>I agree fully with the Senator that a seven-month delay is inordinately long when people require an access pass, sticker or licence to park.  In some cases, the parking space can be outside someone's door, in a church car park or a shopping centre.  The point raised by the Senator is important.</p> <p>Senator Colm Burke referred to Ireland's ranking in the World Economic Forum's democracy index, which we welcome.  The figures portrayed for the increase in positions in the HSE and its management structure beggar belief.  It is important that there be a rolling debate on health.</p> <p>I apologise again to Members for the change to the Order of Business.  If it is agreeable, we will not take No. 1 first but suspend the sitting until 2.45 p.m. when we will take Committee Stage of the Sea-Fisheries (Amendment) Bill 2017. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#N01300"><p>Is the change to the Order of Business agreed to?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.133" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.134" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.35 p.m. and resumed at 2.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.135" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#AA00100">Sea-Fisheries (Amendment) Bill 2017: Committee Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.136" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#AA00300"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Creed, to the House.   I note that if amendment No. 1 is agreed, amendments Nos. 2 to 5, inclusive, cannot be moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#AA00400"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 3, lines 14 to 19, to delete all words from and including &ldquo;, unless&rdquo; in line 14 down to and including line 19 and substitute &ldquo;(within the meaning of section 85), or is otherwise authorised by law to do so.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>I have to say various Governments have had a very poor track record in fisheries.  They have never really regarded it as a national resource for the people of Ireland.  Over many years, I have listened to people talking about how much we got out of the European Union and so on, while neglecting the fact that about &euro;200 billion of Irish fishing was handed out over the years to European Community fishing.  </p><p>In this legislation, the Government is trying to push through new legislation which is aimed at reinstating what was determined to be an unlawful provision under which millions of pounds of Irish shellfish were taken out of Irish waters by British companies.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->An upstanding Irish citizen, Paul Barlow from Dunmore East, who is a shellfish fisherman and three other shellfish farmers successfully challenged what had been happening in the Supreme Court.  The practice of the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine of allowing some British vessels to fish inside an area specifically designed for Irish fishing vessels was undermining Irish sovereignty and taking away what amounted to Irish natural resources and putting local shellfish fishermen out of business.  That is very serious.<br/><br/>The policy was to set aside the law and not prosecute fishing vessels particularly if they came from Britain or Northern Ireland.  The policy was called <i>voisinage</i>, which with my limited schoolboy knowledge of French I take to amount to neighbourliness.  It is not terribly good neighbourly behaviour to fish out local shellfish resources.  Various Ministers responsible for the marine alienated marine natural resources on the absurd principle that these fish and shellfish species were not a natural resource and did not in some fashion belong to the State.  The Supreme Court decided in favour of the shellfish fishermen and declared positively and specifically that marine shellfish were a natural resource and belonged to the Irish people.  I remember the principles enunciated by a former Minister that Irish resources belong to the Irish people and should be treated as such and it is a pity we have departed from this principle.<br/><br/>During the 50 years and more of this practice, British vessels were in fact fishing illegally in Irish waters.  Parliamentary questions were asked and misleading or inaccurate answers were given.  A stock answer was that this arrangement existed under a 1964 convention, which was very misleading.  After the Supreme Court judgment the Minister is trying to readjust the situation and bring back in the process that the Supreme Court determined to be illegal.  He is frustrating a decision of the Supreme Court, which is wrong.  The provision I am opposed to states: </p><blockquote>Subject to section 9, a person on board a foreign sea-fishing boat shall not fish or attempt to fish while the boat is within the exclusive fishery limits, unless he or she&mdash;(a) is on board a sea-fishing boat owned and operated in Northern Ireland while the boat is within the area between 0 and 6 nautical miles ...</blockquote><p>This once again provides for British vessels to fish up to the shores and all around the Irish coast and not be liable for prosecution for doing so.  I think we are remarkably tolerant of all these invading species, not only the British and the Northern Irish but the Spanish, who have fished out their own waters, are coming in here.  Our own record is appalling.  I remember when we built the <i>Celtic Dawn</i>, the largest factory fishing vessel in the world.  It was so devastating to fish stocks that it was banned from European waters.  It went off to Africa and fished out the resources for local African people, putting the tribal fishermen out of business.  They were jobless and came to Europe where they were described dismissively as economic migrants.  It is perfectly legitimate to be an economic migrant.  If the financial circumstances in one's country are so very bad and difficult it is perfectly natural to go somewhere where there are resources and jobs available.<br/><br/>This Bill provides for a British vessel to fish up to the shores all around the Irish coast and not be liable for prosecution.  There is no clarity on what vessels will make use of this provision.  Has there been an impact assessment of how this unqualified fishing will have an impact on the small national fleet that relies so heavily on this area or of the impact on fish stocks because we could be in danger of fishing out certain species?  The four people who took this action risked their personal livelihoods to safeguard a national asset.  We should salute them for so doing because they were extremely courageous in taking a case to the Supreme Court, which can be expensive and difficult if it goes against one.  They were from Waterford, Donegal, Limerick and Wexford, which essentially covers the entire island.  I will be pushing this amendment to delete the offending paragraph. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#BB00200"><p>The Minister knows the Labour Party's position on this legislation.  We rehearsed the arguments in some detail on Second Stage.  I support the views expressed by Senator Norris.  I am concerned that this Bill is being tabled without pre-legislative scrutiny.  My amendment No. 2 seeks to make an unfair situation for the owners of Irish vessels slightly fairer.  If the State is preparing to copperfasten in law access rights to the zero-to-six nautical mile limit, which gives a right to foreign vessels to fish our inshore, it is incumbent on us as public representatives and on the Minister to establish ways in which we can restrict and manage that access as best we can, and to lay down transparent qualifying criteria that can be understood by everybody.  We have to police this arrangement properly and I am sometimes at a loss to understand how.  If this legislation is to pass, and I would prefer if it did not, we do not want to hand an unfair advantage to our competitors for all of the reasons I outlined on Second Stage.  Restricting the size of the vessel is one way to do that.  I look forward to the Minister's response to that.</p> <p>Related to my amendment is the idea of regulating vessels from Northern Ireland, as the Minister clearly is committed to legislating for this.  Even if, in the spirit of genuine North-South co-operation we were to figure out a way to do this, it is not clear to me that we can in some way define what constitutes being owned and operated in Northern Ireland.  To the best of my knowledge, and I have researched this extensively in recent weeks in co-operation with some vessel owners, we cannot be specific about what comprises a Northern Irish vessel.  These vessels are registered in the United Kingdom.  There is no clear Northern Irish designation.  Can the Minister reassure me and the vessel owners to whom we are accountable in the Republic of Ireland that this can be done logically and in law?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerald Nash:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2281"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2281&amp;amp;pid=GeraldNash&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->He might address in his response any consideration he has given to an option I wish to see pursued, namely, the keeping of a register of vessels that would be open and accessible to members of the public, the citizens and vessel owners of the Irish Republic.  That register could be compiled and made available and could be checked in real time to establish not just the whereabouts of foreign vessels, if I can use that phrase, but those that are qualified or otherwise to be here.  We need to be clear about that.  We need some reassurance about that.  I am not convinced, from what I know about the registration of fishing vessels, that we can establish whether the vessels we are talking about are actually owned and operated in Northern Ireland or somewhere else.  I have come across one case in particular in recent days of a vessel from across the water that is owned by a major Dutch company, is operating out of Belfast and was fishing and accessing mussel seed from beds on the Republic of Ireland inshore.  In nobody's language does that mean Northern Irish vessel.  The Minister might try to reassure Members about how he can confirm and clarify the qualification criteria he will lay down for vessels that would be able to benefit from this legislation and, most importantly, whether that is feasible and possible in law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#CC00200"><p>I welcome the Minister.  I am not going to try to portray myself as an expert on fisheries, even though the college I attended was originally set up as a fisheries school.  I have real and serious concerns in this regard.  I have said in the House on a previous occasion that I would have preferred to see this measure go through pre-legislative scrutiny, where we could have had proper discussion and an in-depth conversation about the impact this will have on the mussel beds on the east coast.  The conversation is happening in a vacuum.  We are trying to respond to this and I do not think any of us would claim that our amendments are 100% correct or that there are no unknown consequences relating to the amendments concerning the Common Fisheries Policy.  However, I do not believe the Minister can provide any certainty either about the unknown consequences of putting this into legislation so quickly.  I appeal to the Minister to take a week or two and put this back into a D&aacute;il committee and allow interested bodies to give evidence - be they inshore fishermen or Northern Irish fishermen - where they can be given what I would call a fair hearing.  I support Senator Norris's remarks about how brave the fishermen themselves were and how they put their own financial future at risk by taking this to the courts.  That has to be applauded and praised.  If we are to give this issue its fair dues and fair comment the least we could do is allow three or four hours in committee rooms and ask the fishermen to come in and present their evidence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#CC00300"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#CC00400"><p>I do not think we are doing justice to them today by discussing this Bill in a vacuum and without having given them a fair hearing.</p> <p>Senator Nash mentioned boats registering in Northern Ireland.  Can the Minister give guarantees that Dutch mussel producers have not been registering vessels in Northern Ireland or registering holding companies in order to claim a legal right to fish in our zero-to-six-mile zone?  Can the Minister give me an undertaking that this is not happening?  The evidence that is being presented to many Members of the House is quite the opposite.  Are we opening up this questionable legislation to the rape and pillage of our mussel beds along the east coast and making them financially unviable for our own fishermen?</p> <p>Can the Minister reassure me that Northern Irish shellfish farmers were not allocated thousands of tonnes of mussel seed in the Republic of Ireland without a fishing licence or even a boat?  What are the safeguards to prevent that from happening with regard to this legislation?  </p> <p>Senator Norris touched on the issue of invasive species.  We already have invasive species in Belfast Lough.  The slipper limpet has already smothered UK species.  It has out-competed native species in many European countries and is in Belfast Lough.  This is the very area where we are proposing to give licences for boats coming down from Northern Ireland to our mussel beds on the east coast.  The Minister has said there are safeguards.  Where are they?  This has destroyed mussel seed beds right across Europe, yet we are now opening up our mussel seed beds without proper consideration.  </p> <p>I do not have enough knowledge to support this Bill.  I believe it needs further consideration.  We should have the good manners to allow people who earn their livelihood from this sector to come in and give evidence and then let us make an informed decision.  I do not believe we will be making that informed decision today.  Amendments have been tabled, including by my party, concerning the reduction of the size of boats.  I am not necessarily 100% sure that it is the right way to go.  We certainly could tease it out if we allowed the experts to come in and give evidence.  Then perhaps we could do the right thing by our fishermen because for decades we have sold them out.  Let us try and support a small group of fishermen who are engaged inside the six-mile zone.  Let us support them and ensure that they get a fair hearing.  Let them come before a D&aacute;il committee for pre-legislative scrutiny and let us take this in good faith and see if we can progress it.  Even if the amendments were accepted I would have to oppose this Bill today, because it is rushed, there has not been due consideration and the very people this will affect have not had an opportunity to make their case to the Minister or ourselves on Committee Stage.  I respectfully ask the Minister to consider withdrawing for a couple of weeks to allow the experts to come in to give evidence and allow us to take a considered position on this issue and do our utmost to protect our Irish fishermen who actually depend on the nought-to-six-mile zone for their livelihood.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#CC00500"><p>If we in Sinn F&eacute;in could be assured that those availing of this proposed legislation were Irish fishermen resident on the island of Ireland availing of an Irish natural resource we would support that, in line with our support for the Good Friday Agreement and North-South co-operation.  My difficulty is that I see no evidence presented that can guarantee what I regard as loopholes under the <i>voisinage</i>exchange of letters.  It should not be called an agreement because it has no legal status.  In terms of the <i>voisinage</i>exchange of letters, if Sinn F&eacute;in could be reassured that the principle of those letters was for Irish fishermen resident in the island of Ireland to avail of an Irish natural resource in a sustainable and managed fashion, that would be fine.  That is what the Supreme Court case was about.  I understand that there are other pending court cases that have not been resolved which are connected to the Supreme Court case.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2321"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2321&amp;amp;pid=PadraigMacLochlainn&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Everything that I see tells me, despite the Minister's personal good intentions, that it is premature.  I would not support Senator David Norris' amendment if I could be reassured about all of these matters, but I am not.  That is why I think his amendment is probably the safest way to proceed in the absence of clarification.<br/><br/>The Minister knows that coastal communities believe Irish fishing waters have been given away to a large extent under European treaties and the Common Fisheries Policy.  There is a real sense that we have not benefited from this immense resource as an island nation.  The Supreme Court's decision which confirms that there is no legal basis whatsoever to <i>voisinage</i>offers an opportunity to go back to the drawing board and make sure the natural resource within the zero to six mile limit is protected and used for the benefit of coastal communities.<br/><br/>This legislation is premature and rushed.  It should be agreed to on an all-Ireland basis.  We should seek reassurance about the residency of people who could avail of that opportunity, that is, licence holders based in Northern Ireland.  All of these matters are currently absent, which is why I support the proposition that we go back to the drawing board.  Perhaps the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, on which I serve, with several of my fellow Senators, might look at this matter in more detail and make recommendations to the Minister.  Unfortunately, the legislation as presented is not in line with the Good Friday Agreement because it is open to exploitation.  Its loopholes could be exploited by foreign multinationals, as they have done in recent times, to the detriment of coastal communities.  I appeal to the Minister, even at this late moment, to consider withdrawing the legislation.  I am sure everybody in this Chamber agrees that the Minister should announce that he is withdrawing the legislation for further consideration by an Oireachtas committee or him, subject to consultation with all stakeholders, particularly fishermen around the coast who have not been involved in this process so far.  I reluctantly have to support Senator David Norris's amendment and hope all colleagues can do the same in the absence of the legislation being withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD00200"><p>I thank Senator David Norris for his amendment and Senators Gerald Nash, Kevin Humphreys and P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn for their contributions.</p> <p>Senator David Norris has proposed an amendment which seeks to remove section 10(1)(a) from the Bill.  It would have the effect of removing the principle of access for sea fishing boats owned and operated in Northern Ireland to fish in our zero to six nautical mile zone.  In a way, I am perplexed by the Senator's approach to this matter-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD00300"><p>I am a Unionist.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD00400"><p>-----as a self-described Southern Unionist, particularly considering that the authorities in Northern Ireland are continuing to allow reciprocal access for our boats.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD00500"><p>It is far smaller.  More fools them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD00600"><p>No.  This is the point the Senator misses: under the <i>voisinage</i>arrangements, our boats can fish in Northern Ireland fishing waters on the exact same terms as Northern Irish boats.  Until the Supreme Court ruling of 27 October, Northern Irish boats were entitled to fish in our fishing waters on the exact same terms.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD00700"><p>Why does the Minister think the Supreme Court reached that decision?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD00800"><p>I will come to that matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD00900"><p>Please do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01000"><p>Let us remember that the Supreme Court upheld the High Court's finding that the <i>voisinage</i>arrangements were not invalid but that, as they stood, they lacked sufficient legal legislative provision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01100"><p>In other words, they are unconstitutional.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01200"><p>It never stated anything about the provisions being unconstitutional.  It stated the arrangements which had been in place up to 27 October which were effectively a gentleman's agreement were not a sufficient legal framework, not that they were unconstitutional.  I will come to a specific quotation from the judgment which might, if the Senator's mind is open to alternative facts-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01300"><p>Minister Trump.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01400"><p>-----convince him of the Supreme Court's view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01500"><p>Fake news.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01600"><p>The Bill seeks to address what the Supreme Court identified as being required - giving the arrangements a legal footing and cementing our ongoing relationship with Northern Ireland.  For that reason, I cannot support the Senator's amendment.</p><p>In the Supreme Court judgment Mr. Justice O'Donnell called the cross-Border approach to fisheries &quot;an important area of co-operation between the two jurisdictions&quot; and said &quot;there is much to applaud&quot;.  He also noted that such co-operation was &quot;arguably an implementation of the constitutional provisions which have been in place since 1999 which expressly contemplate cross-Border co-operation in a number of areas.&quot;  The reciprocal arrangement has been in place since an agreement between Se&aacute;n Lemass and Terence O'Neill was made in the early 1960s whereby they exchanged letters and as a consequence of which we had reciprocal access.  Boats from Northern Ireland were entitled to come here and fish in the zero to six-mile zone in the exact same circumstances as Southern Irish boats.  Our boats were entitled to fish in Northern Ireland fishing waters under the exact same arrangements that applied to Northern Irish boats in their jurisdiction.  On 27 October the Supreme Court did not state this was illegal. rather it lauded it.  It stated it was entirely appropriate and an important area of co-operation but that the exchange of letters was not a sufficient legal framework for it.  To regulate an arrangement that had been in place for nearly 50 years there was a requirement to give it a legislative framework.  This is not breaking new ground.  It goes back to something that was in place on 21, 22, 23, 24, 25 and 26 October 2016, but on the 27 October the Supreme Court stated there was no legal framework.  Our boats have continued to be entitled to fish in Northern Ireland fishing waters under the <i>voisinage</i>arrangements, but Northern Irish boats are not entitled to come here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01700"><p>How many Irish boats fish in Northern Ireland fishing waters?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01800"><p>I will deal with all of the points raised.</p> <p>An important point is that at the heart of this legislation is reciprocity.  It is about mutual co-operation.  When Senator David Norris said he saluted the people who had taken the Supreme Court case, against whom I bear no ill will, he said that because they were from Waterford, Limerick, Donegal and Wexford, it covered all of the island.  Unfortunately, it does not.  It is a partitionist view of what is a 32 county island.  What we are-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD01900"><p>It is not yet a 32 county republic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#DD02000"><p>It is a 32 county island.  This is saying there is enough that divides us.  We can have areas of co-operation, which has continued since the 1960s.  That is what the court stated.  It stated it was good.  It stated it was an appropriate area in which to have co-operation, as envisaged under the Good Friday Agreement.  Taking Senator Norris's Southern Unionist partitionist approach is baffling in this context.  If his amendment is carried, it will be the death knell for the <i>voisinage</i>arrangements which might be considered good in some quarters.  I passionately believe we should have good relationships with our colleagues in Northern Ireland, that we should continue the reciprocal arrangement and that, arising from the Supreme Court's judgment of 27 October, we should give the arrangements a legal framework.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Michael Creed:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=259"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=259&amp;amp;pid=MichaelCreed&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is not breaking new ground.  As I said, this is something that has existed since the 1960s.  It ran into a High Court challenge and a Supreme Court challenge, where it was ruled on.  Elements of this case are still ongoing so I am constrained in certain respects.  In respect of this issue, I am not constrained.  It does not have the legal framework.  It is a good thing.  My response and the Government's response is that we should, as a gesture of goodwill, reinstate the fishing opportunity that is reciprocated for our boats that currently go to Northern Ireland to fish.  Those are simply the facts of the matter.</p><p>The point has been raised about boats owned and operated, etc.  Back in the 1960s, perhaps the world was a simpler place.  A man owned his boat and fished in his lough or whatever.  The world has moved on quite significantly.  The Supreme Court acknowledged that it is a different world in its judgment.  There are many corporate bodies.  Corporates in the fishing world sue me on a regular basis.  They are not all Dutch corporates or UK corporates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE00200"><p>I did not use such an example-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE00300"><p>No, but I make the point that the ownership model that may have been prevalent in the 1960s when this was envisaged has moved on very significantly.  In the context of the European Union, for example, there is free movement of goods and services.  Bear in mind, whether we like it or not, that there is an EU dimension to all of this.  Our nearest neighbour is about to leave the European Union and in whose waters we fish-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE00400"><p>I would not bank on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE00500"><p>Some 40% of the Irish fishing fleet's fishing endeavour comes from UK territorial waters.  I am not talking about the zero to six nautical mile zone.  I am talking about-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE00600"><p>The North Sea.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE00700"><p>-----UK territorial waters.  It makes up 40%.  Among the most valuable of those species, pelagic fish, it is significantly more than 40%.  With prawns, it is much higher than the average-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE00800"><p>One cannot get a Dublin Bay prawn in Ireland nowadays.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE00900"><p>Why would it be prudent today, as we seek to negotiate the best possible outcome for the Irish fishing industry in the context of Brexit, effectively to give two fingers to our neighbours in Northern Ireland and say they are not coming into our nought to six nautical mile zone, though we can still go North and would like to hold on to what we catch in their UK waters?  It just-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE01000"><p>It is a return to the 800 years of brutal British oppression.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE01100"><p>In <i>realpolitik</i>, it is an illogical position to adopt.  For many good reasons, primarily because this operated successfully for nearly 50 years, because it is the right thing to do for our neighbours in Northern Ireland, because it is not partitionist and is all-island, because it was envisaged in the Good Friday Agreement and because it would be strategically and politically wise in the context of Brexit to do so, we should not say that they cannot come down any longer.</p><p><i>Voisinage</i>was a good idea in the 1960s and it continues to be a good idea.  As I said, the world in the 1960s was a much simpler place.  Ownership was a much simpler structure.  Under EU regulations, I can go to the UK, reside there and set up a business there.  I can go to Germany and to Holland.  That arrangement is reciprocal in the sense of their movement of goods and services.  That is part of what we wholeheartedly embrace as members of the European Union.  What the Senator wants to do now is simply to cherry-pick that and say that by this legislation we want to revert back in some way to the 1960s and ensure the man who owns and operates his boat and lives in Northern Ireland is the only person who is entitled to benefit under <i>voisinage</i>.  That view of the world changed very significantly as the European Economic Community and the European Union evolved with the free movement of goods and services, establishment rights, residency rights, etc.</p><p>Points were made about the resource itself and invasive species and all that.  I am getting drawn into a specific view of the world here that is dominated by mussel seed.  This is not the only fishery that is affected by this legislation.  Let us deal with it.  We have a joint managerial approach North and South for the management of the mussel fishery.  It involves regulations around gear, closed and open periods, consultation and co-operation between two jurisdictions.  It is a template for how we could do greater things and have greater co-operation with Northern Ireland.  Why would Senator Norris want to tear it up and walk away?  I think that would be calamitous in terms of what we could do and achieve together.  Yes, it needs to be regulated and managed as a resource.  That has been the case all along.  There is a management approach to this, as I said, that has closed periods and restrictions on gear.  It operates on a North-South basis and I believe it operates pretty well.</p><p>On the issue of registration for mussel seed, there is a requirement for a secondary authorisation from the Northern Ireland authorities to operate specifically in the mussel fishery areas.  One can register in the UK, but to be a part of the mussel fishery operation, which is one element of the <i>voisinage</i>fishing arrangements inside the zero to six nautical mile zone, there is a secondary authorisation required in Northern Ireland.</p><p>Senator Norris spoke with what I appreciate is a widely held view of the history of our fishing industry, the European Union and all that.  I ask him to bear in mind that when we joined the European Economic Community back in the 1970s, the Irish fishing industry was a fraction of the industry we have today.  We now catch 40% of that industry's effort in UK territorial waters.  The access the EU has given to us means our industry is much bigger.  I accept that we would like it to be even bigger still, but in the EU we share our resources.  Part of the threat we face in our nearest neighbour leaving the EU are the resources it takes with it.</p><p>I cannot say what the landing spots are going to be in the context of those Brexit negotiations.  Obviously, whether this legislation passes is in the gift of this House.  I cannot determine whether this amendment or legislation will pass.  At a later stage post Brexit, it may be opportune to revisit this when we see where those negotiations are.  However, I think it would be folly in the extreme now to undermine gratuitously our negotiating position.</p><p>That aside and Brexit aside, on the basis of an all-island approach, it was right in the 1960s to have reciprocal arrangements and it is right to continue those today.  I hope I have dealt with most of the issues that were raised on the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE01200"><p>The Minister is all sweet reasonableness.  I believe the record should show that he is completely in command of his brief.  He spoke just now without reference to notes and without consulting his advisers.  On this, I commend him.  It is obvious he has a clear and deep knowledge of the situation.  However, I am little bit alarmed that the Minister said that in the 1960s, our fishing fleet was only a fraction of what it is now.  So what?  We are not talking about the intensity of the fishing industry.  We are talking about the giving away of natural resources.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE01300"><p>If the Senator might yield-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE01400"><p>Certainly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#EE01500"><p>The point I was making was that when we joined the European Union, our industry was a fraction of the industry we have now.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Michael Creed:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=259"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=259&amp;amp;pid=MichaelCreed&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That was in the 1960s.  The point is irrelevant because the Common Fisheries Policy only came into existence several years after we initially joined the European Union.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF00200"><p>Yes, but my point remains that it does not matter.  Even if there were no fishing boats at all, it is still a natural resource belonging to the people of Ireland.  I have to say I strongly support the Keating principles that the natural resources of this Republic belong to the citizens of the Republic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF00300"><p>Did the Senator vote to join the European Union?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF00400"><p>I certainly did, yes, and I would still sustain that despite the fact the European Union and governments all over Europe and in the United States have betrayed the people by deciding their priority was to save the financial institutions and let the citizens go to hell.  That is what has happened all over Europe and it is why there is such a rush to support people like Le Pen and Trump.</p> <p>I am also a little alarmed that the Minister has almost indicated that it was free range for all the European countries under free movement of goods and services, and that any trawler from a European country could come in here and do what it liked with the fishing.  That seemed to be the implication of what he said.  I will yield to the Minister once again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF00500"><p>In practice, that has not been the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF00600"><p>The Minister is saying it could be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF00700"><p>There is no evidence over 50 years that it is the case.  There is a requirement for secondary approval-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF00800"><p>There is plenty of evidence of Spanish trawlers coming in all over the place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF00900"><p>The Senator should not confuse apples and oranges.  The Spanish are not coming in under <i>voisinage</i>.  <i>Voisinage</i>is-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01000"><p>They are coming in anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01100"><p>They are not coming in-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01200"><p>They certainly are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01300"><p>I ask the Senator to please understand that this legislation is entirely to do with the zero to six nautical mile limit, and the Spanish are not coming in there at all.  He is confusing apples and oranges.  There may be an issue where the fishing industry in its broader manifestation perceives that because we are in the EU, Spain takes fish out of what we perhaps traditionally consider &quot;our&quot; territorial waters.  However, under <i>voisinage</i>this is absolutely and only an arrangement for Northern Ireland boats to come to our waters and for our boats to go to Northern Ireland waters on exactly the same terms as Northern Ireland fishermen fish in their waters.  What we are seeking to do in this legislation is to provide that reciprocal arrangement, in other words, that they could fish in our zero to six nautical mile zone on exactly the same terms as our boats would fish in theirs.  It has nothing to do with the broader Common Fisheries Policy or member states other than the Republic of Ireland and Northern Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01400"><p>I thank the Minister.  That was helpful.  The Minister spoke about seeking the best provisions for the Irish fishing industry.  In that case, perhaps he can explain to me why four named fishermen from different parts of the Republic of Ireland have decided it is in their professional interest to take this case to the Supreme Court?  They obviously do not agree with the Minister that the Government is at the moment providing the best arrangements for the Irish fishing industry.</p><p>The Minister indicated in his speech, as I understand it, that he cannot guarantee that fishing boats registered in Northern Ireland are actually Northern Ireland-owned boats or boats with Northern Ireland personnel on them.  Can the Minister give any information on what are the respective <i>per annum</i>tonnages of fish caught in this zone, shellfish in particular, for Republic of Ireland vessels fishing in Northern Ireland and for Northern Ireland vessels fishing in Southern waters?  What are the respective tonnages and what is the level we are at?  I am not sure if the Minister will be able to provide this information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01500"><p>I will see if I can elicit that information but I do not have it off the top of my head.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01600"><p>I thank the Minister.  It will be interesting to read that but the moment will have passed because we will be voting today on this Bill.  I thank the Minister for his courtesy and his knowledge of the situation but I do not agree with him.  I am alarmed that vessels registered in Northern Ireland may not actually be Northern Ireland vessels at all.  That is a real problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01700"><p>The reverse also applies in so far as there may be boats registered here that are not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01800"><p>That should be countered as well.  I think it outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF01900"><p>In the context of the European Union and free movement of goods and services, it is entirely contrary to that principle.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF02000"><p>I thank Senator Humphreys for attributing to me concerns about slippery kippers, or whatever they were.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF02100"><p>Slippery limpets.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF02200"><p>I never mentioned that at all but I am very happy to take credit for whatever anybody else says in this House, as long as it is sensible and well informed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF02300"><p>The Senator will take the credit but not the blame.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF02400"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#FF02500"><p>I welcome the Minister to the Chamber.  He was here on 8 March when I said I had serious concerns about this Bill.  I am fully in support of Senator Norris.  I would like to draw the Minister's attention to the fact the island of Ireland has a coastline of about 7,500 km whereas Northern Ireland has a relatively small part of that coastline.  We are talking about the history of this, whereas I would rather let the history go and talk about the future.</p> <p>I am extremely concerned that this Bill is opening up the whole area from the cliff and the shoreline at Tramore right out to six nautical miles, or from the shoreline of Dublin or Donegal out to six nautical miles.  It is being opened to Northern Ireland fishermen, which I can understand, and there is no doubt the Minister is passionate about this and really wants it to happen.  He said that what is happening at the moment is illegal and he would like to legalise it, and I understand that also.  However, as I said on 8 March, it is British-registered vessels which are operating out of Northern Ireland, which means the whole of the UK can potentially have access to the whole of Irish waters from the east coast of Northern Ireland right around the south, the west and on to the north.  For me, we are giving away much too much in this situation.</p> <p>I have spoken with fishermen and with different sectors of the fishing industry.  The lobster fishermen of Dunmore East have done a lot in terms of working to earn an income for their families but they have also worked to conserve the lobster by using the notching method, so they are looking after the resource.  A fisherman said to me that we could potentially have fishermen from Northern Ireland and perhaps from England, Scotland and Wales coming in right around that edge line of the Irish coast.  I do not think it is a fair deal.  I simply ask that we stop this Bill in its tracks - can we just stop it?</p> <p>We have the Brexit negotiations coming up and we are putting the cart before the horse again.  The Minister has not engaged enough with the public.  He has engaged with some of the sectors but, having spoken to fishermen from different organisations, we know they feel there has not been sufficient consultation.  I agree wholeheartedly with Senator Norris.  I think there is a principle here and I do not believe the Irish public are aware of what the Minister is planning to do.  What he is planning to do at this stage is create a situation where that strip out to six nautical miles will be opened up.  If we were to measure that zone right around the coastline, it would be clear we are handing away a huge amount of our resources.  We might be talking about particular sectors here, such as mussel or lobster fishing, but there are other sectors that are also a resource.  My heart is always in favour of share and care, and so on, but I believe we are not looking after the fishing industry and fishing families.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Grace O'Sullivan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2467"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2467&amp;amp;pid=GraceOSullivan&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Minister said the industry is doing better than ever, but for whom?  Is it doing better for the big fishing vessels?  What about the smaller fishing families to whom I have spoken?  What about those in the middle?  I might be out of order but I sense that some elements of the larger fishing sector are doing way better than the smaller fishing families.  The Minister's Government keeps talking about supporting rural communities and so on, but this legislation actually rasps away at potential incomes.  I appeal to him to put the Bill aside until he sits down at the Brexit negotiating table and the resources begin to be considered.  At this point, I am afraid the implications of what he proposes are not being fully researched or considered and I believe, from speaking with the public, that there are concerns in this regard.  I do not think the Minister has done his homework in informing the public.  If we are to go forward as a democracy, empowering people to understand the natural resources we have, the Bill is an absolute disgrace.  This statement might not make me popular, but the Bill before us, albeit concerning matters underwater, reminds me of the Heritage Bill.  It is poorly put together.  I therefore fully support what Senator Norris said and I hope the Minister will take time to consider what has been said here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG00200"><p>Tell them they can have this arrangement if there is a united Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG00300"><p>I have read the Supreme Court judgment in great detail over the past few days.  It says many things, and we can all selectively quote from it to back up our arguments.  I am not necessarily accusing the Minister of doing so.  The judgment ventilated the idea that laws must be made in public, by the elected Oireachtas, and promoted and mediated in public and that people need to be aware of what it is we are considering.  I do not think we can say with sufficient confidence that the public at large is aware of the implications of what it is we are deciding upon here.  For this reason, I support what my colleague, Senator Humphreys, said earlier, namely, that this should be delayed and that we should scrutinise in detail the provisions of the legislation and its impact on the fishing industry and coastal communities in this country.</p><p>I wish to make a further point directly related to one the Minister made in his earlier contribution when he referred to and quoted from the Supreme Court judgment, which makes very interesting reading.  The Supreme Court judgment states that the <i>voisinage</i>agreement does not have any legal foundation.  This decision was made for the right reasons, and I think everybody accepts that.  However, the judgment does not instruct the Minister to make that agreement law.  It is up to this Legislature to decide what becomes and does not become law in this country, and it is to the fishermen and their families who took the case that we are accountable - nobody else - and we need to be mindful of that.  There is absolutely no requirement that the Minister give legislative foundation to the arrangements reflected in the <i>voisinage</i>agreement - and I use that term advisedly.  Neither, from what I can establish, was there any degree of reciprocity.  We can see here illustrated very clearly on a Marine Institute image from 2016 very limited activity around the Northern Irish coast.  <i>De facto</i>, and from what I am told, there is no fishing - at least, very limited fishing - going on in this area by vessels registered in the Republic of Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG00400"><p>From the image I see, though, I do not think the activity is occurring inside the zero to six nautical mile limit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG00500"><p>It looks damn close to me, to be perfectly frank.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG00600"><p>It is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG00700"><p>I am open to be advised on that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG00800"><p>It is not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG00900"><p>-----but this image is from 2016, a period which mostly predates the Supreme Court judgment at the end of 2016, which stated quite clearly that this had no legislative foundation and that, therefore, from that date, any fishing by Northern Irish vessels in the Republic of Ireland's zero to six nautical mile zone was not lawful.  It is a moot point whether there is any reciprocal arrangement in place now at all because once the arrangement is undermined and once it finishes, surely, by definition, the reciprocal arrangement falls as well.  I am very concerned about the haste with which the Minister is moving to give this legislative foundation when there is absolutely no requirement to do so and the Supreme Court has not said there is a requirement to do so.  The Supreme Court would never tell the Legislature, given the division of powers in the Constitution, that we must legislate in a certain way.  It is a ministerial decision, an Executive decision, to propose legislation to this House, and this is legislation about which we are very concerned.</p> <p>The point the Minister made earlier about the ownership model moving on is very interesting, and it has moved on from the 1960s.  If the ownership model has moved on and is more complex now than it was in the 1960s, why are we seeking to legislate for an arrangement that was applied in the 1960s, 1970s, 1980s and so on?  This is absolutely open to exploitation and abuse and is not in the interests of Irish fishing vessels and the Irish fishing industry.  The system has moved on and we are trying now to legislate for an arrangement that was in place in the 1960s and reflects 1960s behaviour and a 1960s industry, not an industry dominated, as it is now, by large corporations.  Those corporations have been active in Irish waters and have been foreign-owned.  They may very well have had licences from the North.  I remain to be convinced about that but I accept what the Minister says at face value and I accept his bona fides in that regard.  It is very interesting that a vessel can be owned by a company in the United Kingdom but is required to get a mussel licence from Northern Ireland to access mussel seed in Republic of Ireland waters in that zero to six nautical mile zone.  I am not convinced the Minister has answered my earlier question about reassuring me as to how we can have a proper registration system to establish the bona fides of Northern Irish vessels fishing down here.  This confuses me.  We are co-opting out management of this to another nation because we do not appear to be able ourselves to define what is Northern Irish-owned and operated and what is Northern Irish-registered.  That will be someone else's problem, it appears to me, and that is no way to do business.</p> <p>I will conclude by saying something I said the other day.  It is absolutely bizarre and reckless, although the Minister clearly does not agree, that we would make and copper-fasten arrangements such as this in our legislation a matter of days or a week before the triggering of Article 50 and the Brexit negotiations.  I do not support it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#GG01000"><p>We did not mean to imply in any way an anti-Six Counties or anti-UK sentiment earlier.  As a matter of fact, I would say the thoughts and prayers of everybody in Ireland at the moment are probably with the citizens of London because of the atrocities that have taken place there this afternoon.  Certainly, my thoughts and prayers are with them.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2017&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->What Se&aacute;n Lemass done with Terence O'Neill-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH00200"><p>Did.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH00300"><p>I thank the Senator for his correction.  I never got the opportunity to go to Trinity College.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH00400"><p>Never mind.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH00500"><p>I am sure my English would have been much better if I had gone there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH00600"><p>If the Senator had come to my lectures, his English would have been grammatically perfect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH00700"><p>Thankfully, there is now access to Trinity College for people from the inner city.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH00800"><p>There is plenty of access.  Senator Lynn Ruane is a splendid representative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH00900"><p>She is much younger than me.  I am sorry I started that.  I should not try to correct the Senator.  </p> <p>The agreement reached by Terence O'Neill and Se&aacute;n Lemass was very much of its time.  As the Minister has rightly pointed out, as a result of globalisation, it is now difficult to legislate and regulate.  This attempt to move a good neighbour agreement reached in the 1960s into legislation will have untold and unintentional consequences.  We have not had an opportunity to assess this.  I would not compare this Bill to the Heritage Bill 2016.  It is not quite as bad as that, but it is going in a similar direction.  We have to protect the rights of our fishermen.  We also have to protect the environment.  The last time the Minister was in the House, he mentioned the Marine Stewardship Council's certificate.  The first time it was introduced in relation to Irish bottom mussel seed production was in 2013.  The source of the data for 2000 to 2060 values is Bord Iascaigh Mhara.  We have seen a significant decrease since 2004 or 2005 and there has to be concern.  The regulations were not being enforced and there was no sign of their enforcement.  I have to return to that point and sincerely urge caution in that respect.  I accept the good intentions of the Minister in pointing out that there are problems with Senator David Norris' amendment.  Members of this House have had to react to the Bill without having an opportunity to be properly informed on it.  That is why I repeat that this legislation needs to go back to Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn's committee for indepth scrutiny.  All Members of the House who are being fair will join me in urging the Minister to take a breath and allow time for a proper investigation before making an informed decision on the legislation he is proposing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2017032200002#HH01000"><p>The Minister has challenged the veracity of the Marine Institute's map as it pertains to the zero to six-mile limit.  What evidence has he presented for the scale of fishing by vessels registered in this state that has been ongoing in waters off the North of Ireland since the Supreme Court's decision?  Does he have evidence of the scale of fishing taking place?  He has made an argument about reciprocity.  If he looks at the <i>voisinage</i>letters - I refuse to refer to an agreement because it is my view that an agreement should be grounded in law - he will see that it is clearly stated on the British side that this arrangement will apply as long as the authorities of the Republic of Ireland continue to accord to Northern Irish vessels the same treatment accorded to vessels of the Republic of Ireland in the waters around its coast.  In their opinion, this arrangement, as they refer to it, is clearly based on its continuing to be adhered to by this side.  Therefore, there is no arrangement.  According to the letters to which the Minister is referring, there is no arrangement as we speak.</p><p>I query the issue of reciprocity, which is obviously fair to do.  Of course, reciprocity is central to all-Ireland co-operation and the Good Friday Agreement.  I ask what is happening.  How many boats registered in this state are actually fishing in Northern waters at this time?  How much fishing has been taking place since the Supreme Court's decision?  According to the actual letters about which the Minister has spoken, the basis of the goodwill in this area, the arrangement ceases.  That has to be the case following the Supreme Court's decision.  Obviously, the Supreme Court's decision is sovereign and has to be respected by the Government.  The Supreme Court interprets the Constitution and laws.  It is for that reason, based on the actual <i>voisinage</i>letters, I suggest this arrangement is null and void.  It no longer applies.  Therefore, we are back to the drawing board and if we are going back to it, that takes me to my next point.</p><p>The Minister quoted from the Supreme Court's decision on all-Ireland co-operation and suggested this was in line with the spirit of the Good Friday Agreement.  Of course, that is positive.  As I said in my earlier comments, if Irish fishermen resident on the island of Ireland were utilising the resource around the island of Ireland in a managed and sustainable fashion, surely the Minister would be positive about it.  I will explain my frustration.  The Minister referred to all-Ireland co-operation.  I accept that point in so far as it relates to residents of the North of Ireland.  The difficulty is that a glaring loophole in the licensed registration process in the North allows foreign multinationals to access a precious natural resource which is under profound pressure.  The Minister can see the numbers.  The reduction in the productivity of the bottom mussel seed industry, for example, in recent years is unchallenged.  This natural resource is under serious pressure.  As a result of the loophole I have mentioned, this resource which has immense potential to create jobs and prosperity in coastal communities is being handed to foreign multinationals.  That is not in line with the Good Friday Agreement, rather it takes advantage of the goodwill of the Agreement.</p><p>This legislation is way too premature.  If we are serious about the Good Friday Agreement and all-Ireland co-operation, we should make sure the Northern authorities are asked to ensure the registration process for their legislation guarantees that those who avail of these licences are resident on the island.  I have no problem with the Minister receiving advice from his officials to enable him to respond to the points I am making and believe he is sincere.  I accept that he believes in the all-Ireland markets provided for under the Good Friday Agreement.  He is sincere in his appreciation of the importance of all-Ireland co-operation in ensuring the resources of this island benefit all of the people on the island.  The difficulty is that there is a huge loophole that has yet to be closed fully.  This legislation invites that loophole to be exploited yet again.  The Supreme Court's decision closed that loophole, but this legislation provides for it to be reopened, which is not prudent.  We should have engaged in negotiations and discussions with our Northern counterparts to ensure there would be a level playing pitch for all fishermen on the island.  I refer, for example, to differences in licensing.  It is not fair that one can obtain a licence in the North way cheaper than in this state.  We should make sure those who avail of these licences are resident in Ireland and contributing to the economy on the island, in line with the Good Friday Agreement.  I am not going to argue that they should have to be Irish citizens.</p><p>If ever there was legislation that should be subject to pre-legislative scrutiny, this is it.  The Bill should have come through the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  We should have been able to bring in the stakeholders - the fishermen around the coast - to make an argument about the reality for them versus that for those who will benefit from the Bill.  I remind the Minister that the <i>voisinage</i>letters are very clear.  There is no other way to interpret them.  Following the Supreme Court's decision, the arrangement is null and void.  Dr. Beamish is advising the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2017-03-22a.226" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>