<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to consider prioritising the re-introduction of the local improvement scheme in 2017.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paudie Coffey of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to explain why more than 90 University Hospital Waterford patients, who have been on a waiting list for more than a year, must undergo cardiac diagnostic procedures elsewhere in the country and to outline his proposals to ensure unacceptably long waiting lists do not occur again and that the cardiology services at University Hospital Waterford are sustainable into the future.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to set out the position regarding the reopening of the Garda station in Maynooth, County Kildare.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maura Hopkins of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State with responsibility for regional economic development to provide an update on plans to introduce a grant scheme for underwater search and recovery in accordance with the commitment in the programme for partnership Government.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government to outline what funding his Department has given to Rural Resettlement Ireland over the past five years and what are his plans to support this organisation into the future.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Communications, Climate Change and Natural Resources to explain if he is aware of the deep community concern in Rialto, Dublin 8, following the closure of the local post office service and to outline what plans he has to deal with the situation. </blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by Senators &Oacute; Domhnaill, Coffey, Boyhan, Hopkins and Conway as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators &Oacute; Domhnaill, Coffey and Boyhan and they will be taken now.  Senator Hopkins has had to withdraw her matter. Senator Conway may give notice on another day of the matter that he wishes to raise.  I regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Devine on the ground that the Minister has no official responsibility in this matter.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#A00350">Local Improvement Scheme</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#A00400"><p>I thank the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport for coming to the House.  It is nice that a Cabinet Minister is present to reply to a Commencement matter and we appreciate that.</p> <p>This matter relates to the local improvement scheme.  I am not sure if the Minister was familiar with the scheme in his constituency but, in rural constituencies, the scheme was essential for providing small amounts in grant aid, up to a maximum of 90% of the overall cost, to individuals who resided on roads that are classified as accommodation roads.  They are private roads but they accommodate road users, farm activity and rural recreation activity.  The budget allocation for the scheme was small but the value for money was significant.  A contribution was made by those who lived on the road and the council would come in and carry out the work.  While I had questions previously about the value derived from the work in respect of who should carry it out, whether it be the council or whether it would be tendered, that is a separate issue.</p> <p>The primary issue is that the scheme should be renewed in 2017, if possible.  This would merely cost a few million euro in the context of the overall transport allocation to cover the entire country.  If a pot of &euro;20 million was made available next year, it would help.  The scheme was discontinued in 2011 and, as a result, a large number of roads that would have been repaired under it have fallen into a severe state of disrepair and the individuals living on them do not have the resources to carry out the necessary maintenance or upgrading works.  They require a scheme to assist them in maintaining the countryside.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2261"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2261&amp;amp;pid=BrianODomhnaill&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are environmental benefits to the scheme, as well as benefits relating to transport.  There are certainly benefits for people living in rural Ireland in particular.  Will the Minister of State give serious consideration to reintroduce this scheme at an early date?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#B00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this matter, which I recognise as important.  I can understand why he might have thought I am not terribly familiar with it and it is a fair assumption.  It is not the case now but it would have been the case six or eight months ago.  Several of my comrades in Government have made me familiar with it and I hear of little else from Deputy Kevin Boxer Moran and others.  I am familiar with the need for it and I am sympathetic to its cause.  As the Senator knows, it is in the programme for Government that it should be fully restored.</p><p>The improvement and maintenance of regional and local roads is the statutory responsibility of each city and county council, in accordance with the provisions of section 13 of the Roads Act 1993.  Works on those roads are funded from the council's own resources, supplemented by State road grants.  The initial selection and prioritisation of works to be funded is also a matter</p><p>for the council.  Ireland has just under 100,000 km of road in its network and the maintenance and improvement of national, regional and local roads places a substantial financial burden on local authorities and the Exchequer.  As a result of the national financial position, there have been very large reductions in Exchequer funding available for roads expenditure over the past number of years.  For this reason, the focus has had to be on maintenance and renewal.</p><p>Maintenance of private laneways and roads not taken in charge by local authorities is the responsibility of the landowners concerned, as the Senator noted.  There is a local improvement scheme in place whereby a contribution can be made by the State towards the cost of maintaining these laneways or roads. Local improvement schemes are permitted under section 81 of the Local Government Act 2001.  Due to the cutbacks in roads funding, it was necessary for the Department to stop making separate allocations to local authorities in respect of local improvement schemes.  The approved scheme remains intact and within it local authorities can use a proportion of State grant funding, which was 15% of the discretionary grant in 2016, for local improvement schemes should they wish to do so.</p><p>The reason a separate State grant allocation is not being made for local improvement schemes is that given funding constraints, a ring-fenced allocation would result in a <i>pro rata</i>reduction in funding for public roads in a situation where public roads are significantly underfunded.  Whereas 2017 will see a modest increase in funding for roads, it will take some years yet under the capital plan to restore steady State funding levels for regional and local roads.  The primary focus will have to continue to be on the maintenance and renewal of public roads.  I do, however, expect that local authorities will continue to be able to use a proportion of their discretionary grant for the local improvement scheme in 2017.  In light of the provision in the programme for Government indicating that as the economy recovers, the Government will promote increased funding for local improvement schemes, I will be raising the issue of increased funding in the context of the planned review of the capital plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#B00300"><p>It is a good result, Senator.  An bhfuil t&uacute; s&aacute;sta?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#B00400"><p>Go raibh m&iacute;le maith agat.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.14" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#B00450">Hospital Waiting Lists</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#B00500"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for taking a very important Commencement matter and the Minister of State for making time in her very busy schedule.  Cardiac care for patients in the south east has been an issue of concern for quite some time.  I have raised many times with the Minister of State and her predecessors the issue of inequality of access to cardiac care for patients in the south-east region and especially for those who reside in east County Waterford, south Kilkenny and south County Wexford.  These people are not in close proximity for interventional cardiology care after hours.  This is a matter of deep concern that must be addressed.  Access to interventional cardiology in the event of a heart attack after hours is simply not available, which is unacceptable.  The reason we do not have this access is quite clear from some recent controversies; it is because we do not have a second catheterisation lab.  Dublin, Cork and Galway have numerous catheterisation labs and Limerick, a city in the west of Ireland, has numerous catheterisation labs as well.  This is a matter of equality of access to health care in the country that must be addressed.</p> <p>Further to this, I was deeply concerned to learn recently that University Hospital Waterford patients have been on a waiting list for over a year to access cardiac diagnostic procedures.  They are now being outsourced to private hospitals in other parts of the country.  I understand over 90 patients have been transferred to other hospitals for this care, which is unacceptable for patients in the south-east region.  How many more are on the waiting list and are to be referred to this private service?  How much is this costing the State, as I know the Minister of State is rightly concerned about the health budget?  It seems we are spending far more money in referring these patients to private treatment rather than dealing with them within the public health service.  University Hospital Waterford already has expert cardiologists and staff and the service must be enhanced, as recommended in the recent Herity report.</p> <p>The Minister of State might be able to clarify the issue.  My understanding is that the HSE at University Hospital Waterford has applied for a mobile second catheterisation lab to deal with this waiting list.  It would be far more efficient in delivering a good public health service if these patients were treated in the hospital in which they are patients.  I am interested in the Minister of State's response this morning and this is a matter of deep concern.  As I stated before, as a Government Senator I see it as no longer acceptable that people, patients and citizens of this country are treated in an unequal way in comparison with patients in other parts of the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#B00600"><p>I thank Senator Coffey for raising this important issue this morning.  I also convey the apologies of the Minister, Deputy Harris, who is personally unable to attend this morning.</p> <p>The Minister, Deputy Harris, visited University Hospital Waterford recently and is aware that there are waiting lists for cardiology procedures at the hospital, which is managed by the Health Service Executive, as the Senator knows.  The Minister is keenly aware of waiting lists in cardiology and other specialties in hospitals around the country and I assure the House that the Government is committed to improving waiting times for patients.  For that reason, last August, the Minister, Deputy Harris, requested the HSE to develop an action plan on waiting lists, focused on those patients waiting longest.  Since then, under the waiting list action plan, over 8,000 patients have been removed from the inpatient and day case waiting list, either through the provision of treatment, clinical validation or because the patient has been given a date for the procedure.</p> <p>The Senator may wish to note that &euro;11.25 million in funding from the winter initiative contingency funding has recently been allocated to progress treatment for patients on inpatient and day case waiting lists.  Of course, supporting waiting list measures under the winter initiative contributes to ensuring that people receive timely treatment and consequently do not end up requiring emergency care.  I am glad to advise the Senator that the HSE has put in place process improvement plans in all hospitals in order to drive improvements in waiting list management at hospital level.</p> <p>In that context, University Hospital Waterford is arranging to outsource 90 patients from the cardiology waiting list to undergo cardiac diagnostic procedures in public and private facilities.  These 90 patients, referred to by the Senator, have been on the waiting list for over a year and because of this outsourcing initiative, these patients will, I hope, receive their procedure by year-end.  All of these procedures will be undertaken in the Munster area, with the majority being undertaken in Cork University Hospital.  The House will be aware that both Cork University Hospital and University Hospital Waterford are members of the South/South West Hospital Group.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Marcella Corcoran Kennedy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2339"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2339&amp;amp;pid=MarcellaCorcoranKennedy&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am pleased that this hospital group is operating to maximise capacity to diagnostics across the group and that spare capacity in the Cork University Hospital's catheterisation laboratory is being used to address the Waterford waiting list.</p><p>Budget 2017 provides for our longest-waiting patients.  Some &euro;20 million will be allocated to the National Treatment Purchase Fund in 2017 and this will increase to &euro;55 million in 2018.  It is important to note that additional funding will be provided to University Hospital Waterford in 2017 to implement the recommendations of the Herity review, which has been mentioned by Senator Coffey.  In his review of the need for a second catheterisation laboratory at University Hospital Waterford, Dr. Herity recommended that investment be made to enhance cardiology services at the hospital.  Funding will, therefore, be provided to increase the number of weekly catheterisation laboratory sessions currently provided.  This will help to address waiting times and provide improved access for patients.  Details of this investment will be set out in the HSE's national service plan for 2017, which will be brought to the Government shortly.  I have not yet had sight of the plan, but I am looking forward to reading it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#C00200"><p>While I welcome the enhancements that are recommended under the Herity report and University Hospital Waterford should engage in those improvements immediately, I have to say I am disappointed with the statement in the Minister of State's response that "the majority" of patients will continue to be referred from University Hospital Waterford to Cork University Hospital.  The Members of this House who are from Cork will confirm that Cork University Hospital is already experiencing capacity pressures.  I understand that patients are being referred to the Bon Secours Hospital in Cork, which is a private hospital, but the Minister of State did not mention this in her response.  The cost to taxpayers of referring patients to this hospital is far greater then the cost of providing a second mobile catheterisation laboratory in Waterford to deal with the waiting lists.</p> <p>I advise the Minister of State to take into account that some decisions are being made by officials in the Department of Health.  I suspect that an effort is being made within the Department to downgrade cardiac services.  Many of my colleagues share my concerns in this regard.  I welcome the presence in the Chamber of Senator Grace O'Sullivan in support of what I am saying.  We need to act on this.  I ask the Minister of State to engage with the officials in the Department of Health and to write back to me in detail in response to my questions.  What would be the cost to the Department of having these patients transferred into private services?  What would be the cost of providing a mobile catheterisation laboratory, which is the obvious solution the Department should consider?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#C00300"><p>I emphasise that the hospitals across the country are managed by the HSE and not by the Department of Health.  The funding that is obtained by the Minister for Health in the budget is allocated to the HSE, which manages the budgets that are needed to run hospitals.  According to the information I have received from the HSE, there is spare capacity in Cork University Hospital.  There is no reference in the information I have received to patients being referred to the Bon Secours Hospital.  I will make further inquiries for the Senator to ascertain whether such referrals are being made.  It is clear that any spare capacity that exists within our own public hospitals should be used.  The point I would make with regard to the downgrading of cardiac services is that the patient has to be at the centre of everything we are doing and at the heart of the policies being developed by the Department of Health.  It is clear that patients have to come first.  Therefore, the downgrading of any cardiac services would be a retrograde step and would certainly not be condoned.  I will ask the HSE to provide the Senator with the details he has sought with regard to costs.  I will also make inquiries about the use of private hospitals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#C00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#C00500"><p>No problem.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.22" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#C00600">Garda Stations</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#C00700"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#C00800"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting for debate as a Commencement matter the question of the lack of a full and comprehensive Garda station in Maynooth, County Kildare.  I spoke to officials in the Garda Commissioner's office yesterday to confirm some facts, which I will now outline.  Maynooth Garda station opens for two hours a day from Monday to Friday.  The highest ranking officer in the station is a sergeant.  This is an issue of concern in light of a vicious attack that took place outside the local university recently.  I will not go into the details of this ongoing matter, other than to say that the incident has heightened tensions, sensitivities and awareness of security among local residents.  Numerous councillors from all parties have contacted my office in the past two weeks to ask what is going on.  There is an unusual dynamic in Maynooth because there are 14,000 people coming and going on the university campus and a further 16,000 people living in the immediate catchment area.  This means that the Garda station has to police 30,000 people, which is a huge number by any stretch of the imagination.</p> <p>There is a general feeling in the north Kildare area that something needs to be done.  There are Garda stations in Leixlip and in Clane.  The people of Maynooth are crying out for the Garda station in the town to be fully resourced so that it can open seven days a week.  Members of the D&aacute;il from all parties and none have spoken previously at length about the need to do something.  It is certainly not acceptable that the Garda station opens for just two hours a day, five days a week, and is of such limited capacity.  I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, for coming to the House and I look forward to hearing what he feels he can do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#C00900"><p>I am responding to the Senator on behalf of the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality, who cannot be here today, unfortunately.  She sends her apologies to the Senator.</p> <p>I thank Senator Boyhan for raising this important issue.  He will be aware that the Garda Commissioner is responsible for the distribution of resources among the various Garda divisions and that the T&aacute;naiste has no direct role in the matter.  It is a matter for the Garda Commissioner.  As the Senator knows, Maynooth Garda station is in the Leixlip Garda district, which forms part of the Kildare division, and is open from 10 a.m. to 12 noon from Monday to Saturday.  Furthermore, neighbourhood watch and community alert schemes are in place in the Leixlip area.  The district officer in Leixlip attends municipal forum meetings, joint policing committee meetings and other meetings in respect of Maynooth town and its environs.  During the academic year, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na liaises closely with the university security and staff of NUI Maynooth.  Each September, garda&iacute; deliver a presentation to all first year students during freshers' week to address matters like personal safety, general behaviour and community engagement.</p> <p>I am informed that on 31 October last, which is the latest date for which figures are readily available, there were 307 members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na assigned to the Kildare division, 12 of whom were assigned to Maynooth Garda station.  The division is also supported by 22 members of the Garda Reserve and 29 civilian staff.  The work of local garda&iacute; is supported as appropriate by a number of Garda national units, such as the national bureau of criminal investigation, the national economic crime bureau and the national drugs and organised crime bureau.  The 57 Garda vehicles that operate throughout the division provide a highly visible and mobile Garda presence.  Garda management keeps the distribution of resources under continual review to ensure the optimum use is made of them.  This is reflected in the fact that local Garda management in the division has implemented additional policing measures in response to recent incidents, including additional Garda foot patrols, checkpoints and patrols by the regional support unit.</p> <p>A Programme for a Partnership Government recognises community policing as the embodiment of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na because it provides a means of recognising that every community, both urban and rural, has its own concerns and expectations.  It commits the Government to ensuring there is visible, effective and responsive policing in every community, with the most minimal response times possible.  In support of this objective, the T&aacute;naiste has asked the Policing Authority to oversee a review of, among other things, the dispersement of Garda stations in rural areas.  I understand the authority has formally requested the Garda Inspectorate to examine the dispersement and use of resources available to the Garda in the delivery of policing services to local communities and to make recommendations for the provision of a more effective, visible and responsive policing service that takes account of the changing environments in rural, developing, urban and suburban areas; the views of local communities; the allocation to and deployment of Garda resources at local policing level, including the use of the Garda Reserve, Garda facilities and Garda equipment; and relevant recommendations made in previous inspectorate reports.</p> <p>The T&aacute;naiste recently announced that the Government has approved her proposal for an overall Garda workforce of 21,000 personnel by 2021, comprising 15,000 Garda members, 2,000 Garda Reserve members and 4,000 civilians.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy David Stanton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1053"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1053&amp;amp;pid=DavidStanton&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For 2017, funding has been provided for the recruitment of 800 Garda recruits and up to 500 civilians to support the wide-ranging reform plan in train in An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Approximately 300 appointments will also be made to the Garda Reserve.  I understand that since the reopening of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na College, 679 recruits have attested as members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, of whom 35 have been assigned to the Kildare division.  In addition, it is anticipated that in 2017, as recruitment continues, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na will be in a position to allocate more probationer garda&iacute; to the division.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply.  Will he keep this matter under review?  It is unique.  This is more than a rural Garda station.  There are 14,000 students on campus and 16,000 living in the catchment area.  It is unique.  Recent events have heightened the anxiety of people.  I call on the Department and the Minister to keep the issues around the station under review.  I thank the Minister of State for his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1277" speakername="David Stanton" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#D00300"><p>Again, on behalf of the T&aacute;naiste, I thank the Senator for raising this important matter in the House.  As I have stated, the Government is committed to ensuring visible, effective and responsive policing in every community, including by way of minimal possible response times.  In this context, Garda management keeps the distribution of resources under continual review to ensure optimum use is made of these resources.  Garda management has implemented additional policing measures in response to the recent incidents in the Kildare division to which the Senator has referred.  Additional measures include Garda foot patrols, checkpoints and patrols by the regional support unit.  This is in addition to the high level of Garda co-operation with local communities in the Maynooth area and the local university.  The division has already benefited from the Government's accelerated Garda recruitment programme.  It is anticipated that in 2017, as recruitment continues, An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na will be in a position to allocate more probationer garda&iacute; to the division.  Again, I thank the Senator for raising this important matter and for his interest in these vital issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.05 a.m. and resumed at 11.35 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.30" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re appointments to the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business without debate; No. 2, Health Insurance (Amendment) Bill 2016 - Second Stage, to be taken at 1.30 p.m. and to conclude no later than 3 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given five minutes to reply; and No. 3, statements on the funding of Orkambi for cystic fibrosis patients, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 2, with the time allocated to this debate not to exceed one hour and the contribution of Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given five minutes to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#G00300"><p>I want to raise the issue of sentencing policy and the increased use of firearms in this city.  On Tuesday at 4.30 p.m., in broad daylight, armed raiders entered a McDonalds in Crumlin village and terrorised both staff and customers.  This is a quiet residential area where firearms would never be seen.</p> <p>In 2009 minimum mandatory sentences were brought in to deal with firearms and they had a certain welcome effect.  However, I believe we need to go further.  I call on the Minister for Justice and Equality to introduce minimum mandatory sentencing for first-time offenders.  We need to update and strengthen our sentencing laws in regard to gun crime.  It is commonplace in this city for garda&iacute; and drug lords to don their bullet proof vests every morning before going to work.  The carrying of firearms seems to have become commonplace on the streets of our city.  We have to ask what we can do to ensure that the possession of firearms does not become commonplace among our citizens.  I ask the Minister to attend the House for a proper debate about strengthening sentencing laws in regard to firearms and codifying and making consistent firearms law in order to protect our citizens and communities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#G00400"><p>I want to raise the ongoing debacle over the auction of the P&aacute;draig Pearse surrender letter, which is of immense importance to this State.  I attended a protest last night.  What I cannot understand is that the Government is, at huge expense to the taxpayer, appealing the decision of the High Court in regard to Moore Street and securing that monument after years of failure by various Governments, but it does not want to spend money purchasing this letter.  I cannot understand this, given the year that is in it, of all years.  Obviously, it is being sold to take advantage of the 100th anniversary of 1916 and to increase the potential.</p> <p>Last night, it did not meet the &euro;1 million threshold they had hoped for and they are now looking for an export licence for this letter which, in my opinion, should be the property of the Irish people for future generations to celebrate our heroes.  The owner says he feels relieved of his responsibilities because the State or the Minister are not going to purchase this letter.  I ask that the Leader would bring this to the attention of the Minister, Deputy Heather Humphreys, and the Taoiseach.  I assume everybody in this House supports the call that the State would purchase this letter-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#G00500"><p>I do not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#G00600"><p>-----and secure it in a museum.  I assume that is the case.  The Government has a choice.  It can spend a fortune appealing a High Court decision against the families of the 1916 leaders but it cannot purchase this letter.  I will let people out there make their decision about the logic of all of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#G00700"><p>In times of darkness, it was great to see a positive light being shone on Europe recently, with the election of the Austrian President, Alexander 'Sascha' Van der Bellen.  On behalf of all of my Green colleagues across Europe, I welcome this great election.  Hopefully, other countries will take some lead from Austria so we can work towards a united Europe, as I believe that united we stand, divided we fall.  This man is taking the lead in Austria.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#G00800"><p>I ask the Leader to amend the Order of Business to introduce a new Bill which I drafted, along with my Labour Party colleagues, the Pensions (Equal Pension Treatment in Occupational Benefit Scheme) (Amendment) Bill 2016.  I know my colleague, Senator Norris, will be seconding it.  The Bill aims to do the same thing that Senator Norris's proposed amendment to the Finance Bill sought to do yesterday, which is to address an ongoing discrimination against LGBT employees in pension schemes which required that they be married or enter into civil partnership before a specific date in order for their partners to qualify for survivor's benefit.  This arises out of a case taken by David Parris against Trinity College Dublin which is before the European Court of Justice.  Just a week ago, Mr. Parris unfortunately lost the case but there is nothing in European law to stop us introducing in our own domestic law a provision to ensure people will not be discriminated against just because they could not enter a legal marriage before a particular date.</p> <p>This is an ongoing discrimination.  Even after the great result in the marriage equality referendum in 2015, we still see people who, like Mr. Parris, could not have entered a legal marriage or a civil partnership before the necessary date, in his case, the date of his 60th birthday, in order to achieve certain benefits and entitlements under the occupational pensions scheme.  This Bill would only affect a small number of people but it will address a very serious continuing issue of discrimination for those people.  As I said, Senator Norris sought to address this by way of amendment to the Finance Bill.  This is an alternative way to address it, namely, by introducing a Bill which will amend the pensions legislation to ensure people in Mr. Parris's position do not suffer ongoing discrimination.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ivana Bacik:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2248"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2248&amp;amp;pid=IvanaBacik&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is in tandem with the Bill that Senator Nash introduced this week to resolve the problem of individuals having offences on their record for acts that were decriminalised in 1993, after the decriminalisation of homosexuality.  People are still suffering a chilling effect.  This has been a huge issue in Britain and Senator Nash has called for an amnesty or pardon for those people to have their convictions effectively struck from the record given that the intercourse was no longer criminalised after 1993.</p><p>Can the Leader organise a debate on judicial appointments in light of the comments-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H00200"><p>I take it that it that the Senator is proposing is that No. 12 be taken before No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H00300"><p>Yes that is what I should have said.  I would thank the Leader if he is willing to exceed to that request.</p> <p>I would like a debate on judicial appointments in light of the comments by the chairperson of the Free Legal Advice Centres, FLAC, Peter Ward, about the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross's, highly critical comments on the Judiciary, pointing out very serious issues around the encroachment of the Executive on the powers of the Judiciary.  There has been a serious delay in the appointment of further judges and, as a result, there are delays in people accessing the legal system.  FLAC has a really proud record of standing for the rights of individuals and their access to the courts, notably in the case of Dr. Lydia Foy, whose litigation ultimately led to the passing of the Gender Recognition Act 2015.</p> <p>I wish T.K. Whitaker a very happy 100th birthday.  I note his enormous service to this State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H00400"><p>We all join the Senator in that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H00500"><p>I also congratulate T.K. Whitaker on his 100th birthday.  He is the architect of modern Ireland.  He got rid of the protectionist policies and effectively opened up free trade.  He was Secretary General of the Department of Finance having joined the Civil Service in 1934.  He was named Irishman of the century in 2002.  I thank him for his work, now that he is 100 years young.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H00600"><p>I have received correspondence about the Irish Coast Guard and the lack of legislation which covers it.  As a medic working on the west coast I regularly liaise closely with our coast guard service and experience first-hand its members' bravery and commitment to serving the public while putting their own lives in danger.  They face peril on every call out.</p> <p>Yesterday, family members of missing people gathered in Farmleigh House to mark National Missing Persons Day.  At the event the Minister of State at the Department of Justice and Equality, Deputy Stanton, thanked members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na for their work and continued support for those families whose loved ones are missing.  He also said it is important to remember Irish Coast Guard volunteer Catriona Lucas, who gave her life in the line of duty in September of this year.  Ms Lucas was the first volunteer coast guard to die in the course of duty and her tragic death brought home the true nature of the job.  They really are unsung heroes.</p> <p>It is quite unbelievable, therefore, that their work as a primary response agency is not afforded protection under legislation.  A few weeks ago the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, addressed this House and said safety at sea is vital to this island nation.  I commend the Irish Coast Guard, the volunteers, the Royal National Lifeboat Institution, RNLI, and all involved in ensuring safety at sea on their bravery, remarkable courage and heroism in the service of others.  These salutations are well meant and well placed but they are not enough.  More needs to be done to enshrine in law the duties, roles and rights of our coast guard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H00700"><p>"Is it little more than a fiction that Parliament and Government are sovereign? [...] Are Governments nowadays to be compared to the totally deaf Beethoven in his later years, just being allowed to go through the motions of conducting the orchestra while the real control is being exercised elsewhere?"  This is a quote from T.K. Whitaker, dated over 30 years ago.  I too wish him a happy birthday.  He has done an excellent job in the public interest and for this State.</p> <p>Last night, psychiatrist Peter Rice from Scotland addressed the Irish Cancer Society.  He is the chair of the executive committee of the Scottish Health Action on Alcohol Problems.  It is telling that this series of talks around the country, hosted by the Irish Cancer Society, is called "Decoding Cancer".  A total of 900 incidents of cancer are directly related to alcohol intake and 500 deaths a year are due to alcohol-related cancers.  This is important because we will be discussing and hopefully passing the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill 2015.  Awareness of alcohol as a cancer-causing agent is very low.  People are aware of cirrhosis of the liver and so on but women in particular should be aware of the incidence of breast cancer which rises as alcohol consumption by women is rising.  I would like the Leader to support the presentation by the Irish Cancer Society to decode cancer for Members of this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H00800"><p>In the last Seanad the Seanad Public Consultation Committee produced a comparative report on the damage that alcohol causes and cancer.  It was very successful.  I can empathise with the Senator&rsquo;s point of view while being Cathaoirleach and impartial.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H00900"><p>I second Senator Bacik&rsquo;s amendment to the Order of Business.  This is a matter that we have all been pursuing.  I instanced it first at the passage of the Civil Partnership and Certain Rights and Obligations of Cohabitants Bill 2010 because this was an anomaly then affecting the Civil Service.  Subsequently David Parris took an action which I am sorry he lost.</p><p>A couple of days ago I received a telephone call from a very old friend of mine, Victor Griffin, the former dean of St. Patrick's Cathedral.  He is 93 and had been sent home from Altnagelvin Hospital to die of cancer.  As a Christian he is quite happy with that and is in no distress at all.  He wanted T.K. Whitaker's address because he wanted to write to him as an old friend and colleague to congratulate him on his 100th birthday.</p><p>This is something well worth doing.  I am glad it has been raised by my colleagues here.  He was a very distinguished Member of this House.  He was very young when he entered the Civil Service in a senior position.  For a while the great poet Thomas Kinsella was his private secretary, which is a rather curious and interesting fact.  He was also instrumental in improving relations between the South and the North of this country.  He entered discussions with the private secretary to the Prime Minister of Northern Ireland which led to meetings between Sean Lemass and Captain Terence O'Neill.  He worked with the Ford Foundation to launch the Economic and Social Research Institute and for a long time he was president or chairman of that institute.  He was chancellor of the National University of Ireland, president of the Royal Irish Academy, a member of the Board of Governors of the Guardians of the National Gallery of Ireland and he had a great love of the Irish language.  The seminal collection of Irish poetry, <i>An Duanaire: Poems of the Dispossessed 1600-1900</i>, was dedicated to him.</p><p>It is also interesting and very heartening that on an RTE television programme which held a mass vote for the greatest Irishman of the 20th century, which Senator Feighan mentioned, he was up against all kinds of armed revolutionaries such as Michael Collins and beat the hell out of them.  That is a terrific tribute to the feeling of the Irish people for the parliamentary democratic tradition of this country.  I am very happy to wish the former Senator T.K. Whitaker a very happy birthday.  I am sure the whole House would want to do this too.  I only had the pleasure of meeting him once.  He was a friend of former Senator Feargal Quinn who last year gave a lunch party in his honour and I had the opportunity to exchange a few words with him then.  He is a great Irishman.  We are all living with the positive benefits of the economic plan that he conceived.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H01000"><p>I call the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H01100"><p>That was a short Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H01200"><p>We kept the best wine to the last.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#H01300"><p>I thank the eight Senators who contributed to the Order of Business.  I join those who have acknowledged today the centenary of the birth of T.K. Whitaker and I wish him a happy 100th birthday.  It is important to acknowledge and pay tribute to him today as a former Member of this House, appointed by both Jack Lynch and Garret FitzGerald, which was a sign of his ability to override political divides.  He has rightly been described as the Irishman of the last century and his contribution is one that we should underline in respect of the new modern Ireland.  We can differ about ideology and politics but T.K. Whitaker put in place the structure that is now Ireland, economic and otherwise.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I acknowledge his contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J00200"><p>If Mr. Whitaker keeps going as he is, and he may well do - I wish him the best because I had the privilege to meet him once or twice - he may also become the Irishman of this century.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J00300"><p>True.  That is a fair point.</p> <p>It is important - something we do not do enough in this country - to pay tribute and recognise greatness, no matter who they are.  T.K. Whitaker is certainly a person who, for all of us as young people growing up, was the person who we looked up to.  He was the architect of modern Ireland.  I wish him well and thank him for his service.  His life is the epitome of what good public service should be.  On behalf of all us, I wish him well and a happy 100th birthday.</p> <p>Senator Ardagh raised the issue of firearms and sentencing.  The Senator is right to raise the matter in terms of the issue around the right to bear arms and the way in which people are using it at present.  It is a tragedy.  It is an awful indictment that we have people masquerading with guns in the streets of Dublin, in particular, and killing and injuring people.  There was an incident in my native city of Cork last night.  I would be happy to have the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality come into the House in regard to the issue of firearms and licensing.</p> <p>Senator Mac Lochlainn raised the issue of the P&aacute;draig Pearse letter and the Senator makes a valid point in terms of its importance.  On foot of reading the exchange in the D&aacute;il between the leader of Sinn F&eacute;in and the Taoiseach, I note the Taoiseach has stated the Government is not in a position to buy it.  I note from talking to the Minister, Deputy Heather Humphreys, that her departmental officials have spoken to Adam's auctioneers.  Her officials also have spoken to other stakeholders in the cultural institutions on the price of the letter.  One cannot perhaps put a value on it, but as for the value of &euro;1 million to &euro;1.5 million - it has been withdrawn from auction - my information is that such expenditure would not be value for money.  I am not in any way trying to put a value on it.  It is important that we preserve a lot of letters, paraphernalia and artifacts.  We have some very valuable pieces, including letters and clothing, and the Government has bought Nos. 14 to 17 Moore Street.  We have invested &euro;5 million in Kilmainham Courthouse and another &euro;5 million in the Military Archives.  I hope that we will not allow the letter to be taken overseas.  In an ideal world, the letter should be kept here as part of an exhibition.  It is something I, on behalf of the House, can communicate to the Minister that has been raised this morning here.</p> <p>Like Senator Grace O'Sullivan, I congratulate the new President of Austria on his re-election and wish him well.</p> <p>On Senator Bacik's amendment to the Order of Business, I would be happy to accept the amendment and I commend her on the work that she is doing in terms of the Pensions (Equal Pension Treatment in Occupational Benefit Scheme) (Amendment) Bill 2016.  We had a discussion here on the Order of Business yesterday on judicial appointments and I would be happy to have the Minister come to the House.</p> <p>Senator Swanick raised the issue of the Coast Guard and the lack of primary legislation in that area.  Senator Lombard raised it two weeks ago in the House as well.  It is a matter for the Departments to work out, but Senator Swanick is correct that the men and women who serve in the Coast Guard are first responders as well.  They provide a significant service to the State, saving lives and rescuing people, and putting their own lives at risk in the process.  We can revisit that in the new year and we will have the Minister come to the House.</p> <p>Senator Devine raised the important connection between cancer and alcohol.  I would be happy to work with the Senator on the issue.  It is important that we have the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill 2015 back in the new year and that we can reduce the harm that the misuse of alcohol can bring.  The Cathaoirleach rightly said that the Seanad Public Consultation Committee in the previous Seanad did a powerful piece of work on alcohol.  It is an issue that we can revisit because it is one that will not go away.  It needs cross-party and Independent support to keep this message up.  In particular, Senator Devine is correct to link the issue of women and cancer.  It is something that we have to be vigilant on.  It transcends the political divide.  I would be happy to talk about that and move that along in the new year with the Senator.</p> <p>Senator Norris raised the issue of the Parris case, seconded Senator Bacik's amendment to the Order of Business and spoke of T.K. Whitaker.  I do not quite get what Senator Norris mentioned about the former dean of St. Patrick's Cathedral.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J00400"><p>It was just that he is an old friend.  Even though he is very ill and he is 93, he contacted me because he wanted to write a note of congratulations.  That is what alerted me first to the fact that it was T.K. Whitaker's 100th birthday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J00500"><p>Okay.  I missed that.</p> <p>That is probably the quickest reply the Cathaoirleach will get to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J00600"><p>Senator Bacik has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 12 be taken before No. 1."  The Leader has indicated he is prepared to accept this amendment.  Is the amendment agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.57" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.58" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J00800">Pensions (Equal Pension Treatment in Occupational Benefit Scheme) (Amendment) Bill 2016: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J00900"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the provisions of the Pension Act 1990 relative to equal pension treatment in occupational benefit schemes in order to provide for cases where employees who were unable to marry persons of the same sex may be deprived of certain pension benefits, and to provide for related matters.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J01000"><p>Is there a seconder?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J01100"><p>I second the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.62" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J01300"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J01400"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J01500"><p>Is that agreed? Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.66" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 13 December 2016.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.67" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J01700">Garda Sochna Ombudsman Commission: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#J01800"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann, noting that the Government-(a) on 27th September, 2016 nominated Ms. Justice Mary Ellen Ring for reappointment by the President as a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission and as its chairperson, recommends, pursuant to section 65(1)(<i>b</i>) of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005, that she be reappointed by the President to be a member and to be chairperson of the Commission; and<br /><br />(b) on 6th December, 2016 nominated Mr. Kieran FitzGerald for reappointment and Mr. Mark Toland for appointment by the President as members of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Ombudsman Commission, recommends, pursuant to section 65(1)(<i>b</i>) of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005, that Mr. Kieran FitzGerald be reappointed and Mr. Mark Toland be appointed, by the President to be members of the Commission.&quot;</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.69" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.70" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.55 a.m. until 1.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.71" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#T00100">Health Insurance (Amendment) Bill 2016: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.72" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#T00300"><p>I am pleased to have the opportunity to address the House regarding the Bill, which concluded its passage through the D&aacute;il last week.  More than 2 million people in Ireland have private health insurance, which is community rated.  This means that when someone purchases health insurance, their age, gender and health status does not affect the price they pay.  Older and sicker people pay the same price as younger and healthier people.  Our community-rated health insurance market means that the cost of health insurance is shared across all members of the market.  In general, everyone, with certain exceptions, can buy the same policy at the same price.  Older and sicker people pay much less for health insurance than they would in a risk rated market and people who are less likely to need health care pay more than they would in a risk-rated market.  Our market is based on generational solidarity.  Younger and healthier people effectively subsidise older people who may be less well and need more care.</p> <p>Community rating means that health insurers must offer health insurance policies at the same price to everyone, regardless of a person&rsquo;s current or potential health status.  There are a limited number of exemptions to this, including lower prices for children and young adults and higher prices for people purchasing health insurance for the first time after the age of 34.  Community rating is a different concept from the usual way of selling insurance premiums.  In risk-rated markets, the premium charged is based on the insurer&rsquo;s estimate of each person's risk, taking into account relevant factors such as age and existing medical conditions.  Healthier people pay low premiums and sicker people pay high premiums.  The premium for someone who has held health insurance for many years will rise if his or her health deteriorates under a risk-rated system.  Our system of community rating ensures members are not penalised for getting older or for developing an illness.</p> <p>In 2015, private health insurers in Ireland paid out &euro;2.1 billion in claims.  Average claims costs vary significantly for different age groups.  In a community-rated market like ours, the risks are shared across the market as a whole.  This means health insurance is more affordable for sicker and older people than it would be in a risk-rated market.  While community rating does not tell insurers what price they can charge, it ensures that they charge everyone the same price.  We have community rating because we want to ensure that the cost of private health insurance is shared between everyone who decides to buy it.  Community rating provides all insured people with peace of mind and also the certainty that if they get sick, their health insurance premium will not increase as a result.</p> <p>The Health Insurance Act requires all insurers to apply community rating.  However, older and sicker customers are not shared equally across the market because of the relatively recent arrival of competition.  This is the crux of the issue.  Some insurers have worse risk profiles than others given that they have a much higher proportion of older members.  In a competitive community-rated market like ours, insurers have a strong incentive to try to attract low-risk people and avoid those who are high risk.  Claims costs for older individuals can be up to 25 times higher than those for younger people.  Insurers, understandably, want to attract healthy people and they do this by advertising in a particular way or by offering additional benefits that appeal to younger and healthier customers.  They try to avoid sicker people by designing products that don&rsquo;t provide services that older and sicker people are more likely to need.  We do not want insurers to compete like this; we want them to compete by offering better health insurance products to everyone at lower cost.</p> <p>In order to support community rating and reduce the incentives for insurers to target or avoid particular groups of people, some form of risk equalisation is required.  This policy objective has been shared by many political groups in the House in recent years.  Community-rated health insurance systems across the world use risk equalisation to share some of the higher costs of older and sicker patients across the entire  market.  The US, Australia, Germany and the Netherlands are a few examples of other countries that use risk equalisation to support community-rated health insurance markets.  Risk equalisation supports community rating by providing cross-subsidies between insurers with different risk profiles.  It aims to neutralise, in an equitable manner, the differences in insurers&rsquo; costs that arise due to variations in the age and risk profile of the insured members.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Risk equalisation is a transfer mechanism whereby money flows from insurers with healthier members to insurers with sicker members.  The overall goal is to channel competition in the health insurance market in a way which benefits everyone who wishes to purchase private health insurance.  Risk equalisation reduces insurers&rsquo; incentives to attract only low risk consumers or to charge higher prices for products that are marketed to high-risk people.</p><p>A permanent risk equalisation scheme was introduced in Ireland in 2013.  Under the scheme, credits are paid to all insurers for their older and sicker members.  These credits are funded directly by stamp duty levies on all health insurance contracts written.  In effect, the scheme redistributes funds between insurers in order to meet some of the additional costs of insuring older and sicker members.  The scheme is self-financing and Exchequer-neutral.  It is how we share the cost of insurance between all insured people and ensure that sicker and older people are treated fairly.  </p><p>As well as sharing the cost of insurance, we also want to keep private health insurance affordable for those who wish to purchase it.  This is done in a number of ways.  Insurers must compete with each other to attract customers.  In a competitive market insurers have a strong incentive to manage their costs and offer insurance at the best possible price.  Premiums have increased in recent years.  The prices of individual policies have gone up.  However, the average premium paid by people buying health insurance has not increased to the same extent.  By exploring lower-cost options with the same level of cover, people have avoided paying the very large increases in premiums that they might otherwise have experienced.  The State also supports affordable health insurance in a number of ways, including by providing tax relief at source of up to &euro;200 for everyone with private health insurance.</p><p>Supporting affordability in an ageing market is a challenge.  The Society of Actuaries in Ireland estimates that the ageing of the private health insurance market accounted for approximately 2.5% of the increase in claims costs each year between 2009 and 2015.  This consists of ageing of the overall population, a lower proportion of younger people with cover and a higher proportion of older people with cover.  The society estimates that claims costs will increase by 1.7% per year in the next ten years due to market ageing.  Attracting younger and healthier people into the market reduces the average cost of insurance across the market.</p><p>In 2015, we introduced lifetime community rating.  Loadings now apply when someone buys health insurance for the first time from the age of 35.  This measure has encouraged and will continue to encourage people to take out health insurance at a younger age.  We also introduced young adult rates up to the age of 25 to smooth the transition to full adult rates.  This measure encourages younger people to retain their health insurance.  I am pleased to say that the number of people insured increased last year by over 100,000 following the introduction of lifetime community rating and young adult rates.  This also reflects positive employment trends, which are a key driver of the demand for insurance.  This upward trend continues, with a further increase of almost 18,000 in the first nine months of this year.</p><p>Legislation is needed each year to update the amount of credits paid to insurers under the risk equalisation scheme and the amounts of stamp duty levied on health insurance contracts to fund the credits.  The Health Insurance Authority carries out an evaluation of the market and recommends the level of credits that should apply in the following year.  This analysis is supported by my Department&rsquo;s actuarial advisers.  The Minister has considered and accepted the recommendations made by the authority.  Higher credits will be required under the scheme next year for a number of reasons.  Claims costs have increased.  Payments to public hospitals have also increased as a result of the changes to charging regimes for private patients in public hospitals.  The market has continued to age and insurers must also cover the cost of medical innovations in treatments and new drugs.  No changes are proposed to the existing level of hospital utilisation credits provided to insurers under the scheme.  These remain at &euro;30 for each day case admission and &euro;90 for each overnight stay.</p><p>The Minister proposes to significantly increase the age-related credits paid to insurers in respect of older people.  For example, the credits for women aged 85 years and over holding advanced cover will increase by 33% to &euro;3,700.  The credits for men aged 75 to 79 years holding non-advanced products will increase by 49% to &euro;1,750.  This means that all insurers with 85 year old female members with advanced cover will get &euro;925 more credits in 2017 over 2016, while insurers with 75 to 79 year old males holding non-advanced cover will get &euro;575 more in credits.  This is a reasonable measure to reduce the average cost of insuring older people.</p><p>Due to the fact that the scheme is designed to be self-financing, the total amount of credits provided matches the stamp duties raised.  The stamp duty on health insurance products will increase by 10%.  This means that the stamp duty on advanced cover products for adults will increase from &euro;403 to &euro;444 and on non-advanced products will increase from &euro;202 to &euro;320.  It is important to note that increasing the stamp duty levies does not increase costs across the market.  This is a very important point and one which various commentators in the media need to remember.  We need to encourage our insurance companies not to use this as an excuse to hike up insurance premiums and we certainly do not need people defending it as an excuse.  All money raised is paid back to insurers in the form of credits.  Increasing the credits and stamp duties under the scheme is needed to continue to share costs across the market.  The examples of increases in credits clearly show that the levy increases should not equal higher premiums.  The amount of any increase or reduction that individual insurers pass on to consumers is a commercial decision for each of them.  It is important to note that all of the money raised in stamp duty levies under this scheme goes back to insurers in order to ensure that we continue with our community-rated scheme, which provides support to older and sicker people with health insurance.</p><p>In previous years, the revised credits and stamp duties have come into effect from 1 March.  This year, the proposed effective date for the revised credits and stamp duties is 1 April.  This change in date will facilitate the administration of stamp duty collection by the Revenue Commissioners and provide an additional month&rsquo;s notice to insurers.</p><p>While the changes to the credits will help to maintain existing levels of support for community rating - sometimes referred to as the effectiveness of the risk equalisation scheme - I am pleased to note that further improvements are planned.  The Minister is committed to making the risk equalisation scheme as effective as possible in a way that promotes fair and open competition.  The introduction of a more refined measure of health status for the allocation of credits between insurers is required.  Using diagnosis-related group, DRG, data in the future will allow for better targeting of credits to all people who require higher levels of health care.  We need to ensure that the support provided in the form of credits is getting to where we want it to be in the market.  Refining the health status measure using DRG data will further reduce the incentive for insurers to attract low-risk people and avoid high-risk people.  Introducing this change will take time as there are complex data collection and system issues to be addressed.  The Minister has asked his officials to focus on progressing this, in conjunction with the Health Insurance Authority, in the months ahead.</p><p>The risk equalisation scheme was approved by the European Commission earlier this year as a compatible state aid for the period 2016 to 2020.  The scheme underwent detailed examination by the Commission to ensure it is administered in a fair and transparent manner and does not unduly distort competition in the market.</p><p>As part of the process of achieving Commission approval, two changes to the scheme are proposed in the legislation before the House.  First, the Health Insurance (Amendment) Bill 2016 provides for a new objective to be considered by the Health Insurance Authority when recommending the level of credits to apply under the scheme.  The net projected average claims cost for all age groups aged 65 and over should not be less than 125% of the projected market average net claims costs.  This limits the amount of credits that can be provided under the scheme while allowing credits to increase in monetary terms to reflect any claims cost inflation.  As Minister for Health, Deputy Harris must also have regard to this objective.  Second, the measure of reasonable profit, used to ensure that no insurer is overcompensated by the risk equalisation scheme, will be defined as an average return on sales, gross of reinsurance and excluding investment income, of 4.4% or less over a three-year period.  Using return on sales to measure reasonable profit has a number of advantages over the existing return on equity measure.  It is based on easily observable accounting profit and sales data and it avoids the valuation and allocation of assets between different services.  These proposed changes to the operation of the scheme will ensure that competition between insurers is protected.</p><p>People are naturally concerned about any increase in the price of health insurance.  While both the Health Insurance Authority and I would encourage people to keep their options open and compare between insurers to obtain the best value, I also understand that it can be difficult to make a decision when there are so many products on the market.  This is a real problem.  There are many products offering similar benefits at very different prices and it is not easy to pick the best option when so many products are available.  The market needs to be simplified.  I am pleased to see that the number of products on the market has decreased in the past year from 381 to 354.  I hope to see this downward trend continue and I encourage our insurance companies to continue to simplify the list of products that are available to customers so it is easier for them to compare and contrast policies and their cost.  The Health Insurance Authority has launched an information campaign to advise consumers of the significant savings that can be made at policy renewal time by actively reviewing their health cover to ensure they are getting the best value.  This comes on foot of research conducted on behalf of the Health Insurance Authority which found that only one quarter of policy holders have switched providers at any time since taking out private health insurance.  Keeping consumers informed of their rights and options is a key priority in supporting community rating.</p><p>This Bill provides further clarity for insurers about when they can withdraw products from the market.  It also ensures that when a person's existing plan is withdrawn, they will be offered a plan which provides at least the same level of benefits as their current one.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These proposed changes will mean that the existing lifetime cover regulations are no longer required and the Minister will revoke them in due course.<br/><br/>I will now briefly outline the specific sections of the Bill.  Section 1 defines the principal Act as the Health Insurance Act 1994.  Section 2 substitutes subsection 7AB(3) with a new subsection that provides that insurers cannot change a plan from advanced cover to non-advanced cover or <i>vice versa</i>except on 1 April each year from 2017 onwards.  This is a technical amendment to facilitate the administration of stamp duty levies.<br/><br/>Section 3(a)(i) is a technical amendment to section 7E of the principal Act to delete the reference to &quot;bed&quot;.  Section 3(a)(ii) is an amendment to section 7E of the principal Act, which provides that the Health Insurance Authority must have regard to the objective that the projected net average insurance claim payment per insured person for a relevant group of insured persons should not be less than 125% of the projected net average insurance claim payment per insured person for all age groups, which is a point I outlined a moment ago.  Section 3(b) is an amendment to section 7E of the principal Act, which requires the Minister for Health also to have regard to this objective.  Section 3(c) inserts a new subsection 7E(4), which provides for definitions of &quot;net&quot; relating to the average insurance claim payment per insured person and &quot;relevant age group of insured persons&quot;.<br/><br/>Section 4 amends section 7F of the principal Act to provide that from 2016 onwards, a reasonable profit for the purposes of determining over-compensation of a net beneficiary of the scheme is defined as a return on sales gross of reinsurance and excluding investment income that does not exceed 4.4% per annum over a three-year period.<br/><br/>Section 5 amends section 9 of the principal Act to set out the circumstances when a health insurer can withdraw products from the market.  It also provides that when a particular product is withdrawn from the market by an insurer, people holding the product being withdrawn from the market must be offered a replacement contract with the same level of benefits, subject to small differences in excess amounts.<br/><br/>Section 6 amends section 11C of the principal Act.  It provides for 1 April 2017 as the effective date for revised risk equalisation credits to be payable from the risk equalisation fund.  Section 7 replaces table 2 in Schedule 4 to the principal Act with effect from 1 April 2017.  The risk equalisation credits payable from the risk equalisation fund for certain classes of insured persons are revised.<br/><br/>Section 8 amends section 125A of the Stamp Duties Consolidation Act 1999.  It specifies the applicable stamp duty rates from 1 January 2017 to 31 March 2017 and from 1 April 2017 onwards.  Section 9 provides for the Short Title, collective citation, commencement dates and construction of the Bill.  Sections 5 and 8 will come into operation on 1 January.  Sections 6 and 7 will come into operation on 1 April.  All other sections will come into operation when the Bill is enacted.<br/><br/>This annual adjustment of the credits and levies under the risk equalisation scheme provides us with an opportunity to reflect on the role of private health insurance in the health service.  One of the first priorities the Minister identified when he took office was the need for a long-term consensus on the direction of health policy.  To help achieve this, the Committee on the Future of Healthcare has been established to devise cross-party agreement on a single long-term vision for health care and direction of health policy in Ireland.  I have no doubt the current and potential role of private health insurance both as a source of funding for the health service and as a driver of the model of care people receive will be considered as part of the committee's work.  We look forward to receiving the committee's deliberations.  Through the work of the committee, I hope we will be able to articulate clearly our desired model of care, the implications of moving towards it and how it can be achieved.<br/><br/>We want to move towards a sustainable public health service in which all our citizens can have confidence and trust that they can access the care they need when they need it.  In the meantime, we must maintain our support for the core principle of community-rated private health insurance.  By revising the credits and the stamp duties required to fund those credits to take account of market trends, we can continue to provide the necessary support to ensure the costs of health insurance are shared across the insured population.  We must not fall into the trap of believing spin on this matter.  These stamp duties go to our insurers, every single cent of them, to ensure our sicker and older patients can continue to access private health insurance without being penalised for being older or sicker.  It is a principle we, as a House, have valued and it is a principle that should not be used by private health insurance companies to exploit customers.<br/><br/>I commend the Bill to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#V00200"><p>I welcome the opportunity to speak to this Bill and welcome the Minister of State to the House.  Fianna F&aacute;il will be supporting this Bill, although it is disappointing that risk equalisation levies are set to increase in 2017.  The Health Insurance Authority, which regulates health insurance, states the increases are designed to support risk equalisation and sustain community rating in our health insurance market in order that older citizens and people with illnesses can afford health insurance and are not discriminated against in favour of younger, healthier people.  Risk equalisation and community rating is something we have always supported as a party.</p> <p>The Bill provides for a 10% increase in health insurance stamp duty levies, as recommended by the Health Insurance Authority.  Stamp duty in respect of products providing advance cover is to be set at &euro;444 per adult, an increase of &euro;41, and &euro;148 per child, a rise of &euro;14.  Whereas we accept the judgment of the regulator as to what is needed to maintain stability in the market, this is a very big increase.  A big problem with the levy is that it is a flat levy, so it is socially regressive from a taxation perspective.  Somebody who pays &euro;700 for a plan has a levy of &euro;444, the same as somebody who pays over &euro;5,000 for a plan, which is nonsensical.  There is no other stamp duty that operates like this within the system.  VHI competitors feel the flat rate of the levy acts as an advantage for VHI, as it has the highest premiums in the market and hence is most advantaged by putting in place a flat levy.  It is the case that the flat levy means that those on the lowest plans are paying disproportionately more than those on higher plans.</p> <p>There is another issue that arises with the levy, particularly the fact that the full levy is payable the moment a person pays his or her first premium, even if it is subsequently cancelled.  Credits are only provided on a monthly basis and this mismatch causes problems that have previously led to a surplus in the scheme, pocketed by the Revenue Commissioners.  In 2009, Fine Gael claimed a &euro;160 levy was anti-competitive and a means to prop up the State-dominated player, while VHI remained super-dominant in the health insurance market.  The levy has increased from &euro;160 to &euro;444.  Our values as a party are to support older and sicker people.  It is not just from a sense of obligation but because we respect and value older people and the dignity of each person in his or her illness, medical condition or disability.  That is why while in government we decided on a comprehensive set of actions to support older and sicker people who have private health insurance.  We are firm in our view that the principle of solidarity should apply in private health insurance as well as in public health services.</p> <p>Private health insurance has played an important role in funding and organising health care in our country for more than 50 years.  In 2010, it was funding &euro;1.7 billion of health care claims.  As the Minister of State knows, in excess of 2 million people in this country have private health insurance cover and among them nearly 340,000 people are aged 60 and over.  Many have been paying for health insurance all their adult lives and have the entirely fair expectation that the health insurance market will not be permitted to change in a way that diminishes their cover.  It is entirely right for people to expect that they would not face higher health insurance prices just because of their age or a particular medical condition.  This is because consistent State policy has been that the health insurance market should be community rated, and people have known and relied upon this.</p> <p>Irish Life Health has indicated the largest provider of hospital services in the State to the private sector is the Health Service Executive, HSE, which now receives in excess of &euro;620 million from private health insurance.  Additionally, it is estimated that consultants working for the HSE also receive in excess of &euro;140 million from fees generated from private work in public hospitals.  Irish Life Health also indicates that the evolution of legislation within the health insurance market has led to private health insurers being forced to drive customers into public hospitals and public bed charges have created a situation where public hospitals have a financial incentive to prioritise private patients over public patients, which is morally wrong.  This has created inequity for public and private patients, who in effect pay twice to receive the same service.  Private patients are charged &euro;813 per night for the same public bed or, in some cases, the same trolley.  Normally, they would be seen by the same consultant they would have as a public patient.  These people have paid for the service through taxation so they have a double hit.  The logical conclusion is that if equity is to be achieved within the public health system, the HSE should cease providing all private health care services and concentrate services on public health.  This would require additional funding for the HSE and a fundamental reassessment of the reimbursement model for consultants working within the HSE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#W00100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank her for bringing forward this legislation.  I agree with my colleague.  We are concerned when any levy is increased.  That is the challenge we face over the next 15 or 20 years.  If one looks at the growth of the population over 66, it will continue to increase.  Pensions alone will cost an extra &euro;200 million per annum because of the increase in the number of people who are reaching retirement.  There will be an average of 20,000 people per annum added to the number of people entitled to draw an old age pension.  That is also reflected in the change in the health services.  The one frightening figure we find in health services is that 51% of all hospital beds are occupied by people over 66 years of age.  We will have a growing problem over the next ten to 15 years.</p> <p>My understanding is that the number of people over 66 will be approximately 1 million by 2030.  It is around 600,000 at present.  Therefore, we will face a major challenge in this area.  It is something we need to look at.  We also need to look at the fact that, per head of population, the cost of health care in this country is higher than in other EU countries.  How can we continue to improve and increase the level of services we provide while at the same time ensuring we get cost efficiency?  We will have another debate later on about the cost of a particular drug but we seem to have a major problem in this country with the overall cost of pharmaceuticals.  That is part of the huge costs in our health service.  If one looks at the Department of Health and the HSE budget, it is &euro;14.5 billion this year.  There is another &euro;3.5 billion to &euro;4 billion for private health care across a whole range of areas.  We are talking about over &euro;18 billion per annum in health care.  That will continue to increase.  In order to keep people paying for insurance, there has to be risk equalisation.  This is the fairest way of doing that.  While no one welcomes any increase, unfortunately because of the changing demographics, it is likely to continue.  I note where the changes have come in.  The other area where it is increasing is in the over-85 age group, which has increased by over 20% over a very short time period of six to seven years.  In the Bill, the contribution for someone over 85 is &euro;3,700 per annum.  It will obviously be a growing figure each year.  I welcome the Bill.  We have to continue with this equalisation process.</p> <p>While we welcome that an additional 100,000 people have begun paying for private health insurance in the past 12 months, that will probably level off.  Other challenges such as the cost of renting and buying housing will have a knock-on effect when trying to increase the numbers of young people who have private health insurance.  If we do not increase the numbers, the problem is that risk equalisation will have to continue and will increase the cost.  That is one of the challenges we face.  We need to look constantly at how we can make the system more efficient and deliver a top of the range service while at the same time not increase additional costs.</p> <p>I will touch on one other issue with people paying private health insurance which I came across as recently as yesterday.  It is in respect of eye care and involves a person who has insurance but requires a particular treatment in order to prevent them from going blind.  The cost of the operation for each eye is around &euro;4,000.  They are now being advised that their policy does not cover them for this particular type of operation.  One of the things that is happening is that people sometimes buy into insurance thinking they are covered for a whole range of areas and then find when the issue arises that the cover is not there.</p> <p>The other issue I have come across is where a particular treatment is not available in Ireland but is available in the UK, for instance.  The treatment recommended to the person is in their best interest, yet there is reluctance on the part of the insurance company to get involved in providing cover.  We have ended up going in and battling with the insurance company to try to bring it on board.  There is a huge long-term saving for the individual and also for the company because if the particular procedure recommended is not completed, the person will end up spending longer in our hospital service.  Sometimes when we look at problems, we look at the here and now but do not look at the long-term issue of how to save costs at a later date.  I welcome that we are now progressing with this matter.  We need to have an overall discussion on this matter in the long term.  How will we face the challenges over the next five to ten years on this issue?  The age profile is continuing to change.  In order to make sure we do not have the same increase next year and the year after, we have to increase the numbers who are paying private health insurance.  Otherwise we will have to continue to increase the levies that apply in each category.  I thank the Minister of State.  We will support the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#W00200"><p>The greatest deficiency and most damaging factor in the Irish health system is the absence of universal health care.  There is an incurable reliance on a two-tier system.  The Fine Gael and Fianna F&aacute;il parties are responsible for building this inadequate health service over decades which has led to our poorest citizens suffering and dying because of their inability to pay.  Disturbingly, we have built a public health service which survives precariously on life support due to private sector intervention at huge cost to the taxpayer.</p> <p>I read with interest the Minister for Health's response to the debate on Second Stage in the D&aacute;il.  One thing that struck me in his remarks was his reference to risk equalisation and that if we did not advance this, we would be "leaving some of our sickest and some of our most elderly citizens who access private health insurance" exposed.  He said this legislation would "protect them from much higher premiums were we in a risk-rated free market type approach to this".  The Minister took issue with some speakers who criticised private health insurance and its influence on the development of a universal system.  His remarks were that "we cannot close our eyes, put our hands over our ears and pretend that almost 50% of our citizens do not have private health insurance".</p> <p>We cannot not support the passage of this legislation, but we wholeheartedly reserve the right to criticise the flawed model upon which the two-tier health system is currently based and which creates and entrenches deep inequalities.  It is clear that it is the poorest and sickest who find it hardest to pay charges no matter how small those charges are and who find it harder to negotiate access.  It is also the poorest and sickest who have to wait longest for care.  Care should not be provided based on ability to pay.  The fear of being left high and dry in an hour of need is what drives 50% of our people to private health insurance.  This is not acceptable.  </p> <p>Reference was made to the 100,000 people coming back into health insurance.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In the horrific years of austerity, health insurance was the first thing to go in people's budgets as they tried to survive the bills.  Now they are coming back in, but the burden placed on the health service over that decade was enormous.  We are still suffering from it now.</p><p>We should be building an all-Ireland public hospital system that will look after our citizens on the basis of need and regardless of wealth or location.  The Department does not collect specific data on the cost to the Exchequer of operating a private system of health care.  If we are investing in the NTPF without recourse to what could be done to enhance services in the public system or if we are enabling a private insurance market, we must have some idea of the cost of the two-tier system for the Exchequer.  Last week, my colleague in the D&aacute;il, Deputy Louise O'Reilly, asked for the data relating to the number of treatments commissioned from the private sector versus the number of treatments carried out; the number, type and value of services and surgeries commissioned from the private sector and the number, type and value of those carried out; and the cost and savings to the State of services and surgeries carried out by the private sector.  This is important information when discussing capacity issues in the public health system, but Deputy O'Reilly was advised that the detailed information sought was not available at the time, that the NTPF had been asked to provide the information requested and that it would be forwarded to her.  At a time when the Minister is reactivating the NTPF, allocating &euro;20 million to it and with that figure to rise to &euro;55 million in 2018, and when contracts are being entered into with the HSE, he does not have available to him data relating to the efficiency and value for money of embarking on this course.  One need only look to the various reports that were produced in England recently to see that this course did not increase capacity.</p><p>Align all of this with the fact that the full capacity protocol was deployed an amazing 2,300 times across a 321 period in 2016 across 26 hospitals.  The protocol of last resort is being used with such worrying frequency that alarm bells must be going off in the Department of Health about the lack of capacity.  Despite the Government's rhetoric about the largest investment in health in years, it appears that it is not enough.  International research definitively shows that insurance based systems are more expensive and cause inequalities.  In Ireland, 45% of the population have private health insurance, yet it contributes less than 10% to the overall budget.  At a meeting of the Committee on the Future of Healthcare, Dr. Sara Burke explained that this is due to the fact that private health insurance in Ireland largely insures somebody for inpatient or day case elective hospital care.  It does not cover most other matters, such as most outpatient care, outpatient appointments with specialists in the first instance, the cost of drugs and most primary care payments.  This is a blatant example of poor value for money.  It shows that the public system is subsidising the private system, because while 45% of the population has private health insurance, the majority of the expense of health care is not paid for by private health insurers.  This was an issue for the Minister, and there is a new charging regime for private patients in public hospitals.  However, if private insurance is only providing one link in the chain, with the rest left up to the public sector, it means we are subsidising the private sector.  That sector cherry picks and takes the best and most profitable parts, leaving the public health service to pick up the pieces.  It is called privatising profits and socialising losses.</p><p>How far have we come since Susie Long's untimely death?  How is promoting private health insurance a step towards universal health care?  It is not.  Our public services are under-funded, they cannot retain or recruit staff and there are chronic waiting lists of almost 500,000 at the last count.  I hope the next time the Minister comes to the House with a Bill such as this, there will be a plan for untangling the marriage of public and private health systems.  We will not support this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#X00200"><p>I thank the Senators for their support, for the most part, for the Bill and for their contributions to the debate.</p> <p>To recap, the main purpose of this Bill is to specify the risk equalisation credits and corresponding stamp duty levies from 1 April 2017.  The Bill also makes a number of changes to the operation of the scheme, providing for a new benchmark of reasonable profit for the over-compensation test and placing a limit on the amount of credits that can be provided.  The Bill also clarifies the circumstances where an insurer can withdraw a product and seeks to ensure that people are offered a replacement product with at least the same level of benefits.</p> <p>Sharing costs across the community-rated private health insurance market must take account of the realities of the market and, as Senator Colm Burke mentioned, our increasing population and demographics.  The proportion of people in their 70s with health insurance has increased by almost 40% in the past 13 years and the proportion of people over 80 years of age with health insurance has doubled.  At the same time, there were large decreases in the proportion of people in their 20s and 30s with health insurance.  The introduction of lifetime community rating, young adult rates and the improved economic environment have helped to reverse this trend.  To echo Senator Colm Burke's point, the number of people with health insurance is generally associated with employment levels.  As our unemployment rates continue to decrease and as we continue to offer incentives to encourage young people to take up health insurance, we hope that number will not stabilise but will continue to increase.</p> <p>These changes, coupled with the ongoing increases in employment, which is a key driver in the demand for health insurance, will support the market and everyone wishing to avail of private health insurance.  The Bill provides for 10% increases to the existing stamp duty levies.  However, the Bill's primary purpose is to provide the necessary credits to insurers to reduce some of the additional costs they incur by insuring older, sicker members.  It is proposed to increase those credits significantly to insurers.  These changes will not offset all of the additional costs of insuring older and less healthy people, but they will help to keep health insurance more affordable for them.  With regard to the percentage based stamp duty, in 2015 and 2016 one of the insurers indicated a preference for switching to the percentage based stamp duty.  While this view has been taken into account by the authority, it has not recommended changing from the current system of fixed amounts to stamp duty.  Under the scheme all of the money raised in levies from insurers is paid into a fund for the sole purpose of supporting the market in the form of credits payable.  Any decision to pass on the benefits of higher credits or the cost of higher stamp duty levies to consumers is a commercial pricing decision for each insurer.</p> <p>Most Senators raised the issue of public versus private health care.  Changes to the charging regime for private patients in public hospitals have contributed to some of the increase in claims costs.  The Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, recently met with all of the health insurers and listened to their concerns about charging private patients in public hospitals.  I understand the HSE and insurers have met twice since then to discuss and resolve the issues.  There is ongoing engagement, which is welcome.  People using our public hospitals are fully entitled to opt to be treated as public patients.  If they hold private health insurance, they are also free to waive their entitlement to public treatment, opt to be treated as private patients and use their private health insurance.  The charges for private patients in public hospitals go towards meeting part of the cost of providing the hospitals' services to private patients.</p> <p>As regards the issue of universal health care, and in recognition of the issues outlined by Senator Devine, the Committee on the Future of Healthcare is examining this issue.  I hope we can achieve a system of universal health care in the future with a role being played by private health insurance.  However, that is something to be discussed in that committee.  This Bill allows us to maintain our support for the core principle of community-rated private health insurance.  By revising the credits, and the stamp duties required to fund those credits to take account of market trends, we can continue to provide the necessary support to ensure that the costs of health insurance are shared across the insured population.</p> <p>I commend the Bill to the House and I agree with Senators that further discussion will be required at a future date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.81" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and declared carried.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#X00400"><p>When is it proposed to take Committee Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#X00500"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.84" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Committee Stage ordered for Tuesday, 13 December 2016.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.85" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 2.20 p.m. and resumed at 2.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.86" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#Z00100">Cystic Fibrosis Treatment: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#Z00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Harris, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#Z00300"><p>I thank the Seanad for giving me an opportunity to address this important issue today.  I look forward to listening to the contributions of Senators.  I hope it is clear that everyone here shares the absolute objective of securing access to this medicine for Irish patients at an affordable price.  Irish cystic fibrosis patients should have access to innovative treatments.  This is the clear objective of the HSE, which is negotiating on behalf of Irish patients.  I consider it essential for the HSE to receive the full support of all public representatives in its efforts.  When negotiations of this nature are taking place, we should not forget that the HSE is the only party in the room that negotiates on behalf of Irish patients.  This is not about attacking big pharma.  This is about supporting Irish patients and supporting the people who are working to get the very best deal for Irish patients.</p> <p>It is unacceptable that cystic fibrosis patients have been used as pawns in this process.  It is regrettable that many of them and their families have been put through a harrowing time.  The company in this case has refused from the outset to put a fair and reasonable price on its treatment, in line with the price guidance provided not by the Government, the HSE or the Department of Health but by Professor Michael Barry and his team in the National Centre for Pharmacoeconomics.  The company has refused to give absolute certainty to patients on managed access schemes or programmes that they will continue to receive their treatment for the rest of their lives, regardless of the outcome of the commercial negotiations with the HSE.  It has actively sought to place Irish cystic fibrosis patients in the centre of its commercial negotiations with the HSE, with a view to maximising the return for its executives and shareholders.  This type of behaviour is not unique to this drug, unfortunately, and is certainly not unique to Ireland.  Similar pricing strategies have been employed in the past.  My counterparts in other EU member states inform me that this type of behaviour is evident in their countries too.</p> <p>As Senators will be aware, I attended a meeting in Lisbon yesterday to discuss drug pricing, innovation and the sustainability of European health systems.  I took the opportunity to raise directly the situation in respect of Orkambi and the manner in which the company is treating cystic fibrosis patients and their families in Ireland.  It was clear from my discussions with health Ministers from other countries that the current situation is not sustainable.  Advances in medicines have played a key role in improving the overall health of Irish people.  However, health care systems throughout Europe are quickly reaching a point at which patients cannot access new and innovative medicines because of the pricing strategies of manufacturers.  Innovation is not of any use if patients cannot access it.  As we have seen with medicines like Orkambi, the price the company is seeking to charge means innovative products may never reach the patient.  This is not acceptable.  Equally, it is not acceptable that health systems are finding themselves unable to afford the prices being quoted.  This can be viewed as a funding problem or a pricing problem, but my view is that it is primarily a pricing problem.  If we are to ensure innovative medicines are available to patients with unmet needs, companies like Vertex need to fundamentally reassess their pricing models.  I appeal to them today to do so.</p> <p>I will focus on price because it is the main barrier to access in this instance.  The National Centre for Pharmacoeconomics has independently assessed the evidence and benefits of this treatment.  Based on a detailed examination of costs and benefits, including reductions in other treatments, the national centre considers that an annual price of &euro;30,000 per patient would be appropriate.  At this price, the HSE would pay &euro;15 million a year for Orkambi, or &euro;75 million over the next five years.  This is a significant investment.  Any public statement from the company on prices should be compared to these figures.  There has been an attempt to undermine these figures as inappropriate for this type of treatment.  I remind the House that at &euro;30,000 per patient per year, this would be one of the most expensive treatments in Ireland.  In fact, it would be sixth on the high-tech drugs list in this country.  I am not in any way attempting to undermine the benefits of the treatment.  I am doing the opposite - I am acknowledging its benefits for Irish patients.  Unfortunately, the price the company has put on this product is many multiples of the figure I have mentioned.  Despite the company's claims, in the absence of verifiable evidence to the contrary it appears that the main driver of the price is an estimate of the maximum amount that this country can pay and is not connected to the health benefits of the treatment or the cost of bringing the medicine to the market.</p> <p>There has been a significant debate in recent days on the outcomes-based model, which is something I support.  To put it simply, it involves the company having the confidence in its product to provide the treatment to all eligible patients, but not to seek payment until the treatment delivers benefits to Irish patients.  The HSE has confirmed that Vertex has made it clear that it is not willing to engage in an outcomes-based model that addresses the HSE's core pricing concerns.  This is very disappointing.  If the company has the same level of confidence in Orkambi as many patients and all of us - we know it can make a difference to people's lives - it is time for it to put the product where its mouth is and to engage in an outcomes-based model.  Vertex should provide the drug to every patient who could benefit from it and we will pay based on who can benefit from it.  It is very disappointing that the company is not in a position to do this.</p> <p>As Vertex is refusing to release the HSE from commercial confidentiality requirements, the HSE cannot provide this House and, more importantly, cystic fibrosis patients with a transparent understanding of Vertex's proposals in the negotiations.  Taking account of the outcome of negotiations and having considered the recommendations of the National Centre for Pharmacoeconomics and other expert advice, the HSE's drugs committee has not recommended reimbursement for Orkambi.  Where do we go from here?  I repeat that we all share a unified view of wanting to make the most innovative treatments, including Orkambi, available to Irish patients.  I want to assure cystic fibrosis patients loudly and clearly on the record of this House that this is not the end of the process.  The HSE directorate will consider the drugs committee&rsquo;s recommendation, taking into consideration the manufacturer's price offer.  This decision will be made on objective scientific and economic grounds and in line with the Health (Pricing and Supply of Medical Goods) Act 2013, as passed by this House and the other House.  This is the next formal stage in the statutory assessment process.  The HSE has made it crystal clear that it is open to meaningful engagement with the company.</p> <p>Drug companies and public relations companies have gone into overdrive in their efforts to assert that I will not attend negotiations.  I want to make it very clear that this is a complete misrepresentation.  The law of this land, as passed in 2013 by Senators in this House and by me and my colleagues in the D&aacute;il, makes it clear that the HSE is the body with statutory responsibility for decisions on pricing and reimbursement of medicines.  It carries out the negotiations.  However, I have been in regular contact with the HSE.  It is ready to make this happen.  Vertex should do the same.  It is not the case that there is one rule for Vertex and a different rule for every other drug company.  Vertex must respect the laws of our country, our processes and our democratic decisions.  The HSE does the negotiations.  It is time to stop the spinning.  If the company spent less time spinning in the media and more time engaging in a meaningful manner, we could try to get this matter resolved.  When the spinning stops, we can get back in the room, start the talking and get on with making this happen.  I want to assure Vertex and, more importantly, cystic fibrosis patients that the people from the HSE who are needed to help to make these decisions will be in the room.  We should not try to politicise this.  I ask Vertex not to interfere with our political system and the rules of our country.</p> <p>As I have mentioned, this situation is not unique to Ireland.  I am looking at every option to make progress with this issue and other issues in relation to drug pricing in collaboration with other countries.  This is a very viable option.  I have contacted health Ministers in four other countries - the UK, Scotland, Canada and Australia - where Vertex&rsquo;s very high pricing has prevented reimbursement for cystic fibrosis patients.  I believe there is potential for joint co-operation in seeking to have a positive influence on the manufacturer's pricing strategy.  As I have outlined, I raised this issue with health Ministers in Lisbon yesterday.  I will continue to do so as part of moves to consider pricing for expensive drugs across Europe.  Despite the claims of the company, there is very significant value achievable to patients and health systems from such collaboration.  We should be working at EU level in relation to this.  It is nonsense for companies to say this will take years.  The company in this case is negotiating with many countries and has failed to conclude negotiations with Canada, Australia, the UK, Scotland, the Netherlands and Ireland.  It is right and proper for countries to talk to one another to share information and try to adopt a common approach.  All health Ministers in the EU and beyond want to make this drug available to our patients.  We are charged with looking after the interests of the patients in our countries.</p> <p>I appreciate that this is a stressful time for cystic fibrosis patients and their families.  I have had an opportunity to meet a number of them.  I am in regular contact with some of them.  I strongly urge Vertex to provide this drug at a fairer price for the benefit of our patients as quickly as possible.  As Professor Michael Barry has said, it is time for the company to put its patients first and to significantly reduce its price to one that is fair, equitable and sustainable.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I fully support the HSE in its efforts to reduce the price of medicines in order that our CF patients can be treated with it.  I call on all public representatives, including Members of the Seanad, while rightfully highlighting the concerns of CF patients, to make sure that that concern is not accidentally diverted in a way that is used to help Vertex rather than our patients.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#AA00200"><p>All Senators called will have five minutes to contribute.  The debate is due to go on for one hour.  We will have about nine slots.  I will be strict on time because I see many Members indicating a wish to contribute.  I call Senator Swanick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#AA00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House to discuss this important issue.  On Tuesday, many of us listened in the AV room as Ms Jillian McNulty gave a heart-wrenching account of what her life is like living with cystic fibrosis.  In Jillian's words, without Orkambi, she would not be here.  Her lung function has improved by almost 10% and she has spent up to a year less in hospital.  Jillian&rsquo;s situation is unfortunately not unique.  Ireland has one of the most severe strains of cystic fibrosis in the world and the highest incidence per head of population, which is three times the rate in the United States and the rest of the European Union.  Ireland should be at the forefront of new technologies, research and strategies to deal with the condition, but we are not.</p> <p>About 550 to 600 people in Ireland with CF have the potential to benefit from Orkambi.  That is 600 lives which could be improved beyond recognition.  I understand the Minister, Deputy Harris, travelled to Portugal yesterday for an EU health Ministers meeting on pharmaceutical drug costs.  He sought the assistance of other EU nations to force pharmaceutical firms to slash exorbitant prices, which make it effectively impossible to access new treatments.  We need to be realistic here.  Vertex Pharmaceuticals has asked the State to pay approximately &euro;150,000 per person annually for the drug and HSE experts are saying a price of &euro;30,000 is fairer.  The HSE has challenged the company to stop hiding behind confidentiality clauses.</p> <p>I welcome the statement by Vertex Pharmaceuticals last night that said it would be entering into renegotiations with the HSE in an effort to reach an agreement on costs.  The statement included the following: "Vertex has met with HSE representatives six times in five months, presenting a range of specific workable proposals that could expedite access for all eligible patients."  Vertex has said that it has received no response from the HSE to date.  The statement continued: "These proposals have included significant price reductions, guarantees of budget certainty, novel access schemes such as a risk-sharing agreement and ways to reduce the timelines on reimbursement decisions for patients in the future as new medicines become available."</p> <p>If this is true, it is simply shocking.  The clock is quite literally ticking for these people.  It is a matter of life and death.  On the one hand, Vertex invested millions in developing new ground-breaking drugs for CF and there are not many patients on which to make a return.  Vertex claims it has to get its money back to reinvest in further research.  On the other hand, the HSE has the right to get the best price for the product, which is fully supported by Cystic Fibrosis Ireland.  We have to be mindful that this is the first drug to treat the underlying cause of the double delta-F508 strain of cystic fibrosis.  The drug slows down the progression of cystic fibrosis and reduces hospital admissions by 40%.  We all know that a hospital bed costs &euro;1,200 per day.  It may make the difference for a patient receiving a lung transplant or not.  There is enormous human cost to the patient as well as the financial cost to the State.  At the end of the day, a solution needs to be found.  If the two parties cannot reach agreement on price, consideration should be given to bringing in an international mediator to arbitrate on this matter to the satisfaction of all.</p> <p>Before I finish, I will describe an anecdotal situation.  In my own area in the west of Ireland, there is a family that I am very much aware of.  A good few of the siblings have cystic fibrosis.  One young girl lost her life to cystic fibrosis a number of years back.  Her brother lost his life to suicide.  He also had cystic fibrosis and suffered from a perceived lack of hope.  Now that there is a drug that can help, let us all work together to ensure that the people who deserve to get this drug get it in a timely matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#AA00400"><p>The very fact that the Minister is in the Chamber today shows his commitment and his concern for this issue of Orkambi.  I compliment the Minister for being present because, very often, senior Ministers send along a junior Minister to one of these events.  Clearly, he is concerned.  Professor Michael Barry spoke on Morning Ireland about a week ago.  It is an extremely difficult thing for a man in his position to come out and publicly explain why he cannot purchase a drug at the exorbitant cost that was being sought by the company, knowing in his heart of hearts that there are people listening who are desperate for this drug.  It is absolutely terrible that a drug company played roulette with the patients they hope to serve.  From that point of view, Professor Barry and his team deserve our admiration for the work they do.</p> <p>The Minister touched on my concern in his presentation.  My concern is that, when it suits us, we live in a single market and when it does not suit us or suit certain interests, we do not live in a single market.  We operate as a single market for agriculture, fisheries and all sorts of things.  The drug companies seem to be the difference.  I met a colleague of mine from my old profession down in Lanzarote some time ago.  He bought his blood pressure tablets for the year at a cost of &euro;14.95.  He told me that the same tablets were costing him more than &euro;1,000 in Ireland.  Ultimately, it was not costing him, but the State.  I am delighted that the Minister is talking with his counterparts from all of the various jurisdictions that he gets the chance to talk to.  The time has come for the European Commission to look at competition and to state that there is no competition in these situations.  Drug companies, in effect, have monopolies until such time as the patent on a drug runs out or until a competitor develops a similar but slightly different product.  I believe it is time the Commission tells the companies that if they want to deal in Europe, they must deal with Europe.  The EU could then divvy the drug out to the rest of the European community.  I believe that is the way it should be done.</p> <p>Pricing should be done on the basis of a single market.  I am sure the Minister is aware of the fact that we now have people in my age group and upward going on what they call their "medical holiday".  They go to Spain to buy their drugs for the year.  They take a week's holiday, fly Ryanair down to Spain and come back with change in their pocket from what they would have spent had they bought their drugs at home.  That is not good.  It is not good for the pharmacy industry in Ireland, for the people themselves or for the Department of Health.  I am sure the drugs are the same in Spain, but we do not know that for certain.</p> <p>The representatives of a drug company had the notion to tell our Minister for Health that they will negotiate with him but not with some second or third party.  How dare they.  Who do they think they are talking to?  The Minister has rightly pointed out that this House and the Lower House have passed laws in this country.  We have decided who will do our negotiating for us.  We will stand over that, regardless of any pressure that comes on it.</p> <p>Yesterday, I went out to the front gate to meet my sister, who had travelled from Galway with her husband and her two sisters-in-law.  They had all taken a day off work and had lost money to come here.  Thankfully, my sister's children are healthy, but her nieces and nephews were not and have passed away.  Three different sides of my family have CF.  If we look around Ireland, every family has been afflicted at some stage.  It is almost as pervasive as cancer, to some degree.  It is not something that we can take lightly and I do not believe the Minister is taking it lightly.  I believe we need to send a message out from Seanad &Eacute;ireann today to Vertex saying, "Guys, you either deal with us or we will turn the PR machine against you".  The offer that has been made by this country is a reasonable one.  Drug companies must be entitled to get a return on their investment and nobody is denying Vertex that.  However, &euro;75 million over three years is an awful lot of money.  The offer that has been made is one that Vertex should grab with both hands.  Let other drug companies learn from this.  Ireland will not be bullied into paying exorbitant prices.  I ask the Minister to go back to his colleagues in Europe, particularly to Commissioner Phil Hogan, to ask if something can be done to turn the drugs and medicine industry into a single market.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#AA00500"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I appreciate his coming in here and taking time out from his busy schedule.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is an extremely important issue because people with cystic fibrosis face major challenges every day and we must do everything possible to assist them.  We must also consider how to resolve this issue soon.  Vertex has done major research but someone cannot dictate the rules thereafter for access to the product.  The Health Service Executive cannot disclose certain information under a confidentiality agreement.  If Vertex is satisfied that it is truthful in everything it says why can it not waive the confidentiality agreement and let the HSE release what has occurred over recent meetings?  The negotiations on this started in 2012.  Over 500 people could benefit from this drug.  The National Centre for Pharmacoeconomics has checked and cross-checked the economics and benefits of this drug.  It has done several tests and assessments and its figures indicate that we should be talking about a cost of &euro;30,000 per patient per annum whereas the company says it should be &euro;159,000 per patient per annum.  We have to make sure we are not held to ransom.<br/><br/>The cost of pharmaceuticals in this country went from &euro;570 million to over &euro;2 billion in ten years.  We now pay the highest cost <i>per capita</i>for pharmaceuticals of any European country.  If we give in on this one we set another series of increases in the cost of pharmaceuticals.  The figure for 2015 is approximately &euro;2.6 billion between hospitals, the drugs repayment scheme and private buying.  That is a huge sum of money for a country this size.  It is important to put some restraint on what the drug companies ask for.  I welcome the fact that Vertex has agreed to come back into negotiations.  Let us have all the information in the public domain.  We need to prioritise coming to an agreement on this matter because there are over 500 people who need it as do their immediate families who have to give them support every day.  That is a huge strain on those families.  I hope we can conclude this matter. <br/><br/>If we pay out the &euro;159,000 per patient per annum that will set the tone for all future negotiations about new drugs.  It also raises the question of where we cut the health services.  I agree with other speakers who said if a person is on this drug it saves money on days in hospital.  We have to make sure we are getting full value for money and helping people.  We are prepared to pay extra to ensure these people get the benefit of the drug.  The drug company has to be reasonable about what it wants in order to make sure people can access the product.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#BB00200"><p>This is a heartbreaking but potentially lifesaving topic.  Last week we heard the personal testimonies of distraught parents of seriously ill children whose survival they see in the prescription of Orkambi.  Yesterday, there were hundreds of people, some of them extremely ill, outside Leinster House, dragged onto the streets to demand what could be a lifesaver for them.  They are desperate people in a desperate situation.</p> <p>I do not envy the Minister or his position.  We disagree on much politically but on matters such as this, politics is put to one side and we work together for a collective goal.  The single biggest problem in providing this drug to cystic fibrosis sufferers is mass global pharmaceutical companies and their unrelenting quest for mega profit.  These companies do not care about the hundreds of people that were outside these buildings yesterday or about Finn, who is two and a half years old and has been hospitalised 38 times. </p> <p>Disturbingly, these protests and personal stories probably help the drug companies and their financially unrealistic demands of governments around the world.  They can literally charge whatever price they like for the drugs they produce in patent.  Playing roulette and brinkmanship with people's lives on the basis of money is abhorrent and morally wrong.  We need cool heads to prevail and a determination to deliver this life-saving drug to extremely ill people in a cost-effective manner.  What is most important is that it is delivered and precious lives are saved.</p> <p>I am under no illusion about the scale of this problem.  Today it is Orkambi and tomorrow it will be the next life-saving drug.  Shamefully caught in the middle is a precious human life that needs to be saved.  The HSE and the Department of Health need to establish a working group that will bring forward appropriate decision criteria for the reimbursement of orphan medicines and technologies.  This approach should include an assessment system similar to that for cancer therapies established under the national cancer control programme, NCCP.  This recommendation was contained in the National Rare Disease Plan for Ireland 2014&ndash;18.  Two years into this period we learn that the terms of reference for this group are only being developed.  We need to continue this without delay. </p> <p>The cost of this drug, Orkambi, has been determined by the HSE at &euro;392 million over five years.  Vertex, the drug company, has seriously disputed this amount and it is publicly known that Vertex is willing to negotiate.  It needs to be transparent about how much it will accept for this drug.  Ireland sets the cost per quality adjusted life at &euro;45,000.  This is a long way off from the cited cost of &euro;160,000.  These large drug companies argue that the thresholds used to calculate cost effectiveness are too low.</p> <p>Governments need to take back control of mass research.  We cannot allow pharmaceutical companies hold our Government or any other government to ransom for profit while playing with peoples' lives.  Pharmaceutical companies by their very nature and desire for high margin profit are specifically targeting orphan drugs because of the small concentrated group of patients they can treat in line with the low volume, high margin business model that they can manipulate.  We are cognisant of the fact that Orkambi was rejected not because it did not work or because the authorities are not aware of the very real lives of Irish citizens and their debilitating illnesses such as cystic fibrosis, but because of the huge price tag put on it by Vertex.  We have to promote reviewing the ten-year exclusivity granted to pharmaceutical companies which, along with generous tax credits, also face less intensive regulatory practices to get these drugs off the ground.</p> <p>Once these drugs are approved, pharmaceutical companies are effectively given a licence to print money.  They have a ready made audience and provision of treatment becomes extremely emotive because of the rarity of the illnesses backed up with strong, intensive lobby groups eager to secure previously unavailable treatments.  This is done in good faith out of care for loved ones or indeed to secure their own lives.  The major problem is the despicable greed of the pharmaceutical industry.</p> <p>Vertex says it has yet to turn a profit on this drug but its trading figures tell a different story.  The priority for us is to secure Orkambi for our very ill citizens.  We should create risk-sharing arrangements where the manufacturer must share risk with the purchaser, co-operate with other countries to negotiate more powerfully and increase bargaining power.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Co-operating with other countries will also enable us to present a larger patient pool.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#CC00200"><p>Thank you, Senator Devine.  There are others waiting to contribute and we have limited time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#CC00300"><p>There is another drug on the market called Kalydeco and I ask the Minister whether that product is in the mix in the negotiations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" speakername="John Dolan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#CC00400"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for coming to the House for this debate.  A number of Senators have spoken about people they know or people close to them who suffer from cystic fibrosis and everyone in the House knows someone with the condition.  I agree with the Minister that it is unacceptable that cystic fibrosis patients are being used as pawns.  There is no doubt that these people and their difficult situations are being brazenly used.  It is hard not to come to the conclusion that there is something unorthodox, if not rotten, about the way some elements of the international pharmaceutical business operates in terms of pricing policy.  Families in this situation are going to look to the nearest point to them, namely, the HSE or the Minister to help them.  It is great to see solidarity and understanding in the Seanad today in the sense that we all agree that we must deal with this collectively and must call out where the real issue lies.</p> <p>The Minister said that he has been in contact with four other countries.  I totally endorse the remarks made by Senator Craughwell.  He rightly asked why, as members of the European Union, we cannot deal with drugs pricing across the whole European family.  Today, tomorrow or next week, a family will be told that their little boy or girl has cystic fibrosis and the unedifying situation in which we currently find ourselves is horrendous in that context.  It is bad enough to have to deal with such a serious condition but to be pawns in a game that seems to be just about profit is totally unacceptable.  </p> <p>I am very heartened by the tone and nature of the discussion we are having today.  I wish the Minister, his Department and the HSE the very best in their efforts to get the price of this drug down to an acceptable level.  We have already put the slide rule over that and know what price is about right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#CC00500"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  This is an extremely important issue.  To bring it down to basics, people with cystic fibrosis did not wake up one morning and say, "I want cystic fibrosis".  I know many people with the condition.  I am thinking in particular of a young woman in her early 20s.  She is in college and is bright and articulate.  I have spoken to her about Orkambi as she would qualify for it.  She is not looking for an improvement in her lung capacity but just wants it to be stabilised.  If her lung capacity can be maintained at its current level she can live a normal life and stay out of hospital.  She is not looking for a rapid rate of increase in her lung capacity but for stability.</p> <p>I have met representatives of Vertex, as have many others, and it must be said that without Vertex, Orkambi and Kalydeco would not be available.  The company did the necessary research.  The question is whether the charge for these drugs is effectively extortion.  </p> <p>Confidentiality is normal in commercial discussions but in this particular case, the details should be made public.  Furthermore, discussions must recommence with immediate effect because we are dealing with peoples' lives.  As a society, we must make both moral and financial decisions.  This is business and the best negotiators we have must be in the room with Vertex.  The company must come to the table and make a deal that is fair.  We need to put a results or risk-based model in place.  We are not certain how many people will benefit from using Orkambi and we must put a pricing structure in place that reflects that.  The discussions are critical and Vertex must engage with a view to striking a price that is fair.  The HSE must find a way to make Orkambi available to those people who so desperately need it.  </p> <p>I welcome the fact that a new cystic fibrosis unit has opened in University Hospital Limerick.  There are nine isolation beds in the unit which is very significant.  However, University Hospital Limerick urgently needs 96 new acute beds.  The numbers going through the accident and emergency department, an estimated 64,000 this year, are the highest in the country.  Cork has 800 beds for an estimated 60,000 people while Limerick has only 400 beds.  I ask the Minister to provide money to University Hospital Limerick to enable the design process to begin before the mid-term capital review.  The sum of &euro;25 million is urgently needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1398" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#CC00600"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House and thank him, on behalf of all of those we represent, for his investment in this issue.  I know he is personally heavily invested in it as I have been following his progress on it for some time now.  For what it is worth, he has my support in terms of the approach he is taking.  I think it is the right, responsible and sensible approach.  I hope he can find a way to ensure that those who need this treatment so badly can get it in a timely fashion.  We all know people who suffer from cystic fibrosis.  I know many people from my own immediate area, who I would have gone to school with and played with as a child, whose families have lost them to cystic fibrosis.  It is a very debilitating and life-limiting condition.  We all know about the disease and its impact on our communities.</p> <p>I have listened very closely not only to the Minister's pursuit of these issues in recent times but also to all sides of the debate.  In this House, there are not two sides to the debate.  It is rare enough that this type of solidarity breaks out in a Chamber that is, by definition, political but everyone is on the same page on this issue.  There may be differing views on the tactical approach but we all want the same outcome.  I am glad that the tendency in this country to make emotive issues like this into political footballs has been avoided.  We all need to express our solidarity with those who we represent, those who need this drug and their families while also taking a responsible approach.  We are not just having a political discourse here.  We are being watched very closely, not just by this particular pharmaceutical company but by many others, in terms of our approach to this issue. </p> <p>The Minister is absolutely right not to be making any political interventions as Minister for Health by dealing directly with the company.  That would set a bad precedent.  I have every confidence that the HSE has the capacity to deliver a result for the Irish people.  To use an appropriate analogy, I would never, in my time as Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, have intervened in an industrial dispute.  To do that would be to escalate the situation and that would be to nobody's benefit.  I support the Minister's approach and the strategic approach of his Department.  We all stand united behind the cause of assisting the Minister to get the right outcome for cystic fibrosis patients in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#DD00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House.  I have three questions.  First, how many countries have done a deal with the company?  Second, have any of those countries done a deal on the basis of risk sharing?  Finally, what price did they end up paying?  Obviously, these are benchmarks on which we could base our negotiations.</p> <p>Many colleagues have touched on other issues to do with cystic fibrosis.  One feature of CF is the consequences of having a diagnosis and the fact that there is now hope for patients.  There is a drug that offers hope for some, but it does not offer hope for all.  That is where risk sharing comes in to play.  This is where we could possibly improve and lengthen lives.  Indeed, we could not only lengthen lives but improve the quality of life.</p> <p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House today to take this debate.  He did not send anyone.  He has come himself.  The Minister was sent out to bat on an equally tough issue in 2013 when it came to organ donation.  The House was recalled at the time.  We had a number of debates on radio, television and in other locations.  As the Minister will recall from those debates, the system of organ donation in this country is a disaster.  The EU regulation brought in at the time was signed on the last day designated by the European Union for signature.  The 27-page EU directive was the first tranche of legislation in the history of the State to do with organ donation.</p> <p>Our system is so bad that 65 people per year are dying on our organ transplant waiting list.  The figure does not include those who are taken off the waiting list because they are too sick or deemed to be too ill to receive a transplant.  They do not even feature as a statistic in our organ transplant system.  We have 650 people waiting for organ transplants.  Some 500 of this number are awaiting a kidney transplant.  If we simply reformed the organ donor system for kidney transplant alone, we would save over &euro;1.3 billion in a decade.  More important than saving such a vast amount of money is that we would be saving and transforming lives.</p> <p>In the overall context of the debate, this drug, Orkambi, is one element.  The question is how to pay for it, regardless of whether we decide to pay such a vast sum.  I am not suggesting the amount in question should be paid this minute, but we need to know what other countries have done.  That is why I have asked my questions.  If the Minster does not have the answers to hand, I would appreciate it if he sends on the information to us.</p> <p>I know the Minister has met organ transplant organisations.  Our system is failing people from start to finish.  The issue of organ donor co-ordinators was central.  As a result of the debate in 2013, several were appointed.  I will highlight how bad our system is.  Some hospitals in the country have never asked any family to consider donating the organs of a loved one.  Over the course of a decade, not one organ donation has come from some hospitals in this State.  Why is that?  It is a systems failure from top to bottom.</p> <p>An opportunity was missed at the time of the EU directive in 2013.  I will not go into all the elements of it now, but the foregone opportunity is not only relevant to this issue.</p> <p>The answer to the questions will come from the evidence of what other countries have done, whether they have been involved in risk sharing and what price they have paid.  Furthermore, if we can get an EU solution, it will be all the better.  The fact is that this drug gives hope.  There is nothing worse than to know that there is a solution but to be denied that solution and, by extension, be denied the hope that a child or loved one will be given a chance - that is all patients and families are hoping for.</p> <p>I would hate to be in the Minister's position.  A Minister of the Government gets lambasted from all sides.  Now, the Minister is in a situation whereby it is a life or death decision for people.  It is no easy position to be in when that simple question is put in front of the Minister.  It is a complex question.  Many issues must be weighed up, including the cost and the future impact in respect of purchasing other drugs for other sicknesses and illnesses.  Anyway, this is really for the families that the Minister and all of us have met.  It is a life-or-death decision.  I hope the Minister will support them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#DD00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  I have no wish to be distracted from what we are discussing, but I listened to the last speaker discussing transplants.  As the Minister of the day at the time I know of the extra money and the transplant office put in place.  I know of all the additional transplants that have taken place since then and, therefore, I would find it difficult not to respond.  Notwithstanding that, there is a great deal more work to be done.  That is part of what we are about today.  All these things have a cost and when budgets are tight &ndash; they are better now than they were some years ago &ndash; these things become serious issues.</p> <p>I am delighted we are having the debate but I am saddened that it is necessary.  Science has a long and proud tradition in this country and across the globe of bringing new developments to improve the lives of people.  Many scientists are seen as heroes, and rightly so.  While I do not expect us to go back to the days of Faraday and all the discoveries he made and which he shared freely with the world, I believe we have gone to the other extreme with Orkambi and this company, Vertex.  This is a political forum and I intend to take advantage of it to speak my mind.  This company seems to be very much focused on extracting a price that it believes the market will bear, one that does not relate in any way to the patients for whom it is intended.  The company was given considerable sums of money by charitable organisations throughout the globe and, I have no doubt, received much by way of grants and tax incentives, just as we do in this country.  Ultimately, we have all invested heavily in this.</p> <p>The goodwill and celebration we should be having today with regard to our citizens who suffer with cystic fibrosis and who could benefit from this drug is sadly soured by this situation.  I am very much of the view that we have passed the tipping point and that the Minister now, rightly, should engage with our EU counterparts.  When I was Minister for Health, an EU directive was passed at the EU Council that would allow EU member states to come together to purchase vaccinations.  The move allowed smaller countries gain from the buying power of bigger countries.  I believe that will have to be activated in respect of these orphan drugs.  I know this is something many will resist and there are many vested interests against the idea.</p> <p>I am not remotely against the pharmaceutical industry.  I think we have a great industry in this country and those involved have been responsible.  They drive a hard bargain and that is right, but it is important to point out that the organisation representing those companies, the Irish Pharmaceutical Healthcare Association, does not represent Vertex.  Vertex is not a member of that group.</p> <p>I think we have crossed the Rubicon.  I wish to make it clear that I know the Minister wants our patients with cystic fibrosis to have this drug, as does the Government.  As a doctor, I want my patients with cystic fibrosis to be able to avail of this drug.  I would call the bluff of Vertex and call on the company to let us have an immediate response on whether the company will be prepared to risk-share.  We know that this drug can improve quality of life for one in four of those who have the genotype.  It can work for them.  If the company agreed to that, it would represent significant progress and a start.</p> <p>It is important for everyone to acknowledge that the HSE is acting on behalf of the Government which is, in turn, acting on behalf of the people to get value for money and to make this drug available for patients.  The HSE needs our support.  I see people trying to separate Professor Michael Barry from the HSE.  He works for the HSE.  He is the face of the HSE in that room doing his damned best on our behalf and on behalf of our patients to secure these live-saving drugs.  If we pay out these exorbitant sums here, then whose home help services are we going to cut over there?  What wards will we not build over there?  What vaccinations will we not make available elsewhere?  Opportunity cost is a factor here.</p> <p>I wish to reassure those who suffer with cystic fibrosis and their families that I know the Government, and the Minister for Health in particular, are very much on their side and battling for them to get this drug to improve their lives.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator James Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2180"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2180&amp;amp;pid=DrJamesReilly&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I ask that we all get behind the HSE on this, that we are not diverted and that we get a deal so this drug can be made available to the citizens of our country who could benefit from it.  </p><p>We will not stop here because next week there will be another drug and next year there will be five more.  The current approach by certain pharmaceutical companies of seeing what the market will bear and demanding it because they feel they are in a position of monopoly cannot be allowed to pertain.  Cognisance must be taken of the fact that many charitable organisations, patient advocates and governments in their own way put a lot of funding through companies to help them research these products.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#EE00200"><p>I welcome the Minister, Deputy Harris, here this afternoon.  I compliment him on the interest he has shown in the provision of the drug, Orkambi, to cystic fibrosis sufferers.  When the Minister was in Limerick in early October to open the cystic fibrosis unit he saw it at first hand and met many of the patients who were there.  The main thing that a number of people who have come to my office wanted to stress was the quality of life of those who are suitable for taking this drug.  There was a report issued on 28 October 2016 on people who are currently taking the drug, which showed there has been a 40% decrease in hospitalisations.  It has slowed down cystic fibrosis for those currently on the drug.  These are two very important points because if fewer people are being hospitalised because the drug is working for them, it frees up beds for other people.  There are more than 550 cystic fibrosis patients across the country.  In the past, people from Ireland travelled abroad because we did not have suitable treatment in this country.  I know people who went to America for treatment.  We have come on so much in this country in terms of Beaumont Hospital and Cork and Limerick hospitals being centres of excellence.  They are the hospitals where people go for their treatment.  People are conscious of the fact that it is a large amount of money.  Vertex Pharmaceuticals is looking for &euro;159,000 a year per person for Orkambi when it has been said it should cost roughly &euro;30,000.  The Minister has the right approach in getting other European countries to come on board in negotiating and trying to get the price down.  I hope a resolution will be found to solve this matter.  Everybody here today would be of that way of thinking.  I compliment the Minister.  The sooner the HSE and Vertex can come around the table and try to come to a successful conclusion the better.  Vertex is holding us and the HSE to ransom.  They are the people in the driving seat.  They are looking for their price.  It is incumbent on all of us to bring to bear as much pressure as possible to bring down the price.  I agree with my colleague, Senator Kieran O'Donnell, on the 98 beds that are certainly very much wanted and needed for University Hospital Limerick.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#EE00300"><p>There is no one else indicating.  The Minister has five minutes to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#EE00400"><p>I thank all Senators from all sides of the House for the great solidarity we have collectively shown today with cystic fibrosis patients in this country and for the very clear message we have collectively sent to Vertex, the drugs company.  We want to make this drug available for our people, we want to pay a reasonable and fair price but we will not have extortion of our people and we will not have our cystic fibrosis patients used as pawns or held to ransom, as Senator Byrne has said.</p> <p>I begin by urging Vertex to stop talking through the media and start talking again in a room with the HSE, which is the organisation that this and the other House have decided will negotiate on drug prices.  That can start immediately.  There should be no preconditions for those talks.  There is no need for any faffing about here.  We need to get back on track with this negotiation and that can happen today.  Senator Swanick referenced Jillian McNulty and I too want to pay tribute to her.  I am reluctant to name any one person because it affects so many people but she has been a very vocal advocate on this issue.  She has also been a vocal advocate full of common sense.  She and many people with cystic fibrosis have better things to be doing than protesting outside the gates of Leinster House.  None of us wants that to happen.  We want this to be resolved.  </p> <p>A number of Senators mentioned the benefit of Orkambi.  Let me be clear, I believe there is a benefit to Orkambi.  I am not medically qualified to believe that but I believe it because that is what the doctors tell us.  That is what Professor Barry tells us.  It is what the patients tell us.  The benefit is beyond doubt.  That is not what this debate is about.  It is about a fair price and making sure we do not have a company that has a monopoly and says it has this medication but we cannot have it for our patients unless we pay a ridiculously large sum of money.  I also agree with people who say companies must get their money back.  Whatever one thinks of pharmaceutical companies, they are businesses and have priorities in that regard.  However, the valid point was made by Senator Reilly that lots of drug companies receive research and development grants and tax incentives.  This company in particular received a number of charitable contributions towards the development of this drug.  Let us not get caught up in this idea that the company has pumped loads of money in and it must get all the money back.  It also must recognise that it received a lot of assistance, including from charitable sources, in developing this drug.  That is important.</p> <p>I thank Senator Craughwell for the tribute he paid to Professor Michael Barry.  It is one that is very fitting.  He is a man full of integrity who has worked tirelessly and has not been afraid to get out front and centre and explain the rationale to people.  When I became Minister for Health, I said it was very important we did not have politicians making clinical decisions.  I would certainly rather have decisions and determinations made by somebody called Professor Barry than Minister Whatever.  I thank him and his team for their ongoing work in a very difficult area.  I agree with Senator Craughwell and many other Senators, including Senators Byrne, Reilly, Dolan and Devine on European collaboration.  It is very important.  We cannot just be in a Single Market for certain things when it suits us.  This is an area where there are huge chances to make progress.  It was palpable yesterday when I met with a number of EU health ministers in Lisbon that they too want to get engaged in this.  Already the Benelux countries have piloted the purchasing of a number of medicines, three I understand, through an arrangement.  My officials are working with the Dutch to see if there is a potential for Ireland to get further involved in that group.</p> <p>I also thank Senators for pointing out that we, as a country, have decided who does the negotiation and no pharmaceutical company will make that decision for us.  These are the rules of our land.  If they want to negotiate in our country, they should come in and respect the law of our land, just as we would respect the law of theirs.  That is an important point.</p> <p>On the confidentiality agreement and Senator Colm Burke's suggestion that it should be waived, it certainly would be very helpful.  There is much misinformation out there and many reports that the company has said one thing and the HSE has said another.  That is just getting terribly confusing for everybody.  I would like to see a situation where we could keep the likes of CF Ireland up to date with accurate factual information about what stage the negotiations are at and what the strategy is and to be able to ask them what its members think.  If Vertex was to waive that confidentiality agreement, it would be very helpful.  </p> <p>I agree with Senator Devine.  This is a heartbreaking situation.  Party politics aside, we all want to resolve this.  The Senator's call for cool heads to prevail is valid.  There is no need for preconditions from people but just the need for people to get back in the room.  I will take on board the suggestion the Senator made about our assessment system in general.  For the record of the House, it might be useful to say there is a clear enough assessment process in place.  The National Centre for Pharmaeconomics, NCPE, carries out the health assessment of the drug.  It goes to a HSE drugs group which has clinicians on it.  That group then makes a recommendation to the HSE.  Only if the HSE does not have the money to purchase the drug or if it needs additional resources does it come to the Minister of the day.  To mount pressure politically and engage in that kind of emotive debate and say the Minister should go in and sort it out is very helpful for the drugs companies.  That is not what the law our land says and is not the process we have in place.  If we deviate from that on this drug, where do we end up next week or the week after with another drug?  I fully agree with Senators who talk about risk-sharing or what we call outcome-based pricing.  This is clearly a very innovative process.  Vertex believes it will work for many patients.  I believe it works for many patients.  Let us pay for those for whom it works.  It is regrettable that Vertex was not interested in that model but let us hope they re-engage on it.  I encourage the company to re-engage on it.  </p> <p>On the issue of University Hospital Limerick that Senators Kieran O'Donnell and Byrne raised, there are pressures there and I will examine the issues raised and revert to the Senators.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I genuinely thank Senators for their support.</p><p>Senator Mark Daly asked the clear question about what other countries have done a deal with Vertex on Orkambi.  To the best of my knowledge, Austria very recently reached a deal to make the drug available to its public patients.  I am not sure of the terms and conditions of the deal but, as far as my research shows, no other EU country, or indeed any other country, has managed to make the drug available to its public health patients through an agreed reimbursement price.  We are therefore not on our own in this regard, and this is the point.  Ireland is not an outlier.  Colleagues around the globe are finding the same pressures, and it is therefore time for Vertex to reconsider its strategy in this regard.</p><p>I acknowledge the point Senator Reilly made about the drugs industry in this country.  Not every drug company behaves like Vertex does, and this is an important point to make too.  We have a drugs agreement in place that will see significant savings of &euro;750 million.  It was hard-fought and negotiated by the HSE and officials in the Department of Health with the Irish Pharmaceutical Healthcare Association, IPHA.  I acknowledge IPHA's comments this week that it wants to be very clear that Vertex is not a member of its group and does not act or speak for it.</p><p>I would be happy to come back before the House to have a more substantial discussion about the issue of organ donation, as requested by Senators Mark Daly and James Reilly.  That would be very useful.</p><p>Finally, I say to CF patients and their families that we are doing everything we possibly can and we will do everything we possibly can.  Let the negotiations recommence without posturing, faffing around or preconditions.  However, I will not be bullied or intimidated by these drug companies, I will not ignore the laws or our land and I will not stand for the exploitation of our country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#FF00200"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016120800002#FF00300"><p>At 2.30 p.m. next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-12-08a.111" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 3.30 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 13 December 2016.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>