<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300002#A00150"><p>I have received notice from the following Senators that they propose to raise the following matters:</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300002#A00175">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300002#A00200">Cycling Facilities</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300002#A00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth, to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300002#A00400"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach sincerely for allowing me to raise this matter.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth.  It is always a pleasure to have him in the House as he gives open and frank answers to Senators when we raise issues.</p>  <p>I would like to have a discussion rather than make a request.  Like many others, I welcome the huge amount of money being invested in active travel such as walking and cycling routes.  It is fantastic.  It is wonderful to see access routes to some schools, particularly those near villages and towns, and young children cycling and walking to school, which all of us will agree is far better.  The issue I want to discuss is how we improve these routes to schools in rural areas.  On quieter, narrower roads where verges are often overgrown, the cost of putting routes in place would be significant in some cases.  I would like the possibility of adding a new phase to the routes being put in place, perhaps via a pilot scheme in some counties, to be explored.</p>  <p>Children love to cycle and walk.  They love nature and weather does not seem to phase them.  We all accept that walking and cycling are far healthier.  Roosky, like many other towns and villages, is becoming more walking and cycle friendly.  We have a few issues with local schools.  Part of the bridge over the River Shannon is in Leitrim and part is in Roscommon and it is unfortunately very narrow.  If two vehicles are passing on the bridge, a child, adult or parent with a buggy cannot pass.  It would be a wonderful idea - and it has been spoken about - to install a footbridge.  It would be environmentally friendly and would provide safe passage across the bridge for cyclists and walkers and help children going to school.</p>  <p>It would be nice to have pilot schemes for rural schools for which access is an issue because of road width.  To make these roads safe, hedges would have to be cut back and perhaps replaced with timber fencing and drainage pipes would need to be put down to close off drains along roadsides.  As I said, this involves a big cost but substantial money is now being spent on active travel, which is a very good thing for all of our people.  Perhaps this proposal could be considered.  I look forward to the Minister of State's reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300002#A00500"><p>I thank Senator Murphy for raising the safe routes to school programme and providing me with the opportunity to address the Seanad about this topic on behalf of the Minister for Transport.</p>  <p>The programme for Government sets out an ambitious and wide-ranging set of commitments in relation to walking and cycling.  It committed that &euro;360 million in cross-government funding would be spent on walking and cycling every year over the lifetime of the Government.  This is equivalent to 20% of the 2020 transport capital budget.  This investment is helping to support the planned delivery of almost 1,000 km of improved walking and cycling infrastructure by 2025 and additional investment in greenways.</p>  <p>Earlier this year, the Minister for Transport, Deputy Eamon Ryan, announced an allocation of &euro;289 million for active travel in 2022 and an additional investment of &euro;60 million for greenways.  This year's allocation builds on significant progress.  In recent years, expenditure on and delivery of active travel projects has increased substantially.  It has quadrupled from approximately &euro;45 million in 2019 to &euro;184 million in 2021 and this high level of funding will continue in 2023.</p>  <p>The National Transport Authority, NTA, works with local authorities to allocate this funding to specific projects.  In 2022, Roscommon County Council received &euro;3.2 million in active travel funding, while Leitrim County Council received &euro;2 million.  Provision for projects under the safe routes to school programme in both local authority areas is included in this funding.  The programme was launched by the Department of Transport in 2021 and it has the aim of supporting walking, scooting and cycling to primary and post-primary schools and creating safer walking and cycling routes within communities through the provision of infrastructure interventions.</p> <p>There was a fantastic response to the call which was sent to all schools in the country.  Some 931 applications received and 170 schools were notified on 21 June 2021 that they had been selected for inclusion in the first round of the programme.  Two schools have since deferred their applications and one school has withdrawn, leaving 167 schools in round 1.  It should be noted that all schools that applied to the original call for applications were accepted into the programme.  If not selected in round 1, they will be selected for forthcoming rounds.</p> <p>The safe routes to school, SRTS, team in the NTA, and An Taisce have confirmed that no schools in Rooskey, County Roscommon, itself applied to the programme.  The nearest school to Rooskey that was included in round 1 of the programme is Scoil Mhuire in Newtown Forbes, County Longford, which is currently at options development phase.  There are five schools in County Roscommon which applied and were selected for round 1 of the safe routes to school programme.  These are Carrick National School, Ballinlough, and Scoil N&aacute;isi&uacute;nta Cruach&aacute;in, Croghan, which are also at options development phase, and St. Joseph&rsquo;s National School, Col&aacute;iste Chiar&aacute;in, Summerhill, Athlone, and St Paul&rsquo;s National School, Castlerea, which are at preliminary design phase.</p> <p>In terms of overall progress under the safe routes to school programme, 17 schools had front-of-school measures completed under the programme, 16 schools are in the detailed design phase and three are under construction.  The remainder are under development or design or are involved in statutory processes or public consultation.  In addition, under a separate branch of the programme, 303 schools have had cycle parking installed.  Since its launch, about &euro;3 million has been spent to date.  Due to the overwhelming initial response to the programme, with over one quarter of all schools in the country submitting an application, there are currently no plans for an additional call for schools to join the programme at this time.  It is worth noting that schools which did not apply to the programme may be eligible for mainstream active travel funding towards walking and cycling interventions.  Schools seeking such funding should contact their local authority directly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300003#B00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State's statement and acknowledge the significant amount of money that has come into counties Roscommon and Longford.  The positive thing about this is that of the 170 schools that were notified they had been included, only three opted out for genuine reasons.  I presume some of them will come back on stream again.  It shows that schoolchildren, teachers and parents are very much pro this type of activity.  In the area I am talking about, particularly regarding national schools and the local knowledge, there is Ballyfeeney National School out from Rooskey, there is Rooskey school, there is Slatta school, and there is Cloonfour, all in the immediate region.  The problem we have is that it is extremely difficult to put routes on rural roads and in rural.  We have to get it safe, we cannot take chances, and we all acknowledge that.  I acknowledge that to put some of those routes in place would be very expensive.  I presume, what the Minister of State will say is that schools can apply again when the time occurs and see what could be done in terms of possibly putting in part of route, whereby it may be possible for people to be dropped off at a point and then take their bikes to the school.  That would be good.</p>  <p>I welcome the statement.  I will go back to the schools about this.  I am encouraged that the Government policy will be to continue this type of funding.  The money is there now for next year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300003#B00500"><p>I thank the Senator.  Right now, money is not the problem or the constraint.  Under our programme for Government, &euro;1 million a day is available for walking and cycling improvements.  What better way is there to spend that than to make it safe for children to walk and cycle to school?  It has multiple benefits, but part of it is just health and happiness and not making parents have to drive their children to school before they go to work, and so on.  It is a very good thing to do.</p>  <p>Any school that did not apply or was not included can go to the local authority.  My understanding on the local authorities is that the problem is not the lack of money but that the local authorities are not getting around to spending the money.  Local representatives should lobby their local authority to allocate the money and spend it.  This is not money which is specially targeted to urban or suburban areas.  If a national school is one kilometre outside the village and has no footpath, the money can be spent on footpaths.  It does not have to be about cycling and bikes.  It can be about making it safe to walk to school; even just providing an option.  That is the reason parents do not allow their kids to walk to school.  When we do the research about why children are driven to school, it is all about safety.  If we can provide a safe route, a safe alternative, we know it will happen.  In my county, in one of the schools where interventions were made, 90% of the children are now walking and cycling to school, which is an incredible change from where it had been.  It had been about 30%.  It can work.</p>  <p>Regarding Leitrim County Council and walking and cycling infrastructure across the river in Rooskey, I know the NTA has granted an allocation for this project in the 2022 active travel allocations and it is expected the local authority should be in a position to have a consultant in place before the end of this year to undertake the initial concept and feasibility study for the provision of a suitable measure at this location.  That could be a footpath across the river, a shuttle system or some other intervention.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300003#B00550">Education and Training Boards</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300003#B00700"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach's office for choosing this Commencement debate.  I welcome the Minister of State to the Chamber.  As the Minister of State is aware, the education and training boards, ETBs, came into being in 2013 and will celebrate ten years in existence on 1 July 2023.  They follow on from the vocational educational committees, VECs.  In total they have about 32,000 staff throughout the country, with a spend in excess of &euro;2 billion.  I take this opportunity to congratulate a colleague in County Galway, Councillor Michael "Moegie" Maher, on becoming president of the Education and Training Boards Ireland, ETBI, recently.  He will be in that position for the next two years.  The ETBs are a major provider of educational services at second and third level.  In County Galway there is a huge array of colleges, including Galway Technical Institute, Galway Community College, Clarin College, Col&aacute;iste an Chreag&aacute;in and post-primary schools including Col&aacute;iste an Eachr&eacute;idh, Col&aacute;iste Bhaile Chl&aacute;ir, Col&aacute;iste Cholmcille, Col&aacute;iste na bPiarsach, Col&aacute;iste na Coiribe, Col&aacute;iste Naomh &Eacute;inne, Col&aacute;iste Naomh Eoin, Col&aacute;iste Naomh Feich&iacute;n and Merlin College in Galway city as well, and recently, a couple of community national schools.  Galway-Roscommon ETB has a footprint across the city and counties of Galway and Roscommon.</p>  <p>D&eacute;anann Bord Oideachais agus Oili&uacute;na na Gaillimhe agus Ros Com&aacute;in s&aacute;robair ar son an oideachais in iar-bhunscoileanna, i gcol&aacute;ist&iacute; breisoideachais agus, le n&iacute;os d&eacute;ana&iacute;, i scoileanna n&aacute;isi&uacute;nta pobail trasna an d&aacute; chontae.  T&aacute; s&eacute; ag lorg sol&uacute;bthachta agus neamhsple&aacute;chais maidir le c&uacute;rsa&iacute; earca&iacute;ochta laistigh den fhoireann a bh&iacute; aige roimh an morat&oacute;ir.</p>  <p>Flexibility and independence are things that ETBs had in the past and they wish to have again in the future for more efficient management of their affairs.  A report commissioned by then Minister for Education, Michael Woods, in October 2000 by Sean Cromien suggested VECs at the time would benefit from greater independence and autonomy in that this would reduce the need for recourse to the Department on issues which would normally expect to be within the remit of the chief executive and there was considerable scope for delegation in the vocational education sector.  On the requirement for the Minister for Education to approve individual teacher appointments in VECs, he said this appeared to be unnecessary.</p>  <p>This is a problem.  For example, for small issues, if a staff member has to go out on maternity leave, the board has to get permission from the parent Department to sanction and allow that.  If a staff member needs or wishes to go on a career break, equally, the board does not have that delegated authority within the ETB.  It has to get permission from the Department of Education.  If there is a critical illness, there is no independence or autonomy within the ETB.  It has to go back to the parent department.  This seems unnecessary.  It is about managing the resources that are sanctioned within the ETB.  There is a headline figure or a whole-time equivalent, within, for example, Galway-Roscommon ETB.  It is not about seeking independence to go over that; that is a different matter.  It is about managing the resources within the allocation of staffing.  It is about the chief executive being able to know he or she can replace someone who goes on maternity leave or a career break or that there is a pathway to progression for somebody, that the chief executive knows that if a grade 7 staff member leaves, that person will be replaced.</p> <p>That is what we are asking for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Kyne.  I invite the Minister of State to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C00300"><p>I thank the Chair and Senator Kyne.  The Minister for Education has asked me to answer this question about staffing arrangements for ETBs on her behalf.   As Senator Kyne may be aware, the arrangements for the allocation of teaching posts and the allocation of special needs assistants in all schools, including ETB schools, are set down in various circulars issued by the Department of Education.  As regards such posts, schools and ETBs have autonomy in the recruitment and replacement of staff within the agreed and approved staffing allocation granted to the school in question and subject to relevant procedures and criteria set out in circulars from the Department.  The Department also provides each ETB with an administrative and maintenance staffing allocation and an associated pay budget to support its individual ETB schools and head office.  It is the responsibility of each ETB to recruit and manage staffing levels within this allocation, including the assignment of such staff to the different functional areas of the ETB in accordance with the needs and priorities of the organisation.  In line with the general position across the public sector, every ETB must operate within overall approved staffing and pay budgets for its administrative and maintenance staff.  ETBs have discretion to temporarily employ a substitute for existing ancillary staff in schools who are temporarily absent due to sick leave and so on, where the temporary absence would otherwise result in either no secretary, no caretaker or no cleaner being in the school on the days in question, and where the ETB can fund the temporary employment of the substitute from its existing pay budget for non-teaching staff.</p>  <p>However, ETBs are required to seek prior approval from the Department for new posts or to replace existing sanctioned administrative and maintenance posts on a temporary or permanent basis.  In considering such requests, the Department will consider factors such as the particular circumstances and needs arising for the ETB concerned, and will also have regard to the affordability of the post, or replacement post where applicable, within the administrative and maintenance pay budget of the ETB itself, and within the relevant pay budget for the ETB sector as a whole.  I can confirm that over recent years the Department has, as resources permitted, granted a significant number of additional administrative and maintenance posts to the ETB sector.  In the period since 2015, the Department has increased the number of approved posts in head offices by 29% across all sectors.  I can also confirm that the vast majority of replacement head office administrative posts sought by ETBs are granted by the Department.  For example, since 2017, 85% of such requests have been granted.  The Department remains fully committed to supporting ETBs and will continue to work closely with individual ETBs and with the sector collectively to ensure they are adequately resourced to deliver their very important work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the response from the Department.  The Department states in the response that in the period since 2015, it has increased the number of approved posts in head offices by 29% across the sector.  Of course that is because of the lifting of the moratorium so they are getting back to where they were.  The point is that the ETBs had this autonomy and independence in the past.  It was taken away from them during the financial crisis and the moratorium, and they wish to see it relaxed and to get it back.  Why is it necessary for an ETB to have to go to the Department for permission to replace somebody going on maternity leave or on a career break or somebody who is out with a serious illness?  That is the question that has not been answered in the Department's reply.  Could I ask the Minister of State to go back to the Minister for Education to get those questions answered in relation to restoring the autonomy that the ETBs once had?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C00600"><p>My understanding is that the ETBs, and I was a board member of the Dublin and D&uacute;n Laoghaire ETB in the past, have autonomy and independence in hiring staff and choosing how they spend their staff budget and so on.  The problem arises when they are hiring a replacement staff member whose pay is additional to the budget that has already been allocated.  As the Senator is shaking his head, I may have that wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C00700"><p>That is not what we are being told.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C00800"><p>When somebody is on long-term sick leave, for example, and an additional person needs to be hired, there is an increase in the budget costs and the ETB is required to go back to the Department to seek sanction.  The Department's view on this is that it is approving 85% of applications in that situation.  I suppose the intention is for the ETBs to live within their budgets, not to exceed the amounts of money allocated in the budget at the start of the year, and to stay within the fiscal prudence envelope.  I can pass on Senator Kyne's concerns to the Minister and he can ask me outside this forum if he has any clarifications he wishes to put to me.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.24" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C00950">Disability Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C01000"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, for joining us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300004#C01100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I hope she can catch her breath now.</p><p>In August, it was announced that a new multidisciplinary primary care assessment hub for children under the progressing disability services, PDS, programme was to open in Castleknock.  That is very good news and is much welcomed.  Obviously, it has prompted a lot more communication from parents to me about the children's disability network team, CDNT, waiting list in the area.  I will give an overview of some examples I have received.</p><p>I have been contacted by a parent whose son is heading into secondary school.  He has had one stage 1 desk-based interview.  He has severe hearing loss, dyspraxia and, potentially, autism.  His waiting time is 37 months for a stage 2 assessment of need clinical assessment.</p><p>I have been told about an eight-year-old who has been on the waiting list for an assessment of need for a year.  This child, who has been referred to primary care services, is on a waiting list for child psychology but no time period has been indicated, and is facing a two-year wait for occupational therapy.  This is in the Dublin 15 area.</p><p>Another parent has told me that since the switch to the CDNT system, in one year their child has seen the speech and language therapist, SLT, four times; the occupational therapist, OT, three times; and the physiotherapist twice.  The SLT has left and there is no-one to replace her.  Under the early intervention team, EIT, her son had one-to-one therapy at least every second week.  That is in Blakestown.</p><p>In relation to transfers from the early intervention team in Blanchardstown, it seems that one person is manning the emails and the phones.  I have been told by a few parents that they get the same text in response to emails.  It reads:</p> <blockquote> 	We have received waiting lists of children from various services, HSE, CRC, DOC, school-age team and Beechpark Services.  [They have amalgamated those multiple lists and are afraid to say that the waiting list is long.]  The original date of referral for your child will be honoured.  Currently I am unable to give you a timeframe when they will be seen by the team. </blockquote>  <p>Another email said that the current waiting time is three years, and another said it is in excess of three years.</p><p>I would like to quote from correspondence from another parent:</p> <blockquote> 	When we were with early intervention we could access an OT, SLT and psychologist.  They answered their phones and if they could not they would get back to you within 24 hours.  On EIT we had regular phone support services with OT, psychologists, SLT, even though no diagnosis his needs were addressed and I felt empowered.   </blockquote>  <p>The question that she wants answered is: are they still doing that?</p><p>I am hoping the Minister of State can give me some clarity around the transfer to the EIT system and the CDNT system, with reference to the waiting lists for these parents and what is actually happening behind the scenes.  </p> <p>They feel their basic needs are not being met.  I know the Minister of State hears this all the time and is committed to changing it but the children and their families are exhausted.</p> <p>This issue boils down to resources.  Where are we with resources for CHO 9?  Has there been a change to the HSE national panel of recruitment?  I am consistently asked by psychologists if that issue is being addressed.  These families are paying privately and they come from all walks of life and have different experiences and socioeconomic backgrounds.  One family informed me their child will soon be seen because the HSE has outsourced the multidisciplinary assessment to a private company.  Is that now happening?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300005#D00200"><p>I thank Senator Currie for giving me the opportunity to discuss CHO 9.  I will just reverse a little, if the Senator does not mind.  When we started the assessments of need in October 2020 one of our largest lists in the entire country was in CHO 9.  This meant it was one of the last lists to be completed at that point in time.  We were completing the assessment of need process, which was the old assessment of need rather than a preliminary team assessment or anything like that, and we got through it all.  The Senator is right that we faltered at the end.  We got stuck in approximately 33 cases due to the psychology and complexity involved in them.  However, we got all the lists cleared.</p>  <p>While we were doing those assessments of need, the reform of progressing disabilities took place.  This was challenging in the Senator's area for the simple reason that we pulled it all apart.  The parents are probably telling the Senator that it was all pulled apart.  Various teams were put in place.  St. Michael's House, the Central Remedial Clinic, CRC, Avista and the HSE were the teams left in charge of the Senator's area.</p>  <p>There is no denying that since then, retention and recruitment in the area of children's disabilities has been incredibly difficult, particularly in Dublin.  To that end, I compliment St. Michael's House, Avista and the CRC because they have addressed the issue.  They are making their own arrangements for recruitment and have moved ahead of where we were on the PDS roadmap.  They could not wait for the central office of the HSE to make a decision.  Supported by Olive Hanley, they decided, because they were in a crisis, to start their international recruitment.  They set a target to fill 96 posts across all the various levels, specifically speech and language therapy, occupational therapy and psychology.  They are being supported by the HSE in that intensive recruitment drive, which has been ongoing since June.  I see the fruits of it coming through in the teams.</p>  <p>This is of little comfort for the families who have emailed Senator Currie asking her specific questions.  On the question as to whether early intervention is still happening, the answer is "No" because they are now all part of one team.  Early intervention teams used to be a separate piece but are now part of the wider CDNT team.  However, the skill set is still there and early intervention is still the priority.  It was the one piece of the jigsaw that worked very well in the HSE and the various organisations.  While people may not have got an assessment, they got the early intervention and were listened to and communicated with.</p>  <p>A lot of work is taking place, as the Senator has said, in providing responses by email or telephone and telling parents when they can expect to get a call back and that they have not been forgotten about.  In last year's budget, money was set aside to ensure every single CDNT team had proper administration to answer emails and phone calls.  Those administrative positions are being filled or have been filled in the Senator's area to support the teams.  We do not want clinicians to be answering phones or writing emails.  We want them to be face-to-face with children.  To be fair, from what I can see on the ground, this is turning around.  CHO 9 has been the most challenging of all the CHOs but they are working together as a collective rather than in isolation.  It is not a matter of, for example, Blakestown being in one team and another area having another team.  They are sharing resources and skill sets and the recruitment drive in CHO 9.  I can see that transitioning down.</p>  <p>To be honest with the Senator, I get uncomfortable when someone is told it will be three years before someone is seen.  The teams cannot say it will be three years for the simple reason that we are working with teams that are 74% populated.  Some of the teams in the Senator's area had recruitment figures as low as 50%.  That is starting to increase slowly but surely.  If that figure was to come down to what I could identify as an acceptable level of clinical risk, we would be in a comfortable position.  There is a challenge regarding the 96 posts.  The target is to fill them within eight months and we are getting through them by working together and knowing what disciplines are needed from one team to the other.  The teams have taken ownership of this and I and the HSE are supporting them with whatever they need.  Senior managers in Avista, CRC and St. Michael's House have been able to recruit and I can see the difference this has made.  This is of little comfort to the parent the Senator quoted but in six months' time, we will have a pathway towards good skill sets.  I will discuss this with the Senator shortly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1648" speakername="Emer Currie" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300005#D00300"><p>I would like to see the progress the Minister of State is seeing.  I do not know how I will get to see that by tabling a parliamentary question to the Minister every month.  I need to see it so that I can tell the parents who are in contact with me.  The communications they are receiving indicate it will be three years.  They are not getting the communication they used to have and need and want.  The Minister of State spoke of targets of eight months and six months and I will hold her to those.</p>  <p>I will ask her again about the panel of recruitment.  How does that fit into what is happening?  What is happening as regards the therapists who were to be brought back into special schools?  I have heard there has been an intervention by F&oacute;rsa in that regard and we are not seeing those therapists back in the schools.  Will the Minister of State comment on that?  Is recruitment for those specific roles necessary?  Is that the approach that will be taken or will these therapists come from the CDNTs?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300005#D00400"><p>The other evening I referred in my speech to F&oacute;rsa.  It is amazing what happens on the floor of the D&aacute;il because since Tuesday evening, the HSE and F&oacute;rsa have met twice and I hear that progress is being made.  I also spoke to John Kearney of the National Council for Special Education, NCSE, this morning and I will issue communications to all the special schools.  I am waiting for the head of disabilities, Bernard O'Regan, to tell me the outcome of this.  I assume everybody wants to see children getting an intervention and being supported.  I have no doubt the union wants that as well.  I do not want to assume but I am hopeful a common sense approach will be taken and we will see therapists going into the schools.  I have allocated &euro;13.5 million to recruit 133 staff to go back on to the teams.  While we are taking them from the teams, they are still part of the team and just happen to be spending a certain number of hours supporting the school side.</p>  <p>We have blown the panels open completely because I needed to get as many people as possible into the CDNT teams to support the schools.  We abandoned the panels.</p> <p>To be fair to Damien McCallion in the HSE, he went in there and said they had to tear it apart and blow it open to ensure that we can get everybody off panels and into either the CDNTs or back into the schools.  I think I have answered both questions.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.32" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300006#E00200">Health Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300006#E00300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House.  I am speaking today on behalf of families in County Longford, and indeed, all the families that have been affected by cancer.  I want to take this opportunity to compliment everyone involved in Longford Hospice Homecare and all the community nurses who are based in Longford.  Longford Hospice Homecare has been operating in my county for all of my lifetime.  A tremendous amount of work and fundraising has been done.  I want to compliment the work the organisation does.</p>  <p>The issue I am raising today is one that I raised 12 months ago.  It concerns the need for additional palliative care beds at St. Joseph's Care Centre.  A massive redevelopment was announced by the former Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, a number of years ago, with over &euro;5 million in funding and planning processes and discussions.  We were told that there would be a minimum of two palliative beds, yet we still only have one.  I wrote to the HSE and got a letter back basically saying that any decision to designate one or more beds would have to be made by the HSE at a national level, and any commitment to increasing the number of palliative care support beds at the expense of long-stay beds would have to be accompanied by an appropriate budget allocation to compensate for the fair deal income reduction in order to maintain services for current and future residents.  I do not think that is acceptable.</p>  <p>I have submitted evidence and have written to the HSE regarding getting more updated figures for the last number of months.  I was given a figure of 64% bed capacity in 2021, but it was actually higher.  We have seen that in recent weeks &euro;20 million has been allocated to a 20-bed unit in Tullamore to cover the midlands area, but the reality is that we still have just one palliative care bed in St. Joseph's.  There are numerous families with loved ones who are spending their last days in acute hospital settings or in palliative care outside their county and not close to home.  That is not fair on the families and it is not acceptable.  There are areas within the campus in Longford where extra beds could be facilitated.  A gentleman that I knew all my life passed away in the last 24 hours.  God rest him.  He was unable to access a palliative care bed in Longford because there were none available.  This needs to be addressed.  It is not acceptable.  We want changes made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300006#E00400"><p>My condolences to the family of the individual the Senator mentioned.  The Minister of State has four minutes to reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300006#E00500"><p>I, too, want to be associated with the condolences expressed.</p>  <p>I am taking this matter today on behalf of the Minister for Health.  I would like to thank Senator Carrigy for raising this important issue.  The Government is strongly committed to providing high-quality, evidence-based palliative care in Ireland.  The Department of Health, in line with the national palliative care policy of 2001, is committed to furthering the development of palliative care across the country, ensuring a seamless pathway for patients who need palliative care across inpatient, home care, nursing home and day care services.  St. Joseph's Care Centre, Longford, provides 24-hour nursing care for up to 68 residents in an invaluable service that is embedded in the community.  There are planned refurbishment works for St. Joseph's Care Centre in Longford and the HSE is committed to providing a second palliative care support bed when works are complete.  The HSE has held meetings with the Longford hospice committee and will continue to do so to review the plans to achieve the optimum location to facilitate the second palliative care support bed.  Currently, the HSE in the region also has a consultant-led specialist palliative care team that supports individuals in their homes.  It engages with community nursing staff and midland regional hospital to support patients and families.</p>  <p>In September 2022, the Taoiseach announced capital funding of &euro;20 million to progress the development of a 20-bed specialist palliative care unit in the midlands.  The announcement of this funding is a significant milestone for palliative care in the midlands and will deliver on the programme for Government commitment to progress plans for a specialist palliative unit in the midlands.  The new hospice will be co-located at the midland regional hospital and will provide a hub for the provision of specialist palliative care services across the midlands, including day care, outpatient and inpatient community services.</p>  <p>In line with the programme for Government, the extensive refurbishment of St. Joseph's Care Centre in Longford aims to prioritise and protect the most vulnerable.  The HSE has committed to providing a second palliative care support bed at the site when works are complete and is engaging with Longford hospice committee about the plans.  This Government will continue to work with local organisations to ensure that people with life-limiting conditions across the country receive the level of palliative care they require.</p>  <p>In the time that I have left, I wish to state that while the response is a very comprehensive answer in respect of the midlands, it does not answer the Senator's specific question about beds in Longford.  I propose to set up a meeting between the Senator, his colleagues, the Minister for Health and representatives of the HSE locally to discuss the timeline and the funding, and where we are with the delivery of a second palliative care bed for the Longford region.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300006#E00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response, which comprehensively states that we are going to have a second palliative bed.  It is something that we have been looking for for many years.  I thank the Minister of State for her proposal to set up a meeting.  I will take her up on the offer to attend the meeting with my colleague, Councillor Peggy Nolan, who the Minister of State knows well, who has fought the fight for many years to ensure that we maintain and improve the services that we have in Longford, and in St. Joseph's Care Centre in particular, where there is an excellent staff.  I know, from personal experience, of the work they do there.</p>  <p>The Minister of State mentioned evidence-based palliative care.  I am delighted that the evidence that we submitted last year proved that the need was there, when we were told that it was not.  The need is there.  I ask that the situation is monitored continuously and that where there is additional need, it be met through the provision of additional beds.  That must be guaranteed.  I thank the Minister of State for her commitment and the offer to set up a meeting with the Minister for Health.  I will take her up on that offer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="11:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300006#E00700"><p>To sum up, the Government is committed to support people in all regions, but particularly the hospice and palliative care community.  We need to take an evidence-based approach.  Where there is evidence, we must look at it, take it on board and prioritise it.  I look forward to setting up the meeting with the Minister, the Senator and his colleagues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.38" nospeaker="true" time="11:00:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 11.17 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 12 noon.<br />Sitting suspended at 11.17 a.m. and resumed at 12 noon.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.39" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300007#K00100">Teachtaireacht ón Dáil - Message from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300007#K00200"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures and Miscellaneous Provisions Bill 2022 on 12 October 2022, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p>  <p>Before I call the Acting Leader to propose the Order of Business, I welcome Caroline and Martin Smith from Trim in County Meath to the Gallery.  This year is the seventh anniversary of the loss of their son, Stephen.  I know they are here because the Leader will propose an amendment to the Order of Business and introduce legislation which it is hoped will recognise the loss of their son.  I thank them both for being with us here today.  I call the Acting Leader to propose the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.41" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300007#K00300">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="11:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300007#K00400"><p>Our guests are very welcome.  The Order of Business is No. <i>a</i>1, Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures and Miscellaneous Provisions Bill 2022 - all Stages, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business, and the proceedings thereon shall, if not previously concluded, be brought to conclusion after one hour and 45 minutes by the putting of one question from the Chair, which shall, in relation to amendments, include only those set down or accepted by Government; the time allocated to the opening remarks of the Minister in the debate on Second Stage shall not exceed ten minutes, the contributions of group spokespersons shall not exceed five minutes, those of all other Senators shall not exceed three minutes, Senators may share time, and the Minister shall be given not less than eight minutes to reply to the debate; and Committee and remaining Stages to be taken immediately thereafter; and No. 1, motion for early signature of Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures and Miscellaneous Provisions Bill 2022, to be taken without debate on conclusion of No. <i>a</i>1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="11:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300007#K00500"><p>Today and this week mark baby loss awareness week and it is now in its 20th year.  It is a wonderful opportunity to bring people together as a community in a safe and supportive space to support anybody who has been touched by pregnancy and baby loss and to allow people to share their experiences, feel connected and share each others' grief.  It is probably a little known fact that one in four pregnancies in Ireland results in the loss of a baby.  It is a devastating loss to parents and to the family, and anybody who knows that loss knows it only too well.  A collaboration of charities and agencies across Ireland, through baby loss awareness week, try to raise the awareness of key issues affecting those people and families who experience pregnancy loss and baby loss.</p>  <p>One of the really severe issues that exists in Ireland is that the State does not recognise the existence of a large number of the babies who are lost during pregnancy.  Two people who have become good friends of mine and have worked tirelessly over recent years, Caroline and Martin Smith, are in the House today and I thank the Cathaoirleach for welcoming them.  They genuinely have worked tirelessly to address the issue that has hurt them and so many other families like them over the years, that is, the State refusing to recognise their loss and the member of their family who is much loved, their son Stephen.  Stephen was born seven years ago next week.  He was 420 g at birth and Caroline was 20 weeks and two days pregnant.  Despite Caroline giving birth to Stephen, the State does not see him as ever having existed because he did not reach the milestones as set down in the stillbirth definition by the WHO.  There are many families like Caroline and Martin and many little babies like Stephen.  I cannot begin to imagine what it must be like to live with the grief of loss when your own State does not even recognise that your much-loved baby, from the first hiccup to today, ever even existed.</p>  <p>Today, I am seeking leave to amend the Order of Business to introduce, with my colleague Senator Seery Kearney, a Bill called the Civil Registration (Amendment) (Certificate of Life) Bill.  It is on behalf of Martin and Caroline and their son Stephen and all the other Stephens in Ireland that I do this.  I want the State to establish a non-statutory register that allows these births, these lives and these losses to be recognised by the State in order that families can grief, move on, and live with the devastating loss without the obstruction of the State not recognising the citizen who is and was and has passed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300007#K00600"><p>The Leader has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, that No. 16 be taken before No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="11:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300007#K00700"><p>The Leader will be aware, and we have read in today's newspapers, that the Irish dancing organisation at the centre of the feis fixing scandal has received a report from Mr. Justice Peart.  We now understand that the next phase of that will be an internal process within that organisation.  Parents and teachers who have contacted me over recent weeks and again this morning are deeply unhappy with the way matters have transpired.  The information, or leaks if you want, which led to this investigation was provided to the organisation back in July.  It took until September for it to involve itself in a process by appointing the judge and only after the same information started to make its way into the public domain through social media.</p> <p> The teachers and parents who have spoken to me have no faith in the process now under way.  Teachers have been meeting around the country over the past few nights.  As I understand it, there are some 2,000 Irish dancing teachers across the world, with about 800 in Ireland.  They are deeply unhappy with what has happened.  A relatively small number of teachers and judges have been involved in this.  The teachers want a resolution.</p> <p>While the State does not provide funding to An Coimisi&uacute;n Le Rinc&iacute; Gaelacha, Conradh na Gaeilge is the patron body of this organisation.  I appeal to Conradh na Gaeilge to use whatever good offices are available to it to try to bring some sense to bear here.  We need a proper transparent process.  I am hopeful that, collectively, the organisation and its patron will ensure the report being prepared by the judge is passed to the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin.</p> <p>Since An Coimisi&uacute;n Le Rinc&iacute; Gaelacha is registered as a charity, I believe the judge's report should go to the Charities Regulator at a minimum.  I and the teachers who are not involved in this - and only a very small number are involved - hope the management of the organisation will appear before the Oireachtas joint committee.  I understand such a request is about to be made and from what I hear, there seems to be some resistance from within the organisation.  This process needs to be open and transparent.</p> <p>Let us not forget that this organisation is the international guardian of Irish dancing.  Within its charter it sees its role as promoting the Irish language.  Many in this House have an interest in the Irish language and we want to see it promoted.  We want to see Irish dancing and our culture promoted.  We do not need anything that undermines that.  This is a very serious issue that must be addressed.  I hope that what I have outlined can be brought to pass.  I ask the Leader to request that the Minister, Deputy Catherine Martin, come to the House at the earliest opportunity to discuss this matter.</p> <p>If the Cathaoirleach will indulge me, I will raise one other matter.  The budget reintroduced the 13.5% VAT rate for the hospitality sector, which includes hotels and restaurants.  This came on the back of what many of us identified as price gouging by hotels in Dublin.  For example, when there is a shortage of rooms or hotels get to their last couple of rooms they jack up their prices, doubling and trebling them at weekends.  This is unacceptable behaviour.  The Cathaoirleach represents a constituency like mine that is steeped in tourism and has lot of hotels.  There is no Dublin hotel in County Clare and none in Kerry either.  Nor would hotels in Clare or Kerry be able to sustain those prices.  Significant pressure is being put on other hotels as a result of the actions of hotels in this city.  I would like a debate in the House with the Minister for Finance on the possibility of splitting hotel rooms in Dublin from the rest of the country.  If that is not possible, we should split hotels and hotel rooms - accommodation - from the food sector.  We recently heard from Adrian Cummins of the Restaurants Association of Ireland that it had never before seen the number of closures coming down the tracks.  We need to address that.  Having supported the industry during tough times using taxpayers' money, we do not want these entities to close as a result of the changes in the VAT structure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L00200"><p>It is strange that every time I come into the Seanad for the Order of Business, something derails my line of thought.  Senator Doherty has certainly derailed mine today.  I have a sister who lost two children at full term.  I cannot begin to tell the House the pain that she has felt in her life at the loss of those children.  I fully support what Senator Doherty is trying to do.  I offer my deepest sympathies to Caroline and Martin Smith, who are in the Gallery.</p>  <p>I congratulate the Acting Leader on his elevation.  I spent four days in Estonia at the Tallinn Digital Summit, the lead summit in the area of cybersecurity and digital security.  I was rather disappointed that there was no other Irish representative present from official Ireland.  The summit was attended by prime ministers, ministers and senior civil servants from all over the world.  One of the key topics for those whom I met, as an Irishman, was Ireland's lack of defence capability, given that 95% of the world's data cross the Atlantic into Europe.  We do not know what is going on beneath our sea and it has been the fault of countless Governments for running our Defence Forces into the ground.</p>  <p>I reviewed the recent statement made by the Minister for Defence, Deputy Coveney, in the House.  I was not here for the debate with him.  He does not answer questions but talks down the clock.  That is all the Minister does.  I then opened a newspaper to see that a private security firm had been employed to look at the cables coming into Ireland.  It was somewhat hard to understand whether this involved electrical cables, gas pipes or data cables.  It does not matter.  Are we at the stage now where we outsource the security of the State to some private security company?  That is beyond acceptable.  For this reason, I wish to move an amendment to the Order of Business to ask the Minister to come to the House - I do not care if it is at 10 o'clock tonight - to explain to the people of Ireland how we have allowed our country to finish up in a situation where our Naval Service is virtually inoperable, we do not have an air force and depend instead on the RAF and we-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L00300"><p>The Minister was in the Seanad last week.  He is here more often than Senator Craughwell is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L00400"><p>I am aware that my colleagues want to talk about my trip to Qatar.  I am quite prepared to give a detailed report next week on that.  It is a cheap shot but leaving that aside-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L00500"><p>The Minister appeared before the House last week to discuss the Defence Forces.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L00600"><p>Please allow Senator Craughwell to continue without interruption.  Senator Buttimer knows the rules on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L00700"><p>The bottom line is this.  What an embarrassment that this State, in which we constantly talk about our sovereignty and neutrality and hear all the other nonsense about the defence of the State, is unable to protect the very lifeblood of data that come through this country or the economic zone for which we are responsible?  People speak about the "cloud" as if it was up there.  It is not.  It is beneath sea and is coming in off our west coast.  We have no idea what is going on there.</p>  <p>We must remember one thing, however.  In the middle of a war in Ukraine, the Ukrainian Government was able to roll out a digital system that allows citizens to access some 7,000 government services.  So humbled were the Estonians by that, and they are the leaders in digital technology in the world, at the recent conference that they said they hoped to emulate in Estonia what has happened in Ukraine.  When we tried to introduce a public service card here some years ago, as the Cathaoirleach will recall, it caused consternation.  At the hotel in Estonia, I was speaking to a young woman who told me she gets supermarket discounts using her public service identity card.  She is able to bank with the card and can electronically sign documents with it.  Where are we going in this country?  The defence of the country is my key concern.  We need the Minister to come to the House and actually answer questions rather than talk down----- </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L00800"><p>He was here last week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L00900"><p>I am well aware that he was here last week.  There are times when other Ministers are here and Senator Buttimer is not.  I was away on business and the Senator can like it or lump it.  The Minister needs to come to the House to explain.  The story only broke in the last few days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L01000"><p>On a point of order, I was not referring to Senator Craughwell's travels.  I was referring to the fact that we had a debate on the Defence Forces in the House last week.  That is what I was referring to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" speakername="Mark Wall" time="11:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300008#L01100"><p>I welcome Caroline and Martin Smith to the House today.  I thank Senators Doherty and Seery Kearney for introducing vital legislation, which I look forward to supporting as it goes through the House.</p>  <p>I support my colleague Senator Craughwell.  In fairness, it is correct that the Minister was in the House last week.  He was answering questions when the bells rang for a vote and unfortunately he had to go.  He offered to come back to the House.  Senator Craughwell's call should be supported and I am sure the Minister will come back to answer those questions.  As I said, he was in the middle of answering some detailed questions but unfortunately the bell rang and he had to stop.</p>  <p>It is good to see the Acting Leader in the Chair.  I raise the issue of the entitlements of surviving cohabitants to a widow's or widower's pension.  I raise it again in light of a recent High Court decision in which a Tipperary man, Mr. John O'Meara, was refused a widower's pension following the death of his loving partner of 20 years.</p> <p>According to RT&Eacute;, "It was the role of the Oireachtas to decide exactly who should benefit from this pension, the judge said, adding that the making of such decisions 'is not a role which this court can legitimately play.'"</p> <p>I introduced a Bill on behalf of the Labour Party in October 2021 to address this exact situation, entitled the Social Welfare (Surviving Cohabitant's Pension) Bill 2021.  The Bill, as introduced, sought to amend the Social Welfare Consolidation Act 2005 to entitle surviving cohabitants to a contributory widow's pension and to provide for related matters.  The concept of family, as we all know in this House, has changed.  It is time to bring Ireland into the 21st century.  We all want families to be treated fairly, whether they are married or not.  It is estimated there are 150,000 or more cohabiting couples in this country.  The 2016 census showed there are more than 75,000 cohabiting couples in Ireland with child dependants, meaning these families will also lose out on the &euro;8,000 grant provided to a widower with dependent children on the death of a married partner.  I ask the Acting Leader for time in the House to discuss this important matter with the Minister for Social Protection.</p> <p>As the Acting Leader is aware, I have spoken many times in this House about rural transport.  I welcome the introduction of the new 821 rural link service in Kildare South that will link Newbridge with the town of Naas and the train station there.  This new service is to be welcomed in that it will provide a seven-day Local Link public transport service to the villages of Kilmeague, Robertstown and Carragh for the first time, as well as an increased service for Milltown, Allenwood and Prosperous.  I have continually raised over recent years the lack of public transport services from these villages.  It is one of the biggest issues that has been raised with me by local residents.  I wish to thank Kildare Rural Transport Link, its manager, Alan Kerry, and indeed the National Transport Authority, NTA, for listening to locals and public representatives.  I look forward to the new service commencing next Monday, 17 October.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="11:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300009#M00200"><p>I want to begin by honouring the Smith family and thanking them for their tireless work.  I hope that Baby Stephen is the first to be registered.  I believe that should happen.  He can lead the way for so many other babies who need to be recognised.  I am thankful to the Leader for allowing me to be a co-sponsor of the Bill.  A certificate of life is an extremely important thing for people who have experienced loss.  From the moment the two lines appear on a pregnancy test, a lifetime is lived with that baby.  Walks in the park are imagined.  There is discussion of schools that will be attended.  Names are speculated about.  There are considerations of sharing the news with wider family.  That couple, the family and the mother go through that whole experience.  It is very important that that life is recognised by the State, because when that life is no more, the loss is great.  We are seven years on and Baby Stephen is as much a part of the Smith family today as he was then.</p>  <p>I am 14 years on from my first miscarriage.  On 29 December every year, we go to the grave of my grandparents because I do not have anywhere else to go.  There is no other place where my first baby can be remembered.  We lay a wreath and remember, as a family, the lifetime that was lived in that period of time our baby was due and was a member of our family, and continues to be a member of our family.  Today is a very significant day.  It is a real honour to be part of it.  I thank the Smith family for all of the work they have done and for all of the recognition they are going to bring for themselves, for Stephen and for all of the other families in this country who deserve the recognition of their grieving and their loss.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300009#M00300"><p>I thank the Senator for seconding the proposal and for sharing her story, which is, unfortunately, the story of so many.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1634" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="11:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300009#M00400"><p>First, I welcome the Smith family to the House.  It is great to see them here.  I also thank the Leader, Senator Doherty, and Senator Seery Kearney for their proposed legislation.  I look forward to supporting it.  It is timely, appropriate and necessary.  I particularly thank Senator Seery Kearney for sharing.  We are not very close in emotional aspects of anyone's life.  It makes it very real when the lived experience and emotion is brought to the House.  I acknowledge that and thank Senator Seery Kearney and the Leader for it.  I wish Senator Gallagher well.  It is great to see him in the Leader's chair and I wish him well with that.</p>  <p>Yesterday we had a heated debate about peat.  I will not go into it now.  Suffice it to say the Acting Leader has been very active in it in terms of horticulture.  It was a very heated debate.  I advised the people from the representative bodies of the horticultural sector and the agrifood sector who attended that meeting that they need to get political and they pull the lever on their Deputies, Senators and sitting county councillors in their communities.  They are simply not being listened to.  I flagged a bit of hope to them in relation to the words of the T&aacute;naiste who said that the issue simply has to be resolved.  He recognises the difficulties.  I thank him and the members of his party who have faced up to that.  There is a great frustration and a need to do something about it.  I would like us to have a debate on the matter if possible.</p>  <p>I would like to highlight the publication of the report on Issues Impacting Dog Welfare in Ireland, which will be launched at 1 p.m. in the audiovisual room.  Many Senators are members of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  The report is a very substantive piece of work.  There is great interest in animal welfare in Ireland and within these Houses.  I commend the report to Senators.  If they are available, I invite them to come to the audiovisual room at 1 p.m..  There is also a photo opportunity at around 12.50 p.m.on the Plinth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300009#M00500"><p>Before I call the next speaker, I welcome Deputy Troy and his guests to the Visitors Gallery.  They are most welcome.  I call Senator Buttimer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="11:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300009#M00600"><p>It gives me great pleasure to ask the Acting Leader to bring the Minister for Education to the House for a debate.  I say sincerely and genuinely that, notwithstanding the issues with Covid, and I appreciate a gargantuan effort has been made with the leaving certificate, we are now into mid-October and the junior certificate students still have not got their results.  That is very unfair.  I accept the challenges around leaving certificate appeals and understand the leaving certificate was a priority, but it is now 13 October.  Many students who are in transition year or fifth year have to make subject choices for their leaving certificate.  I hope the Minister for Education will come to the House for a wide-ranging debate on the role of the State Examinations Commission, the review of the junior and leaving certificate curriculums and the education system in general.  I hope the Acting Leader can put in that request.  It is an important matter and one that is causing stress and angst for many people.</p>  <p>I commend the Leader and Senator Seery Kearney on their work and welcome the Smith family.  I was 2 lb when I was born.  I was 14 weeks premature.  The life of Baby Stephen we are discussing today is one that many of us can associate with.  We all have family members, relations, cousins or friends who have had miscarriages.  It is important this Bill is fast-tracked by Government because it is about people.  I commend the Leader and Senator Seery Kearney on their work on it.</p>  <p>I hope that, as I have facilitated the Acting Leader in the past, he will facilitate me in inviting the Minister for Education to the House.  I will not propose an amendment to the Order of Business, but I know the Acting Leader will facilitate my request.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="11:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300009#M00700"><p>I, too, congratulate both the Leader on her work on this Bill and the Smith family.  It means an awful lot to so many people.  We cannot be anything but moved by Senator Seery Kearney's words, because so many of us have experienced that loss.  We are here and we are listening because we know that that life matters.  Even though they are not here, they matter every single day of the week and every single day of the year.  I really welcome the Bill and congratulate the Leader.  I thank the Leader and the Smith family for their work on it, because it is very important.</p>  <p>I came in today to congratulate the Irish women's soccer team on their historic win against Scotland and to highlight the importance of that.  I remember standing in my kitchen as a young girl, looking at Alan McLoughlin scoring that goal to get us to the 1994 World Cup.  Now, Amber Barrett is a national hero.  I never thought an Irish girl could don the Irish jersey and represent her country at a world cup.  We really have created new national heroes.</p>  <p>However, moving on from that, the story that has brought down the heroism is a problem we have to highlight.</p>  <p>As a country, we have failed to recognise what "Up the 'RA" means.  It is not simple.  We should apologise to these young women because we have not educated people on what that slogan means.  It is not an innocent catchy slogan; it means death, explosions, heartache and agony.  We have failed to describe and explain the filthy rotten reality of the war that went on all around us on this island and what the IRA were and are to this day.  They were indiscriminate murderers, rapists, drug dealers, smugglers and extortionists who threatened communities all around this country.  There was no beautiful glorious search for independence involved in threatening neighbours to keep their mouths shut because they could be next.  When the IRA went looking for protection money, if you had paid the other crowd, you did not have to pay the IRA.  It was filthy and rotten.  There is nothing to celebrate about either the British Army or the IRA because both perpetuated the agony of war and are now responsible for prolonging that agony.  We have elected representatives standing at the graves of terrorists, and soldiers who were involved in collusion and murder have been talking out of both sides of their mouths in respect of the truth of what happened to many victims.  When families such as that of Columba McVeigh are not able to bury their loved ones, we have serious problems.  We need to stop misrepresenting history and trying to change it and lie about the truth of the IRA.  These people murdered, attacked, raped, threatened and stole.  That is the truth.  We have a choice.  We can keep pretending that it is innocent to say "Up the 'RA" when we are referring to an organisation that murdered fathers, mothers, pregnant women, daughters, nieces, friends and nephews.  This House, this State and this entire country has a choice.  We can either act to educate people and face up to bitter reality or we can continue to ignore the truth of the slaughter that went on and continue to make little of this slogan.  We have a choice and we should make the right one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="11:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300010#N00200"><p>I welcome the Acting Leader and the Smith family, who are here on behalf of their son, Stephen, to the Chamber.  I congratulate the Leader, Senator Doherty, and Senator Seery Kearney on the Bill they have proposed.  I look forward to supporting it.</p>  <p>Today, I remember a colleague, the former city councillor, John Mulholland, from Galway city.  He was mayor of Galway city twice, from 1986 to 1987 and from 1996 to 1997.  He was elected as a councillor for Fine Gael in 1985 and served until 2009, some 24 years.  He was a businessman, a bookmaker, best remembered on his pitch at Ballybrit and in the numerous shops he had in the west of Ireland in particular.  He was a gentleman and family man who was proud of Salthill and Galway city.  I offer my sincere condolences to his wife, Margaret, to his children, Alan, Lisa, Eddie and Aoife, and to his brothers, sisters, grandchildren, extended family and friends.  Ar dheis D&eacute; go raibh a anam d&iacute;lis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="11:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300010#N00300"><p>I thank Senator Kyne for remembering a man who gave a great deal of service to his city, his county and the racing industry and who was well known around the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="11:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300010#N00400"><p>I welcome the Bill being presented by Senators Doherty and Seery Kearney and the family of Stephen Smith, if I can put it in those terms.  It is a Bill that makes perfect sense.  It is an unfortunate stain that this has not been the situation up to now.  I know we would all welcome it.</p>  <p>I will raise the issue of non-consultant hospital doctors.  We have approximately 12,000 doctors working in hospitals, about 8,000 of whom are non-consultant doctors.  Up to 5,000 of these are in formal training contracts whereby they will spend about a quarter of their careers gleaning the skills and experience needed to operate as consultants, healing, looking after and curing us.  We know we have a retention problem.  It is difficult for health workers, whether doctors or other health workers, and retaining them is a major problem.  I was dismayed to see an advertisement from the state of Victoria in Dublin last night calling on nurses and other healthcare workers to go to Melbourne and place like that in Victoria to work.  We cannot afford to lose those people.</p>  <p>Non-consultant hospital doctors will spend a lot of their formal training period travelling around Ireland, going to hospitals in Dublin, Letterkenny, Castlebar and Cork.  People in the later stages of their careers may well have families, children and partners who may be uprooted as a result of these travels or who may not move with them, with these doctors ending up working away from home.  At the moment, if they do that, they are paying a second set of rents, utilities and other expenses that would have been consolidated into one if they were to be left at home.  The State and the HSE provide no assistance with these additional costs they are obliged to take on.  There is a proposal from the Irish Medical Organisation which makes perfect sense.  It is to simply make those extra expenses, including rent and utilities, tax-deductible for people who can prove they have left a family scenario.  Approximately 500 doctors are affected by this each year.  It would cost an average of &euro;6 million to the Exchequer but it would be a powerful step in recognising their roles and the need to retain them and would make it easier for them to do their training and their work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="11:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300010#N00500"><p>It is very nice to see Senator Gallagher in the Leader's chair today.  I certainly hope he is elevated to it one day very soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="11:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300010#N00600"><p>No chance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="11:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300010#N00700"><p>I unfortunately missed the speeches of Senators Doherty and Seery Kearney earlier but I will definitely support the Bill they spoke about.</p>  <p>I wish to raise the recent clusters of meningitis and septicaemia in Limerick, Dublin and Galway, which are very concerning.  We have had a number of deaths with cases appearing in young adults as opposed to children under the age of five, where these infections are usually found.  Those with knowledge of meningitis know just how vital it is to catch it in the early stages before the infection spreads into the body.  Dr. Kenneth Beatty is a public health specialist in the mid-west who says that we need to get the message out to people in their late teens, around when people start going to college, so that they know the early warning signs of meningitis and what to do when they see them.  Warnings similar to those we are now seeing from the HSE were given back in 2019 as a result of a similar cluster.  The articles published in our newspapers on this topic over the past week are extremely informative and I urge people to read them and to know the signs.  These include a sudden high fever, headaches, nausea, vomiting, confusion, difficulty concentrating, sensitivity to light or sleepiness.  All of these can point to meningitis, which can be fatal within days or sometimes within hours without prompt treatment with antibiotics.  With something this serious, I am not sure we can leave it up to individuals to go out of their way to seek information.  Is there any chance the HSE or the Department of Health could run an awareness campaign on this?  Could posters be placed in universities and secondary schools or could some social media advertisements be run?  Will the Minister for Health have a conversation with his Department or the HSE to this end?  Any small steps we can take to raise awareness of the issue of meningitis and its early warning signs and symptoms would be justified.  Could the Minister let us know what can be done in this area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" speakername="Paul Daly" time="11:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300010#N00800"><p>I too welcome the Smith family and compliment the Leader and Senator Seery Kearney.  As someone who has a little angel of a sister whom I never actually had the pleasure of meeting, I was very moved by Senator Seery Kearney's contribution.  Some 50 years later, I still try to live her life in my head and my imagination and to think about where she would be now and how things would have progressed.  I compliment all of those involved.</p>  <p>I will raise an issue far removed from that emotion.  As the Deputy Leader will be aware, I keep hammering the agricultural drum in here.  The big debate in agriculture at the moment relates to sustainable food production, food security and how we are going to help the climate while still producing more food, which is what we need to do if we are to keep pace with a rising population.  I read a small report on a recent survey regarding food waste carried out by Coyne Research on behalf of Aldi.  Approximately 800,000 tonnes of food is wasted across the world every year.  That is 25% of all food produced.</p> <p>That means the fertiliser, gas, fuel, work, labour and everything that goes into producing that food is also wasted and dumped, not to mention the major problem we then have of disposing of that food.  Some 47% of the people surveyed said they throw away edible food every week while 65% said they were uncomfortable about doing so but still do it.  Some 35% said they threw out food because it had reached or passed its best before date, which is a fallacy.  Food on or after its best before date is still quite edible and there is nothing wrong with it.  The best before date is a guide.</p> <p>We need a debate to start highlighting this issue.  I do not know which Minister the Acting Leader should ask to come to the Seanad.  Education may be the route we need to go down in order to start to solve this problem and to create awareness of it.  The Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine is rolled out every time, but I do not know if it can control consumers, which is where waste actually occurs.  I will leave it in the Acting Leader's capable hands but a debate in the Chamber would, if nothing else, start highlighting the importance of the issue, how much food could be saved and how big a help saving the 25% in food waste would be to the environment. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="11:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300011#O00200"><p>I welcome the Smith family.  I also welcome the proposed legislation on civil registration of stillbirths.  My wife is a midwife and I do not think a Christmas goes by where this issue is not discussed.  It is very important legislation on an issue that affects so many families on a daily basis.  It is very important that we progress this, if we possibly can.</p>  <p>The other issue I will raise is where our tourism industry is going.  In my part of the world, like the Cathaoirleach's, we are very dependent on tourism.  American tourists, in particular, are very important to the trade.  From Kinsale to Clonakilty and into Killarney, the need for American tourists is very much there.  The currency issue at present is actually very positive for us when it comes to American tourists.  In 2012, American tourists spent $1.30 for every euro, whereas today they are getting parity, which means we are a very good place for American tourists to visit.  We need a very good strategy over the next 18 months to capitalise on that.  The potential is there for places such as west Cork and County Kerry to get multiples of the people who are coming from America at present, if we just market it correctly.  From talking to the Americans I met last Saturday night in Kinsale, they said what great value Cork, and west Cork in particular, was because of the exchange rate.</p>  <p>We need to have a real, decent debate with the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media in this Chamber in the next few weeks about our strategies for the next few months so we can capitalise on that exchange rate.  There are issues regarding transportation and car rentals, which is a very important issue for counties Cork and Kerry.  We need to make sure those issues are solved for next year's season.  The potential and appetite are there.  We need the Minister to come to the Chamber to give us her long-range plan for the next 18 months so that areas such as west Cork can benefit from the potential that is there at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="11:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300011#O00300"><p>I concur with the comments of Senator McGreehan.  Our teaching of history is something I always have issues with.  We learn more about the Boer War and the First World War than we do about Irish history.  Unfortunately, the younger generation is learning about Irish history through social media rather than learning the facts.  This is something that needs to be looked at and should have been looked at before now, especially during our decade of centenaries.  We need to know and understand the facts of our history.</p><p>I will also raise the issue of affordable housing income thresholds.  As the Cathaoirleach well knows, I come from County Longford, which is not eligible for the affordable housing scheme.  It is one of the very few counties in the country in that position.  Yet, when we look for an increase in the income thresholds for social housing, we are not eligible for that either.  A number of other counties recently had their thresholds increased by &euro;5,000 up to &euro;30,000 for a single person and <i>pro rata</i>for a married couple.  We have a significant number of families who are locked in a position where they are not eligible for social housing and are in areas that do not have an affordable housing scheme.  In addition, no private houses are being built in the county at all because no developer is able to get the finance, or the market is not there as we do not have an affordable element in developments.  We are almost being discriminated against as a county with regard to our housing.  As I said, a large number of families and young couples are looking to get into the market.</p><p>A review needs to be done.  We cannot have a situation where someone is eligible in one county but is not in another.  That happens to be the case in my constituency of Longford-Westmeath, where there are affordable housing schemes in Westmeath but not Longford.  It all depends on what side of the border someone is on.  That needs to be reviewed.  Everybody in the country should be eligible for any scheme we introduce.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" speakername="Vincent P Martin" time="11:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300011#O00400"><p>Last weekend, Naas and Kill saw the inaugural F&eacute;ile Liam O'Flynn, a festival on a national stage that will become an annual festival to celebrate the life, times and contribution of famous and renowned Kildare uilleann piper Liam O'Flynn.  It also celebrated the contribution of so many Kildare people to music.  There were workshops, scholarships and sessions, and thousands flocked to Naas.  There were full houses and exceptional goodwill and atmosphere, supported by the spouse of the late Liam O'Flynn, Jane O'Flynn.  We were so lucky to have her there.  I was privileged to chair the festival's founding committee.  My lasting memory is of the dedicated efforts of volunteers.  Everyone on that committee was not just exceptionally dedicated but was so professional and patriotic in their endeavours.  The culmination of the weekend's festivities was the awarding of the inaugural F&eacute;ile Liam O'Flynn perpetual trophy to well-known Kildare man, D&oacute;nal Lunny, in order to recognise his contribution to music.  The aim of the whole festival was to celebrate traditional Irish and folk music and how it is the heartbeat of our nation.  To see people flock to Naas from the four corners of Ireland and abroad did the heart good and emboldened us.  This festival is definitely here to stay.  Last weekend in Naas and Kill was a wonderful experience.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="11:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300011#O00500"><p>I welcome the Smith family.  I am sure it is a poignant day for them.  I also compliment the Leader and Senator Seery Kearney on co-sponsoring this Bill.</p>  <p>I agree with the comments of Senator Keogan on meningitis.  There have some very sad and tragic deaths of young people because of meningitis throughout the country in recent weeks.  I also agree with Senator Daly on food wastage.  It is noteworthy to see coverage in the newspapers about the growing number of people in the world who are facing starvation because of an alleged lack of food yet, as Senator Daly pointed out, we are dumping so much food in this world that it is appalling.</p>  <p>It is nice to see Senator Gallagher in the Acting Leader's chair.  I am not a member of the Oireachtas Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, but peat industry representatives appeared before it yesterday.  I know this issue is very close to the Acting Leader's heart.  I appeal to the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications and its officials not to allow the horticultural industry in this country to completely collapse because of the lack of peat.  None of us want to destroy our bogs completely but the reality is the mushroom industry and much of the horticultural industry needs to survive.  They are now at the point of non-survival in this particular business.  That is the reality, as the Acting Leader knows.  I compliment the Chair of the joint committee, Deputy Cahill, who has done everything in his power, along with Senator Daly, who is also on the committee, to try to get people to see sense and give some extra time to allow peat to be extracted for necessary works and to keep jobs in place.  We have to keep jobs in place.  I would be very thankful if the Acting Leader would give that message to the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications and his officials.  I plead with them one last time to do what is necessary in the short term to save the horticultural industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="11:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300011#O00600"><p>It is good to see Senator Gallagher in the hot seat today.  I promise I will go easy on him.</p> <p>I begin by apologising to Senators Doherty and Seery Kearney for missing their contributions this morning.  Having heard the contributions of other colleagues, I look forward to engaging with them on their Bill.</p> <p>Earlier this week, when we debated Second Stage of the Consumer Rights Bill 2022, I indicated to the Minister of State, Deputy Calleary, that I would table a number of amendments on Committee Stage of the Bill essentially seeking to make product labels bilingual.  As Senators will know, in places such as Canada, Belgium and the Basque country the packaging on toothpaste, paracetamol tablets, chocolate bars and so on is bilingual and sometimes multilingual.  The same applies to signs in shops, whether they are indicating where the toothpaste aisle is, where the bakery is or whatever it might be.  Likewise, with ATMs throughout Europe in particular.</p> <p>Given the constitutional role of the Irish language as the first language of the State and given that my proposal is a positive step forward, I ask colleagues across the House to reflect on my amendments and hopefully support them.  It is a great way to platform and visualise the language across society.  It is a great opportunity for learners to engage with the language and to see it out there.  My proposal would be a welcome step forward and is worthy of support.  I am giving a signal of intent for Committee Stage of the Consumer Rights Bill, which will take place next week.  Irish language speakers and those in Gaeltacht communities are consumers too.  They consume products and this Bill is about consumer rights.  In the context of trying to promote the language and knowing all of the benefits that a multilingual society brings, we should see that step taken in this State.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="12:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300012#P00300"><p>I thank all Senators who contributed.  We started with Senator Doherty, who spoke about her Bill.  I welcome the Smith family to the House this afternoon and thank them for their work in this area.  I commend Senator Doherty on the work she has done on this very worthwhile Bill and thank Senator Mary Seery Kearney for her input.  I am sure the entire House, as many Members have already stated, will fully support it.</p>  <p>Senator Dooley raised the controversy surrounding Irish dancing and referred to the importance of people having faith in the process.  People are seeking transparency, which is vital.  He requested that the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, come to the House to debate this issue.  I will see what I can do in that regard.</p>  <p>The Senator also raised the hospitality sector.  As we know, the VAT rate for the industry is due to an increase early next year.  This is a matter of great concern, particularly for people in hospitality outside of the capital.  The Senator mentioned price gouging and unfortunately that has occurred.  However, many businesses throughout the country were not involved in that and now have grave concerns about the future of their business as a result.  I understand the Government is looking at some imaginative ideas on how that blow could be lessened.  We will see how that develops.  </p>  <p>Senator Craughwell thanked Senators Doherty and Seery Kearney for introducing their Bill.  He raised the security of the underground cables in our seas and asked that the Minister for Defence come to the House.  As many other speakers alluded to, the Minister is a regular visitor to the House and has been very forthcoming with his time.  I am sure all Members are grateful for that.  In relation to the specific issue the Senator raised, I understand the Taoiseach has had negotiations with the Estonian Prime Minister on this issue and progress is being made.  It is, as the Senator said, a vital issue and it is important that all citizens have confidence in the security of our data.  We will see what Senators have to say on that. </p>  <p>Senator Wall spoke about the widow&rsquo;s and widower's pension and contributions, which are very worthwhile.  I speak as someone whose mother has been a widow for the best part of 40 years, so I can understand the challenges there.  Senator Wall would like the Minister to take that on board and we will pass on that message to the Minister.  The Senator also spoke about rural transport and Local Link and welcomed the progress made in that area in County Kildare.  We all welcome that.  Local Link has been a huge success and if there is potential to expand it further, we look forward to that happening.</p>  <p>I thank Senator Mary Seery Kearney for sharing her personal journey with us.  I am sure it has been very traumatic and I have no doubt the Smith family know all about that.  I am sure I speak for all Senators in saying I would like this worthwhile Bill to pass both Houses as a matter of interest.</p>  <p>Senator Boyhan and a number of other Senators, including Senators Paul Daly and Eugene Murphy, mentioned peat.  This is an issue close to my heart and I know Senator Doherty has championed it as well.  We have worked together on legislation to try to solve this problem.  It is frustrating that we have still not found a common-sense solution to this problem.  It has reached a critical stage.  The issue straddles a number of Departments but somebody needs to take a lead on it because jobs are at risk.  Coming from County Monaghan, the home of the mushroom industry, I am well aware of the importance of turf and I will contact the Minister on the matter. </p>  <p>Senator Buttimer spoke about the delay in issuing the junior certificate results.  I will bring the matter to the attention of the Minister.  The Senator called on the Minister for Education to come to the House to debate a wide range of issues related to education.  We can arrange that.</p>  <p>Senator McGreehan welcomed the Smith family and complimented Senators Doherty and Seery Kearney on the Bill they have tabled.  She spoke about the Irish soccer team and the issue with some of the chants in the dressing room in the aftermath of their famous win this week.  I congratulate the entire team on their fantastic achievement.  Not long ago, these women were sharing tracksuits and changing in airports.  They have come a long way and we are extremely proud of them.  I come from Donegal and I listened to Amber Barrett being interviewed after the game in the wake of the events of the week that has just passed.  She spoke about where her family is from and their connections with Creeslough.  It was truly inspiring.  It is disappointing that this particular incident has clouded the airwaves, if I can put it that way.  Senator McGreehan called for education in relation to all these matters.  It is vitally important that we all have a full grasp of our history.  That is something we can look into.  I thank the Irish soccer team, the FAI, Vera Pauw and the entire squad for the lift they have given this country last week and, God knows, we badly needed it.  </p>  <p>Senator Kyne spoke about former councillor John Mulholland from Galway and his legacy, not just as a member of a local authority but also as someone involved in the racing industry and a businessman.  Our deepest sympathies go to his wife and family.  </p>  <p>Senator Ward complimented Senators Doherty and Seery Kearney on tabling their Bill.  He spoke about the role played by non-consultant hospital doctors and how, unfortunately, we struggle to hold on to these excellent people, not only doctors but also nurses.  He referred to the attraction of moving to Australia and the pay and conditions attached to that.  Unfortunately, many of our good people are leaving.  The Senator raised a valid point about non-consultant hospital doctors being transferred from one end of the country to the other and having to keep two houses and pay two rents.  He asked that the expenses associated be made tax deductible.  That is a fair and reasonable argument and we can raise the matter with the Minister.</p> <p> Senator Keogan also supported the Bill.  She spoke about meningitis, septicaemia and the need for more of a public awareness campaign on that, especially for our young people, including teenagers.  That is very worthwhile.  It can be a cruel disease with fatal consequences so if there is more public awareness then that is to be welcomed.  I will bring the Senator's proposals to the Minister for Health to try to get a public awareness campaign moving.</p> <p>Senator Paul Daly talked about food waste and said that 25% of the food we produce is dumped.  That is a waste in every regard.  Thousands of people in the country are starving and it is a crazy situation.  It is something we should have a debate on and I will try to arrange that debate.</p> <p>Senator Lombard talked about tourism and American tourists and his point was well made.  American tourists coming to Ireland are getting exceptional value with the currency being as it is.  That is something we should cash in on so it is worthwhile and timely that we would have a debate on that and on how we can redouble our efforts to take advantage of the marketplace as it is presenting itself.  That is something I will bring to the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media, Deputy Catherine Martin, with a view to having a debate on it.</p> <p>Senator Carrigy mentioned history, how it is taught in our schools and its importance, with which we all agree.  He talked about affordable housing and how in places like Longford, the thresholds are such that a lot of people are not eligible for affordable housing and there are many counties in a similar situation.  The Government and the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, have introduced the serviced sites fund whereby local authorities can put forward serviced sites for first-time buyers and young people.  Housing is an important issue and the Government has to do all it possibly can in order that our young people will have houses whenever they require them.</p> <p>Senator Martin talked about the f&eacute;ile in Kildare last week.  I compliment him on being chair of that committee and it is great to see the huge success of that event.  I am sure that was down in no small measure to the Senator&rsquo;s energy.  I have known him for a long time since he was a member of Monaghan County Council and I know that when he puts his mind to doing something he does it to the best of his ability.  It is great to see that so many visitors came to Kildare and I have no doubt that will be an annual event going forward.  We look forward to it progressing down through the years.</p> <p>Senator Murphy also mentioned peat and he would have expertise on the horticultural sector.  It is vitally important that we find a solution to that issue.  He mentioned Deputy Cahill and Senator Paul Daly's work on the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine and their efforts in trying to highlight this issue.  It is disappointing that they have gone so far and not found a solution.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile talked about the Consumer Rights Bill that is before us.  He talked about the bilingual aspect to that Bill and about trying to promote the Irish language.  He is bringing forward amendments in that regard and he is asking us all to reflect on that.  It is important that we protect and promote the growth of our national language.  I thank the Senator for bringing that up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q00200"><p>Members were referring to the Acting Leader as a Minister because of the seat he is in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q00300"><p>We will see.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q00400"><p>Senator Doherty has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That No. 16 be taken before No. 1."  Senator Seery Kearney has seconded the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.84" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q00600"><p>Senator Craughwell has moved an amendment to the Order of Business: "That a debate with the Minister for Defence on the operational capacity of the Defence Forces be taken today."  I regret that I have to rule that amendment out of order as it involves a repeat of the statement of the high level action plan for the Report of the Commission on the Defence Forces which was taken on 4 October.  In any event the amendment was not seconded and therefore lapses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.86" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.87" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q00800">Civil Registration (Amendment) (Certificate of Life) Bill 2022: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q00900"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to amend the Civil Registration Act 2004 to establish a non-statutory register called the Certificate of Life to recognise a child that does not conform to World Health Organisation stillbirth standards of less than 500 grammes and a gestational age of less than 24 weeks. </blockquote>  <p>I thank colleagues for their initial levels of support.  In the coming weeks we will convene in the audiovisual room with the Smiths and families like them so that everybody has an opportunity to hear first-hand about the emotional heartbreak that this lack of recognition has caused.  I look forward to the continued support of Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.89" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q01100"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q01200"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q01300"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.93" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 18 October 2022.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.94" nospeaker="true" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q01500">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:10:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300013#Q01600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  Before we begin the official proceedings I welcome to the Gallery, Brendan Teahan, Lynda and all the family, including the in-laws.  They are most welcome.  Brendan had to suffer through my first campaign in 2007, which involved us driving 26,000 miles.  The Minister of State will have to close his ears for this.  To give the scale of that it is equivalent to driving around the world once and another 2,000 miles with it.  Not only did he have to do all of that but he also had to listen to me for the entire campaign, which was a tough thing to do.  We were on the road for 56 days without coming back to Kerry, which of itself was a political safari.  I thank Brendan for doing that.  He promised never to do it again and he was dead right.  That is why he will remain married.  One should not go on political campaigns like that.</p> <p align="center"><b><font color="#000080">Visit of Western Saharan Delegation</font></b></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300014#R00200"><p>I welcome to the Gallery the Western Saharan Prime Minister and his delegation who are here on a very important diplomatic mission.  They will later meet the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Defence.  I thank them for coming to Seanad &Eacute;ireann as part of their visit in terms of making representations on behalf of their country and people.  We welcome them to the Seanad today.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.98" nospeaker="true" time="12:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300014#R00300">Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures and Miscellaneous Provisions Bill 2022: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.99" nospeaker="true" time="12:20:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="12:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300014#R00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and I thank him for taking this debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="12:20:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300014#R00600"><p>I welcome our guests in the Gallery and they are all very welcome.  I would never judge anyone for their mileage because I live in a county that is only 10 km by 10 km, so I understand that some have a greater challenge than me.</p>  <p>Having regard to the continued rise in electricity prices, I am pleased to commend the Electricity Costs (Domestic Electricity Accounts) Emergency Measures and Miscellaneous Provisions Bill 2022 to the House.  I shall open this debate by setting the broader context for the action to be taken on foot of this legislation, which will establish an electricity costs emergency benefit scheme II under which a total of &euro;550 will be paid to each of 2.2 million domestic electricity accounts in three payments between November of this year and April of next year at an estimated cost to the Exchequer of &euro;1.2 billion.</p>  <p>Everyone in this House will be only too well aware of the impacts we are seeing from the continued and unprecedented rises in the cost of energy driven in a very large part by the volatility in international gas markets caused by the Russian invasion of Ukraine.  The steep increases in gas prices brought about by the invasion are also leading to windfall gains for some energy companies across Europe, especially those companies involved in the production of fossil fuels and those who produce energy at a much lower cost than the cost of gas.</p>  <p>On 30 September, the Council of Energy Ministers agreed the EU Council regulation on an emergency intervention to address high energy prices and windfall gains.  The headline measures agreed include a voluntary overall reduction target of 10% of gross electricity consumption and a mandatory reduction target of 5% of the electricity consumption during peak hours; a temporary solidarity contribution based on taxable profits for fossil fuel production and oil refining; and a cap on market revenues of for specific technologies in the electricity sector which have not seen significant increases in costs, so that includes wind and solar.  This is known as the windfall tax.  Estimates of the potential revenues that may be realised from a solidarity payment and from a windfall tax are currently being prepared by the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications.  Estimates will depend on policy choices related to the flexibilities that are set out in the regulation and will depend on the wholesale gas price over the coming months.  The cap on market revenues must be implemented by the start of December and the solidarity contribution must be implemented by the end of December.</p>  <p>The Government is keenly aware of the impact of this volatility on consumers as a household electricity bill has now increased from an estimated annual average of &euro;1,006 in January 2021 to &euro;2,020 in October 2022.  In the face of an impact on this scale, the big advantage of this scheme is that it uses the meter point registration number or MPRN to identify accounts and ensure payments are made directly and automatically to those accounts without the need for means testing, application or approval.  This meant that, under the first scheme, payments could be made directly to 2,138,939 domestic electricity accounts or over 99.36% of all eligible accounts, including pay as you go.</p>  <p>It is important to be clear that this scheme is just one part of a much wider package that includes targeted measures.  Particularly important in this context is the &euro;400 lump sum for recipients of the fuel allowance.  This is in addition to the &euro;924 people entitled to the allowance receive over the winter and goes along with the broadening of the threshold for this benefit.</p>  <p>I will now outline the Bill's subject matter and how the scheme will operate.  The Bill provides for the establishment of a scheme for the purpose of making the electricity cost emergency benefit payments of &euro;183.49 to domestic electricity accounts to be paid in each of the November-December 2022, January-February 2023 and March-April 2023 billing cycles.  The moneys for the scheme will be allocated by the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas.  The amount will not exceed &euro;1.211 billion.  This figure makes provision for 2.2 million domestic electricity accounts.  The Commission for the Regulation of Utilities, CRU, will provide oversight of the scheme.  It will put in place administrative and operational arrangements to ensure ESB Networks - ESBN - and suppliers perform their functions under the scheme.  It will be operated by the distribution system operator, ESB Networks and electricity suppliers.</p>  <p>The Minister, Deputy Ryan, will provide, under regulations, for a date, to be known as the relevant date, on which the distribution system operator will calculate the total number of domestic electricity accounts in the State, based on MPRNs.  ESBN will notify the Minister of this number, which will allow the estimation and necessary allocation of moneys for the scheme.  On the effective dates for each payment period, which will also be set out in regulations, ESBN will notify each electricity supplier of the assigned MPRN for each domestic electricity account they supply and the amount of money they will transfer to them for the purposes of the scheme.  The Minister will set out in regulations the payment periods within which ESBN will transfer the funds to suppliers for the sole purpose of making payments under the scheme.  Following receipt of these funds, suppliers will then, within the payment periods set out in this Act, credit each domestic electricity account held with it on the effective date with a payment of &euro;183.49.  Suppliers and ESBN are required to repay any moneys received by them which have not been used for the purposes of the scheme.</p>  <p>I will provide a section-by-section summary of the Bill, which has 13 sections.  Section 1 is a standard provision which provides for definitions, while section 2 provides for the establishment of the scheme.  It provides for the allocation of the moneys for the scheme, up to &euro;1.211 billion, by the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p>  <p>Section 3 provides the basis for the transfer by the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, to the distribution system operator of the moneys for the operation of the scheme.  This will be paid to domestic accounts in three payments of &euro;183.49, excluding VAT.</p>  <p>Sections 4 and 5 provide for the functions of the distribution system operator and suppliers, respectively, for the purposes of the operation of the scheme.  Section 6 provides for the amendment of section 9 of the Electricity Regulation Act to create the oversight functions for the CRU.</p>  <p>Section 7 deals with an amendment to the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997.  This amendment is to exempt the electricity costs emergency benefit payment from income tax.</p>  <p>Section 8 provides for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to make regulations, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, for the purposes of the Act.  Section 9 provides that the distribution system operator and electricity suppliers shall bear their own expenses.</p>  <p>Section 10 provides for a drafting amendment to section 34 of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999 to include specific reference to the relevant market participants registration framework established under Part IIIA of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999, in the context of terms for connection to and use of transmission or distribution systems, to make it clear that relevant market participants can enter into </p>  <p>Section 11 provides for the amendment of section 35 of the Electricity (Supply) Act 1927 to include specific reference to the relevant market participants registration framework established under Part IIIA of the Electricity Regulation Act 1999, to make it clear that relevant market participants can sell electricity or supply electricity for sale.</p>  <p>Section 12 amends the National Oil Reserves Agency Act 2007 to provide for a reduction in the petroleum product levy, which is more commonly known as the NORA levy.  The NORA levy is a charge of 2 cent per litre applied to most petroleum products sold in the market for the purpose of funding the operations of the National Oil Reserves Agency and the climate action fund.  The levy will now be reduced to a nominal amount.  The reduction will come into effect from 12 October to offset the carbon tax increase on petrol and diesel road fuels which will apply from that date.  It will remain in place until the end of February 2023.  It should be noted that NORA has a significant financial reserve and that this temporary levy reduction will not impact on its ability to carry out its functions in the event of the occurrence of an oil emergency.</p>  <p>Section 13 contains standard provisions concerning the Short Title and commencement of the Act.</p>  <p>I have outlined the main provisions of this emergency measures Bill.</p> <p>I have also provided detail on each section, which I hope will be of assistance to Senators.  I look forward to an informed and meaningful debate and to working constructively with Senators on all sides of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300015#S00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and look forward to the swift passage of the Bill.  It is important legislation that attempts, in so far as possible, to address the crisis many families and individuals will face over the coming months.  We all are aware of the spiralling cost of gas, the impact it is having on the electricity market and how that permeates down to each individual household.  To some extent, the potential crisis is masked at the moment by the reasonably good weather we have had.  Therefore, many homes have not had to increase the heat in their homes, as they often would at this time of year.</p>  <p>This Bill is a pre-emptive strike by the Government and is particularly welcome.  It builds on the previous scheme, recognising there were some gaps in the system.  Having read the Minister of State's speech and some of the background notes, I see an effort is being made to address the situation of Traveller families who had difficulties accessing the previous scheme because of the way in which their meters were appointed and funded through local authorities, albeit that they ended up paying the charges anyway.  We must address that.  I understand also, as the Minister of State might confirm in his concluding remarks, that there is an effort to assist the small number of individuals who are in rental accommodation and operating off a bulk meter through a landlord.  While I understand an effort is to be made to ensure they get the compensation, I hope it is not just a case of the &euro;200 being spread among up to ten, 15 or 20 people.  It should not just be an allocation of &euro;200 per meter but an allocation based on the number of individuals using that meter.  The quantum of money must be linked to the number of units rather than just to the meter.  I ask the Minister of State to consider that.</p>  <p>There was a haste by some to comment on the approach of the Government in attempting to resolve the difficulties people are suffering.  The notion of a blanket cap on the cost of energy from the different suppliers has been bandied around by some to give the impression the Government is not targeting energy producers.  The reality is that such a measure has to be done at European level.  I see from some within both the media and politics a sort of lazy approach in suggesting a cap can be put on what energy companies may charge.  Of course, nothing could be further from the truth.  Many people have been led to believe prices can somehow be capped and the energy companies will carry the can.  The reality is very different.  What would ultimately happen, as is happening in the UK, is the Government would have to plug the gap between the cost to the companies and the price at which they might be forced to sell.  This would give no incentive whatsoever to the people who are making an effort to reduce their energy consumption and would have a negative effect in that regard.</p>  <p>Contrary to what some have put forward, those with a very large energy usage, including those who are particularly well off and use vast amounts of electricity, would benefit most.  That is the reality.  I was in the company of Michael O'Leary when he said he does not need the &euro;600, which I am sure he does not.  If we were to cap the price at which electricity is charged and the Government were to subvent the energy companies, it is people like Michael O'Leary - I do not mean to single him out in particular; I am referring generally to individuals who use large amounts of electricity - who would benefit the most.  The Government's measure is a progressive approach to assisting those most in need and is to be welcomed.</p>  <p>I listened with interest around the time of the budget to the arguments from Government members that the measures now in place are very much to address what can be perceived as the potential increase in costs, but there is no certainty in this regard.  There are fluctuations in the price of oil and gas on a daily basis.  From the time one gets up in the morning until one goes to bed, prices increase significantly.  The Government indicated, and I hope it follows through on it, that moneys will be kept in reserve to enable it to intervene again should the market require it.  That is important.  I heard some politicians on budget day being critical of the Government for not being able to give certainty around the cost of energy.  We are in a war situation, with the prices fluctuating on the market on a daily basis.  Of course no certainty can be given as to where international prices will be in the next few hours, let alone over the coming months.  The most important aspect that needs to be highlighted is the commitment by the Government, in so far as it can give such a commitment on behalf of the taxpayer, to retain some moneys that can be provided early next year if that is necessary.  The Minister of State might comment on this in his concluding remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300015#S00300"><p>The Minister of State is welcome.  I am glad the Bill, which I welcome, is before the House.  It allows for money to be put back into households around the country and it will be received gladly.  This is a technical Bill to establish the new electricity credit scheme.  The big question in the minds of many leading up to the Bill and when the scheme was announced in the budget is whether households that are on pay-as-you-go arrangements with their energy supplier will be included in the scheme and benefit from it.  It was a relief to hear the Minister of State laying out last Tuesday that the scheme will include customers with pay-as-you-go meters and will help them, alongside bill-pay customers, with their electricity costs.</p>  <p>I understand the Commission for Regulation of Utilities, CRU, has been in communication with the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications on the difficulty in paying any additional credits to pay-as-you-go customers due to the inability of the metering system to provide the data to identify those people.  Will the Minister of State advise the House as to whether that issue has been resolved and, if so, by what mechanism will pay-as-you-go energy consumers receive moneys under the scheme?  We cannot have a situation whereby households utilising those meters have to go begging for their credits.  It cannot be that the onus is on them to ask for credits when the meter is running out.</p>  <p>There were calls on Tuesday in the Lower House for the fees for switching from pay-as-you-go arrangements to bill pay to be eliminated for everybody.  The Minister of State stated: "It is free for people to change from what are sometimes known as hardship meters to a bill-pay option."  We must ensure this is the case for all energy providers.  I urge all 350,000 householders who are currently using a pay-as-you-go meter to switch to bill pay for the next few months, providing it is free to do so, if it would serve to streamline the receipt of the energy credits provided under the scheme.  That wold be worthwhile.  These are the most vulnerable energy customers.  They have already paid &euro;100 to get the meter in and they pay a higher rate than bill-pay customers.  The latter pay 43.27 cent per kilowatt, while the former pay 46.23 cent.  Pay-as-you-go customers are being hit all the time and it is absolutely crucial to get the credits to them.</p>  <p>I welcome and support the Bill.  However, it is not as if we did not see this issue coming down the line.  I would like to hear the Government's plan for energy supply in the medium term.  What are we to do before the Minister's army of wind turbines is standing tall?  The curtailment of fossil fuel energy production in order to reach climate objectives prior to the establishment of a viable sustainable alternative is a policy of utter foolishness.  As always, it is the people who pay the price.  We must be realistic about the timeline for developing our green energy infrastructure.  We cannot stand by and watch people suffering in the meantime.  I would very much appreciate the Minister of State's thoughts on this.</p>  <p>On the comments that have been made regarding the war, our country is neutral and we have always been known as peacemakers.  I urge those in power in the State, whether it be the Taoiseach or the Minister for Defence, to try to get people around the table to stop this war.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="12:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300015#S00400"><p>Before calling the next speaker, I welcome our visitors from Skibbereen Community School to the Seanad.  I congratulate them on their sustainability project and wish them the very best of luck in their work.  They are joined by Deputies Michael Collins and Christopher O'Sullivan, who are also very welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="12:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300016#T00100"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it.  A Bill very similar to this one was debated in February.  At the time, Sinn F&eacute;in tabled amendments removing the references to it being a once-off measure.  We knew, as did every expert and the dogs in the street, that this crisis was not going away and certainly was not going to be fixed by a one-off payment.  Here we are with more legislation being rushed through the Houses.  Once again, the approach of the Opposition has been vindicated.  Maybe this time the Minister of State will listen to the Opposition and adopt our amendments.</p>  <p>There are several problems with the design of the electricity rebate.  People with holiday homes lying idle for most of the year will now get even more money to help keep the lights on.  The most recent census identified 61,204 holiday homes in the State.  It is outrageous these vacant holiday homes have still not been excluded from this scheme.  On top of the previous &euro;200, they will now get another &euro;600.  That is a total of almost &euro;50 million of taxpayers' money to keep the lights on in the second homes of predominantly well-off individuals.  There are a further 166,752 vacant homes receiving &euro;600.  That is a further &euro;100 million going where it is not exactly needed.  It is shameful the Government has not found a way to exclude these homes in the eight months since the scheme was first legislated for.  The Government likes to claim this is an emergency and there is no time to tailor the measures.  That might have flown the last time but it cannot be trotted out this time around.</p>  <p>The Government likes to say there is a certain fairness in treating each home the same by giving each electricity meter &euro;600.  That is not really true when homes are not evenly distributed through society.  A millionaire with five homes is getting five times the help compared with an ordinary working-class family struggling to make ends meet in a rented apartment.  How can the Government try to tell us that is fair or universal?  We have a number of amendments seeking to exclude vacant homes and holiday homes.  We have chosen a method put forward by the Central Statistics Office, CSO.  The CSO&rsquo;s analysis of metered electricity consumption found that electricity consumption can be used as an indirect indicator of vacant and holiday dwellings.  Houses that use very little are likely to be empty.  This measure would exclude 130,266 ESB meters from receiving the rebate.  That would mean &euro;69 million euro could be saved by the Exchequer.  The Government has continually dismissed amendments aimed at targeting this measure to those who need it on the grounds that it would slow down the roll-out.  Nothing in this amendment delays the proposed timeline.  This could simply and quickly be applied by ESB Networks and suppliers.</p>  <p>There were issues with Travellers on halting sites being excluded from the original payment.  We are led to believe that approximately 1,000 Traveller households in local authority accommodation were excluded from the original payment.  Will the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications work with the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to devise a way to reach these homes with future supports?  It is simply not good enough, eight months after the original scheme, for the Government to say it is looking into it.  What does that tell Traveller families about the priorities of this Government?  Some of these households are living in extreme energy poverty already and need immediate assistance.  "We are working on it" is not going to cut it.  The Minister needs to give a commitment that these families will receive the full &euro;600 this winter on top of the &euro;200 they did not get originally.</p>  <p>Pay-as-you-go customers are another category of households that are let down by this Bill.  There are 346,000 households using prepay meters in this State.  They face higher tariffs, higher standing charges, and people on low incomes are offered no protection against cut-offs.  The Minister, Deputy Ryan, had the brass neck to go on "Morning Ireland" today and laud these meters&rsquo; so-called efficiency.  That efficiency comes from people self-disconnecting and not feeding the meter.  The "efficiency" is them going without light and heat.</p>  <p>Sinn F&eacute;in has made its position clear.  We believe an electricity price cap is needed this winter to give households certainty.  We need to reduce electricity prices back to pre-crisis levels and cap them.  Regarding what Senator Dooley said, price caps have been introduced right across Europe but this Government has chosen a different path of giving three energy credits this winter.  Although we disagree with this approach, we will support the Bill because the &euro;550 in electricity credits will still help offset some costs for people this winter.  We will support this Bill but hold firm to the position that reducing electricity prices to pre-crisis levels and capping them at that cost this winter is a far better solution and would give households much greater certainty.  Let us do that instead.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="12:40:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300016#T00200"><p>As we all know, more than 900,000 households are facing into fuel poverty this winter.  Fuel poverty has been a permanent feature of this country through good times and now through bad.  The choices facing this State, particularly when the public finances are in such a remarkably healthy situation, raise very serious questions about the extent to which the State is willing to go the extra mile to help those households in fuel poverty.  It is not even that they have a minor difficulty in paying their bills; this is actual poverty.  We very much believe the State has been found wanting in that regard.  People will of course welcome the three instalments of &euro;183, but when that is set against the &euro;2,000 increase in average energy bills over the past 18 months and the projection that that will further increase by &euro;1,200, that support is really in the ha'penny place.</p>  <p>I have heard the Minister of State talk about the increase in the fuel allowance threshold.  That is all very welcome but there are thousands of households in this country that should be entitled to the fuel allowance but are not because of their circumstances.  Perhaps there is somebody else in the home, or they are marginally over the increased threshold, or they are not in receipt of the social welfare payment that would make them eligible.</p>  <p>While we will support this Bill, we believe serious changes need to be introduced to it.  I refer in particular to situations where tenants are in rented accommodation where the landlord pays the utility bill.  We need to ensure it is the tenants who benefit, that they do not lose out and can share in that payment from the State towards those who are paying the utility bill.  The landlord is effectively just passing on that utility bill to the tenants, but if they are the person with the MPRN, then they will only pocket the payment.  The second issue is that not all renters are covered by this Bill.  Licences are the main form of tenant agreement in co-living spaces or for short-term leases.  We need all renters to be included in this Bill.</p>  <p>The other key issue, which has been referred to, is the outrageous fact that some households may benefit on the double from this payment.  This needs to be targeted at households that actually need the payment.  Those with holiday homes or other homes that happen to have a live MPRN should not be benefiting.  There has been insufficient effort on the part of the Government to try to control that.</p>  <p>While we need to get people through this winter, and I accept we will have to have once-off measures, my main interest is the permanent fix.  The Government has acknowledged that &euro;28 billion needs to be spent this decade to retrofit 500,000 homes to a B2 standard.  Yet the Government is only stumping up &euro;8 billion of that.  The budget only provided for an additional 10,000 houses to be retrofitted next year on top of what was retrofitted this year.  The ambition to get to that 500,000 target is far off track.  The money being put into retrofitting is far from sufficient and the waiting times at the moment are simply disgraceful.  It is taking 26 months to access retrofitting under the better energy, warmer homes scheme.  We are talking today about the once-off measures to get people through the winter, but we also need to hear from the Minister of State about the permanent fix.  We know from many of the energy experts, and we can see it ourselves in the energy sector, that prices are not going to retreat to where they were at the start of this year or last year.  They are going to remain at elevated levels.</p> <p>That will have a significant impact on households, particularly considering the difference between heating a two- or three-bedroom apartment with a building energy rating of F or G and a similar unit with a rating of B2.  The difference can be up to &euro;3,500 per year.  My figures are from before the energy crisis.  They are obviously a lot worse now and may get worse again in the future.  Therefore, we need to hear from the Government about the permanent fix.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1674" speakername="Eugene Murphy" time="12:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300017#U00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State back to the House.  I support this Bill, as do all Members, despite the criticism, as far as I can understand.  That is good because we need to move forward on this.  I welcome the energy credits and accept everything is not perfect, but if one were to go down the road of separating customers with holiday homes from others, the credit would, according to the experts and others, be a long time coming to those who desperately need it.</p>  <p>Although everybody said the credit was not enough, nobody referred to the benefits of the fuel allowance.  For example, it has now been announced that there will be a &euro;400 top-up to the fuel allowance on 14 November, on top of the approximately &euro;500 already being paid.  The income threshold for the fuel allowance will increase by &euro;80 from &euro;120 to &euro;200 in January 2023.  For people aged over 70, the threshold will increase in January 2023 to &euro;500 for a single person and &euro;1,000 for a couple.  The disablement benefit and half-rate carer's allowance will be disregarded in the means test for the fuel allowance in January 2023.  It is only fair, if one gives one side of the argument, to give the other side too.  A genuine effort is being made by the Government to acknowledge and support people who would be in difficulty without its support.  There will be six, seven or maybe eight different payments to people in the coming weeks to help them.  That is only right.  It is only right that the Government use the taxpayers' money it has collected to help people with their heating bills throughout the winter.</p>  <p>I do not agree at all with the capping of the energy prices because we are in a no-man's-land.  The UK is going to be in real trouble over this.  It has cost it &pound;120 billion already.  What will happen come January or February if it experiences the same kind of crisis?  It will be a disaster for it.  We will be moving to collect the windfall tax, which I hope will be redistributed, if necessary, to the domestic and business customers who need an allowance because of rising energy prices.</p>  <p>I accept this is a most difficult situation for many people, but, in all fairness, one has to agree that the Government has moved on it.  When I speak to members of the general public, they clearly say the Government is making an effort.</p>  <p>Let me refer to a vital point about spending all the money on the announcement of the budget.  I believe Senator Dooley referred to it.  There is &euro;6 billion, and the Government has made it quite clear that if it is necessary in the new year to support people with electricity bills, it will be available.  The Minister of State might confirm this.  I am confident that the Government is on top of this and making the right moves to bring this country through a very difficult period.  It is not just a crisis in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1662" speakername="Alice-Mary Higgins" time="12:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300017#U00300"><p>I will be brief because I have several amendments that will give me an opportunity to discuss the specific issues.</p>  <p>As said by others, it is right to recognise that many households are facing an emergency regarding energy costs but I believe more could and should be done to ensure that while we address the energy crisis, we also address the associated crisis, namely the climate crisis, and the transition we need.  We do not have the luxury of a single crisis but need to move forward in ways that act on both.</p>  <p>While supplementing bills may go some way towards assisting as an interim measure, the real problem concerns the bills, the extent of their escalation and the fact that we see profiteering.  We need to use other measures.  In this regard, some members of the Government have advocated a proper and substantial windfall tax on the major profits in this area.  We argued at EU level in favour of proper separation of gas prices and electricity prices, which would allow for a different cap and threshold to be set in terms of electricity prices.  If that measure were applied properly, it could be really useful in making renewable energy very affordable and making it the affordable option.</p>  <p>I will not be able to make financial amendments to the Bill, but I believe in actively supporting the transition from dependency on gas-fired central heating, on which Ireland is highly dependent, towards more use of electricity.  One of the ways in which we could do that is not by supplementing bills, almost regardless of the form of energy being billed, but by having really targeted additional measures that help people to make the transition.</p>  <p>Standing charges comprise a major issue.  It is a genuine problem if people are being told to manage their energy, switch and be efficient while at the same time having their standing charges increased.  There does not seem to be a willingness to regulate.  In this regard, I refer to our talk about capping the price or, at a minimum, capping the standing charges so they will not increase incrementally.  We know the position on the regressive move in May regarding the low-cost standing charge.  When representatives of the CRU appeared before the climate committee, they pointed out the position on those who benefited from the lower standing charge.  There may be an issue with those with holiday homes and so forth but there are other ways to tackle that.  There was also an issue with people with an A-rated house or those who produce their own solar power.  They benefited from a lower standing charge, which was a great incentive, but it was removed and the standard rate was applied to them.  Therefore, instead of incentivising the transition, we are penalising it.  In this regard, we need many other measures not just to help people to pay the bills but also to tackle the runaway escalation and really help people to make the transition.</p>  <p>When considering electricity usage and all the very difficult decisions made on it and energy use, we need to revisit and strengthen the discussion we have been trying to have for two years on data centres and the fact that Ireland's electricity demand over the past five years has increased by 9%.  By comparison, the average change in demand in other EU countries has been 0%.  Meanwhile, I believe the data centres' demand has increased by over 200%.  Therefore, we are really looking at large energy users escalating their use of electricity massively, thereby having a disproportionate impact on our electricity market.  We should be considering targeted measures to discourage this form of electricity usage specifically.</p>  <p>We talked about demand reduction but all we have got from the regulators consistently was demand management.  This is not demand reduction; it is about determining the time of day the demand might arise.  This is not the same as seeking to reduce demand overall.  These are related issues.  I am raising them to highlight that we have a wider issue concerning electricity and energy usage that extends beyond the measures in this Bill.  It is appropriate to raise them because, if we do not, will be applying Band-Aids time and again and not fixing the underlying problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-10-13a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="12:50:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022101300017#U00400"><p>I want to make a brief comment.  It would be remiss of me not to do so.  I very much welcome this Bill.  I spoke to the Minister of State previously about how we are wasting so much wind energy produced in this country by not utilising it.  It is important to do so.  I put it to the Minister of State and the officials who are present from the Department that one way of utilising the energy is through EnergyCloud, which involves a ready-to-go mechanism and is a cost-neutral way to provide energy to the most vulnerable in the community.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>