<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Colette Kelleher that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health provide an update on women&rsquo;s access to surgical abortions in each of the hospital groups where the gestation is between 11 and 12 weeks.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Kevin Humphreys of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to provide an update on the measures being taken on the BusConnects and MetroLink projects to keep costs within budget.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Grace O'Sullivan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on the number of tree fellings across the country in the past two weeks.</blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators and suitable for discussion, I have selected those proposed by Senators Kelleher and Humphreys.  They will be taken now.  I regret that I had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Grace O'Sullivan on the grounds that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#A00350">Abortion Services Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#A00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  Since the passing of legislation to regulate termination of pregnancy, early medical abortion has, for the most part, been provided to women by general practitioners and community providers.  Clinical guidelines allow for the provision of early medical abortion in the community where gestation is less than ten weeks.  These cases are being dealt with quietly and efficiently within the community.  However, whereas the legislation permits provision of abortion where the gestation has not exceeded 12 weeks, pregnancies that are ten weeks or more are to be provided for in a hospital setting for clinical reasons.</p> <p>Where gestation is between ten and 12 weeks, clinical guidelines advise GPs to refer women to hospital, where the abortion can be provided.  It appears the method of abortion in the vast majority of these cases is medical.  This method is safe and effective.  However, it carries a small risk - less than 1% - of ongoing pregnancy following the process.  If the pregnancy is ongoing following early medical abortion where it is nearing the 12-week gestation limit, the most effective way to complete the process is by surgical abortion.  The availability of surgical abortion in Ireland is not clear to the community providers.</p> <p>The Southern Taskgroup on Abortion and Reproductive Topics, START, in Cork and the surrounding region, which provides an abortion service in the community, has found that despite initial difficulties, pathways for women seeking abortion are relatively straightforward where gestation is between ten and 11 weeks.  That said, there is a concern on the part of this group of GPs that pathways for gestation over 11 weeks are less than clear.  Many GPs across the country have found that pathways for the referral to a hospital were created locally as the need arose after the beginning of the provision of services from 1 January last year.  Nonetheless, GPs in several parts of the country are concerned that there are no actual pathways for women seeking termination where gestation is between 11 and 12 weeks.  It is deeply concerning that should such a case arise, time will be of the essence and it is important that GPs and community providers would be given clear and reliable information about referral pathways for all patients coming under the provisions of the Act, regardless of how close to the 12-week limit they may be.</p> <p>Will the Minister of State confirm that the State is providing abortion services for all women where their circumstances meet the criteria set out in legislation, regardless of how close to the 12-week limit they may be?  If that is so, how many hospitals are participating in this and which ones are they?  Will the Minister of State seek to have clear and public published referral pathways for these cases so the community providers can refer women to a hospital that can provide these services in a seamless, established and agreed process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#A00500"><p>I am taking this matter on behalf of the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris.  I thank Senator Kelleher for her insight and for giving me the opportunity to provide clarification.</p> <p>On Friday, 25 May 2018, the Government held a referendum arising from the Thirty-sixth Amendment of the Constitution Act 2018.  The people of Ireland voted overwhelmingly in favour of deleting Article 40.3.3&deg; in its entirety and substituting an article in the Constitution, the object and effect of which is to articulate clearly the principle that laws may be enacted by the Oireachtas to provide for the regulation of termination of pregnancy.  The Health (Regulation of Termination of Pregnancy) Act 2018 was passed by the Houses of the Oireachtas on 13 December 2018 and signed into law by the President on 20 December 2018.  The legislation provides for a termination to be carried out in cases where there is a risk to the life or of serious harm to the health of the pregnant woman, where there is a risk to the life or of serious harm to the health of the pregnant woman in an emergency, where there is a condition present that is likely to lead to the death of the foetus either before or within 28 days of birth and without restriction up to 12 weeks of pregnancy.</p> <p>A public information campaign, My Options, commenced upon the enactment of the legislation.  Services for termination of pregnancy have been offered from 1 January 2019 and there is regular ongoing engagement between the Department of Health and the Health Service Executive, HSE, to facilitate the smooth running of the service and to resolve any issues that may arise.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Catherine Byrne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2186"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2186&amp;amp;pid=CatherineByrne&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> As of 1 March 2019, 290 GPs nationally had signed contracts to provide termination of pregnancy services in the community and terminations up to 12 weeks of pregnancy are being provided in ten maternity hospitals or units in the following hospital groups: Ireland East hospital group - National Maternity Hospital, Holles Street and Midland Regional Hospital Mullingar; RSI hospital group - Rotunda Hospital and Our Lady of Lourdes Hospital, Drogheda; Dublin Midlands hospital group - Coombe Women and Infants University Hospital; Saolta hospital group - University Hospital Galway and Mayo University Hospital; University of Limerick Hospitals - University Maternity Hospital Limerick; and South/South West hospital group - Cork University Maternity Hospital and University Hospital Waterford.  A woman requiring a termination at one of these maternity hospitals or units must be referred by a GP.</p><p>While most terminations up to nine weeks of pregnancy will take place in the community, some may need to take place in a maternity hospital or unit for medical reasons.  However, all terminations between nine and 12 weeks of pregnancy must take place in a maternity hospital or unit.  When the service for termination of pregnancy was first introduced, an issue arose whereby some maternity hospitals or units were operating an 11-week cut-off for terminations in early pregnancy.  However, this issue has been resolved.  Terminations of pregnancy carried out in maternity hospitals or units can be either medical or surgical.  The type of termination carried out is a matter for the relevant medical practitioner and the woman concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#B00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  She stated, "Terminations of pregnancy carried out in maternity hospitals or units can be either medical or surgical."  Can she confirm that they are both - as is the right pathway for the woman - because medical can be the right way to go or surgical can be the right way to go?  I refer to the particularity of the pathway for a woman who is in her 11th week.  There seems to be some doubt in the minds of GPs about the clarity of that pathway.  The Minister of State offered me some clarity but she did not offer me the clarity that I am seeking on the issue of the clinical pathway for a woman presenting at 11 weeks and the access to both surgical and medical in the hospital groups.  The Minister of State did not answer that question but I would like if she could do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1307" speakername="Catherine Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#B00300"><p>As already stated, terminations of pregnancy carried out in maternity hospitals or units can be either medical or surgical.  The type of termination carried out is a matter for the relevant medical practitioner and the woman concerned.  It is clear from this that they can be either.  This comes down to the decision of the medical practitioner.</p> <p>I am not sure to what the Senator is referring in the context of pathways.  Perhaps I can get the Minister to revert to her on the exact pathways that are being taken.  From reading the script I was given, it is clear that there is a pathway through the GPs to the effect that, up to nine weeks, it can happen in the community.  Thereafter, however, it is essential that women have their procedures in a hospital environment.  That is what is happening.  However, if the Senator persists, I will seek a reply from the Minister for her on the pathways and on the concerns raised by some of the GPs she mentioned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#B00400"><p>I would welcome that.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#B00450">Transport Costs</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#B00500"><p>As ever, I welcome the Minister, Deputy Ross.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#B00600"><p>I thank the Minister for attending.  He always makes himself available to take transport issues in the Seanad and I thank him for that.</p> <p>I tabled this matter because of a concern about overruns.  In the case of the national children's hospital, which was originally budgeted at &euro;650 million, for example, we are looking at a cost of possibly &euro;1.7 billion or more, an increase of 260%.  Hopefully, this will not happen.  If overruns of the same scale were to occur elsewhere, the cost of BusConnects would increase from &euro;2 billion to &euro;5.2 billion and that relating to MetroLink would increase from &euro;3.8 billion to a possible &euro;8 billion.  There have been significant increases in construction costs and increases of between 12% and 20% in labour costs.  Previously, there were substantial overruns when the ticketing system was realigned with the Leap card.  The latter is a cashless payment system.</p> <p>In the context of the core bus corridor project, the National Transport Authority, NTA, originally estimated that the cost of compulsory purchase orders, CPOs, would be between &euro;22 million and &euro;24.  That appears to have been a gross underestimate and the new cost is estimated at approximately &euro;32.5 million.  In some areas of the Dublin Bay South constituency, the devaluation figure relating to properties is approximately 25%.  Without legal fees, valuation and reinstatements, we are looking at approximate devaluation of &euro;500,000 per unit.  On the basis of a conservative estimate per unit, the land take could cost up to &euro;500,000.</p> <p>I am concerned that the Minister should ensure that there are adequate checks and balances in respect of the budgets for BusConnects and MetroLink.  We have not seen the estimates relating to the change in the line for the MetroLink on the northside and the impact the latter will have on the overall budget.  What I do not want to see is that we go so far and the overruns are so extensive that this project is dropped like a donkey.  I certainly do not want to see it dropped like a dead donkey.  I am anxious to hear what adequate checks and balances are included to monitor both the budget and to what is happening in the context of overruns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#B00700"><p>I thank Senator Humphreys for raising this issue.  I understand his concerns.  I hope I will be able to reassure him.  I ask the Senator's indulgence for a moment.  I will give him my script afterwards.  I brought some copies along and I think I left them in the anteroom.  I will give the Senator my script afterwards and I will try and answer his questions off-script as well.</p> <p>I agree completely with the Senator that we need to ensure rigorous and appropriate monitoring of mega-projects, such as BusConnects, the DART expansion and MetroLink.  The Government plans to invest billions of euro of taxpayers' money in public transport over the next ten years.  Recent events have obviously made us even more conscious of the need to be forensic in our examinations.  I know that the investment to which I refer is welcomed by all sides of this House.  While we can all have opinions about particular issues within these mega-projects, I would hope we could all agree on their absolute necessity.  However, we need to ensure that the funding involved is spent wisely and well and that, ultimately, the taxpayer gets value for his or her hard-earned money.</p> <p>Delivery of these projects and programmes is led by the State agencies responsible, primarily the NTA in these cases, but with funding provided by my Department.  That funding is subject to the public spending code, which sets out the appropriate structures for monitoring and management of publicly-funded capital expenditure programmes.  My Department has long had responsibility for significant capital expenditure programmes and, obviously, we have well developed monitoring and oversight systems in place already.  We absolutely recognise that these mega-projects bring unique challenges and we need to keep our governance arrangements for the years ahead refreshed and effective.  I assure the Senator that my Department is keenly aware of the need to maintain appropriate oversight as these projects really take shape over the course of this year and beyond.  We can all recognise that this governance will need to be flexible and will take different forms at different stages - just like the projects themselves.</p> <p>Not only will there be different phases over the life cycle of these projects in respect of which different skills will be required at various times but also the projects differ considerably from each other.  BusConnects and the DART expansion, for example, are both programmes of capital expenditure made up of many different projects, each required to give the overall benefits expected of the programme, whereas MetroLink is in some ways unique.  MetroLink is the development of a largely underground link from the city centre to Swords and a connected requirement to increase capacity along the Luas green line.</p> <p>Delivery of these projects and programmes will be led by very experienced State bodies such as the NTA and Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII.  They are widely recognised as having successfully implemented a number of significant public transport projects through the years.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Shane Ross:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1974"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1974&amp;amp;pid=ShaneRoss&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Of course at a departmental level we need to monitor and oversee delivery in line with the public spending code and also advise the Government in its role as the ultimate sanctioning authority at certain key decision points.  At the relevant points along the way, we will need to augment our skills with specialised knowledge to ensure we are providing the best advice we can to the Government.  We have been discussing what those requirements are with relevant stakeholders in recent months.  I assure the Senator, and the House, that the good governance of these, and indeed all projects and programmes in my Department, are of the utmost importance and we will strive to ensure the taxpayers' interests are protected at all times.</p><p>I will add to that because I want to give more specific information to Senator Humphreys in response to what he said.  When we get a business case in such situations, we normally tear it apart and then we go to the Government with the budget.  If one takes, for example, the Irish Rail situation at the moment where there is &euro;480 million budgeted for it for the coming year, the independent Commission for Railway Regulation, CRR, meets with my Department every quarter.  The National Transport Authority, NTA, on the other hand, on projects like the ones mentioned by the Senator, namely, the metro and BusConnects, meets on a monthly basis to discuss the budgets.  It looks at all the expenditure, tracks it and it reports to the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform if there is any diversion beyond a margin which I think is about &euro;100,000.  The Senator should not quote me on that but it is something of that order and that is reported to the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform if there is any diversion or wavering outside the set parameters.  Expenditure is monitored strictly, on a monthly basis in the case of the NTA, while Irish Rail monitors its projects on a quarterly basis.  Senator Humphreys can be absolutely certain that we are looking out for any kind of diversions from the original budgets and they will go straight back to the Department of Finance-Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C00200"><p>As the Minister mentioned Irish Rail, I compliment it as it has brought a number of significant projects in on time and within budget.  Irish Rail's record in that regard may be a good example for the rest of the public sector.</p> <p>I am a little cautious in response to the Minister saying it is the responsibility of the NTA to report to the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.  It must be the responsibility of the Minister.  It is a significant investment in public transport, which is badly needed, and we must monitor the budget extremely carefully.  I believe there have already been significant overruns.  Could the Minister refer in his response to the significant overruns that have already been indicated in relation to the core bus corridors?  I imagine the overruns have already exceeded &euro;100,000.</p> <p>An amount of money has already been spent on those projects and concern has been expressed in regard to that.  I understand they relate to Government policy in terms of the 2040 plan.  I am also concerned by the fact that some Fine Gael Ministers and backbenchers have said they have no confidence in BusConnects and that they will resist any further progress on it.  If Fine Gael is saying it no longer has confidence in BusConnects then let us stop spending further money on it.  I have extensive quotes from various Fine Gael Ministers and Deputies saying BusConnects is not going ahead.  If the project is not going to proceed because the Minister's partners in government no longer have any faith in it then for heaven's sake let us not spend taxpayers' money and flush it down the drain.  If the project is to proceed, let us make sure that there is support for it from the Government parties.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C00300"><p>The Senator has had an extra minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C00400"><p>I will respond to that extra minute.  You are very indulgent, a Leas-Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C00500"><p>I assure the Minister that I will be equally indulgent with him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C00600"><p>I know that.  Of course you will.  In fact, I would rather you would cut me off very quickly given what Senator Humphreys said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C00700"><p>I will oblige the Minister if he wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C00800"><p>BusConnects is going ahead.  Let there be no doubt about that.  The Senator should be aware that a consultation process is going on.  Many people, including Ministers, are not terribly comfortable with what is happening in their constituencies, which is inevitable in a project of this sort.  I have said to my colleagues, I have even said it at the Cabinet meeting, and I say it openly here, that it is open to them to go to the public consultations and I hope they will.  They can suggest improvements to some quite radical steps which are being taken in their area, which are not universally popular.  It will be difficult in certain circumstances for a project of this sort to go ahead and there will be resistance in certain places, but for the greater good BusConnects will go ahead.  It will reduce the commuting times for getting people to work and it will hopefully get more people not just into buses but also on their bicycles.  In the meantime, the public consultation on BusConnects is going ahead on both the network and on the corridors and there will be continuous consultations.  We will not have the last ones-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C00900"><p>What about the overruns?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C01000"><p>I cannot comment on the initial cost overruns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C01100"><p>I thank the Minister and Senator Humphreys.  I was equally indulgent to both of them.  That concludes the debate on Commencement matters.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.30" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C01200">Message from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#C01300"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann has passed the Withdrawal of the United Kingdom from the European Union (Consequential Provisions) Bill 2019 on 6 March 2019, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.32" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 10.55 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.33" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00200"><p>I call on the Leader to outline what is proposed for today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00300"><p>Is the Leas-Chathaoirleach trying to provoke?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00400"><p>I am just being correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00500"><p>As always.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00600"><p>I was recently reminded that it is for the House to decide.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00700"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00800"><p>The Leader proposes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G00900"><p>It is for the Leader to set the schedule for the House to decide.  That is correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G01000"><p>I think the Leader is in much better humour than he was last night, thanks be to God.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G01100"><p>I hope all Members are.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G01200"><p>Do not poke the bear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G01300"><p>We will hear the Leader now, please, without interruptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G01400"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the arrangements for the sitting of the House on Tuesday, 12 March, to be taken at the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; and No. 2, statements on the national children's hospital, to be taken at 1.30 p.m. and to conclude at 2.30 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, time can be shared, and the Minister to be given not less than six minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#G01500"><p>I express concern and dismay at comments made by the Northern Irish Secretary of State, Karen Bradley, about killings by British soldiers and police officers during the Troubles.  Her statements were provocative, especially in the wake of a decision on whether there will be criminal proceedings arising out of the Bloody Sunday incident and other incidents and shootings in Northern Ireland.  Ms Bradley should keep in mind the victims and their families who will be very upset by her unhelpful remarks in this fragile time for the peace process, with Brexit looming.  She should withdraw her comments and apologise, especially to the families of the victims.</p> <p>I want to speak about the Tusla report on fostering services, especially those in Dublin South Central.  This issue was raised by me and other colleagues in the Seanad two years ago when the previous report was published.  There were also difficulties at that stage in Dublin South Central.  The current review is scathing and states that child safeguarding in Dublin South Central have regressed over the past two years.  The area includes many very disadvantaged and extremely disadvantaged households.  The report also states that nine foster care households in which persons over 16 years of age were residing had not been Garda vetted.  It seems like a post code lottery.  A foster child living in Dublin 10, 12 or 20 and Dublin South Central in general will not get the proper care he or she deserves.  Children in foster care are in the care of the State and essentially children of the State.  It is a sad and damning indictment of the Government that it places vulnerable children at risk, depending on which area of the country they live in.  The Minister should make a statement in the House on this issue and comment on the fact that nothing has been done since it was highlighted previously.</p> <p>There have been recent shootings in west Dublin.  This morning, a friend of mine who was dropping her child to a cr&egrave;che in Blanchardstown found a burnt-out car outside when they arrived.  This problem seems to be commonplace.  The Garda does not seem to have a handle on the shootings that are taking place every second day in the city.  It is time the Garda was given more resources to put more effort into intelligence work.  It is not fair on people going about their daily business that shootings are becoming commonplace.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->My friend dropped her child off at a cr&egrave;che.  A few hours earlier a car used in a shooting was burned out.  It is not right.  The people of this city deserve a safer city.  They also deserve to know that shootings such as this will not happen on their doorsteps.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1431" speakername="P&aacute;draig &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#H00200"><p>T&aacute;im ag iarraidh labhairt ar feadh c&uacute;pla n&oacute;im&eacute;ad mar gheall ar ghn&oacute;lachta&iacute; beaga agus me&aacute;nmh&eacute;ide - small and medium-sized enterprises, SMEs.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach chaired the meeting of the Seanad Public Consultation Committee focused on SMEs.  We hope to have a draft report ready for the committee's approval in the coming weeks.  I am the rapporteur to the group and much work has been put into the report.  We are looking forward to presenting it to the Seanad and, hopefully, the Lower House in time.  I will focus on two or three of the main challenges that have arisen.  Access to finance is a major issue, while geopolitical uncertainty is another key issue.  One would not expect that to affect SMEs but it is a significant factor.</p> <p>I was invited to Westminster on Tuesday as part of a group of 25 or 30 business people from all over Europe examining the impact Brexit may have.  Brexit is not just an issue for Ireland but very much a European issue.  During our visit, a Bill concerning Gibraltar was being debates on the floor of the House of Commons.  I believe some 95% of the population of Gibraltar voted to remain in the European Union.  This is now becoming a hot potato for the British Parliament and Government.</p> <p>To focus again on Ireland, I note the Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, speaking to the Institute of Taxation just over a week ago, flagged his intention to examine entrepreneurs' relief, which is a fraction of what it is in England.  A key factor for us is ensuring that businesses can continue to evolve and there is movement and flow in the ownership of businesses.  Owners need to move their businesses on to give new energy and life to their enterprises.  </p> <p>I strongly support the Minister looking favourably at this matter and setting the relief for SMEs in Ireland at a minimum at the same level as those in England to ensure entrepreneurs have access to reliefs and flexibility and people are encouraged to start a business.  As the Leader knows, the skill sets required to start a business are totally different from those needed to grow a business.  Those are not the same things, as I have learned.  I have the scars from that process.  A different leadership style is needed in growing and scaling a business.  We need to give entrepreneurs who have the vision and creativity to start a business the ability to start bringing in those skill sets and not penalise them when they transfer or sell their businesses.  I ask the Leader to consider inviting the Minister for Finance to the House to share with us his view and strategy on entrepreneurs' relief.  The sooner that debate takes place, the better as it will give some degree of certainty and clarity to SMEs, particularly in light of the upcoming train crash that appears to be happening with Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#H00300"><p>The remarks of the British Secretary of State, Ms Karen Bradley, in the British House of Commons were disgraceful and deeply offensive to the families of those killed by the British Crown forces, publicly, formally and illegally, through collusion with loyalist death squads.  The mentality demonstrated by the Secretary of State led to the killings happening because British Crown forces had impunity to kill at will with no consequences for their actions.  It is clear from the remarks of Secretary of State Bradley that she is giving a licence to kill and impunity from prosecutions to those who killed and those who sent them out to kill.</p> <p>Her remarks are a direct interference in the judicial process, coming as they do days before the decision on whether to prosecute British troops from the Parachute Regiment involved in the Bloody Sunday massacre.  Her remarks also come after the courts handed down welcome decisions in the Pat Finucane and Pearse Jordan cases and after a decision was made to fund the legacy cases, something called for by relatives' organisations and the Lord Chief Justice in the North for years.  The Secretary of State's remarks clearly show she has no sympathy for the relatives of those killed and no interest in assisting them to get the truth.  She is more interested in protecting the killers.  This is enormously upsetting for the families who have been waiting decades for inquests and the truth.  It is appalling to see somebody in the position of Secretary of State come out and make those remarks.  </p> <p>I have just attended a presentation given by members of Border Communities against Brexit in the audiovisual room.  I was really struck by their statement that the economic devastation that may result from Brexit might only be surpassed by the damage to the peace process.  The group is calling a day of action on 30 March and for political parties, and others, to sign a declaration on Brexit.  The devastation Brexit will bring was clearly outlined.  In particular, a pharmacist spoke about the health implications in respect of shared services in the north west and the absence of any contingency plans.  That is the case even with something as simple as the ambulances that cross the Border.  </p> <p>Ear, nose and throat, ENT, services serve counties Fermanagh, Tyrone, Sligo and Leitrim.  How will that work after Brexit?  Some 60% of medicines we get in this country travel through Britain.  Clarification is also required on cross-Border cancer care for the Donegal Action for Cancer Care group.  There also needs to be clarification on that issue.  I know we have legislation coming through next week but these issues arise now in the ordinary lives of people.  We need to hear from the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, in this House as to what these communities are to do post-Brexit, whether that is hard, soft or something else.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#H00400"><p>I raise the issue of defective developments all around the country.  I have an eight-page document detailing housing estates and apartment complexes everywhere from County Louth to County Wicklow.  They are in Swords, Sandyford, Spencer Dock, Belmayne, Kilmainham and Ratoath, and the list goes on.  The residents of those estates have got much tea and sympathy.  I am not laying the blame for these defective developments at the door of the Government.  The system of self-certification that caused this problem was brought in by a previous Government.  Developers were allowed to use their own employees to self-certify the completion of apartment blocks and housing estates.  Real people with real families, however, have been left to face the fallout.  The bills from contractors to put right things that should have been done properly in the first place vary from &euro;20,000 to &euro;60,000 and &euro;70,000.</p> <p>The argument being advanced by the Minster for Housing, Planning and Local Government, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, is that the State cannot take on unlimited liabilities in respect of this issue.  However, given that a Fianna F&aacute;il Government brought in the system of self-certification, the State has to take some sort of responsibility.  We cannot leave these hundreds, if not thousands, of families in this position.  They already have large mortgages and now face having to pay out large sums to fix dangerous accommodation which they were told was fit to live in.</p> <p>The previous Government was able to resolve similar problems when they arose.  We were ready to bring forward solutions for residents.  The Government needs to apply itself to finding a mechanism to assist families in these circumstances.  I am putting the Leader on notice that if a solution is not brought forward regarding these issues, I will call on the Minister to come to this House and discuss the crisis these families are going through.  I have met heartbroken families from the Beacon South Quarter in Sandyford who have been left with enormous bills.  This has been discussed in the House but no solution has been advanced.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There was talk of low-cost loans and going after developers but nothing has happened and families have been left with the bills and the worry.  This can no longer continue.  I am putting the Leader on notice that, if a solution is not brought forward shortly, I will propose an amendment to the Order of Business calling for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to attend the House to discuss this serious issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J00200"><p>I also decry and deplore the comments made by Karen Bradley.  I fail to see how she can ever regain the confidence of nationalists and families of those who suffered during the Troubles.  Have we forgotten Bloody Sunday?  Have we forgotten the Miami Showband and all the other issues?  She needs to consider her position.  We decried the actions of a Sinn F&eacute;in MP in this House and he later stood down, and we need the same response in this regard.</p> <p>I wish to raise another issue of national importance, which is the fact that two out of every five of our children are now either obese or overweight.  The greatest threat to health in the western world, and in the developing world, is not infection but non-communicable diseases such as diabetes, high blood pressure, stroke, heart attack and cancer, and obesity plays a major role in all of them.  Last night, however, I heard that Fingal County Council has given planning permission to a 6,000 sq. ft fast-food restaurant with a drive-through facility.  It is 50 m across the road from a cr&egrave;che which is attended by 100 children and 300 m from a primary school with 400 young children.  Myriad Government documents underpin policy relate to fighting obesity and I was particularly proud to launch Healthy Ireland.  The local authority is ignoring them but it is not just Fingal - they all do it and it is a national issue.</p> <p>The Ministers for Health and Housing, Planning and Local Government need to issue an edict to all local authorities advising them of Government policy and that these types of development are not appropriate.  This is a small neighbourhood shopping centre and there were hundreds of objections from local residents in Skerries, and the Barnageeragh Cove area in particular, because of their concern.  I hate to say it but it smacks of the tactics of the tobacco industry in the way the fast-food industry is trying to "get them young and keep them for life."  It is a cradle-to-grave approach but we do not want such an approach and if we are going to be serious about a cross-Government coherent strategy to fight what is an epidemic, the Government needs to act accordingly.  I hope the Leader will convey this message to the relevant Ministers and I hope they will take action.  Otherwise, the issue will come back to this House and the Ministers in question will have to come in to explain themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J00300"><p>At a meeting of the Joint Committee on Rural and Community Development, Jim Connolly, a former bank official, called safe deposit vaults a "medieval lost and found".  They are in all banks and the Bank of Ireland in Dublin has serious vaults.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J00400"><p>On St. Stephen's Green.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J00500"><p>The committee is looking into the issue and they are looking at the Dormant Accounts Act 2001 in this regard.  It is proof positive that there is need for a wills Bill.  Many of those deposit boxes are contained within a will which has never been found.  The safe deposit box is now in the banks, lying dormant and never to be opened.  It is about time we looked at the situation.  I welcome the passage of the Registration of Wills Bill 2016, which was co-sponsored by Senator Catherine Ardagh, our leader in the House, as well as our deputy leader, Senator Clifford-Lee.  It will now go to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann and I will work with our spokespersons and Members of the D&aacute;il to make every effort to enact the Bill.  I express my thanks to all the parties on the Government side who took a courageous decision to support a Bill that is in the public interest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J00600"><p>This is a Second Stage speech.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J00700"><p>The efforts of the Law Society on this Bill over the past 14 years has been unacceptable.  The Law Society is led by Ken Murphy, the director general, who is paid more than An Taoiseach and he protects solicitors who pay his wages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J00800"><p>We cannot rehash last night and I do not want the Senator to name people who are not in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J00900"><p>I am emphasising the point that he protects solicitors who pay his wages.  They do not represent the public.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01000"><p>The Senator is making charges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01100"><p>The grounds for objections are not there, as Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen said last night.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01200"><p>The Senator is making charges and I cannot tolerate it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01300"><p>Furthermore-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01400"><p>The Senator is out of order.  He cannot make charges against the Law Society in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01500"><p>There is a solicitor in the House who supports the Bill and co-sponsors it.  She is not controlled by any organisation but is a representative of the people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01600"><p>The matter was decided last night and we are not reopening it now on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01700"><p>Perhaps Senator Leyden should be put in the vaults.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01800"><p>I met the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection last night.  We are the best of friends and we will meet again shortly to discuss the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J01900"><p>I am glad to hear that but this is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J02000"><p>I thank members of the Fine Gael party in the House because most of them supported the Bill.  They have to go along with their Whips.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J02100"><p>The Senator is a longstanding Member of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J02200"><p>I am very grateful to the Leas-Chathaoirleach for the way he chaired the debate last night and to Senator Diarmuid Wilson for his skilled approach to getting it right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1439" speakername="Ian Marshall" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#J02300"><p>I acknowledge the trip to Belfast on Tuesday by the Seanad Special Select Committee on the Withdrawal of the UK from the EU.  The trip was ably chaired by Senator Joe O'Reilly, deputising for Senator Neale Richmond, and present were Senators Black, Paul Daly, &Oacute; Donnghaile, Craughwell, and I.  We met many businesses and other organisations such as the Northern Ireland Food and Drink Association, Manufacturing NI, the Ulster Farmers Union, Retail NI, the Freight Transport Association, the Federation of Small Businesses and the Northern Ireland Retail Consortium.  We also met many civic groups such as the initiative for civic space, civic nationalism, Belfast City Council's Brexit committee, assistant chief constable of the PSNI, Mr. Tim Mairs, as well as academics and media folk.</p> <p>It was a full and busy schedule but it highlighted the complexity of the situation at the moment, as well as the fears and concerns of all the people who will be impacted.  It gave us an indication of the diversity of opinion and the risks of oversimplifying this problem.  We talked about trade, human rights, policing, security, agriculture and freight and the issues were complicated, which meant we often struggled to get a grasp of what the right solution would be.  A lot of knowledge was gained from the visit and credit must be given to all the secretarial staff who made it happen and who put the plans in place.</p> <p>The most moving meeting we had was the final meeting of the day at Elizabeth House on the Holywood Road in Belfast with the Training for Women Network, TWN.  The chief executive, Norma Shearer, and the chair, Patricia Lewsley-Mooney welcomed us and introduced us to a group of staff - women from both the loyalist and republican communities.  These women had been directly involved in the conflict and directly impacted by the horrors of the Troubles and the atrocities that took place.  They shared stories of the devastation to them, their families, their communities and their lives.  At one stage we were speechless when one lady stood up and recounted, with tears streaming down her face, her horror as she was instructed to take her son to a punishment shooting.  When Senator Craughwell asked her why on earth she would take her son to a shooting, she said it was because if she did not, there would have been a summary execution of her child.  We were dumbfounded and astounded by this.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ian Marshall:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2486"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2486&amp;amp;pid=IanMarshall&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They tried to relate to us the horrors of living in these communities, which were completely out of control, and trying to bring up their families in that situation.  The important thing for us to note is that these women have had an impact on the lives of hundreds of other women.  They have engaged women by bringing together women from completely diverse backgrounds and communities, training them and giving them space and support to lift their families out of the cycle of apathy, alienation and despair.  </p><p>Leader, these women have given hope and inspiration to many people in diverse communities.  I suggest that we invite them to Leinster House to tell their stories, share their experiences, and inform those who did not live through this and those who do not understand it just how sensitive everyone needs to be to the cultures, identities, pain and hurt, and to dealing with rebuilding.  On Tuesday, these women told us, in their own words, that they were the glue that held the families and communities together during the Troubles.  I have no doubt that they will be the glue that will connect the blocks in the rebuilding process.  They need all of our support and assistance to ensure that their fantastic work is maintained and expanded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#K00200"><p>Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#K00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#K00400"><p>I, too, agree with the view expressed by Senator Marshall that we need to treat a lot of the issues in Northern Ireland with sensitivity.  The comments made by Karen Bradley in the House of Commons yesterday were insensitive, out of touch and caused hurt and offence.  However, I recognise that she has said she will go back to the house and correct the record of the oral questions, which I welcome.  When I consider what is happening in Westminster I realise that she is just listening to one voice.  She is listening to the DUP and other MPs.  A nationalist voice is missing from Westminster, that of the Sinn F&eacute;in MPs who are not taking up their seats.  We lost three SDLP MPs as well.  Mark Durkan, Alasdair McDonnell and Margaret Ritchie carried that moderate nationalist voice, which is missing.  We must understand that without that voice comments will be made like those based on what Karen Bradley is listening to.  She has caused a lot of hurt and pain to families but I acknowledge, and in politics we should acknowledge, that she has said she will correct the record of the house, which is welcome albeit late.  Both here and in the D&aacute;il we talk about British politicians not understanding Northern Ireland.  A vast majority of politicians in this country have no clue what goes on in Northern Ireland and sometimes their statements cause hurt and offence.  Maybe we must consider why this happens and be aware that in Westminster that nationalist voice, especially from Northern Ireland, is very much missing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#K00500"><p>I find it remarkable that the lack of Sinn F&eacute;in presence in Westminster would be used to excuse the comments made by the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland yesterday.  Her comments were not due to her listening only to one voice.  I contend that she is listening not only to the DUP but to the layers of establishment that exist in London.  Her comments go right to the heart of that establishment.</p> <p>I want to comment on the Eurovision song contest.  Israel's continued abuse of international law damages the two-state solution.  Added to that, Israel is using the Eurovision as a way to present its prettier face, and to whitewash and distract attention from war crimes.  Two days after the Eurovision final last year Israeli forces killed 62 Palestinians in Gaza.  Tomorrow, there will be a protest at RT&Eacute; as the national broadcaster is set to announce Ireland's entry.  There should be no entry from Ireland.  Time and again the international community remains silent.  The routine statements of concern must translate into sanction.  Israel cannot be allowed to act with impunity when committing murder.  The Irish Government has a role to play.  It must take the lead and send the Israeli ambassador home.  Ireland must also recognise the state of Palestine, as approved by the D&aacute;il over five years ago.  The passing of the Control of Economic Activity (Occupied Territories) Bill in the Seanad is a momentous step towards banning the import and the sale of goods, services and natural resources from Israeli settlements.  On the issue of the Eurovision 2019, Palestinian artists have appealed for a boycott of the song contest.  I appeal to all artists here in Ireland to do the same.  Israel is an apartheid State and Eurovision 2019 whitewashes apartheid.    </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#K00600"><p>Senator Leyden may be leaving the Chamber at this minute but I must say that he is eminently qualified to be appointed as curator of all of the artefacts that are in the vaults of the banks.  He would bring a breadth of experience to the role.  It would be research in terms of the whole area of living wills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#K00700"><p>I would love to search the vaults; it would be lovely to get the General's paintings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" speakername="Kieran O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#K00800"><p>I want to take up the point made by Senator Marshall and follow on from what was said by Senator Feighan.  We have reached a point, particularly down here, where we need to get a full understanding of the North of Ireland, which we can only get from the people who have experienced same.  I very much support Senator Marshall's suggestion that we invite people, particularly women, to come in here and inform us.  When he was speaking I was reflecting on the women who came together and were awarded a prize.  In all walks of life, women are the pragmatists and, in many cases, ultimately the voice of reason.  The suggestion that Senator Marshall has put forward here could be a major conduit in terms of us getting a full understanding of what is happening in the North.  I hope that the Leader and the Cathaoirleach will arrange a debate as quickly as possible to start a dialogue on how to reach a full understanding.</p> <p>The statements made by the Secretary of State, Karen Bradley, should not have happened.  It is something she will have to reflect on.  I acknowledge that she will correct the record of the House the Commons but she will have to question whether that is enough.  Last night, I watched a programme on one of the news stations that showed at best there is a dearth of knowledge or ignorance about what is happening in the North.  The comments made by the Secretary of State were unfortunate at best.  A Secretary of State must take all factors into account.  Certainly, what Ms Bradley stated in the House of Commons yesterday was not reflective of the true situation.  </p> <p>To end on a positive note, we should arrange as quickly as possible a discussion here with women from the North, as suggested by Senator Marshall.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#K00900"><p>I ask the Leader to invite the Taoiseach to come to the House and explain the statement he made last night about my party not being wholehearted in its support for the Government's strategy on Brexit.  Admittedly, the Taoiseach was talking to a convention of his Fine Gael Party.  His remark was, at least, a very careless remark and, at worst, a remark that could destabilise his own Government.  It is extraordinary that we have a Taoiseach who seems to be constantly going out of his way to destabilise his own Government.  It is unprecedented.  I ask the Leader to invite the Taoiseach here to explain his statement.</p><p>The House should be very grateful to Fiach Kelly of <i>The Irish Times</i>for lifting the lid on the interesting political pond life that is the extreme left-wing in Ireland.  We have always known that there is a communist group in the country.  They prefer not to call themselves communists.  They do not openly called themselves Trotskyites but they are.  Trotsky was responsible for the deaths of countless thousands and millions of people.  He exulted in those deaths.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ned O'Sullivan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2233"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2233&amp;amp;pid=NedOSullivan&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->His political philosophy has failed everywhere it has been tried.  It is up to Sinn F&eacute;in to comment on what the paper related about it being a capitalist, <i>petit bourgeois</i>party.  That is not for me to decide.  Most people reading the papers that have been published were probably mostly amused and bewildered that such undergraduate thinking would obtain in Irish politics and be represented in the Lower House.  At the same time, perhaps there is a legitimate fear that something untoward and subversive is happening.<br/><br/>The Trotskyite religion has no loyalty to any state or government.  It is loyal only to that failure of a philosophy, the Communist International.  It is quite chilling to read in the report that reference was made to &quot;Kerensky being used as a gun-rest to shoot Kornilov&quot;.  This type of thinking is worrying.  Will the Leader ask the Minister for Justice and Equality to come to the House and advise us on whether there is a clear and present danger to the State from revolutionary Trotskyite groups?  I am sure they are a greater danger to themselves than to anybody else but it would be reassuring to know our security forces are on the job with regard to what has been a revelation to most of us.  Mind you, there has been stunning silence from the principal parties so far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L00200"><p>I am a former soldier who served in two armies.  On Tuesday afternoon in Belfast, the horrors of the Troubles came back to me.  I take grave exception to people talking about members of any security force being murderers.  I accept that there were rogue groups who murdered people but I draw the attention of the House to Ranger Best, who was taken out of his house in Derry and brought to Donegal to be shot.  Were the people who did that not equally as bad?  There were also the loyalist terror groups that went around and killed at will.  Were they not equally as bad?  Raking over the past does nothing.</p> <p>The people who served in the security forces and colluded must be brought to justice at some stage.  All soldiers, regardless of where they served, carried with them authorisation cards that gave them the five instances in which they could open fire.  I take grave exception to people who once supported murderers turning on other murderers and trying to make out in some way that what they did was worse.  This country was torn apart, particularly the North of Ireland, by terrorist groups on all sides.  There is a triangle and it is not just two sides; there were three sides.  There were those in the security forces who colluded.  We must remember that there were also those in the security forces on this side who colluded.  Let us not all be running around the place claiming to be whiter than white and purer than pure.  Ultimately, the woman we met on Tuesday evening had brought her child to a predetermined place to have his kneecaps shot off because he had transgressed a rule laid down by some unelected person.  The same sort of terror goes on in these communities every day of the week.  Many communities in Northern Ireland are not able to turn to the official Police Service of Northern Ireland to deal with issues.  The women of Northern Ireland carry with them the trauma of what went on up there.  Those who committed atrocities must answer for what they did but let us not try and pretend that it was a one-sided affair because it was not.</p> <p>Yesterday, I met people from the South East Fermanagh Foundation.  This group deals with survivors of the Troubles.  One of the points made to me is that there are people in the Republic who were traumatised as a result of the Troubles but we have no dedicated service to look after them.  They are told they must go to the HSE for psychological services but what do they get?  They get put on a list whereby they will be dealt with at some stage.  My colleague, Senator Marshall, might or might not agree with me but one of the things we have to do down here is take full ownership of the Good Friday Agreement.  This means dealing with the issues that people who are living on this side of the Border have to deal with.  We cannot be borrowing from services in the North of Ireland that are not funded.  If we are going to use those organisations we must fund them.  I am sorry but I am a little annoyed over this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L00300"><p>The Senator is also a little over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L00400"><p>I reiterate that if security services were involved in incidents - Ballymurphy and Bloody Sunday come to mind - they must answer but the mother of Ranger Best and those who were murdered by the loyalist butchers are also entitled to answers.  We need to be real about this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L00500"><p>I request a special debate on Northern Ireland.  I second the proposition of Senator Marshall that we invite those women and others to the House.</p> <p>The remarks made yesterday by the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, Karen Bradley, were totally crass and out of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L00600"><p>I am advised the Senator cannot formally second something that has not been proposed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L00700"><p>I take that back.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L00800"><p>The Senator can support the proposition.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L00900"><p>I do support it.  I thank the Leas-Chathaoirleach.</p> <p>The Secretary of State's remarks were crass and inappropriate and should not have been made.  I hope that, at a minimum, she retracts them and apologises in the House of Commons.  It is almost like trying to throw petrol onto a fire that is partly extinguished and trying to reignite it.  It is totally out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L01000"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#L01100"><p>I support Senator Marshall in the context of bringing the particular group of women to the House but I would also extend the invitation to other groups over a period.  It would not be realistic to have them all at one time but I would like to think that, over a period, all of the groups we met could come before the House.  I thank Senator Marshall for the kind remarks he made about my input to the all-day meeting in Belfast of our Brexit committee.  We all thrive on affirmation.</p> <p>No matter how Brexit goes, we will be left living on this island together as a community, North and South.  This is why I want our debate on Northern Ireland to centre on how we can continue co-operation in the area of health.  There is no reason not to have specialties in the various hospitals on the Border and interplay between them.  There is no reason we could not have heightened co-operation in the area of education, such as exchange programmes.  There is no reason we could not continue to co-operate on economic grounds, irrespective of what type of Brexit occurs.  We must think about living beyond Brexit and the fact we will be here together afterwards.</p> <p>I want to make a specific proposal that is relevant to the State and the Government.  I propose that when people apply for a sports capital grant, CL&Aacute;R grant or various forms of community funding, one aspect of the application that should get points weighting for approval is evidence of interchange with Northern Ireland.  There should be evidence that a sports club has played at least a couple of challenge matches against teams from Northern Ireland.  There should be evidence that a community group has links to Northern Ireland.  This would be an acutely heightened necessity in Border regions but why should it not extend throughout the island?  I want the Leader to convey to the various Ministers, including Deputies Ring and Griffin, who are responsible for these grants, that we adjust the grants and make a link to Northern Ireland a prerequisite.  If we do not build human interaction, mutual understanding and real interpersonal communication, any abstract discussion on unity will remain abstract.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We must build relationships.  There are two ways to do this, by initiative and by making it a prerequisite to get State funding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M00200"><p>I am reminded that these are meant to be two minute slots.  I have been at fault.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M00300"><p>He was very interesting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M00400"><p>There is no doubt about that.  I now call Senator Conway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M00500"><p>I commend the contribution of my colleague, Senator O'Reilly, including the work he did in Belfast as part of that committee along with Senator Marshall and others.  We have a responsibility to ensure that we develop, enhance and foster links with Northern Ireland and various communities there.  I agree with Senator O'Reilly that the best way to do that is through sport, to create indelible links between GAA clubs and soccer clubs in the North and the South and other groups such as tourism groups.  Maybe tourism facilities that are funded through the rural regeneration scheme and other grants should be required to run a special tourism promotional drive in the North, perhaps twinning with other facilities in the North.  I recall the work that Clare tourism council did with the former Newry and Mourne District Council in the late 1990s and early 2000s.  Those linkages were very important.  Considering the challenges, uncharted waters and the stormy conditions that we undoubtedly will face, we need to develop links.</p> <p>I was glad to note before I came in here that the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, Karen Bradley, has apologised profoundly for what she said.  It will be welcomed by all sides of the House.  What she said was totally inappropriate and not proper.</p> <p>As part of our engagement with civil society, and the address by the president of the GAA in the House last month was a very beneficial engagement, we should invite the directors of the Abbey Theatre, which is our national theatre, to present to the House in a similar way.  I think back to our former colleague, Fiach Mac Conghail, and the superb contributions he made to this House.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M00600"><p>That proposal should be made to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges rather than here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M00700"><p>I am probably introducing a new step in that I am asking that the Leader recommend it to the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M00800"><p>I have no doubt he will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M00900"><p>On the Order of Business, I am formally requesting that the Leader would convey such a request as it would have a lot more clout and power coming from the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M01000"><p>I am sure that the Leader can bring that up with the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M01100"><p>I have huge power, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M01200"><p>An engagement with the directors of the Abbey, based on some of the controversies recently about the use of Irish actors and so on, is something that this House should consider, in the absence of former Senator Mac Conghail who kept us informed about what was happening in the national theatre during his five years here.  He organised a couple of field trips to various shows.  It would be a very useful exercise of which Seanad &Eacute;ireann would be the beneficiary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M01300"><p>I do not think that the Abbey could teach some of the people in here anything about acting.  Last but not least, I call Senator Wilson.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M01400"><p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach would be an excellent adjudicator in any performance that might take place.</p> <p>I endorse the comments of my constituency colleague and good friend, Senator O'Reilly, regarding a debate on Northern Ireland.  That should be a rolling debate.  Senator Humphreys raised an important issue that affects ordinary people who took out a mortgage, bought a property that had been signed off on by various regulators, architects, etc. and now find themselves in serious difficulties and having to come up with money they do not have to remedy the difficulties.  We should focus on the insurance companies that insure these building firms which built these buildings that turn out to be unsatisfactory.  I always believed that we neglected the people of this country by not pursuing the insurance companies that insure the banks and the auditors who signed off on fraudulent banks in this country.  They are the people who should have been pursued for the money that was outstanding.</p> <p>On the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, Karen Bradley, I accept what Senator Conway has said that she has apologised profoundly for her comments but it is not good enough.  She is the Secretary of State responsible for the province that has been occupied, the Six Counties of this country, and the onus is on her to know the people and the situations she is dealing with in that territory.  Considering that she did not know, and the fact she was unaware inquiries had been set up by her Government, some of which are ongoing and which she may have been prejudiced, it is time she resigned and gave the job to somebody who is capable of doing it.</p> <p>All unlawful killing is wrong.  I would go so far as to say that all killing is wrong, whether lawful in the eyes of some, but during guerilla warfare there is a particular onus on the supposed professional soldiers to follow orders.  If they are following orders, it is the people who gave those orders who should be before the courts, not the ordinary soldiers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M01500"><p>I thank the Senator and call on the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#M01600"><p>I thank the 15 Members for their contributions.  I commend Senator O'Reilly for the line of the morning, that we all thrive on affirmation.  I join Senators Ardagh, Conway-Walsh, Reilly, Feighan, Warfield, Kieran O'Donnell, Craughwell, O'Reilly, Wilson and Conway in their condemnation of the remarks made by the Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, notwithstanding her apology this morning.  As Senator Wilson said, all killing is wrong.  This morning, in accepting her apology for her insensitive and inappropriate remarks, I believe she should reflect on her position.  As Senator Reilly said, it is about building trust and about what former President McAleese said about building bridges with all communities.  The comments in this House this morning have been in the main about reconciliation, building bridges and extending the hand of friendship, particularly in a post-Brexit era where, on this island, we need for all our traditions and beliefs to work together to ensure our island works together, north, south, east and west, green, white and orange.  The visit by Senators O'Reilly, Marshall and Craughwell on Tuesday was an important one.  Senators Marshall and O'Reilly spoke of inviting the women they met.  However, as Senator Conway-Walsh said, it is also about listening to different voices in order that we can plan and not go back to the past but go to the future with confidence and hope.  It is about belief.  If we had stayed in the past, we would not be where we are today.  We would not have the Good Friday Agreement, or the solidarity we have with the majority of people in the North who voted to remain.  It is about ensuring there is justice and accountability on all sides of the violence in the North.</p> <p>On Senator Feighan's contribution, all of us have an interest in, and a contribution to make on, the North.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is, as Senator Joe O'Reilly said, by engagement and human interaction that we can learn and build.  I was struck by his contribution in terms of the CL&Aacute;R and the sports capital grant and equally by the fact that is about engagement, by the visits of last Tuesday and by the people Senator Conway-Walsh spoke about and by having them in Leinster House, the people's house.  We are the representatives of the people.  It is about listening to and engagement with people that we can do that.  I would be very happy to have that debate on the North and to have the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Coveney, come to the House after the St. Patrick's Day break.  I thank Members for their positive contributions this morning.</p><p>The most important point from this morning's debate on the Order of Business is that we are open to working with and to engaging in dialogue to represent the people and to build a better Ireland.  That is an Ireland where we are all equal and in which we can all aspire to be who we want to be.</p><p>Senator Ardagh raised an issue which Senator Devine raised the other morning, namely, Tusla.  As I said then, and I will repeat it, the report was baffling and I will invite the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Zappone, to the House after St. Patrick's Day.</p><p>Gangland crime is a major source of worry to all Members and all communities.  Senator Ardagh failed to recognise that this Government and the previous one  reopened Templemore, the Garda training college and &euro;1.8 billion has been given to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to combat gangland crime and to look at ways to deter the criminal and the thug from continuing on this murderous spree.</p><p>Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh made a good contribution on small and medium enterprises and I would be very happy to have a debate following on from the report of the Seanad Public Consultation Committee.  Competitiveness is important as are the points made by Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh in the context of Brexit.  He must have listened to the Taoiseach's speech about tax, recognising entrepreneurship and enabling people to get up early and go to work.  I am glad Senator &Oacute; C&eacute;idigh is listening to the Taoiseach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N00200"><p>What about those on night duty?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N00300"><p>The point he made, which is very relevant, is that it requires different skill sets to start and to grow a company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N00400"><p>Many men and women get up early and go to work but cannot live on the wages they are paid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N00500"><p>The good news Senator Craughwell is that unemployment is decreasing and there are more people at work now that at any time in the history of our State.  Senator Craughwell was in Belfast when I made the point on the Order of Business about the increase in wages, but we will have a debate on that in due course.</p><p>I referred to Senator Conway-Walsh's comments and the important point is that in a post-Brexit era it is about listening to and working with Border communities.</p><p>Senator Humphreys spoke about the defective housing in housing estates.  <i>The  Irish Times </i>ran a series of articles on the matter.  The worry for all of us, and the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government is not wrong, is that there is an open-ended liability if that is the line we follow.  I agree with Senators Humphreys and Wilson that there is a need to go after those responsible.  I have been in apartment complexes where one could put a car through the hole in the wall.  In my city of Cork, one such apartment block was demolished.  I am aware of Priory Hall.  I agree with Members that we need to find a solution but it is a complex issue and has to be balanced by addressing the needs of the residents who bought apartments and houses in good faith and the responsibilities of the developer and the insurance companies.  I will be happy to have the Minister come to the House to have a debate on the matter.  We may not get a solution to it that might to the liking of Members but I will be happy to have a debate because I am aware that some councils have spent money on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N00600"><p>Solutions have been found in the past.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N00700"><p>I am open to finding solutions.  What I said was that we might not find a solution during the debate but I am open to finding one because we need to recognise the hurt and the financial distress to homeowners in these cases.</p> <p>Senator Reilly spoke about obesity and the decision to grant planning permission to a fast food outlet in Fingal, which is disturbing.  We are trying to promote Healthy Ireland and to reduce the level of obesity.  I note there was a report today that called for the removal of vending machines selling chocolate and sweets in hospitals.  The same principle applies in terms of the proximity of such places to cr&egrave;ches and schools.  This is a worry that should be addressed.</p> <p>Senator Leydon in his interesting contribution spoke about the contents of the deposit boxes in the bank vaults.  I do not know whether I agree with Senator Kieran O'Donnell's proposal.  The point he made on bank vaults was that the banks have an opportunity to work with the families of those who own the properties and the documentation in the vaults.  The Dormant Accounts Fund has proved very successful.</p> <p>Senator Warfield raised an issue in respect of the Eurovision Song Contest.  I note his contribution.  There is a part of me that agrees with him, that Ireland should boycott the Eurovision but another part thinks we should not.  I agree that Israel must not be allowed to use Eurovision as a propaganda weapon or tool or  that any immoral or illegal behaviour cannot be condoned.  It should be condemned outright.  The Eurovision is not a political event and has never been used, apart from the voting perhaps, as a political activity but there are legitimate concerns being expressed by a variety of people on the hosting of the Eurovision by Israel.  I am slow to boycott.  If it was a sporting event, I would say the same thing, but I understand the points made and the right to legitimate protest is one that I welcome.  I thank the Senator for raising the matter on the Order of Business.</p> <p>Senator Ned O'Sullivan raised the issue of the Taoiseach's remarks last night.  I was not in Clontarf Castle for the speech to which he referred.  I think he should have said also that the Taoiseach recognised that the role played by Fianna F&aacute;il in offering political stability was to be welcomed.  The point made by the Taoiseach was that the Fianna F&aacute;il spokesperson raised points about overselling the political declaration and that it might not work but it has worked.  The political declaration, or the withdrawal agreement-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N00800"><p>We have to see that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N00900"><p>It is early days yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01000"><p>In fairness, it is not early days now.  The reality is that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01100"><p>Withdraw that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01200"><p>There were a number of points that I was not going to make but now that I am being heckled, I will make them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01300"><p>Please.  We have to be reasonable with one another.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01400"><p>It is time to make love and stop bickering with each other.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01500"><p>We have to be honest.  Let me make two points.  There is no such thing as a good outcome from Brexit.  The party opposite is in this malaise about being prepared.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01600"><p>The Leader's party is in government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01700"><p>Senator Wilson wishes his party was in government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01800"><p>The Leader, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N01900"><p>The party opposite is in a malaise about preparedness.  Not one member of the Fianna F&aacute;il Party has explained to me or to the Irish people how can one be fully prepared for a hard Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N02000"><p>We did not ask that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N02100"><p>Read it.  The reality is that the Fianna F&aacute;il Party has had an incoherent position since the beginning.  The Taoiseach said also that the Fianna Fail leader is pretty good at wagging the finger the whole time.  He is one of the best men I know for never being wrong about anything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N02200"><p>He has plenty to wag about.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N02300"><p>He has to wag the finger at the members of his own party as he has to control some of the Members opposite.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N02400"><p>Be respectful, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N02500"><p>I am being very respectful, but may I agree with Senator Ned O'Sullivan on his very interesting discourse on the Trotskyites and the far left in our country.  We are joined by some of them in this House, perhaps.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N02600"><p><i>Petit bourgeois</i>capitalists.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#N02700"><p>Senator Ned O'Sullivan just stole my words.  In that article by Fiach Kelly, they are not too far from the centre.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#O00100"><p>Leave Senator Craughwell out of this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#O00200"><p>The point the article highlights is that the centre must always hold in politics.  I agree with Senator Ned O'Sullivan's comments in that regard.  The other point relates to the threat to themselves or to us.  We should all condemn the people to whom the Senator refers who are protesting outside the homes of Government Ministers and other politicians.  Such behaviour has no place in a democracy.  These protestors should be condemned out of hand.  The Taoiseach was right in this regard.  We are fair game on one level.  By all means people may come to our offices and meet us but they should not engage with our families or our staff.  I make that point very strongly.</p> <p>Senator Conway's contribution regarding civil society, the Abbey Theatre and any opportunity to address the Seanad in this regard is really a matter for the Committee on Procedure and Privileges.  I would be happy to defer to the committee in respect of these matters.</p> <p>I thank Senators in advance for their co-operation on the Brexit omnibus Bill, which is due to come before the House next week.  We are due to sit earlier next Tuesday.  I encourage all Senators to participate in the debate.  It is the biggest and most important debate we will have in the context of the future of our country.  I hope all Senators will participate in the Second Stage and Committee Stage debates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.140" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.141" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#O00400">Sitting Arrangements: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#O00500"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That, notwithstanding anything in the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, the Seanad shall meet at 12 noon on Tuesday, 12th March, 2019 and the Order of Business shall be proposed at 1 p.m.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.143" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.144" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.40 p.m. and resumed at 1.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.145" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#T00100">National Children's Hospital: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#T00200"><p>I am very grateful for the opportunity to update the Seanad on the new children's hospital project.  Over the past number of weeks there has been significant debate and discussion regarding the development of the new children&rsquo;s hospital and the increase in the cost of the project.  I advised Government in December 2018 that the overall cost to complete the project is &euro;1.433 billion, &euro;450 million more than advised to Government in April 2017 when it gave the green light for the construction of the hospital and the two satellite centres.  Some &euro;319 million of the additional cost relates to construction costs and the balance of &euro;131 million, which includes &euro;50 million in VAT, relates to costs associated with staff, consultants, planning, design team fees, risk and contingency, and management equipment service.</p> <p>I have already made myself extremely clear in this regard; the Government and I, and all those involved in this project, were and remain deeply unhappy at the cost escalation of this project over what was originally committed to by the Government.  On 18 December, at the same time as the Government approved the construction investment to allow phase B of the hospital to be instructed, the Government also approved the commissioning of an independent review of the escalation in cost.  As the House will know, this independent comprehensive review process is under way and will examine the contributory factors and associated responsibilities so that any potential weaknesses are identified and comprehensively and speedily resolved in the interests of the successful completion of the project and the effective management of public funds. The terms of reference also require the review to develop recommendations which may identify any areas of potential cost savings or reductions which are consistent with the applicable contractual undertakings and the delivery of the project.  It is also required to address major residual risks, control and oversight issues and bring greater oversight of performance and value for money.  The report from this review process is expected to be completed by the end of March.</p> <p>This debate, however, would not be complete without a reminder of the progress made on this project and the game-changer it represents in the delivery of services for children.  It is important that we do not forget the purpose of this project, which is to deliver transformational change in the delivery of healthcare for children in Ireland.  I have said many times before, and will reiterate here again today, that the children and young people of Ireland have been waiting far too long for a modern healthcare facility.  This new children&rsquo;s hospital project will transform the delivery of children&rsquo;s healthcare.  The capital investment will be underpinned and complemented by a new model of care for the delivery of services to children.  We will be replacing outdated hospital buildings with modern and appropriate infrastructure, including fit-for-purpose, single en suite rooms for every child designed to best serve the needs of our children, of their families and of the staff who care for them.  There are currently 14 theatres, including one cath lab, in the three existing hospitals, which has to be supplemented by outsourcing procedures to other hospitals.  This limits our ability to tackle the long waiting times for surgeries for our children.  In our new hospital there will be 22 theatres, including two cath labs, which will have a profoundly positive impact on activity levels and on theatre waiting times for children.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Harris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2338"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2338&amp;amp;pid=SimonHarris&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The equipment at the new children's hospital will include five MRI machines, with space for two more, three CT scanners, 30 ultrasound machines and seven X-ray rooms, all of which will be state of the art.  As part of the project, new outpatient and urgent care centres will also be provided at Connolly and Tallaght hospitals.  These centres will expand outpatient and urgent care capacity and provide services in modern facilities.  Overall, the three new sites will significantly increase capacity across all types of care, including increases of 16% in inpatient capacity, 7% in emergency department attendances, 26% in day case capacity and 47% in outpatient capacity.  These are significant figures indicating the scope of improvement that children and their parents will experience.</p><p>Commentary relating to the new hospital sometimes seems to be about a project that only exists on paper and has not yet commenced.  I invite Members to go down to the St. James's site or to Connolly hospital and see that this is certainly not the case.  Considerable work has been undertaken on the project since April 2017.  Phase B works are under way at the St. James's site.  Works at Connolly hospital are on target for practical completion of the building this year, with the opening scheduled for this summer.  The outpatient and urgent care centre at Connolly will start delivering improvements to healthcare for children this year, under the responsibility of Children's Health Ireland.</p><p>Works at Tallaght are under way, with a target handover date of July 2020.  The establishment of Children's Health Ireland by legislation passed by this House at the end of last year was a major milestone in this project and will further assist the ongoing operational integration of the three hospitals in advance of the opening of the new children's hospital and outpatient and urgent care centres.  The hospital will have a leadership role nationally in the implementation of the national model of care for paediatrics and neonatology, working closely with paediatric service providers in other hospitals across the country, in the primary care service and in the community.</p><p>We have an unprecedented opportunity to deliver a considerably positive change in healthcare for Ireland's children and young people.  While we must, and will, learn from the issues that have arisen in the project thus far, the priority is and continues to be delivering on the vision to improve health services for the children and young people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#U00200"><p>The Minister will be called to reply no later than 2.24 p.m.  Group spokesperson have eight minutes each and may share time, with the agreement of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#U00300"><p>I thank the Minister for coming to the House.  He has given us a great run down of what exactly we will get in the hospital, and we are grateful for that.  While we do not dispute the need for the hospital, we dispute the cost management associated with the rolling out of the project.  This is where the grievance lies.  The Government found out the project was &euro;450 million in the red in November.  In February 2017, I divided this House and called on the Minister to come in to discuss cost overruns after comments made by Mr. Tony O Brien at a meeting of a health committee.  At that time, the Minister sent in Minister of State, Deputy Catherine Byrne, who said the cost overrun was just 5%, which we now know was untrue.</p><p>The Minister was told of an overrun of &euro;191 million in August of last year and of another &euro;200 million that was disputed.  A month later, it was learned through a parliamentary question that the budget for the project was on track.  The Minister told members of my party that the Government overrun was on track.  In December 2018, Mazars pointed to a lack of early warning systems.  It materialised that costs were ballooning and issues with estimating costs accurately had been evident from the very start.  It is clear that structures needed to be implemented to ensure individuals were held accountable.</p><p>The estimated cost of the new hospital on the campus of St. James's has risen from the original cost, &euro;450 million, to in excess of &euro;1 billion.  A significant proportion of the &euro;450 million increase, which was undisclosed during Fine Gael&ndash;Fianna F&aacute;il budget negotiations, can be traced back to this time, including some &euro;100 million in omissions and an underestimation of material costs.  The preliminary investigations by Mazars, delivered last December, determined that a 56% increase in construction costs led to the cost per square metre of the new hospital jumping from &euro;3,600 to &euro;5,600.  It is clear that construction inflation was an issue.  It seems not to have been taken into consideration at all by the board.  The report examined a number of issues, including the cost increases and the reporting of those increases.  Among these issues was the fact that the final design added some &euro;94 million in cost to the original budget due to the apparent understatement of the quality and quantity of materials needed.</p><p>The National Paediatric Hospital Development Board has seen four chairman come and go along the way.  It was reported on 6 February in <i>The Irish Times</i>that the children's hospital project steering group, the body overseeing the &euro;1 billion project, consistently flagged issues related to capital costs as far back as October 2017.  To say this is a saga is an understatement but now the project is having serious knock-on effects in other areas.  Yesterday, the HIQA report into fostering services, which the Minister's Department oversees, showed that Dublin South-Central alone has been greatly affected and that there has been a regression in care for minors in foster care.  There is a serious lack of oversight.  We have been promised primary care centres in Drimnagh and elsewhere but they have not materialised.  It seems this is because the cost overrun at the hospital is taking funds from projects run by the Department and from other Government funds.  The total in funds to be paid out in SUSI grants will drop by more than &euro;2 million in 2019.  The Minister for Education and Skills, Deputy McHugh, has proposed a cut to third level funding in the region of &euro;15.5 million from the education budget.  An analysis published by the Parliamentary Budget Office, PBO, clearly indicates the Government is deprioritising education.</p><p>This mismanagement by the Department of Health is having a serious knock-on effect on other Departments, and we are seeing deprioritisation of projects within the Department of Education and Skills and, more seriously, the Department of Health itself, particularly in regard to primary health care centres promised in 2011 by the Fine Gael&ndash;Labour Government.  The latter have not been delivered.  One of the excuses we are given is the cost overrun at the children's hospital.</p><p>Not only has the cost of the hospital increased by &euro;450 million but we do not know at this stage what the exact final cost will be.  We are aware that residents living near the hospital have brought actions against the hospital because of subsidence at their homes.  This is before the courts and we do not know what the court actions will cost.  The Department will have to pay these costs to compensate the residents.  I have made inquiries and have been told by the Department that the matter is <i>sub judice</i>.  Nothing is being done, therefore, to help the residents.  The Minister has invited us to see the hospital site but I invite him to go to Clancourt and see the destruction caused to many residents' homes owing to subsidence.</p><p>The project is worthwhile and it is important that it proceeds but the cost overruns and management not only of this capital project but also of many others around the country have to be considered.  Anyone who builds an extension, even on a small scale, is conscious of costs overrunning and the cost of bricklayers and electricians.  It is something we all keep an eye on to ensure projects proceed according to plan.  If one does not have the money, one cannot go ahead with a project.  There is basic mismanagement in the case of the children's hospital.  Taxpayers are disappointed the money has been spent without any proper consideration as to what it is being spent on and without any departmental foresight.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#U00400"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire.  It took a while to get here.  As my colleague said, we have been asking for him-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#U00500"><p>I am here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#U00600"><p>-----to star in the Seanad regarding the national children's hospital for several weeks now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#U00700"><p>Years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#U00800"><p>Not quite years.</p> <p>Where does one start?  The scenarios presented to us regarding ever-increasing costs, or the runaway train, are not so much fairytale-like as nightmarish.  The public have found them incredible.  The train has no driver.  The Minister is the driver but seems to have taken the day off sick because the train keeps going.  I hope the brakes have now been applied and that some prudence has been exercised to address the waste of public money.  I am not saying the children's hospital itself is a waste.  The mothers, fathers and children of Ireland need it but do not need the waste arising from the ever-increasing costs, which should have been capped at the beginning.  The public purse is being robbed time and again.  Perhaps we are used to it but this time the public was just gobsmacked by the extent of the increase.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I also juxtapose the optics of a few weeks ago of nurses on the picket line at St. James's demanding something that would have cost perhaps &euro;260 million and standing under the shadow the foundations of the children's hospital that we believed then would cost at least over &euro;1 billion, if not, as many say, over &euro;2 billion.  That was not lost on the people.  They were able to do the maths when they looked at those images.</p><p>I refer to the conflicting timelines, unanswered questions, and who knew what and when.  It is incredibly important for this to be certain for accountability.  It was simply not credible that the Minister did not discuss the catastrophic overrun with his Cabinet colleagues earlier than November last given that in May the joint construction and finance subcommittee noted that the capital programme for the project would have to be submitted before mid-September to ensure funding prior to budget.  If that was the case, they would have known the overrun much earlier.  However, it did not happen.  The explanations thus far are unsatisfactory.  In simple terms, the Minister and the HSE still need to explain why this occurred.</p><p>There is loads going on with this hospital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#V00200"><p>It is being built.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#V00300"><p>It is my turn to speak.  I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#V00400"><p>I will adjudicate on that.  Senator Devine, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#V00500"><p>I thank the Acting Chairman.  I do not know where to start.  I have lots of notes and I will just to through them quickly.</p> <p>The mental health services in the hospital will be an improvement on what we have throughout the country, given that Linn Dara day patient services remain closed and I am still not getting answers on that.  I acknowledge this is a hospital and the Minister is concentrating on inpatient services, especially mental health services, and the eating disorders which are prevalent and for which medicines have to be imported.  In terms of Brexit, what will happen seeing as this hospital will not be operational for another few years?</p> <p>While the emphasis of a hospital is on inpatient services, what community services will it offer to day patients or children attending for outpatient services?  Home is the best place for children, in particular, children with mental health needs.  How will we encourage community day care and what will the hospital offer on a national level apart from inpatient services in those instances?</p> <p>I keep asking about the future of the Temple Street and Crumlin sites.  Rumours abound about land being sold off.  In particular, the deed for Our Lady's Children's Hospital stipulates the need for part of the site to retained for medical purposes.  If the Minister could get me that deed to have a look at it, I would be grateful.  We need to know the position.  It is owned by the people.  I would like to see what clauses the deed contains if the hospital, or part of it, was up for sale.</p> <p>I refer to the impact that this overrun will have, as did Senator Ardagh.  She and I are from the same area.  My street is right underneath the children's hospital.  I have put up with much inconvenience but I will go into that later.  On the re-profiling, who dreamt that word up?  It is a great word, and it is very American.  Basically, it is the diluted way of saying that it will not happen.  Whoever came up with it should get a pat on the back.  In the use of language, Trump might be proud of us.</p> <p>This is a local issue, in particular, for me and my neighbours and the surrounding areas off the South Circular Road in Kilmainham, Ceannt Fort, Mount Brown.  I refer to the significant impact that this has had on these areas.  Dublin City Council has now designated all our areas for 24-7 parking much to the disquiet of some residents who did not vote for it.  There is a push to commercialise our historic neighbourhoods in that area.  It is part of the inner city and it is obviously in high demand as the city grows.  However, we have not protected residents in that area.  We have taken away much of what there was previously.  There is BAM, St. James's Hospital and the development board of the children's hospital and nobody will answer a question.  They send one from Billy to Jack and nobody seems to take responsibility.  I would be grateful if the Minister could have a little word with them, in particular, BAM, which apparently is a considerate contractor and is on the considerate contractors' scheme.  If the Minister talks to anybody in the vicinity of the hospital, he will find that it is not considered to be a considerate contractor.  Traffic management is chaotic and dangerous.  I refer to the rat infestation and the subsidence of houses which has resulted in a legal wrangle for their owners with no response yet.  It has taken two years so far.  In 2015, the board was told about the unsuitability of the black soil at Ceannt Fort both by myself and residents.  Engineers 100 years ago pointed out on a map prior to the estate being built that this land was not suitable for building.  We were told not to worry that it was black soil but 100 years ago, without the technology we have today, engineers were able to point that out.  However, that was ignored in the rush to get this hospital built.  It was decided to ride roughshod over any objections at the time and to placate us in the hope that we would go away.  The residents will not go away.  However, I would like the Minister intervene and ask BAM to be more considerate and address the needs and questions of the local residents.</p> <p>There is much more to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#V00600"><p>There is not.  The Senator has no time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#V00700"><p>I am out of time.  This national children's hospital is badly needed and it is a shame that it is being mismanaged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#V00800"><p>I thank the Minister.  My apologies for being slightly late and for not being here when he arrived.</p> <p>It is important to outline what the children's hospital will contain because some are giving the impression that it will have only 473 beds.  As I understand it, there will be 380 inpatient beds and 60  acute beds.  This must be considered from the overall context of the young population we have in this country.  More than 1.25 million people are aged under 18 years and a state-of-the-art facility is needed to look after that population.  The health, both physical and mental, of the vast majority of that population will be perfect but some people will run into difficulties.  Even from the day they are born, some will have healthcare problems and it must be ensured the best system is in place to look after them from start to finish.</p> <p>A number of hospitals currently deal with paediatrics.  There has been a long process.  It is interesting that we have gone through 22 Ministers for Health since this hospital was first talked about.  Instead of talking about it, the Government is building it.  That is the difference.  We will have a hospital which will have more than 6,150 rooms, run 140 clinics at any one time, and will have 380 inpatient beds, 93 of which will be for day care.  It will also have 53 rooms for parents who want to stay overnight.  One must bear in mind that the 60 acute beds will be for children whom staff will not know, at 11 p.m. or midnight, whether they will come through by 8 a.m.  It is important, therefore, as well that parents are looked after because they play an important part in making sure that the best care is provided for these children.</p> <p>There have been delays but the Government had a choice to make.  An Bord Plean&aacute;la turned down the planning permission for the Mater site in February 2012.  On the new planning permission, the Government had to go back to the design stage and go through the planning process.  The new planning permission was granted by An Bord Plean&aacute;la in April 2016.  That is less than three years ago.  Ministers have got on with doing the job of getting in the tenders and going through and getting the work done to excavate the site, lay the foundations and building, most importantly, rather than putting it back for further consideration.</p> <p>Yesterday I was on a conference call with people who are developing a children's hospital in Ontario in Canada.  I had been in touch with the Canadian embassy and officials gave me the contact names.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In fairness to the people in Canada, they rang me at a set time yesterday and I spoke to three people.  As much as $800 million Canadian dollars has been raised for the children's hospital project there.  The total cost of the project is $3.7 billion Canadian dollars, which includes the building of an office complex and the children's hospital.  The target is to raise $1.3 billion Canadian dollars and I understand the state will provide about $2 billion Canadian dollars for the project.</p><p>Interestingly, the people with whom I spoke yesterday advised me that in Toronto building inflation has increased by 1% each month over the past 15 months and they expect it to continue to rise over the next number of years as the project proceeds.  They must first build new office accommodation for more than 3,000 staff in the form of a 22-storey building, which will be funded by their own resources.  It is intended to decant all of the existing administration staff into the new office building, after which a major demolition job will be required before the children's hospital can be started.  Another interesting point is that they must provide all of the funding for the equipment that will be go into the hospital.  I am not saying we should go down that road but when people compare and claim various projects were done for X number of euro or pounds, they have obviously not considered the real issue.</p><p>The children's hospital in Manchester, which I understand has 370 beds, cost &pound;504 million or between &euro;650 million or &euro;660 million.  It started in 2004 and took five years to build.  When we make comparisons, let us do so properly.  Let us consider the national children's hospital project on the basis that we are providing a state-of-the-art facility alongside an existing adult hospital, which will have more than 1,020 beds and key expertise for adult care across a range of areas, including a burns unit.  These experts will also be available should the need arise in terms of children facing major health issues.  That is why the co-location with St. James's is so important and the project needs to be fully endorsed as the best way forward for healthcare in this country.</p><p>We can talk all we like about a lack of full transparency.  I am a member of the Joint Committee on Health and every document and set of minutes that I have sought has been produced.  People were concerned and expressed concerns about the way things had changed but we had a choice.  Planning applications do not include a definitive and detailed description of each and every room.  The planning permission was for the basic structure, the supply of all the services, emergency exits and so forth but the application did not feature the fine details of each and every room.  The board had a choice, which it was advised of, to wait 12 months to have the fine detail worked out and then invite tenders, or it could invite tenders and get on with the project, which is what it did.  That was the right decision because we are now between a year and 18 months ahead of schedule in dealing with the project.  We can park the issue, decide not to go ahead and have another debate but that would mean going through another five Ministers for Health before the hospital is finally built.  Our challenge and job is to go ahead and get the project built.  We are accountable in terms of cost and taxpayers are entitled to know exactly how much everything costs.  That information has been provided.  It is important that people study the documents that have been published and made available.  We should also wait for PricewaterhouseCoopers to produce its report and if issues arise, we need to deal with them.</p><p>I thank the Minister for being here to deal with this matter today. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#W00200"><p>The Minister may see this debate as an opportunity to update the Seanad on the "new children's hospital", to use his words.  I see this debate as an opportunity to ask him certain questions that he has not satisfactorily answered.  This comes down to two core issues.  The first issue, which I asked him about at a meeting of the Joint Committee on Health, is whether the massive cost overrun associated with this hospital is associated with the complexity of the St. James's site, as opposed to building this hospital on a greenfield site.  The answer to that question is obvious and the political system has been at fault for not holding the Minister to that question.</p> <p>The second issue is related.  The Minister and Government have made much of the ultimate desirability of the children's hospital somehow justifying and excusing all errors along the way.  The issue, however, is whether the Minister is failing to build the hospital that is needed to guarantee, inasmuch as is possible, children's health and welfare in future, in particular having regard to the inability to co-locate a maternity hospital at this site.  In other words, in addition to the insult to the taxpayer caused by the appalling management of public funds that has occurred, the Minister is adding the future injury to children's health and safety, as many people believe, including eminent medical people associated with the Connolly for Kids project.  I am astounded at how little the media and the main Opposition parties have attended to that fundamental question of children's welfare in addition to the question of the spend.  The reason is that there has been a failure of the imagination to consider whether even now the Government should withdraw from this location as being the ideal location for the hospital</p> <p>In recent weeks, we have been drip-fed news of construction delays, huge cost overruns and suggestions that bidders for projects are trying to extract maximum profit from the taxpayer.  Above all, we have seen a total lack of accountability and contempt for any notion of democratic accountability of the Government to the elected Members of the Oireachtas.  We have been here before.  It happened before during the planning stage of the original site at the Mater Hospital.  Before that, the same pattern emerged during a wide range of public projects from the Dublin Port tunnel to the building of the motorway network.  The scale of the proposed cost overruns for the children&rsquo;s hospital is almost difficult to believe, the original tender having been &euro;636 million.  We have had a gradual attempt to deflect the blame for this catastrophe from the Minister and his Department.  We had a remarkable statement from Mr. Robert Watt, Secretary General of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, reported today that the State will no longer commit to projects until the design and price are clear.  Is that not an absolutely scandalous statement?  Does it not reflect on the shambolic management of public finances and projects that have gone on here?</p> <p>Initially, the blame was directed at the board of the hospital project and its chairman resigned.  Next up, were the bidders for the project who were accused by Taoiseach of "low-balling" their tenders.  Last weekend, it emerged that the Government intends to shift the blame yet again by pointing the finger at consultants who made the initial examination of the St. James's site.  All I see here is skilful public relations, a sea of headlines and scrum of recriminations that allow the Government to avoid the fundamental question at the heart of this issue, namely, whether it was correct to choose the St. James's&rsquo; site in the first place when other greenfield sites were on offer.  The Minister's fingers are on this, as are those of the Taoiseach and Senator Reilly.  What I hear now is political ass-covering by Government and its supporters in government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#W00300"><p>That is unparliamentary language.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#W00400"><p>I do not hear fundamental concern for the best option, having regard to children's welfare.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#W00500"><p>I am sorry for interrupting but the Senator may wish to rephrase his previous remark about a certain part of the body.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#W00600"><p>As soon as I think of a better phrase, I will offer it to the House.   The question strikes at the heart of the Government in view of the political damage caused by the abandonment of the previous Mater site.  Surely any examination of the cost overruns must address whether the choice of the St. James's site is part of what caused the problem.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2250&amp;amp;pid=RonanMullen&amp;amp;year=2019&amp;amp;month=03&amp;amp;day=07"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is certainly possible, if not likely, that the complexity of building the hospital in a congested city centre location, rather than on a greenfield site, is what has caused the escalating costs.  The Minister was unable to deal with that question satisfactorily when I asked him in the Joint Committee on Health.  The Minister's defence of the choice of site at this point is that there can be no further delays to the project and that the new children&rsquo;s hospital must be co-located with an adult teaching hospital.  He will know that I do not rate him as a protector of children anyway in view of what happened in relation to abortion legislation and the endangering of children's lives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X00200"><p>The people made their decision.  That is an unfortunate remark and it should be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X00300"><p>Senator Humphreys, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X00400"><p>The remark should be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X00500"><p>One moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X00600"><p>The Senator is right, it should be withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X00700"><p>It is my job to interpret what should or should not be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X00800"><p>It is a total slander.  I am no fan of the Minister but I would not like to see people being slandered in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X00900"><p>I wish to make it clear that Senator Mullen is making a political charge in his contribution.  He is entitled to do that.  If people want to take issue with it, and they have yet to speak, they may do so when they speak.  The Minister will have an opportunity to do so in his closing remarks, if he wishes.  Senator Mullen has a minute remaining.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01000"><p>I think I am entitled, in view of interruptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01100"><p>That time is including the interruptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01200"><p>I am drawing a line between what I regard as the Minister's position on one issue and the cynical dressing up of Government choices as being about protecting the best interests of children in this case, when many experts, people at the coalface of children's medicine, are tearing their hair out at the choice this Government has made.  The most cynical thing of all, and I have heard the Government and its supporters go on about it, is the claim that the co-location of the children's hospital with an adult teaching hospital somehow meets the needs involved when the experts are saying quite clearly that where co-location is desirable is the co-location of a maternity hospital with a children's hospital or perhaps a maternity hospital with an adult hospital.  The third matter, and well down the list, is the argument about the co-location of a children's hospital with an adult hospital.  The Government and the Minister for Health have spun mercilessly on that particular point which is an indictment of the Minister's stewardship.  I am not a medical person, no more than the Minister is not one, but I quote Professor Chris Fitzpatrick who said "with neither money nor space, plans for a tri-located maternity hospital are now a pie-in-the-sky fantasy."  That would be all right if it was not so important.  However, according to the 2012 O'Reilly expert group, if we wish to improve the clinical outcome for sick children, the most critical adjacency for the national children's hospital is with a tertiary maternity hospital where high-risk babies can be delivered.  The Minister has heard this many times because he heard from the Connolly for Kids people.  They briefed every single member of the Government extensively on the crucial importance of the issues that were at play here yet the Government went its own way.  It did so, I think, because of political cowardice because it was not, in the end, primarily motivated by welfare of children.  It was motivated by the idea that we could not countenance backing out of the wrong choice yet again, no doubt because of the attitude that would have been taken by other political groups.  Frankly, the Minister's job is to govern in the best interest of the children and families concerned.  Even now, the Minster is showing a failure to unthink the unthinkable.  The Government's argument that it could not delay any longer for the sake of the children of Ireland holds no water when medical experts, people who care and who know about caring for children, say even now it should be revisited.  Yes, there would be-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01300"><p>Thank you, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01400"><p>-----a significant financial cost but the Government has already exposed us to that anyway.  I put my questions and I stand over my points.</p> <p>My core questions were whether the financial overrun is connected with the complexity of the site the Government chose, whether in persisting with the site it chose, it is endangering children's welfare into the future, as many medical experts claim, and whether that is not the ultimate indictment of the Minister and the Government's handling of these issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01500"><p>I call Senator Humphreys who has eight minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01600"><p>The national children's hospital is a very important point of discussion and we should put children first.  Yes, it should be a game-changer in relation to care for children.  We have not provided good facilities for children.  Yes, it should be a state-of-the-art facility and I look forward to seeing it.  It must move on as quickly as possible.  Yes, there should be accommodation for parents to stay with sick children and support them during their time there and there should be the best quality theatres open on a 24-7 basis to ensure we can guarantee the proper care of our children, which has not happened in the past.</p> <p>However, the cost overrun has led to a serious loss of faith among the public, not only of the Government's capability but also that of the Civil Service, to deliver a hospital on time and within budget.  This is part of the frustration because so many capital projects are happening and the public no longer has faith that they will be delivered on time and within budget.  We need to rebuild that faith and trust among the people, and we need to do so quickly.</p> <p>I have two questions for the Minister.  I hope the National Maternity Hospital which is being co-located in Elm Park will be delivered on time and within budget.  Will the Minister update the House on it?  He may not be able to do so but I would appreciate it if he could update me on the National Maternity Hospital at a later stage as I place that on a par in terms of the delivery of a good and proper service.  Will the Minister outline also the mechanisms that have been put in place in relation to projects of this size?  There needs to be a level of expectation in respect of costs and delivery times so that people can have faith that projects such as the National Maternity Hospital and the national children's hospital will be delivered within budget?  This morning I questioned the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, on bus corridors, the metro line and whether we were getting proper estimates for costs.  He said the National Transport Authority reports to the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform on a fortnightly basis.  Do the same mechanisms apply to the HSE to ensure that if there are overruns, they are identified early on so that corrections may be made?  We must be honest with the citizens because they demand these services but want them at a reasonable cost.</p> <p>I have no intention of grandstanding and calling for the national children's hospital to be moved or whatever the populist opinion is now.  We need to get on and build the national children's hospital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01700"><p>It is not grandstanding, it is medical experts-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01800"><p>We need to get on and build-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X01900"><p>Senator Humphreys, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02000"><p>It is fine.  I do not find the interruptions at all unhelpful.  If one looks at the track record, it has been proved on many occasions that others are a lot more in tune with the public than the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02100"><p>It is my job to ensure the Senator is not interrupted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02200"><p>I am speaking through the Chair and I accept  I am eating into my own time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02300"><p>I am only returning the compliment to Senator Humphreys.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02400"><p>I gave the Senator no compliments, so he should not take it that way.  I think he slandered the Minister in relation to the health of children.  I do not think the Minister goes out to purposely damage any children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02500"><p>The Senator does not care about the children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02600"><p>Senator, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02700"><p>I am quite happy with my record on repealing the eighth amendment and I will take no nonsense from Senator Mullen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02800"><p>The Senator has no credibility on children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X02900"><p>Let us get on and build a state-of-the-art facility for children.  Let us do so quickly and make sure the care of our children is the best in the world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X03000"><p>We cannot do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X03100"><p>Senator, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X03200"><p>Let us make sure we have a National Maternity Hospital we can be proud of and that we build it as soon as possible.  I hope I kept within my time, Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#X03300"><p>The Senator certainly did and I thank him.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00100"><p>I thank all the Senators who made contributions to the debate today.  I have listened carefully to the views and concerns, many of which I share.  What I have heard from most speakers is two things: will we please get on and build the hospital, which we are going to do, and will we please make sure, in the building of the hospital, that we get value for the taxpayer and that lessons are learned in regard to other capital projects.  I heard a number of local but legitimate and important concerns for the community raised by Senators Devine and Ardagh, and I will certainly follow up in regard to those matters and will revert directly to both Senators.  However, I hear a general agreement from most that the children of Ireland and their families deserve this modern hospital and have been waiting too long.</p> <p>A very important point that I made in my opening contribution is that this is now under way.  I will answer Senator Mullen's questions shortly but when I hear debates about where it should be, I find it odd at this stage because the hospital is under way, &euro;200 million has already been spent and the foundations are well in place.  Anyone visiting or driving by the St. James's site who looks down will see building well under way.  The Connolly part of the hospital is actually due to open this year, will start serving children this year and will see outpatient appointments take place this year, and the X-ray facilities, for example, were delivered to the hospital in recent weeks.</p> <p>With regard to Senator Mullen's specific questions, I thought I had dealt with this issue at the health committee but perhaps not to his satisfaction.  When we deal with the cost overrun, it is important to point out that the cost overrun relates to a decision to build on the St. James's site and the approval for that in April 2017, and the cost of the St. James's site now.  It is not a comparison with the building of another site.  The amount the Government budgeted, which was &euro;983 million in April 2017, was for the St. James's site and the current cost projection is also for the St. James's site.  The Senator asked would it have been cheaper to build it on another site but I think that misses a number of points.  It misses the fact that building on a greenfield site would not have seen the benefits of not just bilocation but of trilocation.  A point on which I agree with Senator Mullen, and I am sure we all agree, is that we need a maternity site located there as well.  It is the plan for the St. James's site to have the St. James's adult acute teaching hospital, which is there now, serving our population, and to have the new national children's hospital and the Coombe Hospital relocated to that site.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00200"><p>That is pie in the sky.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00300"><p>The Senator may call it pie in the sky.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00400"><p>Professor Chris Fitzpatrick calls it pie in the sky and he knows more about it than the Minister and I do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00500"><p>The Senator may call it pie in the sky but let the record show those comments in due course.  That is the intention and has been the intention.</p> <p>With regard to the site, the Senator talked about accountability and standing over the decision.  I did not pick the site and I was not a member of the Government when the site was picked, but I fully support it.  It was a decision taken after great scrutiny and great debate following consideration of the Mater site and the &euro;40 million wasted there.  It was democratically tested in the Houses of the Oireachtas.  When I was not long Minister, and before construction had started, some Independent colleagues of the Senator's, perhaps, tabled a Private Members' motion in the other House asking that the location be changed.  The D&aacute;il, democratically elected by the popular vote of the people, and a Chamber of these Houses, voted to reject that motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00600"><p>I agree.  They are all in this together.  That is why they are getting away so lightly.  The parties cannot point a finger at the Minister without pointing it at themselves as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00700"><p>It is a conspiracy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00800"><p>Order, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y00900"><p>The Senator talked about democratic accountability.  Deputies in the D&aacute;il had an opportunity to vote before construction started, thanks to the Independent Deputies who tabled the motion, and that House spoke very clearly in that regard.</p> <p>There is a benefit, which the Senator somewhat accepted, of being co-located with an adult teaching hospital.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01000"><p>A benefit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01100"><p>Let me tell the Senator what the benefit is first.  I have not slandered the Senator or used unparliamentary language in my contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01200"><p>I did not slander the Minister either, by the way.  He has an opinion with which I disagree, as many people do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01300"><p>And more people do not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01400"><p>The spokespersons from each group had an opportunity to make their contributions and the Minister is now being given an opportunity to respond, without interruption.  This has to end within the next four minutes.  In fairness, if we want questions answered, we need to please give the Minister the opportunity to answer them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01500"><p>I want to do that.  I want to make a point about the children in our paediatric hospitals today, for example, teenagers who travel to hospitals like St. James's for their cancer treatment.  As many of us will know from personal experiences and political experiences concerning our constituents, teenagers of 17 or 18 might not want to go to adult services and the idea of being co-located benefits a number of specialties, including cancer treatment for our teenagers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01600"><p>Does the Minister accept there is much less benefit, given the lack of-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01700"><p>Senator Mullen, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01800"><p>For him to stress that, when medical experts are pointing out how relatively-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y01900"><p>What medical experts are we talking about?  The medical institutions came down in favour of St. James's.  Go read the reports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y02000"><p>Order.  I am not allowing this to descend into a cross-examination of the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y02100"><p>It is incorrect information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y02200"><p>The Senators had the opportunity to make their contributions.  They have asked their questions.  Please give the Minister an opportunity, in the limited time that remains, to answer them.  That is if they want them answered.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1251" speakername="Simon Harris" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2019030700002#Y02300"><p>Senator Humphreys makes a very fair point that, clearly, lessons need to be learned, and that is 100% correct.  I am pleased to inform him and the Seanad that, when we were looking at this issue recently, the Minister, Deputy Donohoe, brought forward a number of sensible, constructive proposals in regard to the approval process and the oversight process, not, as the Senator rightly said, just for this project but also for all large capital projects.  Thankfully, we are back in a period when we will be spending a lot of capital, and we need to see that spent on delivering projects and minimising overruns.  I agree with him on that.</p> <p>Senator Humphreys asked about the National Maternity Hospital.  I will write to him to reply but let me tell him this much now.  I was able, just before Christmas, to inform the Government that enough progress had been made on a number of important issues in regard to governance and ownership that I could advise the Government that we should proceed with the new pharmacy building and the car park at St. Vincent's.  That approval has been given and those works are, therefore, under way.  As the Senator knows, given he has taken a very active interest in this project, the planning permission is in place.  I hope we will be able to go to tender later this year, around the summer, but that is subject to the finalisation of some agreements.  Obviously, the final costs of the project will not be known until the tender is in, so I do not wish to second-guess that.  I will certainly keep the Senator informed on this matter.</p> <p>I do not feel I need to convince Senators of this.  There is huge benefit in regard to this hospital.  We are not just going to build one hospital but a hospital with a centre at Connolly and another at Tallaght.  This is not about a Dublin hospital; it is going to transform the model of care for all of our kids.  We will go from 14 theatres to 22 theatres, from two MRIs to five MRIs, with room for more, and there will be an increase in the number of CAT scan machines.  This will have a dramatic effect on waiting times for our kids.  Recruitment is actively under way for these facilities and a huge body of work has already taken place that we have not even had a chance to discuss.  At the end of last year, these Houses passed the Children's Health Bill, where we took Crumlin Children's Hospital, Temple Street Children's Hospital and the paediatric part of Tallaght Hospital and brought them together as a new statutory entity to deliver for children's healthcare in Ireland.  That is now the entity.  Even though we have three sites at Crumlin, Temple Street and Tallaght, we have one body, Children's Health Ireland, delivering healthcare for children across the country, which is real progress.</p> <p>I look forward to the Connolly facility opening later this year, the Tallaght facility opening next year and the St. James's facility opening in 2023.  I look forward to the lessons of the PwC report being learned by all, as Senator Colm Burke said, and being published so we can scrutinise them in these Houses and at committees, and to keeping the Seanad informed as we deliver this transformational project.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2019-03-07a.225" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.30 p.m. until 12 noon on Tuesday, 12 March 2019.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>