<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Maria Byrne that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to outline any incentives he proposes to introduce to encourage tourists to use all regional airports and hotels in light of the shortage of hotel beds in the Dublin area and the high cost currently in obtaining a hotel room with 90% of all tourists now  coming through Dublin Airport.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Jennifer Murnane O&rsquo;Connor of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on the current status of the Holy Angels Day Care Centre in Carlow town.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Colette Kelleher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to outline how the &euro;22 million provided under the national dementia strategy for intensive home care packages has been spent, to comment on what supports will be provided in budget 2017 to allow people with dementia to remain living in their own homes, and to clarify how his Department intends to address the need for multi-annual, ring-fenced funding for home care supports for people with dementia and for legislation creating a statutory right to home care.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Catherine Ardagh of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update in relation to the progress of a primary care centre in the Crumlin-Drimnagh area and to ask the Minister what stage of development the primary care centre is at.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine  of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to respond to the grave concerns on the proposed 50% cut of night nursing staff at Cloverhill Remand Prison.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to state if he approved the landing or transit through Irish airspace of certain US military aircraft and if so why given that the presence of these aircraft, belonging to a belligerent state, in or over Irish territory is a clear breach of Ireland's international law obligations as a neutral state.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerard Craughwell of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Defence to explain why the decision of the Defence Forces Ombudsman on the redress of wrongs in relation to Lieutenant Colonel John Hamill have not yet been implemented.  </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to establish a forum involving all interest groups in the provision of elderly care, including the HSE, the Department of Health, Nursing Homes Ireland, general practitioners, GPs and geriatricians.  </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Ivana Bacik of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to inform the House when she proposes to implement the recommendation of the copyright review committee in its report, Modernising Copyright, published October 2013, concerning the extension of the small claims procedure in the District Court to include intellectual property claims up to the value of  &euro;15,000, as provided for within the draft statutory instrument prepared by the committee.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Grace O&rsquo;Sullivan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to urgently address the impact large-scale seaweed harvesting will have on delicate coastal kelp ecosystems and small-scale local harvesting.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Ged Nash of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to discuss the Government's response to the UK referendum vote to leave the European Union and the implications for jobs, businesses and communities in the Border counties.</blockquote><p>I regard the matters raised by Senators Byrne, Murnane O'Connor, Kelleher, Ardagh, Devine, Gavan, Craughwell, Colm Burke, Bacik and Grace O&rsquo;Sullivan as suitable for discussion.  I have selected the matters raised by Senators Byrne, Murnane O&rsquo;Connor, Kelleher and Ardagh and they will be taken now.  Senators Devine, Gavan, Craughwell, Colm Burke, Bacik and Grace O&rsquo;Sullivan may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.<br/><br/>I regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Nash on the grounds that the matter anticipates statements on the UK referendum result and is more suitable for discussion as a substantive motion.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800003#B00350">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800003#B00400">Regional Airports</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800003#B00500"><p>I am delighted to see that there has been a substantial increase in tourism over recent years.  In 2015, 29.8 million passengers passed through Irish airports.  Of these, more than 24 million or 83.8% of the total passed through Dublin.  Cork handled 6.9% and Shannon 5.6% while the remaining airports were responsible for only 3.7%.  Passenger numbers to Cork continue to fall annually.  The Shannon Airport Authority has worked very hard to increase throughput of 1.68 million in 2015 but this is far from the 2.95 million it handled in 2008.  This is neither desirable nor sustainable and is certainly very far from the kind of regional development we need.</p>  <p>In 2015, the number of overseas visitors reached 8 million, an increase of more than 14% on the previous year and in February and March 2016, there was a 16% increase on the corresponding period last year.  In 2015, tourists spent &euro;4.1 billion with the airlines and ferry companies earned &euro;1.3 billion, a huge boost to the national economy.  The Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport believes that the tourism industry is directly responsible for providing 205,000 jobs in Ireland, with the accommodation and food sector providing 137,000 of these.  The challenge we face is to manage and grow this very valuable resource.  Dublin Airport is operating at or beyond full capacity while the regional airports are capable of handling much greater numbers than they do now.  The chairman of the International Airlines Group, IAG, Willie Walsh, has aired his concerns about bottlenecks in Dublin.  He believes this could have a negative impact on future expansion by IAG at the airport.</p> <p>I am aware of the Dublin Airport Authority plan to invest &euro;320 million in constructing a second runway, but it will not be operational until 2020 at the earliest.  Difficulties with the transport infrastructure between the airport and the city centre still need to be addressed.</p> <p>Dublin hotels had a room occupancy rate of 82% in 2015 - much higher than the rest of the country.  In Limerick, which has the lowest average room rate in the country, the occupancy rate was 68.3%.  We all know how difficult it can be to get hotel accommodation in Dublin for most of the year.  In addition, average room rates in the capital have increased from &euro;77 in 2010 to &euro;111 in 2015, and the rate has subsequently increased further.  We could face cost and capacity issues going forward unless more tourism activity is redirected towards the regions.</p> <p>Apart from Dublin, Shannon is the only airport that has direct flights from the United States, a growing market.  It provides excellent facilities and ease of access to Limerick city, and is strategically located on the Wild Atlantic Way.  Surely it makes sense to assist the airport authority in marketing it as an alternative to Dublin.  The airports in Kerry, Knock and Donegal can be promoted as gateways to the Wild Atlantic Way from Britain and Europe, while Cork and Waterford, as well as Dublin, provide easy access to Ireland's Ancient East - indeed, Cork would serve both attractions.  There are excellent accommodation and catering facilities available in all of those locations.</p> <p>I maintain that there is an opportunity to greatly increase tourism visitor numbers by highlighting and promoting the use of regional airports to access the numerous attractions around the country.  We should strive to develop this very valuable resource, not at the expense of Dublin, but to the benefit of the regions.  I request the Minister to favourably consider the points I have made and look forward to hearing his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1213" speakername="Shane Ross" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800004#C00200"><p>I thank Senator Maria Byrne for raising this important subject.  I agree with much of what she said, and although I am very new in the Ministry I am still rather staggered by the number of people who prefer to come to Dublin despite the inconvenience and the expense.  Senator Byrne put her finger on many of the difficulties.  Hotel rooms are a major difficulty but people still seem to pay those sorts of prices.  I suppose the problem is that the hotels themselves might be killing the golden goose and we may get to a point where they go over the top.  Perhaps Cork, Shannon and other places will benefit as a result, and the market might even itself out, but at the moment there is no sign of that happening.</p>  <p>I also share Senator Byrne's puzzlement about the fact that Cork, Shannon and other airports do not seem to attract the passenger numbers one might expect because of the lack of capacity at Dublin Airport and the crowded conditions there.  That has not happened yet.  I am looking at the entire airport scenario.  Many of the airports are not commercially viable.  They are not working very well and they need to get subventions from the State to survive, but they are a very useful add-on and contribute to the prosperity of local communities.  There is no doubt about that, even if they make a commercial loss.  That has been Government policy for some time.</p>  <p>I do not know whether it is worth spending an enormous amount of money transferring people from one place to another.  I do not know at the moment and I do not think Senator Byrne would expect me to do so at this stage in my sojourn in the Department, by means of the incentives and attractions to which she referred, because I do not know enough about it yet.  However, I will do shortly and I will consider such matters over the summer to see whether there are any fundamental changes that might be made.  I do not promise anything, but I am just saying the Senator is kicking at an open door if she has new ideas.  The point she made is a very good one, and there are certain problems related to the concentration of tourism in Dublin which we are trying to address.</p>  <p>My Department is committed to strong regional dispersal in tourism.  It is vital for the sector to increase the geographical spread of activity as well as lengthening the season and increasing activity outside the peak summer months.  With Dublin city accommodation close to full capacity at peak times, it is especially important to provide visitors with credible, compelling and attractive reasons to travel outside Dublin.  None the less, it is important to recognise that Dublin is the main point of arrival for visitors coming to Ireland from abroad and should continue to be promoted as a destination in itself and as a gateway to the rest of Ireland.</p> <p>Further growth in tourism nationally is being progressed under the tourism brand experiences, namely, the Wild Atlantic Way, Ireland's Ancient East and Dublin: A Breath of Fresh Air.  These geographically based brand propositions have been designed to achieve international cut-through, secure customer attention and promote the regional spread of visitors.  They are tailored towards the most promising consumer segments in overseas source markets and utilise their natural and built assets to grow tourism to that region.</p> <p>Of course, air connectivity between Ireland and the UK, continental Europe and further afield is critically important for further tourism growth.  Thankfully, our efforts are well placed to attract and accommodate increased passenger numbers.  Cork and Shannon airports play a vital role in providing regional access.  In addition to Dublin, Shannon is one of the only airports in Europe to offer US pre-clearance facilities, allowing US bound passengers to clear all US entry controls prior to departure, giving the airport a significant competitive advantage in its efforts to retain and promote transatlantic services.  Furthermore, Cork Airport is launching nine new routes and services in 2016 and passenger numbers are expected to make a good recovery this year.</p> <p>In addition to Cork and Shannon, the national aviation policy, published by my Department last August, acknowledges the role played by regional airports in Donegal, Ireland West Airport Knock, Kerry and Waterford.  It recognises that they promote a level of international connectivity to support the tourism and business sectors in their regions and confirms that these four regional airports are being given the opportunity to grow to a viable self-sustaining position.</p> <p>In this regard, my Department's latest regional airports programme 2015-19 will continue to support safety and security measures, where appropriate, at these airports.  An extra &euro;10 million in capital funding is provided in the programme for Government for the regional airports, in addition to the &euro;28 million already provided in the capital plan 2016-22 which will enhance my Department's ability to further support the four airports.</p> <p>With the specific goal of encouraging regional access and enhancing the geographical spread of tourism, my predecessor last year announced a specific funding allocation under the regional co-operative marketing programme to support co-operative marketing activity to points of entry outside of Dublin.  Under this programme, &euro;1 million has been made available to Tourism Ireland in 2016 for co-operative marketing activity, to encourage new access and maximise the potential of existing air and ferry services to the regions.</p> <p>As well as the &euro;1 million being provided by my Department, local authorities and tourism interests in the regions added to the funding for routes serving their access points.  The fund was also matched by carriers and overseas partners for maximum benefit.  The &euro;1 million fund leveraged an additional investment of &euro;1.5 million.  This generated promotional activity worth a total of &euro;2.5 million for regional access and delivered visitors directly to the Wild Atlantic Way and Ireland's Ancient East.  As a result of all of the measures outlined, I am confident that Ireland will welcome increased numbers of visitors outside Dublin this year and beyond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800005#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his reply.  It is very positive that he acknowledged he is aware that most tourists come through Dublin.  There is a problem with bed capacity.  I welcome that the Minister has acknowledged it is something he is willing to examine.  I look forward to hearing about whatever plans he has for the future.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800005#D00250">Special Educational Needs Service Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800005#D00300"><p>I will give the Minister of State a brief synopsis of this matter.  The Holy Angels Day Care Centre opened in Carlow in 1978 in the basement of Carlow's old district hospital by a Presentation nun, Sister Columba.  She was given a cheque for &pound;100 from the south east health board and with the names of five children with special needs from the local area, Holy Angels was set up to provide a day care service for children with special needs of preschool age, that is, those aged from 18 months to six years of age.  In 1983, a new site was bought in Straw Hall at a cost of &pound;52,000, on which prefabs were erected.</p> <p>In 2005, a needs assessment was carried out and the school was told that the current site would not allow for expansion due to the number of children being looked after.  In 2007, the Holy Angels received a donation of a site from a businessman in Carlow.  Following that, the HSE assigned a design team to have plans drawn up.  In 2011, the HSE told the Holy Angels it could go to tender but in 2012, the HSE came back and advised that the Holy Angels could not have this until the site was in its name.  This was the first we had heard of that.  The site had been given, everything was going ahead and it was at the design stage.  We then met with the then Minister for Health, Deputy Leo Varadkar, in Carlow.  He said that he could not believe this and that the HSE, as far as he was aware, did not need to have the site in its name before progressing.</p> <p>It is now 2016.  There are 35 children in the Holy Angels, ranging from 18 months up to six years of age.  There is a waiting list of 20-plus.  In addition, the roof is leaking, the doors need to be fixed and the floor needs to be replaced.  The school has been waiting 11 years for capital funding for a new school.  It has been overlooked for years and is now at the stage where it cannot expand or take in the children who need to attend the school.  It is 38 years since the school opened and it has gone from the basement of an old school to prefabs and it is still in prefabs.  This is 2016 and there are children with a disability, the most vulnerable in our society, still in prefabs.  I wanted to give the Minister of State a rough idea of how the Holy Angels started as this is just not good enough.</p> <p>The Holy Angels has a great manager and staff and a great fundraising committee, which has been fundraising to help with the building of the new school.  Some &euro;4 million is what it is looking for.  As I said, the site has been donated and the school has been given several commitments that it will be given this &euro;4 million to build a new school but it has not happened.  It is unacceptable that again Carlow is totally forgotten.  We have a school, or prefabs, with a leaking roof and floors in need of replacement.  It is absolutely appalling that young children and babies are still in prefabs.  I will bring this up every month because this cannot be allowed to happen in this day and age.  I am ashamed to say that 38 years on, no funding has been given to this preschool.  It is unacceptable.</p> <p>I am sure T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g has been in contact with the Minister of State too.  It is a respite centre.  I will give the Minister of State a rough synopsis of this as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E00200"><p>The Senator will not have the time to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E00300"><p>Will I not?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E00400"><p>Her four minutes are up.  Very quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E00500"><p>It is the same situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E00600"><p>Get to the point.  The time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E00700"><p>Do I have to finish?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E00800"><p>Finish.  Does the Senator want to say another sentence?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E00900"><p>New politics.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E01000"><p>This is so important because unless one knows the particular details-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E01100"><p>The Chair is bound by timing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E01200"><p>Can I have two more minutes, please, a Leas-Chathaoirligh?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E01300"><p>I am afraid I cannot allow the Senator two more minutes but she should do the best she can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E01400"><p>To give a rough outline, T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g was set up in 2005.  It is a respite service for the children of Carlow and was opened for 11 years.  It first opened with ten children and then it had 42 children attending it.  It was a weekend service with a waiting list of 30 or so.  It was closed by the HSE in December 2015 and because of the need for the service, a weekend one was put in place but with no overnights, just some half days.  We are now asking the Minister of State to have this respite centre opened.  A new site was donated, again by a businessman.  It will only cost &euro;350,000 to build this respite centre.  Again, we were given the go-ahead from the HSE to get plans drawn up.</p>  <p>The Holy Angels is in dire need of a new school and T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g respite centre has closed, with only &euro;350,000 needed to build a new respite centre.  Approximately 60 children are looking to attend it, so this is not good enough.  I ask the Minister of State to consider this and come back to me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800006#E01500"><p>I thank Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor for her question and congratulate her on being elected to the Seanad.  I wish her well in the future.</p> <p>I will outline my initial reaction when I heard about this.  It is not acceptable to wait 11 years for capital funding and to have children with disabilities in prefabs.  There seems to be some confusion about the figures.  The Senator spoke about &euro;4 million and then about &euro;350,000 for T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800007#F00200"><p>That is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800007#F00300"><p>I will cover all of the major issues in my response.</p>  <p>Again, I thank the Senator for raising the issue of the funding needed to reopen the T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g respite centre in Carlow which was closed in December 2015.  I welcome the opportunity to outline the current position in regard to this matter.  Holy Angels day care centre is a disability agency that provides services, including a preschool service, for children with disabilities in Carlow.  The facility is funded on an annual basis by the HSE under section 39 of the Health Act.  In 2015, it received funding in the region of &euro;720,000.</p>  <p>As the Senator said, respite services for children in Carlow were previously provided by T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g in Carlow.  In December 2015, the Holy Angels day care centre advised HIQA and the HSE of the decision of the board of management to close the centre from January 2016 after it received notice from the landlord.  On 16 December 2015, the HSE disability services manager wrote to the Holy Angels day care requesting Holy Angels to develop a plan regarding an alternative approach to respite service provision to be completed in consultation with families in receipt of respite and notifying them of the discontinuation of the existing respite service due to lack of premises.  The families were also informed that they would be invited to meetings in January 2016 in regard to these respite services.</p>  <p>T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g provided respite breaks to 42 children and their families with each client being offered a one to two-night respite break every three months, with the current service open six nights per month.  The children range in age from 18 months to 18 years and have a wide range of disabilities from mild to severe.  There are additional children on the waiting list.  In March 2016, in order to address the current respite provision requirements, an alternative respite provision was set up in partnership with the HSE and Holy Angels and is currently provided, via the Holy Angels, at the Delta centre as an interim arrangement.</p>  <p>The HSE estates unit is actively - I stress the word "actively" - seeking to purchase or rent suitable accommodation for future service provision.  It was decided that should the HSE find a suitable residence for respite in either counties Carlow or Kilkenny that services will be provided for both Carlow and Kilkenny from that location until purpose-built accommodation is completed.</p>  <p>The long-term intention of the HSE is to develop a new purpose-built respite service for County Carlow.  With this intention in mind, a capital submission was sent to the HSE's capital steering committee in respect of Carlow.  The capital steering committee considered the submission on 8 March 2016.  There was a problem with the submission because the &euro;20 million available for capital funding in 2016 was targeted and changed to supporting situations that dealt with congregated settings, which is the HSE's priority at the moment and is something that I have pushed personally.</p>  <p>The HSE met the families in Carlow to receive feedback and hear their opinion on the development of a future respite service.  This feedback has been incorporated into the specifications that will be used in the process to put in place a new service provider of children's respite care in Carlow.  With these specifications, the HSE has committed to the provision of an overnight respite service for children in Carlow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800007#F00400"><p>Has Senator Murnane O'Connor a brief supplementary question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800007#F00500"><p>Yes.  I welcome the Minister of State's response but I think we are both suffering from a bit of confusion.  The respite service was closed in December 2015 because it was in a private house in a housing estate and the house required improvement works, such as changing the doors, in order to comply with HIQA standards.  That is a reason it closed.  The facility had great staff.  The children who availed of the service miss staying overnight in the facility and they need that option.  The Minister of State did not give me any information in his reply.</p> <p>Is there any timescale?  What is going to happen?  When is the overnight situation going to be looked at?  Is the Minister going to look at the site that has been given?  Is the &euro;350,000 coming out of capital projects?  Are we getting the money?  I do not want to be negative here but I represent Holy Angels as well, which is part of T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g.  We have spent 38 years in basements and prefabs and it is not acceptable.  I do not want to be here again next year asking the Minister where the &euro;350,000 is for us to build T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g.  We and the children need it so I ask the Minister to come back to me with the answers as to where the funding is that was committed to Holy Angels, as well as the &euro;350,000 committed to T&iacute;r na n&Oacute;g.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800008#G00200"><p>I agree in respect of the broader issue.  The Senator asked very important questions on HIQA and the house being closed.  The overnight service was an excellent service.  I can give her a commitment that I will go back and look again at the issue of the site.  She also asked about the &euro;350,000 and the answer is "Yes, absolutely."  My role as Minister of State with special responsibilities for disabilities is to find out where this money has gone and why it is not being used for services for people with disabilities.  There have been major cuts in the past seven years and the first thing I did when I took over as Minister of State some six weeks ago was to put out the fires of crisis in our services.  I have immediately targeted the 1,500 school leavers who come out at 18 and have no service at all.  I accept the Senator's point that respite, residential and day services also have to be a priority.  I will come back to her on her specific questions.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.39" nospeaker="true" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800008#G00300">Home Care Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="15:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800008#G00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Helen McEntee, to the House.  She has been a staunch supporter of the Alzheimer Society of Ireland, both locally and nationally.  There are almost 55,000 people living with dementia in Ireland and I guess that most of us will know somebody, a family member, a relative or a neighbour for whom this is a reality.  The numbers are set to grow to 68,000 people in ten years' time so it is a massive challenge for individuals, for their families and for society as a whole.  People with dementia need a wide range of supports that reflect the complex and changing needs of the condition.  It is important to diagnose it early to plan ahead and then to get access to counselling services and other services which one will need as the condition advances.</p>  <p>My focus in today is on home care.  Most people with dementia live at home and the majority want to stay there in a familiar environment because familiarity is a really important part of being able to live well with dementia.  People want to stay in their homes and in their communities.  Pat Hume spoke recently about John, and how important being at home in Derry is to him.  A recent report by the Alzheimer Society of Ireland, Age Action and the Irish Association of Social Workers in UCD found that the preference of older people is to stay at home for as long as possible and that more than half of older people could remain in their own homes instead of going into long-term care if more services and home supports were available.  It is official Government policy to support people to stay at home but it is not happening.  We only need to look at the funding divided between long-term residential care and community-based care to see the reasons for this.  Between 2009 and 2015, funding for residential care was increased by &euro;84 million whereas the funding for home care decreased by &euro;11 million.  One possible explanation, and an issue that must be addressed, is that there is no statutory entitlement to home care.  It is discretionary and when the budgets run out, it runs out.</p> <p>However, there is an entitlement to residential care under the nursing homes support scheme.  Later this week, the Alzheimer Society of Ireland will launch its pre-budget submission calling on the Government to invest &euro;67 million in 2017 for home care supports for people with dementia.  This initial investment would meet the needs of 10% of people with dementia who live in the community.  It amounts to a mere 6.7% of the total amount spent on long-term residential care.<br/><br/>There have been some positive moves towards better home care for people with dementia and this must be built on for the future.  Under the national dementia strategy, &euro;22 million was set aside by Atlantic Philanthropies and the Health Service Executive, HSE, for intensive home care packages.  Will the Minister detail how this money is getting through to people?  It is one thing to make the argument that money is being set aside but is it reaching people?  To date, we understand that 130 home care packages have been provided out of a promised 500.  Will the Minister clarify those numbers?  People with dementia have a right to their home and family life just like every other citizen.  In April, the Alzheimer Society of Ireland and the Irish dementia working group, which is made up of people who have dementia, launched a charter of human rights for people with dementia.  During the launch of this important document, Helen Rochford Brennan, who has dementia and is a wonderful advocate for the cause of advancing dementia care in Ireland, said: </p><blockquote>Our rights outlined in the charter launched here today are fundamental to us living well but also for our families.  We have a right to information, to diagnosis, to post-diagnosis support.  We have a right to community based services and home care, and to be cared for in the place of our choice.  We have a right to be part of our community, no matter how progressed our dementia is.</blockquote><p>However, we need investment for those rights to be realised.  Just as somebody once said that one cannot eat scenery, one cannot eat rights unless they are backed with resources.  There must be multi-annual centralised funding and there must be entitlement.  I call on the Minister to ensure this issue is addressed in the forthcoming budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800009#H00200"><p>I thank Senator Kelleher for raising this matter and I congratulate her on the work she has done to date.  I am aware that she continues to work specifically in this area.  As with the other part of my portfolio, mental health, everybody knows somebody who has been affected by dementia, be it a neighbour or friend, and the numbers affected will continue to increase.  Also similar to mental health, there is still a stigma surrounding dementia and the lack of information among the public makes it more difficult to tackle that stigma.  It is an issue we must work on and I intend to do that.</p>  <p>As the Senator correctly pointed out, it is estimated that there are 55,000 people living with dementia in Ireland today.  By 2041, we expect this to increase to more than 140,000 people.  Living with dementia presents challenges for those with the condition, their families and their carers.  The majority of people with dementia live at home and this requires proper supports and interventions to be put in place.  Earlier diagnosis allows for better planning and management of the condition and is in the best interests of those with dementia and their families.  It is important that there is clarity about the options that are available, so families and carers can make good choices in an informed way.  As both the Senator and I mentioned, there is often a stigma associated with this condition which is largely based on stereotyping and, as a community, we must tackle this.</p>  <p>In December 2014, the Irish national dementia strategy was published with the objective of increasing awareness, ensuring timely diagnosis and intervention and developing enhanced community-based services for people with dementia.  The main aim of the strategy is to enable people with dementia to live well in their own homes and communities for as long as possible and it sets out ways of achieving this.  People live longer, healthier and happier lives when they are in their homes, regardless of whether they have dementia.  Resources should be directed to provide the best possible outcome for those with dementia, their families and carers.  The strategy is accompanied by a resourced national dementia strategy implementation programme which is co-funded by the Health Service Executive and Atlantic Philanthropies.  This programme represents a combined investment of &euro;27.5 million over the period 2014-17, with Atlantic Philanthropies contributing &euro;12 million and the HSE contributing &euro;15.5 million.</p> <p> Key elements of this initiative include: &euro;22.1 million for the roll-out of a programme of intensive home supports and home care packages for people with dementia; &euro;1.2 million for the provision of additional dementia-specific resources for general practitioners, who are the critical and initial point of contact with the health system for those with dementia - the resource material will include training materials and guidance on local services and contact points; &euro;2.7 million for measures to raise public awareness, address stigma, and promote the inclusion and involvement in society of those with dementia; and &euro;1.5 million for the establishment of a HSE national dementia office.</p> <p>A significant element of this investment programme will focus on the delivery of intensive home care packages for people with dementia, with up to 500 people with dementia and their families expected to benefit from these packages over the lifetime of the implementation programme, which will extend over a three year period from 2015 to 2018.</p> <p>The roll-out of intensive home care packages commenced in January 2015 and monitoring of the allocation and uptake of these packages is ongoing, as the Senator rightly said, with only 133 persons benefiting to date.  At present, there are 85 people with dementia in receipt of an intensive home care package, and perhaps I could revert to the Senator specifically on the speed of the uptake and how that is progressing.</p> <p>In addition to the intensive packages the Health Service Executive, HSE, will continue to provide mainstream home help, routine home care packages and other appropriate community based supports, such as day care, respite, etc., to people with dementia whose needs have been assessed as requiring these supports and within available resources.</p> <p>I am examining the question of putting this issue on a statutory footing and I would welcome the opportunity to discuss that with the Senator.  I am aware that Members of this and the other House will meet with the organisation this week so we will hear more following that meeting.  There is still much work to be done, and the focus of our funding needs to change in terms of where it is going.  We must make sure it goes to the right place, that is, to keep people in their homes.  I look forward to working with the Senator on this issue and I would welcome the opportunity to meet with her.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800010#J00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  I know that is a sincere offer and I will take her up on it.  Eighty-five people are getting access to the intensive home care packages but all of us in the Seanad probably know 85 people who need them.  The need is vast, and we must make sure that we are getting to the body of people who need that kind of help because people are struggling in the here and now.  People have lost faith in strategies.  It has been said that we have strategy deficiency implementation disorder in Ireland.  We encourage people to believe there is real intent but we must ensure those strategies, commitments and investments are reaching people with dementia to allow them live well, as they wish to and can do, and that their carers are properly supported.  I believe that until such time as this service is put on an entitlement and a statutory footing, we will continue to struggle with this it.  I welcome the Minister's commitment to work on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800010#J00300"><p>I agree with the Senator.  Through the bodies, groups and individuals I have met in recent weeks, I am aware that everybody is on the same page and knows we have enough reports and strategies.  What we need to do now is TO implement them.  Implementation is key at this stage and we need to make progress on that.  The figures are increasing at a high rate within such a short space of time and we have a window to try to deal with it now before it gets out of hand.  I look forward to working with the Senator.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.46" nospeaker="true" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800010#J00350">Primary Care Centres Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800010#J00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending.  I raised this matter previously in the House.  In 2012, the Fine Gael-Labour Party Government made an announcement about the provision of 35 primary care centres.  By way of written response received in December 2015 on one primary care centre in the heart of my constituency in Dublin South-Central, the answer received by the Minister was that the planning was not completed in the timeframe for public private partnership.  It is a net issue and I seek the Minister's response on the matter.</p>  <p>The rationale for allocating the primary care centre to Crumlin and Drimnagh was that it was needed; it was not for a political reason.  There is a massive need in the community for such a centre.  I would like to know when the centre will be commenced, if planning permission has been applied for, if there is a plan in place, and the progress that has been made on that particular centre.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1337" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800011#K00100"><p>I am taking this matter on behalf of my colleague the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, but if there are specific questions, I ask Senator Ardagh to let me know and we will get back to her.  I thank the Senator for raising this issue.</p>  <p>The programme for a partnership Government commits to a decisive shift within the health service towards primary care in order to deliver better care close to home in communities across the country.  Enhancing and expanding capacity in the primary care sector is crucial to ensuring delivery of a preventive, joined-up approach to the management of the nation's health and the modernisation of primary care delivery.  Primary care centres facilitate the delivery of multidisciplinary primary care services and shift the focus of the health service from a hospital-centric model towards a primary care model whereby services can be delivered more effectively and efficiently.  I know the Senator is aware of this.  In a fully developed primary care system, 90% to 95% of people's day-to-day health and social care needs can be met in the primary care setting.  Essentially, the goal is to provide the right care in the right place at the right time.  Primary care centres throughout the country significantly enhance the accessibility of health services in local communities.  They enable people get the care they need as close to home as possible.</p>  <p>I can advise the Senator that more than 90 primary care centres are already operational.  A further 82 centres are at varying stages of development and will, when completed, significantly enhance and expand capacity in the primary care sector to deliver a preventive, joined-up approach to the management of the nation's health and the modernisation of primary care delivery.  These additional primary care facilities across the country will be provided through a combination of direct build, public private partnership, and the HSE's primary care operational lease mechanism.</p>  <p>As the Senator has correctly pointed out, the Crumlin-Drimnagh primary care centre was one of 16 locations selected for delivery through a PPP project.  I am advised by the HSE that the Dublin City Council decision to grant planning permission for the development was appealed to An Bord Plean&aacute;la by third parties.  I am further advised that the planning permission grant from An Bord Plean&aacute;la for the development was, however, not received in time for the site to be included in the PPP project.  An alternative means of funding the development is through the HSE's capital plan. However, the HSE has advised that it is not in a position to allocate funding to this project until 2020, although further consideration could be given in the context of the 2017 capital review.</p>  <p>Notwithstanding this, there are a number of primary care developments in the area which support the delivery of primary care services in the Crumlin-Drimnagh area.  These developments include the extensive refurbishment of the Old County Road health centre in Crumlin, which has recently been completed, and a primary care centre to be provided by way of operational leasing at Cashel Road, Walkinstown.  This centre is currently in construction and is anticipated that it will be operational by the fourth quarter of 2017.  In addition, a primary care centre is also planned for in Rialto, again for delivery by way of operational leasing.  Planning approval has been granted and it is anticipated that construction will commence before the end of the fourth quarter of 2016.</p>  <p>I can assure Senator Ardagh that the development of primary care is central to the Government's objective to deliver a high-quality, integrated and cost-effective health care system.  I intend to consider future infrastructure in the context of the implementation of the health commitments in the programme for Government and having regard to the funding available to facilitate such measures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800011#K00200"><p>I would appreciate if perhaps the Minister of State could ask the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, to outline how he would go about including the Crumlin-Drimnagh project in the 2017 capital review plan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800011#K00300"><p>Does the Minister of State wish to add anything?  No.  I propose that we suspend until  3.30 p.m.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.51" nospeaker="true" time="15:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.52" nospeaker="true" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800012#N00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800012#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion re reinstatement of the Competition (Amendment) Bill 2016 to the Order Paper, to be taken on the conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate and; No. 2, statements on the UK referendum result, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 1 and to conclude not later than 6.45 p.m., with the contribution of all Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be called upon to reply not later than 6.40 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="15:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800012#N00300"><p>As leader of the Fianna F&aacute;il group, I welcome the Government's decision to increase the rent supplement in line with the confidence and support agreement with Fianna F&aacute;il.  It must be noted that it is just one of a suite of measures designed to tackle the housing and homeless crisis.  Many families are at risk of losing their homes due to rapidly rising rents and that is the reason Fianna F&aacute;il ensured the Government would increase the rent supplement as a short-term measure.  It is the right thing to do, as one of the measures designed to alleviate the housing crisis.  The Government's decision to increase the rent supplement in major urban areas such as Dublin will help in the short term.  Ensuring that the supplement reflects the reality in the market will also help to stop the practice of illegal top-ups that are putting families to the very pin of their collar.  It is important that the law banning landlords from refusing tenants because they are on rent supplement is also fully implemented.</p>  <p>The Dublin local authorities, with Dublin City Council as the lead local authority, in response to homelessness are managing what is a critical and unprecedented situation in relation to the demand for their homeless services on a daily and nightly basis.  In April 2016, the Dublin local authorities provided accommodation for 888 families, with 1,786 child dependants.  Of those 888 families, 218 families were accommodated in homeless accommodation while 670 families were accommodated in commercial hotels.</p>  <p>I also wish to draw the House's attention to the eviction from a Dublin hotel on 9 June of a young family for drawing attention to the substandard emergency accommodation which suffered from damp and mould to a level so severe that their young children aged from nine months old who were recently out of hospital could not stay in the room.  After requesting a change of room and appearing in the media over the conditions, they were confronted by management and the family then received a telephone call from Dublin City Council minutes later to inform them that their room had been cancelled.</p> <p>No alternative accommodation was offered and they have been informed that their contract with the hotel is now terminated.  </p> <p>These types of incidents should not happen.  This is a very serious crisis that the Government needs to tackle head on.  Each night there are so many children in emergency accommodation, which makes this an unbearable crisis.  Even though the matter is talked about in every council chamber every day I feel that the crisis has still not been taken seriously.</p> <p>The measures announced today go some way towards alleviating the crisis.  However, the measures should form part of the overall housing package to ensure supply is increased in the future.  The Government should act quickly and ensure that all of the recommendations made by the Oireachtas Committee on Housing and Homelessness are implemented.  The Government must also ensure that there is proper investment in housing to ensure that families no longer have to sleep on the streets at night or take the humiliating step of approaching their local authorities to secure emergency accommodation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O00200"><p>I call on the Leader to organise a debate on competition, particularly in aviation.  I had reason to book a flight to Paris with Ryanair which cost &euro;285.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.57" nospeaker="true" time="15:40:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O00400"><p>I could not leave on the day requested and, subsequently, booked a flight for one month later for exactly the same period.  I sought credit for the flight that I could not take and Ryanair did so.  Were I to book the flight for 30 July it would have cost me &euro;287.  As I had already paid &euro;287 for a flight in June, Ryanair credited me for the money I had spent on the flight and only charged me &euro;189.40 to change my flight, which was an outrageous abuse.  When Ryanair has one's money it says, "Stuff you, we're keeping your money."  If one wants to change a flight one has got to practically pay the full price to travel on an alternative flight.  If one took the Government taxes out of what Ryanair allowed me, then I would get nothing back and I must pay for the full flight the second time around.</p>  <p>We need to bring the relevant Minister in here to debate the matter.  Looking around the House I can see on the faces of Members that other people have suffered the same fate as me.  Ryanair's charging system is an outrageous abuse.  One can change a seat on a ship that is due to sail to the UK or France and the shipping company will not penalise the customer.  One can change travel details for most other transport methods.  Indeed, a couple of years ago in the United States I had reason to change flights.  The airline in question bent over backwards to facilitate me and charged me $40.  Recently Ryanair changed focus to become customer friendly.  If this is customer friendly then I shall eat my hat.  I ask the Leader to arrange for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to come in here for a full debate in order to see if we can do something to curb such practices.  The only two airlines that provide flights all over Europe are Aer Lingus and Ryanair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O00500"><p>The uncertainty generated by Brexit last Friday poses urgent and immediate challenges for the Republic of Ireland.  Sinn F&eacute;in wants Europe to be socially, democratically and environmentally friendly and one that promotes-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O00600"><p>The Senator will have another opportunity to discuss the matter later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O00700"><p>I know but it is important that I set out a couple of points.  Is that all right, a Leas-Chathaoirligh?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O00800"><p>I am not so sure.  The Senator can make her points early in the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O00900"><p>We are discussing the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01000"><p>Yes.  The item has been ordered to follow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01100"><p>Yes, I understand.  Is the Leas-Chathaoirleach excluding Sinn F&eacute;in from mentioning Brexit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01200"><p>I am not excluding Sinn F&eacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01300"><p>Absolutely not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01400"><p>We are discussing the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01500"><p>Order, please.  The Chair will rule but I shall allow a little latitude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01600"><p>Does the Chair have to rule in accordance with Brexit?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01700"><p>The Chair will take nothing from anyone now.  I shall determine what happens next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01800"><p>This country is only a few years in the EU.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O01900"><p>Sorry, I shall allow the Senator a slight latitude because she is the leader of her group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O02000"><p>I shall keep my comments very short.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800013#O02100"><p>I would like other Senators to respect my decision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800014#P00100"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800014#P00200"><p>I thank the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800014#P00300"><p>I will keep it very short; I have just a few points.  A better European Union, which promotes and serves the sovereign and democratic needs of its member states of 500 million citizens, can only be achieved by campaigning for change and reform from within the EU institutions.  Brexit presents us with the potential loss of investment, negative implications for border controls and common travel and the prospect of less protection for workers' and other rights.  A British state withdrawal from the EU represents a major setback for the political process in the North of Ireland and relationships between the two islands.  Brexit also poses a direct challenge to the integrity of the Good Friday Agreement and internationally binding treaties and undermines all-Ireland co-operation.  In broader terms, the financial losses of EU investment, subsidies and funds to the North of Ireland and the southern Border counties arising from the British withdrawal is in the region of &pound;2.5 billion.  There are negative repercussions for foreign direct investment and the development of the North's export capacity in regard to access to EU and global markets and that is why there is now an immediate imperative for the Government to open negotiations with Britain over the constitutional future of the North of Ireland.</p>  <p>I want to add another point, a Leas-Chathaoirligh, if I may, not regarding Brexit but regarding the report this morning that many young people with disabilities who sat their leaving certificate did not have the environment they needed in order to be able to participate fully in that examination.  That is absolutely disgraceful.  Will the Minister responsible come to the House to reassure us that it will never happen again to those with a disability who have overcome very many challenges to get to sit their leaving certificate in the first instance?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800014#P00400"><p>In regard to the Order of Business, I welcome that we will have the opportunity today to discuss the Brexit referendum.  It is important we discuss it in terms of our relationship with the UK and in terms of the future of Europe, looking beyond the question of negotiations to the kind of framing we would have for Europe, in particular how we might address the toxic language of racism and anti-immigration sentiment and how we can look to a Europe that sends a stronger signal of inclusion and participation.  I look forward to that debate.</p>  <p>I welcome the reinstatement of the Competition (Amendment) Bill 2016 to the Order Paper.  It is a very important Bill in respect of freelance work and for those who are often caught in what might be false or non-actual freelance work which can be a vulnerable situation for many vulnerable workers.  It is excellent to see this Bill on the agenda.</p>  <p>The National Economic Dialogue took place yesterday.  Last week, there was a lengthy debate in the D&aacute;il on the Government's summer economic statement.  The timing of the summer economic statement and the National Economic Dialogue is unfortunate in that they have taken place around the Brexit referendum, which changes radically the context in which we are looking at future economic and social planning.  I would like to mention to the Leader that it would be useful in future for this House to have the opportunity to discuss the summer economic statement.  It goes beyond the simple question of moneys and the kinds of assumptions, values and priorities set out in such a statement.  This House would have much to contribute to that debate in the future and also to the National Economic Dialogue.  </p>  <p>Last weekend in Galway, the annual conference of the International Association for Feminist Economics took place.  It highlighted very crucial issues not least among them the importance of care, for example.  Care is the lifeblood of our society and yet neither the cost nor the contribution of care has been recognised in the summer economic statement.  Neither seem to be present at as high a level as they should be within our economic and social planning going into next year.</p>  <p>I want to highlight a very interesting and an important report published yesterday by the Higher Education Authority on the importance of gender equality in Irish higher  education institutions.  The expert review group was chaired by the internationally experienced and the expert M&aacute;ire Geoghegan-Quinn.  The report is very important to me as the first woman elected in 35 years on the National University of Ireland panel.</p> <p>I welcome the recommendations of that report.  I know we will have an opportunity to discuss it during statements on education, and I would appreciate it if the Minister addressed this report and told us how he plans to implement these very concrete recommendations to address the fact that, although Ireland has an extraordinary number of highly qualified women graduates, they are not recognised or represented at the highest level within our institutions.  This is a real opportunity to ensure our institutions are world class and that gender equality is recognised as a key indication of quality and performance.  I look forward to the opportunity to discuss this further with the Minister for Education and Skills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800015#Q00200"><p>I thank the Leader for organising statements today on the result of the UK referendum on EU membership.  The result not only is deeply disappointing but represents a seismic shock in terms of its political and economic fallout, which is being felt on this island, in the UK and across the European Union.  I look forward to participating this afternoon.</p>  <p>I thank the Leader for ensuring the restoration of the Competition (Amendment) Bill to the Order Paper and Senator Alice-Mary Higgins for her kind words about the Bill.  This Bill was introduced in Private Members' time by the Labour Party group of Senators in January and it passed Second Stage with Government approval.  The aim of the Bill is to provide for collective bargaining rights for freelance workers, particularly actors, journalists and so on, who are working freelance and are currently denied collective bargaining rights due to a particularly rigid application of the Competition Act.  This Bill provides a simple amendment to that Act to ensure they have collective bargaining rights.  It was warmly welcomed in January by SIPTU, the NUJ and Equity, among others, and I hope it will pass through Committee Stage when we take it in Labour Party Private Members' time next Wednesday.  I ask colleagues across the floor of this House for their support for this Bill.</p>  <p>I join with Senator Higgins in welcoming the report on gender in third level institutions and I look forward to debating that.  I commend the huge work of Micheline Sheehy Skeffington in this area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800015#Q00300"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800015#Q00400"><p>She is a tireless activist in this area and a very eminent academic who had the courage to take the case which prompted this report and which has highlighted public awareness of gender discrimination in universities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800015#Q00500"><p>In the tradition of her grandfather.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800015#Q00600"><p>Yes, in the tradition of her grandfather.  I ask the Leader for a debate on criminal justice policy and penal reform.  I had the pleasure of attending a conference at NUI Maynooth last week on criminology and, today, a round-table discussion hosted by the Association for Criminal Justice Research and Development on criminal justice, in conjunction with the Department of Justice and Equality and the Probation Service.  We looked at different issues around criminal justice reform and penal policy.  Some excellent work was done by the Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality on penal reform in the previous cycle.  I hope we will see certain Bills restored to the Order Paper and that they will be debated in this House, among them a sex offences Bill which would introduce changes to prostitution law and really important changes to the law with regard to evidence and procedures concerning sex offence trials.  I also look forward to legislation on domestic violence.  I ask the Leader for a general debate on these issues and whether the legislation might be brought before us very swiftly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800015#Q00700"><p>One of the reactions to the decision of the UK to leave the EU has been a surge in applications for Irish passports both in the UK and in Northern Ireland.  It is my understanding that there are millions of people eligible for Irish passports who have not previously applied, although things can sometimes be exaggerated in the media.  The Passport Office does a wonderful job, sometimes with limited resources, to cope with applications for passports and to get them out on time, and some of us have been guilty of not renewing our passports on time.  This is also a particularly busy time of the year.  Is there a surge in applications?  If that is the case, what are the plans to deal with this?  The Passport Office would need additional resources if this were the case.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="15:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800015#Q00800"><p>I would like to be allowed to publish the Registration of Wills Bill 2016.</p> <p>This is a Bill to provide for the registration of wills and I seek leave of the House to amend the Order of Business to allow the Bill to be published and circulated.  In due course, we will have the opportunity to debate it during Private Members' business.</p> <p>To follow up on Senator O'Mahony's point about the Brexit referendum, nobody has expertise on what will happen because nobody knows what will happen.  When Article 50 of the Lisbon treaty is activated, there will be two years of negotiations with all the experts.  I have read a great deal since last Friday.  Quite honestly, people are in a state of shock.  Certainly, in my area, it is the main focus of attention at present, with the drop in the price of cattle, worries about exports, worries about the Border and other such concerns.  I concur with Senator O'Mahony on the issue he raised.  I also support Democratic Unionist Member of Parliament, Ian Paisley Jr., who has advised people in Northern Ireland to get Irish passports following the Brexit vote.  Incidentally, he voted for Brexit but he now recommends strongly that all our friends and fellow Irish men and women in Northern Ireland apply for their passports under the Good Friday Agreement.  We will have a united Ireland in passports.  They will have Irish passports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800016#R00200"><p>The first step.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800016#R00300"><p>It will allow our friends in Northern Ireland to travel the length and breadth of Europe and beyond with an Irish European passport.  The same applies to Irish people in Britain.  A total of 90,000 people born in England applied for and received Irish passports over the past decade, while 150,000 people born in Northern Ireland are entitled to passports through parents or grandparents and they applied for them in the last ten years.  This will be a major change.  I also hope that under the negotiations, they will not be excluded because of their address.  An Irish passport is a European passport and that is how it will remain.  We will fight to ensure that any person who holds an Irish passport will be entitled to full access to the European Union.  This must be part of the negotiations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800016#R00400"><p>And to the vote.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800016#R00500"><p>A vote, indeed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800016#R00600"><p>The Senator should address his remarks to the Chair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800016#R00700"><p>I recommend to the Passport Office that it open a dedicated section in Balbriggan or Dundalk to deal exclusively with passport applications from Northern Ireland and Britain.  At present, it is taking approximately 15 days to get a standard Irish passport and every Member has been inundated with requests to expedite passports.  If the new applications arrive, it will absolutely inundate the Passport Office.  That office is doing an excellent job but it needs more staff.  It should allocate more staff to the Balbriggan office or open a new dedicated office in Dundalk.  It is the only positive side to Brexit that I can see at present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800016#R00800"><p>The high cost of fertiliser is a serious concern for farmers.  It is not a new issue as the cost has been high for a number of years.  It is notable that the cost has not decreased as one might have expected with the reduction in the cost of a barrel of oil, as that is one of the feed-in costs to the production of fertiliser.  Why is that?  The Irish Farmers' Association, IFA, commissioned a report from the International Food Policy Research Institute which points to a particular problem.  It shows that it is due to the failure of competition within the Single Market and the European Union.  There are a few players and these players, it appears, are ensuring that the price is kept high, notwithstanding the cost to them of producing the fertiliser.  It is estimated that this is costing farmers in Europe approximately &euro;1 billion per year.</p>  <p>This issue must be taken up by the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  In particular, it has been estimated that the cost of fertiliser can be tackled by the market being opened to imports into the European Union.  At present, there are very high tariffs and taxes but if that can be tackled, it would deal with the competition issue that is leading to the high prices, which could see a saving of up to &euro;70 million per annum for Irish farmers.</p> <p>That is a very important issue which has gone on far too long.  I would like the Minister to come to the House to address it and also issues concerning Brexit, particularly in terms of farmers' concerns about exports.  There is a big market in the United Kingdom for our agricultural produce and notwithstanding the British vote to exit the European Union and the Single Market, milk farmers, lamb producers and so on are experiencing difficulties already with commodity prices.  It is a very serious and I would like to see the Minister in the House to discuss those matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S00200"><p>Some 30 years ago I initiated the first Independent Group with my colleague, former Senator Joe O'Toole.  We were entirely university Members at that stage.  After the last election I tried to put together a larger group because there were so many Independents but Senator Alice-Mary Higgins and Senator Lynn Ruane, with some others, formed a separate group.  We then had a meeting.  I was elected leader and given the foreign affairs portfolio.  Senator McDowell introduced two new members and suggested that since they were new members we should re-run the election.  This we did today, and I put myself forward again.  Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell got six votes, I got two and Senator Craughwell got one.  I regarded this as a vote of no confidence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S00300"><p>Does the Senator really need to inform the House of that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S00400"><p>I think so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S00500"><p>With respect, that is hardly a matter for the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S00600"><p>We must have transparency in everything.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S00700"><p>I take Senator Reilly's point very much to heart.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S00800"><p>No, hold on.  The Chair will rule, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S00900"><p>I regarded this as a vote of no confidence-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01000"><p>It is not relevant, Senator.  It might be interesting-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01100"><p>-----and, as a result, I have resigned my position in the Independent Group.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01200"><p>You can read about it tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01300"><p>This also means I will forfeit my position on the foreign affairs committee.  Senator Marie Louise O'Donnell is unique in having been nominated for a second time by the Taoiseach and she has been a stirring voice in this House.  I wish her and the group well.</p><p>I also disagreed with the group in putting forward a Bill about Seanad reform that contained some good measures but that was concocted by a group of lawyers and would lead inevitably to the extinction of the Trinity seat and opening it up to 1 million voters.  I will, therefore, be the only independent Independent when my former group has notified the office of this.  <i>Le roi est mort, vive la reine</i>, but I remain father of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01400"><p>I am sure you will do well, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01500"><p>In deference to the father of the House, I wish him well.</p>  <p>I pay warm tribute to and welcome our former colleague and Leader of the House, Maurice Cummins, and his very special guests who are in the Gallery.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01600"><p>Forgive me, Senator Mullins.  With my macular oedema, I am slightly short-sighted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01700"><p>I thought I was the one who could claim that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01800"><p>You are overdoing it, Senator.  Carry on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="16:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800017#S01900"><p>On that note, I hope they have a very enjoyable day in Leinster House.</p>  <p>This morning, I had the great privilege of giving the opening keynote address in a very important seminar on equality, recruitment and employment organised by the Mid-West Disability Inclusion Forum.  It is a new forum formed to help industry engage with people with disabilities in a move to promote greater access to the workplace.  Companies such as Dell, Northern Trust, GE Capital and GCAS, and the University of Limerick, are participants in what is a super project.  It has achieved results already and based on the energy at the event I addressed in Limerick this morning, I believe it will achieve many more.  An engagement between industry and the University of Limerick to promote equality of access and the breaking down of barriers to people with disabilities in the workplace is a great initiative.</p>  <p>I took the opportunity also to update the attendees on the strategy launched before Christmas by the Taoiseach.</p> <p>It was known as the programme to encourage people with disabilities to get involved in employment.  It is called the Comprehensive Employment Strategy for People with Disabilities and is now considered a very important strategy with some key focus points in terms of engaging with industry, making work pay, breaking down barriers and ensuring that the right environment is in place to ensure that people have the opportunity to engage.  Will the Leader to invite the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to the House, possibly in the autumn, to give it an update on the strategy on promoting employment for people with disabilities?  Unfortunately, people with disabilities are 50% less likely to get access to employment compared to their able bodies colleagues, which is a great pity.  Now that we are seeing a significant number of jobs being created - hopefully, many more will be created in due course - statements in the House on this issue with the Minister would be important.  I encourage the Leader to organise that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800018#T00200"><p>I dtosach b&aacute;ire, ba mhaith liom tr&eacute;asl&uacute; le na foirne sacair agus rugba&iacute; at&aacute; againn in &Eacute;irinn a rinne thar barr ar fad sna cluich&iacute; san Eoraip, san Afraic Theas agus sa chraobh domhanda ag an deireadh seachtaine.  Tr&eacute;aslaim chomh maith leis an lucht lean&uacute;na a bh&iacute; thar barr ar fad sa chaoi a d'iompar siad iad f&eacute;in le linn na gcom&oacute;rtas &eacute;ags&uacute;la.  I congratulate all our Irish teams which were competing and our fans on how well they represented Ireland when abroad.</p><p>I wish to raise what I believe to be a very serious issue.  Last week, during a debate in the House on bin charges, the Minister, Deputy Coveney said:</p><blockquote>People from all parties and none asked me to engage with the industry and ensure that no household would be ripped off as we try to move to a pay-by-weight charging structure.  That is exactly what I did.  Last Friday, the day after those questions were raised, we met the waste industry for at least three hours.  I had a very direct discussion with them.  I told them that under no circumstances would the Government allow a situation whereby households would be mandated to switch over to a new charging system that would result in dramatic increases for many households.  It would not happen, and it has not happened, and people are talking in this debate as if it will happen.  It will not. </blockquote><p>It has happened and is happening as we speak.  It has been clarified to Raidi&oacute; na Gaeltachta, which has investigated the issue, that the only people whose charges will not be increased are those who are already registered with waste collection companies.  As we know, the current situation is almost a 50-50 in that 50% of people are not registered with waste companies because they get rid of their own waste or they are using the bag system and purchase bags in shops.  It is our understanding that those people are now going to be compelled to register, pay a standing charge and pay by weight.  This is totally contradictory to what the Minister said.  This is an incredibly serious issue.  Wittingly or unwittingly, the Minister misled the Seanad.  Either he was aware this would be the scenario and withheld the information or the companies with whom he was in discussions for the three hours withheld the information from him.  If they did, then there is a huge issue around how trustworthy the companies are to implement the statutory instrument.</p><p>Last week Fianna F&aacute;il Members fully supported the Minister and said they had full confidence in him.  Wittingly or unwittingly, either Fianna F&aacute;il Members knew or did not know about this scenario.  If they knew about this scenario, they were complicit in the collusion but if they did not know about it, they were misled by the Minister.  We need to find out the truth.</p><p>I call for an amendment to the Order of Business that the Minster, Deputy Coveney, comes to the House today because these waste charges are to come in on 1 July.  I want the Minister to clarify the situation and tell us if he misled the D&aacute;il and the Seanad.  If he did, will he correct the record?  What will the Minister do to address the situation where people across this country are going to be ripped off by the private refuse companies unless the Government does something about it?  I propose that amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="16:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800018#T00300"><p>At this stage, the Leader is used to Senators - in some cases, very reasonably - criticising Government agencies or Government Departments.  On this occasion, I am happy to be doing the opposite.</p> <p>I want to pay tribute, through the Leader, to Mr. Martin Shanahan, the chief executive officer of IDA Ireland, and then I want to add a request.  I pay tribute to Mr. Shanahan for being proactive in writing to 1,200 employers stating that we are potentially now the only English-speaking gateway to the EU, an excellent location for inward investment and an attractive option for those firms.  I am delighted he did it and I commend him on it.  Given the recent unfortunate events and as, hopefully, more firms locate in Ireland, I would like the Leader, through the Minister, to impress on Mr. Shanahan the need for a good regional spread.  Perhaps a debate in the House would be helpful.  Given the housing crisis in Dublin, the price of accommodation along the east coast and all that goes with that, and the improved infrastructure on a number of levels throughout the country, it is imperative that we do what Mr. Shanahan is doing and try to attract new inward investment.  We wish him luck with the initiative, which needs to be stepped up.  However, the inward investment must be spread regionally.  I would like to see places such as Cavan-Monaghan and others throughout the country getting a fair spread of the new potential employment that can arise from inward investment.  I know that the Leader, as a Munster man, will appreciate the importance of spreading this around.  From a spatial perspective, we do not want job creation in just the one area.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800019#U00200"><p>Did Senator Ruane offer?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800019#U00300"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800019#U00400"><p>I have to go across the floor.  I call Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800019#U00500"><p>Is the Leas-Chathaoirleach sure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800019#U00600"><p>I am following the rota for the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800019#U00700"><p>A Leas-Chathaoirligh, I am here to second the amendment proposed by Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800019#U00800"><p>Senator Warfield can do that in a minute.  I will call him - he need not worry - when it is his time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="16:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800019#U00900"><p>I join with Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh on two points.  He has previously asked for a debate on the Irish language in this House and that is something we should definitely have in the coming weeks.  Will the Leader arrange it?  It is an important debate.  I say that deliberately in English because it is a debate for all Members of this House.  We should be inclusive about the discussion on the status of our native language.</p>  <p>I also join with him in congratulating the Irish team which came back from the European Championship yesterday.  I am delighted that we are having a debate later today about Brexit because, just when we feel the world is falling apart somewhat, sport can always cheer us up.  In particular, the Icelandic football team last night gave us all great reason to cheer another "Brexit" that was perhaps not expected.</p>  <p>We should have a debate on sport.  It may be that it enters our political consciousness only at times of great competition or achievement, but sport means a huge amount to people throughout the country.  It brings people together and provides a fantastic opportunity for communities to come together.  It can be an opportunity for those on the edges of society to participate.  It reflects well on us.  Given the great achievements of the Irish soccer team as well as the Northern Irish soccer team in the European Championship, perhaps now is the time to have cold reflection on the state of the game of football in Ireland, including the League of Ireland, the women's game, the under age game, the game throughout the island, and where we go from here.  Participating in sport is about representing one's town, place and parish, and there is an awful lot to be positive about.</p>  <p>What can the political circle do in terms of investment or strategy for the next five, ten or 15 years?  I am thinking of the volunteers throughout the country who line the pitches, put up the nets and take the training sessions for the under-7s and under-8s.  These are the real heroes when it comes to participation in sport in Ireland.  Could we have a debate in the coming weeks with either the senior Minister or the junior Minister in the Department to see what support we can give to develop football and other sports in Ireland over the coming years?</p>  <p>The potential for an all-Ireland team has been mentioned, which is something I think I would support.  There are other strategic things we could do in the short term with regard to an all-Ireland league when comes to progressing football in Ireland.  Sport is not an add-on or a luxury.  It is integral to the life of people in Ireland.  People get excited about it, and if people get excited about it it has to be considered important.  I suggest that the House have at an appropriate time a debate on sport and discuss exactly what can be done in the long term and in a strategic fashion to support and promote games of whatever kind in Ireland.</p> <p>I would be very happy to support it and I look forward to it coming before the House.  </p> <p>I would also like to voice my support for Senator Leyden's proposal to locate a passport office in Balbriggan in north County Dublin.  It is ideally located close to Dublin city centre, but also the Border.  I would also like to extend a very warm welcome to our friends in Northern Ireland who are from the Unionist tradition but now want to be take part in the Irish nation.  We very much welcome it and I look forward to welcoming them south of the Border.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800020#W00200"><p>I would like to support Senator Conway's call for a debate with the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation on equality regarding those with disabilities.  It is a very serious issue.  I wish to advise Senator Clifford-Lee that there is a passport office in Balbriggan which needs to be expanded.</p>  <p>I refer to Brexit.  There has been a lot of talk about its impact on us, its potential negative impact and the challenges we face.  Undoubtedly, they exist.  Notwithstanding the regrettable result, we have a great opportunity.  Martin Shanahan's action is to be commended, as Senator Joe O'Reilly said, in pointing out that Ireland has long been within the eurozone the only English-speaking country, and now we will be the only English speaking country in the EU.  We are very well placed, given our well-educated, young and diverse population, in particular in north Dublin which has the youngest population in the country, if not Europe, to attract new industries.  Many countries are already looking to Ireland as a stepping stone and those which were considering the UK will now look to Ireland.  We must grasp this opportunity.  The tone of our discourse should be one that is conciliatory towards the UK because we still have very great ties with it.  Many of us have family there and many living there have family here.  We need to keep that closeness and build on that strength, even if it is under a new set of conditions within the EU.</p>  <p>The Dublin Airport plan for 10,000 more jobs in the shorter term and new facilities for businesses to locate there needs to be expedited.  I fully support the plan.  It makes it all the more important that metro north is progressed as quickly as possible to increase connectivity with the city.  It would also assist people such as Senator O'Reilly's constituents in Cavan, Louth and Meath.  There could be a park and ride facility to ensure people would not have to face the congestion of the city.  </p>  <p>We have a wonderful opportunity to turn a challenge into an opportunity and what looks like adversity into advantage.  I welcome that the Minister will come to the House today to take statements on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800020#W00300"><p>I apologise to Senator Boyhan.  I did not realise when I called Senator Norris that he was now groupless.  I am sure he will forgive me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800020#W00400"><p>He still has a home here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="16:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800020#W00500"><p>I thank the Leader for organising for the Minister to come to the House for statements.  I heard a number of Senators voice their opposition to statements, but on this occasion it is a good use of time.  I will hold my comments on Brexit until later.</p>  <p>I want to raise one simple issue.  Last week, RTE, the national broadcaster, did the State yet another service.  It exposed a terrible litany of allegations regarding the charity Console and its financial transparency, and raised serious issues about finances in many charities.  In Ireland, charities are big business and there are now serious questions about why members of the public or the State should support them.</p>  <p>It was clear from the RTE "Prime Time" programme that there was no clear definitive list of funds given by the State to specific charities.</p> <p>It is a really extraordinary position for the State, and the public, to find themselves in.  I ask that the appropriate Minister, or whoever is relevant to this section, would come in or that we would have some debate on how we can regulate and improve the entire charity sector.  RTE has done the State service yet again.  The programme has exposed a number of very serious shortcomings and I wish to pay tribute to its work- this House should pay tribute to its work also - because it is an important part of democracy and for public broadcasting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800021#X00200"><p>I congratulate the blueshirts, as I am sure would the rest of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800021#X00300"><p>For losing the election.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800021#X00400"><p>Of course I mean Iceland, on its brilliant win last night.  I wish the team well for the future.  We all have a team we can support now.  We have much in common in that Iceland is also an island with a very small population.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800021#X00500"><p>Does Senator Butler not support the Germans?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800021#X00600"><p>I also welcome our team home and congratulate the Irish teams, North and South, on a wonderful tournament for the two teams.</p>  <p>I wish to raise a recent report which indicates that &euro;20 million is being taken out of the social welfare system each year by companies employing people on a self-employed basis.  A PAYE worker pays between 14% and 15% but when one is self-employed one pays an S class stamp and that is only 4%, which leaves the company paying nothing.  The worker is described as being self-employed when in reality he or she is not self-employed.  It sounds very good but it is a nightmare when companies fold or go bankrupt.  It leaves the Department of Social Protection out of budget and the person who is out of work has very few entitlements.</p>  <p>I have seen many such cases following the crash in 2010, 2011 and 2012.  That practice must be examined and new legislation must be introduced to combat it.  I am aware of a courier company that employed everyone on a self-employed basis during the Celtic tiger and when the company folded, families were desperate and had difficulty in putting food on the table, paying their mortgages and surviving.  I advise anyone who is due to be employed by a company on a self-employed basis to please check it out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800021#X00700"><p>I second the amendment proposed to the Order of Business by my Sinn F&eacute;in colleague, Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="16:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800021#X00800"><p>I join with colleagues in congratulating the Irish team and all the people involved in its performance in the championship.  They did the country proud, as did the supporters in the way they behaved, in that they put forward a very positive message for Ireland.</p>  <p>An issue that is coming up more and more in rural areas is that community groups and sporting organisations require people to work for them but the people available do not qualify for the various community employment schemes.  As a result, the organisations are not able to employ people.  It is time for the Minister for Social Protection to examine the entire area and consider revising the schemes and amending the rules in order to facilitate organisations, especially sporting and community organisations.  I refer in particular to people over 62 years of age.  It appears there is a big problem at the moment because people in that age group do not currently qualify for many schemes.  The issue was raised recently in the north Cork area by a number of councillors and it is an issue we must examine in order that those who provide services and facilities for young people are given the necessary State support.</p>  <p>Senator Boyhan raised the issue of funding to various voluntary organisations.  The HSE budget is approximately &euro;13.8 billion and out of that, &euro;3.6 billion goes to approximately 2,600 organisations.  We never get a breakdown of what each organisation gets until we table questions on it.</p> <p>That is what I did in the last health committee.  As a result, a number of issues came to light on how that funding was spent.  Over &euro;3.6 billion of the health budget goes to those organisations.  That is quite a number of organisations to audit and supervise.  We need to make sure that we have proper mechanisms so that every euro we give is properly managed and used.  We should not be leaving it to the national broadcaster to highlight inefficiencies in those organisations.  The Minister should look at how we could put in place a proper audit system to ensure taxpayers' money is used properly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800022#Y00200"><p>I recently renewed my television licence.  I did so with some reluctance.  I do not think I am alone when I say it grates with me to hear RTE running free advertisements, not just to get us to pay for our television licence, which we are required to do by law, but at the same time telling us how great it is.  What is more, it picks issues and events on which perhaps not all voters were agreed and tells us how great those events all were.  A State-funded broadcaster funded by taxpayers' money and using those resources to advertise not just payment of the licence, but its own merits, is going too far.</p>  <p>While I have great respect for the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Denis Naughten, who will be a great Minister, I was disappointed recently to read him dismissing so lightly criticisms that there might be issues of fairness and balance or left-wing bias in RTE in particular.  Therefore, I would like very much for the Minister to come to this House so we can share with him our different perspectives on the quality of public service broadcasting in this country and on issues that some of us believe need to change.  It is time for amending legislation on broadcasting and to examine the types of advertising we allow on publicly accessible channels.  We need to strengthen and indeed introduce sanctions where broadcasters, specifically tax-funded broadcasters, are found to have misused their position, been biased or lacked impartiality.  There needs to be a mechanism under which they can not only be found to have acted inappropriately but issued with sanctions to ensure it does not happen again.  That would be a healthy and helpful debate to have.  I request that the Leader ask the Minister come to the House to discuss those issues with us.</p>  <p>Very briefly, on Brexit, it is too soon for people to draw certain conclusions about what will happen as a result of what the British people have decided to do, but one thing is very clear. There is an appalling lack of political leadership in the Western world, on all sides.  We saw the British Commissioner immediately resign, instead of sticking to his post until such time as Britain does leave and doing his job.  He is not even supposed to be representing British interests at the Commission; he is supposed to be acting in the interests of the entire community.  We have seen a lack of leadership on both sides of the British referendum debate, and we have seen Mr. Juncker's comments about an amicable divorce - just appalling stuff.  The only figure I saw in recent weeks come out with honour in this-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800022#Y00300"><p>The Queen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800022#Y00400"><p>-----was Gordon Brown.  The British Labour Party would do very well to invite him back to mainstream politics in Britain and give the kind of leadership that British politics needs right now in a time of massive confusion, where leadership seems to missing on all sides.  I am not even sure that Mr. Shanahan of IDA Ireland, although he was praised in this House, should have spoken as though Britain had left for definite.  Ireland needs to be respectful of Britain and of the British people, even as it makes its case.  In conclusion, because we took the pain, out of solidarity, and because we embraced austerity - highly controversially - the EU needs to show that it really is about solidarity now and respects the needs of small nations, particularly Ireland's very special interests, in the time ahead.  That will be the test of whether it really is a project worth supporting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="16:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800022#Y00500"><p>Like my colleague Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, I rise to send out congratulations to our near neighbours and cousins in Iceland.</p> <p>Last night was one of the most joyous sporting occasions that an Irish team was not involved in.  I have nothing against England and just feel that the match was wonderful.</p> <p>I am very worried about one thing that we will talk about in the next debate.  For the past three months on public service broadcasting, on the BBC and in press statements people made racist comments.  These people were accused of being fascist and right wing but they were not.  They were racists and bigots.  We are going through a very difficult race to the bottom.  Since the referendum result a petrol bomb has been thrown at a halal butcher's shop in Birmingham and there has been a 57% increase in racist attacks.  The same situation could happen in this country so we must be vigilant. </p> <p>We need to invite the Minister for Tourism, Transport and Sport and Mr. Niall Gibbons, CEO of Tourism Ireland, to discuss the aftermath of what happened in France where supporters of the Republic of Ireland and Northern Ireland mingled together and worked closely together.  There can be a huge tourism benefit and other benefits as a result.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z00200"><p>Before I call on the Leader to reply, I advise Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh that I must rule his amendment out of order as such a debate would be repetitious of the debates on the motion to announce statutory instruments-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z00300"><p>A point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z00400"><p>Order, please.  I am speaking.  His amendment is ruled out of order as it would be repetitious of the motion to annul SI 24 of 2016, which took place last Wednesday, 22 June.  My ruling is in accordance with Standing Order 46.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z00500"><p>It took place without debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z00600"><p>Can I comment, please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z00700"><p>I cannot allow it on point of order.  I have ruled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z00800"><p>I suggest we suspend.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z00900"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.154" nospeaker="true" time="16:50:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01100"><p>On a point of order.  The Chair's ruling is preposterous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01200"><p>I ask the Senator to sit down, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01300"><p>Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh has asked for a point of order for ages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01400"><p>That is outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01500"><p>Hold on.  I have given a ruling and I am not going to allow my ruling to be challenged.  I have stated what Standing Order my ruling is in accordance with and call on the Leader to respond to the debate on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01600"><p>On a point of order, can the Leas-Chathaoirleach clarify-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01700"><p>The Senator can discuss the matter with me afterwards in the office.  Is that okay?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01800"><p>Can the Leas-Chathaoirleach clarify how this debate is the same-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z01900"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02000"><p>-----when I raised an issue that has come up-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02100"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02200"><p>-----since we had the debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02300"><p>There has been no change in the situation since.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02400"><p>This issue came up on Friday-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02500"><p>The Senator knows that he is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02600"><p>-----post debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02700"><p>Sorry, Senator, I regret that he is out of order.  I have ruled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02800"><p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach's ruling is wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z02900"><p>If the Senator wishes to discuss the matter with me then he may do so in my office afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z03000"><p>The ruling is wrong.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z03100"><p>Does Senator Ardagh wish to make a point of order?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z03200"><p>I have a point of clarification to make.  I ask Senator &Oacute; Clochartaigh to immediately withdraw his remark that Fianna F&aacute;il was complicit in misleading the Seanad last week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z03300"><p>I shall ask my question during the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z03400"><p>Sorry, Senator Ardagh, I did not hear the remark.  I call on the Leader to respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="16:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016062800023#Z03500"><p>I thank the 23 Senators who spoke this afternoon.  I join with colleagues in welcoming former Senator Mullins, his family and friends to the Gallery today.  I thank him for the valuable contribution that he made to this House when he was a Member.</p>  <p>I am happy to accept Senator Leyden's amendment to the Order of Business for a Bill to be printed.  It is not a problem from our end.  </p>  <p>Senator Ardagh, in her remarks, raised the issue of rent supplement.  It is important, as the programme for Government is adhered to and implemented, that we see the Government support people.  The rent supplement plays a pivotal and careful role because 55,000 people are in receipt of the payment.  The revised rates will provide for an increase in payments to people who live in the commuter belt areas, and in many cities and towns, which is welcome.  Indeed, &euro;450 million is paid out to people who live in private rented accommodation through the housing assistance payment and the rental accommodation scheme.  It means that 100,000 people benefit.  It is important that the Minister responsible for housing, Deputy Coveney, is allowed carry on his work of putting together a housing plan.  It would mean that more houses would be built and the crisis in social housing would end.  People would be able to live in proper and dignified conditions.  It behoves all of us to work together to ensure, at local authority level and national level, that we bring forward a scheme that assists people to realise their ambition of living in their own home.  </p>  <p>A total of 14 Senators raised the issue of Brexit and passports.  I shall not name all of the Senators.  We will have this important debate.  I thank the Senators and the party leaders, Senators Ardagh, Conway-Walsh and Bacik, for contacting me over the weekend.</p> <p>We are meeting this evening to take statements on the UK referendum result and to give the Seanad as a House an independent voice from the D&aacute;il on this issue.  It is time for leadership within the European Union.  I agree with Senator Mullen that the decision of UK Commissioner, Lord Hill, to resign was short-sighted.  What is required from the United Kingdom and from all member states is a calm and prudent approach to the plan for a UK exit.  As a country, we must ensure our interests are addressed in a careful and calm manner.  It is time for Ireland as a country to be politically united and for politicians to stand together to forge a clear path to the protection of our economic interests and our people North and South of this island.  We must work together to seek agreement at European level on issues such as the common travel area, policing and judicial arrangements and the non-return of the North-South Border.  </p> <p>Ireland is the gateway to Europe.  We now have an opportunity to stand as an enhanced jewel in the crown of Europe but this will require political leadership.  I have no doubt that the Taoiseach, the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade and the Government will seek in this regard to be leaders within the European Union.  Today and tomorrow are important staging points in beginning of the next phase of the European project.  It behoves all of us who are committed Europeans to reflect upon the institutions of Europe and the way in which democracy works in Europe so that we can make it better for all citizens.</p> <p>There has been much criticism of the European Union.  Ireland has benefited in a multiplicity of ways from its membership of the European Union, particularly economically.  This should not be forgotten.  As stated by many Senators, it is important that we now focus on the relationship between North and South.  Senator Conway-Walsh and others made reference to the Border poll.  The Good Friday Agreement is clear on that issue.  We have not lost sight of the unity by consent approach.  As a committed republican, I do not think a Border poll at this point would serve any purpose other than to further polarise and divide opinion on this island.  We must take the political gain achieved over the period of the peace process and the economic prosperity brought to our nation to ensure that the relationship between North and South continues.  </p> <p>It is equally important in the light of the decision of the UK last week that negotiations on the free movement of people, services and trade on this island are brought to a successful conclusion.  This is critical to Ireland as a nation and to Irish people.  I hope that the remaining member states of the EU will take time to reflect on the tone of their language in regard to what it means to be a member of the European Union and on the future direction of the European Union.  Hopefully, the United Kingdom will take time to reflect on how it envisages its future as part of Europe.  I am sure all Members of the House will support my call that there be no rush to racism or engagement in behaviour that in any way polarises or alienates people.  That would serve no purpose in any part of the world.</p> <p>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins raised the issue of the summer economic statement.  It was my intention to provide for a debate on that issue this week but owing to the events of last week that was not possible.  The Minister, Deputy Noonan, will come to the House on 14 July to discuss that issue.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell raised the important issue of transport and competition.  The point he raises about small print and it often not being read or understood is an important one.  There is a duty of care on the carrier not to use an airline ticket as a means of collecting revenue.  The carrier should instead work with customers.  I am happy to ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to come to the House to address that issue.</p> <p>Senator Alice-Mary Higgins also raised the issue of the national economic dialogue, which has been very successful this week.  I will endeavour to have the Minister come before the House to discuss that issue further. </p> <p>Senators Bacik and Alice-Mary Higgins called for a debate on criminal justice policy.  I am happy to ask the Minister for Justice and Equality to come before the House for such a debate.</p> <p>Senators O'Mahony, Clifford-Lee, Reilly and Hayden called for a debate on the Irish passport.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-06-28a.181" nospeaker="true" time="17:00:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>