<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Catherine Noone that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to consider the installation of phone box or similar style defibrillators in all towns and villages to facilitate identification and access.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Frank Feighan of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to set out the present position regarding the proposed development of and funding for integrated education in Northern Ireland.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter: </p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of Transport, Tourism  and Sport to consider the inclusion of Limerick city on the Wild Atlantic Way corridor. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Ray Butler of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to clarify as a matter of urgency how an imminent reduction in the service of the No. 111 bus route from Athboy to Dublin via Trim can constitute an &quot;enhanced bus service for the customers in the towns of Athboy and Trim and their environs.&quot;</blockquote> <p>I regard the matters raised by three of the Senators as suitable for discussion and have selected Senators Noone, Feighan and Byrne, who will be taken now.  I regret that I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Butler on the ground that the Minister has no official responsibility in the matter.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#A00300">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#A00450">Northern Ireland</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#A00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending.  On a visit last year to two integrated schools in Northern Ireland as Chairman of the Joint Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement, I saw at first hand the success of bringing children and staff from Catholic and Protestant traditions, as well as those of other faiths or none, together in one school.  The two schools were Strangford Integrated College in Newtownards and Hazelwood Integrated Primary and Nursery School in Newtownabbey, Belfast.  There was a clear emphasis on respecting and celebrating different backgrounds and I sensed a genuine atmosphere of tolerance, respect and curiosity among students for one another.</p> <p>A number of key issues arose during my visit.  For example, applications to the schools were increasing in number, showing a need for capital investment to provide the resources required to implement the curriculum properly.  Further investment was urgently required in one school for programmes that addressed students' special needs at an early age, thus preventing the need for interventions at later stages.</p> <p>There are 62 integrated primary and second level schools in Northern Ireland with a total of 22,000 pupils, accounting for 7% of the region's entire student population.  It is important to state that the Good Friday Agreement notes that an essential aspect of the reconciliation process is the promotion of a culture of tolerance at every level of society, including through initiatives to facilitate and encourage integrated education and mixed housing.</p> <p>A great deal of good work is being done in terms of integrated education.  As part of the island of Ireland, we must continue to play our part.  Between 2007 and 2014, the reconciliation fund of the now Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade made a total of &euro;283,000 available to the Northern Ireland Council on Integrated Education.  I would like an update on these funding resources and any further plan to support the development of integrated education in Northern Ireland.</p> <p>This is a good news story.  It was clear from my visit that integrated education could be a strong and powerful force for bringing people together and promoting genuine understanding.  I hope that the Minister of State's response will refer to more funding for integrated schools.  They have made a significant difference.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frank Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They have been at the vanguard of change in Northern Ireland and we must play our part, too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#B00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important topic for discussion.  It is an issue in which he has had a keen interest for many years and I am delighted to be in a position to update the Seanad on it.  The Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Charles Flanagan, has asked me to convey his apologies and regrets that he cannot be here.</p> <p>As co-guarantor of the Good Friday Agreement, the Government remains committed to supporting and encouraging integrated education in Northern Ireland as an essential aspect of the reconciliation process.  Considerable progress on reconciliation has been seen in the 18 years since the signing of the Agreement on 10 April 1998, but, as the Seanad will be aware, Northern Ireland continues to be, in large part, a segregated society.  Integrated education which brings together students of Catholic and Protestant traditions and those of other faiths and none offers huge potential to address the divisions that persist and help to promote a culture of tolerance throughout all communities.  It is through meaningful shared experiences such as education that young people will have the opportunity to truly begin to get to know people from different backgrounds and leave behind the burdens of the past.</p> <p>The commitment of the Irish and British Governments, as well as the parties in the Northern Ireland Executive, to encourage initiatives in support of integrated education, as well as shared education, was further stated in the 2014 Stormont House Agreement and the 2015 Fresh Start plan.  In this regard, the announcement in March 2016 by the then Secretary of State for Northern Ireland, Ms Theresa Villiers, on the release of funding in support of the Stormont House Agreement and Fresh Start commitments was a welcome development which should support the provision of additional integrated schools and facilitate the building of new facilities for a number of existing integrated schools.</p> <p>In support of the Irish Government&rsquo;s long-standing commitment in this area, the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade&rsquo;s reconciliation fund has provided financial support for many years for organisations working in the area of integrated education, including the Integrated Education Fund and the Northern Ireland Council for Integrated Education.  I take the opportunity to commend both organisations for the joint work they carry out on this issue.  Since 2011, &euro;158,000 has been provided in grants for the Northern Ireland Council for Integrated Education, including a grant of &euro;25,000 in 2015.  A further application is pending.  In the first round of 2016 funding, the Integrated Education Fund received a grant of &euro;10,000 from the reconciliation fund.  To date since 2009, over &euro;91,000 has been allocated to the Integrated Education Fund in support of its work.  In addition to this, the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, including through the Irish Joint Secretariat in Belfast, engages closely on the issue of integrated education and provides a range of additional supports for organisations working on this issue, including through the hosting of events to highlight this important aspect of reconciliation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#B00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response.  I also thank the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade and the Minister, as well as previous Ministers, for being generous with funding and the time allocated to the issue of integrated education, as well as many other cross-Border and peace initiatives across the island but particularly in Northern Ireland.  I also pay tribute to the officials of the Department in Belfast, the Republic of Ireland and further afield for the work they have done.</p> <p>This is a good news story.  Integrated education has made a huge difference in Northern Ireland.  It has been at the vanguard of change in the way education is delivered in Northern Ireland and has been of enormous help in terms of social integration.  I wish to mention one person, a great friend of mine, Baroness May Blood, who comes from the Shankill area and sits in the House of Lords.  The House will know her from the work she has done at the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly.  She has been a tireless worker on the issue of integrated education and raised &pound;15 million during the years.  I thank her and all members of the Integrated Education Fund in Northern Ireland for the work they have done.  They have made a huge difference.  It behoves us to support their great work in every possible way.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.13" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#B00350">Pre-Hospital Emergency Care</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#B00400"><p>I ask the Minister of State if it would be possible to provide defibrillators in telephone box style or similar structures in all towns and villages which would be easy to identify and access in an emergency.  The life of the teenager Tom Geaney was saved in Killarney through the use of a defibrillator.  He recently opened such a structure in Killarney, the first of its kind in County Kerry, for which a reconstructed telephone box was used.  Unfortunately, there are very few telephone boxes left in the country.  Historically, the telephone box played a huge part in Irish communities, in helping to keep families together by allowing them to communicate with one another.  The remaining telephone boxes could be used to house life-saving devices and help the public to recognise and remember the location of defibrillators.  It has been proved that use of a defibrillator significantly improves the chances of survival of someone who has an out-of-hospital cardiac arrest.  </p> <p>Earlier this month the Health Products Regulatory Authority highlighted the fact that approximately 750 automated external defibrillators required urgent safety and maintenance updates.  I have carried out some work on this issue in recent weeks and organised a meeting with Mr. Paul Bradley, director of corporate affairs with Eir, the company which owns most of the remaining telephone boxes in the country.  It is my understanding Eir has been approached by a number of local authorities with a view to converting the remaining telephone boxes into defibrillators stations.  However, Eir has a concern about liability issues.  Liability must be taken over because, as a telecommunications provider, Eir does not want to have responsibility for the maintenance of defibrillators.  I am sure this issue can be resolved.  I would be grateful if the Department took responsibility and liability for the remaining telephone boxes and converted them into defibrillator stations.  In that way, people would be able to access them out of hours.  I am sure there is technology available that would facilitate access to the nearest defibrillator station when people called the emergency services.  This is a great idea and I do not think there would be an enormous cost involved in reconstructing telephone boxes or providing similar structures which would be easily identifiable as defibrillator stations.  There are defibrillators available in many GAA clubs and other locations, but they should also be available in the centre of towns and villages.  The recent opening of the first defibrillator station in a reconstructed telephone box in Killarney by Tom Geaney illustrates the usefulness of such structures in emergencies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#B00500"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter.</p> <p>The Pre-Hospital Emergency Care Council, PHECC, is the independent statutory agency with responsibility for standards, education and training in the field of pre-hospital emergency care.  The council is the regulator for emergency medical services and its role is to protect the public.  Automated external defibrillators can be placed in cabinets which are widely available for interior and exterior deployment and use.  The PHECC has adopted the international liaison committee on resuscitation automated external defibrillator signage.  This is defibrillator signage with a specified standard attached to it.  The sign must be a green square without markers.  The safety sign requires a cross in the right hand corner as part of the requirements of the standard and a heart and flash are standard symbols that must make up the sign.  The standard allows text to be provided in a separate box to improve comprehension.</p> <p>I advise the Senator that one of the means to help to improve health outcomes in this area is through the expansion of the national first response network.  Community first responder groups comprise this national network.  They are people from local communities who are trained in the provision of basic life support and the use of defibrillators who attend a potentially life-threatening emergency in their area.  They are then able to provide for an early intervention in situations where a person has a heart attack or cardiac arrest by, among other things, resuscitation and defibrillation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Marcella Corcoran Kennedy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2339"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2339&amp;amp;pid=MarcellaCorcoranKennedy&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Cardiac First Responders Ireland which was launched in 2015 is the national umbrella organisation for community first responder groups.  It works with the National Ambulance Service, the Pre-Hospital Emergency Care Council and the centre for emergency medical science in University College Dublin.  There are 141 community first responder groups tasked by the National Ambulance Service.  If an emergency 999 or 112 call for cardiac arrest, choking, chest pain or breathing difficulties is made to the National Ambulance Service in an area where a community first responder group is established, the on-duty community first responder receives a text message from the National Ambulance Service at the same time as an ambulance is despatched with location and call details.  The community first responder goes straight to the scene and administers initial care, including defibrillation, if required, until the National Ambulance Service emergency resources arrive.</p><p>The National Ambulance Service supports the establishment of new cardiac first responder groups around the country and encourages all communities to consider the establishment of such a scheme in their areas.  I am familiar with the excellent work such groups do in my local area.  I welcome the work of Cardiac First Responders Ireland, as part of which initiative valuable life-saving assistance and help are provided.  This is especially important in non-urban areas where an immediate intervention may be required pending the arrival of an ambulance.</p><p>On the suggestion made by some local authorities on the use of existing telephone boxes, I will be pleased to convey the Senator's message in this regard to the relevant Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#C00200"><p>Who is the relevant Minister?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#C00300"><p>As the matter is one for local authorities, the relevant Minister is the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government, Deputy Simon Coveney.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#C00400"><p>While I am very pleased that the Minister of State has provided more detail about Cardiac First Responders Ireland, her response does not address the question I asked.  I appreciate her comments on the issue of emergencies, but I asked about specific structures or the installation of identifiable boxes in towns and villages.  It is heartening - the Minister of State should pardon the unintentional pun - to hear how great the emergency services are, which I do not doubt for one moment.  I will contact the Minister for Housing, Planning, Community and Local Government on the role of local authorities.  I hope my proposal will secure the backing of the Department of Health.  While the Minister of State's reply does not address the question I asked, I appreciate the information she has provided all the same.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1339" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#C00500"><p>Clear standards are in place and everyone must sign up to them.  Anyone who knows what a defibrillator looks like - Senators will have seen them in various locations - is aware that the standards are outlined clearly.  Given that no reference had been made to Eir or local authorities before my arrival in the House, the information provided by the Senator is new to me.  I have given an undertaking that I will convey the Senator's suggestion to the Minister.  It would be helpful if she were to liaise with him.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.21" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#C00600">Wild Atlantic Way</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#C00700"><p>I call on F&aacute;ilte Ireland to include Limerick city in the Wild Atlantic Way route before the commencement of the 2017 tourism season.  I also ask the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to put his weight behind my proposal.  In 2015 I submitted a motion on this issue to my local authority, Limerick City and County Council, which received unanimous support.  While we subsequently contacted F&aacute;ilte Ireland on the issue, no action has been taken to date.  Given that Limerick is the capital of the mid-west, I cannot understand the reasons the city and Shannon International Airport were not included as attractive options in the original Wild Atlantic Way project.</p> <p>The Wild Atlantic Way has developed into a phenomenal success.  Its route extends from County Donegal to Kinsale and is focused on the coastline.  It incorporates a number of well known tourist routes such as the Ring of Kerry in the county of the Acting Chairman, Senator Ned O'Sullivan, and the Connemara and County Donegal coastlines.  </p> <p>The Wild Atlantic Way vision is to create a world class, sustainable and unmissable destination brand that will engage and energise visitors in order that they will become powerful advocates and want to return for more.  This is a powerful statement.  Limerick city offers a number of excellent visitor attractions, including King John's Castle, the Hunt Museum, the Georgian quarter and Thomond Park, to name but a few.  An increasing number of overseas visitors are interested in history and culture and Limerick and its environs offer many opportunities to explore both.  There are theatres and art galleries, as well as excellent hotels, restaurants and sports venues.  Visitors to the area take in Ennis, Bunratty folk park, the castles at Bunratty and Knappogue, Lough Gur and Adare and rejoin the main route to Foynes.  Accommodation stock is concentrated in counties Cork and Kerry which account for more than half of the tourist properties and 44% of beds along the Wild Atlantic Way.  A large proportion of highlighted activities and attractions are also to be found in these counties.</p> <p>Limerick city and environs could provide for a substantial and sustainable increase in accommodation, activities and attractions in a central location along the Wild Atlantic Way route.  I cannot understand the reason Shannon International Airport is not strongly promoted as an entry point to the Wild Atlantic Way.  The airport offers easy access routes from many countries and would surely contribute to increased visitor numbers if highlighted as a convenient way of joining the Wild Atlantic Way.  The area is an ideal destination for those who would like to take a short break and explore part of the route. </p> <p>Tourism is a critical component of the health of the economy and particularly important to the western half of the country.  As well as large-scale business operations, there are numerous micro-enterprises in the region which provide much needed employment in local communities.  It is Government policy to seek to increase revenue from overseas visitors.  The Wild Atlantic Way is a key component of this policy and the inclusion of Limerick and Shannon would greatly assist in achieving this aim.  We need to maximise visitor numbers and do everything possible to extend the tourism season. </p> <p>Limerick and its environs would be an attractive addition to the Wild Atlantic Way project during the off-peak season.  I am not seeking a major change.  My proposal would provide an option for visitors who would like to experience the attractions Limerick city has to offer without travelling far from the current route.  It would add variety to the overall visitor experience, which is surely a worthwhile aim.  Limerick is not far from the Wild Atlantic Way in that the tide visits the city twice daily.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#C00800"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  The Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport is responsible for the formulation of national tourism policy, while F&aacute;ilte Ireland has operational responsibility for tourism initiatives such as the Wild Atlantic Way.  Both Ireland's Ancient East and the Wild Atlantic Way have been phenomenal additions to the tourism offering.</p> <p>The Wild Atlantic Way project was born out of a decline In visitor numbers to the west in successive years.  It is not simply a touring route but a means of guiding and attracting visitors to particular areas.  Its purpose is to guide visitors to what is on offer on the western seaboard, while also providing easy access to a range of experiences along and near the route.  Its objective is to motivate more overseas visitors to visit the west, give them reasons to linger longer and encourage them to engage with communities along the route. </p> <p>Communities on and near the Wild Atlantic Way are already using the route to generate more tourist traffic and revenue.  The route was developed using a collaborative approach in which regional steering groups were convened to inform route development.  In total, 366 feedback submissions were made containing 862 individual comments.  The initial capital funding for the agreed route was directed towards route signage and developing 188 discovery points along the route, including 15 signature discovery points.  More recently, the work involves installation of photo points and interpretation panels at all 188 discovery points.</p> <p>F&aacute;ilte Ireland is investigating the possibility of piloting a number of drives along the Wild Atlantic Way, with a view to offering visitors the opportunity to explore the breadth of visitor experiences adjacent to the route.  The purpose of this would be to encourage a greater regional spread of visitors across the country and mitigate against congestion in high traffic spots along the route.  County Limerick which is my local area and adjacent to County Kerry, from where the Acting Chairman comes, is situated within the region of the Wild Atlantic Way known as the cliff coast which stretches from Galway to Ballybunion.  Foynes Island is a discovery point along the Wild Atlantic Way route and Limerick city and Adare are identified as places of historical interest on the Wild Atlantic Way map.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Patrick O'Donovan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2316"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2316&amp;amp;pid=PatrickODonovan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Limerick city is not directly on the Wild Atlantic Way but has an important role as a gateway city and accommodation hub for the west.  It has not been included on the route as it is not a place where the land meets the Atlantic Ocean in a wild manner, even though Senator Byrne is correct in that the tide comes in and out twice a day.  Limerick is not regarded as an inland city; rather it is an estuarine city.</p><p>Limerick businesses are well-placed to take advantage of the Wild Atlantic Way initiative.  Limerick offers Wild Atlantic Way travellers an urban experience with its history, as Senator Byrne outlined.  It is extremely well-equipped to exploit the Wild Atlantic Way proposition given its ease of access, range of food, high-quality accommodation etc.  F&aacute;ilte Ireland is working closely with tourism businesses throughout Limerick to help them exploit their position close to the Wild Atlantic Way.  It has invested significantly in the Limerick tourism product over the recent past.  For example, it invested &euro;4.7 million in the redevelopment of King John's Castle as an attraction which is already exceeding visitor targets.  A number of initiatives have been progressed by Limerick City and County Council within both the city and county areas.  It is vital for the sector to increase the geographical spread of activity along the Wild Atlantic Way.  There has been enormous positive feedback from traders along the Wild Atlantic Way route over the recent past, with occupancy levels as an all-time high.</p><p>Since being appointed Minister of State with responsibility for domestic tourism, I have taken this issue to heart.  I invest a lot of time with local authorities.  Last week, I met representatives of the County and City Management Association.  We discussed the issue, specifically the development of the tourism potential in local authority areas.  It is my intention over the next short period of time, in conjunction with F&aacute;ilte Ireland and city and county managers, to examine specific initiatives that are local authority-led, supported by F&aacute;ilte Ireland and concentrated in areas that have the greatest level of immediate potential for spin-off from the Wild Atlantic Way.  I hope to be able to make an announcement to that end shortly.  I expect Senator Byrne will be pleasantly surprised by the announcement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his positive response.  It is something I have beaten the drum about for a while.  I am delighted to hear the Minister of State is willing to take my point of view on board and is working on some initiatives on tourism attractions.  I await his positive response in the near future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#D00300"><p>Senator Byrne referred to Shannon Airport.  No airports along the west coast, including Kerry, Shannon, Cork and Knock, are directly on the Wild Atlantic Way route but they all have an incredible offering.  Tourism Ireland, through its international fund for regional marketing, and F&aacute;ilte Ireland have a keen interest in making sure investment will be in place to promote ease of access for those airports, as well as for Cork Harbour and Rosslare.</p> <p>Local authorities are empowered under the Local Government Act.  As I said last week during a debate to which the Acting Chairman contributed, I would relish the opportunity to return to the Seanad for a more detailed discussion on my plans and actions for domestic tourism and tourism on the island.  Local authorities have a much stronger position and legal basis under which they can drive initiatives like those to which I have referred from a Limerick and Clare point of view - I have put them together and both managers are working on an initiative I am trying to progress.  A number of things are happening.  I would welcome the opportunity to have a proper discussion, listen to the views of Senators and have Senators hear what I am doing.  They have a strong affinity for local authorities, which are key in the development of this product.</p> <p>This is not all about branding and the Wild Atlantic Way will not go through Carnsore Point or eventually find its way into Greenore.  There will not be extensions to the Wild Atlantic Way as we know it now.  Rather, there will be future development opportunities where that brand can be used in a local, regional and national context to develop the tourism industry in adjoining areas.  That is my priority and that of the Department and F&aacute;ilte Ireland.  I hope we will have positive news in the future.</p> <p>Senators might consider having a full debate.  They are closely associated with local authority members and we could discuss how they can assist me and I can assist them in making sure that the strategies we hope to be able to deliver in the early part of 2017 can be driven by local authority members.  The Seanad has an important role to play and I would welcome the opportunity for it to assist and co-operate with me in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#D00400"><p>On a humorous note, I had the privilege of being a director of Limerick Harbour and of Shannon Foynes Port at different times.  There were some fairly wild encounters, as I am sure the Minister of State and Senator Byrne will know.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1267" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#D00450"><p>Not on the water, however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.29" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.05 a.m. and resumed at 11.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.30" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Heritage Bill 2016 - Committee Stage (resumed), to be taken at 2 p.m. and to be adjourned no later than 4 p.m., if not previously concluded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00300"><p>I wish to raise the issue of climate change.  I understand that a fantastic event was held yesterday in Buswell's Hotel to highlight the issue in a novel and practical way.  Unfortunately, I was not able to attend due to unforeseen circumstances but I was very impressed by all the feedback I received.  Fianna F&aacute;il takes climate change very seriously and we have a strong record of introducing progressive measures to tackle climate change, which is perhaps the greatest threat to the future of our children and our grandchildren.  We are fully committed to meeting the targets set out for Ireland in the 2009 EU renewable energy directive to meet 16% of our energy requirements from renewable resources by 2020.  Ireland is committed to meeting 40% of electricity demands from renewable sources with 10% for transport and 12% for heat.</p> <p>Fianna F&aacute;il is committed to meeting our 2020 targets in these areas and has detailed steps to achieving this including, but not limited to, reducing carbon emissions in home heating, reducing greenhouse emissions in agriculture, supporting transport emissions reductions and increasing renewable energies.  We also welcome the support of the D&aacute;il for the UN Paris Agreement on climate change.  The emissions reduction targets agreed at the COP21 Paris climate change conference present huge opportunities as well as challenges for Ireland.  Ireland is not fully energy sufficient and we are excessively dependent on energy importation to power homes and businesses.  Ireland should, therefore, focus on reducing energy consumption and carbon emissions rather than seeking to dramatically increase reliance on wind at a very high cost.  Other alternative renewable energy resources must also be pursued, such as bioenergy, solar and other technologies, to provide Ireland with a diversified renewable generation portfolio by 2030.  I call on the House to schedule an in-depth debate on the UN Paris Agreement on climate change today without further delay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1428" speakername="Joan Freeman" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00400"><p>Having requested last week that the Minister for Health should attend the Seanad today to answer questions I am disappointed, but not surprised, that he has not turned up or given a positive response to my request.  I repeat the request to invite the Minister to the House to debate the reduction of funding for mental health services and to question the misrepresentation of the &euro;35 million for the budget, which we now know is over two years and not one.  If I do not get a debate I will ask for the Order of Business to be suspended.  Because of the lack of concern over mental health, I note that when Pieta House opened quite recently in Waterford, 485 people attended within the first few weeks, 40% of whom were children under the age of 13.  The mental health budget must be questioned and the Minister for Health must be brought into the House to highlight how disappointing and disgraceful it is that mental health is once again the poor second cousin of the health system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00500"><p>It is with great disappointment that I raise the trolley crisis in our hospitals again.  Yesterday 588 citizens were waiting on trolleys and there were four in Mayo General Hospital, which is good and means they must be expecting a Minister again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00600"><p>That is not correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00700"><p>That is what they did.  When the Minister came on a Saturday they cleared the place, as they are ordered to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00800"><p>Repeating something again and again does not make it true.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#G00900"><p>If Senator Mulherin talks to the people there she will see for herself.  In a response to a parliamentary question by my colleague, Deputy Louise O'Reilly, the Government has admitted that the much-hailed bed capacity review promised in the programme for Government does not yet even have terms of reference framed for it.  Perhaps the Government Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute; could answer this when they stop sniping at Sinn F&eacute;in.  It is Government inaction, not complaints from the Opposition, that is the root cause of this crisis.  The programme for Government was signed off last June, it is now November and such a delay in getting a vital scheme up and running shows either incompetence or a complete lack of understanding.  We want the review to be started, staff morale to be restored and, ultimately, a free health service based on need.</p> <p>Sinn F&eacute;in advocates an all-Ireland service free at the point of need.  On such a small island there is no economic logic to having two separate health services, which results in the duplication of those services.  Day after day the Leader, in summing up, talks about Sinn F&eacute;in's economic policies.  Even this morning while speaking on "Morning Ireland", Dr. Hickey from Sligo said we had not had sufficient beds in the system since 1997, under Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael Governments separately and under the Fianna F&aacute;il-Fine Gael Government together.  That is what has been delivered by the centre right, to whom we cling desperately and are told to cling by media commentators.  In more than 19 years of their leprechaun economic policies they have still not delivered enough beds - do they need another 19 years?  I am sorry but they do not deserve another 19 years.</p> <p>My colleague, the health Minister in the Northern Ireland Executive, Michelle O'Neill, MLA, recently launched a vision for health which stresses the benefits of, and seeks to build on, already existing co-operation.  We need an all-Ireland health service and a Government that will produce sensible economic policies to look after the most vulnerable in the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00100"><p>I support Senator Joan Freeman on the importance of funding for mental health services.  In west Tallaght, there was a cluster of five suicides in a short space of time.  One of those cases involved a 15 year old young lad.  His mother's husband killed himself last year while her mother killed herself a few years ago.  She is trying to access support services because she and her 15 year old daughter are now at high risk, given the impact of three suicides in her family.  Services, however, are so under-resourced that she will wait weeks to access support services.  The ripple effect from suicide clusters means the young girl in question is at high risk of suicide ideation.</p> <p>Friends of the young lad who killed himself have set up a memorial with flowers at the wall near where he passed away.  They gather there every night.  This is their grieving process and they are trying to come to terms with it.  However, there is a stigma around it.  The other night a caller on FM 104 and others in the media told these young men and women to get over it and stop hanging around this memorial wall.  That is an absolute disgrace.</p> <p>Will the Leader invite the Minister for Education and Skills to address the Seanad to answer concerns relating to Caranua, the State body which administers the fund for survivors of institutional abuse?  This fund was intended to provide support, relief and training for those who suffered the worst treatment imaginable in the industrial schools.  The legacy of the industrial schools is one of the greatest stains on our history.  While I applaud the intention to provide State support to survivors, it is clear this fund, and how it is administered, is failing the very people it was intended to help.</p> <p>It must be kept in mind that it is an ageing population, which has access to this fund, and how important it is they are treated with respect and dignity.  Survivors have reported extraordinarily negative experiences when dealing with Caranua.  They have contacted a number of elected representatives to express their dismay.  They are a group of people who are understandably distrustful of engaging with any bureaucracy.  It is unacceptable they are being dealt with so poorly.  The delayed 2015 report of the appeal officer showed a State body being administered poorly which needs to be further investigated.  Survivors have also reported the sudden erroneous closing of active cases by the body with no adequate reasons given.  Will the Leader call on the Minister for Education and Skills to discuss this matter in the House?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00200"><p>I call Senator James Reilly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00300"><p>Clearly, the issue of mental health-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00400"><p>I apologise but I overlooked the Labour Party Member, Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, who was offering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00500"><p>So did the last Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00600"><p>I will allow Senator James Reilly to go before me.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00700"><p>That was my mistake.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00800"><p>I thank my Labour Party colleague for his generosity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H00900"><p>The bed is still warm.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.48" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01100"><p>That is open to all sorts of interpretations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01200"><p>Yes, it is but we are on the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01300"><p>They suffered for their generosity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01400"><p>The bed is made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01500"><p>On the serious issue of mental health, all sides of the House, and the other House, will acknowledge our Minister of State with responsibility for that area is hugely committed to it and has had a personal tragic experience of mental health issues in her own family.  I have no doubt she would have no problem explaining how the moneys are being spent and the Government's commitment to this area.</p> <p>However, we have limited resources.  We have wage demands right across the public sector, which will compete with the moneys we have to put into services.  We need to live in the real world.  It is all very well for the Sinn F&eacute;in leader, who has since left the Chamber because she is not interested in the responses to her delivery here, to talk about people challenging her economics.  Sinn F&eacute;in's economics seem to be everybody can have everything they want and somebody else will pay for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01600"><p>We will not subsidise the rich.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01700"><p>That is not the real world.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01800"><p>The Government gave &euro;21 million in tax relief to the rich.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H01900"><p>That is not the real world as Senator Paul Gavan knows as a trade unionist himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02000"><p>Order, please.  Senator James Reilly has only two minutes left.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02100"><p>I want to end on a positive note.  This week a new book on designing houses for people who face mental health challenges and how design can help them was published.  I commend this book and I want to take the opportunity to advertise the fact that architects, builders and planners should refer to it.</p> <p>Before I finish, there is another little bit of good news.  In St. Ita's Hospital, a large psychiatric institution-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02200"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02300"><p>Well, if I had not been interrupted so much, I would have finished sooner.</p> <p>The fine building of St. Ita's is being used as a film set with Sean Penn and Mel Gibson.  I want to ensure the moneys which accrue to the hospital as a consequence of the filming, are ring fenced and used to the benefit of the clients who reside there, not for any other purposes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02400"><p>What are they filming there?  "One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02500"><p>It is a reasonable for Senators to request a debate with the Minister of the day.  I was a bit taken aback that a request was made several weeks ago but it was not adhered to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02600"><p>That is not correct.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02700"><p>We do want to be having votes on the Order of Business to facilitate a debate on an issue and no Minister turns up.  Senator Rose Conway-Walsh raised the interview on "Morning Ireland" with Dr. Hickey and what he is projecting for the winter months for Sligo hospital.  I found it quite frightening.</p> <p>Regardless of political persuasion, and before we get into arguments about how things should be paid for and using phrases such as "leprechaun economics", we should have a reasoned debate on where the health system is going, particularly over the coming months.  In my area, there is a constant strain on the facilities at Beaumont Hospital.  There has been a request from the hospital's senior management for a major investment of &euro;45 million for a better accident and emergency department.  That is the suggestion from people at the coalface.</p> <p>It is only reasonable that when individual Senators, in good faith, make a request for the Minister of the day, be it for mental health or the overall health system, to come to the House for a debate in a non-partisan fashion, it should be adhered to and facilitated.  In fairness, the House, across the board, has worked quite well on the many issues affecting people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#H02800"><p>Last weekend, I led a delegation of the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs with Senator Gerard Craughwell, our clerk and adviser to the committee to the COSAC, Conference of Parliamentary Committees for Union Affairs, meeting in Bratislava, Slovakia.  The great concern at this meeting was Brexit and the lack of any knowledge of what is proposed by the UK Government when it triggers Article 50 next year.  All the implications of Brexit for all European Union member states are immense.  However, one realises that for Ireland, this is very serious with a 499 km border with the United Kingdom - not of our making, but of theirs - and trade of &euro;1.2 billion per week.  The Slovakian Prime Minister made the point that 70,000 of his people live and work in the United Kingdom.</p> <p>I regard the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy Charles Flanagan, as the lead Minister as far as Brexit is concerned, as the Government has decided not to appoint a separate Minister to deal with it.  Will the Leader ask him to come to the House to discuss this issue?  We must examine what we can do in the meantime.  We must plan and prepare.  One area is in passports.  There has been a massive increase in Irish passport applications from Northern Ireland, and rightly so.  People in the United Kingdom who had Irish parents or grandparents are also applying for Irish passports.  I welcome as many as is possible applying.</p> <p>There is another side to the story, however.  I am not advocating anyone to apply for a British passport.  However, if one or one's parents were born prior to 1948, when Ireland was not a declared Republic, then one has certain rights.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Irish people working in England are worried about their status after Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J00200"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J00300"><p>I know that but the time is nigh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J00400"><p>The time is up and we have to be sharp.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J00500"><p>I suggest that there be a special unit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J00600"><p>The Senator will have plenty of time to make the suggestions.  I am sure the Leader will accede to his request.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J00650"><p>I do not have as much time to write to councillors as the Leas-Chathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.74" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J00800"><p>That is a separate matter and it is not relevant to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J00900"><p>Finally, I would like to say-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01000"><p>Say it quickly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01100"><p>-----the Department should have a separate advisory section in the embassy in London to advise Irish citizens-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01200"><p>I think we hear you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01300"><p>-----on their rights and opportunities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01400"><p>We hear you.  Thank you, Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01500"><p>With regard to judicial issues, I am conscious that there is a separation of powers between the Executive and Judiciary.  I am going to read what I have to say, and I will do so in the two minutes allowed.  An issue arises over the judicial council Bill and there is much concern over it.  The Government remains completely unaware of when this Bill will actually be published.  The first motion I tabled in this House was on the establishment of a judicial council.  In fairness to the Minister, she gave a very comprehensive response and said it would be published.  Speaking in the House on 12 October, the Minister said the Bill would be published.  The Taoiseach told the D&aacute;il on 26 October that the heads of a Bill would be published in November.  The Minister, however, said just a few days ago in the D&aacute;il that she hopes the Government will be in a position to publish the legislation before the end of the year.  We read in <i>The Irish Times</i>this week that the publication of the Bill is likely to be delayed until next year.  I am not a lawyer but I am familiar with the well-known maxim, &quot;Justice delayed is justice denied.&quot;  What is holding up this judicial council?  We hear on a daily basis a plethora of arguments, both inside and outside the House, on the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross, and the appointment of judges.  This is clearly a problem for the Government.  It requires the Taoiseach to take action and a certain amount of discipline and control.  The Government is required to clarify the position on the vacancies that currently exist.  There are people queueing up in the criminal courts and there is a lack of judges.  The issue is critical and it needs to be addressed.  Is there a row going on?  Clearly, there is.  Does it need to be clarified?  Yes, it does.  Who should clarify it?  In the first instance, the Minister for Justice and Equality should come back here and tell us whether the date for the Bill has been changed.  It is my intention to issue a further and very detailed statement about this issue today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01600"><p>I agree with Senator Freeman on the issue of mental health.  I would be very happy to have a debate on it in this House.  It was only last week that it was requested, in fairness.  I am sure the Minister of State's diary has to be checked but I am sure, for the reasons outlined by my colleague, Senator Reilly, she will not have any difficulty coming to the House to explain the position.  I agree with the Senator that this must be discussed urgently.</p> <p>I wish to raise the issue of vaping.  I am no fan of smoking, nor am I a fan of vaping, besides the fact that I believe it looks a bit ridiculous.  I believed it could be a gateway to smoking for some younger people.  I have misgivings about the content of the products.  We are really just starting to discover what is in vaping products.  The Public Health England review found that vaping is approximately 95% safer than smoking, based on the best information available to date.  According to Vape Business Ireland, 99% of those who vape are ex-smokers.  Among those who have successfully quit smoking, 32% used vaping products.  This is a good indicator of how useful it can be.  Therefore, it is fair to conclude, contrary to the notion that vaping is a gateway to smoking, which I believed, that it is in reality proving to be a successful aid to smokers.  I raise this because the Government needs to clarify its position on vaping.  If vaping is continually placed in the same category as cigarette smoking and regulated as such, its benefits will not be realised.  It is imperative that we do everything we can to tackle smoking.  We have been very successful to date.  Clearly, however, placing vaping products in the same group as cigarettes is not helpful.  While it is not ideal to have people vaping, it represents a much better option.  I would be grateful for clarification from the Minister on the Department's position on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01700"><p>Yesterday, as Senators know, I brought up the issue of public service pay and stated how out of touch the Government is with how ordinary people are feeling.  I wish to raise today another issue of which the Government seems blissfully unaware, namely, the time one must wait for State benefits.  The average waiting time for the carer's allowance is 40 weeks, as we know from an answer to a parliamentary question.  The overall waiting times for some other benefits are 27 weeks for a State pension and 21 weeks, on average, for an invalidity pension.  I encountered an example of someone in Limerick who was waiting seven months to be awarded the carer's allowance.  This person had to give up work to care for a sick relative who is terminally ill.  The individual was at a huge financial loss as a result of the delay.  Does the Leader have any idea of the hurt and hardship this is causing?</p> <p>Who is in charge of this?  It is none other than the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Leo Varadkar, hailed by many as the future leader of Fine Gael.  He cannot run a tap, never mind a Government Department.  He left the Department of Health having made a hames of it, and now he is causing chaos in the Department of Social Protection, yet Fine Gael wants him as its future leader.  There are only two possibilities here: one being that Fine Gael does not know what is going on with regard to waiting times and the other being that it does not care.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01800"><p>In fairness, this is not relevant to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J01900"><p>It certainly is.  Perhaps Fine Gael has calculated on the fact that people on welfare do not vote for its members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02000"><p>The Order of Business is about what has been announced by the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02100"><p>I am asking the Leader to bring the Minister to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02200"><p>That is legitimate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02300"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02400"><p>The rest is extraneous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02500"><p>Maybe Sinn F&eacute;in should let us know how to go about changing a leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02600"><p>That is not relevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.94" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02800"><p>Order, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J02900"><p>When we talk about voodoo economics, let us talk about a Government that advocates cutting the universal social charge-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J03000"><p>The Senator is a bit giddy this morning.  Calm down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J03100"><p>-----while people are dying in our hospitals.  Let us talk about the economics that saw 66 people waiting on trolleys in Limerick just last week.  Let us talk about Dr. Emmet Kerin, who declared that elderly patients with life-threatening illnesses are refusing to go to University Hospital Limerick because of the chaotic conditions.  After six years in government, the best the Government can do is go from one crisis to another in health.  It is out of touch and shortly it will probably be out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J03200"><p>Is the Leader aware of the amount of lobbying by the alcohol industry on the Public Health (Alcohol) Bill?  I am shocked by the amount of lobbying.  I have seen it with my own eyes.  I saw seven people from the industry standing around one Deputy in the coffee dock some days ago and I was absolutely horrified.  I bumped into one Deputy who told me he had been lobbied five times in one day.</p> <p>The Bill is about public health.  It is a matter of health versus business.  We are talking about saving lives here.  Three people will die today because of alcohol.  I am dealing with the families on a daily basis.  It is shocking and I really cannot believe what is occurring.  There are Members of the Seanad who are fighting against this Bill and trying to water it down.  They have constituents in their own areas who have lost loved ones to alcohol.  It is absolutely horrendous and something needs to be done about it.  The lobbying really has to stop; it is ridiculous.  We have to stop listening to the industries whose representatives are in here fighting against saving lives.  Something has to be done about it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#J03300"><p>Three years ago at one of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly meetings, I met a professor of European history who forecast exactly what would happen after so many years of difficulty in Europe.  He forecast that the United Kingdom and United States would opt for far-right leaders.  He said that after times of difficulty, people look for a strong leader.  I asked him what he meant and he said that in the 1930s &mdash; I am not assuming the United Kingdom and United States will go down this road &ndash; the people in Germany wanted a strong leader and they got one.  We are facing very interesting and difficult challenges that arise every so many decades.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frank Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Yesterday, the National Party was due to set itself up in the State, representing the people who look at multiculturalism with dismay.  It is their right to set up a party, with whatever views they have, but I see that the hotel in question withdrew its hosting of the launch.  While we must be careful that we do not give the oxygen of publicity to a party that is against human rights, we must also allow them to effectively participate in democracy.  I am not saying they are far-right or far-left, but we need to be vigilant that parties who wish to set up in the State represent the ideals of democracy, and whatever they do I hope they live up to those ideals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K00200"><p>I have spoken already with regard to the National Maternity Hospital at Holles Street, its failure to move to the Elm Park site to co-locate with St. Vincent's University Hospital, Dublin and the amount of money - over &euro;150 million - being made available from the Government.  There is frustration at this situation.  The Health Information and Quality Authority, HIQA, has reported that Holles Street hospital is an unsuitable location.  Still we are frustrated.  Each Sunday, in one of the national newspapers, we read that the situation is about to be resolved.  Now 11 months have passed and we are still without a resolution.  We now find that the Coombe Women's and Infants University Hospital has serious hygiene issues in its operating theatres.</p> <p>What is going on in our national maternity hospitals? We have spoken about many health issues this morning but this situation is one issue that we need to address.  The arrival of a baby should be a joyous occasion; Senator Frank Feighan and his partner have recently had a baby and I congratulate them.  I know the staff are excellent but there is funding of up to &euro;200 million available to be invested in our maternity services and yet it is being constantly delayed.</p> <p>There are a number of issues that the Minister for Health needs to address in the House.  I ask that the Leader of the House schedule this.  We need to seriously look at our national maternity service and the dangers to which women and children are being exposed, not because of lack of investment from the Government but because progress is being blocked by management boards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K00300"><p>I wish to raise the issue of gender imbalance in the primary teaching sector and the message that sends out to our children.  An interesting statistic that highlights this problem shows that in the early 1960s, nearly 40% of all primary teachers were male.  Today that figure is less than 15%.  We need to get a grip on this issue because what kind of message are we sending out to our school children? Are we saying that if a person wants to be a school teacher that it is primarily a female profession? I believe that is the wrong message and it needs to be addressed.</p> <p>On a separate issue I welcome the fact the First Minister, Arlene Foster, MLA, was in Dublin to meet the Toaiseach this week.  By all accounts, from reading and seeing media reports of the meeting, it seemed to go quite well.  Perhaps the Leader could extend an invitation to the First Minister and to the deputy First Minister, to address this House on the issue of Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1418" speakername="Diarmuid Wilson" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K00400"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K00500"><p>Brexit requires an all-island approach in order to safeguard the interests of all the people who live on this island.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K00600"><p>That has already been done Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K00700"><p>That is fine, but I would like to repeat the request because I have heard no progress in that regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K00800"><p>I ask the leader to invite the Minister for Education and Skills to the House to discuss funding for third level institutions.  It has been brought to my attention that some of those campuses that are attached to main colleges are in difficulty, particularly in Castlebar where the Galway Mayo Institute of Technology, GMIT, is going through a difficult period.  This has consequences for staff and students; there are some 1,000 students and quite a number of staff on the GMIT campus.  It has consequences for the courses, the accommodation and other aspects of the provision of third level education in towns and cities.  The funding of third level education, with particular emphasis to the campuses attached to main colleges institutions, needs to be debated in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K00900"><p>The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport was in the House yesterday.  There are over 40 board appointments remaining vacant in the State, particularly in the area of harbours, etc.  The Minister must be invited back to the House as I do not believe sufficient time was made available yesterday for people to discuss the issues with him.  I ask the Leader to try and organise this as a matter of urgency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01000"><p>The Minister answered those points yesterday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01100"><p>Senator Leyden made reference to the COSAC meeting in Bratislava that he and I attended recently.  The closer we get to Brexit the more concerned I get.  I am very much aware of the work being done by the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade and by the Taoiseach.  I am not so sure the rest of Europe is as concerned or as rapid and advanced in their preparations.  It is regrettable that Ireland does not have a dedicated Minister for Brexit.  We constantly talk about our relationship with Britain.  I do not have a concern about our relationship with Britain but I have a concern about the other 26 member states and how they might look upon the Border, how they might want the Border to be closed and how they might want to dictate to us how things would be done.  The Germans at the COSAC meeting were clear that they wanted no bilateral discussions whatsoever.  They want all discussion to be done in a joint fashion through the European Union.  As the Leader knows well, Ireland does not have a seat at that table when it comes to negotiations.  It is regrettable that we do not have a Minister with responsibility for Brexit.</p> <p>I understand that Galway, Mayo, Sligo and Kerry county boards have passed a motion condemning the GAA for selling the rights to some of the championship matches to Sky broadcasting.  Senators in this House are very much aware of how difficult it is to get tickets for an all Ireland final.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01200"><p>Not if the Senator buys them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.113" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions)</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01400"><p>Please Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01500"><p>Based on the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01600"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01700"><p>-----moneys that the Oireachtas has made available to the GAA-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01800"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K01900"><p>-----I believe we should have some input into its decision to sell the viewing rights of championship matches and perhaps the Leader might find some time to debate that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K02000"><p>May I congratulate Senator Craughwell on his contribution to the COSAC meeting?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K02100"><p>Senator Leyden may not, as he has already contributed.  I invite Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile and I apologise for that interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K02200"><p>Two heavyweights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K02300"><p>We were an excellent team.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#K02400"><p>It is not even an ordinary full moon this week, it is a super moon.   A few weeks ago we had the privilege of the Taoiseach coming to the House and he committed to returning to this Chamber before the Christmas break.  The Leader will recall that during the course of the Taoiseach's contribution I asked him again about the time-frame for presidential voting rights to be extended to Irish citizens who are resident outside the State.  The Taoiseach dodged the question masterfully ; it is no wonder he is the father of the other House.  He did, however, commit to return here.  Unfortunately, on Tuesday in the D&aacute;il he indicated that there would be no referendum, as was indicated by the Minister of State with responsibility for the Diaspora and Overseas Development Aid, Deputy Joe McHugh.  The Taoiseach said it was unlikely there would be a referendum on the issue before the next Presidential election, to be held in 2018.  That is not good enough.  The Constitutional Convention - the Leader and I discussed this via Twitter the other day - was very clear in demanding the enfranchisement of Irish citizens beyond the State.  That includes people like me.  I am aware that some Senators were a bit disparaging about having a Senator from Belfast in the House, but it would also include people like Senator Billy Lawless - who is in Chicago - and the people he stands up for and represents so eloquently and capably in the House.  I would indicate to the Leader that in the North especially there is a lot of frustration, anger and hurt and it is not exclusive to Sinn F&eacute;in members or voters.  It extends across the Nationalist family.  At a time when we should be building and embedding bonds across the island we are seeing a delay and a hindrance to the ability to do that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2477"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2477&amp;amp;pid=NiallODonnghaile&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Right across the board people want the opportunity to vote for the President.  I hope the Government will take this matter seriously and reflect on it as one of human rights and equality.  It is past time it acted on it and if it does not act soon, it will hear the response from citizens in the North and among the Diaspora.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L00200"><p>Politics is very confusing and contradictory.  We have Bugs Bunny in the White House, the Famous Five in 10 Downing Street and Inspector Clouseau in the &Eacute;lys&eacute;e Palace.  I was quite surprised to hear the leader of Sinn F&eacute;in on the wireless this morning complaining about the lack of action on the system of direct provision.  I raise this matter in the context of the fact that in the last Parliament, approximately 18 months or two years ago, I introduced a comprehensive Bill that would have dealt exhaustively with it.  The Minister of State with responsibility for the issue at the time was my colleague, Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in.  He is passionately committed to dealing with it and it really looked as if he would move forward on it.  He said something would happen within a month or two, but 18 months later, nothing at all has happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L00300"><p>That is not true.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L00400"><p>Very little has happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L00500"><p>That simply is not true.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L00600"><p>Very, very little has happened.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L00700"><p>I can outline-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L00800"><p>I would welcome the opportunity to have a debate on direct provision.  I ask the Leader to arrange a debate on it in order that the matters in dispute between Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, whose work as a Minister of State I applaud, and I can be teased out.  Very little has been done.  The matter could and should be addressed and, with the impetus of Seanad &Eacute;ireann behind it, perhaps it might be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L00900"><p>Two years ago the people were given an opportunity to deliver a resounding kick to the posterior of this House.  They were urged to do so by almost all of the main political parties, with the exception of my own, Fianna F&aacute;il, but did not take the opportunity.  Less than 18% of the population felt this House should be abolished.  One would imagine that, as a result, the media would have some respect for us.  I have always been a subscriber to the maxim of Benjamin Disraeli who advised his colleagues, in the context of media comment, never to complain and never to explain.  However, an article in today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i>takes the biscuit.  I am not sure if my colleagues have read it, but it is the most po-faced, cynical article I have ever read about this House.  I will highlight just one aspect of the piece.  The columnist suggests those Senators who live more than 150 km from the House make the round trip every day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01000"><p>Come on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1394" speakername="Ned O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01100"><p>Yes.  That would mean a round journey of approximately 200 miles a day.  Given that many of us spend five full days in Dublin, it would amount to travelling 1,000 miles a week.  Would the columnist be willing to travel 1,000 miles a week to clock in to receive his salary?  The net salary for most of us is under &euro;40,000 per year.  I am breaking my own golden rule about never commenting on the media, but this article takes the biscuit.  I ask the Leader to ensure the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission or some other entity will answer it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01200"><p>There is a troubling report in this week's edition of the Farming Independent on possible abuses in the poultry sector.  Following a complaint by a chicken farmer in County Cavan, Mr. Alo Mohan, Ms Marian Harkin, MEP, raised questions at EU level about possible VAT avoidance schemes in the Irish poultry sector.  This appears to have been confirmed by the Minister for Finance, Deputy Michael Noonan, before the European Parliament.  If it is true, it is certainly embarrassing to have our dirty linen laundered at European level, but we should be grateful that it is being laundered.  However, it is the human side which concerns me more.  I am troubled by a line in Mr. Darragh McCullough's report that "Mr. Mohan ... contends that he lost out on &euro;25,000 per year because he did not participate in various VAT arrangements".  The report goes on to state Mr. Mohan ceased trading with his processor late last year and has since failed to find a new purchaser for his birds.  Ms Harkin describes Mr. Mohan as a "law abiding man, concerned only with doing the right thing," yet his family business of 60 years is no longer trading.  It is actually worse than this.  This farmer is no longer able to earn a livelihood from what was a very well kept and high quality farm.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01300"><p>I should not-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01400"><p>I am coming to my request to the Minister-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01500"><p>I should not have to advise the Senator that he should not name individuals in the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01600"><p>I accept that, but so far I have only named individuals whose affairs are already public.  I totally support what has been said and want to know what exactly is happening.  Are we talking about an abuse of power?  If the man in question and his farm family in County Cavan have done nothing wrong, why do they not have an outlet for their produce?  Are they being blackballed by their previous processor who is not an individual but, I believe, Carton Brothers and Manor Farm in Shercock, County Cavan?  Where are the other processors?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01700"><p>I am sorry-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01800"><p>Where is the competition in the market for the produce of the man in question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L01900"><p>The Senator should not make an allegation about an individual.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L02000"><p>I have not made an allegation.  I am raising a matter of serious public concern and want to know what is going on.  There is a smell and it is more than the smell of rotting chicken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L02100"><p>I thought-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L02200"><p>We have heard from the Minister for Finance, but now we need to hear from the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  There is something going on and I ask the Leader to ensure the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and his Department will look into it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L02500"><p>The Senator is over time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1401" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L02600"><p>We may need to take steps to protect the livelihood of an honest broker and prevent or punish any possible abuse of power that may be ongoing or may have occurred in the past.  Are the big corporate interests bullying the common man in County Cavan in the same way as they seem to be doing elsewhere in the world?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L02700"><p>I refer to the disgraceful situation in emergency departments in hospitals across the country.  Yesterday there were 416 individuals on trolleys in hospital emergency departments, the two worst culprits being Letterkenny University Hospital and Cork University Hospital.  In the case of the former, 26 of the 45 individuals who were awaiting an impatient bed were on trolleys.  The HSE system within emergency departments is completely dysfunctional and not fit for purpose.  A leading emergency medicine specialist, Dr. Fergal Hickey, raised awareness of this issue on "Morning Ireland" this morning.  He stated categorically that, in his professional opinion, people would die this winter as a result of the dysfunctional nature of emergency departments in hospitals.  To date, there has been no intervention by the Minister to deal with the issue.  The HSE has its head in the sand.  It is not dealing with the issue which does not only relate to emergency departments.  There are other factors at play, including the need to free up medical beds in hospitals.  However, this goes against the HSE's policy of closing community hospitals which could provide respite care and step down facilities.  I call on the Leader to facilitate a debate with the Minister for Health on the issue.  We must find out why the HSE is not meeting its own targets as set out in the winter initiative.  We must discuss the issue before people die, particularly during the critical months of December, January and February.  I appeal to the Leader to invite the Minister to come to the House to discuss the matter as soon as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#L02800"><p>I echo the points made by my colleagues about the number on patients on hospital trolleys.  Meetings have been cancelled in the emergency department at St. James Hospital this morning because staff are being pushed to the limit.  We are now at breaking point.</p> <p>I again refer to the treatment of mothers and their children.  One of the scandals that was allowed to occur in mother and baby homes in the 1960s was the carrying out of vaccine trials on women and children.  The inquiry of the Commission to Inquire into Child Abuse is the second State inquiry to investigate these vaccine trials.  It has just been discovered, as reported today, that the files of residents were altered in 2002, just weeks after the commision had sought them.  This is in keeping with the behaviour of the responsible authorities throughout various State inquiries.  One of the victims, Ms Mari Steed, was born in Bessborough in the 1960s and is listed as one of the residents who had her records changed.  She has taken legal advice and intends to make a formal complaint to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and the Data Protection Commissioner.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator M&aacute;ire Devine:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2468"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2468&amp;amp;pid=MaireDevine&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The HSE and now Tusla are in possession of the document, which outlines the changes made to these records since 2011.  It is unacceptable that they have lain there since and that no action has been taken.  The Minister needs to come before the House to explain the shocking action, which is a further wrong carried out after the terror inflicted on Mari Steed and many others across Ireland.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M00200"><p>The Senator cannot name individuals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M00300"><p>It is in the news so I can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M00400"><p>Whether it is in the news or not, we cannot do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" speakername="Maire Devine" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M00500"><p>This is about the treatment of our women, children and mothers across the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M00600"><p>Senator Ardagh raised the issue of climate change and the Minister will come before the House on 7 December for a debate on the matter.</p> <p>Mental health was raised by a number of Senators and as Leader of the House I take the request very seriously.  I try, on Members' behalf, to facilitate debates with Ministers and since the beginning of this Seanad we have had ten cross-departmental debates and a rolling debate on Brexit.  We must balance the ministerial diary with passing legislation and Private Members' time.  We have already had statements on mental health in the House but I would be happy for the Minister and the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Helen McEntee, to come to the House to discuss this issue.</p> <p>I would be happy for the Minister to come to the House to debate health, the HSE and trolleys.  Senator Gavan did not mention that the Minister for Health has secured the highest budget in the past eight years and has announced a winter initiative.  He is dealing with the pressure on emergency departments and I agree that we need more beds.  Senator Reilly asked about the role the design of houses could have in mental health issues.  I would welcome a debate on the funding for that purpose.  Senators Leyden and Craughwell commented on the COSAC meeting which they attended last week and I would be happy for the Minister to come before the House to discuss it, but the Taoiseach is the lead Minister for Brexit. </p> <p>Senator Boyhan asked about the judicial council Bill but that is a matter for the Minister for Justice and Equality.  I suggest he raise it as a Commencement matter.  Senator Noone asked about vaping, which is an important topic.  Given all we have done with plain packaging for tobacco it is something we need to address further.  Senator Black asked about lobbying but I do not know of anyone who is trying to dilute the Bill.  I am supportive of the Public Health Bill but people are entitled to lobby.  They must be registered and meetings must be recorded.  I met with Musgraves, I am happy to do so and it is recorded.  We should focus on how we can diminish the harm done by alcohol in society and I will work with Senators in this regard.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M00700"><p>Everybody accepts the Leader's good faith.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M00800"><p>Senator Feighan spoke about the new far-right party but that is a matter for them.  In answer to the point raised by Senator Humphreys, I would be very happy for the Minister for Health to come to the House to discuss maternity as it is an important issue.  Senator Gallagher raised the issue of gender in education and I would be happy for the Minister to come to the House for a debate.  The question of inviting Arlene Foster, MLA, and the Deputy First Minister has been dealt with by the CPP.  Senator Paddy Burke asked about third level education.  The Cassells report has gone to committee and the Minister has already come to this House on the matter. He is committed to returning on the matter.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell asked about the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Shane Ross.  The Minister took an inordinate amount of time in his remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M00900"><p>He took 41.5 minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01000"><p>It was unfortunate but he is committed to coming back to the House and I would be very happy for him to do so post-Christmas.  Board appointments are a matter for the Department and the Minister, not for this House.  It is a matter that has to be resolved, however.  Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile asked for the Taoiseach to come before the House but he will not be here before Christmas because we have a schedule of legislation to get through.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01100"><p>Another broken promise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01200"><p>Order, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01300"><p>The Senator attends the meetings I attend every week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01400"><p>The Senators can have their own discussion on this outside the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01500"><p>I am not going to get into a game of broken promises.  Since I came into this position I have worked in good faith with all sides of the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01600"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01700"><p>I am not going to be accused of playing a game.  I am giving an honest answer.  We have legislation to pass and if the Senator wants to be here in the first week of Christmas that is fine.  His colleagues do not, however,</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01800"><p>We are not questioning the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M01900"><p>I was a member of the Constitutional Convention and was one of only two people who missed none of its sittings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M02000"><p>On a point of order, we were not questioning the Leader but the Taoiseach.  It was he who made the promise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M02100"><p>That is not a point of order.  We will not have a debate about this now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M02200"><p>The real point of order is that we address the Chair.  We do not address each other across the Chamber.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach needs to enforce that rule.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M02300"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M02400"><p>The Minister for the diaspora and the Government are committed to exploring the issue.  If it takes time so be it because we need to make sure we do it right.  There is a profound implication in what is being proposed and we will work to make it happen.  The Constitutional Convention does not have the power to instruct but to recommend.</p><p>Senator Norris raised direct provision and there is a huge amount of work being done on that.  Senator &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in was the Minister of State and the working group is going through the 173 recommendations, of which 140 have already been implemented.  Senator O'Sullivan raised the issue of the report in <i>The Irish Times</i>today.  I have not seen the report but I would be happy to talk to the CPP about it.</p><p>Senator Mullen asked for a debate with the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Michael Creed.  It is more a matter for a Commencement debate.  Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill and others asked about health and whether I would be happy for the Minister to come before the House.  The matter Senator Devine raised today was raised by Senator Boyhan yesterday.  It is something we should talk about at a later date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M02500"><p>What about Caranua?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M02600"><p>I think the Senator's matter is more suited to a Commencement debate.</p> <p>I want to announce to the House that, from today, I am only going to reply to people who stay for the full Order of Business.  A lot of Members have left and it is not fair to those who have stayed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#M02700"><p>Everybody accepts the Leader's good faith.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.178" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.179" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 12.30 p.m. and resumed at 2 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.180" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X00050">Heritage Bill 2016: Committee Stage (Resumed)</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.181" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>SECTION 1</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.182" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Debate resumed on amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X00300"><p>The Minister was in possession.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.184" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X00500"><p>Ci&uacute;nas, le do thoil.  A new grouping has been proposed for section 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X00600"><p>On a point of order and without being discourteous to the Minister, I will express concern that this information process has been very last-minute.  We have only just received the groupings and working them out is complex.  It is bad that we are getting them at the last minute.  In the past five minutes, I have been told that three of my amendments have been ruled out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X00700"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X00800"><p>It does not help the correct processing of legislation.  I just wanted to enter that caveat first.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X00900"><p>That is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01000"><p>I thought that it would be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01100"><p>It is a caveat.  I call Senator Humphreys.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01200"><p>Go raibh maith agat.  I just wanted to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01300"><p>The Cathaoirleach said, "Senator Humphreys".</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01400"><p>I am sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01500"><p>Is this a point of order?  The Minister has possession.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01600"><p>The Minister and I joke now and again.  In earlier times, we were considered man and wife; we were never seen together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01700"><p>Now, there is a question of sexuality for you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01800"><p>Just to remind the Senators, the Minister has possession.  Does Senator Humphreys have a point to make?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X01900"><p>It is a serious point about the Bill.  A large number of amendments only appeared on Monday.  In fairness to the Bills Office, I understand why there was a delay regarding the groupings.  I suggest that the Minister take a deep breath and use this opportunity to consult offline with those Senators who have a deep interest in this matter to try to resolve the many issues that have arisen with the Bill in recent days and months and make it a true heritage Bill, rather than a hedge cutting Bill or one that fundamentally changes the canals.  That would be worthwhile for the House and the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X02000"><p>The Bill has been scheduled.  Senator Higgins.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X02100"><p>I wish to raise a point of order on the groupings.  It would have been useful had they been provided to us earlier.  I cannot rule out further points of order on the groupings as we reach them.  We have literally only seen them in the past two minutes.  While I appreciate the pressure on the Bills Office, a longer period of consideration would have been useful for all parties.</p> <p>The debate is already under way on amendments Nos. 1 and 6, which relate to the issue of road safety.  Amendments Nos. 1b to 1g, inclusive, relate to a different section and topic, namely, the canals, but they have been inserted into the ongoing debate.  On a point of order, we must finish our debate on amendments Nos. 1 and 6 before looking to debate amendments Nos. 1b and 1g, which are additional.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X02200"><p>That is a reasonable request, so we will proceed with amendments Nos. 1 and 6.  The Minister has possession.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#X02300"><p>I will respond to some of the concerns raised by Senators at our last meeting.  I recognise that hedgerows are important wildlife habitats, providing food, shelter, corridors of movement, nests and hibernation sites for many of our native flora and fauna.  It has always been my intention that the change in the timing of cutting set out in section 8 of the Bill would not interfere with any of these functions.  Therefore, the regulations that I will propose on foot of this legislation will require that any cutting in the month of August may only be of the current season's growth and should not involve the use of heavy flails.  I am doing this on a pilot basis.  It will allow for the trimming back of one year's growth on land where reseeding or tilling is taking place.  When a farmer is preparing a field for ploughing, reseeding or sowing crops, he or she will have an opportunity at that point to trim back one season's growth.  This is not about permitting the use of flails and causing the type of damage to hedgerows that was mentioned in the Chamber.  There was a great deal of scaremongering at our last meeting.</p> <p>I intend for my Department to carry out studies to determine what, if any, effects there are during the pilot phase.  The studies will involve the use of control areas where cutting within the prescribed period under the Wildlife Acts can be compared with cutting of the current year's growth under the Bill.  If farmers and others need to carry out heavier cutting of hedges, such as grubbing and flailing, they must do so during the existing permitted period, that being between September and the end of February.  This is being done on a pilot basis and is mainly for the purpose of road safety, although there are other special circumstances.  If a farmer is reseeding or sowing crops, it would make sense to cut back one season's growth at that time.</p> <p>The best advice is that heavier cutting of hedges should be carried out every three years.  If people want to get the best results out of their hedges in terms of seeds, berries and flowers, it is best to perform a light cutting every year.  This is recognised to be the best husbandry and leads to a better production of flowers, seeds and berries.</p> <p>I have addressed most of the issues save one.  The National Parks and Wildlife Service, NPWS, is a part of my Department.  NPWS staff were involved in this work throughout and managed the consultation process.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Heather Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2308"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2308&amp;amp;pid=HeatherHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I rely on the advice of the NPWS and it will draw up the guidelines and regulations and bring them to me.  It will also oversee the monitoring during the pilot phase.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Y00200"><p>Has the Minister considered the debate on the last occasion in the House during which a very important point was made by Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill, that is, that there is a substantial difference between hedges that actually face the roadway and internal hedges?  Road safety measures cannot in any sense be construed as leading to any treatment of hedges that are within the farmland and do not have any road frontage.  Has the Minister considered that?  Would she consider producing a Government amendment if Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill has not tabled one?  I have not seen one.  There is a very substantial difference between the two types of hedges.</p> <p>I have received a note that states Met &Eacute;ireann rainfall data show that extending upland burning into March makes no sense as March rainfall is greater than that in February, and that it makes much more sense to burn in the autumn, if at all.  It claims the EPA has grave reservations about the environmental impact of burning from air quality, water quality and general nuisance perspectives.  It cites the mechanical removal of gorse, for example, as often being more effective.</p> <p>A full-time farmer, a Fine Gael voter, was in touch with me to say he has been involved in nature conservation at local level and strongly urges us not to lengthen the period for hedge cutting.  He says the season for cutting back vegetation is quite long enough at present for anyone to carry out needed work.  That is a very good point.  I have an e-mail from another farmer who points out that the problem is that farmers often do not do the cutting when they have the opportunity.  They are actually making up time rather than operating on the basis of a need to cut.  They might not have cut the hedges for a couple of years.</p> <p>When one takes into account the volume we are talking about &mdash; this relates to my first point &mdash; one should consider the difference between the different kinds of hedges, namely, those that face the road and those that are internal.  The hedgerow area in Ireland is estimated to be 37% of the total forest area.  I had no idea it was so extensive.  More than one third of the entire forest area of Ireland consists of hedgerows.  I would like the Minister to consider these points.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Y00300"><p>In response to the Minister, I acknowledge it is quite difficult for her to respond to so many issues at the same time.  Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill has explained that if his proposal were accepted, it would clarify and eliminate the road safety issue in a very clear manner.  I believe there are adequate controls and that the road safety regulations could be improved to manage the roadways.  If the Government is dispensing with the myth that this is a road safety issue, it could opt for the Senator's proposal whereby internal hedges would not be cut.</p> <p>I come from a pharmaceutical background where I learned that if something is done on a pilot basis, there is normally a control area.  It has been pointed out time and again that one should not carry out a pilot programme on the Twenty-six Counties in one go.  One has to have controlled areas and understand what one is trying to find out while engaging in the pilot.</p> <p>The Minister mentioned the cutting back would just pertain to the most recent season's growth.  Although I am a Dub &mdash; my wife is from Roscommon &mdash; I realise that our rural hedgerows, rivers and canals are highways for nature to move around.  Hedgerows are important as a food source.  It is the food source that is being cut down in August.  The blackcurrants are just forming on the bushes.  That is what one is talking about cutting with regard to the internal hedges.  If we are to have a pilot study, let us have a valid one with a control area and proper criteria.  To carry out a pilot study on the basis of the Twenty-six Counties and on every single hedgerow is totally unacceptable.  I will certainly be asking the Senators to press their amendment.  It is a logical amendment.  Fianna F&aacute;il has been considered in the compromise it put forward.  I would strongly consider the compromise if I had to and if I am not successful.  There is good logic to it.  Fair dues to those concerned.</p> <p>I urge the Minister to take a breath, reflect and meet Senators who have a really keen interest in this matter between now and the next time she is in the House.  I do not expect this legislation to go through on Committee Stage at this point.  We all want to protect our heritage and canals and to ensure we have highways of nature right throughout Ireland.  The Minister will chastise me by saying the Bill went through Cabinet but it did so when we were heading towards a general election.  There was no proper consideration.  If this had been considered by my parliamentary party before then, it would have been enraged.  The more one reads this legislation, the more one worries about its name.  It is not actually about protecting our heritage; it is actually putting our canals and hedgerows in danger.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Y00400"><p>Towards the end of her speech, the Minister provided a clarification.  I have spoken to her about the position of the NPWS on this.  Where I am from, a rural area, the NPWS has quite a reputation for doing its job.  If I heard the Minister correctly, she said the legislation was put together in conjunction with the service, which falls under the remit of her Department.  The service approves of the pilot project and will be overseeing it.</p> <p>I do not doubt that Senators are genuine in what they are saying.  It is good to tease it out.  After the Minister was last in the Chamber for this debate, somebody from BirdWatch Ireland mentioned to me that the NPWS was not in favour of this measure.  Perhaps the Minister could set out the position very clearly.  Perhaps that organisation could have a role in the pilot project and an input into how it might be conducted.</p> <p>Safety is a consideration because the councils do not cut all the hedgerows; they are cut by individuals.  Senator Daly made a very valid point on the last occasion, namely, that farmers are not rushing around seeking to cut hedges unless they have to.  Road safety is one element.  For certain farming practices, such as tillage farming, which is not the most dominant practice where I am from because the land is not the best, the month of August is critical.  I refer to reseeding and the planting of winter crops, including winter barley.  It is, therefore, not just about road safety but also about accommodating farm practices in an environmentally appropriate manner while respecting habitats, ecosystems etc.  Farming is a livelihood and August is the month available to the farmers.  The weather is so unpredictable and it is a question of trying to strike a balance.</p> <p>I am minded of Senator Norris's great praise and admiration for the British hedgerows and his remarks on how neat they are.  They are neat because they are being cut, and that is what people are trying to do here also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Y00500"><p>They cut them at the appropriate time.  They have always cut them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Y00600"><p>We all know there is much better weather in the United Kingdom anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00100"><p>We should never have left the empire.  We would have had better weather if we had stayed with Britain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00200"><p>I am not so sure about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00300"><p>I welcome this.  It is a major issue particularly for farmers, and those concerned about environmental issues and birds.  I agree with that too.  As one speaker said when a pilot scheme is set up, it has to go back to the local authority.  Who will enforce it?  Who will police it?  These issues need to be addressed.  Is the Minister providing extra funding to local authorities because this will mean extra work for every local authority?  If this has to be enforced or policed, the Minister needs to let people know.  The biggest issue with introducing heritage Bills or any legislation is lack of information.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00400"><p>And lack of finance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00500"><p>That is the biggest issue Senators and councillors deal with every day.  People are not aware of legislation that comes in.  Anything that goes through here must be communicated to the public so that the people understand the legislation.  I ask the Minister to confirm that.  I listened to the Labour Senator there.  That party blocked all this when it was in government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00600"><p>Humphreys.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00700"><p>Senator Kevin Humphreys.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00800"><p>We need clarification on all this.  The Bill deals with this, that and the other, but at the end of the day unless it is policed or enforced, it will not work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z00900"><p>I thank the Minister for returning to the House.  As the debate was adjourned, it enabled us to get some more information to bring to her attention.  She spoke about the public consultation.  No report came from the consultation process.  I did some research into local authority submissions to the public consultation on the issue and found that of the 19 participating councils only four called for an extension of the cutting period, including two that were only concerned about the road-safety issues.  Three made no reference to the hedge-cutting dates and 12 indicated either no changes or even an extension to the closed season, which suggests a strong emphasis on wildlife protection.</p><p>In discussing the Part 3 provisions, the Minister said about the repeal of existing laws that would make it an offence to interfere with an office enforcing the Wildlife Act and reset fines for offences back to the 1976 levels.  I have heard that sections of the National Parks and Wildlife Service are not happy with this and regard the amendment as a danger.</p><p>Regarding the consultation and communication process, from my information the National Parks and Wildlife Service was not fully consulted.  Last week the Minister advised the Seanad that she had &quot;met with the environmental pillar&quot;.  I have three e-mails from it showing that this is not the case.  One, dated 15 June 2016, states:</p><blockquote>Dear Minister Humphreys,<br /><br />The Environmental Pillar would very much welcome the opportunity to meet with you, at your earliest opportunity, in regard to issues relating to natural heritage, regional and rural development and sustainable tourism.<br /><br />Kind regards<br /><br />Michael Ewing</blockquote> <p>A letter in response from the Department of Arts, Heritage, Regional, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs stated:</p><blockquote>I wish to acknowledge receipt of your correspondence to Minister Heather Humphreys requesting a meeting in regard to issues relating to natural heritage, regional and rural development and sustainable tourism.<br /><br />Unfortunately due to extreme time constraints on the Minister&rsquo;s diary she is unable to commit to such a meeting...</blockquote> <p>That is just one of three letters and its response showing that the environmental pillar sought to speak to the Minister and was unable to do so.  Several other NGOs, including BirdWatch Ireland and the Irish Wildlife Trust also felt they did not have the opportunity to consult with the Minister on the process.</p><p>The Department has generally not communicated very well on the Bill.  Why was a regulatory impact analysis not conducted in advance of the introduction of the Bill?  I understand this is normally part of the process, but it has not happened in this case.  As I said last week, I have consulted with many farmers, rural dwellers, landowners and members of the IFA in preparing to scrutinise the Bill.  I have yet to be convinced that an extension to the cutting and burning season is a priority for the majority of the people I have met so far.</p><p>I appeal to the Minister to adjourn the debate.  She should go back to the Department and take the time to meet the many stakeholders that represent the views of the many citizens who are concerned about the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#Z01000"><p>Before dealing with the amendment on road safety that we are debating at the moment, I want to respond to some of the issues the Minister has highlighted.  I concur with those who look for more consultation on the matter.  There are proposals here, but the proposals she spoke to today are not reflected in the legislation.  I urge the Minister to ensure that if there are amendments, if there are proposals, if there is a tightening of the focus that she wishes to put forward, then it should be put forward in the legislation here.  There may even be opportunities for Members of her party to table constructive amendments in that regard.</p> <p>The Minister spoke about only allowing one season's growth, but then spoke about heavier cutting being needed every three years.  There might be a bit of a technical contradiction.  She is making the case for heavier cutting every three years as an argument for the amendment, but then she is also saying it would only involve the current year's growth.  The heavier cutting every three years should be done in the correct six-month period and would be done in the correct six-month period because under the Bill as the Minister is describing it, that heavier periodic cutting would not be done if we are talking about a one-year growth.  It is just a technical issue, but it needs to be clarified.</p> <p>Others have spoken about the role of the flower season and berries.  Based on e-mails I have received, people are concerned over mixing things up.  We are hearing that these are agricultural proposals.  Why is the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine not putting them forward?  We were told there were concerns over road safety.  Now we see that the proposals relate to a combination of concerns over road safety and agriculture.  We need more nuanced and clearer information on that.</p> <p>The National Parks and Wildlife Service was mentioned and I am sure we will get to discuss that later.  There are serious concerns over the repeal, in later sections of the Bill, of very basic protections for those enforcing these amendments, such as National Parks and Wildlife Service, including the right to not be assaulted in the course of their duties.  That is a very serious concern.</p> <p>We talked about the weather being unpredictable and August being the month that is available.  However, there are six months.  Based on the debate, it could be suggested we are saying there should never be cutting.  There are six months of the year and while the weather in Ireland may not be as wonderful as in other parts of Europe, Ireland has a range of decent weather and within a six-month period there are usually suitable periods of time.</p> <p>Many concrete proposals have been made.  For example, much of the cutting that takes place in spring here takes place in autumn in Scotland.  I am sure we will come to that when we address the relevant section.  Perhaps the Minister might seek to add some more detailed information when we deal with that section.</p> <p>We are dealing with amendments Nos. 1 and 6 relating to road safety.  Some very important additional information has come in.  We have heard of the need for the Minister to consult with environmental groups and key stakeholders in the area.  However, speaking in the House yesterday, the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport clearly said that his role in the Department covers road transport and road safety.  He seems to be clear that road transport and road safety are within his remit.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is a question as to the reason the work should be left to the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport or whether the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Regional, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs, Deputy Humphreys, may look to engage more actively and constructively with that Minister.  This issue was raised already but could we hear whether there are attempts to do that?  The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross, stated:</p><blockquote>My Department, in conjunction with other key stakeholders, is continuing to pursue the goal of safer roads through actions across a broad range of fronts.  A mid-term review is taking place this month on the Road Safety Strategy 2013-2020, which contains 144 actions intended to make our roads safer for all users.</blockquote><p>On the specific amendment in respect of road safety will the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, let us know whether she has engaged with Deputy Ross on the mid-term review of the road safety strategy, or whether she plans to engage with the Minister on it?  Is it not the case that a mid-term review would be an appropriate place for the issue to be discussed?  Might the 144 actions to make our roads safer not be the means to address our concerns about road safety? <br/><br/>The Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport also stated: &quot;High-level meetings are being held between me, the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Justice and Equality,.... and other stakeholders....&quot; .  He is meeting other Ministers and I urge Deputy Humphreys to ensure she is also among the &quot;other stakeholders&quot; and is meeting him.  It is surprising that when road safety was being highlighted, the road safety strategy was never mentioned.  I think it would be very useful for those who are putting forward road safety concerns to put forward sensible proposals.  There were sensible proposals put forward.<br/><br/>I am strongly supportive of amendment No. 6 which offers within the existing roads legislation the appropriate place for concrete measures which allow us to genuinely strengthen the operation of section 70 of the current  Roads Act.  This is crucial.  It is not simply a matter of giving people <i>carte blanche </i>to cut the hedgerow.  We know there are many landowners who should cut back their hedgerows to make the road safer who may not request section 70 orders.  The strengthened proposals we have put forward would allow any concerned citizens to put forward a request for a section 70 order which would allow it to go through.  There is full provision legally for this at present, but our amendment strengthens its operation.  I urge Members to support amendment No. 6.  Constructive proposals have come from across the House and perhaps Senator Grace O'Sullivan will speak on that.  I hope the Minister would be willing to meet with all parties to see how that amendment could be strengthened to address all road safety concerns.  If there is a specific proposal in respect of tillage farmers, let the case be made for them in its own right and separately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#AA00200"><p>I thank the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, for coming to the Seanad again today to address Members.  As a follow-on from last week's discussion, the Minister has made it clear there are two aspects of hedgerow management, one in respect of ensuring farmers have the ability to manage hedgerows in a restricted way both for tillage and reseeding.  It is very important that farmers have an ability to ensure productive farming.  This is in some way assisting them to do that.  Second, there has been a great deal of discussion in respect of road safety.  It is very important that we try to reduce hazards and improve visibility for drivers.  I continue to get numerous calls on hedgerow management and the challenges for motorists using particular public and private roads in my area.  This provision is an important step and is a pilot project to assess its impact.  We know that hedgerows are very important as a wildlife habitat for our flora and fauna.  It is essential that an appropriate and in depth assessment is carried out to look at the potential impact, but this is not about tearing ditches down.  That was a point alluded to in last week's debate.  It is not about that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#AA00300"><p>That was never said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#AA00400"><p>It is about ensuring that we are able to have hedges managed in a specific way for two reasons, first, in respect of road safety and, second, in regard to tillage farmers reseeding their land.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#AA00500"><p>I welcome the Minister's return to the House.  I will confine my remarks to the section under review.  I raised the question of distinguishing between different types of hedgerows.  The Minister gave a commitment last week that she would consider this before Report Stage.  There are many types of hedgerow.  Senator Norris stated that 37% of all trees and shrubberies in the country are in hedgerows.  When one breaks down where hedgerows grow, the statistics show that 19% of all hedgerows are fronting onto the road network.  Tillage farmers who are planting winter barley put forward the argument for allowing them an opportunity to cut hedges in the closed period of August.  If the objective of the Bill is to address the concerns in respect of road safety and the needs of tillage farmers, let us debate whether we put it in the Bill.  To give <i>carte blanche</i>does not distinguish between the types of hedgerow.  It is not being fair to everybody.  Many citizens have raised concerns, not only to Senators but to county councillors around the country.  We need to ensure that if we are debating public policy which will impact on wildlife and agriculture, we need to be clear about the pathway to where we are going.</p><p>Amendments have been tabled on hedgerows and burning scrub, but unfortunately the Heritage Bill 2016 covers three areas, aspects of the wildlife Act, the heritage Act and the canal network.  Personally, I think this is a mistake.  There should have been a standalone Bill to deal with the canals.  Everything is being muddled up.</p><p>Farmers contacted me to question why I was holding up the passage of this Bill.  I am not delaying the Bill.  I am performing my role as a legislator to scrutinise legislation line by line, no matter how long it takes.  If the Minister wants to bring the Bill to the House next week, we can go through it all week, sitting Monday and Friday.  The Senators on this side of the House will not cause delays.  We want to debate the Bill line by line and tease out all of the concerns and provide a balanced approach to the legislation.</p><p>There are issues in regard to section 70 of the Roads Act and I am not sure if this is the appropriate way to deal with the legislation.  The first thing that needs to be enshrined in the Bill, whether it is done in this House or in the D&aacute;il, is to distinguish between the various types of hedgerow.  If we are concerned about road safety, we are only talking about the hedges that front onto roads.  I think there are approximately 300,000 ha under tillage.  Some tillage farmers grow spring barley, but it is the tillage farmers who grow winter barley who need to cut hedgerows.  I am told that only affects 4% of the farming community.  That is a small percentage and it does not affect other farmers.  There may be arguments from the farming groups to look at other aspects of hedgerows, but they should put the case out in the open so that we can discuss it publicly.  </p><p>The Minister gave a commitment that she would look at tabling an amendment on Report Stage to address the issues in regard to roads raised in the amendment tabled by Senator Grace O'Sullivan.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2261"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2261&amp;amp;pid=BrianODomhnaill&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If that is still the position, we have a major problem.</p><p>Section 6 deals with the regulations the Minister and her successors will make on hedge cutting.  If the Bill is passed in its current form the Minister would presumably would have to sign a statutory instrument or regulation for the cutting of hedges in August.  This House and the other House generally do not sit after the middle of July.  If the Minister were to sign the regulation in early or mid-July, the 28-day period for consultation with the Oireachtas may not be possible because the Houses would not be sitting and the amendments would not come before us and yet the regulation would stand.  There are issues of technicality on that.  I have previously made this point on other Bills.  If a Minister introduces regulations that are not specified in primary legislation, as is the case here, those regulations should come before the Oireachtas committee relevant to that Minister, so that they can be discussed before the 28-day period expires.  It may mean that regulations for the August hedge cutting will have to be made well in advance of the Houses going into recess, which typically happens in the second week of July.</p><p>We need to tease out those practical elements because there has to be give and take here.  Some of the concerns raised are very well founded.  I do not agree with all the amendments and other people may not agree with my position.  However, we need to achieve some form of balance which the ordinary citizen deserves.  We have to take into consideration the issues with hedgerows relating to birds.  I hope the Minister will accede to providing some leeway to satisfy the position on this side.  She should fulfil the commitment she made last week by introducing an amendment on Report Stage or facilitate it in the D&aacute;il.  Any changes that might be made in the other House would ultimately end up coming back here anyway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB00200"><p>I wish to make some general points.  Everybody is giving out about Donald Trump and he is on the lips of all the media in more ways than one.  He is the seat of misogyny, despair, sexual innuendo, abuse - he is the seat of everything.  I do not believe that for a moment.  However, I have one problem with him, which he has no concept of climate change or the protection or preservation of our environment, which is very serious.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB00300"><p>We could put the Senator in his cabinet; she would be a great woman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB00400"><p>I am wondering about the relevance to the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB00500"><p>There is a spurious link to what I am about to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB00600"><p>I hope it is not spurious.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB00700"><p>It is trumpery rubbish.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB00800"><p>Most of what I have heard in here has been quite spurious up to now.</p> <p>It is an interesting point because climate change is an enormous issue.  Protection and preservation, and the knowledge of how to protect and preserve our environment are tantamount because without our environment, none of us will be here.</p> <p>I am concerned about the Bill and I agree with Senators who say that we do not have information.  I do not see what hedgerows have to do with road safety.  I understand the lack of visibility on country roads, but road safety usually relates to speed.  There is no one reason for fatalities and accidents on the roads.  There are lots of reasons, but hedges and hedgerows are not among them.  There is a mismatch as to why road safety is sitting in the middle of this as a major reason for cutting them down when it should not be.  Road safety should not be in a heritage Bill.</p> <p>I have received hundreds of e-mails and letters from stakeholders involved with wildlife, bird watching and biodiversity; they cannot be wrong.  These are people who work in this area and know what they are talking about.  They are trying to give us advice on the Bill - mostly against it - and I want to believe them.  Again I do not have enough information.</p> <p>In the past six months I have travelled extensively throughout Ireland.  I cannot believe what I have seen.  On the previous day, Senator Humphreys alluded to the destruction of the foliage, trees and bushes on the side of the roads.  They are hacked to death by the wrong hacking instruments in order to improve visibility.  It is outrageous.  If that is the kind of hedge cutting that will happen, I give up.  They are hacked to death.</p> <p>As Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill said three major areas are involved - wildlife, hedgerows and the canals.  I am all mixed up because each of them has demands.  The Department is an arts Ministry incorporating rural revitalisation and heritage; the Minister is trying to run a huge area.  This is a part of it that is also enormous.  When we come to dealing with the canals, it deals with alteration, regulation, prevention, obligations for removal and charging, but very little about the actual cleaning.  The canals in Dublin are filthy.</p> <p>I wanted to make the general point that I am not happy about this.  We need more information and we need to look at it more closely.  We need to take advice from some of the experts.  I return to my original statement.  The US President-elect seems to know nothing about climate change and how preserve and protect our environment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB00900"><p>I seek clarification on section 8(2).  In the Minister's initial comments she mentioned one year's growth, which is not what is stated in section 8(2).  That section refers to "during the month of August ... grubbing or destroying otherwise".  Does the Minister propose deleting section 8(2) and replacing it with what she proposed at the start, which is one-year's growth and not the grubbing as specified in the Bill?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" speakername="Frances Black" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#BB01000"><p>So much has been said today.  As Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell said, we have received many letters from different organisations.  One letter from Neil Foulkes in County Leitrim sums up everything we are discussing today.  It states:</p><blockquote>I am writing to you in connection with the proposed changes to the hedge cutting dates contained Section 40 of the Wildlife Act referred to in 8(2) of the Heritage Bill. <br /><br />I am hedgerow manager and hedgerow consultant with over 25 years experience of working on hedgerows and hedgerow related matters including working with Local Authorities.  I have followed the debate in the Seanad and offer these thoughts in the hope that they might add to the ongoing discussions.<br /><br />There is a lot of genuine and justifiable concern about public health and safety in relation to roadside hedgerows.  We talk of 'public health and safety' as though the issues are straightforward, black and white but, as in all things, there are complexities.  The risk factors that influence safety issues interact in complex ways and there is no scientific method of defining road safety problems.  Obscured signs, reduced visibility at road junctions and encroachment of vegetation are obvious issues, but cutting back all roadside vegetation may be counter productive as there are aspects of hedgerows that contribute to road safety.  There needs to be a rational approach to defining and addressing safety issues that recognises the complexities involved.  The fact that health and safety issues are not black and white is reflected in the Roads Act whereby a land owner can appeal against a notification from the Roads Authority under Section 70 on the grounds that &quot;the structure (or the use of such structure), tree, shrub, hedge or other vegetation, as the case may be, is not a hazard or potential hazard to persons using a public road or does not obstruct or interfere with the safe use of a public road or the maintenance of a public road, &quot; S70 3 (a) (iii).</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Frances Black:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2474"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2474&amp;amp;pid=FrancesBlack&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Mr. Foulkes continues:</p><blockquote>As part of my work I have canvassed roads engineers and found contradictory views expressed on a number of different aspects of road safety related to roadside vegetation.  This disparity of opinion indicates the complexities involved and a need for a wider discussion on the subject.  In my experience, and I believe that most road engineers would concur, the major problem connected with the excessive growth of roadside vegetation is not landowners who want to cut hedges and cannot.  The problem is the landowners who should cut their hedges and do not do so.  The changes proposed in the Heritage Bill do nothing to address this situation.<br /><br />Road engineers are on the front line and based on my feedback from them there is a lack of clarity on the current legislative provision.  The amendments proposed to the Bill seek to provide some clarity and are a definite improvement and I was pleased to hear that the Minister agreed in principle with some of what has been put forward.  The logical place for dealing with legislative matters in connection with the management of vegetation on public roads is through section 70 of the Roads Act.  Trying to cover road safety issues and agricultural issues in one clause, as in this Bill, is a blunt approach that is unlikely to lead to good legislation.  At the very least, amendments that separate and deal with the issues individually should be considered.  However, given the level of public concern on this matter I would suggest that what is required is a full public consultation on the issue of the management of roadside vegetation so that all of the issues can be taken on board and appropriate and considered mechanisms, including, but not exclusively, legal mechanisms, can be developed and introduced. I have been recommending for a number of years that a task force, involving all key stakeholders, needs to be established to fully address this issue.<br /><br />The proposed changes to the Wildlife Act contained in the Heritage Bill are a restricted and inadequate attempt at addressing the issue of road safety and, if passed, could result in a false sense of security that the issues have been dealt with.  The fact that safety issues can arise at any time of the year but the proposed changes only relate to August shows the fallacy of this position.  If this aspect of the Bill goes through as is then the management of roadside hedges probably will be off the legislative agenda. Do we want to see a token measure that probably goes a very little way, if any, beyond the current provision in law in this regard at the expense of a full and considered approach to what is clearly an issue of huge public concern on many grounds?</blockquote><p>That is the question this wonderful man, Neil Foulkes, from County Leitrim, has asked.  He should be heard today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC00200"><p>I was unavoidably absent last week and for that reason I wish to take this opportunity to welcome my constituency colleague, the Minister for Arts, Heritage, Regional, Rural and Gaeltacht Affairs, Deputy Heather Humphreys.  I did not get the opportunity to do so last week.</p> <p>As a general point I suggest that the real and true custodians, those who have more than a vested interest in rural Ireland, are our farmers.  I come from a rural community and I know this.  With a few dishonourable exceptions the farming community of Ireland love the land, their environment and nature and they are the true custodians of these.  I mean this and I am not suggesting complete deregulation or anything of the sort.  What I am suggesting is that the House can rest assured that the farmers of Ireland can be trusted with the land and the hedgerows of Ireland.  No matter what legislative framework is in existence the love of nature and the goodwill of farmers will endure.  The passion and extraordinary connectivity they have with the beauty of the environment and the historical connection and the heritage that exists will ensure farmers will protect, by and large, our environment.  Indeed, they do this on a daily basis.  The take-up of the green low carbon agri-environment scheme by farmers and the execution of the GLAS scheme with such excellence is testimony to their love of nature and the land and their willingness to preserve it.  Department report after report confirms this.</p> <p>The Minister has made a number of reassuring points today.  I can understand why colleagues might ask the Minister for further specifics around certain points.  That is reasonable and fair enough.  As Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill has said, that is precisely why we are here.  That is our job and there is no issue with that.  The Minister made some encouraging and reassuring points.  I suggest to the House that we should accept the bona fides of the Minister and she will go through further detail on it.  The Minister said that we were only discussing the growth of the current season and that she was not facilitating nor would the legislation or any statutory instruments arising facilitate the butchering of hedges or major incisions into hedges in the month of August.  That is not what is suggested.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.237" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC00400"><p>Bear with me and we will all have our opportunity to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC00500"><p>On a point of order-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC00600"><p>There is no point-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC00700"><p>The legislation does not refer to one year's growth.  The legislation refers to growing out.  This is simply misinformation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC00800"><p>That will be dealt with by the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC00900"><p>That is not a point of order.  I will give everyone a chance to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC01000"><p>It is important to echo the point the Minister has made to the effect that what is at issue is one year's growth.</p> <p>We are not talking about heavy flails or heavy-machinery-type cutting or incision into hedges.  I will set out why I wish to emphasise this point.  A good neighbour of mine is a community activist in the town in which I live.  He is a great person for local heritage causes, a wonderful person.  He wrote to me with a concern that there was something akin to a major attack on the hedges that would amount almost to a removal of ditches in the month of August.  I am happy to have a reassurance to bring back to that good citizen.</p> <p>The Minister made a point but my good friend, Senator Alice-Mary Higgins, misunderstood the point made by the Minister.  The Minister said that ideally hedges need a heavy cutting every three years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC01100"><p>She did not.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC01200"><p>Yes, that is the case.  However, the Minister did not for a moment suggest that this should happen in the month of August.  That is not what is at issue.  What is at issue in the month of August relates to road safety.  The heavy cutting that Senator Alice-Mary Higgins is rightly concerned about would take place in the traditional season and would only happen on a three-year basis.</p> <p>There are a number of important areas for farmers.  There are difficulties with entering the land in the type of farming terrain and the area that Senator Hopkins comes from and represents so competently.  The same applies in the area that I have the privilege of representing.  Senator Gallagher is from that area too.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC01300"><p>Senator O'Reilly does not represent a geographical constituency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC01400"><p>I will take Senator Norris's point.  I am referring to the area where we have the privilege to live - I suppose we represent the entire country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.249" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#CC01600"><p>In tillage areas where there is re-seeding this is a necessary exercise.  There are specific difficulties in certain types of areas where small farming is carried out as well as wetland areas.</p> <p>It is important to emphasise another point that has been getting insufficient emphasis: this is a pilot scheme.  In other words, there is a remedy if any operational difficulties arise in terms of misuse.  I made the point at the outset that I am perfectly confident about our farmers in this area.  Any misuse, any operational difficulties or any supervisory difficulties that arise during the pilot programme will of course be corrected in future statutory instruments.  Senator Mulherin made an important point in respect of the involvement of the National Parks and Wildlife Service from the outset.</p> <p>I wish to turn to road safety.  Anyone who lives in rural Ireland who understands it.  I have great respect for Deputy Marie-Louise O'Donnell, who lives there on a day-to-day basis.  People who live there know how to negotiate their way around those areas, but there is a real safety issue here.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That issue relates to hedgerows.  I refer to the Oireachtas Library digest which was circulated prior to the Bill's introduction.  The digest quotes the Road Safety Authority's submission during the consultation period.  The reasons I insist on recording it will become apparent.  It states:</p><blockquote>From a road safety perspective, we would support the introduction of any measures that would ensure that hedges are kept in such a way as they ensure the visibility of road signage to road users all year round, do not cause damage to mirrors fitted to vehicles, especially large vehicles such as HGVs, buses and agricultural tractors.</blockquote><p>In that regard, my good colleague, Councillor Peter McVitty, who is known to many in the House and who is a leading member of the Irish Haulage Association, has been in contact with me regularly to say that this is a difficulty for his drivers and a health and safety issue for them on a daily basis.  The Road Safety Authority submission continues:</p><blockquote>The issue of overgrown hedges obscuring the visibility of drivers, road signs, and forcing vulnerable road users (pedestrians and cyclists) onto the open road is [one] that greatly exercises the public and generates much correspondence to the Road Safety Authority on the subject.</blockquote><p>This is a road safety issue and it is a concern of the Road Safety Authority.  As such, it is right that it is addressed in those terms.  It is not just an issue for tillage farmers who are seeding and those who have particularly difficult terrain with which to deal and demanding climactic conditions in which to operate.  It is an issue for ordinary people traversing the roads and, in particular, for tourists who have difficulty with the fact that we drive on the left-hand side of the road here.  It is very much a road safety issue.<br/><br/>The clarifications provided by the Minister should alleviate the fears of those who have genuine concerns about this matter.  I welcome the fact that trimming will proceed, that it will be in respect of one year's growth, that it will be controlled and that it will be subject to a statutory instrument and ministerial order.  Also, it is a pilot programme and, as such, will be constantly under review.  Taking all of that together with the rightful concerns around road safety and farming issues relating to tillage, reseeding and the variations in climate and terrain nationally, the Bill is nicely nuanced and modulated.  I make no apologies for finally reverting to the point------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD00200"><p>Will the Senator sing it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD00300"><p>-----that we can trust farmers in the context of their discretion and love of the land.  They have a passion for their hedgerows and nature.  The way they took up and so excellently dealt with GLAS should be noted.  There are abominable exceptions such as one gets in every facet of life, but with few and noticeable exceptions, I have yet to meet a farmer who does not take pride in his or her place and in its efficacy and who does not have a love of all forms of nature.  In fact, they revel in it.  They go out walking their fields and they love to have people visit so that they can proudly take them around their farms.  I do not believe that many the fears that have been expressed are well grounded.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD00400"><p>I welcome the fact that Senator O'Reilly referenced the fact that we are national representatives.  This is a good opportunity to make the case that the urban-rural divide in this debate is problematic.  Senator Black mentioned her joy in travelling across Ireland and I can attest to that having returned from Killarney at all hours of the morning and having travelled to many parts of this island.  It is not simply that the urban people in the room want to protect our hedgerows.  We acknowledge absolutely that covering front gardens in urban areas with Tarmacadam and manicured public realms also fail to support biodiversity.  The students in the Gallery will tell one that eight out of ten plants depend on insects for pollination.  Wild insects pollinate our food and improve yields for the crops we need.  The pollinators help to provide one in every three mouthfuls of our food.  I reject the urban-rural aspect of the debate.</p> <p>I did not make the following point in the previous session.  I do not want to repeat myself.  Under the good agriculture and environmental condition, GAEC, requirements of the Europe Union, farmers are obliged to maintain their land in good agricultural and environmental condition.  This concept includes the protection of soil against erosion, maintenance of soil organic matter and soil structure and the safeguarding of landscape features.  It is member states, not the European Union, that decide the exact specification of these parameters, which set the context for where matters stand today.  The current GAEC requirement states that hedge, tree or scrub cutting is not permitted between 1 March and 31 August, although hedge cutting is permitted in the period when there is a health and safety issue.  These dates help those who farm the land to avoid damaging wildlife and any changes in these cross-compliance hedge cutting dates should be based on scientific research, evidence and the impact on biodiversity and agricultural practices.  Obviously, the Department has no scientific research or evidence on which to base its policy.  The closed period for hedge cutting should remain in line with the North of Ireland and we should not depart from the GAEC position, or the all-island position, in the interests of both our society and our environment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD00500"><p>I have spoken at length on the Bill previously and will not spend that long on it today.  We are here again debating the same issues in the same vein and it is a very positive debate.  In many ways, we have teased out many of the issues that needed to be teased out.  There were questions last week as to why the agricultural community wanted to be involved and that has been clarified with regard to reseeding practices and winter grain practices.  The agricultural community is involved because this is an important step for its members in order that they can be productive.  That matter has been put to bed.</p> <p>Some Senators stated that we need to ask the experts.  Surely, the people who farm, live on and have, for generations, been so much a part of the land are considered part of that expert grouping.  They have a very strong view which is that we need to amend legislation and look at a pilot scheme.  That is why they have been so supportive of this project.  That is why we need to push ahead with this proposal and the pilot scheme.  It is not about flailing the hedges, but about trimming them for a one-year growth period on a pilot basis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD00600"><p>That is not what the legislation says.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD00700"><p>That is the new introduction by the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD00800"><p>I did not interrupt anyone else, to be fair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD00900"><p>Senator Lombard, without interruption, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD01000"><p>A two-year pilot programme where one is not going out there and tearing down the hedges by flailing them, but is only taking a trim, is an appropriate step to give the agricultural community a chance to prove what they are saying regarding the month of August and farming practices in respect of winter grain and reseeding.  It is a very logical argument and I take it on board.</p> <p>I turn to safety issues.  I spent 13 years as a proud member of Cork County Council and this was one of the key issues that came up in every election.  The Cathaoirleach is from the same part of Ireland as I am.  I note the number of phone calls one gets in rural Ireland from people regarding safety on minor roads.  It is a huge issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD01100"><p>This does nothing for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD01200"><p>It is an issue and it would be disrespectful to those rural people to deny that.  It is a big issue on the ground where people cannot walk on the roads safely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD01300"><p>That is about speeding cars.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD01400"><p>To say it is not an issue is absolutely ridiculous.  It is a big issue.  If one looks at the representations I have received over the last 13 years, they are in the tens of hundreds.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD01500"><p>It is everybody's fault but the motorist's.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#DD01600"><p>The representations were from people who wanted the opportunity to cut these hedges in August but who did not have the ability to do so.  To say it is a non-issue now is absolutely appalling.  I was elected by those people.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tim Lombard:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2466"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2466&amp;amp;pid=TimLombard&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I encourage Senators to meet them and ask for their views because they will tell them the truth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE00200"><p>You would be afraid you would be attacked by a hedgerow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE00300"><p>The Day of the Triffids.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE00400"><p>Thirteen Senators have spoken and I have fettered no one; therefore, it is now appropriate, before somebody else wishes to contribute, to allow the Minister to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE00500"><p>I thank all Senators for their contributions.  All birds are protected under existing law.  It is incumbent on anyone cutting a hedge not to interfere with nests or birds during the period in which they are allowed to cut.  It is incumbent on them under the rules and regulations not to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE00600"><p>Do they check it for nests?  I very much doubt that they do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE00900"><p>It is incumbent on anyone cutting a hedge not to interfere with birds or nests.  There seems to be a misunderstanding about this and I have consulted widely on the Bill.  The Senator referred to a letter about a meeting.  I have met those involved in the environmental pillar.  They were consulted and those concerned sent me a letter shortly after I had met them.  I do not know how many times they want me to meet them, but I have met them.</p> <p>The Bill gives the Minister the power to change the dates by regulation on a pilot basis.  The regulations will allow the trimming back of only one season's growth in the month of August.  I propose that we allow the trimming back of one year's growth on land where reseeding or tillage is taking place in the month of August.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE01000"><p>It is included in the regulations but not the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE01100"><p>No; it is included in the regulations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE01200"><p>But not in the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE01300"><p>If farmers and others need to carry out heavier cutting of hedges, including grubbing or flailing, they must do so during the existing permitted period, from 1 September to the end of February.  They cannot do so in August.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE01400"><p>Grubbing is explicitly provided for in the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE01500"><p>Everyone will be allowed back in again.  The difficulty is that there are two arguments.  If a Senator does not like what others say, he or she should allow them to make their case, after which he or she may come back in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE01600"><p>I acknowledge that the Bill may appear complex and complicated to some, but I am happy to work through it and address the Senators' concerns.  I informed Senators last week that I would accept the first part of amendment No. 6 in principle as it provided for the inclusion of notices served by a local authority on landowners under section 70(2) of the Roads Acts as an exempted activity under section 42 of the Wildlife Act.  The amendment goes some of the way towards harmonising the provisions of the Roads Acts on works to be undertaken for safety purposes along public roads with the provisions of section 40 of the Wildlife Act.  I intend, however, to consult the Attorney General on the wording of the amendment and will bring a further amendment to the House on Report Stage to reflect the proposal made by Senator Grace O'Sullivan.  I will also bring an amendment to the House on Report Stage to deal with amendment No. 1 which deals with the collective citation for the Roads Acts.</p> <p>On the second part of amendment No. 6, there are provisions in section 42 of the Act for some strict exemptions from the prohibition on burning and cutting during the closed period - an example being the destruction of noxious weeds for health and safety reasons - and during works permitted under statute.  Specifically, section 40(2)(&iacute;) provides that public bodies such as local authorities can carry out hedge cutting for public health and safety reasons.  The second part of amendment No. 6 provides that all public bodies would have to notify me of all such works during the March-August period.  I do not believe it should be mandatory for public bodies to notify me of all such works.  I would view this as an onerous task which could potentially delay the carrying out of urgent work on health and safety grounds.  I have existing powers under section 43 of the Act to request details of such works from local authorities with a statement on the public health and safety factors involved.  I have used these powers on a number of occasions in recent years.  I believe my existing powers are sufficient in this regard.  </p> <p>On the third part of amendment No. 6, the proposed additions are to the Roads Acts and relate to structures that may pose a risk to public health and safety and are outside the remit of the Bill.  I have pointed out that roads legislation, particularly on road safety, is a matter for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  Accordingly, it is not possible for me to accept the amendments as they do not pertain to an area covered by the Bill; rather, they relate to other legislation.  I will, however, bring the proposals to the attention of the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.</p> <p>It is incorrect to say my staff are against this legislation.  My staff in the National Parks and Wildlife Service will be involved in the monitoring of the pilot programme which involves the use of control areas.  I intend to launch a public awareness process in order that all stakeholders, including local authorities, landowners and members of the public, will be fully informed.  I absolutely agree with Senators that it is important that people be fully informed of the restrictions on hedge cutting and burning.</p> <p>Other issues concerning burning and hedge cutting were raised.  They are dealt with in section 8 and we will deal with them when we reach that section.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#EE01700"><p>It is important that we be very clear.  There has been a lot of conversation today about reassurances that have been made.  Unfortunately, they have been inaccurately described as points of clarification because what we have had is not clarification but a change of position.  If so, I absolutely welcome it.</p> <p>We are not having a general debate or a debate on future regulations but discussing very explicit and important legislation.  It sets out extremely clearly - I will not elaborate too much because we have many points to discuss - that a person who owns land may, during the month of August, undertake the cutting, grubbing or destruction of vegetation growing in any hedge or ditch.  It is stated this is subject to conditions that may be set out in regulations, but it is very clear that the intention of the Bill is to allow grubbing.  Unless we are talking about grubbing one-year-old hedges which I do not believe is common practice anywhere in Ireland, we really need to be clear that this is a different proposition.  The propositions we have heard are different from those set out and from what we are being asked to vote on and support.  Given the seriousness of the divergence between what is being spoken about and what is included in the legislation, we cannot wait until Report Stage.  While I give due recognition to the very nuanced contribution of Senator Brsian &Oacute; Domhnaill, I respectfully suggest we cannot wait until Report Stage.  We certainly cannot wait until the issue is dealt with in the D&aacute;il.  It is not the practice of the Seanad to abrogate its legislative responsibility and transfer it to legislators in the other House.  We have a responsibility to ensure legislation leaves this House having been given due consideration based on the deeply reflective contributions made on all sides.  If the Minister has a more nuanced approach - I might still not agree with it, but at least I would recognise that these issues were being raised - let it be reflected in the legislation.  There will be an opportunity for her colleagues in Fine Gael and others to produce more nuanced amendments to section 8 to allow it to match the description of the section we have heard in the House today, as opposed to the very explicit language used such as "grubbing or otherwise destroy".  Perhaps she might support the amendments of others.  The language used is not inflammatory; it is simply technical.</p> <p>My respected colleague Senator Joe O'Reilly spoke about farmers.  We have been very clear that they are regarded as the custodians and we will have great respect for them as such.  Many small farmers have been contacting us.  Many of them are concerned about their crops.  We have a national pollination plan for a reason.  Pollination is a key concern among agribusinesses, small farmers and various artisan producers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=11&amp;amp;day=17"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Farmers are concerned about the impact of this measure on their crops, particularly organic food crop producers and what it may mean for them.  These are serious issues for pollination and farmers.  As Senator Joe O'Reilly said, many of our farmers are in the green low-carbon agri-environment scheme, GLAS.  They have the role of caretaker, a role which many of them take deeply seriously and about which they are diligent and concerned.  I am concerned the measures set out in this Bill will weaken the case for funding for farmers in GLAS under the Common Agricultural Policy.</p><p>As Senator David Norris said, 37% of our forestry is made up of hedgerows and, as Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill said, they are part of our climate change commitments.  Hedgerows have a serious load-bearing role to play with regard to our climate change targets and commitments, as well as in the justification for GLAS funding for farmers.  Farmers have concerns which need to be addressed.  There are also concerns among tillage producers.</p><p>We also recognise the concerns about road safety.  Amendment No. 6, put forward by my colleague Senator Grace O'Sullivan, specifically proposes that an individual, a community or a school group which has a concern about a hedgerow and road safety would have the power, which they do not have currently, to seek to initiate a section 70 order which would require landowners to trim their hedges.  I do not believe many section 70 orders are refused.  Is it the case many landowners are regularly applying for section 70 orders and are having them refused by local authorities on a systematic basis?  There may be instances where that is happening.  If that is the case, let us address it.</p><p>When we talk about road safety, there is nothing in this regard for concerned members of the public, the ordinary people who live in the countryside but may not themselves be landowners.  There is nothing to give them assurance.  There is nothing to deal with their concerns with road safety.  They are still at the will of a landowner and whether he decides to cut a hedgerow.</p><p>Moreover, we are looking at a great responsibility being placed on hedgerows.  We talk about the regulations put into place.  However, in this Bill, the Minister is removing any accountability.  Given that the Bill gives no detail as to how this will be monitored, how does she then propose to monitor it?  Is it placing all the responsibility on farmers while they are not given any assistance?  We have raised constructive proposals along the lines of those in County Clare, where the local authority works with landowners and practically assists them where there are difficulties in accessing appropriate machinery.  The local authority gives them practical assistance and payment for the cutting of areas of identified concern.  There are practical proposals.</p><p>The Minister spoke about speaking to the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross.  Does she plan to engage in the mid-term review of the road safety strategy?  It is happening this month and is a key opportunity to engage in the overall road safety strategy.  What are the Minister's proposals for engaging with that?  That is an appropriate place for us to be teasing this issue out.  She said she would bring her proposals to the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  Might there be a more deep and nuanced way in which we can engage with that road safety strategy?  We will be engaging with it, as we have engaged with all stakeholders, including the IFA and other concerned groups, recognising there is expertise right across Ireland on this.  It is our shared island and we do all have a stake with what happens with this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#FF00200"><p>This is a peculiar Bill.  When I saw it on the programme for legislation originally, I thought it might have something to do with the protection of historic buildings.  It seems to me that the majority of this Bill's provisions should fall under the remit of the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport or the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine.  The Minister herself has just said that certain aspects were not contemplated by the Bill because road safety was the concern of the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  Road safety, however, is the principal argument for the Government in pushing this legislation.  If road safety is the responsibility of the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, that is where it should lie.</p> <p>With regard to hedgerow and road safety, most reasonable motorists - I am rather a rapid motorist - tend to slow down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.284" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#FF00400"><p>He does drive a Jaguar.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#FF00500"><p>I have a wonderful Jaguar.  It is unscarred by hedgerows.  I have not once been attacked by a wild hedgerow.  Most responsible motorists will slow down when they see the intrusion of vegetation onto the road.</p> <p>There is one important point quoted by the Minister from the National Parks and Wildlife Service with which I would agree.</p> <p>There is a problem with road signage and hedgerows.  A road sign warning about a dangerous turn, for example, could be obscured by vegetation.  One needs only to snip a few feet, however.  That should be the responsibility of the local authorities.  It is their signage and they should make sure it is visible.  It is not the responsibility of farmers.</p> <p>I remember when this Bill was first produced.  It was a blatant sop to the farming community in the run-up to an election.  That is why it went unopposed in this House.  It was fodder for the farmers buying their votes.</p> <p>I have been advised by certain lobbyists that there was no mention of the difference between a one-year cut and a three-year cut.  The Minister says it is in the regulations.  We have to take that on trust as we do not have them.  We are dealing with the Bill, which is very clear.</p> <p>I quoted 37% of our forestation being hedgerow.  Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill said 19% was road frontage.  There might be a little confusion here.  The figure of 19% is more than half of 37%.  If one takes a rectangle, one side only will abut the road while the other three sides will not.  Mathematically, it could not then possibly be 19%.  It must be 19% of the 37%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#FF00600"><p>No, it is 19% of 100%.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#FF00700"><p>I do not agree.  All right; I will clarify.  I did have the wonderful the distinction of getting 11 honours but failing in arithmetic in the leaving certificate, however.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#FF00800"><p>That might explain it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#FF00900"><p>That should be an encouragement to the wonderful students in the Gallery.  They should not neglect mathematics but neither should they break their hearts if they do happen to fail it.</p> <p>It seems perfectly logical that if one has a rectangle, one side cannot be more than half the sum of the other three sides.  I will leave it at that.</p> <p>The final point I want to address is this business of the whole scheme being a pilot project.  However, Senator Kevin Humphreys has dealt with that adequately.  There are no controls.  A pilot scheme deals with a fraction of the general population in order to extrapolate particular information.  That is the scientific basis of it.  One does not do an entire country as a pilot scheme.  For God's sake, that is absolute logic.  I think the Minister has got it backwards.  She is talking about a pilot scheme to find out.  She should get the scientific information before she embarks on this kind of scheme.  She might not be listening but that is what everybody is telling her.</p> <p>I want to go home to my native bog, Laois.  Wonderful Laois County Council believes no changes should be made to the current date for closed seasons until scientific evidence is produced which demonstrates these dates are no longer appropriate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.291" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00100"><p>As does County Clare.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.292" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00200"><p>Yes, County Clare.  A majority of councils have actually said this.  I am not attacking farmers.  God knows, my grandfather was a farmer.  It is spurious to suggest that there is some kind of hostility between people who happen to live in Dublin and people who are decent farmers.  Of course, they are the curators and protectors of the land and we respect them but that is no reason to give in to this Bill in an unquestioning way.</p><p>I will end by quoting from the Environmental Protection Agency.  It states:</p><blockquote>The EPA recommends that if any changes are to be considered that they be based on scientific evidence as to their relative merits as biodiversity protection and enhancement measures and as general environmental protection measures, particularly in relation to air quality and climate change.  If insufficient evidence is available at this point in time and if there is a need for further research and study of the existing controls then it would be more prudent to leave the controls as they are until such research is completed. </blockquote> <p>The Environmental Protection Agency is advising the Minister not to do this until she has the scientific evidence.  If she does not have the scientific evidence, she should not go ahead with it.  I wish the Minister would listen to these words from the body that is charged with the protection of the environment.  She can hardly challenge it.  BirdWatch Ireland, An Taisce, the Irish Wildlife Trust and the Environmental Protection Agency are all singing from the same hymn sheet.  I put it to the Minister that it is obvious that we should await the proper scientific information and that this has not been done.  The only work done on the nesting of birds and so on has been carried out by BirdWatch Ireland.  There is no scientific evidence to support the Minister's case in arguing for this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00300"><p>I must admit that I always hate following Senator Norris who is always a difficult act to follow.  I will respond to a couple of items mentioned earlier.  Senator Lombard said cutting hedges on the roadside is always an enormous issue in Cork.  It has probably been hotly debated on numerous occasions in the council chamber to such an extent that they made no submission in respect of this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.294" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00400"><p>The executive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.295" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00500"><p>One of the things we are arguing about is the executive.  There has been no submission from Cork about it.  Senator Lombard neglected to say that many rural councils were seeking better protection for hedgerows.  Senator O'Reilly taught in Ringsend College on many occasions.  However, I must say that as a teacher, he would not get away with his contribution this evening in Ringsend College.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.296" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00600"><p>He would not get away with it in Ringsend.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.297" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00700"><p>There is a Ringsend upper cut that normally resolves all these things.  What is very clear from the debate is that this is not about road safety.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.298" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00800"><p>Exactly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.299" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG00900"><p>If it was about road safety-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.300" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01000"><p>It would be the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport, Deputy Ross.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.301" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01100"><p>It would be the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport but there would be an enormous exception with regard to amendment No. 6 that clarifies absolutely, and rules out, any ambiguity in respect of road safety so it is not about road safety.  It is not about a pilot scheme because if it was, we would have a controlled area but sure we will wait two years and after a Thirty-two County pilot scheme is completed, we will see whether we have done any damage.  It might be very late for all those nesting birds who are no longer nesting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01200"><p>Farmers will look at the hedges to see if there are any nests.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01300"><p>As we bring legislation to this House, often for very good reasons, we do not bring it here for the majority of people.  I want to say very clearly that I support the farming industry and the vast majority of responsible farmers.  They will inspect their hedgerows and check to see whether there are nesting birds there.</p> <p>We bring in legislation for the ones who are irresponsible.  We do not bring in legislation on breaking into somebody's house for the vast majority of citizens.  We bring it in for the tiny majority of citizens who break into other people's houses.</p> <p>We have protection of hedgerows and we need to improve and increase them.  Amendment No. 6 takes the ambiguity out of it and safeguards hedges.  If we are being honest, we will accept amendment No. 6, tell the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport that this is needed quickly and the nonsense we constantly hear about this being about road safety and a pilot scheme would stop because it is not the case.</p> <p>A certain group among the farming community obviously has somebody's ear and has pushed this ill-thought-out and badly framed legislation.  I am going to oppose it at every amendment and every step of the way because nobody has been listening.  There have been logical arguments and discussion but they have fallen on deaf ears, certainly in the case of Senator O'Reilly, who is a very good friend of mine.  I do not know who he has been talking to and which farming friends were responsible because I imagine that the vast majority of his farming friends do not want this because they have been operating very well.  The Minister and I know exactly where this came from so let us cut out the nonsense and get back to bringing forward good and logical legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01400"><p>That is a different era.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.305" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01500"><p>I felt very insulted by the Minister's comments when she insinuated that the Bill was too complex and complicated and that she would explain it to us.  I want to assure her that everybody in this Seanad has gone through this legislation line by line and that is why there are so many amendments.  We do understand it.  It is not too complicated for us.  What is complicated to understand is why it is before this House in its current form.  I felt insulted and that it was a very patronising comment on the Minister's part.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.306" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01600"><p>Does the Minister wish to respond before we put it to a vote?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.307" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01700"><p>I was told that this Bill was too long and too complicated.  What I was saying is that I am happy to sit here with the Senators and go through it line by line because I do accept that it is complicated and that there are a number of different issues within it.  Let me make it very clear that hedges impact on road safety.  We accept that.  It can happen.  I have responsibility for the dates for hedge cutting.  I am putting forward this Bill so that under regulation and on a pilot basis, we can allow hedge cutting for the month of August.  I repeat that it relates to one season's growth on hedges on the sides of roads.  The second part of it allows cutting of one season's growth on land involving hedges that relate to tillage farmers and re-seeding.  That is it.  No other hedges will fall within those regulations.  I want to make that very clear.</p> <p>Part 1 of this amendment to the Wildlife Acts is under my remit.  I said I would look at that amendment.  Part 3 is an amendment to the Roads Act so it belongs to the Road Act, which is the remit of the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  I cannot change a Bill that falls under the remit of the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport.  I want to be clear on that.  </p> <p>I agree with Senator O'Reilly that farmers are the greatest custodians of the countryside.  We talked about urban dwellers.  Members should remember that urban dwellers are not allowed to cut their hedges.  If urban dwellers are cutting their hedges before 1 September, they should not do so.  I am trying to allow a degree of flexibility here.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#GG01800"><p>The Minister is a friend of the suburbs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.309" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1249" speakername="Heather Humphreys" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#HH00100"><p>What Senator Higgins referred to will be dealt with in section 8 of the Bill; I am currently dealing with section 1 and section 10.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.310/1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#HH00200"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: T, 17; Nl, 24.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: T, Senators Frances Black and Grace O'Sullivan; Nl, Senators Gabrielle McFadden and Michelle Mulherin..</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.310/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2016-11-17" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#HH00200">
            <divisioncount ayes="17" noes="24" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1402" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1408" vote="aye">Frances Black</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" vote="aye">Victor Boyhan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" vote="aye">Gerard Craughwell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1388" vote="aye">Maire Devine</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1419" vote="aye">John Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" vote="aye">Alice Mary Higgins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" vote="aye">Kevin Humphreys</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" vote="aye">Denis Landy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" vote="aye">David Norris</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" vote="aye">Grace O'Sullivan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1377" vote="aye">Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" vote="aye">Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" vote="aye">Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1404" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" vote="no">Colm Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" vote="no">Paddy Burke</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" vote="no">Ray Butler</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="no">Maria Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" vote="no">Lorraine Clifford Lee</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1422" vote="no">Paudie Coffey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" vote="no">Aidan Davitt</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" vote="no">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" vote="no">Maura Hopkins</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="no">Gerry Horkan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" vote="no">Gabrielle McFadden</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" vote="no">Michelle Mulherin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" vote="no">Jennifer Murnane O'Connor</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" vote="no">Catherine Noone</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1374" vote="no">Kieran O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" vote="no">Marie Louise O'Donnell</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1426" vote="no">John O'Mahony</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" vote="no">Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" vote="no">James Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" vote="no">Neale Richmond</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.310/3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#HH00200"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.311" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#JJ00100"><p>I ask the Acting Leader to report progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.312" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#JJ00200"><p>I report progress.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.313" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#JJ00300"><p>He is not acting at all; he is the real one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.314" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#JJ00400"><p>The Leader is currently acting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.315" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Progress reported; Committee to sit again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.316" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#JJ00600"><p>When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.317" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016111700002#JJ00700"><p>At 2.30 p.m. next Tuesday, 22 November.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-11-17a.318" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 4.10 p.m. until 2.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 22 November 2016.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>