<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.1" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.2" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 9:00:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.3" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.4" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.5" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#A00200"><p>I welcome Senators to the convention centre for the first time this year and I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Ossian Smyth, for coming in to answer the matters put down by Senators for the Commencement debate.</p><p>I have received notice from Senator Fiona O&rsquo;Loughlin that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on just transition funding for counties impacted by the cessation of Bord na M&oacute;na activities. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Mary Fitzpatrick of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Finance to end tax incentives for investment funds.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to provide an update on the current level of service being offered by the Passport Office; and if he will consider opening a dedicated passport office in the North of Ireland to meet increased demand. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Ivana Bacik of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to provide an update on the opening of autism spectrum disorder, ASD, units in schools in the areas of Dublin 2, 4 and 6. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator John Cummins of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to review the new household means policy to ensure maintenance payments paid out are deducted from assessable income. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Martin Conway of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the appointment of eye care liaison officers to hospital groups nationally.  </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Education to confirm the number of new school buildings which are at or have completed design stage with the planning and building unit of the Department; and whether these new builds have been designed with whole school ventilation, fossil fuel free heating systems, sufficient outdoor multi-use games areas and safe active travel infrastructure. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement on the authentication and apostilling of documents by his Department. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Garret Ahearn of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister the Health to provide an update on the proposed primary care centre for Fethard, County Tipperary. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to make a statement on the negotiations with the US Administration on the continued suspension of tariffs on beet pulp and molasses given their importance to the Irish feed industry and livestock sector. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Tim Lombard of the following matter:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Transport to make a statement on the legislative basis for the removal of abandoned vessels in Irish waters. </blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion.  I have selected Senators O&rsquo;Loughlin, Fitzpatrick, &Oacute; Donnghaile, Bacik, Cummins and Conway and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.7" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#A00300">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.8" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#A00400">Bord na M&oacute;na</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#A00500"><p>It is a pleasure to be back in the convention centre, where we had our first Seanad meeting of this mandate.  I thank the Cathaoirleach for selecting this Commencement matter, which is important to the people of Kildare, Offaly, Roscommon, Longford and Westmeath and all those impacted by job losses because of Bord na M&oacute;na.</p> <p>I cannot overstate the importance of Bord na M&oacute;na and the employment it gave in my county of Kildare.  I grew up just outside Rathangan, close to Allenwood and Coill Dubh, where Bord na M&oacute;na has since its inception in 1946 created huge employment.  The bog is important not just because of employment, but also because of heritage, the ecological system and horticulture.  The families that came to our part of the country from all over Ireland because of the employment Bord na M&oacute;na offered settled in and have become part of the area.  It is a strong legacy.  Over the last number of years, Bord na M&oacute;na has been operating in a challenging environment as we have been preparing for the transition to a more climate change-friendly environment.  There has been much discussion about the company's long-term viability, particularly in relation to the power stations in the midlands.  As a result of that, the just transition scheme was introduced to provide a solution to the problems we would have in terms of job losses and lack of employment going forward.  The just transition fund's mission was to create economic opportunity for the front-line communities and workers hardest hit by the transition away from peat.  It was to be part grant-maker and part catalyst, to provide investments to help communities create 21st-century jobs and technical assistance, to empower local leaders and communities to act, to advance economic solutions that are equitable, inclusive and low-carbon, to strengthen local economies and to build the resilience of low-income workers.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fiona O'Loughlin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2441"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2441&amp;amp;pid=FionaOLoughlin&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Many of the workers we are talking about traditionally have been low-income workers.  I have attended a number of meetings of the just transition group and I commend the work the commissioner, Kieran Mulvey, has done in this area.</p><p>My colleague, Deputy Cowen, raised in the D&aacute;il last week the slow pace of transition.  Originally, there was talk of the Government offering help, hope, assistance, initiatives, incentives and rewards, but unfortunately that has not come to fruition to date.  While we hoped to have innovation championed at this point, that has not happened.  Deputy Cowen found out in response to replies to parliamentary questions he tabled that not one job has yet been created by just transition funding and only &euro;166,000 has been drawn down to date.  In my area, Allenwood has received significant funding, but again not one cent has been received to date.  Funding has also been awarded to the Umeras peatlands project but nothing has yet been received.</p><p>I welcome the fact the Minister of State, Deputy Smyth, is here to give us an update and I invite him to visit the Lullymore heritage park in my area of Kildare to see the wonderful bog heritage we have.  I look forward to hearing his response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#B00200"><p>On behalf of the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications, Deputy Ryan, and the Government, I welcome the opportunity to set out the actions which are being taken by the Government in response to the announcement of the closure of the peat-fuelled power stations and the end of peat harvesting by Bord na M&oacute;na.</p> <p>The Government is committed to a just transition in the midlands region and has dedicated significant funding to supporting workers, companies and communities affected by the closure of the two power stations at Lanesborough and Shannonbridge.  The Government appointed Kieran Mulvey as just transition commissioner in November 2019 to assist the midlands region in the transition process.  The commissioner has made a series of recommendations to the Government on taking forward the Government's just transition response in the midlands.  A significant package of supports has been put in place in the midlands to ensure the transition away from peat-fuelled power is indeed just.  This includes the midlands retrofitting project at a cost of &euro;20 million, &euro;108 million for the Bord na M&oacute;na peatlands restoration project, &euro;30 million being made available through the just transition fund for approved projects, and &euro;19 million for the National Parks and Wildlife Service, NPWS, peatlands restoration scheme.</p> <p>The Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications approved funding of &euro;108 million for Bord na M&oacute;na's large-scale peatlands restoration project on 24 November 2020.  The plan will protect the storage of 100 million tonnes of carbon, sequester 3.2 million tonnes of carbon out to 2050, enhance biodiversity, deliver significant benefits and contribute to Ireland's target of being carbon neutral by 2050.  The scheme will encompass 33,000 ha of Bord na M&oacute;na peatlands previously harvested for peat extraction for electricity generation.  The Government funding, which will come from the climate action fund, will be bolstered by an &euro;18 million investment from Bord na M&oacute;na, which is committed to a brown-to-green transition.</p> <p>The National Parks and Wildlife Service's peatlands scheme received funding of &euro;5 million in 2020, supported by the carbon tax fund, which enabled the commencement of peatland restoration measures on almost 1,900 ha of raised bog on up to nine raised bog designated sites in the midlands region, along with the development of drainage management plans and other peatland management and conservation measures.  Bord na M&oacute;na has been contracted to manage this programme.  Work has commenced on this project, and an additional &euro;14 million has been allocated to the programme in 2021 for the restoration of a further 2,500 ha of protected raised bog, together with other peatlands conservation measures.</p> <p>Through the NPWS's peatland scheme and Bord Na M&oacute;na's peatlands restoration programme, Bord na M&oacute;na will over time engage 350 employees, some of these on the same seasonal basis that has underpinned Bord na M&oacute;na's support of the local economies to date.  Taking seasonality into account, this equates to 230 full-time equivalent roles.  These projects will support a just transition by not only avoiding job losses based in the Offaly works and across the midlands but also creating opportunities for skilled employment in these areas into the future.  The Government's just transition fund was established in mid-2020 to respond to the closures and to support the transition away from employment in peat harvesting in the most affected communities in the region.  Eight of the most affected counties were eligible to submit funding applications to the 2020 just transition fund.</p> <p>The Government announced provisional funding offers totalling almost &euro;30 million to more than 60 projects throughout the region for projects from the private sector, local authorities and communities to create a strong, green and sustainable economy.  These projects will contribute to making the midlands a more attractive and sustainable place to live and work.  Sixteen projects are already up and running in the midlands with support from the just transition fund.  These projects have created 28 full-time jobs and will support a further 175 indirect jobs.  A further five projects, worth &euro;2.5 million, have now received a grant offer letter from the Department of the Environment, Climate and Communications and will create nine jobs and 18 indirect jobs.  The Department is assisting the remaining projects to prepare them to the grant offer stage and expects to finalise grant agreements in the coming weeks.  The Department envisages a significant ramping up in expenditure in the second half of this year once grant agreements are in place and projects begin to draw down funding.</p> <p>The Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage is supporting retrofitting activities in the midland counties.  A total of &euro;20 million was allocated from carbon tax revenues to retrofit homes to a building energy rating, BER, of B2.  This project was established as a pilot programme to provide economic stimulus to the counties most affected by the cessation of peat harvesting for electricity generation, and it centres on upgrading larger batches of homes in distinct, compact geographical areas.  Offaly, Laois, Kildare, Westmeath and Longford will receive &euro;3.33 million each and Roscommon, Galway and Tipperary are to receive &euro;1.11 million each for retrofitting.  There is also an allowance for administration costs, for example, surveying, project management and BER certificate registration, as it is recognised the ramping up of this programme will bring increased administration and implementation costs to local authorities.  A total of &euro;428,902 has been recouped to local authorities to 30 April 2020 in respect of management and administration fees.  The Department is on course to finish this project in 2021, with at least 750 homes benefiting from the programme.</p> <p>Looking ahead to future just transition supports, the EU just transition fund, part of the European Green Deal, will allocate &euro;77 million to Ireland to alleviate the socioeconomic impacts of the low-carbon transition in the most affected regions.  This fund may be used to support the reskilling of workers, help SMEs to create new economic opportunities, and promote the diversification of economic activity towards low-carbon sectors and progress towards achieving the EU's 2030 climate targets and a climate-neutral economy by 2050.</p> <p>The Department of the Environment, Climate and Communication is preparing a territorial just transition plan, for approval by the European Commission, to access this funding.  This plan will set out Ireland's investment priorities and will identify the sectors and regions to be supported.  The Department envisages that the work will be completed this summer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#B00300"><p>The Minister of State has outlined some figures.  Timelines are very important in terms of the outcomes we expect to see and I would appreciate if they were put in place.</p> <p>I wish to make three brief points.  Retrofitting is very welcome and I am pleased the pilot scheme is being rolled out.  I am aware the pilot scheme is just dealing with houses within local authority housing stock, but it is important that as we move forward we would look at the opportunity for private homeowners to be able to avail of retrofitting also.</p> <p>Bord na M&oacute;na's headquarters is in Newbridge and, as it is looking at making changes, buildings will be available there.  It would be wonderful to see an educational facility such as a third level college there along the lines of An Foras Tal&uacute;ntais, which we used to have in Lullymore, that would be involved in education and research on horticulture and bogs.</p> <p>The final point I wish to make relates to horticultural peat.  It is appalling that those who are involved in the nursery industry, employing 6,000 people directly and providing 11,000 ancillary positions, still have no option at this point but to bring in peat from Lithuania and Holland, which obviously has a significant carbon footprint and is three times the price.  The Government has provided no viable alternative solution or some type of scenario whereby nursery owners could use Irish horticultural peat.  The issue must be addressed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1479" speakername="Ossian Smyth" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#C00100"><p>It is valuable to hear directly the reality on the ground from people who are living in the midlands area where the work is going on.  I am delighted to accept the Senator's invitation to visit Kildare and see for myself because there is no point in making rules in isolation of the reality.</p> <p>Second, the Senator mentioned the retrofit of private homes.  There are two major schemes.  Approximately &euro;65 million is being spent this year on retrofitting council houses and &euro;220 million is available to retrofit private homes.  That private retrofitting will require an element of grant and another portion of credit to make it happen.  These are huge schemes and they become much larger each year.  However, one needs to make sure that people have the money to do it and have confidence in their economic situation.</p> <p>I find the third level college idea very interesting, on a horticultural basis, and retraining will be key.  I am happy to talk about it with the Senator when we meet in the future.</p> <p>The importation of peat products from abroad has been mentioned.  Clearly, carbon leakage always is a concern.  In any policy that we implement to limit the production of high-carbon materials, carbon leakage must be considered.  Bord na M&oacute;na will continue to manufacture peat products until 2024.  I wish to put it on record that it is not the case that Bord na M&oacute;na has ceased production altogether.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.14" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#C00200">Tax Code</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#C00300"><p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for giving time to the House to debate my Commencement matter that calls for action by the Minister for Finance to increase the affordability and supply of housing for our citizens by introducing tax measures that will address the activities of private investment funds in the housing market.  I specifically call for the Minister for Finance to end tax incentives for investment funds to facilitate the wholesale purchase of first-time buyer's homes, and ask him to apply a financial penalty to properties that are left vacant for more than six months in areas of significant housing need.</p> <p>As the Cathaoirleach will know, I have raised this issue in the Seanad previously.  I have discussed it with the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage and the Minister for Finance.  What is required is an all-of-government response.  Since this Government was formed there has been an historic housing budget approved of &euro;3.3 billion.  There is also historic legislation that will have the State take the lead in the provision of affordable housing on State-owned lands.  There is affordable housing both to purchase and rent that will provide affordability and security of tenure for our citizens.  This is all very welcome along with the banning of co-living and the commitment to end the strategic housing development, SHD, process and review the build-to-rent model.</p> <p>At the same time as the Government is taking all of this action to increase the supply of affordable homes, and improve the affordability and security of tenure for citizens, we and the State are being undermined by the activity of private investment funds that spend tens of millions of euro a week outbidding, outspending and gazumping first-time buyers, families, single people, approved housing bodies and, indeed, the State.  The private investment funds have very deep pockets.  Of course there is room for private investment in every market but we have a housing crisis, of which the Minister of State, Deputy Fleming, and the Government are aware.  All of the efforts that we are making are being undermined when private investment firms purchase wholesale new-build homes that were designed and intended for home owners.  As the private investment funds follow the money, so too must the Government and I urge the Minister for Finance to take action.  I urge him to place a significant tax on the bulk purchase of new-build homes and introduce a tax on homes that have been left vacant for more than six months in areas that have a high demand for housing.  We need to go further.  Some of these measures can be dealt with in planning and I know that the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage has committed to do that but planning changes will only affect new developments.  We also need to improve security of tenure for renters, review the rent pressure zones, which I know that the Minister and Government have agreed to do, strengthen rent pressure zones and leverage the State's ability to fund the provision of affordable homes, to purchase or rent, on State-owned lands.  As a Government, we must prioritise the provision of affordable homes for citizens.  We must also take action to stop the undermining of all of that investment by private investment funds that can outbid, outspend and gazump the State and would-be homeowners.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#C00400"><p>I thank Senator Fitzpatrick for raising this issue.  It is a matter that everybody will understand and appreciate, especially in light of activities in the marketplace that we have seen in recent times.  The Government is committed to improving the supply of housing and affordability for first-time buyers.  It has already brought forward significant measures in the Affordable Housing Bill 2020 and the Land Development Agency Bill 2021.  These measures stand as part of an overall housing strategy that provides the highest ever budget for housing in the history of the State of &euro;3.3 billion to support the social housing needs of 28,500 additional households.</p> <p>I am aware of the recent purchase of two housing estates by an institutional investor in an area that would normally have been appropriate to first-time or second-time individual purchasers.  In the context of an unprecedented low-interest-rate environment globally, international investment in property is increasing.  While this increased investment may benefit tenants through improved choice and price moderation, it is not intended that institutional purchasers should be in competition with ordinary households to purchase completed turnkey properties.  This situation illustrates the complexity of the property market.  Housing policy must balance the needs of all tenures - private ownership, affordable or cost-rental, social housing and the private rental sector. </p> <p>Investment funds are a long-term presence in the Irish market as in all other property markets, which has been acknowledged by the Senator.  In recent Finance Acts, the Minister for Finance has made significant changes to the taxation of institutional investors in Irish property to ensure that appropriate tax is collected.  As with investment funds generally, tax occurs primarily at the level of the investor rather than in the fund.  In the case of both Irish real estate funds, IREFs, and real estate investment trust companies, REITs, withholding taxes apply on distributions to investors to ensure collection of tax revenues.  The tax treatment of these investment vehicles is kept under review, most recently in a 2019 analysis produced for the tax strategy group.  This led to the introduction of additional anti-avoidance measures in Finance Act 2019, aimed at ensuring the regimes operate as intended and preventing the avoidance of tax on property profits.</p> <p>The Minister for Finance, Deputy Donohoe, and the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, are currently working together to assess the role of institutional investors in the market and to identify targeted solutions to ensure such investment is directed at increasing overall supply within the housing market and reducing price pressures for tenants and owner-occupiers.  As the Senator and most people will be aware, this topic is a major item for discussion at the Government meeting today.  Both of the Ministers will have a discussion with all of their Cabinet colleagues with a view to making sure we come forward with proposals to deal with this matter in the immediate future.</p> <p>As regards a vacant property tax, in 2018 an independent report was commissioned by the Department of Finance and laid before the D&aacute;il to investigate vacancy levels in further detail.  The report found that the vacancy rate within rent pressure zones, excluding holiday homes, was approximately 6% but that most of these were short-term and medium-term vacancies with a low level of long-term vacancies, which is normally under 3% for Dublin, for example.  In addition, many of these properties are vacant in the long term for reason of dilapidation or because the owner is in a nursing home.  The report estimated that habitable properties that are vacant in the long term account for approximately 1% of properties in rent pressure zones.  On that basis, the consultants did not recommend the introduction of a residential vacant property tax as they did not believe it would be an effective response to deal with housing shortages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#D00100"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire St&aacute;it for his response.  I acknowledge that Cabinet is meeting today and that this item is on the agenda and will be addressed.  We all must remind ourselves, however, of what the purpose of tax is.  The purpose of tax is to raise income to invest in essential community services and supports.  In this instance, the tax system is undermining the State's investment.  It is encouraging activity that undermines the State's investment in the provision of secure and affordable homes.  I urge the Minister of State to urge all members of the Government to review the tax arrangements for private investment firms which are encouraging them to purchase wholesale new-build homes that should have been intended for homeowners.</p> <p>With regard to the tax on vacancies, I accept the Minister of State's response and that a review took place but what I am calling for specifically is a tax on new-build properties left vacant in high-pressure zones.  I am not suggesting we tax families and elderly people in nursing homes.  There is a significant issue in this regard, particularly here in Dublin city and actually right here in the docklands.  New-build properties are lying vacant when they should be available to people who are desperately in need of housing.  I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House today to address this issue but urgent action is required.  People younger than 35 have been impacted most by the pandemic from a financial perspective and they are also those oppressed most by the housing crisis.  They deserve a home, just as the Minister of State and I did.  They deserve an opportunity and they need to believe the Government is committed to tackling this challenge and to supporting them in getting a secure and affordable home.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1590" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#D00200"><p>I will deal very briefly with the taxation situation because it has been mentioned.  Real estate investment trusts, REITs, which I mentioned earlier, are companies and are obliged under the legislation to distribute 85% of their earnings every year.  A standard 25% withholding tax is levied on that.  That is twice the rate of corporation tax which companies pay.  Some people believe these companies should be paying corporation tax but, in fact, the investor pays tax at a rate of 25%, which is twice that of corporation tax.</p> <p>Irish real estate funds, IREFs, are funds rather than limited companies.  We changed the rules regarding their tax situation in 2019.  As a result, in the 2020 findings of the Revenue Commissioners, it was shown that tax was collected at a rate of 18.5%, which is very close to the standard rate of withholding tax, 25%.</p> <p>I take on board everything the Senator has said with regard to vacant properties and organisations which have no role in funding projects coming in at the end of the day, when the development is fully built, and gazumping families who wish to purchase the houses they need.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.19" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#D00250">Passport Services</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#D00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire St&aacute;it ar&iacute;s.  Bh&iacute; s&eacute; linn ar&eacute;ir don phl&eacute; ar an tairiscint Comhalta&iacute; Pr&iacute;obh&aacute;ideacha.  T&aacute; s&eacute; go maith go bhfuil s&eacute; linn ar&iacute;s.  I will preface my remarks by stressing the obvious.  I understand we are in exceptional times with regard to international travel.  While we are all positive about and encouraged by the easing of restrictions North and South, there persists clear and coherent guidance with regard to safety and international travel.  In no way do I seek to take away from or compete with that guidance with my Commencement matter.  Now that the Government has taken the very welcome decision to deem the Passport Office an essential service, which was a belated decision but nonetheless welcome, it is important that people have an understanding of the process for the resumption of services.  In addition to being a document needed for travel, a passport is also a very important document for people personally.  It is also an important form of identification.  It is the right time to hear from Government as to the mechanics of the resumption of services.</p> <p>We will also potentially be facing a backlog.  I heard the Minister, Deputy Coveney, make reference to this on the radio.  He was quite confident the Passport Office would be able to clear this backlog with reasonable speed.  I hope that is the case because I and, I am sure, colleagues here in the Seanad and across the elected political spectrum have been contacted by people who are still awaiting the passports they need for a whole range of reasons.</p> <p>I will raise a final issue which I raise consistently with Government, so I am sure it came as no surprise to officials to see it in my Commencement matter.  The trajectory of passport applications has been consistently upwards.  The staff of the Passport Office do a first-class job.  They are very effective in what they do but they deserve more investment and support to lift the burden on them, which must be very great.  I reflect on the remarks of the Secretary General of the Department who said the staff are under huge pressure as a result of the volume of passport applications being made.  It makes real practical sense for the Government to invest in additional infrastructure and in additional service provision.  This would allow for the processing of this tremendous volume of applications for passport renewals and first-time online applications in a much less stressful way.</p> <p>One of the very obvious ways in which to do this would be to open a new office in the North of Ireland.  There is a clear, demonstrable and identifiable need in that geographical area of our country.  In an emergency situation in which people have to travel, it is not always an easy process for people living in the north east, the north west or the west, whether in Ballycastle or Bundoran.  It can be quite arduous.  We need to put in the infrastructure and to provide services in those areas where they are needed and where people can most easily interface with our efficient first-class Passport Office.  When this service is so successful and so good, we should build on it and share that resource right across the island for the benefit of everyone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1573" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#D00400"><p>I thank the Senator for the opportunity to update the House on the current operational status of the Passport Service, which has significantly scaled up operations since 4 May 2021.  As an essential service, attendance levels are now increasing and I am sure the Seanad will support me in commending the staff of the Passport Service on the emergency services they operated throughout the pandemic and for their commitment to returning to the Passport Office issuing sites as restrictions have eased.</p> <p>At the end of April, there were approximately 89,000 online passport applications in the system.  Taking into account measures to ensure a safe workplace, I am confident these applications can be processed in six to eight weeks.  We are working to process all applications and to return to more reliable turnaround times for our customers by the end of June.</p> <p>Since we began to increase service levels on 4 May 2021, the Passport Service has issued more than 12,200 passports.  There are currently approximately 4,000 more at the final stages of processing.  The Passport Service's goal is to process all passport applications on hand by the end of June 2021 and to ensure we would have the capacity for high levels of anticipated demand for passport applications were current travel restrictions to ease.</p> <p>The Senator correctly notes the Passport Service has seen an annual increase in the number of passports applied for, peaking in 2019 when approximately 935,000 passports were issued.  Our investment in the passport reform programme has focused on ensuring the system is robust enough to support that continuously growing global demand for passports.  It is not intended to open a dedicated passport office in Northern Ireland as we are satisfied we currently have the capacity to meet that demand.  I and my colleagues in Government very much look forward to a return to normal levels of service and to there being shorter turnaround times for our citizens applying from Northern Ireland.</p> <p>I underline that no matter where in the world our citizens are living and applying from, all applications receive the same priority.  We achieve this by processing based on date of receipt and type of application.  For example, the passport online system operates from a central pool of applications which can be processed by staff in any of our three locations.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Colm Brophy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2427"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2427&amp;amp;pid=ColmBrophy&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This allows us to react quickly to daily demand, by distributing the work to where we have capacity and also to match the skill set of our resources to the work that needs to be done. This has dramatically improved the processing times for adult renewals, where the information is the same as the customer's previous passport.  During the highest level of restrictions, Passport Office staff processed approximately 40,000 of these applications.  Where a customer is required to submit supporting documentation, such as when changing his or her name, applying on behalf of a child or as a first-time applicant, the supporting documents are sent to a dedicated location where highly skilled staff verify the documents and prepare them for processing for all three offices.</p><p>I know that for some customers the use of online services is challenging, but it is important to highlight that the online service is extremely easy to use.  Passport Online has won awards for its user-friendly process, including a National Adult Literacy Agency, NALA, award for the use of plain English.  Many customers find that it is very quick, taking only ten minutes to complete, and I would encourage everyone to try it.  Where a customer does not wish to use the passport online system, they will be able to use the paper based Passport Express, or Northern Ireland Passport Express, system later in the year, but the turnaround times for this service will continue to be much longer than Passport Online because of the differences in the efficiencies in processing applications.  It is important to point out that in the event that an applicant has urgent or emergency reasons for requiring a passport, he or she should contact the Passport Office, customer service hub by webchat to make it aware of the situation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for the update on the safe return of the passport service.  I wish staff well and every success in getting back to work safely and clearing the backlog.</p> <p>He referenced the three offices.  There are three offices in specific locations on this island, but there is a large geographical deficit and infrastructural void in terms of this important and much utilised service.  I do not question the bona fides of the Passport Office staff and their dedication, but there are competing narratives here.  We are told of a first-class service, but we are also hearing from the Secretary General of the Department of Foreign Affairs that staff are under huge stress.  If this first-class service is being delivered because workers are under significant stress, we can do much better than that.  There is a clear, coherent and justifiable case for an expansion of the Passport Office.  I again thank the Minister of State for coming here today to address the matter, but it is not one I will be letting go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1573" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#E00300"><p>It is important to note that the passport reform programme continues to deliver major upgrades for the passport services technology platform and business process as well as for the customer service experience.  It is also worth noting that the development of the online service is the future direction of improvements within the passport system.  The appropriate way to speed up delivery and the provision of a better service to people wishing to obtain passports is through that process.  It also has tremendous benefits for people working within the system because it enables them to process more passports for people in a better and quicker way.</p> <p>The passport online system was expanded in April 2021 to include first-time applicants in Australia, Canada, New Zealand and the US.  This means that 98% of Irish citizens worldwide can avail of this service.  This improved delivery and resilience in 2022 will continue when we expect a substantial increase in applications.  As indicated, there was a drop in the overall number of applications this year as a result of the pandemic.  Over the next month, improvements, including the integration of passport online with MyGovID, and further enhancements will continue, particularly to assist parents of young children to use passport online.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.25" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#E00400">Special Educational Needs</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1631" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#E00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Madigan, to the House to take this important issue on the provision of a timeline for the opening of autism spectrum disorder, ASD, units and ASD outreach classes in schools in Dublin 2, 4, 6 and 6W.  In these areas in Dublin Bay South, there is a serious shortage of places in autism units and ASD outreach classes for children.  This is a matter of intense frustration for the many parents, families and children affected.  I know that the Minister of State is well aware of this.  The Labour Party has been working on this matter for some years now.  Along with my colleague, Deputy Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, I have met the representative groups involved.  I thank Autism Equality Dublin Bay, the AsIAm organisation and the parents group, Involve Autism:D6/D6W and Surrounds, who have been advocating on behalf of children in the area and putting forward important points.</p> <p>Currently, every day, nearly 2,000 children from these areas are bused to schools in other areas at a cost, I am told, of approximately &euro;63,000 per annum and at how detriment to the children involved and to their families.  This is the result of poor planning and a lack of local provision.  This must be tackled.  I know that progress is being made.  We need a timeframe so that we can see what progress is being made and identify where places will be available.  I am conscious that there are schools that have stepped up, but these, I am told, are predominantly Educate Together and DEIS schools.  There are large areas in Dublin Bay South where there is no provision of ASD classes or autism units.  Many well established schools in affluent areas, despite being mandated to do so under the section 37A process, have not stepped up and made provision in their schools for children with autism or autistic children.  We need stricter enforcement of the rule such that schools must provide such placements.  We are all conscious of the demand for places and of the fact that children are currently being bussed out of the areas.  That is not acceptable.  It is important to reiterate the immense frustration that parents and children in the areas are experiencing.</p> <p>I have been asked by the groups involved to seek information from the Minister of State on the new forecasting model, which she has spoken about previously.  I have been asked to inquire if she can share details of that model, the prevalence rates and what the Department of Education and the NCSE propose to do about future planning for the area.  This is not just about children who need these placements today, although that is the pressing need, it is also about ensuring that planning for the future is conducted in a well thought out and evidence-based manner such that we do not see children in future also caught in this trap and again having to be bussed out of the areas.  </p> <p>I eagerly await the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#E00600"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important matter.  It is important to say that enabling children with special educational needs to receive an education appropriate to their needs is a priority for this Government and for me as the first ever Minister of State with responsibility special educational needs.  As the Senator will know, this year, in excess of 20% of the total education budget, or &euro;2 billion, will be invested in supporting children with special educational needs.  As a result, the numbers of special education teachers, SNAs and special class and school places are at unprecedented levels.  My Department aims to ensure, always, that there are sufficient school places available to meet the needs of all children throughout the State.  I am using every level available to me to do that.</p> <p>As the Senator will be aware, the departmental policy is that student's with special educational needs should be included where possible and appropriate in mainstream placements with additional supports provided.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Josepha Madigan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2424"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2424&amp;amp;pid=JosephaMadigan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In circumstances where children require more specialised interventions, some of which the Senator outlined, special classes or places are provided.  The National Council for Special Education, NCSE, is responsible for planning and co-ordinating provision at local and national levels and for advising my Department in that regard.  It is open to any school to make an application to the NCSE for the establishment of specialised provision.  Where sanctioned, a range of supports, including capital funding, are made available to the school.  Every school that opens a special class gets support in terms of grants - start-up grants, furniture grants and IT grants.  There is always an incentive for the school to open a special class.</p><p>Irish mainstream schools have a tradition of providing places that respond to the needs of families in their areas.  This is evidenced by the growth in special classes in recent years.  In 2011, there were 548 special classes.  We are now at 1,836, 1,567 of which are autism spectrum disorder, ASD, classes.</p><p>The Senator correctly pointed out that issues had arisen, particularly in recent years, with a shortage of suitable school places for students with special educational needs.  This has primarily been driven by the significant increase in demand and the shortage of suitable school accommodation in which to open special classes and expand special school provision.  Areas of Dublin such as those referenced by the Senator have featured in that regard.  It is the issue of better planning at national and local levels that she spoke about that I have been endeavouring to tackle.  It is my objective for special education places to come on stream to meet emerging demand in a timely manner.  Aside from the section 37A process to which the Senator alluded, it goes without saying the active collaboration by school communities in this regard is pivotal.  The NCSE engages on an ongoing basis and most special classes are set up outside the section 37A process.</p><p>A number of schools in the areas to which the Senator referred have agreed to open special classes.  Some schools have genuine reasons for not being in a position to do so, be it capacity issues or extenuating circumstances.  However, the majority that have been written to are in a position to open such classes.</p><p>We want to ensure no child with special educational needs will be without a place this September.  From September, we will be opening 1,200 special class places throughout the country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1631" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#F00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for her response and I welcome her comments about being committed to better planning.  I also welcome that, from September, there will be 1,200 additional places.  However, I did not hear from her any commitment as regards places in Dublin 2, 4, 6 or 6W.  These are the areas where there is a pressing need for local places.  Children are being bussed out of their areas.  That is not acceptable and a source of immense frustration.  It is to the detriment of those children and their families.  There is no provision on the east side of Dublin Bay South around Ringsend and Sandymount, and well-established schools are not stepping up and providing the places that should be there for children in their local catchment areas.  Despite the incentives that have been provided, there remains a serious issue of a shortage of places for children in these areas.  Will the Minister of State provide a timeframe as to when more places will become available for children in Dublin 2, 4, 6 and 6W?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1472" speakername="Josepha Madigan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#F00300"><p>The Senator may be aware that I have met Autism Equality Dublin Bay, Involve Autism and AsIAm.  I commend them on the work they do in this regard.  It is important I hear from parents and families on the ground.  One of the things I have tried to do since assuming my role has been to take the sting out of trying to find a place in a special class or special school.  City Quay National School and Star of the Sea Boys National School will be opening in the areas the Senator mentioned, as will St. Christopher's, Shellybanks, Ringsend and other schools.</p> <p>Planning using the forecasting model is a departure for the Department.  We are working with the building and planning unit on setting out the five-year forecasting model.  There was never a reason we could not do this, given that an information geographical system for planning into the future is used in respect of other schools.  An important measure I have from the Department is that, from this year on, all new schools will automatically provide for special educational needs.  This will help a significant cohort in the years to come.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.31" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#F00400">Housing Policy</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#F00500"><p>I thank the Minister of State, Deputy Brophy, for taking this Commencement matter.  I congratulate him on his role.  I have not to date had the opportunity to do so in the House, which says much about our curtailed schedule.</p> <p>I will not take my full time.  This straightforward issue has been brought to my attention and warrants a second look by the Department.  I am referring to the new household means assessment policy for local authority housing which was circulated to councils throughout the country and came into force last month.  Section 4 of the new household means policy relates to deductions made.  While it says tax, USC, PRSI and so on are deducted, no deductions are allowable for the likes of rent or travel expenses, which is consistent with the previous 2011 policy.  However, the new policy specifically states there should be no deduction from assessable income for maintenance paid by an applicant or joint applicant.  This seems fundamentally unfair.  If we are honest about it, it will predominantly affect males who have children with a former partner and who are making maintenance payments.  While it is appropriate that maintenance be paid, that these payments are not being deducted from assessable income is a fundamental flaw in the household means policy, especially when one considers that maintenance payments received are counted as income for the purposes of consideration for inclusion on the social housing list under the exact same policy.</p> <p>I will provide a real example of how this policy is having an impact on those who are close to the income threshold for social housing.  I am dealing with the case of a male constituent who applied to Waterford City and County Council for inclusion on its social housing list following the break-up of his relationship with his child's mother.  Prior to the introduction of the new household means policy, this gentleman could have been below the threshold of &euro;30,750 for an adult and a child when his maintenance payments were taken into account.  Now that his maintenance payments are not deducted from his income, he is adjudged to be over the income threshold for social housing and, therefore, he does not qualify to go on the list, which has the impact of him not qualifying to receive the housing assistance payment.</p> <p>This policy will continue to have an impact on males predominantly but not solely.  It does not make sense that maintenance payments received are counted as assessable income whereas maintenance payments paid out are not deducted from assessable income.  This policy needs to be reviewed and maintenance payments should be considered as deductibles.  I would appreciate it if the Minister of State raised this matter with the line Minister and reverted to me, if possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1573" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#F00600"><p>I thank the Senator for tabling this Commencement matter and for his remarks at the start.  Unfortunately, the Minister, Deputy O'Brien, is not available to attend today.  He has asked me to take this matter on his behalf.</p> <p>Applications for social housing support are assessed by the relevant local authority in accordance with the eligibility and need criteria set down in section 20 of the Housing (Miscellaneous Provisions) Act 2009 and the associated Social Housing Assessment Regulations 2011, as amended.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Colm Brophy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2427"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2427&amp;amp;pid=ColmBrophy&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The 2011 regulations prescribe maximum net income limits for each local authority, in different bands according to the area concerned, with income being defined and assessed according to a standard household means policy.</p><p>The household means policy is a document that issued to all local authorities in 2011, and it was reviewed and updated in 2021.  It sets out the manner by which local authorities should assess the means of an applicant for social housing support, for the purpose of determining that household's ability to provide accommodation from their own resources.  The policy sets out what income should be assessed as part of net income, what deductions can be made and what income is not assessable for the purpose of a social housing needs assessment.  The policy also provides for a range of income disregards, and local authorities have discretion to decide to disregard income that is temporary, short-term or once-off in nature.  Under the policy, net income for social housing assessment is defined as gross household income less income tax, PRSI, additional superannuation contribution, ASC, and the universal social charge, USC.</p><p>Furthermore, there is no provision in the policy to deduct any other regular outgoings, such as maintenance paid in respect of family members, from gross household income for the purposes of the income threshold.  When somebody makes a maintenance payment, it is to cover the cost of living for their children, which is the same cost incurred by a couple with children that are still living together as a family unit.  There are no deductions from assessable income for the costs associated with the raising of children for a family unit, so it is reasonable that there are no deductions for these costs for the individual of a separated couple who is paying maintenance.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1647" speakername="John Cummins" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#G00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State.  While I appreciate his response, I still feel there is a fundamental flaw in the system.  Income that is received for maintenance payments is factored into the consideration of assessable income for the individual that receives it yet, on the other hand, it is not taken into account in policy terms for the person who pays it out.  While I appreciate what the Minister of State said in regard to couples, the issue I am raising is particularly associated with separated couples where maintenance is paid as a result of a court order.  In such circumstances, I believe the maintenance payment should be factored into the consideration of deductible income for the purposes of inclusion on the social housing list in the exact same way it is factored into the consideration for the person who receives it at the other end.</p> <p>I would appreciate it if the Minister of State would bring this back to the Minister, Deputy O'Brien, to have a second look at it.  There have been some changes in the new policy as to what is permitted.  This is specifically mentioned in the 2021 policy, over and above what had been the case.  Perhaps there was flexibility in the previous 2011 policy that is not there in the 2021 policy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1573" speakername="Colm Brophy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#G00300"><p>I thank the Senator and I will convey his remarks back to the Minister.  The review of the household means policy has taken place and the position remains that there should be no deduction from assessable income in regard to the maintenance paid.  However, I clearly understand the points the Senator is making and the situation he is describing.  I thank him and I will bring this to the attention of the Minister.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.37" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#G00350">Health Services Staff</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#G00400"><p>I want to raise the very important issue of the appointment of eye care liaison officers, ECLOs, to the hospital groups throughout the country.  When somebody is diagnosed for the first time with sight loss, the consultant will have a one-stop-shop person to whom to refer the individual.  This is a person who will advise them on the various step-down services, peer counselling and supports, from the National Council for the Blind and guide dogs to peer counselling.  That officer will also assist with follow-up medical interventions, appointments, advice and so on.</p> <p>This has been piloted in Dublin between Temple Street Children's Hospital and Crumlin Children's Hospital.  At a very early stage, the number of referrals to the step-down support services has increased dramatically and the result that people go on to live independent lives has been demonstrated in recent years.  Quick diagnosis, early intervention and fast engagement with services has proven to be invaluable.  This has worked very well in the UK and, as I said, it is working in Dublin.</p> <p>I tabled a Private Members&rsquo; motion on this during the previous Seanad in 2019 and it was accepted unanimously that this would be rolled out to all hospital groups.  Following my re-election to the Seanad, I have continued advocating on this specific issue.  The various consultants involved are stressed and are working to the limit.  Some have a very strong knowledge of the aftercare and support services, while others have just a working knowledge.  To bring continuity to everybody in this country, irrespective of where they live, I want ECLOs rolled out in Waterford, Cork, Limerick, Galway and Sligo, and an additional ECLO in Dublin.</p> <p>A meeting took place prior to Christmas between Liam Woods of the HSE and his team and the National Council for the Blind of Ireland, NCBI, which is in charge of the pilot taking place in Dublin.  This was committed to very clearly at that meeting and the HSE agreed with and saw the benefit of the policy, and was happy to commit that the seven additional ECLOs would be rolled out in 2021.  I completely understand that we are in the midst of a global pandemic and I know that things are stressed and stretched.  However, I also know that other healthcare is progressing and there are developments in other areas of healthcare.  That is why I believe we need immediate action on this issue.  It has been committed to, including in this House.  Equally as important, it was committed to by the HSE at that meeting before Christmas.  It is now May so if the commitment to see ECLOs rolled out throughout the country is to be delivered in 2021, we need action. </p> <p>That is the ask and it is a very reasonable ask.  It is a project and an intervention that has worked enormously well abroad, and where it was piloted here in Dublin city, it has been proven to work extremely well.  I look forward to the Minister of State's response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#G00500"><p>I thank the Senator for the opportunity, on behalf of the Minister for Health, Deputy Donnelly, to address the issue of appointing eye care liaison officers, ECLOs.  The ECLO service provides practical and emotional support to patients and their families to meet their needs when a diagnosis of sight loss is made.  The officer works closely with clinical teams and provides a link between acute and community-based services.  The service helps to ensure that patients and families are well informed and understand the condition and the supports available to them.  This service is currently available in the Mater University Hospital, the Royal Victoria Eye and Ear Hospital, Temple Street Children's Hospital and Crumlin children's hospital.</p> <p>I understand that the HSE met with the NCBI in December 2020 to discuss the issue of expanding the service.  The NCBI identified the potential benefits associated with the introduction of ECLO posts and experience from the introduction of such posts in hospitals.  I regret that the HSE was not in a position to allocate specific resources to support this development in 2021.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frankie Feighan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2014"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2014&amp;amp;pid=FrankFeighan&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, the HSE is examining the potential to support NCBI in 2021 with the current resources.  The HSE will engage directly with NCBI in this regard.  The HSE primary care eye services review group report, published in June 2017, sets out the way forward for a significant amount of eye services to be delivered in a primary care setting.  Supported by the clinical programme in ophthalmology and its model of care, the report recommends integrated care provision with hospital ophthalmic services.  This will ensure that hospital ophthalmic departments are focused on patients who require more specialised diagnostics or treatments.  The recommendations of the report are being implemented on a phased basis as resources allow.  This includes primary care revenue funding and the Sl&aacute;intecare integration funding for 2019.</p><p>Implementation to date has focused on establishing and expanding primary care eye teams in Dublin, Kildare and Wicklow.  The initial priority is to address backlogs in waiting lists for paediatric eye care services.  Waiting list numbers show significant progress has been made in this regard by the primary care eye teams in these areas.  The HSE plans to redirect some adult outpatient care from acute services to these teams too.  When this is rolled out, the teams will focus on pre- and post-operative cataract care and the management of stable glaucoma patients.  I expect that the roll out of integrated eye care teams will make a significant contribution to reducing waiting lists and ensuring that hospital ophthalmic departments can focus on surgical activities and more complex referrals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#H00200"><p>I sincerely thank the Minister of State for his reply and note the good work that has been done by various ophthalmologists and teams around the country.  This is specific.  It is about having eye care liaison officers appointed who can advise on the step-down services and how people can emotionally come to terms with the fact that they have been diagnosed with sight loss.  It is an extraordinarily traumatic experience for people who have never experienced sight loss before.  The cost of rolling out these seven eye care liaison officers is &euro;560,000.  In the overall scheme of a budget of &euro;24 billion, it is not a huge amount.  Can the Minister of State, Deputy Feighan, arrange for Liam Woods and his team to meet the National Council for the Blind to discuss this matter further as a matter of urgency in the next couple of weeks?  We are in the middle of the year and a further engagement to recalibrate, establish where we are and come up with a timeframe in which this service can be delivered is critical.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1608" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#H00300"><p>I thank Senator Conway for his interest in the situation.  I will talk to the Minister to organise a meeting between Liam Woods and his team and the NCBI as quickly as possible.  I know that the eye care liaison officer provides an important and worthwhile service by providing non-clinical support for patients and their families and allowing clinicians to focus on diagnosis, treatment and medical follow up.  This approach of allowing clinicians to focus on their specific clinical work is also in line with the integrated eye care teams approach.  Eye care liaison officers are and would be a valuable resource in all hospital ophthalmic departments.  The Minister has asked the HSE to continue to examine how it can best support the appointment of additional eye care liaison officers and to keep me informed of progress in this regard.  We will set up that meeting between the teams and the NCBI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.43" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 10.14 a.m. and resumed at 10.30 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.44" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#K00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#K00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, the Education (Leaving Certificate Examinations) (Accredited Grades) Bill 2021 - Committee and Remaining Stages, to be taken at 11.45 a.m. and to conclude at 12.45 p.m. by the putting of one question from the Chair which shall with regard to amendments include only those set down or accepted by the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#K00300"><p>First, I wish to pay tribute to a great Irish patriot, Mr. Se&aacute;n Lemass, who died on today's date 50 years ago.  He was a democratic, practical and visionary republican.  He believed that social and economic goals should not be in conflict, but should be achieved at the same time.  That is the reason the Lemass era was defined by expanded access to education, new social supports, health services and social housing, the opportunity to have jobs, the attraction of foreign direct investment and, of course, working in co-operation with other European countries.  It is important that we reflect on his legacy today.  The goals he had are still important today.  Thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for allowing me the opportunity to mention that.</p> <p>There are other issues I wish to raise, one of which is driver tests.  We all know there is a massive waiting list of approximately 100,000 throughout the country.  Kildare has one of the highest waiting lists outside Dublin and Cork, with more than 5,000 people on the waiting list for Naas.  We all accept the reasons there could not be driver tests over the last few months, but at this point there is an absolute need to ramp up tests.  I welcome the recruitment of more testers and I am aware the Minister is considering the addition of new test centres.  I suggest that Kildare be one of them.  We also must look at recommencing driver theory tests in conjunction with that.</p> <p>I also wish to raise an issue we all are greatly concerned about, the many challenges facing people who want to have their own home.  Every day, I and every other Member deal with people who are trying to acquire a home, be it through social housing, renting, planning to build or buying privately.  Indeed, those who are trying to buy privately are being pitted against local authorities, approved housing bodies and, as we know from the last week, institutional investors.  We absolutely must take away the financial advantage that has been given to international investment funds.  This must be a priority for us as we move forward.</p> <p>Thank you, a Chathaoirligh, for giving me the opportunity to raise those items.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#L00100"><p>The Leader may recall that before Christmas I asked her - and she agreed - to organise a debate with the Minister for Health present about the working of the new abortion law in the light of the troubling research done by some UCC researchers on the provision of abortion in Ireland.  That was published in the <i>British Journal of Obstetrics and Gynaecology</i>.  As Members will be aware, the three-year review of Ireland's abortion law is scheduled to take place this year as required by the legislation.  When that legislation took effect in 2019 the then chief executive of Britain's largest abortion provider tweeted that to her amazement Ireland now had a more permissive abortion law than even England had.  Everything that has happened since proves her assessment to be correct, with 6,666 abortions in Ireland in the first year.  This represents an increase of between 40% and 75% on the number of abortions in the previous year, depending on how we count it.</p><p>Listeners to &quot;Today with Claire Byrne&quot; on RT&Eacute; yesterday would have been left a rather different impression by the item I heard.  It was a 14-minute package on the review and featured three spokespersons for the pro-abortion position and just one pro-life representative.  The distinct impression was given that the new law was extremely restrictive and that few abortions are taking place.  By any objective measure that could not be further from the truth.  Under the new law babies, having survived the abortion procedure, are being left to die alone without receiving any medical or palliative care.  Doctors are now being trained to perform ghastly dilation and extraction late-term abortions even though voters were promised this would never happen.  Over &euro;20 million of taxpayers' money has been spent to date on the roll-out of abortion provision but no money has been spent on promoting positive alternatives to abortion.  It is a tragic situation but a listener would never think that from listening to RT&Eacute;.  If a listener were to rely on RT&Eacute; to bring any of those harrowing details he or she would never hear them because RT&Eacute; does not interest itself in that side of the story.</p><p>That prompts two reflections.  The Eoghan Harris era may be over but the culture of behind the scenes manipulation of analysis, failure to tell certain truths and unseen manipulation of the public debate, of which Harris was a part back in the day in RT&Eacute;, has not disappeared from RT&Eacute;.  This is especially the case in the coverage of social issues and especially on the issue of abortion.</p><p>That prompts a second reflection relevant to the people who are indignant about that and who decide to withhold their licence fee as a result.  We hear from Jon Williams of RT&Eacute; every time there is a positive or good programme and he says it justifies the licence fee.  Many people believe they are not being fairly treated.  These comprise the one third of the electorate who voted against repeal of the eighth amendment and many more who voted for repeal but who have been shocked by the extent of the new legislation.  Many of these people do not believe they are getting fair treatment by RT&Eacute;.  A decision by them to withhold their licence fee is frankly one that I would support at this stage, because something needs to change about the way the taxpayer-funded public broadcaster is treating important social issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1631" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#L00200"><p>I wish to take strong issue with the comments of Senator Mullen just now as to the reporting of RT&Eacute;.  Senator Mullen needs to remind himself that in 2018 the people voted by a two-thirds majority to repeal the eighth amendment having had sight of the legislation proposed to bring in legal abortion in Ireland.  That legislation was sorely needed for the reproductive health needs of all women in this country.  I wish to remind Senator Mullen of that.  People were not, and should not have been, in any way perplexed by the legislation.  It is reasonable and fair by European standards.  I look forward to the review process that is under way.</p> <p>I take strong issue with the comments of Senator Mullen to the effect that people are pro-abortion.  Those of us who campaigned over many decades for repeal of the eighth amendment are pro-choice.  We seek to ensure that women will have choices and access to the reproductive healthcare that we so badly need.  I wish to remind Senator Mullen of that.  We had a full debate in the House over that legislation even after passage of the repeal amendment in 2018.  Again, I wish to remind all colleagues of that.</p> <p>I welcome the fact that yesterday we saw some positive reopening of society in a cautious and careful manner.  I welcome the ongoing plans for reopening, albeit on a careful and incremental basis.  I welcome in particular the fact that now so many people will be able to see family and friends again and be able to get haircuts.  I am one of those who is very much looking forward to that.  More important, so many people will be able to see their businesses reopening and that is most welcome.  I urge everyone to remain mindful of all the public health guidelines and restrictions.</p> <p>I call on the Leader to convey to the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, what is probably a shared view across the House to the effect that Ireland needs to condemn strongly the terrible carnage that we see unfolding in Israel and Palestine and, in particular, the dreadful killing of so many people.  Some 24 Palestinians, including seven from one family were killed.  Nine of the 24 killed were children.  We are seeing appalling carnage.</p> <p>Ireland needs to push for peace talks and for an end to the carnage.  We need to demand that international law is obeyed and that Israel does not proceed with the eviction of Palestinian families to make way for settlers.  We should also condemn of course the Hamas rocket attacks that we have seen injuring Israeli civilians.  Clearly, the carnage we are seeing in Gaza is terrible and shocking.  I call on the Leader to convey that to the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney.</p> <p>I call on the Leader for a debate on housing and in particular on the housing crisis and the lack of provision for young people to be able to buy their own homes.  My call is in light of the ESRI report by the economist Barra Roantree which shows us that the most severe impact of Covid-19 and the pandemic has been on our young people.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" speakername="Pauline O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#L00300"><p>It is good to be here in the convention centre again, where Deputies have been sitting.  Contrary to some perceptions, it is not costing the State any more money.  It is being paid for today because Deputies are in later today.</p> <p>Often I stand up here and speak about breastfeeding, periods and the different stages in the lives of women.  One thing I have not spoken about is something I was alerted to yesterday.  There is a conversation ongoing in Irish society about the menopause.  The fact is that we do not talk about it in this Chamber despite the fact that it has been on "Liveline" for several days.  This shows that people are afraid to speak about some things relating to the health of women.  It is not only mothers who go through the menopause.  Fully 50% of the country are impacted.  It is time we had a proper conversation about it.  It is time we brought it into all our healthcare debates.  People are joining a particular Facebook group in droves.  They are saying they do not understand fully what is happening to them for many years.  They say general practitioners are not fully educated around hormone replacement therapy or anything else for that matter.  A high proportion - up to 10% - of women who are suffering symptoms actually leave work as a result of the menopause.  When then go to the doctor, this is not really recognised.  They may need a sick certificate for a certain period.  Do their employers recognise the impact this is having on them?  The impacts range across mental and physical health and can be really debilitating.  I would like those of us making up the Chamber to speak about it more.  There are many recommendations we could put forward to the Minister for Health to take on board and recognise what so many women are going through.</p> <p>I wish to make another point about reproductive health and abortion.  I agree wholeheartedly with Senator Bacik.  I am stunned that Senator Mullen continues to say we should have a conversation where it is 50:50.  The people have already voted on this issue.  We have abortion in this country.  It was very much needed and people looked for it for a long time.</p> <p>I look forward to the review of the legislation but we have to put stakeholders front and centre.  These include those who had been leaving the country for a long time and those who continue to leave the country because they do not have everything they need here.  Let us have stakeholders - those who are actually impacted by terminations - front and centre when it comes to reviewing this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00100"><p>Last week, the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Darragh O'Brien, brought the affordable housing Bill to Cabinet.  There are two good proposals in it - an affordable cost rental scheme led by approved housing bodies and a council-run affordable purchase scheme.  These two proposals will only be effective if the Government sets ambitious targets and meets those targets with real cash.  However, we have seen little cash and ambition from the Minister so far.  In budget 2021, just &euro;35 million was allocated for a cost rental scheme and &euro;50 million for the council-run affordable purchase scheme.  That will deliver just 530 homes this year.</p> <p>In 2019, Sinn F&eacute;in proposed increasing to 25% the percentage of a private development that would be set aside for social and affordable units, so it is welcome that a slightly lower proposal of 20% is included in this Bill.  The Government should adopt more Sinn F&eacute;in policies, particularly in housing.  The truth is that the Government does not have the political will to help renters, first-time buyers and people in mortgage distress or to end homelessness.  This has been nowhere more obvious than in the Government's shared equity scheme.  According to the London School of Economics, upon which the Minister's proposal is based, this kind of scheme has increased house prices in London by 6%.  The scheme has a series of price caps, including &euro;500,000 for a Dublin city apartment and &euro;450,000 for a house in Dublin city.  I do not have to tell Members that this is not affordable.  This has no place in housing policy, let alone in an affordable housing Bill.  When does the Leader expect this Bill to come to the House?  I reiterate that we need to ban rent increases, put an amount equivalent to one month's rent back in the pockets of people who are renting and drive supply with a &euro;900 million investment to deliver 4,000 affordable rental homes a year.</p> <p>Finally, t is vital Ireland uses its position on the UN Security Council to call for an immediate end to the armed assault on the Palestinian people.  The Minister for Foreign Affairs cannot equivocate any longer.  The Government must recognise the state of Palestine as the D&aacute;il has done.  We must condemn Israel at the Security Council.  We need actions, not endless gestures.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00200"><p>I propose an amendment to the Order of Business to remove the guillotine on the Education (Leaving Certificate 2021) (Accredited Grades) Bill.  There are only five amendments and mine is the last.  Since the number of amendments is very small, a guillotine is not needed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00300"><p>Is the Senator seeking to adjourn the debate at 12.45 p.m.?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00400"><p>Is the debate going to adjourn?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00500"><p>No.  Is the Senator seeking to adjourn the debate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00600"><p>Yes.  I am seeking to adjourn or finish the debate but that is up to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00700"><p>I second the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00800"><p>Senator Ruane is seeking to adjourn the debate at 12.45 p.m. and remove the guillotine.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M00900"><p>I thank the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Frankie Feighan, for his engagement yesterday.  I am the Chair of the Oireachtas cross-party group on drug policy reform, which I set up during my previous Seanad term after spending some time in Westminster looking at its very active and effective cross-party group on drug policy reform.  We met with the Minister of State and his officials yesterday and it was a good engagement.  There is only so much we can highlight in the Chamber during Commencement matters.  The Minister of State and his officials spent two hours with us yesterday, covering everything from Naloxone to Suboxone to the ageing population using drug services.  We now have an ageing population of people who were on heroin in the 1970s and who still have addiction issues in some cases.  Their needs are changing, including issues such as access to buildings or what they require as older people affected by drug use or abuse.  It was a very positive engagement.  I encourage more engagement with cross-party groups outside the Chamber so that everybody has a fair chance to air a broad range of issues.</p> <p>I also acknowledge that 16-year-olds voted for the first time in Scotland last Thursday.  There are no exit polls indicating how many 16-year-olds voted, but all the articles we read about youth employment indicated a big difference was seen in the kind of policies put forward.  The party manifestos had really geared towards the idea of youth politics.  That is what happens when we encourage different cohorts to get involved in the political process.  We see the agenda of parties change to meet the needs of younger people, especially during the Covid-19 pandemic, when young people lost out on significant generational opportunities and life-shaping parts of their lives, including missing out on all that is involved in attending college or school.  I hope we can look to Scotland and move positively in the same direction over the coming year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1691" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M01000"><p>I wish to raise two issues.  I first wish to express my delight at the reopening of society.  It seems that members of society are like prisoners released to some normality.  We should also be aware that we are on probation and if we disobey the guidelines, we might find ourselves back in prison but, hopefully, that will not happen.  As the tourism season begins, I observe a large influx of people and an interest in coming to places like west Cork or south Kerry, which is very welcome.  In the part of the world I live in, Schull, tourism plays a massive role.  The population of our town, or village as some people call it, multiplies by five in the months of July and August, particularly.</p> <p>Having said that, I am particularly concerned by the plight of small inshore fishermen, not alone in Schull but in Union Hall, Baltimore, Kinsale and other coastal towns.  It has recently come to my attention, and is something I have observed, that there is an influx of approximately 50 or 60 camper vans that come and park on the pier with little regard for fishermen.  These fishermen fish from boats that are approximately 18 ft to 30 ft long; I am not sure what that is in metres.  They are inshore fishermen whose guidelines and parameters for fishing are in accordance with the weather available to them.  They may have to fish on a Saturday, Sunday or Monday because they cannot go out if there has been a terrible week of weather.  They are impeded from accessing their gear, whether it is lobster pots, crab pots, shrimp or whatever, because the camper vans park in such an indiscriminate way.  I raised this matter through a councillor with Cork County Council and it stated that tourism is very important, as if this is in some way relevant.  That is not the case.  </p> <p>I ask the Leader to look at this situation since Schull is not the only place affected.  The rights of traditional fishermen who are, unfortunately, becoming very scarce, must be respected.  Tourists love their gourmet restaurants but they must remember that lobster, crab, shrimp, prawns and so on do not fall from the sky.  The fishermen have to go out and get them.  I ask that small inshore fishermen are respected whether they are in Cork, Kerry, Donegal or Galway. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#M01100"><p>We are back in the convention centre, which might not be the best place for Parliament to sit, but is a wonderful setting and vista.  It is great to see the rejuvenation of this area of Dublin, which has taken place over a large number of years.  Last week in Galway, representatives attended a virtual presentation from Galway Harbour Company regarding its vision for the inner docklands of Galway city.  Some 17 acres of land has the potential to transform Galway city and reshape it towards the sea and the beautiful Galway Bay.  The proposals include the creation of a new urban quarter for significant new residential, commercial, cultural and amenity space in the heart of the city.  We are talking about the heart of the city since this is some two to three minutes' walk from Eyre Square.  All of this will be beside the sea with its view, calming setting and maritime history.</p> <p>This is all possible due to key decisions made by Galway Harbour Company.  As a former director of this company, I am delighted to have been able to assist in the progress of plans for a new, deeper, non-tidal pier and harbour.  Over recent years decisions have been made that have freed up lands for some of this development with the rest of the progress of the new port being built.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Se&aacute;n Kyne:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2343"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2343&amp;amp;pid=SeanKyne&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->An Bord Plean&aacute;la has agreed that the new port should be considered under the imperative reasons of overriding public interest, IROPI, process and the next stage is with the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage for decision.  I am sure he will assess that in the very near future.</p><p>Ports have and will continue to play a hugely important role in Ireland's trade potential and will have a role in the renewable industry.  We must also look at lands that can be utilised, reimagined and re-envisaged, as has been done here in Dublin and as can be done in Galway, and the potential of the urban regeneration development fund towards assisting in that vision and reimagining the port in Galway.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#N00200"><p>The repair and leasing scheme is one that seems good in principle.  It provides upfront funding to property owners to perform renovations on vacant properties and, in return, the property owner agrees to lease the renovated property back to the local authority to provide social housing for 25 years.  I have recently established the number of dwellings delivered by local authorities under the scheme.  From 2017 until the end of 2020 the number of dwellings delivered nationally under the scheme was a mere 234 in four years, fewer than 60 a year.  This is a paltry figure.  In spite of the increase in the scheme's funding limit to &euro;60,000, it is still inadequate to stimulate demand.  Not enough money is being made available to repair the houses.  With steep inflation in building costs, I doubt the budget of &euro;11 million for the scheme in 2021 will deliver the number of units anticipated.  The scheme is another abject failure of the housing policies of Fianna F&aacute;il, Fine Gael and the Green Party.</p> <p>I also raise the issue of the vaccination programme.  Last December, the Government's own national vaccination programme and implementation plan had assigned the central role to pharmacies in the programme.  Why have they not been involved in administering a single vaccine?  Some 2,000 pharmacists have been trained and are experienced vaccinators.  They have a capacity to administer more than 50,000 a week.  If the Government wants to hit its vaccination target by the end of June, I urge it to delay no longer.</p> <p>Finally, on reproductive health and abortion, I say in support of Senator Mullen that the review is welcome.  I was not aware until yesterday that no data on abortions were kept.  I am particularly concerned about the late-term abortions and the question of pain relief for the unborn.  A question and conversation needs to be had no this.  While many support reproductive health, I am sure that, similarly, they will show compassion for the unborn and, it is hoped, agree to support pain relief in late-term abortions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1631" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#N00300"><p>On a point of order, data are kept and there are specific provisions in the 2019 legislation to ensure data are kept on terminations of pregnancy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" speakername="R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#N00400"><p>The Senator voted against them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" speakername="" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#N00500"><p>This is my first day as a returning Member in this Chamber and it is great to be here.  I also echo Senator O'Loughlin's remarks on Se&aacute;n Lemass.  I had already put a few words together, but she has covered most of them.  It is important we remember he was really the driver of the opening up of Irish society to investment from abroad, to foreign direct investment which has provided so much employment and improved our living standards.  He was also the Taoiseach at the time free education was being put through the Houses.  Donogh O'Malley gets a lot of the credit but Se&aacute;n Lemass deserves a fair share of it too.  His legacy lives on with his grandson, Deputy Se&aacute;n Haughey, who is still a Member of this Oireachtas.</p> <p>I really welcome what happened yesterday in the reopening of society.  It was fantastic.  You could hear the joy of people being able to think about going shopping, organising to get their hair cut and feeling there is a freedom there now that was not there before.  However, we are all aware that takeaway pints are being served and hospitality is occurring in a less than ideal regulated environment.  I ask the Leader to arrange for the Minister and NPHET to look at the reopening of the outdoor hospitality sector perhaps a couple of weeks earlier than planned on 7 June, mainly because it is happening already.  It would be more regulated, it would involve social distancing, table service and toilets being available.  It would stop the free-for-all attitude there at the moment.  I also ask that the possibility of indoor dining be pursued as soon as possible for employment and tourism throughout the country.  The sooner indoor dining and socialising is available, when safe, the better for society as a whole.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#N00600"><p>It is great to be back in the Chamber.  I raise An Taisce's decision to appeal a significant proposal by Glanbia to a higher court last week.  It is a really significant decision and something we need to start having a conscious debate about.  The hard-working farming community and food industry are under enough pressure without having An Taisce taking this decision this morning.  It is having a huge impact on the industry and the communities.  The economic and social impacts of this decision could have long-term consequences for rural Ireland.  Unfortunately, An Taisce pulled out of the agrifood strategy consultation phase.  It should be the friend of the farming community but at the moment it is considered anything but.  We need a debate on how we will work with An Taisce and how we progress this.  The Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications and the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage should be brought before the House.</p> <p>The Planning and Development (Strategic Infrastructure) (Amendment) Act 2018 needs to be amended.  It allowed for a fast-track legislative route for housing development and for economically sustained development.  The dairy industry and the agricultural food industry should be a part of any such Bill.  We amended it before for data centres.  We should now look at amending it again to incorporate the food industry.  It is one of the primary parts of our society which directly employs 10% of our economy.  Vast parts of my area and Ireland generally need that protection in law now.  We are not talking about fast-tracking laws but about making sure the agricultural industry can be protected.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#N00700"><p>It is really important to acknowledge the very important research undertaken by the ESRI, published this morning, on how young workers now fare worse in wages and access to housing compared with previous generations.  For years, trade unionists and others on the left raised this and we were told Ireland was different because we had the most highly educated workforce across any EU member state. Well, that is not the case; Ireland is not different.  We now need to hear from the Government about how it will take seriously the employment issues for young workers and the rental and housing crisis that befalls all young people now.</p><p>A paper by Dr. &Uacute;na Monaghan published on 31 March in <i>Ethnomusicology Ireland</i>talked about the mechanisms and structures of the Irish traditional music scene and how it continues to privilege the contribution of men.  This cosseted position is enabling some within the music scene to abuse their power to harass, assault and coerce women without consequences.  Many of us watched the &quot;Prime Time&quot; programme last year which described the culture of fear and sexual harassment perpetrated by some within that scene.  We have enormous thanks to Fair Pl&eacute; and #MiseFosta in their campaign tackling that culture.  There are very serious questions about what we are prepared to do as legislators.  Are we prepared to allow public support and funding to be given to some of those artists who are perpetrating that harassment and coercion?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie Sherlock:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarieSherlock&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Will we sit back and let these women be silenced into saying nothing because of the impact on their livelihoods, their hopes and their ambitions?  We, as legislators, need to do more to ensure compliance with bullying and harassment requirements is made a condition of airplay, performance and other financial support that the State gives to the arts and music sector.  It is no longer acceptable to stand by without having conditions in place for financial support to the music and wider arts sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" speakername="Timmy Dooley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#O00200"><p>I call on the Leader to organise a debate on the Irish Water investment programme at the earliest opportunity.  Every county in the country has issues with water and wastewater.  In west Clare, there is a very serious issue with an ageing asbestos water pipe network that has been there for more than 50 years and has gone beyond its operational life span.  There are recurring incidents of burst pipes in the line.  In the last three or four weeks there have been five or six breaks in a section of the pipe network between Creagh and Cooraclare, which has a major impact on that community.</p> <p>I compliment the staff of the local authority along with Councillor Bill Chambers who have done their best to get the leaks fixed.  However, that as a policy is not good enough.  Investment is required to replace the ageing pipe network.  It is not good enough for the communities that suffer as a result.  Over the weekend I spoke to families who are very severely impacted.  Families with young children need to prepare bottles along with the usual stuff associated with the domestic household.  Unannounced, breaks occur in the line and families find themselves without water.  When the water supply is restored, they have all the associated problems of dirty water for hours.  Sometimes it takes a day or two to flush out that dirty water and there are also airlocks.  Farmers, particularly dairy farmers, are going through a busy period.  They need fresh water to clean out their milking systems but they cannot be guaranteed a water supply to do it.  After the morning milking, it must be completed before the evening.</p> <p>That area of the county is also looking forward to the reopening of tourism.  It is not a great image to portray when trying to welcome people back to tourist facilities and not being able to assure them that they will be able to have a shower in the morning or that there will be water to boil the kettle.  We need a serious debate in this House on that investment programme.  The sooner we can arrange it, the better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#O00300"><p>I echo Senator Lombard's call for planning laws to deal with An Taisce.  The decisions it has made or the lack of acceptance of court judgments are reprehensible in many ways.  This has a real knock-on effect on farmers in my area in Tipperary.  It is attacking farmers in one region and not farmers around the whole country, which is extremely unfair.</p> <p>I want to talk about the arts and entertainment sector, and dance schools.  Some months ago, people representing dance groups protested outside Leinster House asking for clarity on what they could do at the time.  We eventually provided that, but only after they had come to Dublin to look for it.  We are in a similar situation again with a lack of clarity for that sector.  I call on the Leader to write to the Minister, Deputy Catherine Martin, to request clarity.  Clonmel is due to host the Clonmel Arts Festival which is a big annual event.  However, there is no clarity on how it will be hosted, whether it will be outdoor or indoor, etc.  I ask for clarity.  </p> <p>A real game changer in the ability of the arts and entertainment sector to host events will be antigen testing.  We have seen gigs around the world.  Places like Barcelona have hosted gigs with 5,000 people, which went really well.  If we are going to introduce guidelines for antigen testing in the coming days, we should also launch an awareness campaign on the usage of antigen testing.  Anyone who has had a test for Covid-19 knows that it is a bit more complicated than one would think.  It is not as simple as one would think.  There is no point in doing a test incorrectly and assuming the result one has is the correct result.  We need to educate people and provide the public with guidelines and a demonstration on how it should be done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#O00400"><p>I offer my solidarity to two groups of people today, first the Palestinians whom I witnessed at first-hand being denied medical supplies in 2015 when I was there after the Israeli defence forces bombed them.  I also offer my solidarity to the Ballymurphy families who are awaiting the findings of the inquest into what happened to their loved ones.</p> <p>This morning, once again we have woken up to news about how broken our housing system is.  An ESRI report found that home ownership by the age of 30 has halved in the space of a generation.  Young people are forced to stay with their parents or live in the precarious overpriced private rental market.  A second report this morning exposed how a Government agency, set up to boost small house builders, is now ploughing millions of euro into cuckoo developments.  Sinn F&eacute;in warned that would happen.  When the Home Building Finance Ireland legislation was being introduced, we tabled amendments to ensure that those loans would go to small builders and developers.  However, once again Fianna F&aacute;il and Fine Gael sided with the big players and voted against our amendments.  </p> <p>Large-scale investors are ploughing billions of euro into the private rental market.  They are treating our population, especially the young, single and divorced, as cash cows.  Home ownership is out of their grasp and so too is secure low-cost rental.  Today, Sinn F&eacute;in will introduce a Private Members' Bill in the D&aacute;il to rein in the vulture funds that Fine Gael invited in with open arms in 2013 when Enda Kenny said Ireland was a great little country to do business in.  He sure as hell was not messing about.  Real estate investment trusts, REITs, and Irish real estate funds, IREFs, pay no corporation tax and no capital gains tax.  They enjoy preferential tax advantages and exemptions on their private rental business.  Sinn F&eacute;in would end those tax advantages and exemptions, and we would impose a stamp duty surcharge on the purchase of residential property by REITs and IREFs.</p> <p>I call for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to come before this House to outline his urgent plan to address vulture funds.  We hear he has no plans to present to Cabinet today.  The Government ignored our warnings on vulture funds and ignored our warnings on Home Building Finance Ireland, but it cannot continue to ignore the enormous anger among people who just want a secure home.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1656" speakername="Mary Fitzpatrick" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#O00500"><p>Today I wish to remember someone who lived in the Dublin Central constituency.  He was a visionary, a leader, a true revolutionary, and an innovator of unparalleled intellect, integrity and modesty.  I would like to remember Se&aacute;n Lemass.  He grew up on Capel Street.  He attended O'Connell boys' school on the North Circular Road where he was an excellent student.  He fought in the GPO in 1916, the War of Independence and the Civil War.  Along with Eamon de Valera in 1926, he tried to convince Sinn F&eacute;in to recognise the Free State, to oppose the partition of our island and to engage in democratic politics to lead our country and our republic forward.</p> <p>Along with de Valera and others he founded Fianna F&aacute;il.  He is seen as the father of modern Ireland.  He saw economic success as a direct contributor to social success.  He supported innovation and industry.  Most importantly, he championed social values that delivered free education, social housing, investment in health and protection for workers.</p> <p>Today is the 50th anniversary of his death.  I am proud to say that in Dublin Central today, Fianna F&aacute;il in government is true to those values, is championing social housing, will deliver the biggest social housing programme in over a decade, is legislating to have the State provide affordable housing both for purchase and rent on State-owned lands, and is investing more than &euro;120 million here in Dublin's north inner city to ensure there will be a State-led commemorative centre on Moore Street for 1916 and that the dereliction that has dominated Moore Street for more than a decade will be reversed.  There will be a vibrant rejuvenated street market on Moore Street and there will be a national monument that will forever pay testimony to those heroes who brought about our great Republic.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#O00600"><p>I wish to talk about local enterprise offices and the Intreo offices.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=RoisinGarvey&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I seek the support of the House to call on the T&aacute;naiste and the Minister, Deputy Humphreys, to give both these important offices extra supports at this time when we are opening up the country.  According to the latest figures from the Central Statistics Office, we have 248,000 small businesses that employ between one and ten workers.  I do not know about businesses in other places but I know that in Clare one cannot rely on the big businesses and the multinationals as one does not know how long they will stay around.  However, one can rely on small businesses doing everything they can to keep their employees and themselves in business.  The local enterprise offices have played a blinder in the last 14 months in supporting small businesses but I know from speaking to those in that sector that they need extra supports and additional staff.  As we open up the economy, more jobs will come onstream.  The Intreo offices are dealing with people who are unemployed and looking for work.  It is important for those two offices to connect more and to get the supports to do so.  In that way, we could get people off the live register but also give them choices in jobs that might keep them employed, as opposed to being forced to take a job simply because it is available but which they might drop out of later.  We all want to do work that is valuable and for which we are appreciated.  There is no better sector than the small business sector to appreciate its workers.  Working in that sector is more like being in a family than working for a large corporation.  We underestimate the power and importance of the small business sector in Ireland.  We have nearly a quarter of a million small businesses with fewer than ten employees in the country.  Clare has approximately 6,000 small businesses providing 66,000 jobs.  We need to focus more on the Intreo offices and the small business sector to support small businesses in finding staff and also to support people who want to come off social welfare.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#P00200"><p>I wish to raise two related issues.  The first concerns South Westmeath Hospice.  Its current site at the St. Vincent's centre in Athlone is closed and the hospice is to be moved to a newly built nursing unit at Clonbrusk.  The voluntary group which has raised more than &euro;1 million to develop the current site was given assurances last October that the new building would mirror the old one.  However, the HSE now plans to incorporate four hospice beds into the rest of the facility, contrary to the written agreement that was given a few years ago.  This is utterly devastating to the hardworking committee.  I ask for the Minister for Health and the head of the HSE to meet the voluntary committee immediately to alter these plans.  The decision that has been taken is outrageous.  It mirrors an issue in my county of Longford.  Two years ago I and a number of my colleagues met the then Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, at St. Joseph's Care Centre along with members of Longford Hospice.  We got agreement for a two-bed unit to be incorporated into a new building that was being developed there.  Recently, I received a letter from the HSE in response to my following up the matter on behalf of Longford Hospice.  The letter states that any commitment to increasing the number of palliative beds at the expense of a long-term bed would have to be accompanied by an appropriate budget allocation to compensate for the fair deal income reduction in order to maintain services for current and future residents.  That is the response to a voluntary committee which raises funds of more than &euro;100,000 a year to provide vital services.  It is outrageous that we will put a price on providing palliative care for people to be close to their homes before they pass away.  I would like the Minister and the head of the HSE to meet with both committees and reverse these decisions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" speakername="Erin McGreehan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#P00300"><p>Following the ESRI announcement this morning highlighting the difficulties being experienced by young people with respect to housing and employment, we should look towards establishing a State internship programme for young people and not so young people.  It should have a proper established format where young people who come out of college or school could get an internship in a State Department or body and get practical, proper work experience.  I was one of the people who benefited from working in Louth County Council for three summers.  That work experience benefited me and gave me a knowledge of how matters operate at local government level, a taste for economic research and an interest to move on to my master's in economics.  That experience cannot be underestimated.  Under Charlie McCreevy's decentralisation programme, he and Fianna F&aacute;il provided for the creating of State Departments and bodies throughout the country.  We need to have a proper programme to help young people to get into work.  Getting office and work experience will be a problem for young people in the aftermath of Covid because of the change in the way we now work.  It is up to the State to look after young people to give them a boost with respect to their CVs, experience and lives.  That is what I propose this morning.  I would welcome that proposal being discussed at a later date.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#P00400"><p>I wish to raise two issues.  When I called last week for the Minister for Health to come into the House to discuss the vaccination programme, I raised the case of two vulnerable people who had not been vaccinated.  I am ashamed to say that a week later they still have not been vaccinated nor have they received a phone call, even though the respective Departments have given many promises that they will be in touch with them.</p> <p>As we open up society, and now that many people have got accustomed to online shopping, we need to run a marketing campaign to encourage people to stay local, support local and shop local.  Such a campaign needs to be run not only in our local villages, towns and cities but nationally.  As society opens, it is important that small businesses, which were mentioned already, should be supported in every way possible.</p> <p>I said I would raise two issues but I want to also raise a third one.  Limerick Lifelong Learning Festival was launched yesterday.  It will be a virtual festival that will run from 24 to 30 May.  More than 100 presentations will be made during the festival for the young and the not so young.  As we open up our museums and libraries, it is important that education and lifelong learning are supported and highlighted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#P00500"><p>A wide variety of topics have been raised for discussion.  In response to Senator Maria Byrne's matter, I have requested a debate with the Minister for Health on the ongoing vaccination programme.  It is quite disheartening to hear that the two people the Senator brought to this House&rsquo;s attention last week still have not even had contact.  I do not know if my office can be of any assistance but I am willing to help.  If the Senator would like to make contact with me afterwards, I will see if I can help.  I wish the Limerick Lifelong Learning Festival every success.  It will probably be a little bit strange for those involved to be doing it online. but we will find every way possible to make sure it can be a success.</p> <p>Senator McGreehan raised a very good idea and I will ask for a debate on her proposal.  I would highlight that the public sector supported 750 apprentices last year and will strive to do more.  The Minister with responsibility for further and higher education announced only recently that his ambition is for us to have 10,000 apprenticeships.  We can all acknowledge our young people have been adversely affected, as have women, because of the pandemic and the unemployment statistics, which are not pleasant to read.  It is definitely an issue we will have to debate in the future.</p> <p>Senator Carrigy asked for the Minister and the CEO of the HSE to meet a local organisation that has championed the project he raised for the past number of years.  I will write to Paul Reid and to the Minister, Deputy Stephen Donnelly, today to ask them to meet those local people to discuss the ongoing events in the Senator&rsquo;s area.</p> <p>Senator Garvey spoke of the wonderful work our local enterprise offices and Intreo offices do and reminded us there should be more co-operation between the two to specifically home in on what requirements with respect to educational support, mentoring and work experience are needed in each area.  We might have a debate with the Minister with responsibility for employment affairs in the coming weeks on what plans are afoot to make sure we support our unemployed people to get them back into work.</p> <p>Senator Fitzpatrick, as did Senators Horkan and Senator O'Loughlin at the start of proceedings, spoke of the powerful legacy Se&aacute;n Lemass has left that is enshrined in many aspects of Irish life.  I want to say how powerful and passionate Senator Fitzpatrick's contribution was and not only in paying tribute to Se&aacute;n Lemass.  She had not a note in her hand and she delivered her contribution very eloquently.  One would certainly know it came from the heart.  I want to acknowledge that to the House.</p> <p>Senator Boylan spoke of her solidarity with Palestinians and the Ballymurphy families who are awaiting the much anticipated news today from the inquest.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Regina Doherty:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2295"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2295&amp;amp;pid=ReginaDoherty&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am acknowledging that we are thinking of them.  I have requested a debate on the ongoing conflict in the Middle East and, once I have a date, I will let colleagues know when that will happen.</p><p>Senator Ahearn spoke about An Taisce as indeed did Senator Lombard.  It was raised yesterday and I said we will acknowledge and note the comments that have been made.</p><p>Senator Dooley asked for a debate on the Irish Water investment programme.  I will write to the Minister today and ask for that.  It is very poignant, given some of the reports that have been issued this morning and some of the requests that have been made, which should not go down very well not only in political circles but in many other circles in respect of water charges.</p><p>Senator Sherlock spoke about the ESRI research that was also mentioned by other Members.  This is something on which we should possibly have a debate.  Colleagues have asked when we are going to have a debate on the affordable housing Bill, if it is published this week, and I expect it to be published tomorrow.  I will try to start that debate next Monday.  There will be no confinement in that debate and everybody who wants to discuss the very good merits of the Bill will have the opportunity to do so.</p><p>Senator Sherlock also spoke about the vast inequality female artists in this country experience, let alone the discrimination they experience.  It was very nice, therefore, to see Imelda May&rsquo;s long-awaited album go straight to No. 1 in the charts and to see that she is supported by everyone in this country.  Long may she reign.</p><p>Senator Horkan talked about the reopening of society.  We have a debate scheduled and I am just waiting for a date from the Minister and will come back to the Senator on that issue.</p><p>Senator Keogan talked this morning about the repair and leasing scheme.  There are so many facets to the housing response by the State and this is a very good one.  You would wonder sometimes why so few houses, only 234 in four years, which seems like a tiny number of houses, have been put forward to avail of this scheme.  A grant of &euro;60,000 is not that small an amount of money to incentivise people.  We probably need to look to see if there are other routes or if there are other issues within the industry or sector that cause people not to want to reinvest in their houses and lease them back to the local authority.  That should form part of the wider debate on housing we will have in the House in the coming weeks.</p><p>Senator Keogan also mentioned the review, which was also mentioned by Senator Mullen, on the third anniversary of the legislation to repeal the eighth amendment and the introduction of rights for women in this country that we never had before.  That review will take place at some stage this year and we will come back to it once I get a date from the Minister.</p><p>Senator Kyne talked about the Galway harbour company and the vision it has to do something similar to what was done in the Dublin docklands area, which has been much rejuvenated in the past 20 years.  The Government&rsquo;s decision and the port&rsquo;s role in the future development of international trade in this country, given that we are a very small island, will play a vital role in this.  I look forward to seeing that Government decision and of it being in favour of Galway.</p><p>Senator O&rsquo;Donovan talked about reopening and urged us all to be cautious, as indeed did Senator Ahearn with regard to the use of antigen tests.  I mentioned yesterday in one of my musings that rather than being so critical of the use of antigen tests from the perspective of NPHET, we would all have been brought a little bit more along the process had the wording of one of our adviser&rsquo;s tweets been a little bit more encouraging of us and perhaps of having a positive campaign on the best use of antigen tests and how their results can be administered.  I am also mindful, and I do not mean this in any disrespectful way to Senator Ahearn, that women and their partners in this country have been using pregnancy tests since time immemorial and we have no problem reading the instructions and figuring out what the actual results mean.  An antigen test, therefore, is not going to be that much more difficult, but I take the Senator's point.</p><p>Senator Warfield talked about the affordable housing Bill.  As I said, if it is published tomorrow, I hope to bring it before the House next week.  The Senator also acknowledge our position on the UN Security Council with regard to condemning the conflict in Palestine and Israel.  As I said, I will come back again once I have a date for that debate.</p><p>Senator Pauline O&rsquo;Reilly spoke about something that is very topical recently.  A lady I have great admiration for, Anne O&rsquo;Leary, the head of Vodafone Ireland, introduced a menopausal policy in the company, which is one of the largest employers in the country.  It is an example that many more employers could take on board and it is definitely something we could have a conversation in the House about because it impacts not just the many women in this country going through that at a certain time in their lives but also their families, employers and work colleagues because of the impact it has on a woman&rsquo;s health.</p><p>Senator Mullen spoke about our abortion laws.  We can all acknowledge he has a particular view and other colleagues have a different view.  This does not take away from the fact the review of the legislation after three years will take place this year, and it may be appropriate to have a conversation about the review and allow people to express their concerns or indeed their positivity towards the new medical care available for women in this country.</p><p>Senator Bacik spoke about the Minister, Deputy Coveney, and looking for a condemnation.  She also sought a housing debate which it is hoped we will have next week.</p><p>Senator O&rsquo;Loughlin opened with a tribute to Se&aacute;n Lemass and sought a very urgent assessment of the review that is needed of the driving test backlog.  Some 100,000 of our people are looking and waiting to have their driving tests.  Under normal circumstances that would take years and that is certainly not something that can be countenanced.  I look forward to the response of the Minister for Transport as to how he intends to manage that.</p><p>There was one amendment proposed.  Unfortunately I cannot accept it for two reasons.  One is that we are time constrained today and have to leave at 1 o&rsquo;clock, which means the last vote has to be called 15 minutes beforehand.  Probably more importantly, however, the Bill is going to the D&aacute;il on Thursday and I could not ask for it to be rolled over until next Monday.  The four Government amendments are technical ones and should not take any more than about 15 minutes, which would give an hour to discuss and debate the Senator&rsquo;s amendment, which I hope may be enough for her.  I thank the Cathaoirleach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#Q00200"><p>Senator Ruane has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That the proceedings of the Committee and Remaining Stages of the Education (Leaving Certificate) (Accredited Grades) Bill 2021 be adjourned at 12.45 p.m. if not previously concluded."  Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#Q00300"><p>I am pressing the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.82" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.83" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.84" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 11.39 a.m. and resumed at 11.45 a.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.85" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#R00025">Education (Leaving Certificate 2021) (Accredited Grades) Bill 2021: Committee and Remaining Stages</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#R00100"><p>I welcome the Minister for Education, Deputy Foley, the House.  It is good to have her with us again for Committee and Remaining Stages.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.87" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 1 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.88" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 2</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#R00400"><p>Amendments Nos. 1, 8, 9 and 11 are related and may be discussed together, by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.90" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 1:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#R00500"><p>I have tabled four amendments, each of which provides for minor textual amendments to reflect some points that were missed prior to publication.  On the advice of Parliamentary Counsel, the amendments are necessary.  The amendments do not alter the substance of the sections or the schedules where they arise, and they are only technical or clerical in nature.</p> <p>Amendment No. 1 will delete the word "necessarily" from the second line of section 2(2), which is on page 5 at line 4.  Amendment No. 8 proposes to delete &ldquo;Examinations&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;Examination&rdquo; in section 9.  Amendment No. 9 proposes to delete &ldquo;of&rdquo;, where it first occurs in section 9.  Finally, the text of the opening sentence of the Schedule has also been revised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.92" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#R00700"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 5, line 24, after &ldquo;appropriate&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;(taken as a whole and not any one individual(&rsquo;s)result)&rdquo;. </blockquote> <p>This amendment seeks clarity on whether junior certificate results will be based on results' data from the year group or from the individual student's own results.  It should only be the junior certificate data from the year group that is used.  There is a significant difference between the two and a clear answer would be welcome from the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#R00800"><p>I welcome the intention behind this amendment.  I can agree with it in principle and I thank the Senator for tabling it.  Fundamentally, the process of standardisation will operate at national level.  It is preferable to use aggregate or cohort data, as the evidence is that the use of junior cycle data in the regression model is of better predictive quality when done at a class group rather than individual level.</p> <p>I cannot agree to the amendment, however, as in certain cases, it is necessary to rely on the individual junior cycle result of an individual student, where that student is typically an out-of-school learner or a student pursuing a subject out of school.  This was the case in 2020 in respect of calculated grades and it is set out in the published national standardisation group report.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Norma Foley:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=NormaFoley&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We were conscious of this from the outset.  To ensure we were being clear about the junior cycle's potential use in standardisation, the February guide to State examinations and accredited grades for the leaving certificate 2021 stated, "Though the prior performance of the class group in Junior Cycle may be used in this process, the individual performance of the student at Junior Cycle would not be a determinant of their performance at Leaving Certificate, other than when the subject is being taken outside of school."  However, the accredited grades system is, in the overall, subject to the determination of policy by myself.  Specifically, section 2(2)(d) operates in accordance with such policy directions as the Minister may give.  On that basis, and although I am rejecting the amendment, I am happy to include in my determination under section 2(1) a policy direction expressly stating the junior cycle and leaving certificate data used in the process of standardisation will be aggregated or cohort data subject to the flexibility referred to in limited cases, which is our intention in any event.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.96" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#S00500"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 5, between lines 28 and 29, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(iv) be set out in writing and published by or on behalf of the Commission prior to the issuing of results to each candidate;&rdquo;.  </blockquote> <p>As we learned last year, a lack of clarity before the release of results will leave students questioning and doubting a greater number of results.  It makes sense to release as much detail as possible so that students are better placed to interpret their results.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#S00600"><p>The principle behind this amendment - providing transparency in how the process of standardisation will operate - can be agreed with, but the amendment seeks to have the process of standardisation published in advance of results day.  This is not something that can be agreed to because the final composition or application of the process will, or at least may, not be known right up to results day.  I can commit to doing, at a minimum, what we did last year in having the technical details of the model and standardisation process published on results day.  I am also happy to commit to doing so as early as possible.</p> <p>We will be able to comment more on what we hope to publish on the 2021 standardisation process once it has been developed.  However, it is an iterative process.  Accordingly, I do not accept the amendment as drafted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.99" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#S00800"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 6, to delete lines 10 to 12. </blockquote> <p>I will be brief because of the time.  We want to remove this provision in the Bill, which narrows the grounds on which an appeal can be made.  As matters stand, an appeal can only consider the technicalities of how estimated marks are transferred from the school to the State Examinations Commission, SEC.  Since the system is relatively new, appeals should have a far wider scope.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#S00900"><p>I thank the Senator for his co-operation with the process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#S01000"><p>It is important to point out that, as a matter of policy, the provision of estimated marks is grounded fundamentally in the professional judgment of teachers and an in-school alignment before submission to the SEC.  The definition of "estimated mark" in the Bill provides clarity on what professional judgment is understood to encompass.  The process through which professional judgment is exercised would make it impossible that another person unknown to the student could be expected to review the evidence as a candidate's teacher had done, acknowledging that some of it will have been based on observation over the course of the entire senior cycle, and then be asked to provide an estimated mark that could be compared with the one initially provided.  This would make the design of such an appeal system, even if it were desired, difficult and potentially impossible.  The appeal process would also be highly likely to last several weeks, if not longer, and impede the candidate's progression to further study, or at least not facilitate it in terms of later rounds of offers.  Accordingly, I cannot accept the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#S01100"><p>I speak as an educator of 20-odd years in a classroom.  The Minister is right that no one is questioning the professionalism of the teacher.  This is about ensuring the student receives due regard for his or her work, but we must be careful to ensure that, in a new model of education delivery, the appeal system is wide ranging, open and transparent and is not confined within the prisons of certain operations.</p> <p>I understand where the Minister is coming from, but look at how operations have changed in terms of how people can appeal marks and view scripts after the publication of leaving certificate results.  There is an opportunity we need to grasp now where the leaving certificate is concerned.  In the context of this section, is there any willingness on the part of the SEC or the Department's bureaucracy to consider how to make the accredited grades system part of the leaving certificate in future?  I come from a generation that had to learn off poetry and read Peig Sayers.  The Leas-Chathaoirleach is probably of the same generation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#S01200"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#S01300"><p>I loved reading <i>Peig</i>.  I am probably in a minority of one in saying that.  I did not like other aspects of the leaving certificate, though, such as rote learning.  We are on a section that deals with reviews.  We should not adopt a straitjacket approach to reviews.  We have changed the model of education.  We have empowered more people, there is more engagement and there are more consultative processes.  We have a wider variety of activities for parents, pupils and boards of management.  My concern has to do with the qualification a student leaves school with after the leaving certificate.  If a student is dissatisfied for some reason, we have an obligation to ensure he or she can appeal the final determination or have his or her performance examined further.</p><p>I admire the work that has been done by the Minister and her predecessor, Deputy McHugh.  In one way, changes were foisted upon us and have led to a different type of exam process.  We want to consider the welfare of the student.  I am a big believer in the Maslow concept of reaching the point of self-actualisation.  We should allow a student to exhaust all avenues by the end of the process.</p><p>I understand where the Minister is coming from, but I am worried the SEC or the Department is not prepared for a more thorough approach to the end game.  I support the Minister in what she is doing.  &quot;Candidate&quot; is the awful word that is used in the Bill, but it should be &quot;student&quot;.  That student is a person and that person is in a family.  We all know what the stresses and strains of doing an ordinary leaving certificate were prior to Covid-19.  Add to that blended learning, an on-off presence in school and now exams.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I hope the Minister, as an tAire, will at the end of her tenure, whenever that will be, leave a legacy of real reform.  I urge her, as the Minister for Education, to be that innovative and progressive Minister, and abandon the shackles, if any exist, and make the education system a different type - more innovative and more student-centred.</p><p>The Minister is right that the professionalism of teachers and those who educate young people is absolutely unbelievable.  I refer to their quality, dedication and concern.  I have seen all that work as a former educator, as someone who is married to an educator and an uncle of a leaving certificate student but I hope that we can go to the end of the bridge to make it a really different leaving certificate in 2022.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#T00200"><p>I thank the Senator for his professional insights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#T00300"><p>I thank Senator Buttimer and appreciate his particular interest, and ongoing engagement, on matters of education.</p> <p>I suggest that many of the points he made are outside the scope of this Bill.  Be that as it may, I acknowledge that, and I said previously and last Friday, there are learnings in everything from Covid and I am in no doubt that there are learnings in terms of all that we have achieved in respect of calculated grades and now the accredited grades process.</p> <p>The Senator will be aware that we have the senior cycle review and an advisory report is due imminently.  I very much believe that the advisory report will be the catalyst to afford us the opportunity to look root and branch at all of the aspects of senior cycle provision, look at the very many positives and perhaps look at the shortcomings.  The report will allow us an opportunity, in consultation and in partnership with everyone within the education sector, to have a view and opinion on how we can chart our way forward in the very best interests of those whom we serve within the education sector, which is the students, as highlighted by the Senator.  I would also point to the fact that the Citizens' Assembly will have an opportunity to debate this issue going forward.  There is significant provision going forward, although it is not within the gift of this Bill, to address senior cycle issues.</p> <p>Specifically on the provision of an appeal, I want to make it very clear that the provision of the estimated marks is grounded fundamentally on the professional judgment of teachers and an in-school alignment process that includes a group of professional teachers and the involvement of the school principal.  Significant guidelines on the process have also been offered.  The amendment, as it stands, is not acceptable for the reasons that I have given.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.109" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.110" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 2, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.111" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 3 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.112" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#T00700"><p>Amendments Nos. 5 and 7 are related and may be discussed together by agreement.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#T00800"><p>I move amendment No. 5:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 7, between lines 22 and 23, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(b) Where a review is carried out, the Commission shall afford the candidate an opportunity to be heard. &rdquo;.  </blockquote> <p>Amendments Nos. 5 and 7 are the same.  The word &quot;candidate&quot; is used in the Bill.  Indeed, that is an unusual term for students and perhaps they will all stand for election after the campaigned that has occurred.  The amendments seek to give students a chance for their case to be heard.  I know that issues of capacity will be referred to but it is important to bear in mind that only a small number of students will look to present their case and not every student will wish to present in person at an appeal.  Given the impact and lifelong implications, the amendment is important.  Some candidates will have to quickly decide about applying to the Central Applications Office, CAO, or whether to take other CAO offers.  Therefore, my colleagues and I believe that it is important for candidates to get a chance to make their case at an appeal before making any decisions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#T00900"><p>The Bill already indicates that there will be due process so candidates will have an opportunity to present before the State Examinations Commission.  Therefore, I do not believe that there is any need for the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#T01000"><p>Sections 4 and 5 will operate in accordance with the procedures as may be prescribed.  In that regard, regulations are currently being drafted that give effect to the provisions concerned.  I indicated during the Second Stage debate and I, again, confirm here today, as did Senator Dolan, that there will be a robust review process in place that will not lead to decisions being made without considering individual circumstances.</p> <p>While the consideration of the provision is always subject to the constitutional protection of fair procedures and natural justice, and that regulations are in development, section 7(2) expressly requires that the regulations provide for what the amendment seeks.  Section 7(2)(a) specifies that the candidate will be notified should a report in regard to a communication under section 4 be made, what has been referred to as canvassing, or under section 5 if false and misleading may be given.  The candidate then has the opportunity to make representations to the commission.  In this way, the candidate is afforded the opportunity to be heard as the amendment intends.</p> <p>In addition, before any decision to withhold accredited grades is made, a review is carried out and any decision arising to withhold results must be accompanied with reasons for withholding.  That is subject to appeal so there is a second opportunity for the candidate's views to be taken into account.  Therefore, I cannot agree to the amendment, as presented.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#T01100"><p>I have listened to Senator Dolan and the Minister and concur with what has been said.  I am a small bit concerned about the language we are using.  The Minister used the phrase &quot;robust review&quot;, which is fantastic.  We have migrated in two areas.  For example, An Bord Plean&aacute;la holds oral in-person hearings and the Department of Social Protection has an in-person physical appeals system.  The Minister used the phrases &quot;make representations&quot;, &quot;the candidate is afforded the opportunity to be heard&quot;, and &quot;there is a second opportunity for the candidate&quot;.  She is 100% right that the review will be robust and provide a pathway.</p><p>Again, to return to my other point, and I suppose maybe I am getting older, more mature in my old age and becoming more reflective, but we need to cast aside some of the ways in which we have operated before.  I wonder, notwithstanding the remarks made by the Minister, instead of her saying &quot;make representations&quot; can we allow for the in-person opportunity to be heard?  We have an opportunity now.  We have democratised education beyond where it was when I started teaching.  We have student councils.  Plus students can make representations and effect change in a whole variety of ways, which is to be welcomed.  We have given, and rightly so, parental involvement in education a key place and a part, as a stakeholder.  I fear that the one area that we have not continued is in the exam system <i>per se</i>even though we have changed to the State Examinations Commission running exams and so on.  Can the Minister explain the robustness a bit more?  There is a part of me that likes the idea of giving the student or candidate the opportunity to be heard.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I support where the Minister is coming from because I know what will happen and integrity is important.  Why can we not go that little step further?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#U00200"><p>I thank the Senator.  I want to be clear that the candidate is afforded an opportunity to make his or her case.  The threshold is very high.  It will not be easy to find against a student for canvassing.  It is right and proper that it be vigorous and robust and that there be significant engagement around this.</p> <p>On the legal requirements, we have been clear that legal advice was sought and it confirms that the strong review that is afforded to everyone concerned in anything of this nature is a proportionate response.  I am happy that it is a proportionate response and that has been supported.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.120" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#U00400"><p>I move amendment No. 6:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 7, between lines 29 and 30, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(7) The Commission shall not decide to withhold all or any of the accredited  <blockquote> 	grades as provided for by <i>subsection (5)</i>, where it can be shown that the candidate had no knowledge of the communication that was made for his or her benefit by the first-mentioned person. </blockquote>(8) Where a communication is made without the candidate&rsquo;s knowledge as  <blockquote> 	prescribed for in<i>subsection (7)#</i>, the Minister shall make regulations providing for the first-mentioned person to be liable to a fine.&rdquo;. </blockquote>  </blockquote> <p>We touched on this on Second Stage.  I take on board the views of Senator Ruane on this issue but students should not be made to feel responsible for the actions of others, such as parents or guardians, in the weeks ahead.  As it stands, there is no distinction between a joint venture of student and parent and the lone actions of a parent.  When the consequences for canvassing are so serious, there is no room for ambiguity.  Students should be given peace of mind over the coming weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#U00500"><p>I confirm that the procedure under which a review is conducted will seek the views of the candidate in respect of any report made of canvassing.  Section 7(2)(a) expressly provides that the candidate will have the opportunity to submit representations.  If the student was unaware of any canvassing, the candidate has the opportunity to make that case in the representations.  If the candidate does make the case, the review must take this into account in reaching a decision.  The candidate enjoys the protection that any decision following the review must be reasonable based on the information available to the review.  As the intent of the amendment is already provided for, including by virtue of legal principles, the amendment does not improve the Bill.</p> <p>In regard to the drafting of the amendment, it could have unintended consequences and does not develop or elaborate on the policies or principles to be applied in determining how a candidate would show he or she had no knowledge of a communication or how a person making a communication would be afforded fair procedures.  Therefore, I will not agree to the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#U00600"><p>I have contacted the Department of Education to confirm that candidates have been notified through this whole year and through this process about the regulations around canvassing.  This process has to be fair for all students.  It is heartening to hear, as the Minister has pointed out, that the candidate will be able to make his or her case, if it comes to that.  It is positive that notification has been given out to candidates all this year regarding canvassing over these exams.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#U00700"><p>I do not agree with the criticisms of the amendment.  I think it strengthens the Bill and gives peace of mind to students over the coming weeks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.125/1" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#U00800"><p>Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 10; Níl, 26.</p><br/><br/><p>Tellers: Tá, Senators Fintan Warfield and Lynn Boylan; Níl, Senators Robbie Gallagher and Seán Kyne.</p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.125/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2021-05-11" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#U00800">
            <divisioncount ayes="10" noes="26" abstain="0" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1631" vote="aye">Ivana Bacik</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" vote="aye">Lynn Boylan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" vote="aye">Paul Gavan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1663" vote="aye">Annie Hoey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" vote="aye">Sharon Keogan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1673" vote="aye">R&oacute;n&aacute;n Mullen</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" vote="aye">Lynn Ruane</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" vote="aye">Marie Sherlock</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1684" vote="aye">Mark Wall</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" vote="aye">Fintan Warfield</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" vote="no">Garret Ahearn</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1633" vote="no">Niall Blaney</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" vote="no">Jerry Buttimer</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1638" vote="no">Malcolm Byrne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" vote="no"></mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" vote="no">Miche&aacute;l Carrigy</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1640" vote="no">Pat Casey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1641" vote="no">Shane Cassells</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" vote="no">Martin Conway</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1646" vote="no">Ollie Crowe</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1651" vote="no">Paul Daly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" vote="no">Regina Doherty</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" vote="no">Aisling Dolan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1655" vote="no">Timmy Dooley</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1658" vote="no">Robbie Gallagher</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" vote="no">R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1412" vote="no"></mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1665" vote="no">Se&aacute;n Kyne</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" vote="no">Tim Lombard</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1667" vote="no">Vincent P Martin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1670" vote="no">John McGahon</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1671" vote="no">Erin McGreehan</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" vote="no">Fiona O'Loughlin</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" vote="no">Joe O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1693" vote="no">Pauline O'Reilly</mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/1687" vote="no">Diarmuid Wilson</mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="abstain">
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.125/3" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#U00800"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.126" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 4 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.127" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 5</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1686" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#W00300"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 7, between lines 36 and 37, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;(b) Where a review is carried out, the Commission shall afford the candidate an opportunity to be heard.&rdquo;.  </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.129" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.130" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 5 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.131" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Sections 6 to 8, inclusive, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.132" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>SECTION 9</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.133" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 8:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.134" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.135" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Government amendment No. 9:</p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.136" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.137" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Section 9, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.138" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#W01400"><p>I move amendment No. 10:</p> <blockquote> 	In page 13, between lines 4 and 5, to insert the following:  	&ldquo;Legislative review<br /><br />10. (1) The Minister shall, not later than six months after the Leaving Certificate 2021 takes place, carry out a review of the operation of this Act.<br /><br />(2) Without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing, the Minister shall consider&mdash; <blockquote> 	(a) the introduction of a system of accredited grades for the Leaving Certificate Examinations on an ongoing, annual basis following the 2021 examinations,<br /><br />(b) the degree to which such a system may improve educational progression and outcomes for students of a lower socio-economic status,<br /><br />(c) whether such an accredited grade system could run concurrently with the traditional Leaving Certificate or eventually supplant the current model, and<br /><br />(d) potential structural reforms for the current Leaving Certificate model that could be made, drawing on insights gained from the operation of the Leaving Certificate Examinations in 2020 and 2021.  </blockquote>(3) The Minister shall, not later than three months after the commencement of the review under subsection (1), make a report to each House of the Oireachtas on the findings of that review, including proposals for policy and legislative reform.&rdquo;.  </blockquote> <p>I thank the Minister for being in the Chamber again this afternoon.  The amendment is pretty self-explanatory.  It proposes a review, to be put on a statutory footing under this legislation, to ensure that we do not go back to business as normal with regard to leaving certificate reform after the Covid-19 pandemic.  As I said last week, the Minister is in a really great position to bring about real change in this area.  What does it mean to be a teacher?  I do not believe anyone setting out to be a teacher wants to work within very tight parameters or to have to have a push-pull relationship with students to get through a curriculum quickly.  The leaving certificate does not just begin at the age of 15, 16 or 17.  Many kids are streamed into classes at the age of 11 and the futures of many are determined at the age of 12 when they enter secondary school based on an entrance examination.  They may not get to take on a language or they may miss out on certain subjects as their choices are narrowed down by the time they reach second year or third year.  </p><p>With regard to creating diversity in certain sectors, to be a garda or a teacher, one needs particular things at leaving certificate level which, as it stands, are sometimes just not provided for.  I was a lecturer in Maynooth University a number of years ago, working on the first Turn to Teaching programme.  This was aimed at young people who had experienced disadvantage due to a disability, their class or another issue but who really wanted to be teachers.  They would not have been able to do that without the Turn to Teaching programme.  For many of them it was almost impossible to get the adequate level of Irish when so many schools are so far behind on the curriculum, even after studying and trying and even with being able to study for Teastas Eorpach na Gaeilge, TEG, as part of the access programme and being allowed to fail over and over again.  Such young people are not given routes.  Although no one would think that I would aspire to being a garda, I looked into what is required to do so.  Even if one studies Irish and maths at foundation level in this country, one cannot become a garda.  At another level, we talk about having diversity.  </p><p>There is also a great deal of conversation around apprenticeships.  I always get a little bit angry when I hear this conversation because they are put forward as a great thing.  While they can be, one has to look at the demographic profile of those who end up being shoehorned into apprenticeships.  They are not spread across society.  Those from middle or higher classes do not encourage their children into apprenticeships.  It furthers the class divide.  Apprenticeships are often not transferable, which can create problems when economic issues arise.  They reinforce a cycle of poverty as people can develop a lack of transferable skills.  We need many options.  People should have a choice as to what to do with their lives.  They should not do carpentry or some other apprenticeship because they have no other option, but because they truly want to even though they know they could do anything else they wanted.  For a great many students, however, that is not the case.  They enter careers because they cannot choose another.  My daughter said something to me a few years back.  I have told this story previously.  She said that she thought she would be an ice cream van driver when she grew up.  I wondered whether she was for real.  I had dragged myself through college to change my family's practice over generations with regard to going to third level.  She said, however, that she was choosing to be an ice cream van driver even though she knew she could be something else if she wanted to be.  That is the thing.  It is about having choice.  With the leaving certificate at present, there is no choice.  I ask the Minister to accept the amendment which would give her and her Department an opportunity to come back to this Chamber with a full report and review as to how this year has gone in respect of the accredited grades system.  I ask her to accept the amendment and to allow this conversation on leaving certificate reform to continue in this Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1637" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#W01500"><p>I support the principle behind what Senator Ruane is trying to achieve.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2021&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=11"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Senator used the phrase "generational change" and I will add "cultural change" in the context of education.  I am not sure that we need to provide the legislative footing for it.  In recognition of the world we now inhabit, we have embarked upon gargantuan change in education from this time last year up to now, whereby accredited grades have been accepted and we have delivered an opportunity which is different for students from what had been the case hitherto.  I fundamentally believe, and I made the point earlier, that the Minister's legacy will be a positive one in many ways if we embrace the opportunity to bring meaningful change in education.  Who would have thought that, in 2021, blended learning and accredited grades would be accepted, although maybe begrudgingly because of what was foisted upon u?  We have moved from oral and aural, we have brought in practicals and we have changed maths at foundation and other levels.  The Minister spoke about the Citizens&rsquo; Assembly.  In the context of the legislative review, she can bring change in terms of educational progression and empowerment, and I hope she will do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1689" speakername="Fiona O'Loughlin" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X00200"><p>It is very fitting today, as we celebrate the legacy of Se&aacute;n Lemass and all he did for education, that we have the opportunity to discuss this legislation and to talk about what a future legacy can be.  What Senator Ruane has raised and indicated in her amendment is certainly worthy of debate.  It is a debate on which we need to have a full sitting and perhaps it is an issue on which we can invite the Minister back to our Chamber.  There is nothing more important than education in terms of equipping our young people with all they need to find their way in today's world.  While the leaving certificate is a measurement of attainment of a result that will enable a young person to go forward into the world of work, the world of further education or the world of apprenticeship, it should be about so much more.  It should be about equipping our young people with everything they need to deal with all of the challenges and conflicts that life shows.  While the world of the leaving certificate has certainly changed far more in the past 14 months than it had since it first came in, the reform of the leaving certificate is hugely important, and the education committee is taking this on as a piece of work, in conjunction with the Citizens&rsquo; Assembly.  We are on the cusp of a great debate and I am very gratified it is the Minister, Deputy Foley, who is going to lead that debate.  This amendment needs to be taken out of what we are dealing with now and brought to a wider and bigger forum.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X00300"><p>I call Senator Aisling Dolan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1681" speakername="Lynn Ruane" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X00400"><p>We only have one minute left and I wonder if there will be time for the Minister to come back on the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X00500"><p>I call Senator Dolan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X00600"><p>I very much agree that we need to support the socioeconomic side.  However, I believe the senior cycle review is the main focus of this Bill.  We want to see continuous assessment and we also need to see measures such as hot school meals and a DEIS resource identification system being rolled out.  That will support people to move through the school system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1582" speakername="Norma Foley" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X00700"><p>I thank Senators for their contribution and, in particular, Senator Ruane for the amendment.  I am not in a position to accept the amendment for a number of reasons.  The matters outlined for consideration by the Senator are not provided for in this Bill, which is focused on leaving certificate 2021 only.  This amendment, if accepted, would set aside the senior cycle review process, which is at a very advanced stage and the advisory report is imminent.  As referenced earlier today, the Citizens&rsquo; Assembly is another vehicle for consideration of many of the points the Senator has raised.  The amendment does not have regard to section 7 of the Education Act 1998, which, in respect of the determination of national educational policy, requires the Minister to make &ldquo;all reasonable efforts to consult&rdquo;, and that would be with the education partners - in other words, there would be wide consultation, which is very much part of senior cycle review.</p> <p>I acknowledge that the Senator brings incredible passion and commitment to this.  I am very aware of the body of work that needs to be done in ensuring curricula meet the needs of students and 21st-century learners.  Equally, I am especially conscious, as I know the Senator is, that a considerable body of work remains to close the attainment gap, which is very important.  However, there are two very definite vehicles, particularly the senior cycle review group, whose advisory report is imminent.  There will be ample opportunity.  I look forward to engaging directly with the Senator and with all the Members in that regard.  As I said, we also have the Citizens&rsquo; Assembly.  However, what the Senator has outlined is not for this Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X00800"><p>As it is now 12.45 p.m., I am required to put the following question in accordance with the order of the Seanad of this day: &ldquo;That amendment No. 10 is hereby negatived in committee, that section 10 is hereby agreed to in committee, that the Government amendments undisposed of are hereby made to the Bill, in respect of each of the sections undisposed of that the section or, as appropriate, the section, as amended, is hereby agreed to in committee, the Schedule is hereby agreed to and the Title is agreed to in committee, the Bill, as amended, is accordingly reported to the House, Fourth Stage is hereby completed, the Bill is hereby received for final consideration and the Bill is hereby passed.&rdquo;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.149" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X01000"><p>I thank colleagues for their participation and the Minister for her very full answers to questions.  When is it proposed to sit again?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1654" speakername="Aisling Dolan" time="09:00:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2021051100002#X01100"><p>At 10.30 a.m. next Monday, 17 May 2021, in the D&aacute;il Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2021-05-11a.152" nospeaker="true" time="09:00:00" ><p>The Seanad adjourned at 12.48 p.m. until 10.30 a.m. on Monday, 17 May 2021.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>