<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to make a statement on the case of a person, details supplied, who has been held in Maghaberry Prison without charge since 2016; and to outline the engagement the Irish Government has had with the British Government to highlight its dissatisfaction in relation to this case.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to provide an update on the provision of a 20-room unit for cystic fibrosis patients that was included in the programme for Government.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Fintan Warfield of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to review the role of the Standards in Public Office Commission regarding foreign investment into referendum campaigns.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Jerry Buttimer of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to prioritise the rebuilding and refurbishment works required at St. Gabriel&rsquo;s special school, Bishopstown, Cork.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection to undertake a review of the community employment scheme to allow people who have reached 66 years of age to continue to work under the scheme.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Victor Boyhan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Business, Enterprise and Innovation to review the criteria for issuing work permits to farm workers from outside the European Economic Area.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maria Byrne of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Finance and Public Expenditure to provide an update on the proposed legislation to allow public service staff to work until the age of 70.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Rose Conway-Walsh of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government to make a statement on the need for a fit for purpose sewerage scheme in Newport, County Mayo, to prevent sewage floating into the bay.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Kevin Humphreys of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to extend the period for submissions on the MetroLink project.</blockquote> <p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected the matters raised by Senators &Oacute; Donnghaile, &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, Warfield and Buttimer and they will be taken now.  I regret I had to rule out of order the matters submitted by Senators Conway-Walsh and Humphreys on the ground that the relevant Minister has no official responsibility in each matter.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.7" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#B00100">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#B00200">Northern Ireland</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#B00300"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an T&aacute;naiste.  I thank the T&aacute;naiste for taking the time to come to the Chamber.  I know he is very busy, so I appreciate his presence to debate the issue I am raising.</p> <p>I submitted this Commencement matter after last week's meeting of the Joint Committee on the Implementation of the Good Friday Agreement which heard from Mr. Peter Bunting and Mr. Conal McFeely of the independent assessment team.  They repeated their general frustration that the case of Tony Taylor is not getting the public attention it deserves.  Given that over two years have passed since the arrest and subsequent imprisonment of Mr. Taylor, our view is that his continued detention is wrong and a violation of his human rights.  We have consistently stated that if there is evidence against Mr. Taylor, it should be presented to him and his legal team in open court.  I contend that the most basic right of those who find themselves in prison, particularly for such a prolonged period of time, is to have an opportunity to address and challenge any evidence or any case against them, if such evidence or such a case exists.</p> <p>As the T&aacute;naiste will be aware, the problem is that we are being asked to place our trust and our faith in faceless secret British intelligence agencies and services.  The same people have refused to release their files on the Dublin and Monaghan bombings and told us there were weapons of mass destruction in Iraq.  I suggest that these obscure outlets are not exactly the most trustworthy.  Therefore, it is appropriate that any evidence that exists is not kept hidden and is instead put before Mr. Taylor in court.</p> <p>Over the past two years, the British Government has failed to produce any evidence that could justify Mr. Taylor's continued detention in any way.  We have to appreciate the strain this continued detention is placing on Mr. Taylor's wife and on members of his family, including his parents.  I believe their public description of their stress has shifted this case from the political domain, where it warrants much concern, to the humanitarian and human rights sphere.</p> <p>I appreciate the T&aacute;naiste's attendance today.  I was moved to submit this Commencement matter by the frustration of reputable and eminent figures like Mr. Bunting and Mr. McFeely, who are very frustrated about the lack of publicity, focus and attention being given to the case of this Irish citizen.  I hope that through the T&aacute;naiste, we can lift their frustrations and bring the case of Tony Taylor into a warranted public space where we can challenge the very real political and legal concerns that exist regarding his case and his ongoing detention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1286" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#B00400"><p>I am grateful to Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile for raising this important matter.  Last week, I had an opportunity to brief the D&aacute;il on my engagement regarding Mr. Taylor's case.  I assure the House that my officials have been engaging with this matter on an ongoing basis.</p> <p>The background to the Tony Taylor case is that he is from Derry and in recent years was a member of a dissident republican group.  In 1994, he was sentenced to 18 years in prison after he was seriously injured in a premature explosion in Derry.  He was released under the terms of the Good Friday Agreement.  He served a further three-year sentence from 2011 to 2014 for possession of a rifle.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">The T&aacute;naiste:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=250&amp;amp;pid=SimonCoveney&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->In March 2016, he was returned to prison after his early release licence was suspended by the then Secretary of State, Ms Theresa Villiers.</p><p>Mr. Taylor&rsquo;s case has been discussed regularly with the Northern Ireland Office through my officials at the Belfast secretariat.  My officials have also made visits to Mr. Taylor in Maghaberry Prison on two occasions, most recently in the past few weeks.  I have written to the Secretary of State, Ms Karen Bradley, on the case and I spoke to her on the matter when we met in London last Thursday.</p><p>The Parole Commissioners for Northern Ireland held a parole hearing on Mr. Taylor&rsquo;s revocation of licence in May 2017.  The decision of the parole commissioners at that time was to continue the revocation of licence.  A further review by the parole commissioners is under way and there had been an expectation that the review would conclude in the coming weeks.  However, we understand from discussions with the Northern Ireland Office and Mr. Taylor&rsquo;s legal representatives that there may be some delay in that process.  This is clearly not ideal and we have urged that every effort be made to avoid unnecessary delays.</p><p>I am aware that Mr. Taylor has publicly renounced any future engagement in dissident republican activity.  That is to be welcomed as there is no future on this island for political ends to be pursued through violence or the threat of violence.  I have also received a letter from Mr. Taylor's wife, Lorraine, and I am aware of the couple's difficult family circumstances.  I am also aware, as Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile indicated, that there is considerable concern in Northern Ireland across the broad nationalist and republican community about the basis and nature of Mr. Taylor's ongoing detention.  These have all been reflected in our ongoing engagement with the Northern Ireland Office on this matter.</p><p>The recent indications that Mr. Taylor&rsquo;s new parole hearing may take longer than expected is of particular concern, as he has been back in detention for more than two years without being charged or convicted of any offences.  I assure Senators that I and my officials will continue to actively monitor developments in the case and will continue to raise it with the Northern Ireland Office, including, as necessary, the Secretary of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1413" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#C00200"><p>I appreciate the update from the T&aacute;naiste and acknowledge the work he and his officials are doing regarding the case of Mr. Tony Taylor.  The concerns around this case, while predominately emanating from the nationalist and republican constituency, extend throughout a broad spectrum of humanitarian and legal organisations as well as the legal profession in general.  This is effectively a case of internment via remand, which warrants a great deal of concern.</p> <p>I appreciate the T&aacute;naiste's comment that his officials are keeping a watching brief on the issue.  His statement will be welcomed by all those inside and outside the Oireachtas who have an interest in the case.  I also share his concern regarding recent indications of a delay in the case, whether intentional or otherwise.  Is this position satisfactory?  What measures can the T&aacute;naiste take above and beyond monitoring the issue?  I am not asking him to step outside the constraints within which he must operate.</p> <p>I was reminded on my journey from Belfast to Dublin this morning that the average period of internment for those interned between 1971 and 1975 was two years.  Tony Taylor now finds himself in prison without evidence being put to him or his legal team for more than two years.  I thank the T&aacute;naiste again for taking the time to come to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1286" speakername="Simon Coveney" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#C00300"><p>It is important to put this case in context.  It is also appropriate in this debate that we call on all dissident republican groups that have not yet done so to renounce violence and commit to exclusively democratic means of pursuing their political aims.  I pay tribute to An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na for its ongoing work in dealing with the threat posed by dissident republican groups.</p> <p>On the case in question, the dissident republican group to which Mr. Tony Taylor was connected has made clear statements renouncing violence, which I welcome.  I do not know whether information is held on Mr. Taylor that can justify him being in prison.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Simon Coveney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=250"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=250&amp;amp;pid=SimonCoveney&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have raised our concerns about the case.  Holding somebody without publicly producing evidence against them raises real concerns, as I have witnessed in Derry in speaking to people.  I have raised the matter directly with the Secretary of State and will be talking to her again this week.  There is a process under consideration with the parole commissioners.  That is the appropriate process to use in making any decision in this case.  I hope we can ensure decisions will be made without further delay.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#E00050">Standards in Public Office Commission</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#E00100"><p>Senator Warfield, we are waiting on you.  There is a presumption that everything goes to plan.  Those who sit in their offices think we will wait for the next person.  We have already been delayed by a few minutes.  It is not your fault, but it is safer for those who have tabled Commencement matters to be here.  In my time, I was here for the start.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#E00200"><p>I was taking my lead from the title on the television when I was in the anteroom.  I welcome the Minister to the House.  As he will be aware, we are in the full swing of a referendum campaign.  This referendum in particular has taken a turn that is unprecedented.</p><p>The use of social media has been a growing campaigning platform for the past ten years or so.  Unlike other platforms, it has a distinct ability to be financed and co-ordinated online from foreign sources.  This was highlighted by potential Russian influence in the US presidential elections and subversive alt-right campaigns during the Brexit referendum.</p><p>We are only two weeks into the referendum, yet extensive investigative journalism has shown that the use of websites and paid advertising from the &quot;No&quot; campaign has been used at a cost of six figures per day.  Some of the videos are presenting themselves as being RT&Eacute; news bulletins and other websites appearing to be fact-based and objective have been targeted at people's online profiles.</p><p><i>Undecided8.org</i>purported to be unbiased and targeted Facebook users with what seemed to be an unending war chest.  It is linked to the Protect the 8th campaign and it has been sourced, run and funded by a US PR firm linked to Cambridge Analytica.  <i>Undecided8.org</i>used Facebook and Google trackers with the intention of helping with future retargeting, including of people who had clicked on the advertisements before.  The users' data is then vulnerable for future guerilla targeting, as are users of a similar demographic.  <i>Undecided8.org</i>has been shut down thanks to stellar investigation work by technology journalist Gavin Sheridan.  </p><p>However, this is only the start.  Numerous Facebook pages with few followers have suddenly poured resources into paid advertising targeting voters.  These advertisements are dishonest and subversive, and are intended to scaremonger voters who seek to establish their own views.  Referendums have always been subject to differences of opinion and interpretations of proposals.  However, these advertisements are blatantly ignorant of the facts and seek to undermine our democracy.  While I believe the State should never seek to censor campaigns that aim to present their views to the voting public, it also has a responsibility when the voting public has been targeted by a foreign source seeking to deceive undecided voters with resources that eclipse those of the Standards in Public Office Commission, SIPO, and the Referendum Commission and completely undermine their work.  </p><p>In an unprecedented move, Facebook has written to the Government and SIPO on the topic, the first time Facebook has reached out to any state government in regard to fake news during a public vote.  As of the past hour, Facebook has announced that it is suspending all referendum based adverts from sources outside the State.  This is a most welcome move and it should act as a call to action for Google and, more important, the State.  </p><p>We are now in a space where a private entity has done more to uphold democracy in the State than the State itself.  We are also failing to deal with the issue of hundreds of thousands of euro per day from foreign sources being spent by a campaign.  We are failing to uphold any notion of fear and even playing fields.  We are failing to deliver any resources which allow SIPO to effectively investigate whether campaigns receive donations from international sources and are failing to update our electoral legislation to deal with online campaigning as a platform.</p><p>I welcome that the Government has agreed to progress the Online Advertising and Social Media (Transparency) Bill.  Sinn F&eacute;in would amend the Bill and its objectives are timely.  It will make the sources of fake news transparent, but we still do not have regulation from a State level of what comes after.  SIPO needs effective resources and powers here and now.  We are 17 days away from a public vote, and all of the Government responses seem to be after the fact.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Fintan Warfield:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2458"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2458&amp;amp;pid=FintanWarfield&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Like the Brexit referendum and the US presidential election, I fear we will look back on the referendum in late May and say it was influenced by false reports online, and we will be left to deal with the consequences of that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#F00200"><p>I thank Senator Warfield.  I must apologise for the Minister, Deputy Eoghan Murphy, who is unable to attend but he has asked me to respond on his behalf.</p> <p>Senator Warfield is familiar with the 1997 Electoral Act, which provides the framework for dealing with political donations and sets out a wide range of related matters on the funding of political parties; the reimbursement of election expenses; the establishment of election expenditure limits; the disclosure of election expenditure; the setting of limits on permissible donations; the prohibition of certain donations; the disclosure of donations; and the registration of third parties who accept donations given for political purposes which exceed &euro;100.</p> <p>The Act also provides for the independent supervision of the donations regime by the Standards in Public Office Commission.  In broad terms, where a political donation in excess of &euro;100 is received by an election candidate, an account in a financial institution must be opened in the State.  In addition, there are a number of reporting requirements that need to be met in regard to the holding of such an account, for example, financial statements itemising all transactions in the account are required to be produced annually.  While SIPO does not disclose the contents of political donations accounts unless ordered to do so by a court, donation statements made by election candidates, Members of the Oireachtas, Members of the European Parliament or political parties are, on the other hand, made publicly available.  A donation statement is required when a political donation exceeding an aggregate of &euro;600 is received from a donor.</p> <p>Furthermore, under the Act an election candidate, a Member of the Oireachtas, a Member of the European Parliament, a political party or a third party who accepts donations for political purposes may not accept a range of donations, including a donation, of whatever value, from an individual other than an Irish citizen who resides outside the island of Ireland or a donation from a body corporate or unincorporated body of persons which does not keep an office in the island of Ireland from which one or more of its principal activities is directed.  Clearly, foreign donations of any amount are prohibited under the Act and where such donations have been made, it is incumbent upon the recipient to either return the donation to the donor or to remit it to SIPO.  In addition, the recipients of prohibited donations must comply with a direction given by SIPO in the matter.  Failure to do so is an offence under the Act.  The Standards in Public Office Commission may make such inquiries as it considers appropriate and may require any person, political party or third party to furnish any such information as it considers appropriate for the purpose of exercising its duties under the Act.</p> <p>For the avoidance of doubt, the principal purpose of the Act is to provide for openness and transparency with regard to political funding at elections and at referenda.  The Act's provisions relate to persons, political parties and third parties who accept donations for political purposes.</p> <p>The Senator is concerned that under the current law persons or organisations who do not accept political donations do not fall within scope of the Act and are not prohibited from using their resources in support of promoting a particular outcome at an election or a referendum.  Legislating to change that would require considerable consideration by the Oireachtas before it would be changed.  However, the Senator is raising an issue of systematic operations that may be targeting elections that have nothing to do with any of those contestants in the election.  That is an issue we need to consider as an Oireachtas in terms of how it is appropriate that that sort of activity should be regulated but as I said, the Standards in Public Office Commission is empowered to pursue anyone who accepts donations from overseas as they would be breaking the law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#F00300"><p>I thank the Minister.  I understand about political donations.  Many of us here have been through two election campaigns.  Does the Minister welcome today's announcement by Facebook?  Would the Government encourage Google and, by extension, YouTube to do the same?  The Minister mentioned the Standards in Public Office Commission, SIPO.  Could SIPO not be empowered with finance to take on its role under legislation in this campaign?  Are conversations being had at Cabinet level about the regulation of this entire area?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#G00100"><p>Deputy Bruton has explained he is not the line Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#G00150"><p>While I am not the line Minister, everyone recognises that in recent times we have seen a level of activity from forces outside of countries which are seeking to influence the results of elections.  It provides a challenge to us as to how a political system should manage that.  We, of course, value freedom of expression and the right of people to make their views known.  However, there are clearly levels of activity that would be a cause of concern.  It would appear that Facebook also feels that the level of activity is a cause of concern to it.</p> <p>Legislation, however, cannot be made on the hoof.  This is an area in which the Minister cannot assume powers which the Oireachtas has not given him.  We would need to think carefully about the implications of seeking to regulate this area because it goes to the heart of people's right to express themselves.  We need to think long, hard and carefully as to how we would address this issue.  There is no doubt that as one scans the world stage, one sees activities, whether they be bots or other operations, which are a cause of concern to anyone who wants to see citizens make a discerning decision based on objective and fair information being presented to them, as well as people having the chance to campaign for or against a proposition in a fair way.</p> <p>While I cannot speak for the Minister, I recognise there is an issue to which the Oireachtas will need to return if it is not regulated at European level, as this is not just an Irish issue.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.23" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#G00200">Schools Refurbishment</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#G00300"><p>I thank the Minister for attending the Chamber and the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise the matter of St. Gabriel's special needs school, Bishopstown, Cork.</p> <p>The Minister is familiar with the school.  It was originally designed for Scoil Cholumb&aacute;in and Scoil Therese primary schools.  When they closed, St Gabriel's was allowed to use the building.  It is fair to say that this building was never designed to be a special needs school.  The building's conditions are unacceptable for the 43 pupils and staff.  These are children, between the age of four and 18, who are most vulnerable with severe to profound intellectual disabilities.  I have met with the parents and visited the school.  The school campus does not match the mission statement of the school or the philosophy espoused by the Minister and the Department of Education and Skills.  Neither does it match the capital building programme outlined by the Department or the investment in education facilities, particularly in special needs, across the city of Cork.</p> <p>Urgent funding needs to be put into this school's buildings.  The school&rsquo;s parents&rsquo; association has commenced a GoFundMe page.  This is a matter of priority.  This is a statement of how we treat the most vulnerable children who need the help of the State.  The education they are receiving is absolutely exemplary.  The school building, however, is unbelievably bad.  Many of the pupils are non-verbal.  The school enrols children with dual diagnosis with severe to profound intellectual disabilities and autism.  The school building, however, is not fit for purpose.  If we believe in early intervention to allow students to achieve their full potential, then this school&rsquo;s building requires a complete overhaul and a commitment from the Government to change it as a matter of urgency.  I hope the Government will prioritise the upgrading and refurbishment of this special needs school.  It would send a message to the children, parents and staff that we will provide for them.</p> <p>Being involved with the COPE Foundation, I recognise the importance of every individual in society.  I hope the Minister will look favourably on this plea for help from St. Gabriel&rsquo;s school and its community.</p> <p>I thank the Cathaoirleach for allowing me to raise the matter and the Minister for being present.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#H00100"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  My Department clearly accepts that the accommodation in St. Gabriel's special school is not fit for purpose.  It has spatial limitations, particularly for children with challenging behaviour.  The school caters for 43 pupils and it has a strong complement of teachers and SNAs.  The pupil-teacher ratio is 1:1.9 and, therefore, the State provides significant support but there is a recognition that the facilities need to be addressed.  I understand the school applied last year for improved accommodation and my officials have visited the school and assessed that need.  They have also taken the opportunity to discuss with the NCSE the general need in the area and the school will have the potential to expand the scope of its services to meet the local need.</p> <p>The adjacent accommodation is owned by the Diocese of Cork and Ross.  St. Gabriel's special school currently occupies two classrooms in this adjacent building by agreement with the diocese.  My Department will send an official to visit the school authority tomorrow, 9 May, to progress the assessment of the proposed works, finalise the scope of works and work out how they can be moved forward and in what delivery mode they can be done.  My Department recognises the seriousness of the case and will work with the school to seek a solution to its needs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#H00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his positive reply.  It is a unique school and it shares a site with the Brothers of Charity and the Diocese of Cork and Ross.  The staff need has been met by the Department but changes are needed to the built environment and the learning environment.  I hope that tomorrow's visit will be the beginning of a positive progression of the proposed development.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.27" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.15 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.28" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#N00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding arrangements for the sitting of the House on Wednesday, 9 May 2018, to be taken without debate on the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, motion regarding appointment of a member to the Legal Services Regulatory Authority, to be taken without debate on the conclusion of No. 1; No. 3, motion regarding Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 regulations, back from committee, to be taken without debate on the conclusion of No. 2; No. 4, motion regarding Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 regulations, back from committee, to be taken without debate on the conclusion of No. 3; No. 5, Criminal Justice (Corruption Offences) Bill 2017 - Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes, those of all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given not less than five minutes to reply to the debate; No. 6, Private Members' business, Civil Law (Costs in Probate Matters) Bill 2017 - Second Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 5, with the time allocated to this debate not to exceed two hours; and No. 7, statements on corporate manslaughter, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 6 and to conclude within 40 minutes, with the contributions of all Senators not to exceed five minutes and the Minister to be given not less than three minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#O00100"><p>I ask the Leader to clarify the position in respect of Nos. 5 and 6.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#O00200"><p>No. 5 is the Criminal Justice (Corruption Offences) Bill 2017 - Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m., with the contribution of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes, and the Minister to be given no less than five minutes to reply to the debate.  No. 6, Private Members' business, is the Civil Law (Costs in Probate Matters) Bill 2017 - Second Stage, to be taken on the conclusion of No. 5, with the time allocated to this debate not to exceed two hours.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#O00300"><p>I thank the Leader for that clarification.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1414" speakername="Mark Daly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#O00400"><p>I know we had plenty of time for Brexit last week and we will have another debate on Thursday to mark Europe Day, but I would like to speak about Brexit again in the context of Boris Johnson's latest pronouncement.  He said during his visit to the US that the customs partnership is a crazy plan because it will create a whole new web of bureaucracy.  He has gone against his own Prime Minister on this issue.  Of course, he has not offered a different plan other than to come up with what has been termed the "Boris border".  This type of seamless and frictionless border has not been tested because it does not exist anywhere in the world.  We know this because a month ago, it was confirmed in a House of Commons report that no technological solutions, other than the theoretical, are available anywhere in the world to keep the Irish Border open if Britain leaves the customs union and the Single Market.  The enterprise secretary in Westminster has said that thousands of jobs will be lost if Britain does not sign up to one or the other because of the extent of Britain's reliance on frictionless trade with the EU.</p> <p>I thank the Leader for organising statements on corporate manslaughter.  I propose to circulate to Members a letter from the Irish Haemophilia Society on this issue.  This is relevant because the hepatitis C scandal is being seen again in a new guise.  Neither the hepatitis C scandal nor the CervicalCheck cancer issue that is now before us can be attributed to mismanagement alone.  Once more, the health service has covered things up by not informing people when they should have been informed.  That is what happened 27 years ago in the hepatitis C case, which resulted in two tribunals, more inquires and recommendations.  In 2006, the Law Reform Commission recommended that a corporate manslaughter Bill should be introduced to ensure people who fail to act are held to account, not by losing their jobs, resigning or going off with their pensions, but by going to jail for up to 12 years.  Such a Bill has not been passed in this House, however.  There are times when we do statements.  Maybe the next legislation we debate should be the Committee Stage of the Corporate Manslaughter (No. 2) Bill 2016.  I will raise this again during the statements on corporate manslaughter.  Why are we talking about investigations by commissions of inquiry?  Such investigations should follow criminal investigations and interviews carried out by the Director of Public Prosecutions and the Garda.  We can put in place the systems that are required after that.  People have died as a result of mismanagement.  We were told in this House less than two years ago that there was no need for the Corporate Manslaughter (No. 2) Bill 2016 because people could go to jail under existing legislation.  That can be tested now on foot of a Garda investigation, rather than an investigation set up by this House or the other House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#O00500"><p>Last week, I spoke about the need for us to get behind or beneath the Ministers when disasters like the cervical screening disaster take place.  I explained how the Carltona doctrine or principles allow public servants, including those who took decisions and hid information in this case, to remain faceless.  I want to see Tony O'Brien go, but there are other people who need to go too.  If he goes, what about the people beneath him who did not report?  Where does the responsibility lie?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Gerard P. Craughwell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2402"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2402&amp;amp;pid=GerardPCraughwell&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->All too frequently in this world, we look for the head of a big name, while the wrongdoers continue to do the same thing.  Nowhere is more the case than in the health service where we have had scandal after scandal, yet the wrongdoers always remain in place and there is no accountability.  I am all for protecting workers and ensuring they are treated fairly and correctly.  However, when senior officials deliberately set out to hide information that cost people their lives, there must be accountability.  Surely it cannot stop at the desk of the Minister or chief executive officer as they cannot have their finger on every pulse at all times.  <br/><br/>My colleague, Senator Mark Daly, spoke a few moments ago about the British Foreign Secretary, Mr. Boris Johnson.  The <i>EUobserver</i>website features an interesting article under the title, &quot;At Northern Irish border, Brexit risks hard-won peace&quot;.  It begins as follows:</p><blockquote>In Belfast's Alexandra Park stands a very hard border.  A three-meter high wall cuts through the hilly green meadow, separating the republican Catholic and the unionist Protestant communities. </blockquote><p>The piece then discusses the risks presented by a border in the event that Brexit goes wrong.  The utterances of the Foreign Secretary, Mr. Johnson, and some other British Ministers indicate that Brexit is going wrong.  As I have stated numerous times, the Taoiseach, T&aacute;naiste and Minister of State with responsibility for European affairs, Deputy Helen McEntee, have done a tremendous job.  However, all of their work will come to nothing if the Conservative Party in the United Kingdom falls apart and the Brexit negotiations collapse.  It is beginning to look as if that could happen because the clock is ticking and nobody seems to have a clear idea of where we are going.  One of my fears arising from the current cervical screening disaster is that the importance of Brexit may slip off the agenda.  For this reason, I seek an assurance that Brexit remains a high priority.<br/><br/>Last week, I asked for a debate on corporate governance in the public sector, with particular reference to the Carltona doctrine, which protects individuals who clearly act wrongfully in their positions, and how this principle made its way into the Ministers and Secretaries Act.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#P00200"><p>The cervical cancer screening issue has created a number of knock-on issues in terms of legislation.  We must, in legislation, address open disclosure and the issue of corporate manslaughter.  Major questions also arise regarding procurement and ensuring the best and most appropriate outcomes in this area.  I will bring proposals to the House on this issue before the summer.  I hope all sides will work with me on that.</p> <p>Facebook has announced it will not accept advertisements purchased abroad in the lead-up to the referendum on the eighth amendment.  I first highlighted this issue last November at the World Forum on Democracy, which focused on big data.  In recent months, I have been pressing relentlessly for the implementation of necessary regulation and legislation in this area and for social media platforms to step up and take some responsibility in the interim.</p> <p>Just a few weeks ago, officials from Facebook appeared before a meeting of the Joint Committee on Communications, Climate Action and Environment at which I and others challenged them to take action in response to the large amount of political advertising and sponsored content being targeted at Irish voters, including advertisements from unaccountable, unidentified and international actors.  We urged them to ensure Ireland would not be another bad example of this practice.  The committee was informed that Facebook did not have the technical capacity to provide the transparency required.  I urged the company to stop selling advertising if it could not deliver transparency.</p> <p>When I made the same demand last week, I was informed it was almost impossible to meet, yet today Facebook has agreed to stop selling advertisements to unaccountable international actors in respect of our referendum and the decision which is for Irish people to make as part of our electoral process.  The company's decision is correct and in line with the spirit of our electoral laws.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Alice-Mary Higgins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2480"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2480&amp;amp;pid=AliceMaryHiggins&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Nonetheless, our electoral laws and online regulations need reform and the ultimate solution must be legislation.  The onus is on Google, through its advertisements, and Youtube to take responsibility and ensure they follow the spirit of our electoral laws by also declaring that they will not take internationally purchased referendum advertisements.  I urge Google and Youtube which are linked and any other relevant platform to take action.  </p><p>As well as the legislative work needed for online regulation, there is a concern about a loophole in the Data Protection Bill 2018 which could potentially allow parties or candidates to hire companies such as Cambridge Analytica or Cantor.  That is not in the true spirit of Article 9.2(d) of the general data protection regulation.  It exceeds what is included in it.  It behoves the Government to take the opportunity to get this right from the beginning by ensuring we close any loophole which could be manipulated in that way.  I hope the Minister for Justice and Equality will take this on board.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q00200"><p>I welcome the announcement made by Facebook that it will no longer accept advertisements aimed at the upcoming referendum on the eighth amendment if funded by organisations outside the country.  From today such advertisements will be rejected.  <i>The Irish Times</i>reports that a combination of machine learning and good old-fashioned people power will govern this initiative.  Facebook has some automated tools at its disposal that would help to identify and reject advertisements.  In case anything slips through the net, the advocacy groups and the transparent referendum initiative will have an input into the reporting process.  These groups have dedicated communications channels with Facebook.  While there are no facilities for ordinary citizens to contact Facebook directly and report advertisements, one could bring an advertisement to the attention of the advocacy groups and the transparent referendum initiative.  I encourage all citizens to be proactive in the absence of legislation.</p><p>We are in the full swing of the referendum campaign that has taken an unprecedented turn.  <i>undecided8</i>has been shut down thanks to the stellar investigation carried out by the tech journalist Gavin Sheridan.  However, as he knows, it is only a start.  The State has a responsibility to the voting public which has been targeted by a foreign source which is seeking to deceive undecided voters and its resources are greater than those of the Standards in Public Office Commission, SIPO, and the Referendum Commission combined.  It is undermining their work.  This should absolutely be a call to action for Google, Youtube and the State.  The State is failing to give resources to SIPO to investigate effectively whether campaigns are receiving donations from international sources.  Will we continue to have zero defence against foreign influences on public votes and will the online free-for-all continue? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q00300"><p>I acknowledge the transparent referendum initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q00400"><p>The Senator is not allowed to come back in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q00500"><p>That is all I want to say.  I simply acknowledge the transparent referendum initiative.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q00600"><p>Ten minutes was given to dealing with this topic by way of a Commencement matter today before the Senator even mentioned it.  Senator Fintan Warfield was off the blocks ahead of the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q00700"><p>I propose that No. 20, Broadcasting (Amendment) Bill 2017, be taken before No. 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q00800"><p>I refer to the death of a former Deputy, Monica Barnes, who was not a Member of this House.  I do not think there will be formal-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q00900"><p>She was.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#Q01000"><p>I see; therefore, there will be the possibility of formal statements being made.  She was a very old friend and I express my sympathy to her family.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->She was a remarkable woman.  She was very maternal.  She was one of the founders of the National Woman's Council of Ireland, NWCI.  She held passionate views which she expressed strongly but she was never nasty.  There was not a nasty bone in her body.</p><p>Another thing I would like to draw to the attention of the House is the increasing spread of a noxious form of political correctness around the place and employed by civil servants around this House.  I sent a letter to a group of my voters.  It was returned to me on the advice of the joint services committee, I believe, because the letter had the temerity to mention two words, one of which was "abortion" and the other of which was "referendum".  It is bloody ridiculous if, as a public representative, one cannot exercise one's freedom to express one's opinion on these matters which are a matter of significant current national debate.  What kind of little earwigs are there around the place who are trying to stop people from expressing opinions?  It is nonsensical.  I would like to see something done about it.  Is somebody somewhere, apart from myself, going to stand up and say, "Enough is enough".  We are elected public representatives.  We are elected with the intention of expressing our views publicly and it is not up to some little nitpicker to say one cannot use the words "abortion" or "referendum" in a communication with the electorate.  It is absolutely nonsensical.  I would like to ask the Leader if he can do something about it.  Can he raise the matter and see what the committee is at?  Why is it doing these sorts of things?  Why is it curtailing freedom of expression for public representatives?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#R00200"><p>I understand the point you make, but there is a political fortification behind that decision which the civil servants are endeavouring to implement.  Maybe the Leader can raise the matter at a higher level.  I do not think it is emanating from the civil servants within the House.  There is a political foundation for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#R00300"><p>I see.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#R00400"><p>I am subject to correction.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#R00500"><p>Thank you.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#R00600"><p>I would like to echo the comments of Senator Norris on Monica Barnes, who was a superb public representative and fought passionately for what she believed in.  She was one of the individuals in our political system who would have spread enlightenment and brought the country forward.</p> <p>In regard to the second point the Senator raised, I would agree with him if I felt there was any attempt to curtail the right of an elected representative to make his or her views known to his or her constituents or electorate.  I am sure the Leader will address that.</p> <p>I also want to mention that on 26 April I highlighted the very serious issue of the lack of school places for children with autism spectrum disorder, ASD, in the country, in particular in Fingal, specifically Skerries.  There were certain inaccuracies during the course of that debate, which I want to clarify.  S&iacute;olta provides an excellent preschool service for children with ASD free of charge.  Georgina, who was one of the parents I mentioned, is very pleased with her tutor.  </p> <p>Today I want to ask the Minister for Health to publish the two reports commissioned in August 2017, one by the Department of Health and another by the HSE, in respect of autism and those on the ASD spectrum.  We were told they were two essential pieces of work in order to further inform the Bill which was to ensure we have a national strategy for people in the country who have autism.  I know the Minister, Deputy Harris, is extremely busy, especially over the past two weeks with CervicalCheck and the referendum on the eighth amendment, and much else besides.  We need the reports to be published and the ASD Bill to go to D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann.  We need an ASD strategy, and it should contain an action plan such as that which we had for jobs and have for housing.  An action plan is badly needed so that our children and adults with autism can make their full contribution as citizens to their country.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator James Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2180"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2180&amp;amp;pid=DrJamesReilly&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Failing that, I would like the Minister to come to the House and explain what is delaying that Bill, which we first debated a year ago last Thursday.  I ask the Leader to ask the Minister to come to the House to discuss these reports and the Bill.</p><p>I wish to inform the House that over 71,000 people have signed the petition in support of this Bill so the message is loud and clear.  This is an issue that will not go away.  It is an issue that is urgent.  Somebody mentioned earlier that the clock is ticking.  The clock is ticking for these children whose parents watch in anguish when they see more time pass that does not allow them avail of the services that could allow them progress.  I thank the Cathaoirleach.  I ask the Leader to raise the issue with the Minister and encourage him to publish these two reports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#S00200"><p>I am sad to say I am raising yet another issue with the Health Service Executive, HSE.  I am getting calls from people anxious about whether the Government is making investigations into the drug sodium valproate, branded as Epilim, after it emerged that it was linked with birth defects and developmental issues.  The HSE said it was preparing to create a register of all the women in Ireland whose babies may have been damaged in the womb by the drug.  Again, we have families wondering if they are on the register of people affected by this drug.  We are still talking about what will happen to the women affected by the CervicalCheck scandal and here comes another one.</p> <p>There may be as many as 400 Irish children with birth defects and developmental issues because their mothers took Epilim.  Before 2014, there was no warning label on the drug's packaging.  The Oireachtas health committee heard last month that there was a mismatch between risks of the drug being known and women being told about them.  Health professionals in the United Kingdom were warned about the dangers of the drug ten years before those in Ireland were informed.  There was also the difference between what health professionals knew and what patients were told.</p> <p>Again, there is a problem with communications.  Why does the culture still exist whereby doctors can withhold patients' information and leave them in the dark about their own medical history?  Primary care should always put the patients first.  If something shows up on a test and the treating doctor is informed, the patient - man or woman - needs to be contacted over the telephone.  There should never be a practice of sending a text telling the patient to make a new appointment to discuss the matter.  Patients should make an appointment, but they should not have to pay another fee.  The fact that they may be asked to pay a fee for going back to the doctor is another issue.  That practice has to stop.  </p> <p>Patients must be able to trust that they are getting the full facts as soon as possible from their doctors, who in turn must feel free to be able to share the sensitive information without fear of legal consequences.  That has to include issues that become apparent about drugs which were prescribed in the past, but there must be change from the top down.  Too many Departments are keeping things from Ministers, the way the HSE keeps things from its patients across all areas.  Not only does the left hand not know what the right hand is doing, no one knows what is going on.</p> <p>We need to call time on that.  Enough is enough.  We can no longer reel from one controversy to another and act as if it is business as usual.  The HSE has got to work better for us.  We are paying for it.  We can no longer hear the words, "lessons were learned and it will not happen again".  Our citizens voted for us.  We work for them.  We should be their voice.</p> <p>In terms of the HSE, the Taoiseach has said there needs to be radical change.  I am sure people are rolling their eyes now wondering what will change.  If we are still sitting here and getting it wrong, there has to be change.  I would like the Minister to tell us exactly what is happening with this drug.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#S00300"><p>Is the Senator calling for a debate on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#S00400"><p>I am, yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#S00500"><p>I wish to raise two simple matters.  First, can the Leader update us in the coming days on the Adoption (Information and Tracing) Bill 2016?  This Bill was No. 100 of 2016 and was sponsored by the Leader, Senator Buttimer, on behalf of the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs.  I understand there are some difficulties going on in the background with respect to this Bill, which require further work.  Clearly, the Minister is aware of all of that.  I had some discussions with parties on this Bill in recent days and I am led to believe there are now difficulties with it and the progression of the legislation appears to have been stalled, but let us get the correct version of what is happening.  The Leader might forward me a briefing note on it.  The Minister, Deputy Katherine Zappone, is busy.  She is doing a great deal of good work but the Leader might provide me with a briefing note or some clarification on the status of this Bill, where it is now and when it is proposed that the next Stage will be taken.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I formally second the amendment proposed by Senator Warfield regarding No. 20 on the Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1375" speakername="Gabrielle McFadden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#T00200"><p>I also raise the issue of the CervicalCheck helpline which has been raised.  Between 11,000 and 12,000 calls have been made to the helpline but only about one third of these calls have been returned.  The helpline has stated calls from women who had a diagnosis of cancer are given priority, which is proper order.  In recent days, 500 calls were made to people who were concerned about their tests.  The CervicalCheck helpline could not give a date, however, as to when the rest of the calls would be addressed.  That is not good enough.  The Minister has made funds and resources available to GPs to look after patients who have concerns and to do repeat smear tests.</p> <p>While the Minister is busy and should not necessarily be requested to attend the House, would it be possible for Members to get a briefing or update on where we are at with this helpline?  We must not forget the thousands of women whose lives have been saved because of smear testing.  That should not go unmentioned.  We must urge women to continue to have smear tests done.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1385" speakername="Grace O'Sullivan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#T00300"><p>I echo the words of Senators Higgins and Warfield with regard to the announcement by Facebook that it will restrict foreign advertising on the eighth amendment for the duration of the referendum campaign.  This is to be welcomed and we hope Google will follow suit.</p> <p>There may be a loophole, however, with regard to Internet ad-handling companies.  These are Irish-based companies which can receive funding from international companies to advertise on their behalf on the Internet.  We have to be cognisant of this.  There is a short window of opportunity for international companies to advertise and, in some cases, give false information to the Irish people.  We are in the lead-up to the referendum on 25 May.  It is important that the Irish people receive correct information and there is not interference from foreign companies with digital advertising.  Irish companies, which are in the business of ad handling, should be aware that Facebook has taken some leadership today, and it we hope to see Google do likewise.  I hope these Irish-based companies, for the want of a few bob, will not advertise foreign companies and take advantage of a potential loophole.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1399" speakername="Neale Richmond" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#T00400"><p>I join other Senators in marking the passing of former Senator and Deputy Monica Barnes.  I attended the funeral this morning and the homily given by the priest was very fitting of the varied career she had both in politics and education.  I know we are thinking of her husband, Bob, and her family at this time.</p> <p>A recent survey found Irish people have an 80% positive viewpoint of immigration and migration in general.  This is to be welcomed.  When one looks at the atmosphere in the UK, France and across continental Europe where, unfortunately, far-right nationalist parties are beginning to gain traction with anti-immigrant rhetoric, it is good that Ireland, an open country with its own history of migrants - I know myself as someone who emigrated many years ago - is proud of and celebrates immigration.  Will the Leader invite the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, or the Minister of State, Deputy Stanton, to discuss the possibility of an international immigrant day in Ireland in the near future?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#T00500"><p>I thank the Senator for his brevity.  I call Senator Coghlan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#T00600"><p>Senators Mark Daly and Craughwell referred to the British Foreign Secretary, Mr. Johnson.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paul Coghlan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->If one were to pay attention to some of his comments, one might have cause for concern.  However, I prefer to listen to the Business Secretary, Mr. Greg Clark, the Brexit Secretary, Mr. David Davis, the Chancellor of the Exchequer, Mr. Philip Hammond, and the Prime Minister, Mrs. May.  We are well aware of the divisions within the British Government and the Tory Party.  However, they all know they have to avoid a hard border within Ireland and they do not want a border between the islands of Ireland and Britain.  These are matters for negotiation and we will have to be patient while the negotiators hammer out the issues behind all our backs in Brussels.</p><p>Another debate on this would be welcome but not until the outcome of the leaders' summit in June is known.  I plead with Members to be patient until then.  I wish Michel Barnier and all the other negotiators well as they attend to their work diligently.  Let them at it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#U00200"><p>Before I call the Leader to reply, I would like to be associated with the marks of respect and condolences offered to the family of the late Monica Barnes.  I served with her on the justice committee and I travelled abroad with her.  I always found her affable and she was a formidable but fair opponent.  She will be a loss to politics.  If my memory serves me correctly, her father was from Dunmanway in west Cork where he served as a police officer.  She had that west Cork link and she was a close friend of a great ally, and sometimes foe, of mine, the great former Deputy, P.J. Sheehan.  They were great friends but her west Cork connection may be where she got her fighting skills from.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#U00300"><p>I thank the 12 Members who contributed to the Order of Business.  On my own behalf and on behalf of my party, I offer my sympathies to Monica Barnes's husband, Bob, and her family.  I commend her on a life well lived.  She should be extolled for her diligence as a public servant.  She probably was the epitome of the wing of Fine Gael many of us want to be part of.  I had the pleasure of meeting her a few weeks ago at the back door of Leinster House and she was full of life looking forward to the referendum campaign.  She was due to take part in a press conference last week.  That shows how vulnerable we all are and how precious life is.</p> <p>Monica Barnes was a politician I grew to admire and I had the pleasure of meeting her on a number of occasions.  She was always effusive in offering support and encouragement.  As previous speakers said, and as has been reported in the media, she worked tirelessly on behalf of women and her constituents.  She did the State a huge service and I extend my deepest sympathies to her family.</p> <p>Senator Daly raised the issue of Brexit and the ongoing machinations within the UK Government.  It would be preferable if we did not get involved in that.  The Government is clear regarding the priority of Brexit and its position on it.  There has been no deviation from that.  As Senator Coghlan said, Mr. Barnier and Mr. Tusk have been clear regarding the Commission's approach and it is incumbent on us to allow for progress to be made at the next Council meeting.  We are clear as a Government on what is our position.  The Taoiseach, T&aacute;naiste and Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade, Deputy McEntee, will continue to represent the Government and build alliances throughout Europe.  It is important though, as Senator Daly correctly said, that the issue be well flagged and that we highlight the rolling maul that is the British position while, at the same time, recognising that we have an obligation and a duty to respond as a Government on behalf of our citizens and on an all-island basis.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am glad the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, will be in the House later on regarding corporate manslaughter.  I would be happy to have that matter discussed.  I would remind Senator Daly that his own party has Private Members' time any time it wishes to bring the Bill forward.  That time is available to Fianna F&aacute;il.  The Government is not blocking the Bill coming back as he knows quite well.  It is a matter we will tease out with the Minister for Justice and Equality this evening.</p><p>Senator Craughwell raised the issue of accountability.  It is important that we recognise that there is a need for accountability.  The Government has been very clear on that, on the matters of the health system or on any matter to do with governance of public bodies, moneys, utilities or services.  People want accountability and the Government wants it.  We demand that and it should happen.</p><p>There is a question that must be posed and I do not fly a flag for anybody, other than the Irish citizens that we represent.  What do we want to have here?  Do we want to have the HSE chief executive gone now or do we want to see the mess cleaned up?  This is a tragedy.  This is a scandal.  I do not believe it is served by saying a head is needed, and I do not say that Senator Craughwell is saying that to be fair to him.  This is about ensuring that everything that can be done in the next few weeks to reassure the women of Ireland and the families can be done so that we will never revisit this again.  I agree with Senator Craughwell that there is a need to have a high priority in terms of corporate governance and what it means to be in a position of responsibility.  I fully subscribe to that viewpoint.  People cannot be left to walk away and left without having to pay the price of being held to account.  I am always of that viewpoint, but let us get to the facts.  That is why we have established an independent investigation.  Let us then make our decisions based on the results that come back.  I am happy to debate that at any time.</p><p>I refer to the points made by Senator McFadden on the issue of cervical cancer.  I am told the helpline had nearly 11,000 phonecalls.  There are over 7,600 callbacks to be made.  Some of that involves a clinical consultation, some of that involves a doctor or nurse being involved and checking and collating information.  In accepting some of the criticism that has been made, I think it is important to reassure people that the quality of the callback that will be given is important as well.  We all accept that the concerns and fears of the women and families must be addressed and we must do everything possible to ensure that the callback from the telephone helpline takes place in a timely, prompt manner.  I hope that will happen.</p><p>I know the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, and the Taoiseach have been very strong and strident on the returning of calls and the provision of accurate clinical information.  We must respond in a matter of days rather than prolonging it for people.  That is something we need to see continually kept at the heart of this.  We must give information to women and reassure them, as the Taoiseach and the Minister have done, on the smear test and redress.</p><p>I refer to the issue of Facebook as raised by Senators Higgins and Warfield.  I welcome the decision of Facebook to ban paid political advertisements from outside the jurisdiction.  I commend the transparency campaigners who have highlighted the need for this type of influence to be stopped.  It is also important to recognise that Facebook has a responsibility which today it is living up to.  As Senator Higgins rightly said, if there are anomalies regarding the GDPR in Article 9.2(d) then let us get it right rather than having to continually revisit it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The whole issue of social media advertising, as well as publishing on social media, is an area where we need to see quick action taken.  Senator Warfield tabled a Commencement matter this afternoon in which he mentioned the Russian election.  Of course we do not know that the Russians influenced the American election yet but we will await some of the results.  I believe it is important that we call out people who interfere in our democracy.  I welcome the fact this is taking place.</p><p>The level and type of campaigning has changed.  As Senator Warfield said in his remarks earlier, it is important to recognise that the way we do business is different now.  This means we must all be aware of the consequences.  It is important that we have an electoral commission in our country that will grapple with the idea.  This morning we saw a most despicable attempt to denigrate and degrade the Minister for Health, Deputy Harris, by certain people who put up posters outside his constituency office on a route to a school.  It beggars belief that this could be tolerable or acceptable in any democracy.  I condemn such behaviour in any shape or form.  As politicians, we can argue within the four white lines of the D&aacute;il, Seanad or council chambers.  We can participate in elections and we are held to account.  We have rules and regulations under which we are governed, but some of the behaviour is unacceptable and should be called out for what it is: thuggery of the worst type.</p><p>I join Senators Norris and Reilly in seeking clarity with regard to the publication of materials.  You are right, a Chathaoirligh, that it is not from the Civil Service, to be fair.  I believe it has to do with the issue around the McKenna judgment and what can and cannot be used by the Houses of the Oireachtas when it comes to the printing of material.  I do not believe we are precluded from communicating with our constituents but we are prohibited in electoral contests, whether for the D&aacute;il or the Seanad, or in a referendum from expressly asking for a "Yes" or "No" or a number one vote.  However, it raises a question that perhaps we could look at through the Committee on Procedure and Privileges or perhaps in a wider forum such as the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission.  The question relates to how we communicate with people and what we can and cannot do.</p><p>Senator Reilly raised the issue of his Autism Spectrum Disorder Bill.  Again, I am happy to have the Minister come to the House.  It is not that we are trying to preclude the Bill from coming back.  There are issues the Minister is keen to get right in the Bill, from what I am told.  Again, we will be happy to see that come back.  I commend Senator Reilly on his work.</p><p>Senator Murnane O'Connor raised the issue of Epilim medication.  I know that in 2014 and 2017 the European Medicines Agency strengthened and enhanced the advertising restrictions on its use.  I suppose it is fair to say that the majority of doctors, GPs and nurses do not communicate bad news over the telephone.  They do so in a certain way.  Communication over the telephone is not the practice but Senator Murnane O'Connor might be best advised to raise it as a Commencement matter.  She may get a more expeditious response in that way.</p><p>Senator Boyhan raised the issue of the Adoption (Information and Tracing) Bill and the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs, Deputy Zappone.  My information for the Senator is that the work around amendments to the Bill continues as we speak.  Several issues are outstanding, from what I am told.  I do not have the specific information the Senator is looking for.  Amendments were being worked on but I do not have any new information or an indicative timetable for the Member.  However, I would be happy to keep him involved when I get that information for him.  It is important legislation that we need to see coming back to the House.  I am happy to take Senator Warfield's amendment to the Order of Business, which I forgot to mention that.</p><p>Senator O'Sullivan referenced Facebook, and I have responded on that point.  Senator Richmond has an interesting proposal relating to an immigration day.  As he said, it is important to recognise that 80% of people have a positive viewpoint.  That is something I welcome.  I certainly concur with Senator Richmond that we cannot allow a situation where we adopt a far-right approach in our rhetoric, behaviour or attitudes.  One of the best things that happened was when Alan Shatter was Minister for Justice and Equality and he brought in the citizenship ceremonies.  We also have need for an ongoing integration policy that must live up to the highest standard.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I commend Senator Richmond on his proposal.  I thank Senator Coghlan for his remarks on Brexit.  I am happy to accept Senator Warfield's amendment to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X00200"><p>Senator Fintan Warfield has moved an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 20 be taken before No. 1."  The Leader has indicated that he is prepared to accept this amendment.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.71" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.72" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X00400">Broadcasting (Amendment) Bill 2018: First Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X00500"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That leave be granted to introduce a Bill entitled an Act to provide for a minimum percentage of Irish language works in radio music programming, and for that purpose to amend the Broadcasting Act 2009; and to provide for related matters.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X00600"><p>Is there a seconder?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X00700"><p>I second the proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.76" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X00900"><p>When is it proposed to take Second Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X01000"><p>Next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X01100"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.80" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Second Stage ordered for Tuesday, 15 May 2018.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.81" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X01200">Sitting Arrangements: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X01300"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That, notwithstanding anything in the Standing Orders relative to Public Business the Seanad shall meet at 2.30 pm on Wednesday, 9th May, 2018, and the Order of Business shall be proposed at 3.30 p.m.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.83" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.84" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X01500">Appointment of Member of Legal Services Regulatory Authority: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X01600"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann, noting that the Government agreed on 20th March, 2018, to propose, for the approval of Seanad &Eacute;ireann, Sara Moorhead SC to be a member of the Legal Services Regulatory Authority on the nomination of the Bar Council, and pursuant to section 9 of the Legal Services Regulation Act 2015, approves the appointment by the Government of Sara Moorhead SC to be a member of the Legal Services Regulatory Authority to fill a casual vacancy pursuant to section 10(9) of the said Act of 2015.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.86" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.87" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X01800">Health and Social Care Professionals Regulations 2018: Motions</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X01900"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(3)) (Variation of title: Dietician) Regulations 2018,copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 10th April, 2018.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.89" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#X02200"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the following Regulations in draft:Health and Social Care Professionals Act 2005 (Section 95(3)) (Variation of title: Speech Therapist) Regulations 2018,copies of which were laid in draft form before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 10th April, 2018.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.91" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.92" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.20 p.m. and resumed at 4.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.93" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#CC00100">Criminal Justice (Corruption Offences) Bill 2017: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.94" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018050800002#CC00300"><p>I am pleased to introduce the Criminal Justice (Corruption Offences) Bill 2017 to the House this afternoon.  I am also pleased to report that it received broad support on its recent passage through the Lower House.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The Bill is substantial and will completely overhaul Ireland's anti-corruption regime.  It consolidates seven anti-corruption Acts from as far back as 1889 up to 2010.  As well as repealing and replacing the previous legislation, the Bill before us introduces a raft of new offences.  Most important, it will provide for more severe penalties for those who engage in corrupt behaviour.</p><p>The Bill is a central piece of the Government's 2017 white collar crime package.  It is a priority piece of proposed legislation from the Government, aimed at combatting corruption at all levels of society.  This is extremely important as Ireland needs to protect its reputation on the world stage as being a safe place in which to do business.  The Bill is also a response to a number of international organisations which have a monitoring and evaluation role in regard to corruption.  Ireland is a party to a number of these international conventions.  We take these commitments very seriously.  The Bill reflects those international commitments.</p><p>The instruments include the Council of Europe Criminal Law Convention on Corruption, the EU anti-corruption convention, the UN Convention against Corruption and the OECD convention on bribery of foreign public officials.  Our membership of these key international anti-corruption groups affords us a further opportunity to review the various anti-corruption measures we have already in place and to improve our laws in light of our experience and participation in these important international fora.</p><p>This Bill addresses the public and private sector.  However, it has a particular focus on public officials acting in the course of their position and I believe this is only right, having regard to the high level of trust placed in them.  The penalties proposed are severe and fit with the seriousness of the crime involved.  The penalties for conviction on indictment for the main corruption offences are up to ten years imprisonment and-or an unlimited fine.  There are additional penalties a court can impose on certain public officials for a breach of the public's trust through corruption.  The courts have been given powers under the Bill to remove certain officials from office and to exclude them from holding office for up to ten years, subject to the safeguards as set out in the Bill.  This can be in addition to any other penalties under the Bill. </p><p>As regards suspected bribes, while they can already be seized and forfeited under existing legislation, the Bill strengthens these provisions by allowing the courts to order the forfeiture of assets equal to the value of any bribe received.  I am pleased to be providing for a number of recommendations from the Mahon tribunal.  For instance, the Bill provides for a new offences covering public officials who use confidential information obtained in the course of their duties to corruptly obtain an advantage.  There is another new provision which criminalises making payments knowingly or recklessly to a third party who intends, in turn, to use them as bribes.  </p><p>It is also intended to enhance the ability of the Director of Public Prosecutions, DPP, to bring prosecutions by providing for extended presumptions of corruption.  For instance, a presumption of corruption may arise where a person with an interest in the functions being discharged by a public official makes a payment to that official.  This could be, for example, where an applicant for planning permission makes a payment to a planning official.  This presumption will also now apply to payments made to persons connected to the official, such as family members and close business associates of that official.</p><p>Turning to the detail of the Bill, I wish to outline its key provisions.  Section 2 defines the key terms used in the Bill, such as "Irish official", "foreign official" and "Irish public body".  These categories need separate definition as some particular provisions apply specifically to those within the public sector, such as Part 4 of the Bill which contains the presumptions relating to corruption.  The term "corruptly" is defined addressing a recommendation from the OECD in an earlier evaluation in this regard and the text replicates the definition contained in the 2010 Prevention of Corruption (Amendment) Act.</p><p>Section 5 of the Bill defines the offences of active and passive corruption, meaning persons who corruptly offer an advantage which is active corruption and those who corruptly accept a bribe which is passive corruption.  These offences may be prosecuted under this section and no longer contain reference to corruption of or by an agent.  While this term was used in the description of the original offence under the Prevention of Corruption Act 1906, the modern definition of "agent" was expanded to cover a very broad spectrum of people so that the agency principle is no longer applicable.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=05&amp;amp;day=08"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> As was previously the case, the offences encompass corruption within both the public and private sectors and the reference to office employment position or business is intended to cover all public and private sector occupations, including voluntary bodies and sporting and charitable organisations.  Deleting the usage of the term "agent" was recommended by the OECD in the course of its evaluation of Ireland's implementation of the OECD anti-bribery convention.</p><p>Section 6 gives effect to a recommendation from the Council of Europe.  It provides for a discrete offence of trading in influence, which prohibits the promise of an undue advantage to someone who asserts they can exert an improper influence over a public official's decision-making capacity.  Like the corruption offence, this section covers both active and passive trading in influence.  Subsection (3) makes it clear that it is immaterial whether the alleged ability to exert improper influence existed or whether the supposed influence led to the intended result.  The provision in regard to trading in influence is also contained in the United Nations Convention Against Corruption.</p><p>Section 7 criminalises any act of an Irish official carried out in the course of their official position with the intent of corruptly obtaining an advantage for anybody.  It differs from the main corruption offence in that it is not required that another party is involved.  A new provision in subsection (2) makes it an offence to use confidential information obtained through their office for this very purpose.  This new provision reflects a recommendation of the Mahon tribunal.</p><p>Also giving effect to a recommendation from the Mahon tribunal, section 8 contains a new offence of giving a gift etc. to another person where the donor knows or ought to reasonably know that the payment might be used to facilitate the commission of an offence under the Act.</p><p>Section 9 extends the existing offence of knowingly using a false document, to include the creation of such a document with intent to induce another person to carry out an act relating to his or her office or business, and contains an updated modern definition of "document" at subsection (3) covering a broad range of electronic records.</p><p>Section 10 provides for a new offence of corruptly threatening harm to a person, intending to influence someone to carry out an act in regard to his or her office, employment or business.  I believe that this provision is a worthwhile innovation, reflecting the fact that a threat can be used in place of offering a bribe, when seeking to influence the actions of another in a corrupt manner.</p><p>Part 3 of the Bill contains provisions in regard to the jurisdiction of the State in circumstances where elements of the corruption offence take place outside the State or indeed only partly within the State.</p><p>Section 11 clarifies that a person may be tried in the State if any element of the offence occurs here, for instance, where an offer of a bribe Is made abroad but received in Ireland, reflecting a similar provision contained in the Prevention of Corruption (Amendment) Act 2001.</p><p>Section 12 provides for extensive extra-territorial jurisdiction in respect of corruption occurring outside the State, for instance, where the relevant act takes place aboard an Irish ship or aircraft, or where the person concerned is an Irish citizen or official, or an Irish registered company or body corporate as set out therein.  Subsections (3) to (5) of section 12 are additional provisions inserted to give full effect to Article 7 of the European Convention on fighting corruption, and to address certain jurisdictional requirements in this regard.</p><p>Section 13 simply states that where an offence was committed outside the State proceedings may be taken in any place within the State.</p><p>One of the key elements of this legislation lies In Part 4, which sets out the presumptions which are applicable where proceedings for corruption offences under the Act are under way.  They adjust the burden of proof by requiring an accused person to demonstrate that they did not act in a particular way or carry out a particular action as opposed to the usual requirements for the prosecution to prove that a particular act had been carried out.  Of course, these presumptions can be rebutted by evidence proving the contrary.  The standard of proof is the civil one, which is the balance of probabilities.  These provisions are to assist prosecutors in securing a conviction in white collar trials, which are often complex and difficult to prove beyond a reasonable doubt.</p><p>Section 14 contains a rebuttable presumption that where a payment or gift is made to an official or a connected person, and the giver has an interest in the way those functions are exercised, then the payment or gift is deemed to have been given corruptly as an inducement or reward for the person acting or refraining from acting in accordance with his or her duties, unless the contrary can be proved.  Subsection (3) lists the functions or decisions of officials which are applicable in this case, which include the acquisition or sale of property, award of tenders and contracts, licences and passports, as well as the exercise of judicial functions and the administration of justice.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-05-08a.98" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>