<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Leas-Chathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, he proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to set out the progress made to date on the roll-out of a new support payment for sheep farmers.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Michelle Mulherin of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to address the delay in the delivery of new rural groups water scheme to communities without a proper supply which have been in limbo since the abolition of the CL&Aacute;R programme in 2010 and to set out how capital for group water schemes will be funded going forward and how domicile consumers on group water schemes will be billed.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senators Marie-Louise O&rsquo;Donnell and Michael McDowell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to implement the as yet uncommenced sections of the Charities Act 2009 dealing with regulation and enforcement. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Denis Landy of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to state if he will provide an up-to-date report on the proposals to provide 21 step-down beds at Our Lady's Hospital, Cashel, as previously committed to in order to assist in reducing the overcrowding at South Tipperary General Hospital, Clonmel.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to seek a review by the European Commission of the tariff on fertiliser which is imported from outside the European Union.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Gerard Craughwell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to put in place measures that will not require farmers having to withdraw an animal for sale at a mart because one tag has been displaced from one of the animal's ears while in transit between the farm and the mart in view of the fact that the current procedure is costing farmers up to &euro;75 every time this is done.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Maura Hopkins of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to provide an update on the N5 Ballaghaderreen to Scramogue Road project, the estimated timeframe for delivery of this project and the interim measures required to address current identified road safety issues on the existing N5 route, particularly between Frenchpark and Tulsk.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Kieran O&rsquo;Donnell of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on plans for the provision of two new secondary schools at Castletroy and Mungret in Limerick. </blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Kevin Humphreys of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to inform the Seanad of the progress made in the delivery of 500 modular housing units to alleviate the housing crisis.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator M&aacute;ire Devine of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to respond to the grave concerns on the proposed 50% cut of night nursing staff at Cloverhill Remand Prison.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Paul Gavan of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to state if he approved the landing or transit through Irish airspace of certain US military aircraft and if so why, given that the presence of these aircraft, belonging to a belligerent state, in or over Irish territory is a clear breach of Ireland's international law obligations as a neutral state.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Leas-Chathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1881"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1881&amp;amp;pid=PaulCoghlan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Paddy Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Transport, Tourism and Sport to review the Government&rsquo;s policy on the Road Safety Authority's tender process for driving licences to allow post offices to act as agents in processing and co-ordinating applications. </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Aidan Davitt of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to give an update on plans to assist the 90 staff of Imperial Tobacco, Mullingar, with its pending closure and in sourcing new employment and to ensure IDA Ireland replaces these jobs in Mullingar.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Lynn Ruane of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister of State responsible for mental health and older people to indicate whether she is aware of concerns raised by the Mental Health Commission in its 2015 annual report that people with severe mental health difficulties are living in HSE-run 24-hour staffed community residences around the country that are too large, have poor physical infrastructure, lack individualised care plans and, in effect, do not qualify as community care facilities as they are institutional in nature; and to ask the Minister of State to advise how many of these residences exist; if she will extend the remit of the Mental Health Commission to empower it to regulate community-based services, as recommended in the review of the Mental Health Act 2001; and whether she will require the Office of the Inspector of Mental Health Services to conduct annual inspections of all 24-hour staffed community residences.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator P&aacute;draig Mac Lochlainn of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs and Trade to seek a presidential decree for the release of the young Irish citizen Ibrahim Halawa, imprisoned in Egyptian jails for the last three years, following the latest postponement of his trial until October.</blockquote><p>I regard the matters raised by Senators &Oacute; Domhnaill, Mulherin, Marie-Louise O&rsquo;Donnell, McDowell, Landy, Colm Burke, Craughwell, Hopkins, Kieran O&rsquo;Donnell, Humphreys, Devine, Gavan, Paddy Burke, Davitt and Ruane as suitable for discussion.  I have selected Senators &Oacute; Domhnaill, Mulherin, Landy, Marie-Louise O&rsquo;Donnell and McDowell and their matters will be taken now.  I suggest that Senators Marie-Louise O&rsquo;Donnell and McDowell share time as their matters are on the same topic.<br/><br/>Senators Colm Burke, Craughwell, Hopkins, Kieran O&rsquo;Donnell, Humphreys, Devine, Gavan, Paddy Burke, Davitt and Ruane may give notice on another day of the matters they wish to raise.  I regret I have had to rule out of order the matter raised by Senator Mac Lochlainn on the grounds that it involves a repeat of debate on statements on the Ibrahim Halawa case.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#B00200">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#B00300">Agriculture Scheme Administration</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#B00400"><p>I acknowledge the presence of the new Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Andrew Doyle, and congratulate him on his appointment.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2261"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2261&amp;amp;pid=BrianODomhnaill&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I had the honour of serving with him on the last Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, of which he was the Chairman during the last D&aacute;il and Seanad terms.  He did an excellent job and I have no doubt that bringing his knowledge and professionalism to his new role, he will perform excellently as Minister of State also.  I wish him well in Agriculture House with his colleagues and the new senior Minister there.</p><p>The issue I raise today relates to the sheep sector, with which the Minister of State will be very familiar coming from County Wicklow which has a large sheep population.  There is a large sheep population in the Republic and, in fact, there are more sheep than people living in it.  We are highly dependent on the sheep sector as part of the Food Wise 2025 strategy, agrifood exports and live exports.  It is an important part of the farm fabric, particularly in the west where the land is more marginal and sheep farmers struggle to make ends meet.  The margins in sheep farming tend to be low.  I was heartened by the commitment in the programme for Government of approximately &euro;25 million for a sheep premium scheme like the old headage scheme.  I welcome that.  The reason I table today's Commencement matter is to give the Minister of State an opportunity to outline what stage it is at.  Obviously, it will take a budgetary commitment in budget 2017, which will be later this year, to make provision for that.  How will the funding be ring-fenced?  Will it be a premium flat rate per ewe?  Without pre-empting any consultation, what is anticipated?</p><p>It is important to consult the sector.  While there the main farming organisations, there are also organisations which are newly established, such as the Irish Natura and Hill Farmers Association, which have made a number of specific recommendations around young farmers and the equalisation of payments.  Is it envisaged that there will be consultation with organisations like that?  There are the larger farm organisations, with which it is also important to consult.  I call on the Minister of State to ensure that if a payment is made available, it does not discriminate against or in favour of lowland or upland.  There should be some form of flat rate payment.  As there are additional constraints on farming on marginal and hill land, will anything be brought into consideration in regard to that?  Will there be anything for younger farmers to ensure they are not precluded from obtaining the payment for all of their flocks, given some restriction?  They are issues that will be delved into as the year goes on.  Nevertheless, I have tabled the matter at this early stage to provide the Minister with the opportunity to ensure that a wide-ranging consultation takes place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#C00200"><p>This is the first opportunity I have had to address the Upper House.  I am delighted to do so on a subject in which I have some interest, indeed a vested interest as a flock owner.  I am very pleased also that a former colleague on the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine has raised the matter.  On the committee, we proved beyond doubt that it is possible to work constructively across party and non-party lines for the betterment of the sector.  I will set out the official reply which gives the broad outline.  In the follow up contribution, I can discuss the flat rate and so on.</p> <p>The programme for Government commits to the provision of &euro;25 million for the support of the sheep sector in budget 2017.  This provision recognises the commitment of the Government to the development of the sheepmeat sector which is an important element of the national economy.  The sector generated an output value of &euro;320 million and exports in excess of &euro;230 million in 2015.  The sector also makes a vital contribution to the economy by supporting 34,000 farm families directly as well as by providing several thousand jobs indirectly in rural areas.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Andrew Doyle:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2170"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2170&amp;amp;pid=AndrewDoyle&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This commitment is also additional to the support provided through the green low-carbon agri-environment scheme, GLAS, through the areas of natural constraint scheme and through the targeted agricultural modernisation schemes, TAMS.  The inclusion of a TAMS measure to support sheep fencing was recently announced.  This approval, which followed lengthy discussions between the Department and the European Commission, will provide a significant boost to sheep farmers, especially young farmers who wish to commence sheep production by providing them the means to invest significantly in the necessary infrastructure for their holdings.</p><p>The supports provided through these measures are a recognition of the critical importance of the sheep sector, which makes a vital contribution to the economic viability rural areas through farming, processing and marketing as well as playing a central role in shaping the landscape, both in more intensive farming areas and in areas where more marginal land dominates.  This scheme has the potential to deliver targeted support to an important sector of agriculture.  It is my objective that the scheme delivers a long-term cumulative benefit to the sheep sector.</p><p>Support from the Department for the vital work of Teagasc and Sheep Ireland is critically important.  Developing new and more lucrative markets is also a key challenge.  In this regard, my Department works to develop market opportunities by opening new markets and supports the work of Bord Bia in the promotion of sheepmeat in domestic and EU markets.  My Department has been engaged in consultations with farm bodies to inform its work on the detail of the new sheep scheme.  I took note of the Senator&rsquo;s point about the smaller representative organisations which have been in contact.  Any such scheme will have to be approved by the European Commission under the rural development programme.  It must meet the exacting requirements of the rural development regulations in compensating farmers for any actions undertaken on the basis of costs incurred or income foregone.</p><p>Furthermore, in any rural development scheme, actions taken by farmers must go beyond the normal standards of husbandry practice before they can be considered as an eligible cost incurred by a farmer.  The challenge will be to develop a simple and practical scheme which makes a real contribution to the development of the sector, while meeting all of the EU requirements.  There is also an obligation on us to ensure any scheme that provides for support to sheep farmers is targeted at improving on-farm practices which will have lasting and cumulative benefits to sheep farmers and the national flock.</p><p>I am also aware of the need to ensure the scheme is made available to as many sheep farmers as possible.  In that context, it is important that the different systems of production of both lowland sheep farmers and hill sheep farmers are taken into account in any such scheme.</p><p>On the basis of the engagement with farm bodies to date, there is a reasonable degree of consensus that article 33 of the rural development regulation, which provides for support for animal welfare measures, is the most appropriate vehicle for supporting the sector in this instance.  I am particularly anxious to ensure the scheme includes measures suitable for the differing production systems in both hill and lowland flocks.</p><p>At this stage, the Department has had an initial meeting with the European Commission and is working through the detail of the proposed scheme.  The examination of the proposals by the Commission will be forensic, focusing on ensuring compliance with the relevant regulations, additionality and value for money.  As a result of these discussions, departmental officials are working intensively on ensuring any scheme meets the requirements of the Commission.  It is expected there will be further ongoing and detailed communication with the Commission on the scheme&rsquo;s details.</p><p>The scheme will also have to be presented to the monitoring committee of Ireland&rsquo;s rural development programme prior to final submission to the European Commission.  My focus is on delivering a scheme which can maximise the number of participants and deliver tangible benefits to the sheep sector in its impact as regards on-farm practices.  This scheme has the potential to deliver targeted support to an important sector of agriculture.  It is my objective to design and implement a scheme that delivers a long-term cumulative benefit to the sheep sector.  It is important the measures are tangible and give a real benefit while the scheme is kept simple as possible.  The &euro;25 million can cover a flat rate, if it is the preferred option, without having it either frontloaded or capped at &euro;200 or &euro;250 per head.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Andrew Doyle:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2170"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2170&amp;amp;pid=AndrewDoyle&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The budget allows for it to cover all breeding sheep in the system at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1382" speakername="Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#E00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive reply and I agree with everything he said.  Value for money should be to the fore.  When seeking  efficiencies under a scheme and making sure the available money reaches the recipient, flat-rate payments are probably the easiest to administer and, I presume, most farmers would avail of them and find them beneficial.  Using such payments would also reduce paperwork costs and the administrative burden for farmers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1356" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#E00300"><p>With regard to development markets, when Bord Bia or departmental officials participate on trade missions, they will identify traceability as a key issue, particularly for the US.  The dreaded tagging has not been discussed but it will be in the mix at some stage.  There have been submissions on it.  The focus currently is on animal welfare.  I know from experience that a lame animal does not put on flesh and, therefore, does not make a farmer money.  A simple measure can be taken to address that.  Fencing provides access to young farmers to the scheme because they may be starting out with an underdeveloped property or a green field site that was not used for sheep farming previously.  One can never have enough good fencing on a sheep farm.  It is the key to grass management and good neighbours.  Those issues need to be focused on to generate a tangible benefit.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.17" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#E00350">Water and Sewerage Schemes Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#E00400"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  It is with disbelief that I raise the issue of delay in delivery of new rural group water schemes.  Counties Mayo and Galway are particularly affected.  When I was a Member of the Lower House, I had cause to raise this issue on numerous occasions and I had hoped I was making progress as I went along.  Notwithstanding that, 235 houses in far flung areas such as Aghaloonteen, Massbrook, Tonacrick, Kilmurry, Downpatrick, Fermoyle and Carracastle have a water supply that is not fit for human consumption or any other use.  These householders are crying out for assistance from the State.  They live in disadvantaged rural areas, which previously came under the CL&Aacute;R scheme that was abolished in 2010.  They had hoped to receive financial assistance under the scheme to help them with the construction of new group water schemes.  To date, unfortunately, nothing has happened.</p> <p>A commitment was given by the previous Government.  For several years, Mayo County Council received &euro;200,000 annually to progress some of the schemes.  The major problem is it costs a great deal per household to deliver a scheme because of the topography and ground conditions compared to an area where ground conditions are more friendly.  Last year, new rules were devised following much deliberation by the national rural group water committee and &euro;400,000 was allocated to Mayo County Council.  Not one red cent of the annual allocations has been spent.  Last year, the issue was supposed to have been resolved through a new process - the rural water multi-annual programme.  However, I recently learned that this issue, which comes under measure 3 of the rural water multi-annual programme, is before an expert panel again.  I also understand from the local authority that whereas in previous years it would have received funding by now under the rural water programme, it has only received a small portion this year, which is funding private companies on contracts to design, build and operate schemes.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They have not received all the other funding to help group water schemes cleanse water to ensure it is up to date - that is aside from new group water schemes, the category I am particularly concerned about.  The local authority needs to spend from an overdraft and does not have the funding.</p><p>The people have been let down.  Hard working committees in disadvantaged areas have gone out and collected money, not to pay for the water but to pay for the provision of pipe work and to retain consultants.  Those involved in these schemes have spent hundreds of thousands of euro and have not been reimbursed.</p><p>With domestic households on group water schemes paying directly to Mayo County Council, the problem now arises that other people are not paying for their water.  They are looking at what is happening nationally and the lack of delivery on the ground to households that are very willing to pay for their water.  They understand that pipes do not just appear in the ground and that getting quality water is not just a case of putting out a bucket and getting water from the sky.  These are practical people and have been greatly let down.  As somebody who has represented them, I feel very let down with the lack of action.</p><p>What is to happen now?  People are demoralised.  The water quality is very bad.  I am not talking about cryptosporidium or anything like that but about iron oxides through the water.  When the tap is turned on, what comes out is red; it is not possible to wash clothes in it.  Elderly people, people who are sick and people with children are affected by this.  With all the controversy over the chairman designate, Mr. Joe O'Toole, I wonder if anybody is thinking about these people.  Why is nobody marching on the streets for them?  This has been going on for years.</p><p>I understand we came through difficult economic times, but people were led to believe that something was being progressed and yet last year the water services section of Mayo County Council went through the motions - the council did not think it was going through the motions - with two schemes, Aghaloonteen and Massbrook, thinking they would be top of the list and that each year we would see progress.  However, nothing has happened.  All that work that was done last year has gone by the wayside.  I hope the Minister of State can give me some good news today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#F00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising the issue.  It is clear that excellent work is done by group water schemes.  There has been pent-up demand for some years due to the lack of investment owing to economic circumstances.  Hopefully, we are in a better place now to try to tackle that and we hope to get that money out to them to be spent more quickly.</p> <p>I am speaking on behalf of the Minister, Deputy Coveney.  I am well aware of the excellent work done by the group water scheme and the enormous commitment of local communities in setting up group water schemes.  There is a pent-up demand that needs to be addressed and we need to find ways to channel the money to them.</p> <p>Since 2000, my Department has, under its rural water programme, provided over &euro;810 million towards the capital costs of providing and improving group water schemes.  Financial assistance, in the form of subsidies, has also been provided towards the subsequent running and operational costs of these schemes in providing water for domestic use.  Nevertheless, further work is required and there is a need for continuing investment in the group water scheme sector so as to ensure that the drinking water provided complies with the standards set at both EU and national level.</p> <p>I appreciate that there are particular difficulties in setting up some new group water schemes where the financial viability of the scheme is questionable with schemes in the previous CL&Aacute;R-funded areas being a case in point.  Earlier this year, a new multiannual approach to the funding of group water schemes for 2016 and beyond under the rural water programme was introduced.  This will lead to the development of appropriate prioritised lists of schemes for funding both in 2016 and in future years.  One of the measures in this programme will support social and economic development, and living standards in towns and villages and their hinterlands by providing new group water schemes in areas where a public scheme and private wells are not a viable option.  This measure is aimed at providing assistance towards some of those schemes which Senator Mulherin mentioned.  The Minister, Deputy Coveney, intends to make a decision on the future funding of these and other schemes shortly.</p> <p>Arising from the Government&rsquo;s commitment to suspend domestic water charges for a period of nine months, and to restore group water scheme subsidy levels to those that pertained prior to the introduction of charges so as to ensure equity of treatment with households on public water supplies, the subsidies for those on group water schemes will be restored to their pre-2015 levels.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Damien English:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1781"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1781&amp;amp;pid=DamienEnglishFG&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is being implemented from 1 July 2016 and it will be for the period from then until 31 March 2017 so as to coincide with the suspension of water charges.  These subsidies benefit those domestic consumers on group water schemes with financial assistance towards their running costs.</p><p>While this may not be the answer the Senator wants, I believe there will be a decision quite soon.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#G00200"><p>I appreciate the Minister of State's reply but, in fairness, this was to have been resolved last year.  It is evident there is a problem when &euro;400,000 was allocated last year and &euro;200,000 in previous years, but not a cent of it was spent on these new rural group water schemes.  A lot of work was done to bring into being the two schemes I mentioned but it has all fallen by the wayside and another panel has now been put in place.  I do not know how to explain it.  I know the Department deals with a spectrum of types of group water scheme and that different measures are being delivered under the rural water programme.  However, these new group water schemes have not been looked after and another expert panel is now looking into the matter.</p> <p>The Minister of State said the Minister intends to make a decision but, at the moment, it does not seem that much is happening.  I also question why the local authorities have not received their funding and why they are on overdrafts, trying to provide basic supports and services to these new rural group water schemes.</p> <p>On another point, how will capital projects be funded for rural group water schemes?  Will that continue to be State-funded or it is envisaged Irish Water will get involved at some stage?  With regard to domestic water charges in these areas, will Irish Water or the county council collect the charges?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1264" speakername="Damien English" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#G00300"><p>Water supply and water quality are issues that are dear to the heart of the Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney, and ones on which he will take action.  As the Senator knows, he is not a Minister who sits around waiting for decisions.  He is only in the job less than two months and he has made it very clear that he will make announcements in the very near future in regard to these schemes, and that this will be dealt with.  These schemes will not be left waiting and it will be clear exactly what will happen.</p> <p>With regard to the future of group water schemes, the Senator will have seen that the expert commission on water services includes an expert on group water schemes who has done great work in this area for a long number of years.  I am pleased to say the advice of the people involved in this area will be very clearly heard.  Again, it was at the Minister's request that this person was on the commission.  Hopefully, many of the Senator's concerns will be dealt with in the future and the particular schemes she has mentioned will be addressed shortly in the announcements from the Minister.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.24" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#G00350">Charities Regulation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#G00400"><p>It is good to see the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Frances Fitzgerald, in the House.  The charities legislation has had an outrageous historical journey and this has been going on since the mid-1990s.  The Department of Justice and Equality sat on it for years, it next arrived at other Departments and it then came back to the Department of Justice and Equality.  The Bill has been around since the 2000s and has been a very long time in gestation.  It was passed nearly ten years ago but was not implemented.  I have always felt, certainly in the last five years when I was here in the Seanad, that when we enact legislation there is a presumption that once it appears on the Statute Book, it will at least become effective.  In this case, large and vital sections of the Bill remain inactive and important powers are denied.</p> <p>I do not want to go into the background of Console.  It is possibly the worst of all scandals because an organisation like Console murders hope in the people who placed such hope in this organisation.  Of course, it is the people at the head of it, not those who work in it, who murder that hope and abandon the sense of the humane in themselves.</p> <p>Recent scandals in the charity sector have been allowed to snowball because the essential legislative sections have been left uncommenced and under-resourced.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2390"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2390&amp;amp;pid=MarieLouiseODonnell&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Part 4 is the most important one.  Was it about resources?  The official explanation was that insufficient resources were given to the regulator.  He was understaffed and, therefore, without power.  If that is the case, maybe we could allow charities to pay a very small levy to fund the regulatory activity?  If one transfers, as we did, all the functions of the Attorney General to the Charities Regulatory Authority, one must also transfer all the machinery and powers.</p><p>The Minister intends to commence Part 4 in September, namely, the regulator's investigative powers to seize documents, enter premises, to suspend trustees and to have what we would call a full set of teeth when needed, so that reputational damage, like what happened with Console, will not occur again.  Will the Minister outline what additional resources she intends to put in place so that the regulator has all he needs?  Will the Minister indicate why Part 4 cannot be commenced before the recess?  Why must we wait until September since it is already there?  Why must we always wait for a massive problem to arise before we do something about it?  In more instances than one, it is too late.  It is too late for the greed of some, which we have witnessed, and for the fractured fragility of the victims.  Will the Minister please answer those questions?  The regulator needs the powers now as well as the additional resources.  What are those additional resources?  I want to have confidence in respect of the additional resources but I also want to have confidence in the explanation as to why Part 4 cannot be commenced now rather than in September.  I thank the Minister very much for taking the time to be here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#H00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  Needless to say I am deeply concerned by the recent revelations about Console.  I know that people rely heavily on its services and I am pleased that the HSE is ensuring a continuity of its services in the first instance.  It is essential, as the Senator said, that all organisations funded by the State are regulated and managed in an appropriate manner.  Likewise, all moneys donated by the public must be managed appropriately and in line with good corporate governance.  Anything less is a betrayal of the goodwill of thousands of people around the country and, indeed, of the taxpayer.</p> <p>I say betrayal because people's trust has been betrayed.  The unwritten agreement between the charity and the people that the people's money will be efficiently and appropriately used has been broken.  The betrayal also reaches to the collective trust charities place in one another to uphold good governance, standards and public confidence in the sector.  The details the Senator has outlined are particularly disturbing.</p> <p>For the Government's part, it is essential that we progress the regulatory reforms we proposed in recent years.  As Senators are aware, Part 4 of Charities Act 2009 deals specifically with the charity regulator's investigatory and enforcement functions.  Pending the commencement of Part 4, the regulator has put in place - I worked with him last year on this - an interim process for the handling of concerns received about suspected abuse of charitable status or fraud in charities.  However, having had discussions with the regulator and with my officials, I can confirm to the Senator that today I am signing the necessary statutory instrument to commence Part 4 to take effect from 5 September 2016.</p> <p>The Senator asked about the delay.  This commencement date is to allow for the recruitment over the coming weeks of the necessary staffing resources to support these important functions.  I am also examining the legislation to see if there is any other provision.  I think the Senator mentioned section 17.  I am examining that to see if it can be brought in quickly as well.</p> <p>The establishment of the Charities Regulatory Authority was one of my priorities when I first became Minister for Justice and Equality.  Shortly after becoming Minister, it was established as an independent agency on 16 October 2014 under the provisions of the Charities Act.</p> <p>To go back on the history, the Senator is right that the Act was introduced by the Fianna F&aacute;il-Green Party Government.  It provided for the regulator.  Its establishment was delayed because of the economic situation for quite a number of years.  However, the previous Government and I, as Minister, were determined to establish the regulator to restore confidence in the charity sector after a number of other controversies.  I wish to make the following point as it is very important we all appreciate this, as I am sure Senators do, but regulating a large, previously unregulated sector is a challenge.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frances Fitzgerald:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=401"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=401&amp;amp;pid=FrancesFitzgerald&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The scale of the job, about which I will provide some facts, is not to be underestimated.  However, there has been significant progress.  As the Senator will be aware, the aim of the Charities Regulator is to provide for better regulation of charitable organisations through a framework of registration, regulation and support.  This is intended to enhance public confidence in the vast majority of charities that do immense and essential work.  The regulator has a wide range of functions which we could not introduce all at the same time.  It had to be done on a phased basis, beginning with the compilation of the new statutory register of charities.  That was a development of the regulator.  Some 8,000 charities were registered with the Revenue Commissioners and they were transferred to the Charities Regulator immediately once it started registering the authority.  In addition, any of the charities that had not registered with the Revenue Commissioners had to apply directly to the regulator.  Much time was spent last year encouraging charities to register and making sure that they did so.  The take-up was very slow at the beginning but another 1,500 applications came in following the work done by the regulator to make sure that charities registered.  It was necessary to register 3,600 schools that are also registered for charitable status.  A huge amount of work has, therefore, been done already.  Investigations cannot begin until registration is in place and until the charities around the country are known.  The regulator has developed an online system for organisations to apply for inclusion on the register of charities and for information to go out to the charity sector on its obligations and duties under the new regime.<br/><br/>The Senator will, therefore, recognise there is quite a bit of work to be done, given the number of charities in this country.  There are more than 12,500 charitable organisations.  The regulator has received approximately 300 concerns over 132 different entities, the majority of which are charities.  These concerns cover the entire scale, from issues to do with an organisation's purpose to the quality of service provided to a passing comment about somebody not agreeing with the goal of the charity.  Often, therefore, concerns raised with the Charities Regulator are matters to be pursued by other bodies as well.  These concerns relate to about 1% of the total number of charities in the country.<br/><br/>Many charities are companies limited by guarantee.  These are subject to the provisions of company law and are generally required under the Companies Acts to provide certain information to the Companies Registration Office.  There are, therefore, quite a number of bodies that have responsibility for charities and how they are run.  In addition, for example, if there is criminal activity, such as fraud, that is a breach of the criminal law and could and would potentially be investigated by An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  Where there is a fraudulent situation, there is clearly a role for An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na.  We have, therefore, seen a lot of co-operation between the necessary bodies in recent times.<br/><br/>The Senator asked about resources.  Significant additional resources - a budget allocation of &euro;2.665 million, representing an 88% increase over 2015 - was given by my Department for 2016.  That includes additional funding of &euro;1.25 million, which is supporting expansion in the level of staffing and other resources and these are all the building blocks we need to have in place to ensure compliance.  I want to reassure the House that I recognise the urgency of making sure that the Charities Regulatory Authority is up and running with all its functions and with the resources it needs.<br/><br/>I want to draw the attention of Senators to a quotation from Se&aacute;n Moynihan of Alone:</p><blockquote>When people choose to support a charity they do so because they are inspired by the work it does.  People are moved by stories that reach into their hearts and connect with them emotionally ...  However, we also know that we need to link these stories to comprehensive information about where your money goes, the number of people we support and the manner in which we support them.  All charities should be judged on their impact and effectiveness, not just on an emotive story; we must value those that have quality standards, are accountable and transparent.</blockquote><p>Recent controversies give real pause for thought about the current charity landscape in Ireland.  For example, are clients best served by having large numbers of charities to choose from, each providing similar services and each expected to operate on the basis, obviously, of proper corporate governance structures?<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Frances Fitzgerald:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=401"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=401&amp;amp;pid=FrancesFitzgerald&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For example, are clients best served by having a large number of charities, each providing similar services and expected to operate on the basis of proper corporate governance structures, from which to choose?  This country needs a conversation on these issues and how we can best support the ongoing development and regulation of the charity sector.  We want to tap into the vast resources and expertise that are available as well as people's willingness to volunteer, but that needs to be managed.  When it is not managed properly, major issues arise with trust in the sector.</p><p>Charities receive significant State funding, and it is upsetting that people, including the thousands of good people who work in and contribute to the vital services provided by the charity sector, are being let down by poor governance standards in parts of it.  This undermines confidence in a sector that relies on good will.</p><p>I assure the House that I will prioritise the role of the charities regulator and ensure that it has adequate powers and resources to sustain and promote the thousands of charities around the country.  With the announcement of Part 4 commencing in September, today marks another step forward in the better governance of the sector, but I emphasise the scale of the challenge facing the regulator, given the number of charities and the fact that they have not previously been regulated to any degree.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#K00200"><p>I thank the T&aacute;naiste for attending and assuring me that Part 4 will be commenced on 5 September.  The challenge is significant, but there is also a challenge to the Government not to delay or shelve.  The 8,000 charities and 12,500 organisations are performing a public service and the Government rightly backs them, so it is up to it to protect the money that it and the ordinary person on the street give them.  Any undermining of charities should be regulated against.</p> <p>The regulator should not have to beg for regulation or resources; they should be available.  The T&aacute;naiste might address my point, one that may be creative, to the effect that all charities should pay a small levy to go towards an office that the T&aacute;naiste rightly stated would be large, as is the case in many sectors.  This has grown into a large sector.</p> <p>I accept the T&aacute;naiste's response.  I would have liked these measures earlier, but I understand that would not have been as easy.  This may be a lesson that leaving regulations on shelves for too long can have terrible ramifications for the ordinary person on the street.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#K00300"><p>The approach of the Charities Regulatory Authority, CRA, in the first instance was to encourage charities to register, not to erect barriers such as costs.  There is a role for the Government to play, but the charity sector has an important role and, indeed, obligation to promote and operate to the highest ethical and governance standards.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.32" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#K00450">Hospital Accommodation Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#K00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State to the House and thank him for taking this debate on Our Lady's Hospital, Cashel.  In 1996, an agreement was signed with the South Eastern Health Board by those concerned at the hospitals in Cashel and Clonmel to move services from the former to the latter.  In return, the three-storey Cashel hospital would be upgraded through the provision of 25 specialist and geriatric beds, 15 nursing home and convalescent beds, 20 beds for general practitioner, GP, assessment and rehabilitation and five palliative care beds, a total of 65.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Denis Landy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2349"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2349&amp;amp;pid=DenisLandy&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This was in 1996.  One of the people involved at the time, Councillor Tom Wood, from Cashel, is still trying to get beds into the hospital in Cashel.  We will roll the clock forward to the last Government's term of office.  Two phases of refurbishment of the building of Our Lady's Hospital were undertaken.  One was a new reconstruction at a total cost of &euro;10.15 million and the second phase was the main building, which I am discussing now, on which &euro;12.6 million was spent.  The final services were transferred to Clonmel in 2007.  These were the acute services and at that time the commitments were reinforced again.  However, in January 2015 there were still no step-down beds opened in Cashel by the HSE.</p><p>This issue has been raised regularly.  In 2015, the then Minister of State at the Department of Agriculture, Food and the Marine, former Deputy Tom Hayes, announced 21 step-down beds to relieve the chronic overcrowding in Clonmel, which has been ongoing for the last number of years.  It is now 5 July 2016 and there are still no step-down beds in Cashel, after a total of almost &euro;23 million of taxpayers' money being spent on Cashel hospital for what is operating there and on the main building.  There is no return by way of beds for the public and those who are distressed by overcrowding and family situations in Clonmel.  It is time to raise this question again and seek a response from the Minister which, I hope, will stand.</p><p>This matter was brought to the attention of the new Minister for Health by Tipperary County Council in the months since his appointment to office.  The Minister was invited to attend the hospital but the reply the council received, on 20 June 2016, was that the Minister was currently too busy to visit the hospital.  However, he has been visiting other hospitals across the country so I cannot understand why some representative at ministerial level would not visit the hospital to see the great job that was done for the amount of money spent, yet the hospital remaining without the beds despite the chronic situation continuing in Clonmel.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#L00200"><p>I thank Senator Landy for raising this matter.  I also congratulate him on his election to the Seanad.  I am aware of his background of dealing with major concerns over the last number of years, particularly with regard to health and disability issues.</p> <p>With regard to South Tipperary General Hospital, Clonmel, I understand that the increasing demand on the emergency department and the increasing numbers of patients requiring admission have resulted in delays for patients accessing inpatient beds within the current available capacity.  There have been persistent monthly increases in emergency department attendances at the hospital this year compared to the same period in 2015.  Such increases are broadly in line with the national experience.  The Department of Health has been assured, however, that, with a view to improving the current situation, the south-south west hospital group and South Tipperary General Hospital are strengthening the management structures in the hospital, expanding capacity, improving infrastructure, reviewing processes and intensifying relationships with their community and primary care colleagues.  We must focus on these issues for a start.  Management at the general hospital has advised that it does not require transitional care beds at Our Lady's Hospital, Cashel.</p> <p>As the Senator is aware, a wide range of HSE services is currently provided across the campus at Our Lady's Hospital.  These include the minor injury unit, primary care services, leg ulcer wound clinic, radiology and ultrasound.  Additional services provided on the hospital campus are services for older people, disability and intellectual disability services and mental health services.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Finian McGrath:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=1822"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1822&amp;amp;pid=FinianMcGrath&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->A proposal to reorganise the provision of services from St. Patrick's Hospital, also in Cashel, to Our Lady's Hospital was included in the HSE 2013 service plan in order to address the environmental and infrastructural issues at St. Patrick's Hospital.  A unit on the Our Lady's Hospital campus has been upgraded to meet national standards and it is the HSE's intention to transfer residents from St. Patrick's Hospital to the new St. Clare's ward.  This will accommodate 11 elderly mentally infirm residents.  </p><p>The HSE's six-year capital plan for the period 2016 to 2021 includes plans to replace the current St. Patrick's Hospital with a new 100-bed community nursing unit.  It is envisaged at this time that Our Lady's Hospital will be utilised to provide interim accommodation pending the construction of the replacement for St. Patrick's Hospital.  It is important that we recognise that overcrowding is not just a problem for emergency departments alone to solve.  The response has to be multifaceted and health system-wide.  For that reason, A Programme for a Partnership Government has prioritised a number of initiatives which will reduce the numbers of patient attendances at emergency departments by developing alternative services, including primary care; increasing hospital capacity; supporting timely patient discharge from hospital; and improving the ability of the health system to respond to surges in demand for emergency care.   </p><p>The Minister, Deputy Simon Harris, recently announced funding of &euro;40 million for a new winter initiative, to plan for the next two winters.  This is a key provision in any health strategy.  The initiative will seek to support actions to improve patient flow through hospitals and optimum discharge planning.  South Tipperary General Hospital will be considered in the context of the winter initiative.  It will also be included in the national bed capacity review which was committed to in A Programme for a Partnership Government.</p><p>With respect to the Senator's frustration at the fact that the provision of 65 beds was mentioned in 1996, I will raise that matter also with the senior Minister.  The current position is unacceptable.  The Senator said the matter had been mentioned again in January 2015.  He also highlighted the fact that &euro;23 million had already been spent.  I will convey his strong message on the issues raised to the Minister.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#M00200"><p>The Minister of State's response was very well crafted by whoever wrote it.  I compliment the person concerned, but most of the response dealt with St. Patrick's Hospital in Cashel.  I visited that hospital every Sunday for a long time when my grandfather was in it and during that time it was known as the Old County Home.  However, it is Our Lady's Hospital, not St. Patrick's Hospital, that we discussing.  I cannot understand how &euro;23 million was spent at Our Lady's Hospital, &euro;12 million of it on a new main building, and how it was then left standing idle.  South Tipperary General Hospital in Clonmel is not and has not been able to cope.  On checking the Official Report I found part of this structured response to parliamentary questions tabled on this issue in recent years.  There is not enough capacity in South Tipperary General Hospital.  Another hospital is waiting to be filled.  Somebody needs to get the finger out and put patients into it, given that there is overcrowding in Clonmel.  I thank the Minister of State for coming into the House to take this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#M00300"><p>I accept the Senator point and agree with him that the real issue does not concern St. Patrick's Hospital but Our Lady's Hospital.  It is a key priority for me.  I also accept the Senator's point that there is not enough capacity in the hospital in Clonmel.  We have to deal with that issue.  During the talks that took place in agreeing to A Programme for a Partnership government we constantly discussed the urgent need to provide more beds in the health system.  The Senator will have noted that an extra &euro;500 million will be provided for health services this year, but we need to deliver services to local communities in local hospitals such as Our Lady's.  I will convey all of the Senator's concerns and views to the Minister, Deputy Simon Harris, and give a commitment to push these matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.39" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.30 p.m. and resumed at 3.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.40" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#N00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, Proceeds of Crime (Amendment) Bill 2016 - Order for Second Stage and Second Stage, to be taken at 4.45 p.m., with the contributions of group spokespersons not to exceed eight minutes and all other Senators not to exceed five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#N00300"><p>I extend my deepest sympathy and that of the Fianna F&aacute;il group to the people of Iraq, whom I understand are holding three days of mourning for the 215 people tragically killed and the hundreds injured in the latest spate of suicide bombings during the holy month of Ramadan in the name of Islamic State.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is difficult to imagine the grief and the fear these families and communities are going through due to these cowardly and hateful acts.<br/><br/>Two weeks ago to the day, I raised in the House the shooting of a man on Monasterboice Road, Crumlin, which is in the very heart of my constituency.  Today, I rise to my feet again with a sickening sense of <i>d&eacute;j&agrave;</i><i>vu</i>.  Last Friday, David Douglas was shot on Bridgefoot Street in the south inner city.  It is incredible to have three shootings a couple of weeks apart, two of them in my constituency of Dublin South Central, together with the tragic news that a man was critically injured this morning in Lusk.  I cannot help but feel that if these shootings happened in the Taoiseach's or the T&aacute;naiste's constituencies, there would be a much more robust reaction on the part of the Government to deal with these thugs who believe the only way to solve disputes is through the barrel of a gun.  I extend my sympathies to the latest victims' families and the communities in which these shootings occurred.<br/><br/>The Government's performance on law and order is a matter of great concern to me.  The T&aacute;naiste recently allocated additional resources to help garda&iacute; to tackle gangland activities and those resources were to go to a special armed response unit equipped to do so.  The fact that more shootings and murders have taken place since the T&aacute;naiste announced the resourcing is an indictment of her and her Department.  How many more people need to die before the Government wakes up and realises that it is quickly loosing any semblance of being in control?  How many murders must take place in the same blatant fashion as that which occurred last Friday and today's shooting - both in broad daylight - before serious questions are posed as to the T&aacute;naiste's credibility in dealing with murderous gangs?  Another deeply worrying twist in this worsening crisis was highlighted in newspaper reports yesterday to the effect that potential witnesses are being threatened in south inner city pubs and informed that they will get a bullet in the head if they testify in upcoming cases.  This most recent development further highlights the challenges garda&iacute; face in dealing with the criminals behind these threats.  The T&aacute;naiste must wake up and realise that action and resources are required as a matter of urgency.  Failure to provide these will result in many more deaths.  If the Government does not tackle the gangs head-on, it will only be a matter of time before - as happened in Limerick - innocent people who have no connection with the warring families or criminality will be caught in the crossfire.<br/><br/>Further issues which buttress the argument to preserve the Special Criminal Court include the difficulty the State has in getting people to serve as jurors where gun crimes of this nature come to trial.  In 2003, it was not possible to find 12 people in Limerick to act as jurors in the trial of six people who were charged with the murder of gangland figure, Kieran Keane.  Where 729 were called to jury duty, 12 could not be found.  The T&aacute;naiste must outline publicly how she will tackle these criminals.  No further delays in the establishment of the armed response unit can be tolerated.  The T&aacute;naiste must also set out how she will protect witnesses from criminals if they are to testify.  Finally, she must introduce minimum mandatory sentencing for anyone caught in possession of an illegal firearm.  Any person caught with such a firearm should know that he or she will serve a minimum of ten years behind bars.  A sentence of that length is entirely proportionate given the worsening crisis.  We must demonstrate that we are willing to take a very hard stance on serious crimes of this nature.  I propose that the Order of Business be amended and that the T&aacute;naiste be called on to address the Seanad in order that she might outline the measures she is taking to stem the escalation in gun crime and cold-blooded murder in our cities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#O00200"><p>In the context of the conference held by the Association of Irish Local Government last week, I wish to point out that more than 42 new Senators have been elected to the House and that many of us were elected by local authority members.  The Association of Irish Local Government and the Local Authority Members Association have raised numerous concerns with each of us.  I took the trouble last week to take out the literature that was circulated during the Seanad election campaign.  Without exception, everyone elected here from that group gave commitments to highlight issues in relation to PRSI, allowances for councillors and their representational payments.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is an expectation that there would be some debate on this issue in the Seanad before the recess.  I fully understand and empathise with their concerns, frustration and disappointment and, now sadly, their anger.  The challenge is what we will do on a cross-party basis.  I do not want to do a solo run on this - I have left it for the past two weeks - but we need a cross-party commitment.  It is not good enough to be told the leader of Fianna F&aacute;il says something, the leader of Fine Gael says something else or the leader of the Labour Party says another thing.  We need to do something.  We need to use the craft of politics on the floor of this House.  This is how politics is conducted.  Will the Leader agree to have the Minister in the House for statements, discussion and debate in support of our colleagues who do an exceptional job, seven days a week in local government?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#P00200"><p>The Senator has made his point and his time is up.  I call Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#P00300"><p>I want to raise the issue of the recent comments by the chairman of the commission set up to review the charging for domestic water use.  I, like many others, was shocked to hear the chairman express opinions, not only in favour of charging for domestic water but vilifying those who opposed charges.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#P00400"><p>I was shocked.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#P00500"><p>I was actually shocked because I had never before seen a chairperson-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#P00600"><p>I hope the Senator is not going to name anyone who is not here to defend themselves.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#P00700"><p>I was shocked because it undermines the whole credibility of this commission.  It is like the referee setting out the result of a football match before it starts.  It should not be forgotten that this commission is in place during this hiatus and is meant to be independent, so as to assure the public that whatever solution is eventually reached, it is impartial and independent.  Impartiality and independence are what people need in dealing with this serious matter.  There is no point in having this expert commission if its chairman has already made up his mind on the issue and seems to have no respect for those who have an alternative opinion.</p><p>If these remarks are not withdrawn, we will be asking the Minister, Deputy Coveney, to come to the Seanad to explain how the commission can carry out its work appropriately under the circumstances.  It is a serious issue which affects thousands of families across the country.  So as not to undermine the credibility of the commission, the Seanad has a responsibility to address this.  It cannot be ignored.</p><p>Up to 187,112 family carers provide 6.2 million hours of care each week.  This morning I attended an excellent briefing by Family Carers Ireland.  The issue of carers has been discussed in the Seanad before but several matters have come to a head recently.  I know carers in my constituency who are mentally, physically and financially exhausted because of the care they are providing.  It comes as no surprise that carers are a net contributor to the economy and, indeed, to the Health Service Executive budget.  However, the figures of &euro;4 billion to the economy and a third of the HSE budget are staggering, particularly given the difficulties they continue to face in providing such a vital service.  With several months having passed since the programme for Government was published, will the Leader ascertain when phase 2 of the national carers&rsquo; strategy will be published with the associated ring-fenced funding?  This is vitally important because there is no point in having the strategy unless the moneys are ring-fenced to resource it.  It was said in 2012 that phase 2 would be revisited once the economy had recovered.  We were told <i>ad nauseam</i>during the election campaign that the recovery was well under way.  It is now time to set a date for the strategy&rsquo;s publication.  I support the call by Family Carers Ireland for its funding to be increased to meet the 25% increase in the population over 65.  As legislators, we can arrange for a statutory entitlement to home care services as exist for residential care.  That is vitally important.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Rose Conway-Walsh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2462"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2462&amp;amp;pid=RoseConwayWalsh&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Until it is put on a statutory footing, we will not treat carers in the way they deserve to be treated.  Nobody should be impacted on financially in choosing to care for a loved one at home, saving the State money in the long term.  This is a serious issue on which I ask for support across the House.  We have to put carers front and centre in this Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1430" speakername="Colette Kelleher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Q00200"><p>I join Senator Catherine Ardagh in extending condolences to the families and loved ones of those killed so tragically in Iraq.</p><p>I concur with Senator Rose Conway-Walsh in support of the Civil Engagement group for the proposals set out by Family Carers Ireland this morning in its pre-budget submission, in which they seek to achieve fairness for family carers.  It is undoubtedly the case that they are carrying the can for society.  It is overdue that, as a state and a society, we weighed in with them.  The need to put access to home care on a legislative footing was highlighted last week by the Alzheimer Society of Ireland and Family Carers Ireland has also called for this to happen, which we support.</p><p>I refer to the plight of people who are homeless.  I worked for Cork Simon Community for eight years and it is a cause about which I care deeply.  Since yesterday morning, a group of homeless persons have been occupying John's Lane West Hostel off Thomas Street, which is due to close this week.  The group is protesting about the lack of replacement emergency beds.  The hostel is closing because it is to be converted into apartments.  However, the 42 residents of the hostel claim that no alternative accommodation has been provided for them and they are worried about their future.  They have little and that little is disappearing.  One of the residents is a woman by the name of Rosemary Hughes.  She is visually impaired and has a guide dog.  She has lived in the hostel for the past three months.  Yesterday, she said:</p><blockquote>I'm not going anywhere until this is sorted ... we want suitable accommodation; we want respect and we want to be treated like human beings ... people are really worried asthey don't have a bed for tomorrow night.</blockquote> <p>Rosemary who said she had &quot;slept in almost doorway in Grafton Street&quot; was placed in the hostel after being attacked on the streets.  In John's Lane she said: &quot;It's the first time I've had my own room and it feels like forever.&quot;  Asked what she would do if she lost her bed, she said she would have to &quot;go back to sleeping in the doorway of BT2 with Quilla,&quot; her dog.</p><p>The hostel is owned by Focus Ireland and operated by the Peter McVerry Trust.  It first opened in the winter of 2014 as part of the emergency response to the death of Mr. Jonathan Corrie who died on the streets outside Leinster House.  The Government must do everything it can to provide suitable long-term housing for homeless persons like Rosemary.  In the short term, with others, she must be provided with an alternative emergency bed this week.  Similar to the closure of John's Lane West hostel, the Dublin Simon hostel on Harcourt Street is due to close and there are strong objections to the replacement service on Fitzwilliam Square, putting even more emergency beds at risk.  In May 102 people were sleeping rough in Dublin, an increase of 12% since last November.  This is on top of the 4,262 people in emergency beds, of whom approximately 1,800 are children.  Senators and Deputies must ensure the energy and momentum for change generated in the aftermath of the general election are not lost and that the recent recommendations of the Committee on Housing and Homelessness are implemented.  They include the provision of 50,000 social housing units, rent certainty, security of tenure and ensuring no homeless shelters are closed until alternative accommodation is found.  Before the John's Lane West and Harcourt Street hostels are closed permanently, Rosemary and other residents should be provided with safe and secure alternative accommodation.  I would be grateful if the Leader would raise this urgent issue directly with the Minister responsible before tomorrow.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Q00500"><p>The Protection of Life in Pregnancy (Amendment) (Fatal Foetal Abnormalities) (No. 2) Bill 2013 was introduced by Deputy Mick Wallace in the D&aacute;il last week and I support it.  Most Senators realise we need to "Repeal the Eighth" to make a substantial change in this regard.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, we cannot cherry-pick the Constitution.  We cannot say, "I like this bit of the Constitution and I don't like that."  We are either democrats or we are not democrats.  We need to respect the people of the State and their decision as they make it in a referendum.  We can work for change and bring it back, and articulate and argue a case for change within the Constitution.</p><p>I am deeply worried when I hear officeholders using terms such as, "I do not know whether the Bill is anti-constitutional and I do not care."  Article 28 of the Constitution relates to collective Cabinet responsibility.  I am concerned that members of the Cabinet now seem to cherry-pick regarding the advice they take from the Attorney General and whether it is okay to take the advice from the Attorney General on whether to pay one's water charges bill or whether one acts as part of the collective in Cabinet.  I greatly respect the decision of the Minister, Deputy Zappone, to accept the Attorney General's advice on the Bill to be voted on this week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R00200"><p>I do not think we should discuss matters that are more relevant to the other House.  The Senator is naming people-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R00300"><p>This is relevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R00400"><p>The Government is not responsible to the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R00500"><p>There is nothing more relevant to this House than upholding the Constitution.  We can talk in this House about new politics or-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R00600"><p>The Senator is entitled to his opinion, but he should not make assumptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R00700"><p>----- we can talk in this House about reckless politics.  I am asking the Leader of the House to request the Taoiseach to come in here and answer for his stewardship of the Cabinet, regarding upholding Article 28 of the Constitution on collective Cabinet responsibility.</p> <p>The Ministers sitting around the Cabinet table have had the opportunity to hear the advice of the Attorney General and have avoided making a decision today on whether they should have collective Cabinet responsibility.  There is a collective responsibility on the Cabinet to make a decision on whether the Bill before the D&aacute;il is constitutional and they are now avoiding that.</p> <p>I fear this is a downgrading of what has pertained heretofore.  The Cabinet has always upheld Article 28.  I am not putting a motion.  I am asking the Leader to ask the Taoiseach to come here and answer for the role the Cabinet is taking regarding upholding the Constitution.  The issue is far too important to allow members of the Cabinet to cherry-pick the advice they take.  It is not good enough to seek the advice of the Attorney General on payment of water charges and then opt out on another issue of such importance.  That is not acceptable and I ask the Leader of the House-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R00800"><p>The Senator has made his point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R00900"><p>----- to call the Taoiseach to come here to answer for his behaviour this week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1397" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#R01000"><p>I ask the Leader to invite the newly-appointed Minister for Health to come to the Seanad for a specific debate on the strategies that should be employed to ensure that more people are treated in their homes, thus reducing hospital waiting lists and unemployment.  There is huge potential to increase the number of home help hours available.  This should be at worst cost neutral and probably a cost benefit as it would keep people out of expensive care elsewhere.  It is also where people are happiest.</p> <p>We need a debate on increasing the number of home help hours available and getting much more comprehensive home help packages, particularly in the case of people with Alzheimer's disease, dementia, etc., where there should be no age restrictions.  Much can be done with home care packages.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I agree with the sentiments of Senator Conway-Walsh in regard to carers.  Large-scale reform of the home carer scheme is required.  The amount home carers receive and their fringe benefits should be increased and it should be made an attractive option for people to stay at home and care for loved ones, because home is where people want to be.  I believe the potential of home helps, home help packages and carers has not been fully exploited as a method of keeping people at home, eliminating waiting lists and increasing cost effectiveness.</p><p>I ask the Leader to examine this issue.  The Leader is a former distinguished chair of the health committee and will have an appreciation of the potential that exists.  We need to think outside the box, we need to spend a lot more money in this sphere and we need to take action urgently.  It is a very important debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S00200"><p>I wish to propose an amendment in line with non-Government motion 6 on the Order Paper.  The Fianna F&aacute;il group proposes: &ldquo;That Seanad &Eacute;ireann calls for a Seanad committee representative of all the political groups to be established in order to examine councillors&rsquo; terms and conditions, including PRSI class K status, pension rights and other related matters and that this committee would consult with representatives from both the Association of Irish Local Government (AILG) and the Local Authority Members Association (LAMA).&rdquo;</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S00300"><p>Are you proposing that this be taken today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S00400"><p>Yes.  Following the 2014 local government reforms, the areas served by councillors have expanded and their workload has increased.  In counties with a small population, like Carlow, councillors are faced with a shortage of funding to carry out even basic works like grass cutting, for example.  This leads to a lot of frustration.  Councillors have to deal directly with communities who are paying extra taxes, like the local property tax.  The communities, therefore, have greater expectations of the work to be carried out by their local authority, when, in reality, the councils are doing more work.  It is not only important but essential that the Minister sets up this committee to work with AILG, LAMA and all of the political groups here.  Every councillor deserves a proper stamp and proper pension rights-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S00500"><p>On a point of order, I cannot hear what the Senator is saying with the amount of traffic that is taking place in the House, and I want to hear her point.  The Senator is trying to get above the noise.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S00600"><p>I take your point.  Ci&uacute;nas.  Senator Murnane O'Connor should resume.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S00700"><p>Senator O'Donnell is correct that the noise was very loud.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S00800"><p>It is not a train station.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S00900"><p>Absolutely.  It is not only important but essential that the Minister sets up this committee to liaise with AILG, LAMA and all of the political groups.  Councillors deserve a proper stamp and pension rights.  I was a councillor for 19 years on Carlow County Council, and like other councillors and Senators who have been councillors previously, I was honoured to represent my community.  However, councillors have been affected by what is called local government reform.  There have been cutbacks everywhere and local authorities and councillors have been affected.</p> <p>I ask the Minister to address the House.  It is essential that councillors get their entitlements, which is what we in the Fianna F&aacute;il group are looking for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1423" speakername="Ray Butler" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#S01000"><p>I ask the Leader to invite the Minister of State with responsibility for regional economic development, Deputy Michael Ring, to the House for a debate on retail planning in rural Ireland.  We have all been on the Seanad campaign and have gone through large towns and villages in rural Ireland where we have seen many shops closed.  Local planning authorities give planning permission for out-of-town shopping centres and supermarkets, while the local shopkeeper in the centre of town has to pay rates and insult is added to injury due to parking charges.  How can anyone compete when there are 500 free parking spaces on the outskirts of a town?  We want people to shop in the centre of town but they have to pay these charges.</p> <p>This problem arose in England 20 years ago and it devastated towns.  Even in bigger towns like Manchester, Liverpool and Leeds, the centres became ghettos because of out-of-town shopping centres.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Ray Butler:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2303"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2303&amp;amp;pid=RayButler&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some 20 years on planning authorities here are granting planning permission for shopping centres.  In one town alone I counted 23 shops which had been closed on the main street.  Planning authorities in rural Ireland are not taking this on board.  They are granting planning permission to multinationals in order that they can draw in massive amounts in rates, while the ordinary shopkeeper who has survived through the recession is struggling.  They then charge parking fees outside their doors.  We need the Minister, all relevant groups and the local authorities to draw up a plan.  From what I saw while travelling around rural Ireland during the Seanad election campaign, all we need now is tumbleweed in certain towns because no business is being conducted.  This is happening all over Ireland.  I would, therefore, like to see the Minister come into the House and planning authorities in rural Ireland considering this issue which represents a serious problem for retail businesses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T00700"><p>I am delighted to see that interest in our electorate, particularly county councillors, has come to the fore.  I, therefore, ask the Leader to amend the Order of Business to take No. 11, non-Government motion No. 2, first today.  There are three amendments to the motion tabled by my colleagues, Senators Denis Landy and Gerald Nash.  The plight of county councillors has been spoken about in this Chamber, particularly in the past 18 months, but much lip service has been paid to this group.  The way in which they are being treated is absolutely outrageous.  I received an e-mail the other day from a councillor who in the 21st century has a broken black and white printer to deal with his administrative craft-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T00800"><p>Is the Senator also proposing an amendment to the Order of Business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T00900"><p>I am-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01000"><p>To be discussed today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01100"><p>On a point of order, I did not hear the amendment Senator Gerard P. Craughwell said he was proposing.  Will he repeat it, please?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01200"><p>It concerns No. 11, non-Government motion No. 2, the motion I had agreed to take in Private Members' time-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01300"><p>To be taken before No. 1 today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01400"><p>If amendments are to be moved to it - Senator Denis Landy has tabled three amendments to it - it should be the most comprehensive item-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01500"><p>It is not on the Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01600"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01700"><p>I ask-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01800"><p>Does the Senator want No. 11, non-Government motion No. 2, to be taken today before No. 1?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T01900"><p>That is the amendment proposed to the Order of Business.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T02000"><p>It is not on the Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T02100"><p>We will clarify the matter now.  It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T02200"><p>All I can see is a motion on Seanad political reform.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T02500"><p>Order, please.  I will give Senators the page number.  It is listed on page 316.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1415" speakername="Maura Hopkins" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#T02600"><p>I refer to concerns about the need for urgent action on the N5, particularly between Frenchpark and Strokestown.  Locals have informed me that there are black spots along this section of road.  We understand there have been over 20 accidents at a particular one.  I have raised this issue on several occasions in the past year with Roscommon County Council and ask that Transport Infrastructure Ireland, TII, deal with it urgently.  We need to see a review of, or action taken on, the need for better signage, verges and road surfacing on the N5, particularly between Frenchpark and Strokestown.  I am also very concerned about vehicles being driven at excessive speeds through the villages of Frenchpark, Bellanagare and Tulsk.  We know that there is a plan for a new route between Scramogue and Tibohine, which will be a very positive development when it happens.  However, in the interim I call for urgent action to deal with what is a major route to the west.  I will be seeking a meeting with Transport Infrastructure Ireland and ask the Minister, Deputy Shane Ross, and the Minister of State, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan, to take this issue very seriously.  As I have highlighted, there have been many accidents along this section of road and every accident is one too many.  We need to reduce the risk as much as possible.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Maura Hopkins:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2478"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2478&amp;amp;pid=MauraHopkins&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are identified safety risks on this section and I ask for action to be taken as quickly as possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#U00200"><p>I wish to raise the alarming report by Social Justice Ireland today which highlights that we now have 750,000 people living in poverty in this State, an increase of over 100,000 since the onset of the austerity policies.  Within that figure are 230,000 children living in poverty.  It is a huge indictment of Government policies.  I have to ask the question as how this happened.  Was it by accident?  Did we suddenly miss that we had so much poverty and inequality in the country?  Of course, it was not by accident.  It was as a direct result of policy choices made by both the last Fine Gael-Labour Party Government and by the Fianna F&aacute;il Government that bankrupted the State.</p> <p>Rather than choosing to increase taxes on those who can afford to pay more, both Governments chose to cut child benefit, jobseeker's allowance, one-parent family allowance, carer's allowance, means-tested fuel allowance and pension payments.  That is how it has happened.  It is an absolute disgrace.</p> <p>I am calling for a debate on this issue.  I ask the Leader to bring the Minister with responsibility for social welfare into the House.  If we care about poverty, all of us need to ensure that the upcoming budget is equality-proofed.  That way, rather than just talking about the problem, we can ensure that we do something concrete to make sure that this inequality is not exacerbated any further.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#U00300"><p>Is the Senator looking for a debate or moving an amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#U00400"><p>I am asking the Leader for a debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1424" speakername="Frank Feighan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#U00500"><p>Coming from the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly plenary over the last two days, the Brexit issue is of huge importance to this country, the UK and to Europe.  I am disappointed that an all-Ireland forum has not been set up both North and South to address the implications of this serious issue.  It has gone unnoticed in this Chamber, but the North-South Interparliamentary Association has met in this Chamber every six months for the last three years.  Many issues have been discussed, including cross-border tourism and infrastructure.  It has gone unnoticed.</p> <p>There have been politicians of different hues in this Chamber and from different parties in Stormont involved.  After the most important decision that could affect this country in the last 50 years, we really need to look at it from a cross-border, all-Ireland basis.  I call on the Minister to come into the House to explain what exactly is being done and what can be done.  In the last five years, our country has been at the heart of Europe and we can do a lot.  However, we cannot do things in silos when dealing with Northern Ireland, the Republic of Ireland, the island of Ireland, the UK and Europe.  We need an all-Ireland approach.  I ask the Minister to come into the House to try to see if we could have all-Ireland co-operation on this very important matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#U00600"><p>I ask the Leader whether he would take on board the many issues surrounding Brexit.  The one I wish to discuss today is the issue of third-level students and the Brexit vote.  As everybody in this room knows, many students from all over Ireland, particularly from Border counties, attend universities both in Northern Ireland and the UK.  There is a reciprocal arrangement for students from the UK and Northern Ireland who come here to the South of Ireland to go to college to study for their degrees or whatever.  The outcome of the referendum could have a major impact on those students, particularly those from this jurisdiction who are heading either to the North of Ireland or to the UK to further their studies.  It is an issue, among many others, I would add, that needs to be addressed and taken on board.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This vacuum is causing many families concern.</p><p>During the negotiations, which are estimated to last two years, this will probably not be an immediate issue but it needs to be addressed.  Students who sat their leaving certificates or are in the middle of courses are facing the uncertainty of not knowing whether their fees will increase in a couple of years' time.  This issue affects a large number of students and it is essential that it be given priority during the negotiations between Britain, Ireland and the EU.</p><p>Regarding councillors' terms and conditions, I was a councillor for more than 15 years.  It is important that the House speaks with one voice on this issue.  Our ambition is to improve the terms and conditions of councillors.  If we do not, we will find it difficult to get people to enter into local government at a time when we are encouraging many to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1386" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#V00200"><p>I wish to raise the issue of where we are going with the tourism industry.  It is going well in some locations, for example, in my part of the world in Kinsale, Cork, but I am concerned about the change in strategy and policy.  In Kinsale, approximately 2,500 people passed through the tourist office in the past six months but its staff numbers have been reduced.  It had three staff last year but only two this year.</p> <p>The main factor in our tourism industry is our people.  They are key.  The front face is important.  Our people are the friendly faces that guide our tourists.  We must invest in our front face.  There has been major investment in roots tourism and digital media but we cannot forget what it is that Ireland is trying to sell, namely, our people.  This is the key marketing goal that we need to push.  We must debate with the Minister the focus that must be placed on the front-line staff of, in particular, F&aacute;ilte Ireland.  They must be supported and have the resources necessary to show tourists around the country.  When one goes to any other part of the world, the first place one visits is the tourist office.  We must support our infrastructure and the people on the ground.  A debate on this matter would be appropriate and helpful for our tourists and the tourism industry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#V00300"><p>I am delighted that the issue of councillors' terms and conditions has been raised.  I have been raising it regularly and I was the only Oireachtas Member on the review group on local government set up by the former Minister, Deputy Kelly.  We surveyed councillors' terms and conditions, including their work conditions.  The Association of Irish Local Government, AILG, also conducted a survey.  Both surveys showed that, on average, a councillor spent 35 hours per week on council work.  The case is well made for councillors' terms and conditions to be improved.</p> <p>In my amendment to Senators Craughwell and Boyhan's motion, I spelled out what was proposed by the then Minister but which did not get through the process.  One element was to increase councillors' annual allowance from &euro;2,286 to &euro;4,500.  This measure has been proposed and is there to be implemented.  With my amendment, I second Senator Craughwell's motion.</p> <p>I support Senator Murnane O'Connor.  In the previous Seanad, there was a group on which Senator Wilson represented the Fianna F&aacute;il Party.  We met the Minister.  It worked well and caused the review to happen but this is an ongoing process.  It has nearly been brought to finality-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#V00400"><p>On a small point of order, the Senator can only second one amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#V00500"><p>I said that I was supporting it, not seconding it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#V00600"><p>Sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#V00700"><p>I was conscious of that.  I support Senator Murnane O'Connor's amendment.  We can do this without any ministerial approval.  The Whip of each group just needs to nominate someone, be it himself or herself.  We should do that this evening.  It would progress the case for councillors further.</p> <p>There are many new Senators.  Those who are returning and those who were councillors previously know the importance to society and our communities of councillors and the work that they do.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Denis Landy:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2349"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2349&amp;amp;pid=DenisLandy&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is a good day for councillors.  We seem to be receiving cross-party and cross-group support so far today.  We can make progress on this and bring it to finality by way of bringing in improvements for councillors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W00200"><p>I support my colleagues with regard to councillors.  There was a review of local government carried out in respect of the 2014 local elections.  We reduced the number of councillors and expanded their jurisdictions but did not make the appropriate adjustments to allowances and expenses.  In fairness to councillors, they are providing local leadership in their communities and they work extremely hard.  If one wants to survive as a councillor, one must put in the hard work.  They are doing so.  In fairness to the Minister, the matter is under review but it is important that we have some indication from him as to the timeline.  This is the issue about which I am concerned.</p> <p>This matter was raised over 12 months ago.  The local elections were in June 2014.  Two years on, we are nearly half way through councillors&rsquo; term.  It is now that the review should be carried out and delivered on.  I have come across a number of councillors, with young families or children in third level education, who are now finding it extremely difficult to make ends meet.  That must be taken into account.  Can the Minister indicate when the review will be completed?  It is a question of delivering on a comprehensive package and not just a question of a little tweak here and there.</p> <p>On the issue of Console and the charity regulator, we need to grasp the extent of this matter.  Some 2,600 organisations receive funding from the HSE, amounting to &euro;3.6 billion per annum.  We need to have proper structures in place to ensure proper auditing mechanisms.  I ask the Leader to acquire some clarification to ensure all those procedures are put in place.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W00300"><p>On a point of order, I would like the record to be clear on the fact that the review started by the former Minister, Deputy Alan Kelly, is completed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W00400"><p>I am afraid that is not a point of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W00500"><p>There is no need for any other review.  That is only stalling the horse.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W00600"><p>That has nothing to do with procedure.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1387" speakername="Denis Landy" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W00700"><p>The review is completed and the recommendations have been made.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W00800"><p>I must rule the Senator out of order.  He has already spoken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.115" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1373" speakername="Keith Swanick" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W00900"><p>Some 266 people were handed the gift of life in 2015 through organ donation.  This figure has increased substantially due to the diligent work of Organ Donation and Transplant Ireland, which is headed by Professor Jim Egan.  Outcomes for transplant recipients in Ireland continue to rank among the best in Europe.  Currently, organ donation in Ireland is based on a voluntary donation system and it occurs in 32 intensive care units throughout the country.  The National Organ Procurement Service operates a 24-hour service 365 days per year.  Its highly trained and motivated staff travel to the relevant hospital and guide the family through the very traumatic experience.  All stakeholders are treated with dignity and respect.  The service does good work and I ask the Leader to ask the Minister to ensure its funding is secured and maintained.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1380" speakername="Paddy Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#W01000"><p>I wish to support a good Senator in front of me, Senator Butler, in regard to rates on commercial buildings.  Small businesses are under enormous pressure.  The Senator is correct in saying out-of-town shopping centres could affect the life and soul of many towns throughout the country.  Even the small towns have been sucked into the bigger urban areas.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Paddy Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1866"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1866&amp;amp;pid=PaddyBurke&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It is important for the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Minister for Finance to find a way forward to get cheaper money for farmers and small businesses to carry them over at crisis time.  There is no doubt that there is a crisis taking place in farming and that farmers need a certain amount of funding at different times of the year to carry them over.  We see clearly our counterparts in Spain, Portugal and other European member states who have access to interest rates of 2% and 3% on short term or overdraft borrowings to tide farmers and small businesses over at crunch times whether it is to buy in stock or while they wait for cash crops to mature and be sold.  I ask the Leader to arrange at some stage for the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to put at the top of their agendas the need for a special financial arrangement for farmers and small businesses, in particular to tide them over at crucial times throughout the year.  That is what happens in certain countries throughout the year and I have no doubt that it can be done here with a bit of ingenuity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#X00200"><p>These days, there is very little in the way of real politics.  It is all entertainment.  We have people like Boris Johnson and Nigel Farage and this afternoon we were treated to an extraordinary concentration on the doings of local authorities and grass cutting.  For a national parliament, it is obviously just naked electioneering.  We have had the odd laugh out of this mongrel Government, but nothing in the wildest extremes of my imagination could conjure up a situation where there would be a Cabinet crisis over the conscience of Shane Ross.  It calls to mind the resonance of the War of Jenkins' Ear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#X00300"><p>Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#X00400"><p>It has a lot more to do with Mr. Ross trying to take a poke at the Taoiseach.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#X00500"><p>The Senator is out of order.  Pay attention, please.  Refer to the Minister properly by his title.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#X00600"><p>Sorry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#X00700"><p>The person to whom the Senator refers is now Minister Ross.  Please refer to him correctly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#X00800"><p>I beg his pardon.  It is the conscience of Minister Ross.  We have had this fabulous - and I use the word in its correct application - resonance with the War of Jenkins' Ear.  It seems to me that it is avoiding the issue altogether, which is the repeal of the eighth amendment.  The Attorney General is usually quite cautious and says things are unconstitutional and we have to take her word.  There is such a thing as Cabinet confidentiality.  All the medical experts in charge of maternity hospitals tell us this is defective.  Unlike Mr. Cabinet Minister Gove, I would be rather inclined to listen to the experts from time to time on the odd chance that they might have something informed to say on the subject.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#X00900"><p>I welcome the strides being made on the roll-out of the national broadband plan and, in particular, the fact that the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources, Deputy Naughten, has brought to Cabinet today firm proposals as to how it might proceed and how we might see it delivered on the ground.  This needs to be driven forward and the Minister should be commended for hitting the ground running.</p> <p>On the issue of broadband and jobs, I note that we have a state-of-the-art transatlantic fibre-optic cable from New York, which makes landfall at Killala, County Mayo, and goes on to connect New York with London.  It is state-of-the-art in that the data and information capacity of the cable is equivalent to that of all current cables under sea or on the seabed between North America and Europe.  It is significant.  The Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Mary Mitchell O'Connor, is anxious to implement the regional action plan for jobs to see jobs created on the ground.  There is a golden opportunity with this technology.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->With all the capacity of this high-speed cable, one particular area on which we need to focus is data centres.  We know we have an ideal climate for such centres.  At the location where the cable makes landfall, a combined heat-and-power biomass plant is being developed.  One key consideration for developers of data centres is that there would be a source of renewable energy close to hand because they are energy guzzlers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y00200"><p>The Senator's time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y00300"><p>In achieving the objective of delivering jobs and investment in the west and in Mayo under the regional Action Plan for Jobs, will the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation look at the development of data centres at the former Asahi site and Knock Airport?  Will she also ensure all Government agencies are moving in that direction, be it the county council, IDA Ireland, Enterprise Ireland and the Western Development Commission, in dealing with that particular task?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y00400"><p>I seek leave to introduce the Coroners (Amendment) Bill 2016, Jake&rsquo;s amendment Bill.  I discussed this with the Leader previously.  I hope it can go on the Order Paper and be taken next Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y00500"><p>It is still with the Bills Office.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y00600"><p>I hope it can be progressed.  Will the Leas-Chathaoirleach advise me on the process?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y00700"><p>The Senator cannot move the Bill now because it is not on the Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y00800"><p>Do I give notice to the Seanad Office?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y00900"><p>Yes, but the Senator should wait until it appears on the Order Paper.  He cannot make any move until it appears on the Order Paper.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01000"><p>What is the normal timeframe?  I submitted this Bill weeks ago.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01100"><p>The Senator can discuss it with us afterwards.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1400" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01200"><p>Okay, that is fine.  I will discuss it later on.</p> <p>Most Senators would have been circulated with the concerns of the Irish Cattle and Sheep Farmers Association, ICSA, about the recent comments by the German Vice-Chancellor indicating that in his opinion there would have to be cutbacks to the Common Agricultural Policy, following the Brexit vote.  We need to see a strong response from the Government.  The Taoiseach needs to rebuff these comments and reassure the farming community.  Accordingly, will the Leader consider amending tomorrow&rsquo;s statements on farm safety with the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine to widen the debate to deal with the concerns of the farming community following these comments?  We cannot just dismiss these because it is the German Vice-Chancellor and not some minor political representative.</p> <p>I want to record my party&rsquo;s support for other Members on councillors&rsquo; pay and conditions.  We need to address this issue as they are not paid enough nor do they have the entitlements they deserve for the work they put in.  They do not get the respect at national level anyway for the work they put in.  This needs to be addressed and we support whatever efforts are being made to do this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01300"><p>I support other councillors-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01400"><p>Sorry, we are Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01500"><p>Yes, Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01600"><p>You said &ldquo;councillors&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01700"><p>Well I meant to say &ldquo;Senators&rdquo;.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01800"><p>There is very little difference these days in this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y01900"><p>Senator Noone without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Y02000"><p>I apologise for the error.  I think everyone knew what I meant.</p> <p>I support Senator Murnane O'Connor.  I am delighted we have cross-party support because with new politics, it will require the support of all the political parties to get it through.  It is not exactly a popular move in how the public might perceive it.  The Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Varadkar, has already shown a willingness to improve the K class, which is important.  I am glad it is on the agenda.</p> <p>Over the past several weeks, I conducted a survey at supermarkets around the Dublin area on the issue of sugar and food labelling.  Among parents, it seems there is some deception as to how food producers put the content of sugar, salt and other ingredients on their labels.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->With regard to one yoghurt, in particular, of the people questioned, 61% incorrectly believed that the product was a healthy choice for their child.  It is worrying that even though parents are trying hard to decipher their labels, food companies are making it difficult for them.  I compliment an initiative by Q102, a Dublin radio station, which has been good at highlighting matters such as this.  It gives a Sugar Savvy Card to listeners, which outlines basic facts such as 4g of sugar equalling one teaspoon and sugar consumption per day, which should be no more than 12 teaspoons for an adult.  The card also highlights the different ways sugar can be described on a menu, including syrup, honey, malt, cane, molasses and so on.  I raise this issue frequently and I am sure I sound like a killjoy but this is important and I would be grateful if the Leader would agree to bring the Minister of State at the Department of Health, Deputy Marcella Corcoran Kennedy, to the House discuss this in the near future.  There are issues relating to EU law when it comes to traffic light labelling which would make life simpler for consumers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z00200"><p>Senators Feighan and Gallagher raised the issue of Brexit.  When the British Government triggers Article 50 of the Lisbon treaty, the House should have a rolling debate about Brexit because it is the most significant event in the history of the State.  We will face nothing as serious as this.  The British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly completed its most recent plenary earlier.  The House was presented by Senators Paul Coghlan, Wilson, Landy, Feighan, Noone, Boyhan, Horkan and myself.  We have a team to represent the House in discussions with members of the British, Welsh, Scottish, Northern Ireland, Isle of Man and Guernsey parliaments.  I am delighted Ms Arlene Foster has not agreed to set up another body to represent-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z00300"><p>We have run out of time.  I cannot allow the Senator to ramble on, unfortunately.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z00400"><p>I am not rambling on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z00500"><p>We are up against the clock.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z00600"><p>The Leas-Chathaoirleach is a member of the assembly and he will recognise the fact-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z00700"><p>Is the Senator seconding an amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z00800"><p>One of my colleagues has seconded an amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z00900"><p>I am up against the clock.  If the Senator wishes to second something, I would like him to do it.  I call Senator Clifford-Lee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01000"><p>I am not finished yet.  I understand there is no time limit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01100"><p>There is.  Senator Leyden is a long-standing Member and he should co-operate.  His time is up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01200"><p>It is vital that Senators and all elected representatives work together and the BIPA is the body that should discuss and negotiate issues relating to Brexit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01300"><p>If the discussions at BIPA are anything like the comments the Senator has just made, they will not get far.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01400"><p>I second the amendment regarding motion 6.  Having come through town and county councils with Senator Murnane O'Connor, I am acutely aware of the distressing circumstances in which many councillors find themselves.  This is a level headed motion, which will engage with the AILG and LAMA-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.160" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01500"><p>The Senator will have the opportunity to make these points when the matter is dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01600"><p>I second Senator Ardagh's amendment to the Order of Business to bring the Minister for Justice and Equality to the House in light of the shooting earlier in Lusk in my constituency.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01700"><p>It is not the Senator's constituency.  She is a Member of the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1376" speakername="Lorraine Clifford Lee" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01800"><p>I live close by and the people of Lusk and the general area are concerned about the escalation in gun crime.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#Z01900"><p>I would like to mention the shooting in Lusk.  I have been a GP in the town for 33 years and we have never had such an incident.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA00100"><p>Order, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA00200"><p>I have been a GP there for 33 years and we have never had an incident such as this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA00300"><p>Quickly, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.168" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA00500"><p>It is an estate of very young families.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA00600"><p>It is very difficult to hear the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA00700"><p>Yes, it is.  Please, everyone, ciunas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA00800"><p>The danger to them that is manifest by today's episode is one I hope the T&aacute;naiste will address when she comes to the House later today to debate a Bill in which it is proposed to increase the powers of the CAB in seizing the assets of criminal gangs.</p> <p>I also support Senator Ray Butler's call for the Minister of State, Deputy Michael Ring, to come to the House.  There is donutting in places such as Balbriggan.  The main street in Rush is full of derelict buildings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA00900"><p>The Proceeds of Crime (Amendment) Bill 2016 is the next item on the agenda and the Senator will have the opportunity to discuss it then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1421" speakername="James Reilly" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01000"><p>I thank the Leas-Chathaoirligh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01100"><p>I apologise to the following Senators who will be called first on the Order of Business tomorrow, Senators Martin Conway, Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill, Ned O'Sullivan and Kieran O'Donnell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01200"><p>There are only a couple-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01300"><p>I am sorry, but we have run out of time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01400"><p>I thank the 26 Senators who spoke.  We need to take a collective deep breath as Members of the Upper House.  I know that we all still have the "L" plates.  However, this is Parliament and we should all behave accordingly.  If we need to look at how we do our business, let us do so, but the comments of Senator Rose Conway-Walsh came true today.  I believe that on the Order of Business it should be a case of one item per person.</p> <p>Three amendments have been proposed to the Order of Business.  On the two motions on councillors' pay and conditions, I make the following genuine appeal.  Despite what Senator David Norris may think, councillors form part of the electorate that elects Members of the House.  Therefore, it is important, as their representatives, to represent and voice their views.  I will accept Senator Diarmuid Wilson's-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01500"><p>I thought the Leader and his colleagues were elected by the people by delegated suffrage.  I am glad to be told the truth.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01600"><p>I am happy to accept the proposal made by Senator Murnane O'Connor in that regard.  However, as we have done with other elements of Government policy, if there is a serious willingness to acknowledge that the role of councillors, their terms and conditions, work rate and remit have changed, let us not play political games.  Let us collectively form an all-party cross-party group, to include Independents of all views, including Senator David Norris, members of the Independent group formed from the Taoiseach's nominees, Senator Gerard P. Craughwell's group and the political parties.  Let us do this and not play politics with the role of councillors.  We hear about the role of local government and talk about the reform of local government.  The most important people are those who work within it - the officials and public representatives.  I am happy to work with everyone here, provided there is no political gamesmanship and no attempts to score political points to try to get votes.  We want to bring about reform and improve the role, remuneration and conditions of councillors.  Senator Denis Landy made a very good point the last day on the mental health issue, one we need to discuss.  If we are serious about doing this, let us deal with it in a manner that befits this Chamber.  I will be happy to take the amendment on board in the spirit of all Members of the House, if that is agreeable to Members opposite.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01800"><p>In particular, Members on this side.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA01900"><p>It applies particularly to Government Members.  On the first or second day of this Seanad, Senator Paddy Burke had a motion on K class contributions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1416" speakername="Martin Conway" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA02000"><p>There was a debate on the issue last December.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA02100"><p>Order, please.  The Leader to continue, without interruption.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#AA02200"><p>It is my intention to take the Bill on Seanad reform next week when there will be an opportunity to have this issue form part of that discussion.  I know that the Minister, Deputy Simon Coveney, is working on the very serious issue of the terms and conditions and role of local authority members.  He is putting a plan in place, with a package of measures.  In fairness to him, he has had to deal with the issues of waste and water services and now has to deal with the housing strategy which we all agree is the most important issue in performing our role as public representatives.  The Minister is working on it and is very serious about dealing with it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> The proposal by Senator Ardagh in regard to the Minister for Justice and Equality is very important, not least because there is the loss of human life and the threat to human life.  To hear this morning of another serious incident in which a person was critically injured concerns us all.  The Minister was in the House this afternoon for the Commencement debate regarding the issue of Console, which was raised by Senator Marie-Louise O'Donnell, and she will be in the House again later today to deal with legislation on the Criminal Assets Bureau and the proceeds of crime.  I again make the point that the safety of residents, whether they are in north Dublin, south Dublin or in any other part of our country, is important.</p><p>The Minister will not come to the House on this issue today, for obvious reasons.  I ask the Senator to withdraw her amendment to the Order of Business and I will work with her to ensure the Minister comes to the House to deal with the specific issue of gangland crime.  It is an issue we need to address, as a country.  However, let us put this in context.  An additional &euro;55 million is being given to the Garda this year-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1427" speakername="Marie Louise O'Donnell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#BB00200"><p>Excuse me, I cannot hear the Leader speaking.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#BB00300"><p>We have also seen the Garda overtime budget increase to &euro;90 million.  It is this Government that re-opened Templemore, that has provided more resources to the Garda and that recruited more garda&iacute;.  I hope we recognise that it is not the case the Government is not doing anything; to be fair, it is doing much, as is the Minister for Justice and Equality, with the Garda Commissioner.  We have seen the Garda special crime task force put in place, along with a dedicated armed support unit in the Dublin area.  To say that nothing is happening is incorrect.  Resources are being provided, legislation is being drafted and recruitment is under way.  If the Senator will withdraw her amendment to the Order of Business, I will be happy to ensure the Minister comes to the House.</p> <p>On the issue of water, I understand former Senator Joe O'Toole has announced his resignation to the Government as the chair of the independent body.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#BB00400"><p>It is a great pity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#BB00500"><p>It is a pity he has had to resign.  I have known former Senator O'Toole for a long time and it is a pity-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#BB00600"><p>We cannot discuss personalities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#BB00700"><p>In the context of the Order of Business, I am just making the point that new politics means one thing one day and something slightly different another day.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#BB00800"><p>We will not discuss personalities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#BB00900"><p>He is a very astute, good public servant who has done a lot of work for the State on many issues and in many roles.  I understand he has resigned.</p> <p>Senators Conway-Walsh, Kelleher and O'Reilly raised the issue of family carers.  I agree with them that the implementation of the national strategy on carers needs to be a priority in the Department of Social Protection.  I hope we will have the Minister for Social Protection in the House to discuss that in the coming weeks.  The Minister has agreed to come to the House on social protection issues ahead of the budget.  If we can do this next week, I will be happy to do it because the issue of carers is an important one that we need to see addressed.  Carers do a huge amount of work that the State could never do.  These are our own family members and friends in our own communities, so I fully concur with the Senators on that issue.</p> <p>Senator Kelleher raised the issue of John's Lane hostel.  I understand from the agencies involved that alternative accommodation has been provided.  It is an important matter that should be addressed.  I hope that will happen in the context of the housing and homelessness issue.  I know the Minister is working on his strategy and intends to bring it forward before the summer recess.</p> <p>Senator Humphreys raised the issue of the eighth amendment and the role of Cabinet responsibility.  The Cabinet is not taking a position on the Bill.  I agree with the Deputy that the eighth amendment is a very sensitive issue and one we need to see addressed.  The Taoiseach has proposed a citizens' assembly.  The Bill will be brought before the Oireachtas, I am told, before the summer recess, which will provide an opportunity to have the debate Deputy Humphreys has sought.  To be fair, the Taoiseach has never misled the House on his opinions on this issue.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I share his view that the citizens' assembly is the way forward in handling this issue because it allows for the space for people to have that discussion.  Cabinet members have collective responsibility, and there is no halfway house about that.  The problem we have, however, is that there is no Cabinet undertaking or collective decision on the Bill in question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC00200"><p>On a point of order, the Leader-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC00300"><p>No, I will not entertain it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC00400"><p>I ask that the Taoiseach come in to answer-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC00500"><p>Senator Humphreys is out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC00600"><p>The last time we saw-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC00700"><p>I must ask Senator Humphreys to resume his seat.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC00800"><p>The Leader's answer is not acceptable-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC00900"><p>The Senator is being deliberately disruptive.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01000"><p>I ask the Leader to ask the Taoiseach to come before the House to address us on Article 28 of the Constitution-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01100"><p>That is not a point of order.  Senator Humphreys is totally out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01200"><p>I do not accept-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01300"><p>The Senator should sit down.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01400"><p>I do not accept that I am out of order.  I raised the issue of Article 28-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01500"><p>A point of order is to clarify something, and the Senator is not doing that.  He is being deliberately disruptive.  I am telling the Senator to sit down and we will hear the Leader respond.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01600"><p>The Leader has avoided the issue that I raised by misrepresenting it-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01700"><p>I am not responsible for how the Leader handles matters raised.  The Senator is out of order.  I call on the Leader.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01800"><p>I am happy to reiterate to Senator Humphreys-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC01900"><p>Will the Leader ask the Taoiseach to come in?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02000"><p>-----that the example I referred to earlier relating to the manner in which councillors' pay and conditions is handled applies to the eighth amendment and to sensitive social issues.  On two occasions in this Chamber we were able to produce a report and a Bill and to have the issue addressed.  The Attorney General, as I understand it, said - and I am not in Cabinet-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02100"><p>We will not get into arguments about it now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02200"><p>-----that the Bill, as presented to the Lower House, is unconstitutional.  My view is that if one is a member of Cabinet and a Bill is deemed unconstitutional, one should not proceed to vote for that Bill, on two bases-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02300"><p>Will the Leader ask the Taoiseach to come in?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02400"><p>Please, no interruptions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02500"><p>First, one is putting a Bill forward that cannot be enacted and, second, one is giving false hope and playing politics with a very sensitive issue-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02600"><p>Will the Leader ask the Taoiseach to come in?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02700"><p>Senator Humphreys, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02800"><p>I would be happy to ask the Taoiseach to come in but I will not play politics with it-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC02900"><p>I do not play politics with Article 28-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC03000"><p>Senator Humphreys is out of order.  The Leader might address matters through the Chair, rather than looking across at Senators.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC03100"><p>I will.  I apologise; I am still learning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC03200"><p>That is all right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.227" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC03300"><p>I have dealt with the issue raised by Senator Murnane O'Connor regarding councillors' pay.</p> <p>Senators Butler, Paddy Burke and Reilly raised the very important issue of the role of our local towns, particularly concerning small and medium-sized enterprises and rates.  I agree with the speakers, particularly Senator Paddy Burke, that there is a need for the Ministers for Agriculture, Food and the Marine and Finance - with the banks - to come up with a way of being able to get extra money and credit for those businesses that require that type of investment and flexibility around the issue of capital.  The Minister will be here next week for statements on the summer economic statement, and I hope this issue can be part of that debate because it is a very important one.</p> <p>Senator Hopkins raised the issue of the N5 in Roscommon.  This is a very important issue - not least because it relates to public health and safety - and it comes under the remit of Transport Infrastructure Ireland and the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  I would be happy for the Minister to address it. </p> <p>Senator Gavan raised the issue of poverty and Social Justice Ireland's report.  The record shows that our country is moving forward in this regard.  The previous Government, which included the Labour Party, increased the minimum wage twice.  There are now more people back at work.  There is more optimism in respect of our balance of pay and our GDP rate, which is the fastest growing in the European Union-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1389" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC03400"><p>Where did the extra 100,000 people in poverty come from?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#CC03500"><p>I reiterate that the Minister for Social Protection will come before the House and that this matter can form part of the discussion with him.  Let us have a balanced and fair discussion on it.</p> <p>Senator Feighan raised the issue of the all-Ireland forum and Senator Leyden raised the issue of the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly today.  The Taoiseach is right in that we need to have an all-Ireland forum, post-Brexit, to ensure that we, as an island nation, have a roadmap and a plan to protect our interests.  Ireland is an island nation.  We can work with the British-Irish Parliamentary Assembly, at which I spoke today, the Northern Assembly and the North-South Ministerial Council to ensure this.  Senator Gallagher also raised the issue of Brexit and education.  This is something we might consider again after the summer recess.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jerry Buttimer:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2225"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2225&amp;amp;pid=JerryButtimer&amp;amp;year=2016&amp;amp;month=07&amp;amp;day=05"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Senator Lombard raised the issue of tourism, on which I would be happy to invite the Minister to the House to discuss.</p><p>Senator Colm Burke referred to Console and the impact of what has happened.  In replying to Commencement matters, the T&aacute;naiste addressed the enforcement of regulations under the Charities Act.  I hope that we can debate this matter before the summer recess.</p><p>Senator Swanick discussed organ donations, an important issue which is close to my heart.  I was Chairman of the Committee on Health and Children in the previous D&aacute;il, which produced a fine report on organ donation.  We must keep this issue to the forefront and change how people opt to donate organs.  We can support the work of Professor Jim Egan and his staff.  Professor Egan is a tremendous person and has done a significant amount of work, as has the former surgeon, Mr. David Hickey.  I would be happy to work with Senator Swanick to pursue this issue in the House.</p><p>Senator Norris, I am not sure what you raised in your very fine contribution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD00200"><p>Look at the Chair, not Senator Norris.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD00300"><p>The War of Jenkins' Ear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD00400"><p>Senator, please.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD00500"><p>I would be happy to talk to the Senator-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD00600"><p>He asked me what I raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD00700"><p>He should not have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD00800"><p>Regarding the one point that I know Senator Norris raised, this is no mongrel government.  I assure him of that.</p> <p>Senator Mulherin referred to broadband.  I would be happy for the Minister, Deputy Naughten, to attend the House to discuss that issue or for the Minister, Deputy Mitchell O'Connor, to discuss its importance for jobs.  The House has had a sequence of statements on jobs and I hope to continue with those.</p> <p>Senator Mac Lochlainn raised the issue of the Coroners (Amendment) Bill.  He would receive no objection from this side of the House in that regard.  I will ask the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Creed, to discuss CAP during the statements on farming.</p> <p>Senator Noone raised the important issue of sugar and obesity.  I hope that the Minister of State, Deputy Corcoran Kennedy, can attend the House on that matter.  Several Senators mentioned Brexit.</p> <p>I am happy to accept the amendment to the Order of Business regarding councillors' pay and conditions, assuming Senator Ardagh withdraws her motion.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD00900"><p>The Leader might sit down.  Senator Ardagh has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That the T&aacute;naiste address the House on the escalation in gun crime."  In view of the Leader's comments, Senator Ardagh-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.239" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01100"><p>In view of the Leader's comments, does Senator Ardagh wish to withdraw her amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01200"><p>I will withdraw it on the basis that the Minister will attend the House today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01300"><p>I cannot guarantee that, as the Minister will be present for two hours to deal with a particular issue, but I would be happy to try to arrange for the Minister to attend during this or next week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01400"><p>I thank the Leader.  That is perfect.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.244" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01500"><p>May I apologise to the Leas-Chathaoirleach-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01600"><p>No, the Senator is out of order.  I am taking the proposed amendments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01700"><p>-----for being awkward earlier?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01800"><p>The Senator has already spoken.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD01900"><p>I thank the Leader for inviting the Taoiseach to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02000"><p>The Senator had his opportunity.  Now, quiet.  Senator Murnane O'Connor has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 11, non-Government motion 6 be taken today."  What did the Leader say about this one?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02100"><p>I am happy to accept it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02200"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell has proposed an amendment to the Order of Business, "That No. 11, non-Government motion 2, be taken before No. 1."  Is that agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02300"><p>I am agreeable to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02400"><p>The love that dare not speak its name has agreed to pursue-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02500"><p>The Leader is accepting it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02600"><p>He is accepting it.  That is great.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.257" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>(Interruptions).</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02800"><p>Hold on.  I want to clarify.  No. 2 is to be taken before No. 1.  Is that agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD02900"><p>I am happy for us to work collectively in the spirit of both motions.  I was of the understanding that we had agreed a roadmap.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD03000"><p>Is the amendment agreed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD03100"><p>I will offer some clarity.  I will withdraw my amendment on the understanding that the committee called for by my colleagues is set up and the first issue on its agenda is a timeline.  I will not engage in a talking shop.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD03200"><p>That is a matter for the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD03300"><p>Absolutely.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD03400"><p>Is the Leader happy with the withdrawal of the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD03500"><p>Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.266" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD03600"><p>When will the motion be taken?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#DD03700"><p>Tuesday.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#EE00100"><p>The Leader has just agreed to take it today.  Is it after the next item?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#EE00200"><p>Yes, after the next item.  For the information of the House, we are agreeing to the amendment to the Order of Business on the basis that we can pursue that motion at a later time.  It will not be taken today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1420" speakername="Paul Coghlan" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#EE00300"><p>It has to be taken today.  The Leader said it will be taken at the conclusion of No. 1, so the motion will be taken then.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#EE00400"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.273" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.274" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#EE00600">Proceeds of Crime (Amendment) Bill 2016: Order for Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.275" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p></p><p></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1391" speakername="Jerry Buttimer" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#EE00800"><p>I move: "That Second Stage be taken today."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.277" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.278" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#EE01000">Proceeds of Crime (Amendment) Bill 2016: Second Stage</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.279" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question proposed: "That the Bill be now read a Second Time."</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1214" speakername="Frances Fitzgerald" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2016070500002#EE01200"><p>Twenty years ago, when a fearless journalist told the truth about vicious gangsters and paid for it with her life, these Houses, the Government and the agencies of the State responded swiftly, effectively and in a spirit of unity.  Veronica Guerin's murder by ruthless men marked a very dark hour in the life of this country, an enduring loss for her family and friends and an important turning point in the fight against crime.  Six weeks after her murder, the Proceeds of Crime Act 1996 was enacted and two months after that the Criminal Assets Bureau Act was passed.  In doing that, these Houses developed an innovative model for depriving gangsters and murderers of the proceeds of their crimes.</p> <p>The Irish model is one that has been studied and copied by some countries, and envied by many that have not done so.  In the intervening period, the Criminal Assets Bureau, CAB, has retrieved hundreds of millions of euro in proceeds of crime, unpaid taxes and fraudulently obtained welfare payments.  It has been so successful that it has driven some gang leaders overseas, leaving only their accomplices here to run their day-to-day drugs businesses.  We have now reached another turning point.  Those subordinates of the offshore drug barons have brought murder to our streets in an appalling way in recent months.  We must respond, and we are doing that.  We, as the State, the Parliament, the Government, law enforcement agencies and communities, will stand together to face down those who would put themselves above the law and above the lives of others.  Their motivation is greed for wealth, and we will do all we can to deprive them of their wealth.</p> <p>I and my officials met the Garda Commissioner, the chief of the Criminal Assets Bureau and other senior officers to examine what further measures could be taken to pressurise and deal with the lower-level gang activity taking place.  Five weeks ago, I secured the agreement of the Government to a package of measures to increase the pressure on organised criminals.  That package includes the establishment of a special crime task force by the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, in co-operation with the Revenue Commissioners and the Department of Social Protection.  The task force will focus relentlessly on persons involved in gangland activities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2016-07-05a.281" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>