<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.1" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 10:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.4" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#A00100">Gnó an tSeanaid - Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from the following Senators that they propose to raise the following matters on the Commencement of the Seanad:</p><p>Senator Seery Kearney:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Justice to provide increased funding to ensure the deployment of appropriate numbers of garda&iacute; in communities in light of the escalating anti-social behaviour in Cherry Orchard in Dublin. </blockquote> <p>Senator Paul Gavan:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Foreign Affairs to make a statement on the continuing deaths of migrants in the Mediterranean and Aegean seas. </blockquote> <p>Senator Barry Ward:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Finance to make a statement on the Central Bank's current definition of a first-time buyer under its mortgage lending rules. </blockquote> <p>Senator Joe O'Reilly:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage to make a statement on whether changes and improvements to the guidelines and regulations concerning house design, site layout and density would assist in the provision of additional housing units. </blockquote> <p>Senator Maria Byrne:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the T&aacute;naiste and Minister for Enterprise, Trade and Employment to make a statement on the supports available to encourage businesses to increase energy efficiency. </blockquote> <p>Senator Martin Conway:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Health to make a statement on his plans to roll out a public information campaign to ensure the correct use of the emergency services numbers.  </blockquote> <p>Senator Lynn Boylan:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for the Environment, Climate and Communications to make a statement on fossil fuel advertising and sponsorships. </blockquote> <p>Senator Malcolm Byrne:</p> <blockquote> 	The need for the Minister for Tourism, Culture, Arts, Gaeltacht, Sport and Media to make a statement on the Government's strategy to develop film and television production in Ireland. </blockquote> <p>The matters raised by the Senators are suitable for discussion.  I have selected Senators Seery Kearney, Gavan, Ward and O'Reilly and they will be taken now.  The other Senators may give notice on another day of the matters that they wish to raise.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.7" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#B00200">Nithe i dtosach suíonna - Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.8" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#B00250">Antisocial Behaviour</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#B00300"><p>I welcome the Minister for Justice to the House and thank her for taking time out of her busy schedule in her busy Department to take the first matter, which is a very important topic and which was debated in the House only yesterday and on Tuesday.  I ask Senator Seery Kearney to commence the debate.  The Senator has four minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#B00400"><p>I thank the Minister.  I appreciate her coming here in person.  It shows her commitment, the response that she has made all week and the commitment that is there for the community in Cherry Orchard.</p> <p>We have seen the videos online of what happened and they are horrific.  I want to begin by condemning the actions against the two garda&iacute; who went in there.  They were treated in the most disgraceful and dangerous way and that is appalling.  I express concern for them.</p> <p>I have been working with community groups in the Cherry Orchard area for quite some time.  When one first meets the groups, they will point over to the shadow of the prison walls.  Within that community, one is looking over at a huge wall of a prison.  One is looking into a community that has one shop that is the ground floor of a converted house.  It is not even is a purpose-built shop.  There are no main facilities.  There is the beacon of light that is the St. Ultan's school and a complex and they have childcare.  They have a whole heap of supports that are extraordinary and the people there are extraordinary.  There is the work of the equestrian centre and the youth justice programme that is there.  However, they are all working in a situation with the garda&iacute; who are based in Ballyfermot Garda station to try at all times to support that community against what is a small minority of organised criminals working in that area and controlling much of what occurs in the area.</p> <p>People show great initiative.  They go out and they work.  Some I have spoken to who have bricks through their windows when they take the initiative in their community, for example, when they get concerned and go out and clear the playground of drug paraphernalia.  They experience repercussion.  They experience intimidation as a consequence of that.</p> <p>I wrote to the Minister earlier in the year when we were drawing together a group of all the public representatives for the community and I was given a reasonably comprehensive and impressive policing plan and told of meetings, etc., that were going on.  I appreciate that the narrative and, quite probably, the truth is that it was retaliation for action by the Garda over the weekend that there was this sudden display of arrogance and contempt for the rule of law but one car coming from Ballyfermot Garda station with two female officers into what was clearly a frightening situation stands in marked contrast to the policing plan that I saw earlier in the year.</p> <p>According to the discussions I have had on the ground, there are inadequate resources and yet we have a Commissioner who believes that there are adequate resources.  I suppose there is a disconnect between the perception in Garda management and the reality and experience on the ground.  We need bespoke responses for communities that already feel marginalised, on the edge of society and forgotten and that fear we are losing youth workers.  I appreciate that is bigger than the Department.  As I said, I will come back to it.  We need a cross-departmental task force to respond.</p> <p>In terms of increased funding this year, they were invited to apply for the Garda youth diversion fund.  They got &euro;45,000, which on any day is a good result, but they need a great deal more than that.  They need even more resources.  I ask for a concerted effort to treat this in the same way that we have other intervention programmes and to dramatically intervene here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.11" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#B00500"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  As the Senator said, it is not the first time she has raised this.  Obviously, this is an ongoing concern for members of the community.</p> <p>If I could, I will start by supporting the Senator in condemning what happened the other evening.  It is utterly unacceptable that any community should have to put up with this kind of behaviour, as the Senator said, on their doorsteps where people go to work, where children play and where people live, but it is also not acceptable that members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na, who are just doing their best to keep people safe, would be attacked in this kind of way.  I want to convey my best wishes to both members of An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na following what they went through.  I wish them well.</p> <p>We will always support communities affected by anti-social behaviour and this type of behaviour.  I want to be clear to those who are responsible, irrespective of what age they are and irrespective of other issues that are going on and, obviously, the wider response that is needed, that it cannot and will not be tolerated.  The Garda is working closely with the local team on the ground and with the community to make sure that those who are responsible are caught and that there are repercussions.</p> <p>Some people said during the week there is no point in asking people to come forward or go to the Garda because they are afraid but if garda&iacute; do not have the information that they need when this type of behaviour and activity happens, they cannot do their job.  There are confidential ways in which people can come forward and I would appeal to members of the community if there is information that they have to come forward so that we can respond to this effectively.</p> <p>Separately, I have asked the Garda Commissioner to look at what more we can do on anti-social behaviour, to look at the laws that we have and how they are being implemented, and to look at progress that is being made, be it in the area of scramblers or the whole-of-community response.  That is something he is already doing on which he will come back to me.  It is not specific to Cherry Orchard but part of a wider discussion around anti-social behaviour that we must have.</p> <p>It is important to stress, as the Senator outlined, that it has not been felt but there was, based on many concerns that the Senator and others have raised, an increased presence in the area.  There have been a number of operations in the area.  In particular Operation Pr&eacute;ach&aacute;n, which started in the late summer, has resulted in seven people being arrested only in the past few weeks and brought before the courts with strict bail conditions.  There were curfews in place on some of the individuals.  It is that type of policing that we need to see continue.  It is that type of clear determined response that the community need to see happening and continue on an ongoing basis.</p> <p>There is support from the public order unit for the Dublin Metropolitan Region and many of the other policing units but I appreciate, and I will take the feedback that the Senator is giving me, that people are perhaps not seeing it as much on the ground even though there has been an increased presence and an increased number of garda&iacute; for the area, not only since Monday but over the past number of months in response to some of the concerns that the Senator and others in the community have been raising.  I have been given a commitment from the local chief superintendent, Chief Superintendent Murphy, that his increase in resources will continue until this issue is addressed.</p> <p>This is symptomatic of a wider societal problem.  The Senator outlined that there was one shop in the area and few resources.  For a community of this size, it is not adequate.  We all need to respond collectively, not only a criminal justice response but working with the community.  There are fantastic members in the community.  Dublin City Council has a regeneration plan for the area.  We need to get that up and running.  We need to have the full support of Dublin City Council, of the justice sector and the local Garda, but also the community.  That is something that I am working to bring together.  I will work with Senator Seery Kearney and others to make sure that that happens.</p> <p>I will outline - and I can give the figures to the Senator - the youth justice strategy to which she referred.  The overall funding trebled last year and there was an increase of &euro;6.7 million provided through the Minister of State, Deputy James Browne.  That has allowed us to significantly expand on the types of resources and the programmes that are there to try to get to the root of things and stop it from getting to the point of scenes such as we saw on Monday last.</p> <p>Specifically, for this area, there was approximately &euro;300,000 last year.  There is &euro;148,000 for two full-time youth justice workers and one part-time project manager.  In June, there was additional funding of more than &euro;92,000 for a family support worker and one new early intervention worker.  The Cherry Orchard Developing Youth, CODY, which is in Cherry Orchard, received further funding of almost &euro;63,000.  That is specifically to work with young people involved in the anti-social use of scramblers and quad-bikes and related crime.  These type of projects take time.  It is not an overnight fix.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->However, the more investment like that we can have, the more we will get to people at a younger age and the better it is for them and, most importantly, for the community.</p><p>It is important to look at it from two aspects: the community response and how to support the community in the wider picture, and also the Garda and its response.  I assure the Senator there will be an increased presence.  The Garda will continue to do the work it has been doing.  It will make it very clear that this type of behaviour is not acceptable but, also, that where crimes are being committed there are repercussions and that people are held responsible.  I will continue to work very closely with Senator Carey as we try to respond in the most effective way possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#C00200"><p>We will get my name right one of these days.  I thank the Minister for that response.  With the Minister of State, Deputy Browne, I visited the youth justice programme there which was extraordinarily creative through Covid when it had to go out to meet young people.  It had to change how it engaged with young people who were used to either visiting the centre and then did not want people coming to their homes.  The programme was creative in working with the youth.  Certainly, putting considerable resources into that would be very important because we need to give the young people that can get attracted to crime an alternative.  It is very attractive to be a somebody in certain cohorts and to be supplied with jackets and runners.  Mothers have spoken to me about how they combat that.  They are working two or three jobs to try to combat the attraction for their young people.  It is very important that we combat that in a very intentional way.  We have been talking about the Minister coming down to visit the area.  I know all of that is in train and I am very grateful.  I am anxious to progress that and work, in particular, with the parish priest there, Fr. Michael Murtagh, who has been very good.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#C00300"><p>I thank the Senator for the invitation.  I will be in the area to respond and meet with the Senator, others and the community.  This needs to be a holistic and long-term response.  It cannot just be overnight and in the coming weeks.</p> <p>The Senator touched on a longer-term and wider issue which is organised crime.  People are preying on young people because they can give them nice things and show them a life that they think is wonderful which really leads them down only one path which is to prison that the Senator mentioned or even worse.  I hope to publish legislation in the coming weeks on which we have been working around the coercion of minors, to try to prevent younger people being captured into this life which is very difficult to get out of.  It means that communities such as this are in a constant spiral of never being able to get out.  It is part of the wider problem with which we need to deal.  Obviously I look forward to working with the Senator on that legislation and making sure we can progress it.  I thank the Senator for raising this issue and I look forward to meeting with her and members of the community in the coming week or so.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.15" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#C00450">European Union</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#C00500"><p>I am very pleased that the Minister has come in because I have raised some of these issues before with her in the previous D&aacute;il.  I am delighted she is here and I thank her being here.</p><p>Six Syrian migrants, including three children, died from thirst and hunger last week while trying to cross the Mediterranean Sea to Europe.  The children were aged just one, two and 12.  They had drifted at sea for days before eventually being picked up by a merchant ship and taken to Sicily.  More than 1,200 people have died at sea in the Mediterranean this year, adding to the tally of 25,000 deaths since 2014.  Of course, that figure of 1,200 is most likely a significant underestimate of the true figure, as many human beings undertake these journeys and simply disappear without trace.</p><p>According to the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, UNHCR, these deaths are a direct result of the EU's decision to prioritise border security over sea rescue and says that the EU has abdicated its responsibility to ensure search and rescue in the Mediterranean and that no EU ships actively patrol anywhere near where most boats enter distress.</p><p>What is even more disturbing is the EU decision to effectively outsource search and rescue to a group of bandits and criminals who go by the name of the Libyan Coast Guard.  I have raised that issue with the Minister before.  The role of the Libyan Coast Guard is not to save people but, rather, to round them up, push them back and incarcerate them where they are subject to murder, extortion, torture, rape and slavery.  A UN Human Rights Council investigation has found that the Libyan Coast Guard has been involved in &quot;the commission of serious violations, abuses and crimes, including crimes against humanity and war crimes, against the most vulnerable&quot;.  If the Minister has taken the time to read the book by the award-winning Irish journalist, Sally Hayden, entitled <i>My Fourth Time, We Drowned</i>, she will already know all of this and, yet, the EU is happy to continue to train and fund this so-called coast guard.</p><p>The same EU governments and institutions have largely turned a blind eye to unlawful and dangerous push backs of boats to Turkey by Greece in the Aegean Sea.  These push backs by the Greek authorities have resulted in 513 separate cases being filed at the European Court of Human Rights.  A host of well-respected human rights NGOs have declared that Greece is involved with push backs, including the UNHCR, the committee for the prevention of torture, the International Organization of Migration, the UN special rapporteur, Mary Lawlor, who is another fine Irish woman, and the Working Group on Arbitrary Detention, to name just a few.</p><p>Numerous harrowing videos available on social media show masked men on boats, that are clearly identifiable as Hellenic coast guard police, involved in push backs involving terror and violence.  Last Monday, I directly challenged the Greek minister for migration, Notis Mitarachi, during a committee meeting of the Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe, PACE, that I chaired.  His response was to declare all of this evidence and testimonies to be, &quot;fake news&quot;.  Who does that remind the Minister of?</p><p>Another very sinister development is the criminalisation of human rights defenders across Europe.  Human rights defenders and journalists who have been involved in providing humanitarian assistance to migrants and asylum seekers are the main targets of persistent acts of harassment and intimidation.  Sarah Mardini, the Syrian competitive swimmer who was hailed as a hero for saving refugees when she swam out to sea to save a boat and pulled it back to shore, is among dozens of humanitarian workers in Greece facing charges that could see them imprisoned for decades.  Indeed, an Irishman, Se&aacute;n Binder, is facing up to 25 years in jail if convicted of espionage and other charges for the crime of trying to save lives in the territorial waters of Greece.  Human Rights Watch has likened these court actions to putting life saving on trial.</p><p>The Government is in a unique position to make a difference here.  Our Government holds the presidency of the committee of ministers at the Council of Europe, which will be addressed by the Minister of State, Thomas Byrne, the week after next.  Will the Government make a clear call for the EU to urgently increase search-and-rescue missions to save lives?  Will it condemn the ongoing EU support for the disgraced Libyan Coast Guard?  Will the Minister clearly call for an end to push backs by the Greek Government and, indeed, all governments?  Will the Government condemn the criminalisation of human-rights defenders?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#C00600"><p>My colleague sends his apologies for not being able to be here but I am pleased to be able to take this matter.  The Government recognises and the Minister, in particular, has argued that the migration crisis confronting Europe is a major challenge that needs to be urgently addressed.  It is not a straightforward fix but something on which we need to get a handle.  Otherwise, the ordinary men, women and, indeed, babies and children about which the Senator just spoke, will continue to die making these dangerous crossings into the EU, including the Mediterranean and Aegean seas.</p> <p>The terrible events in Ukraine have shown us that the need to flea can arise anywhere in the world.  Migration is not just something that happens to other parts of the world, but it does indeed have wide-ranging causes and effects and can impact anyone, anywhere.  The world currently faces an unprecedented series of humanitarian crises such as the food-security crisis which is indeed exasperated by Russia's aggression against Ukraine.  These, in addition to longer-standing issues of poverty, instability and lack of opportunity, leave many people feeling that their only choice is to leave their home and risk perilous journeys to what they hope will be a better life.  These journeys all too often end in tragedy.</p> <p>Ireland has consistently stated that it believes migration should be safe, orderly and regular and we are absolutely committed to the global compact for safe, orderly and regular migration which was agreed in the UN in 2018.  This followed on from the New York Declaration for Refugees and Migrants, co-facilitated by Ireland in 2016, where UN member states recognised the need for a comprehensive approach to human mobility and enhanced co-operation at the global level.  The Global Compact for Safe, Orderly and Regular Migration aims to reduce the risks and vulnerability that migrants face at different stages of migration, by respecting, protecting and fulfilling their human rights and providing them with care and assistance.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Helen McEntee:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2394"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2394&amp;amp;pid=HelenMcEntee&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->The global compact aims to reduce the risks and vulnerabilities migrants face at different stages of migration by respecting, protecting and fulfilling their human rights and providing them with care and assistance.  It also seeks to address the legitimate concerns of states and communities on the issue of migration and strives to create conducive conditions that enable all migrants to participate in and contribute to socioeconomic development.</p><p>We have consistently urged effective action at EU level.  We fully support EU efforts to deal with the migration issue comprehensively and holistically, including through resettlement and increased legal pathways for migration; addressing root causes of forced migration, which the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, has championed and stressed, particularly among our African colleagues; and reforming the common European asylum system.  We need to prevent the crossings and behaviour mentioned by the Senator by offering other solutions to people.</p><p>Migration is a huge challenge for many of our partners, including our front-line partners, some of which have been mentioned by the Senator.  They include Greece, Italy and Malta.  We have consistently urged the need for fairer burden-sharing and have stated there must be greater solidarity and responsibility on the part of all if any progress is to be made.  Progress is slow, which is extremely frustrating.   We are continuing to engage constructively in discussions on the Commission's migration pact proposals, which offer a template for the kind of collective response I have outlined and that is needed by the EU to address this crisis.</p><p>Regarding our own response, we have tried to step up wherever and whenever possible.  Since 2015, Ireland has accepted nearly 3,800 people under the Irish refugee protection programme.  The current phase will see Ireland welcome up to 2,900 people between 2020 to 2023.  This includes people who have been forced to flee Afghanistan.</p><p>Of course, we have to date also welcomed over 50,000 Ukrainians fleeing Russia's illegal war and invasion.  I have no doubt that this number will increase.</p><p>Ireland is supporting humanitarian responses worldwide with an allocation of &euro;113 million for Irish Aid's humanitarian action in 2022, including funding of &euro;24 million to the UN High Commissioner for Refugees, UNHCR.</p><p>Ireland has also provided humanitarian assistance, in solidarity with other member states, by pledging to take people rescued in the Mediterranean and to process their applications for international protection.  Where there are issues in the Mediterranean, Ireland has never been found wanting.  Where our help has been sought, we have always stepped up and made sure that help has been offered.  By way of example, we were very pleased to welcome 21 asylum seekers, transferred from Malta last year, as a gesture of solidarity and humanitarian assistance.  These actions are a vital part of upholding our responsibilities in helping those fleeing the most harrowing of circumstances, such as war and persecution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1660" speakername="Paul Gavan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#D00200"><p>I thank the Minister for the response.  I am a little disappointed because the greatest human rights scandal of the 21st century is people losing their lives in the Mediterranean and the Greek seas.  The reason they are losing their lives, according to the UNHCR, is the absence of search-and-rescue operations by governments.  I have made a clear request to the Minister this morning to make the call to increase search-and-rescue operations by governments in the EU.  Unfortunately, she has not yet said this is a clear call that the Irish Government will make.  I hope she will in her final response.</p> <p>I genuinely cannot understand, and do not believe there is any excuse for, the complete silence of the Irish Government on the EU support for the Libyan coastguard.  This is an organisation that is involved in rape, torture, murder and war crimes.  This has been detailed.  Silence is not a good enough response.  We are chairing the Council of Europe Committee of Ministers.  I want to see an Irish Minister stand up for human rights and call out these crimes, and also call on our brothers and sisters in Greece to ensure push-backs are brought to an end.  Of course, we need to see equal burden-sharing and greater support for Greece, but, above all, we need to speak up for human rights; otherwise, what is the point in our having such a high position at the committee of ministers?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1502" speakername="Helen McEntee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#D00300"><p>I utterly condemn those who are taking advantage of vulnerable people, encouraging people to cross the Mediterranean and sending people to their death.  I utterly condemn those who are mistreating those seeking help.  I stress that Ireland has always used its voice, as a small country on the periphery of what is happening, to speak up for those who need our help, encourage a more comprehensive and holistic response, and encourage burden-sharing.  We have always offered support where it is needed, be it through taking in migrants or carrying out search-and-rescue missions, and we will continue to encourage the type of response needed to protect as many people as possible.  The ultimate objective should be to get to the root cause and prevent people from crossing in the first instance.  That is something that the Minister for Foreign Affairs, Deputy Coveney, will continue to champion in his role and while we hold the Presidency of the Council of Europe.  I utterly condemn those who are mistreating people and profiteering from those who are trying to flee to safety.  We will continue to do everything we can to support and help the latter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.21" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#D00400">Regulatory Bodies</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.22" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#D00500"><p>I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, to the House.  It is good to have her here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#D00600"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the Chamber this morning.</p> <p>I absolutely recognise the need for lending control and guidelines from the Central Bank on the importance of that lending control.  We all learned an important and very hard-learned lesson over a decade ago when exactly the kind of lending we are trying to prevent allowed things to get out of control and create huge economic problems.  In raising this matter, I am in no way seeking to undermine the importance of those measures or many of the tenets of those measures.</p> <p>People will be aware that the measures I am talking about are essentially the guidelines the Central Bank issues to lenders on the extent to which borrowers can obtain mortgages.  That is specifically what I want to focus on.  Most people cannot get a mortgage for more than 80% of the value of the property being bought, which means one must have a deposit of 20% available to one.  That is the case for the vast majority of people who are second or subsequent buyers of a house, apartment or other property.  A small number of people qualify under what are called the first-time buyer criteria.  They are allowed to borrow up to 90% of the value of the property.  They are required to garner a deposit of only 10%.  Let us be in no doubt but that this is still a challenge for many, which is understandable.  In fact, I understand from my own circumstances how difficult it can be.</p> <p>That the guidelines are in place is important but the manner in which they are applied is a little inconsistent.  I agree with the 20% provision.  It exists to ensure people will have the capacity to repay their loans and not end up in default or losing their homes, which, in fairness, is uncommon in this country.  Banks complain about this but I believe the measure is important.</p> <p>In the constituency where I live, D&uacute;n Laoghaire, the average price of a home is over &euro;500,000.  Therefore, a person who has bought a one-bedroom apartment and who now needs to move out because he or she has a family must gather a deposit of over &euro;100,000.  For most, that is absolutely unattainable, certainly in the medium term.  It is an amount that you might be able to save over a decade or similar period.  However, to obtain that amount to get a mortgage is really difficult.  That is as may be, but there is an inconsistency affecting people who have to start again for some reason.  Where a relationship breaks down and one partner has to leave the family home, which might have been purchased 15 years ago, for example, the person leaving the home, who has to set up again, still has to find a 20% deposit.  Even though such people are not first-time buyers, there is a basis on which we should be saying they should qualify under the first-time buyer criteria.  Equally, where only one member of a couple owns the one-bedroom apartment in which they live, the other member is denied the opportunity to be a first-time buyer if they decide to buy a family home together.</p> <p>This may be a busy week for officials working in the Department of Finance but I suggest that as we consider the crisis facing young people buying homes in Ireland today, we should be flexible in applying the lending rules, where appropriate.  Very often, there are people who cannot buy homes or afford to get a mortgage, with all the difficulties that come with that.  Even though they are not technically regarded as first-time buyers under the criteria, they should still qualify.  That they do not is a major obstacle for them.  I ask the Department to consider the guidelines, work with the Central Bank and state that while first-time buyers are first-time buyers, there are other categories of people, including those who have to start again and those whose relationships may have broken down, who should also be considered.  Someone in a relationship with a first-time buyer should not be discommoded by the status of that person.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Barry Ward:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=BarryWard&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We should consider having some flexibility of those limits to allow greater access to the mortgage market for some buyers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#E00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this issue.  I am taking this on behalf of the Minister for Finance as he is taking oral questions in the D&aacute;il at present.</p> <p>In February 2015, the Central Bank of Ireland, in line with its mandate to protect and safeguard financial stability, first put in place new macro-prudential measures for residential mortgage lending.  These measures apply proportionate loan-to-value and loan-to-income limits to mortgage lending by regulated financial service providers in the Irish market.  The key objective of these measures is to increase the resilience of the banking and household sectors to the property market and to reduce the risk of bank credit and house price spirals from developing in the future.  This is of particular significance for Ireland given that mortgage lending constitutes a large part of overall bank lending.</p> <p>These macro-prudential measures apply certain loan-to-value, LTV, and loan-to-income, LTI, restrictions to residential mortgage lending by financial institutions regulated by the Central Bank.  At present, the maximum mortgage limits are 3.5 times the borrower's income and, for first-time buyers, 90% of the value of the residential property.  For second and subsequent buyers the maximum mortgage limits are 3.5 times the borrower's income and 80% of the value of the residential property, as the Senator mentioned.</p> <p>However, banks and other regulated lenders also have a limited flexibility to provide a mortgage loan in excess of the specified regulatory limits at their discretion.  For example, in respect of first-time buyers, up to 5% of lending to such borrowers may exceed the LTV cap of 90%, while up to 20% of lending may exceed the LTI cap of 3.5 times the borrower's income.  For second and subsequent buyers, up to 20% of lending to such borrowers may exceed the LTV cap of 80%, while up to 10% of lending may exceed the LTI cap of 3.5 times the borrower's income.</p> <p>The Central Bank has indicated that these lending measures have contributed to an improvement in the credit quality of new mortgage loans by guarding against a return to lending at high LTI and LTV ratios, such as those observed in the past.  The Central Bank is the macro prudential authority for Ireland and has the lead responsibility for safeguarding and protecting financial stability.  This in addition to its responsibility for the prudential supervision of individual financial service firms and the protection of consumers.  The power to make regulations for the proper and effective regulation of financial service providers, including macro prudential measures to control lending by such institutions, is provided for in the Central Bank Act of 2013 and that is the power utilised by the Central Bank to set out the mortgage lending rules.  Therefore, the various lending thresholds and detailed aspects of the lending rules is an independent matter for the Central Bank.</p> <p>Since their introduction, the Central Bank has kept the rules under regular review and has made a number of adjustments from time to time.  However, the bank has come to the view that it is now time for a more comprehensive review of the mortgage measures framework to ensure the measures continue to remain fit for purpose in light of changes to our financial system and economy since they were first introduced.  This comprehensive review is ongoing and will assess the objectives of the mortgage measures and whether they remain appropriate.  The review will also consider the tools that are used and the factors taken into account when setting their levels.  It is expected that the Central Bank will conclude its review before the end of this year.  I will let the Senator come in and I will continue with my response later.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#E00300"><p>I totally understand the week before the budget is not a good time for officials or Ministers in the Department of Finance, therefore, I have no difficulty with the fact that the Minister could not be here.</p> <p>I recognise what the Central Bank said about the improvement in the credit quality of new mortgage loans by guarding against a return to lending at high loan-to-income and loan-to-value rates, such as those observed in the past.  I recognised the importance of the limits and the Minister of State kindly acknowledged that as well.  I do not have an issue with the LTI provisions.  What I am saying is that the 20% deposit is insurmountable for many people.  I am delighted about the decision of the Central Bank to do a more comprehensive review of this.  While the bank is right that it has led to an improvement in credit standards and quality, it has also led to a situation where many young people, those coming out of relationships that have broken down, find it incredibly difficult if not impossible to obtain a mortgage for a home, be it a first or a second home.</p> <p>In raising this matter in the House - I think the Minister of State has acknowledged this and the Central Bank is probably aware of it, to one extent or another - I am asking for great flexibility and that people in certain categories should not be locked out of the mortgage market as they are de facto at present.  I hope the Central Bank review, which it will conduct in a comprehensive fashion, will bring about a change of mind in respect of some lenders.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#E00400"><p>I must acknowledge the comprehensive response provided by the Department of Finance.  It shows the flexibility and willingness of the Central Bank to engage and its openness, through the consultation period and the review, in recognition of changes in circumstances and different needs of people as well as the make-up of families.  I will take that back to the Minister and I thank the Senator for raising this matter.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.28" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#E00500">Housing Policy</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#E00600"><p>I welcome the Minister to the House.  The matter I raise is a continuation of a similar theme.  Getting the maximum number of people housed is the issue.</p> <p>Housing for All, the Government's multi-annual, multi-euro programme, is aimed at improving Ireland's housing system and delivering more homes for all types of people with all types of housing needs.  We are all aware in this House that housing policy is undergoing a period of immense reform.  We are also in agreement that such reform is necessary to prevent the housing crisis from being exacerbated in the years ahead.</p> <p>Few would disagree that Ireland's planning system is excessively complicated and burdensome.  In fact, it is for that very reason that my colleague, the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, is setting out to reduce the legal red tape that is hindering the construction industry's ability to accelerate the development of thousands of new homes.  I call on him to continue the acceleration of that process, which I know he will do.  One must condemn nimbyism in these Chambers.  Everyone must see the bigger picture in these times of difficulty.</p> <p>To develop more much-needed housing, it is essential that our planning system is aligned with the Government's housing delivery objectives.  It is imperative that we get this right.  We can have the best intentions, but if the practical implementation of current planning guidelines make certain developments unviable, that needs to be examined.  A key goal in both the national planning framework and the national development plan is the compact growth of cities and towns in a way that creates more attractive places to live and work, preventing urban sprawl.  We have all heard the anecdotes of apartment developments that have been granted planning permission but are not being built because they are unviable.  A strong case can be made for the construction of apartment buildings in our cities - I believe they should be higher but we will come back to that later - and much less of a case can be made for those same units being built outside of our cities.  This is the difficulty faced in some of our commuter towns.  We are building apartments to adhere to the planning density regulations but demand is not there for those apartments.  The apartments cost an average of &euro;450,000 to build compared with &euro;300,000 for a house.  Therefore, there is the whole issue of unviability that needs to be looked at.</p> <p>In some instances, apartments are being built in suburban developments not because they are attractive to owner-occupiers, but because they are necessary to bring developments in line with planning density regulations.  Without them, developments would not reach the required density and, therefore, we need imaginative responses.  We need smaller houses based on the continental model.  Family size and cultures change and that should be reflected in housing size, without going at it radically.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Joe O'Reilly:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=1610"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1610&amp;amp;pid=JoeOReilly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->More supply is the only way to meet the high level of demand that exists for housing.  We need to examine ways to introduce a more streamlined planning approval process with a set timetable on the part of An Bord Plean&aacute;la and to take measures to address the current backlog of planning appeals.  The current practice is bizarre.  Does the Minister of State, on behalf of the Minister, believe that changes to planning guidelines and regulations concerning house design, site layout and density would assist in the availability of housing?  It comes down to increasing planning system efficiency to increase availability.  </p><p>I have other points but in the last minute I will come back to the review under way in the Department.  How is that progressing?  We must look at the whole design, the green areas in front of houses, more allotments for individual families, as well as smaller pitches perhaps, that is, the complex changes there that would utilise space better.  I look forward to the Minister of State&rsquo;s response.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#F00200"><p>I thank Senator O'Reilly for raising this matter.  I am answering on behalf of the Minister of State at the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, Deputy Peter Burke.  The compact growth of cities and towns of all sizes to create more attractive places in which people can live and work is a key objective of the national planning framework, NPF.  The Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage is in the process of developing sustainable and compact settlement guidelines, SCSGs, for planning authorities under section 28 of the Planning and Development Act.  The SCSGs will supersede current section 28 ministerial guidelines for planning authorities on sustainable residential development in urban areas and the sustainable residential development guidelines last issued in 2009.  The SCSGs will also supplement other relevant guidelines such as the sustainable urban housing design standards for new apartment guidelines for planning authorities of 2020, as well as the urban development and building heights guidelines for planning authorities of 2018.  A working group was convened in June 2022 to work through key issues.  The working group included representation from the construction industry, private built environment practitioners, professional bodies and the public sector.  The group, via a series of workshops in June, August and September 2022 discussed the interrelated issues of density, viability, land use, transportation, place-making and quality design.  This included general discussion in regard to housing standards and the potential for new and more compact housing typologies seen in other countries at suitable locations in Ireland.  Following completion, the draft guidelines will be placed on display for a focused period of public consultation.  This is targeted for quarter 4 of 2022.  All interested parties will have an opportunity to make submissions on the guidelines at that stage.  Submissions made during the public consultation period will be reviewed and where appropriate and necessary, amendments will be made to the published draft.  The guidelines will then be submitted for approval and publication by the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage.  Once published planning authorities and An Bord Plean&aacute;la will be required to have regard to the guidelines in carrying out their functions.</p> <p>That is the Minister's response but if I could, in the allotted time, as Minister of State with responsibility for disability, I would like a moment to build on that.  When we talk about the guidelines I hope that people from the disability community would also participate in the consultation.  It is important to discuss universal design and accessibility.  When we talk about the various models and standardisation of the houses, within that we should also have the standardisation of houses that would be suitable for persons with disabilities and their various needs to be incorporated.  They would be part of the overall plan for living within their communities.  The motto of people with disabilities, &ldquo;nothing about us without us&rdquo;, should also pertain to the development of how we look at developing our Housing for All strategy to ensure everybody in the community has a right to access housing.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1692" speakername="Joe O'Reilly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#F00300"><p>I could not agree more with the Minister of State's latter comments.  The current guidelines came into operation in 1999.  They have not been updated since 2009.  That makes the review and updating of them very urgent.  I am happy to note that there is commitment to immediate progress.  We should be looking more at modular homes.  We should look at timber-framed homes and at building up in the cities.  Look at the situation on the Continent.  We can build up in the cities in a way that is beautiful and intelligent.  We have to become creative and imaginative because we cannot have people unhoused and almost fiddle while Rome burns.  We must act in a proactive way to deal with this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#F00400"><p>The national planning framework sets out the vision and strategic objectives to support Ireland's national, regional and local spatial development in economic, environmental and social terms to 2040.  The delivery of increased supply of sustainable, affordable homes for people is an integral part of this vision and remains the Government's top priority.  The sustainable and compact settlement guidelines currently being developed by the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage, the draft of which will be published by the end of the year, will support this increase in housing supply while also supporting the development of sustainable and amenable neighbourhoods that promote a high quality of life for residents.  The significant potential for new housing typologies to meet the need of Ireland's diverse household types has been recognised and officials from the Department will continue to explore these issues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.34" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 11.26 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 12.02 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 11.26 a.m. and resumed at 12.02 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.35" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#K00100">An tOrd Gnó - Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#K00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding the arrangements for the sitting of the House on Tuesday, 27 September 2022, to be taken on conclusion of the Order of Business, without debate; and No. 2, statements on new innovations for people with disabilities (digital assistive technology), to be taken at 1.15 p.m. and to conclude at 2.45 p.m., if not previously concluded, with the opening contribution of the Minister of State not to exceed ten minutes, those of group spokespersons not to exceed seven minutes and all other Senators not to exceed four minutes, and the Minister of State to be given no less than five minutes to reply to the debate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1643" speakername="Lorraine Clifford-Lee" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#K00300"><p>I wish to refer to the war in Ukraine.  We are seven months into the conflict.  I will focus on the sexual violence perpetrated on the women and children of Ukraine.  We know sexual violence is a recognised weapon of war.  There has not been much discussion in Ireland around this aspect of the war but we really need to have a conversation about it.  Rape is recognised as a weapon of war.  It spreads disease, destroys family ties, inflicts harm on generations and is used to terrorise, humiliate and subdue a population.  It also reinforces gender inequalities and normalises sexual violence even after the conflict has ended.</p> <p>Using sexual violence as a weapon surged after the wars in the former Yugoslavia and the genocide in Rwanda in the 1990s.  We know it has been used in a number of conflicts across the globe such as those in Sierra Leone, the Democratic Republic of the Congo, Colombia, Guatemala, Peru, Uganda and South Sudan, and against Yazidi women and we know it is happening in Ukraine as well.  Reports have started to emerge from liberated towns such as Bucha.</p> <p>Last week, I met with other parliamentarians in the Basque country to discuss this topic.  We met two amazingly brave Ukrainian MPs who gave some really harrowing details of what is emerging from various towns and villages across Ukraine.  It is really shocking.  Survivors of war-time rape internationally have reported long-term physical and mental injuries.  There are children born of rape in conflict zones.  This often leads to continuous family conflict, domestic violence and an intergenerational impact on the fabric of that society and the identity of a nation.</p> <p>To mitigate the long-term impact of rape in conflict zones, survivors need access to emergency contraception, abortion care, mental health supports and medical care for physical injuries.  We need to talk about rape as a weapon of war so that Ireland and other countries who are supporting Ukraine as its people fight to protect their country against Putin provide this level of support for the survivors of sexual violence in Ukraine.  We also need to support survivors by recognising the harm done to them and helping to dispel any stigma and shame associated with sexual violence in a conflict zone.  </p> <p>The conversation regarding the prosecution of war crimes in Ukraine has started and a number of people have been convicted.  However, war-time rape is very rarely prosecuted and when it is, it is very hard to secure a conviction.  I would like to see Ireland take a leadership role to ensure that more of these crimes are investigated and prosecuted, and convictions secured.  I would also like a debate in the Chamber with the Minister for Foreign Affairs on sexual violence as a weapon of war in Ukraine.  I urge the Minister to ensure our aid budget has an element of targeted support ring fenced to help survivors get the healthcare they need in a timely fashion and that Ireland uses all its diplomatic power to ensure that war criminals are pursued and prosecuted, and the rape perpetrated on the women and children of Ukraine is dealt with.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#K00400"><p>I rise today because I am quite concerned about many of the projects funded by Pobal and the various local development companies with regard to the rising costs faced by people who have been able to secure funding and grants.  As we all know, a grant could be issued and approved for somebody two years in advance but by the time builders get around to commencing the work, it could take 18 months to two years.  There is significant cost inflation so if somebody was approved for &euro;100,000 two years ago, that sum will only go so far.</p> <p>I am calling for a debate on cost inflation and its effect on community groups, small businesses and people who have secured funding who wish to develop businesses.  I hope we will see a flexible approach with Pobal because it has been brought to my attention not just in County Clare but throughout the country, that letters have issued telling people that they need to draw down the funding by the end of the year and meet the exact specifications of the grant for which they applied in terms of what is being spent.  Flexibility is needed in that regard.</p> <p>I also want a debate here at some stage on Taiwan.  I know we have had all-party motions on Taiwan over the years but given what is happening in Ukraine, we need to open an embassy in Taipei and establish full diplomatic engagement with Taiwan.  We saw what happened over the summer with Nancy Pelosi travelling to Taiwan, which was a great boost for what is a wonderful, vibrant independent country.  We should have a debate on Taiwan at some stage but what really needs to happen is for Ireland to stand shoulder to shoulder with Taiwan and open an embassy there and for the Taiwanese Government to open an embassy in Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#L00100"><p>Yesterday, we had a debate on the issue of search and rescue procurement.  Most of those who spoke agreed that there were questions to be answered and called on the Minister of State to answer them.  The Minister of State was aware of the questions I have been asking since August.  I asked them on the floor of the House yesterday because they needed to be asked.  The Minister of State was not coming in to be surprised by me or anybody else.  I say to everybody that when we allow Ministers to come before the House to provide answers that are vague, to not answer the questions that were asked or to leave themselves in a position where they are unable to say, like most good teachers would say, that they are sorry they cannot answer the question but will answer it tomorrow, we debase ourselves and the very Parliament to which we were elected.  We debase the role of the Oireachtas.  We make a nonsense out of democracy.  It is no wonder that people ask why we have the Seanad.</p> <p>I found the way I was treated in the House yesterday deeply insulting.  I do not blame the Leader, the Cathaoirleach or anybody else.  The Minister of State came here with a prepared speech written by bureaucrats who were then not present in the House when she delivered it.  They assumed they knew what would be asked or wrote a speech that was so vague it covered everything and nothing at the same time.</p> <p>There is no getting away from the fact that the Department is planning to do away with the Irish Aviation Authority regulation of having 12-hour shifts only and move to 24-hour shifts.  There is no getting away from the conflict of interest.  There is no getting away from any of the questions that were asked.  I will be writing to every Member of the Oireachtas and providing transcripts of yesterday's proceedings.  I will also write to the Committees on Parliamentary Privileges and Oversight of both Houses.  If we continue to allow both Houses to be treated in the way they have been treated and if we are going to allow committees to be dismissed by senior civil servants, then we may all pack up our bags, go home and forget about it because we are wasting our time.  It is public money that is being spent.  It is the public interest we are here to protect.  I feel deeply insulted.</p> <p>I thank everybody who spoke yesterday.  Nobody jumped for joy or tore anybody apart.  Only one Member of the House did not agree with the need for questions, and that is his right.  Ultimately, everybody asked for the answers to the questions that have been asked for a long enough.  I will leave it at that.  We need to look at ourselves.  There needs to be a coming together of politicians in the House.  It is so easy to have a crack at government for the hell of it but we are all in this.  Members in opposition today could be in government tomorrow and they should remember this.  We should all stand together when we see a cause worth standing for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#L00200"><p>The House is not responsible for the answers given here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1645" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#L00300"><p>I appreciate that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1659" speakername="R&oacute;is&iacute;n Garvey" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#L00400"><p>I want to highlight an issue that comes to mind again and again.  We all know there is a housing crisis and a housing emergency.  We struggle in areas such as Clare as we look for water infrastructure so we can build housing estates in our towns and villages.  We look at the cost of building houses, builders struggling to get materials and people struggling to find the money to build houses.  I want to flag another issue yet again.  Last night I did a bit of research.  If I look for somewhere to live in Clare in mid-October or the end of October, there are 627 full homes available to let on Airbnb but there are only 36 properties available to rent.  There is 17 times more accommodation available on Airbnb.  These are full homes.  I am not speaking about people using Airbnb to rent a room in a house.  I have no problem with people doing that.  I do not care what they do with the money.  It can go into the mattress for all I care.  As we speak, there are 627 full homes available in Clare on Airbnb.  I would love to know how many of them are registered, how many of them have planning permission to be advertised as accommodation on Airbnb and how many of them are third or fourth homes.  I will have to dig deeper to find out this information.</p> <p>There is something seriously wrong with this situation.  I am sure Clare is not unique.  I know it is a very popular spot to visit.  We value our tourists but we also value our people having somewhere to live.  There has to be a balance.  I am not against Airbnb.  I want to be very clear on that.  When we have 627 full homes available to let on Airbnb in the middle of a dirty winter in Clare and only 36 homes available to rent normally, then we have a serious problem.  The House should seek a proper debate on this matter with the Minister for Housing, Local Government and Heritage.</p> <p>We know we are trying to build houses.  I can see social housing estates being built, which is great.  I can see some affordable housing being built.  I have not yet seen any affordable housing or cost-rental accommodation being built in Clare.  It takes a lot longer to build a house then it does to enforce the relevant rules on Airbnb owners.  It is an absolute disgrace that Airbnb is allowed to advertise these properties that could be people's homes.  We have to prioritise homes for people over Airbnb accommodation for a couple of nights for tourists.  It is just not fair.  This summer, we had a huge issue in north Clare when many businesses could not open all of the hours they wanted to because staff had nowhere to live.  It is great that tourists have Airbnb, but if all of our restaurants and bars are closed because they do not have staff, it is a joke.  This is a serious issue.  We want rent pressure zones everywhere, not only in Dublin.  We also want restrictions on Airbnb.  We need enforcement.  Shame on Airbnb for being part of this major problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#L00500"><p>I want to reflect on some of the statistics released today from last year's census in the North.  There is a substantial amount of detail to get through.  No doubt I will reflect on some of it in the coming weeks.  No one can deny the significant symbolism of the details released today.  It also shows that we are living in a changed and changing society.  In the first instance this tells us in a very obvious and stark way that we need to prepare for further change.  We need to do so in an inclusive, positive and progressive way.  For a long time in the House, I have advocated in respect of the need for a citizens' assembly that would act as a home for this discussion and the preparation and planning necessary for change.  There is a lot of detail to get through.  I do not presume to know it all or, indeed, to know what all of what the detail tells us.  I appreciate the historic symbolism of what we are finding out today, however.</p> <p>What we can deal with is the practical issue of a 63.5% increase in Irish passport holders in the North of Ireland since the census in 2011.  Last year, for the first time, there were more applications for Irish passports in the North than there were for British passports.  I do not say this to presume anyone's particular allegiance or view on the constitutional question.  I merely make the point to highlight a practical issue that warrants a response.  We all know the issues nationwide and not only in the North with the passport service last year.  We know of the delays, problems and difficulties in communication.  This morning's figures of a 63.5% increase and more than 500,000 people holding an Irish passport are welcome.  I hope there is more of it.  A passport is an important document and we all appreciate this.  People need to have a service to interface with directly.  They deserve and are entitled to a proper modern and accessible service with which they can interact and engage when needed.  This is another reminder.  I hope we soon get an opportunity to debate the cross-party motion calling for a passport office in the North.  I take this opportunity to make the call  of the Irish Government once again.  If it ever needed a reason, cause or, dare I say it, a justification, although one of those should not be necessary, it is the figure jumping out at us today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1664" speakername="Sharon Keogan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#L00600"><p>I want to raise the issue of the ongoing shortage of pharmacists in Ireland.  This was raised in both Houses last May.  The situation certainly has not resolved itself.  In fact just last month the Irish Pharmacy Union conducted a survey that showed the shortage is reaching crisis levels.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Sharon Keogan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=SharonKeogan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->These shortages will lead to some pharmacies reducing their hours and services and in some case temporary closures may be necessary.  More than half of the pharmacies surveyed had at least one open vacancy for a pharmacist in the past year and more than one third indicated that these vacancies had remained for more than six months and up to one year.  The report shows that to stay open, at least 20% of the pharmacies are relying on pharmacist locums.  Of the pharmacists surveyed, 42% were first registered in the UK.  This high percentage of pharmacists qualifying outside of Ireland serves to highlight the glaring lack of places for students to study pharmacy here in Ireland. </p><p>The president of the Irish Pharmacists Union, IPU, Dermot Twomey, stated that the profession is being strangled by red tape and bureaucracy and that much of the pharmacist&rsquo;s day is now spent filling out paperwork which provides no benefit to the patient.  This is unfortunately leading to the exodus of well-educated community pharmacists.  Were the HSE to address this it would make the profession more attractive and boost retention.  </p><p>Certain improvements to community healthcare in a pharmacy setting such as the introduction of an electronic prescription handling system have been in the works since 2013.  According to Mr. Twomey the only changes that seem to come quickly are those that involve more red tape.  Will the Minister for Health and the Minister for Further and Higher Education, Research, Innovation and Science get together to thrash out a plan to get more pharmacists into training at third level and see what can be done to make the career more attractive to people who want to fill those places?  Our pharmacists are a vital cog in the wheel of healthcare in this country.  The minor ailment scheme is still on the back burner due to the inaction of the Minister in rolling it out.  We need to support our pharmacists better.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1683" speakername="Marie Sherlock" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#M00200"><p>I express solidarity with the more than 1,000 workers who are out on strike yesterday, today and tomorrow across a number of section 39 organisations and community employment schemes in Cork, Kerry, Galway, Mayo and Donegal.  Most of these workers provide vital health and disability services to some of the most vulnerable people in our communities and yet they have had no pay increase since 2008 and nobody to negotiate with.  They cannot negotiate with their employer because the employer receives a fixed amount from the Government.  When their unions approached the Government, it washed its hands of them.  The question that has to be asked is, are we going to force these workers to strike again in the middle of winter to try to get some improvement in their pay?  They have been left with no option.</p> <p>In keeping with the industrial relations sphere, yesterday it was announced that Patricia King, general secretary of the Irish Congress of Trade Unions, ICTU, intends to step down over the next few weeks.  It is important that we recognise her immense contribution to improve the lives of working people in this country.  She was a trailblazer in the union movement, the first woman general officer in SIPTU, Ireland's largest trade union, and the first woman secretary general of the ICTU.  Her achievements set her apart in coming to national prominence in 2005 during the Irish Ferries dispute and mobilising thousands of people onto our streets because of the appalling breach of that threshold of decency by Irish Ferries.  There was also the 2018 legislation on which she engaged with the Leader when she was Minister with regard to outlawing zero-hour contracts and laying down decent entitlements for those who find themselves on "if and when" contracts.  We will see the fruits of all her background work to improve the right to collective bargaining in this country when we see the transposition of the adequate minimum wages directive into Irish legislation next year.  </p> <p>These are but a few of Patricia King's long list of achievements which started four decades ago.  To acknowledge her immense contribution any of us who had the privilege of working with her know that she had a fierce determination to furthering the cause of working people.  She will be sorely missed across the trade union movement and in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1635" speakername="Lynn Boylan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#M00300"><p>I will speak today about the cost of living protest which will take place on Saturday.  While today might be a miserable, wet day it looks like the weather gods are shining down for those of us who will take to the streets on Saturday because the weather forecast is good.  Many of us will remember the water protests and how they shook the foundations of the Government at the time.  It is hard to believe it has been eight years since those protests first took place.  The protests grew on a monthly basis with increasing numbers each time until a large demonstration of nearly 100,000 people took to the streets in March 2015, a protest I was privileged to address at the time.</p> <p>At the time the Government dismissed the protests, sneered at the protestors and tried to smear them with terms such as "sinister fringes" and such language.  However, despite the arrogance of the Government, by April 2017 water charges were no more.  The protests were a fantastic example of people power, citizens standing up and telling the Government that enough is enough.</p> <p>This Saturday, 24 September, a cost-of-living protest will take in Dublin.  I encourage anybody from around the country to make their way to Dublin for that protest.  It is being organised by the cost-of-living coalition which involves a group of students, activists, unions and politicians who have been brought together by the soaring cost of living, by energy costs, rising inflation, housing costs, ludicrous rents and the ongoing rise in costs across the board.</p> <p>The cost-of-living coalition is calling on all those affected, including people who have seen their mortgage rates go up because the Minister for Finance will not bring in the banks and demand that they do not pass on the interest rates for the moment.  It is essential that the message is sent loud and clear that the cost-of-living crisis has to be addressed by this Government.  I urge everybody to join that protest on 24 September.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1629" speakername="Garret Ahearn" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#M00400"><p>The recent increases in the back-to-school clothing and footwear allowance have been welcomed.  It has been a difficult time for parents with the cost of living and the cost of sending kids back to school.  However, it is very restrictive in regard to who is able to claim the back-to-school allowance.</p> <p>A great many people in County Tipperary have come to me to talk about their experiences of the cost of sending kids back to school.  A recent survey found that it costs about &euro;1,500 per child to include books, clothes, shoes and everything that goes with sending kids to school.  If there are a couple of kids in the house, that is extremely expensive.</p> <p>A number of people came to my office and asked whether people who are working could be given some sort of tax break or some recognition such as a double payment in the children's allowance, that would recognise people who are struggling and do not have enough disposable income.  Some people I know are taking out loans just to be able to pay for clothes for their children.  A single mother came to me who is working full time but on low income and getting nothing.  She gets none of those supports that she feels she needs.</p> <p>Most people have welcomed the back-to-school allowance, which is good, and the increase in it which recognises how people are struggling.  However, working people are also struggling.  We need to make sure they are represented and protected during this time.  If something could be done in the budget next week to recognise that I would be grateful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#M00500"><p>I ask the Leader to arrange a special debate on the experience of children and their families when they are in hospital.  This morning on &ldquo;Morning Ireland&rdquo; we heard the experience of a woman whose child was in hospital with a long-term illness.  She spoke of the cost of car parking and the costs when the child was being treated, for cancer in this instance.  If the child felt sick when the food came around then food had to be purchased later or some special treat obtained to induce a child to eat at a time when the child is very ill.  All of those costs mount up for families.</p> <p>I appreciate that we have removed the inpatient fees for children in hospital which is a great step forward in itself.  However, there are other considerations at a time when we are in a challenging cost-of-living crisis.</p> <p>A survey was done a couple of years ago on promoting children's rights and welfare in healthcare across all European Union countries.  There is additional financial strain on a family.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->They can have additional accommodation, food and car parking costs.  Car parking charges in our children's hospitals are appallingly high, with some charging up to &euro;35 a day.  I do not see why a bespoke arrangement cannot be put in place to support these families.  They are a discrete group that could be red-circled and vouchers or passes given to them.  It is possible to do that and there is no reason it cannot be done.  There are other issues as well.  The woman who spoke this morning talked about the possibility of vouchers for hospital cafeterias for families.  Such simple things would make a huge difference at a time of crisis.  I acknowledge the role of the Ronald McDonald House which is adjacent to Crumlin children's hospital in my own constituency of Dublin South-Central and which I have visited on a number of occasions.  It  provides accommodation to families from around the country and does extraordinary work.  It is not financed by McDonald's itself but it gathers the charitable donations.  It provides home-from-home food, sibling accommodation and so on.  We need to deal properly with children in hospital and their families and I call for a debate on the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1666" speakername="Tim Lombard" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#N00200"><p>In the run-up to the budget there has been a lot of talk about cost-of-living measures and what is going to be required, particularly in the context of energy, to make sure that households and industries are sustainable going forward.  In that context, I would like to raise the issue of our sporting clubs.  The cost of running sports complexes has increased dramatically in the last 18 months.  Obviously there are the normal running costs pertaining to sports halls but some sports complexes are of such a magnitude and nature that they cost an awful lot to run.  A sporting complex in Bandon which had running costs of around &euro;3,500 last year has seen these increase to over &euro;12,000 this year.  The running costs of sporting clubs are traditionally met through lottery funding.  I am referring to lotteries run by the clubs themselves rather than grants from the State.  In the context of the energy crisis, special measures must be put in place to make sure that sporting clubs are sustainable.  We need to take care of householders and industries but we also need to make sure that grants are made available to voluntary sporting organisations that are effectively funded by their members.  I am referring to our local GAA, soccer, basketball clubs and so on.  They all use energy and are going to be affected by increasing energy costs so we need to do something special for them.  If we do not do that, the members will have to pay more through weekly lotteries, draws and so on.  An additional &euro;9,000 in costs for a relatively small sports complex is really significant.  We must think outside the box when designing measures to address energy bills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1695" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#N00300"><p>I wish to draw attention to the fact that 18 September was International Equal Pay Day.  I attended a meeting of the Joint Committee on Housing, Local Government and Heritage this morning that was also attended by the Minister of State, Deputy Burke.  The committee was engaged in pre-legislative scrutiny of a Bill concerning maternity leave and maternity pay for councillors.  In the adjoining room, the Joint Committee on Gender Equality was discussing equal pay.  There is a lot of discussion of these issues currently and we should have a debate on them in this House.  I ask the Leader to organise a debate on equal pay at her earliest convenience because many females feel they are being left behind.  There is quite a significant number of females in this Chamber and it would be good to have a discussion on gender equality and equal pay.</p> <p>I was contacted by a constituent recently who had been away travelling and came back here to work last year.  This person was in a job that paid less than &euro;24,000 per year but was offered a place on a master's degree programme in the University of Limerick, UL and so applied for a grant from Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI.  However, because they had been working for the last 12 months, albeit on a low income, they were only entitled to a small grant towards fees but were not entitled to any maintenance grant.  We really must look after people who are in low-paid jobs.  In budget 2023 we need to look after people like carers and people with disabilities but also people who are engaged in upskilling and retraining.  The individual I spoke to wants to upskill and retrain but is facing barriers as a result of having worked.  Had they been in receipt of jobseeker's allowance or another social welfare payment, they would have qualified for a SUSI grant.  Budget 2023 must provide support to those who want to upskill and retrain, particularly those on lower pay.  I hope supports will be put in place for people with disabilities, for carers and for those who want to work but who need to upskill and retrain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1685" speakername="Barry Ward" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#N00400"><p>Not for the first time in this House I want to raise the issue of water quality in Dublin Bay and the coastal waters off Dublin.  For the last two weeks there has been a "No bathing" advisory notice at Killiney beach because of an overspill from a sewage treatment plant there.  That should not happen and it has had serious consequences for people who had events planned.  I know of swimming events planned for Killiney beach last weekend which could not take place.  The advisory notice will remain in place until tomorrow, at least, as we await the results of sampling.  However, I do not understand why, when the advisory notice applies to Coliemore Harbour, Hawk Cliff and Killiney beach, it does not apply to the Forty Foot, which is less than 1 km up the coast, or to Sandycove, Blackrock or Seapoint.  It does not apply to them and I do not understand how that works.</p> <p>What I do know is that nothing has happened to secure water quality in D&uacute;n Laoghaire, Dublin Bay and along the coast of Dublin.  We have not improved the screening of water that leaves the Poolbeg facility or other sewage treatment facilities in the county.  We do not have 24-hour UV screening of that material and we do not have provisions in place to prevent overspills from sewage facilities.  We do not have proper water quality in Dublin Bay and it is not good enough.  This has been going on for far too long and there seems to be some kind of frozen inaction at departmental and local authority level.  I do not know that is the fault of the local authorities because they are dependent on resources and directions from Irish Water and the Department of Housing, Local Government and Heritage but nothing is happening.  We know how much these facilities are used.  We know that far more people are now swimming in the sea and how good it is for them, for both their mental and physical health.  Let us try to make progress on this.  We must schedule a debate on water quality.  I ask the Leader to invite the relevant Minister to have a discussion about what needs to be done, how it can happen, why it is not happening and when it will happen.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1639" speakername="Miche&aacute;l Carrigy" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#N00500"><p>I want to raise a couple of issues on behalf of groups within my community.  I welcome the recent announcement by the Minister for Rural and Community Development, Deputy Humphreys, of a community centres investment fund for the refurbishment and upgrading of much-needed community facilities across Ireland.  A sum of &euro;15 million has been set aside but I understand that applications have been made for projects totally more than &euro;70 million .  In that context, I ask that extra funding be provided for this fund so that we can invest in community centres throughout the country.  In my own area, projects are planned for the community centres in Newtownforbes, in Granard in north Longford and in Drumlish.  Significant works are planned for these centres which have not had much funding in recent years.  I ask that the fund be increased, which would be particularly welcome in rural areas.</p> <p>The outdoor recreation infrastructure scheme was announced a number of months ago and applications have been submitted for same.  In my own county, a significant application has been made for a rebel trail in north Longford, which will highlight the county's links to the 1798 rebellion and the War of Independence, including General Se&aacute;n Mac Eoin, the Clonfin Ambush, Granard, Ms Kitty Kiernan and so on.  We want to develop a trail from Drumlish, which has connections to the Land League, out to Ballinamuck and so on.  An application for funding has been made and hopefully it will be successful so that we can build that tourism project in north County Longford.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1650" speakername="Mark Daly" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#N00600"><p>Before I call on the Leader to respond to the Order of Business I welcome to the Distinguished Visitors Gallery the former representative, Ms Helene Keeley, who was the Speaker <i>pro tempore</i>of the Delaware House of Representatives.  She was the longest serving member of that House at one stage but I do not know if she still holds that distinction.  She has worked with the board of the St. Patrick's Day Society, among many other organisations.  I have a list before me that is so long that I would never have time to read it all.  It would take longer than our Order of Business.  Ms Keeley worked with the then Attorney General, Mr. Beau Biden, in 2014 on important legislation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2246"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2246&amp;amp;pid=MarkDaly&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am delighted she was able to come to Seanad &Eacute;ireann this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#O00200"><p>Ms Keeley is very welcome.  I congratulate her on such a distinguished career.</p> <p>Senator Carrigy asked for the extension of two welcome announcements, namely, funding for community centres and the recreational funds scheme that have been a resounding success.  I am sure there will be many more applications for the &euro;70 million fund.  It is oversubscribed and needs further funding.  The Senator eloquently described the positive impact this money is having on communities across the country.  We will certainly make his views known.</p> <p>Senator Ward asked for a debate on water quality in Dublin Bay.  The situation strikes me as quite bizarre.  There are similar issues in Balbriggan, Skerries and Rush, which are in the same treasured part of the world in terms of swimming.  I do not know how something so drastic as a sewage spill can affect only some areas.  Perhaps it is something to do with the way the waves move, but it does not make sense, in particular for the people who use the facility.  I will certainly invite a debate on the topic the Senator has raised.</p> <p>Senator Maria Byrne called for a debate on equality, in particular around gender and disability in the context of supports from the State for lifelong learning and just progression within the workplace.  I have the privilege of sitting on the Joint Committee on Gender Equality.  We have this conversation every Thursday morning.  This morning, representatives from the Irish Congress of Trade Unions were in with us.  It would be useful to have a wider debate.</p> <p>Senator Lombard spoke about cost increases for volunteers running clubs throughout the country.  I was mindful of and pleased by the fact that the T&aacute;naiste said yesterday that in any small business package for energy we will announce next Tuesday as part of the budget, we have to consider those in our farming community as small business owners, even though many of them receive their energy bills in the same way as I or other Senators do for a household.  We cannot leave the social fabric of all of the towns, villages and cities we live in, including the GAA, rugby, soccer, basketball, tennis and other clubs we rely on for our children and which are run by volunteers and funded by weekly lottos, out of the budget.  At a time when people are struck by the extra cost of living crisis, we can only assume that the support for those clubs will decline and their bills will go through the roof, just as they will for everybody else.  They have to be countenanced and looked after.</p> <p>Senator Seery Kearney asked for a debate on the additional costs for families when children are in hospital.  It is a serious matter and a debate which is very much needed.  As a Government, there are a lot of extra things we could be doing to support families during times when children are in hospital.</p> <p>Senator Ahearn spoke about the cost of living and sought to extend the back-to-school allowance.  It has been significantly increased over the past number of years, especially by the Minister for Social Protection, Deputy Humphreys, this year through the cost-of-living response during the summer.  The means test relating to applying for the scheme needs to be reconsidered.  It would be helpful if we had a tiered scheme as opposed to the rigid scheme we have now.</p> <p>Senator Boylan spoke about the cost-of-living protests that are going ahead this Saturday.  I hope the sun shines, because it is miserable outside today.  I do not mean to be disrespectful in my response to the Senator, but she made her remarks as if the rest of us are not aware of the requirements of Government for a cost-of-living increase for all sections of society.  That is something which is mentioned by all of her colleagues week in, week out.  We are well aware of the situation.  That is why we will see a significant package in the budget next week, not only for individual households and citizens but also for all of our businesses and employers.  I expect everybody to welcome the good stuff and point out the stuff we might miss next week.  I wish everyone the best of luck on Saturday.</p> <p>Senator Keogan asked for a debate on the shortage of pharmacists, in particular community pharmacists.  I would very much welcome and support such a debate.  Sharon Foley is the secretary general of the IPU and a good pal of mine.  She brought to my attention yesterday a pilot scheme for extending services in our community pharmacists conducted in 2017.  It was a roaring success, yet it has sat on the desks of numerous Ministers for Health since and nothing has happened.  We need to invest not just in college places, but in ensuring that we keep students once they graduate and make it is a viable and decent business to work in and provide the services in localities we all want in the future.</p> <p>Senator &Oacute; Donnghaile suggested that we have a citizens assembly on the changes happening in society in Northern Ireland.  I believe the changes are probably reflected in the rest of the country too.  In fairness, we have Brexit to thank for the increase in the number of people applying for Irish passports.  He makes a very valid argument.  Given the number of people applying for Irish passports in Northern Ireland, it should have its own passport office.</p> <p>Senator Garvey spoke about the stark contrast in housing figures, which is disgraceful.  There are 627 houses available to rent this winter in Clare through Airbnb.  This compares with 36 houses available to rent on a long-term basis.  We have a problem and we need to confront it in terms of the relaxation of regulations around Airbnb.  We probably need to have a debate on that and bring suggestions to the Minister.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell spoke about the statements we had yesterday on SAR tenders.  I contributed to the debate and I believe the Cathaoirleach was also present.  Regarding the contribution of Senator Craughwell, the problem with unanswered questions is that they do not go away.  If they are not answered in this forum, they have to be brought to other forums which are far more public and involve far more scrutiny.  It is a pity we did not get answers yesterday.  I do not think this matter is going to go away.</p> <p>Senator Conway spoke about another group which is experiencing an increase in the cost of living and building.  He referred to the grants for Pobal-funded projects.  They might have been allocated last year or the year before.  Organisations have sought to draw down funding now and the money involved does not meet the bills that will arise once building projects start.  We need to be cognisant of that.</p> <p>Senator Clifford-Lee opened proceedings by asking for a debate on sexual violence and the use of rape as a weapon of war.  That would be incredibly worthy and worthwhile, given our show of solidarity in the past couple of months with the people of Ukraine and the interactions between our respective Parliaments and parliamentarians.  She has had interaction with other European politicians.  It would be very valuable for us to have that conversation and see what we can do to support Ukraine and how the Government can best help not just with money but resources and solidarity.</p> <p>Senator Sherlock spoke about Patricia King, who announced yesterday that she is intending to retire in the next couple of weeks.  I genuinely wish her a very long, healthy and happy retirement.  She is one of the most formidable women we have ever seen in this country.  Senator Sherlock used the term "trailblazer", which I also used in my statement last night.  Ms King is and has been a trailblazer for employment rights and mediation in this country.  Her legacy is something that exists not just because she is a woman but because she is a woman in a world which is male dominated, not just the labour industry but also the political industry.  It will be a long time before her legacy is matched.  I had the privilege of sitting around the leaf table with her for years.  It was a privilege on good days and, by God, it was bruising on bad days.  That shows the power and passion of the woman.  I genuinely hope she has a long and happy retirement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.58" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.59" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#O00500">Sitting Arrangements: Motion</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1653" speakername="Regina Doherty" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#O00600"><p>I move:</p> <blockquote> 	That, notwithstanding anything in the Standing Orders relative to Public Business, the Seanad on its rising on Thursday, 22nd September, 2022, shall adjourn until 12 noon on Tuesday, 27th September, 2022, and the following arrangements shall apply:  	(<i>a</i>) Commencement matters shall be taken at 12 noon;<br /><br />(<i>b</i>) Standing Order 30 shall stand suspended;<br /><br />(<i>c</i>) The Order of Business shall be proposed at 3.30 p.m.&rdquo;   </blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.61" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.62" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar fionra&iacute; ar 12.48 a.m. agus cuireadh t&uacute;s leis ar&iacute;s ar 1.15 p.m.<br /><br />Sitting suspended at 12.48 a.m. and resumed at 1.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.63" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#R00100">New Innovations for People with Disabilities (Digital Assistive Technology): Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#R00200"><p>We will commence with statements on new innovations for people with disabilities - digital assistive technology.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Rabbitte, back to the House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#R00300"><p>I am thankful I have been given the opportunity to address my Oireachtas colleagues with regard to digital and assistive technologies.  I know some Senators present are dependent on glasses, as I am.  I am sure everyone is aware of friends, family or colleagues who use hearing aids, screen readers or other items and technologies that help them in their day-to-day lives.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Anne Rabbitte:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2436"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2436&amp;amp;pid=AnneRabbitte&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is exactly what digital and assistive technologies are about: making life that bit easier and more accessible for people with different kinds of impairments.  The use of technologies has been characterised as a facilitator for the integration of services and the provision of facilities to serve people with disabilities.  In other words, their use can allow people with an impairment to play a greater and more fulfilling role in society.  According to the WHO, more than 1 billion people worldwide require one or more assistive products.  As people turn 50 and get older, they will need an assistive product every year along the way.  The bulk of these are disabled or elderly individuals.</p><p>People of all ages, including those with disabilities, have a variety of functional impairments as they age, and as a result, they require more support.  By 2050, it is anticipated that more than 2 billion individuals will use assistive devices due to the ageing of the global population and the rising prevalence of non-communicable diseases.</p><p>With the help of assistive products, people with disabilities can engage in school, the job market and civic life, helping them to live healthy, productive, independent, and dignified lives of their own choosing.  Additionally, the use of formal health and support services, long-term care and caregiver labour can all be focused on more critical cases with the aid of assistive products.</p><p>Since becoming Minister of State, I have been dedicated to increasing developments, innovation and utilisation of digital and assistive technologies.  Globally, I have engaged with the WHO and made sure that Ireland works with the international community, and, critically, with the disabled persons' organisations to ensure people with disabilities are the drivers of the innovative changes they want to see.</p><p>As a follow-up to the United Nations Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities, UNCRPD, the WHO launched a programme to promote global co-operation on assistive technology entitled GATE.  The goal of the GATE programme is to increase accessibility to high-quality, reasonably-priced assistive goods for those with a range of disabilities, illnesses, and age-related ailments.  Ireland has been a key stakeholder in this.</p><p>The World Health Assembly Resolution 74.8 2021 urges member states to realise the highest attainable standards of health for persons with disabilities, a key part of which is around the development and provision of assistive technologies.  This move was co-led by Ireland, and it is Ireland that is leading out on implementing a rights-based approach to building leadership and governance in health services.</p><p>I was recently at the WHO's European regional assembly and spoke about how important this is.  On a national level, the Government is committed to offering people with disability the services and supports they need to plan their lives, live independently, and customise the supports needed to fit their requirements.  Numerous services are available to shield people and families from paying exorbitant prices for their medical and surgical requirements.</p><p>Before I get into this, I want to bring it back to why there is such a focus on assistive technologies.  As I explained to the Senator before coming in, when Covid-19 landed in this country and people had to go back into their houses, they were very isolated.  To be fair to family members and providers, they saw innovative ways of continuing with communication.  Hence the use of a tablet and finding ways to better connect people.  </p><p>I was in west Cork and I went to the Irish Wheelchair Association.  I thought I was going to meet a lady but in fact, the lady was waiting to meet me on Zoom.  She told me about how she used to come in, using the Irish Wheelchair Association, to attend the service once a week.  What Covid-19 showed her was by learning how to use assistive technology, she could go on Zoom, learn to play bridge, which she now does three times a week, and had more access to more friends.  She was not judged on her disability but on her ability to play bridge.  She had found many more friends.  This got me thinking when I went out to the Central Remedial Clinic, CRC, and saw the wonderful work it was doing.  I went into a class where people had to socially distance.  While there might have been four people in the room, there was another 12 on Zoom.  Very large screens were used to enable people to participate, use their connectivity and let the conversation continue.  This is extremely important.</p><p>I hear about aids and appliances and we talk about the old model of aids and appliances.  "Aids and appliances" is a term that is dated and does not keep up with technology.  We need to be innovative and creative and support the families who understand best and help us shape the role aids, appliances and technology can play.  I have looked to get more involved at an international level to see how Ireland can become part of things and to lever us onto a larger market of access to aids and appliances that will enable our citizens to fulfil what it states in the UNCRPD.</p><p>I am going to move on to some of the projects I have funded in the past year under the Cooperative Real Engagement for Assistive Technology Enhancement, CREATE, programme.  This initiative seeks to ensure service users and providers work together to identify what will make a real difference to individual users of digital and assistive technology.  What I am about to describe are projects funded by once-off funding of &euro;2 million that I got last year in the budget.  To be fair to the various groups that came forward, that &euro;2 million has been very well spent.</p><p>The inclusion of the person is what makes this important.  Funding for this was assessed on the extent to which each proposal was person-centred, as well as how it demonstrated a willingness to work collaboratively across different service providers and to engage with digital and assistive technologies through a clear process of co-design.</p><p>Acquired Brain Injury Ireland will use person-centred digital and assistive technologies to support brain injury survivors, while also establishing a new programme to systematically upskill its staff in a range and functionality of digital and assistive technologies products.  The Brothers of Charity service west are establishing a pilot digital and assistive technologies team to develop a multidisciplinary service focusing on communication and access needs and linking with local advocacy groups for people with disabilities.</p><p>The CRC will establish Ireland's first sit-to-stand wheelchair service, allowing wheelchair users to stand without the need of assistance.  For people with spinal cord injury and Duchenne muscular dystrophy, this may have a range of physical and psychological benefits.  The nine children's disability network teams in community health west will establish a community DAT bank with access based on needs and incorporating digital and assistive technologies into family service planning and integrating with the Department of Education's digital strategy for schools.  That is where we need connectivity.  We need to connect children to their environment, be it in the home or in education.  It is not just children but it is adults as well.  We need to ensure we work across Departments and across areas of involvement.</p><p>Adult disability services in Longford and Westmeath will work with Longford County Council to identify digital and assistive technologies to support people with disabilities living independently in the community and facilitating those on a housing waiting list to take up a house when it becomes available and to ensure that house has the required assistive technology so they can live as independently as possible.</p><p>The Rehab Group will develop a digital and assistive technologies ecosystem with a first-stop-shop for information, advice and guidance on how digital and assistive technologies can enhance person-centred planning, independence and participation in all aspects of life.  Their new digital and assistive technologies training module will be co­produced with people with disabilities.  St. Michael's House will use digital and assistive technologies to enhance the experience of using respite services, incorporating the Sl&aacute;intecare-funded health passport for people with intellectual disabilities.</p><p>Stewarts Care will use digital and assistive technologies to promote the implementation of the meaningful day approach to service provision, by providing a broader range of activities, including greater social interaction between service users and between them and the communities in which they live.  Sunbeam House Services will develop a digital and assistive technologies loan library which, among other things, will support the advocacy group viewpoint, to develop a mentorship programme of expert digital and assistive technologies users.  The National Council for the Blind, NCBI, will provide timely access to digital and assistive technologies nationwide, addressing delays and shortfalls in their provision and offering consistency of support.  I have run out of time. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1691" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#T00100"><p>Cuirim f&aacute;ilte roimh an Aire go dt&iacute; an Teach.  She and I acknowledge the amazing work done in the past year through the &euro;2 million granted in the last budget.  I hope she has a foot against the door on this occasion and that she will get another &euro;2 million, or maybe more, because the money is extremely well spent.</p> <p>The Minister of State mentioned that many people wear glasses.  I believe I will be going down that road as well.  I spent three quarters of an hour this morning in south Dublin getting my eyes tested.  </p> <p>The Minister of State said the World Health Assembly's Resolution EB148.R6 of 2021 urges member states to realise the highest attainable standards of health for persons with disabilities, a key part of which will concern the development and provision of assistive technologies.  If I had been asked in this House five years ago what assistive technology was, I would not have had a bull's notion.  The Minister of State mentioned that she recently visited the constituency of Cork South-West, where I live, and the premises of the Irish Wheelchair Association in Clonakilty.  I would like to enlighten her about the fact that, in Bantry, where I lived for many years, CoAction West Cork was set up in the early 1980s.  Having had ten clients originally and now more than 100, it has done great work.  There is funding for road bowling and days out in the town and surrounding locations.  It does not operate in Bantry alone but also in the peninsulas, including in Castletownbere, Goleen and Kilcrohane.  There is a wide variety of tremendous work done.  For people in Castletownbere or Goleen, which is roughly 100 miles from Cork city, the notion of getting to Cork to a central service was not applicable at the time in question.</p> <p>Digital and assistive technology can do tremendous work for the affected people.  CoAction has been immersed in the community for as long as I can remember.  When it was established, it opened a little workshop close to the house in which I lived at the time.  It has developed since.  It has several houses, and people can live independently in them.  Some have physical disabilities and others have all sorts of other disabilities.  The community support offered by the organisation not only in Bantry but also in Skibbereen, Clonakilty, Dunmanway and the huge region in which they are located, even going into Cork North-West and Kerry South, is tremendous.  It is appropriate that it be mentioned here today.  If it has not already contacted the Minister of State, I encourage it to do so.  Some extra funding would mean a lot to it.  A friend of mine, a councillor who is a wheelchair operator, has worked very closely with the group.</p> <p>The Minister of State mentioned the Central Remedial Clinic, which does extraordinary work.  Ireland's first sit-to-stand wheelchair service allows wheelchair users to stand without the need of assistance.  That is an amazing breakthrough because most people would not even have thought of that historically.  The Minister of State said, "For people with spinal cord injury and Duchenne muscular dystrophy, this may have a range of physical and psychological benefits."  For some with physical disabilities, which they may have either from birth or because of an accident, the emotional and psychological advantage of the modern technology is a huge boost.  When I was growing up, people with a disability, even those with Down's syndrome, were hidden away from society.  This was a shame.  I had an aunt with Down's syndrome when I was a child.  The notion of even taking her out to mass was frowned upon.  It was asked why you would take her out.  This thinking has turned totally on its head, and we are going in the right direction.</p> <p>It is interesting that the World Health Organization is totally involved with this.  It may be a new awakening not alone internationally, through the WHO, but also nationally.  As someone who is fairly well travelled and who lived in England for some years, I believe we are a leading light in this regard.  We are stepping forward and are among the best in Europe.  I have no doubt that the money that has been provided is just a first.  The money is extremely well spent, and I accept the Minister of State's pronouncement in that regard.  However, if she got &euro;4 million this year, which might be a bit of an ask, that money could also be spent throughout the country.  It is a new beginning.  I welcome it.</p> <p>I laud the Minister of State for her tremendous work in this field.  Some do not acknowledge what Ministers do.  This is a case in which the public can learn from what we do in public life.  Sometimes we get criticism, some of which is deserved, but sometimes Ministers, be they Senators or Deputies, deserve a pat on the back for what they do.  Sometimes the public disregards the good things we do and hone in on the negative stuff, which we hear about on social media, etc.  We are moving in the right direction.  I have no doubt that the Minister of State is pushing an open door as far as the Members of this House are concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1699" speakername="Tom Clonan" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#T00200"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending.  Aids and appliances are a means to an end but not an end in themselves.  Although they are very useful, we cannot really consider them in the absence of the requirement for personal assistants and therapists.  I will go from the individual experience to the wider experience within the community.  I echo what my fellow Senators have said about the Minister of State's absolute sincerity and her persistence in advocating for us and our community.  That is without doubt, so she should not take anything I say as a personal criticism.  I am speaking from our own lived experience.  Eoghan, my son, is 20.  Over the years, because of his neuromuscular disease, he has had access to digital and assistive technology.  For example, he has a very large iPad.  His eyesight is compromised but the large iPad allows him to see the print on the screen.  He has had some voice-activated software.  It can speak his requests and needs into a device, and it can communicate, by text or another means, with another person.  Unfortunately, however, because Eoghan has not had any speech therapy since 2007 or 2008, the voice-activated software can no longer discern his scanning speech.  This is one of the points I am trying to make.  In the absence of meaningful therapies, the digital and assistive technologies, in and of themselves, cannot really function.</p> <p>There are also very practical matters to be considered.  Eoghan is unable to plug in or unplug his tablet, laptop and other devices and put them on the tray of his wheelchair.  He would require a personal assistant to do that but he does not have one.  He has somebody who assists him in the morning with getting dressed, showering and going to the toilet, but that person then leaves.  He is on his own in the house all day as a 20-year-old man &ndash; a young man blossoming, a beautiful young man.  Unlike his siblings, he is confined to the house because he cannot go out independently without a personal assistant.  I set him up with his tablet in the morning.  This summer, he watched the whole show &ldquo;Friends&rdquo; from start to finish, but, instead of watching friends on a screen, he would prefer to have friends.  He cannot have friends and is isolated despite the state-of-the-art technology because he cannot leave the house.  He does not have a personal assistant to bring him to Dundrum Shopping Centre or into town to have a cup of coffee.  He is denied all these experiences despite the state-of-the-art technology because an essential support is absent for him, just as it is for tens of thousands of children and young adults throughout the Republic.  I am aware that the Minister of State knows this from her visits around the place.   There is a recurring theme of unmet needs throughout the State.</p> <p>Very many of the assistive and digital technology platforms require intensive input, either from an occupational therapist or physiotherapist with a special interest.  This is from the end user's perspective.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Tom Clonan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=TomClonan&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It takes quite a deal of training and reinforcement to enable a child or a young adult to get the most out of the technology.  If one has one physiotherapy appointment a year, if one is lucky, that lasts one hour, that meaningful interface does not take place.  I know this to be a fact.  The progressing disability services for children and young people policy has failed and Paul Reid has acknowledged that on the record at the Committee on Disabilities Matters a number of weeks back.  The wonderful steps we have taken forward in digital technology are very much meaningless without those human interfaces.  That is the end-user perspective, which I will not beat to death.</p><p>From the point of view then of other service provision, I have had a virtual occupational therapist, OT, visit which did actually work, where Fannin Healthcare came and delivered a bath chair.  The OT, through my mobile phone, was able to look at the bath chair.  One could certainly not provide services such as physiotherapy and occupational therapy virtually or remotely.  It is just not possible given the requirement for the physical intervention.</p><p>I use this opportunity to say that there is a complete requirement for us, and I know that this is the absolute mission of the Minister of State for the lifetime of this Government, to constantly reiterate the fact that we do not have the basic building blocks, that is, the personal assistant, PA, hours.  These are not being provided by the State, by the HSE and are not being provided by the private care providers that are funded by the State.  It is just not happening.  In the absence of those supports, the digital technology is, to a greater or lesser extent, meaningless.</p><p>I will finish on one final negative point and then I will conclude positively.  I am very conscious and I have just come from the third level sector where we delivered all of our lectures virtually.  Virtual delivery of services in things like education or day services to people with disabilities is a very poor substitute for real-world interactions. </p><p>People with disabilities are already isolated because of the lack of support from PAs and so on.  I would hope that the providers will not rely upon digital technology to give lip service to day services and other supports because it further isolates people with disabilities.  I saw it this summer with my son at home, where he is now.  In fact he is on his induction today so he has a PA for the period of the academic year.</p><p>On a final note.  There is hope and I commend the work of people like Professor Brian MacCraith, former president of DCU, and Professor Daire Keogh.  They have the exoskeleton programme in DCU.  Eoghan and I went out at Brian MacCraith&rsquo;s invitation.  It is an extraordinary thing and is an actual skeleton that will wrap itself around a disabled person and assist them to walk.  The technology now has perhaps 500, 600, 700 and up to 1,000 messages per second.  The next generation level of exoskeletons will have hundreds of thousands of messages per second in the sensor so it can tailor itself to an individual person.  Eoghan and I went out and he was shivering with excitement to have the opportunity to see if this could help him walk or move.  When the physiotherapist did the assessment of Eoghan, he found that because of a lack of physiotherapy over the years, Eoghan&rsquo;s contractors had deteriorated to such an extent that he was not a candidate for that technology.  </p><p>Again, this underscores the requirement for the human intervention and while digital technologies provide very significant quantitative leaps forward, qualitatively, they do not really impact to a significant degree on the life and lived experience of people with disabilities.  I thank the Acting Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#U00200"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an gCathaoirleach Gn&iacute;omhach.  At the outset, I acknowledge the great work that an Cathaoirleach Gn&iacute;omhach, Senator Seery Kearney, is doing as part of the Committee on Disability Matters in advancing the cause of people with disabilities and, indeed, the need for equality in this country.</p> <p>We have spoken many times on these issues with the Minister of State and her enthusiasm never ceases to amaze me.  Even two years into office, I see how determined she is to make a difference.  She has made a difference.  I consider the particular grant scheme she has spoken about to be a pilot because funding comes with success.  If something is seen as successful, one would want to be a brave Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform not to provide the funding to keep it going.</p> <p>As Senator O&rsquo;Donovan said, &euro;4 million will be seen as small money in the future.  I have no doubt that each and every one of the projects that she has listed out will make full use of the money that is given to it, and I am sure the projects will commit some of their own resources to them also.</p> <p>In my lifetime, there has been a revolution in technology.  When I was in school, apart from a couple of low vision aids, that was all I had.  Believe it or not, and the House will be shocked to think of it, I wrote my junior certificate exams.  How anyone read them is beyond me but that is another story.  When it came to me doing the leaving certificate in 1993, I believe, I typed it on a typewriter.  If one made a mistake one was not able to correct it.  I then went into UCD where I was lucky enough to do my exams on a PC, and at least I could run a spell check at the end to tidy it up.</p> <p>When one fasts forward then to coming into the Oireachtas, I had an iPad and iPhone.  I can therefore take pictures of something, enlarge it and read it.  If I go into a restaurant and there is a menu, I can pick up the phone, take a picture of it, enlarge it and read it, whereas only a few short years ago I would have needed somebody to read the menu to me.  That is fine because I do not have any chips on my shoulder and it does not bother me whatsoever, but there are other people who would find it very embarrassing to have somebody read a menu to them.  That has now been eliminated with the use of the phone.</p> <p>The Minister of State and I attended the launch of IA Labs, which is a National Council for the Blind of Ireland, NCBI, initiative to ensure that all people with print and vision disabilities will have access to technology, which will basically enhance and enrich their lives.  Every single penny of Government money that is put into technology is worth it and I completely understand what Senator Clonan has just said in regard to people.  If the people are not there to create the link between the technology and the individual who needs the technology, that then is an important cog.  </p> <p>My view is that we will have to spend millions of euro on personal assistants because there will be different types of personal assistants.  We will need personal assistants who can take advantage of technology and assist people with it.  There are other personal assistants in the area of healthcare.  We have a serious job of work to do to bridge that gap.  When the pandemic occurred I found the Zoom meetings very challenging simply because of the chat function on the screen.  I could not read the chat function and it would come and go so quickly.  I remember several times in our own parliamentary party meetings asking Ministers, if they were putting important information out there, to please not put it up on the chat function because I could not read it.  </p> <p>I made a request to the Houses of the Oireachtas Commission for a big-screen.  I got the big screen but it was 12 months late, in that the commission had to obtain three quotations and had to use the cheapest one.  The screen ended up having to be imported from China, and by the time it came the pandemic was essentially over.  Institutions will probably have to say that they will need to move with the times where, if technology is needed now, it is actually needed now.  If we are going to be purchasing it anyway, do not take the good out of it by going through a convoluted procurement process for what is, in truth, just a big monitor.</p> <p>I look forward to the day, hopefully it will happen in my lifetime, when I will be able to walk out my front door in County Clare, sit into a Google driverless car, and pull up on the Plinth outside Leinster House, where technology will basically have brought me from Clare to Dublin safely.  I believe we are not that far away from that happening.  There is a great amount of work being done, with investment, research, technology development and so on.  I sincerely hope we are not that far away.  That helps everyone, not just people with disabilities, as it helps with road safety, etc.</p> <p>I have one final point.  I am running a little campaign at the moment and I have spoken with the Minister of State&rsquo;s colleague, the Minister for Education, Deputy Foley, about it.  The leaving certificate examination papers at the moment are not digitally available and are therefore not digitally accessible.  We are an outlier at this point in time in Europe when it comes to that.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Martin Conway:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=26&amp;amp;MemberID=2347"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2347&amp;amp;pid=MartinConway&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Somebody with a print disability whether it is dyslexia, vision impairment or whatever else cannot use the technology they are comfortable with to access their leaving certificate papers.  We are told it is because they do not want to compromise the integrity of the paper, the confidentiality and so on.  There has to be a way around it.  I want the students who are doing the leaving certificate in 2023 with a print disability to be able to access their exam papers in the form of technology that they are comfortable with.  I want them to be digitally accessible.  Any assistance the Minister of State can give in encouraging the Minister for Education, Deputy Foley, to ensure that can happen would be very helpful.  I am going to Temple Bar this afternoon to the launch of a policy paper on education from the National Council for the Blind of Ireland.  This is a big issue.  Readers have to be employed to read the exam papers.  People should be able to do it in the sphere they are comfortable in.  </p><p>With technology and the people to help people access technology, we can reduce the 86% unemployment rate of people with disabilities to the European average of around 40%.  It would be positive if we could even get it down to 50%.  That can happen with the use of technology and the people to link the individuals to the technology.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#V00200"><p>I thank the Senator for his kind words and well done to him for his persistent campaigning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1688" speakername="Niall &Oacute; Donnghaile" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#V00300"><p>The Minister of State is very welcome.  I thank colleagues for the very informative contributions they have made on this issue so far.  They certainly informed me and I am sure they have done the same for the Minister of State.  It shows the merit and value of having statements like this in the Seanad and taking the time to discuss these issues.</p> <p>As the Minister of State said, technology has had a far-reaching and positive impact on many areas of life.  In particular, it has significantly opened up life for people with disabilities.  Assistive technology, AT, a specific branch of general technology, refers to practical tools that can enable people with disabilities and older people to maximise their independence.  It refers to any device or system that helps to improve the functional capacity of the person.  It has been a central feature of the disability sector for some time.</p> <p>The smartphone is probably the most obvious and versatile form of assistive technology available.  That technology can support people to access their human rights, for example, under the UN Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities.  It can support people to complete their education, get and retain employment, live in their community and become digitally literate.  Examples of AT include screen-reading software that supports people with vision impairment as well as those with literacy challenges, and voice output communications solutions for those who are non-speaking.  It includes control technology such as remote control of doors, windows and lights to enable independence in the home.  There is a growing range of mainstream mobile solutions available via apps on smartphones and tablet devices which can support everything from personal mobility to personal organisation and memory aids.</p> <p>A report based on a survey of 120 service providers by the HSE which examined the impact of AT on disabled people during the Covid-19 pandemic found that people were very positive about how technology helped services continue to varying degrees and helped maintain connectedness, engagement and interaction.  The technologies that helped included WhatsApp, Facebook, Zoom, Skype, YouTube, Wi-Fi and JAWS.  However, the report also found that nothing replaced face-to-face contact, the in-person human connection.  Two leading organisations in the development of AT for disabled people, the Disability Federation of Ireland and Enable Ireland, have raised with the Government their concerns that current service provision for AT is fragmented and under-resourced to meet the emerging challenges of a growing population with disabilities and older people interfacing with technology which is developing at great speed.  One of their key recommendations is an AT passport which they believe will help immensely the way people gain access to AT when and where they need it.  </p> <p>AT has brought new approaches in how disabled people and wider society respond to disability.  These changes need to be complemented by a change in our attitudes as well.  Disability is not solely a health matter.  We need to move away from the medical model to a rights-based model.  We need to realise that society's attitude to disability is problematic rather than a person's impairment or difference.  The Government must also realise that it needs to significantly increase its budgetary commitment to the disabled to do the following: cover housing and individual living supports; eliminate poverty and social exclusion which are among the highest in Europe; end the lowest employment rates in Europe; and significantly improve the educational attainment of the disabled community.  I know the Minister of State will lobby and work hard for that.</p> <p>At a broader health level, last week Sinn F&eacute;in launched its &euro;1.1 billion alternative budget for health 2023, Funding Fairer Healthcare.  This is a ten-year ambitious health plan which invests in all the major areas of health provision.  In the context of the disability debate it commits &euro;153 million to the disability capacity review and the children's disability networks teams.  The plan will reduce the cost of healthcare, tackle waiting times, improve primary and community care, and support mental health services.  It can end the current crisis in the health service which is similar in origin to the housing crisis - a failure to plan.  Sinn F&eacute;in's proposals will end the two-tier health system and deliver health and social care on the basis of need, not the ability to pay.</p> <p>I want to conclude my remarks by thanking the Minister of State for her attention and attendance, and for her hard work and commitment to this issue.  I am fully conscious of some of the things I have said in my script.  It probably would have been a different speech had I had the opportunity to prepare it having listened to Senators Conway and Clonan and the contributions emphasising the need for human contact, personal assistance and person-to-person supports as well as the technology.</p> <p>It is quite easy to get caught up in the glamour of innovative technologies and think sin &eacute;, that is a great innovative solution to a problem.  Really it is as fundamental and as basic as what Senator Clonan rightly said, having somebody to lift the tablet, put it on the desk, switch it on, charge it up.  All of those things need to be fully complementary in order to work and deliver.</p> <p>While investing in and prioritising technologies is key and will continue to have a key role in supporting people to live independently and live the fullest possible lives, it is also so important that we get the basics right alongside it, that we get the human touch right in terms of all this going forward.  I really appreciate today's debate and I know we will look to next week's budget with a keen eye to ensure targeted supports are going to the people who need them most.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1682" speakername="Mary Seery Kearney" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#V00400"><p>This is a great opportunity to make statements and look at the innovative developments the Minister of State is leading on in the Department.  I thank her most sincerely for the constant advocacy, work and dedication that she shows in this Department.  I speak about it every week at my own parliamentary party meeting, as I said to the Minister of State before, also to ensure that she gets all of the supports she deserves.  No better woman.  I am very proud to have her as a governmental colleague.  I think she has been extraordinary and very responsive in ways that are often behind the scenes and that nobody really knows about, in the texts she gets from us sometimes at weekends.</p> <p>On assistive technologies, it is great that innovation has moved to such a place that it assists people in living their lives in a more full way.  I completely take on board everything that Senator Clonan said.  His contribution describes that need to ensure we have all the supports.  The lack of occupational therapists, speech and language therapy and all that is a travesty across the entire HSE for children and for everybody who needs those services.  That is a whole other day's debate but I am highlighting the need for assistance in such very practical ways as well as the more developmental ways.</p> <p>I always come back to the cost of disability, the cost of the loss of opportunity for persons to live their best life, which is one of the sayings of the chief executive of Cheeverstown, TJ Duggan.  TJ has always said to me that this is about making sure people live their best life.  Everybody should have equality of opportunity and assistive technology provides that as long as we have all of the clinical services and supports, as long as we have connectivity.  I am very pleased that broadband has been rolled out and I thank my own party colleagues for that.  We need things like that to make sure there is connectivity wherever people are.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Mary Seery Kearney:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=&amp;amp;pid=MarySeeryKearney&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There are opportunities in employment.  Now that we are working to a hybrid model of employment, there is an opportunity for people with disabilities, mobility issues or challenges to work in a home office that is set up properly, so that they can have the opportunity to reach out and have such access to the workforce.</p><p>Under health and safety law, there is an obligation for a risk assessment to be done.  Risk assessment is essentially the planning for every scenario that might arise, whether it arises or not.  Some part of me believes that schools and employers should be obliged to perform access assessments and inability assessments in the context of enabling.  We are working on universal design, as mentioned by the Minister of State during the Commencement debate.  I know how much we talk about this on the housing committing, and the Minister of State, Deputy Peter Burke, has been instrumental in that.</p><p>I am about to take on an intern who will rely heavily on his assistance dog.  When thinking about that I wonder how that will work in the context of Leinster House, accessibility, and working in my office.  The college has said that there is no problem with him working from home.  I do not want him to work from home.  I want him to have the experience of being in Leinster House.  I want him to have the fullest experience of being an intern in the same way anyone else would have as an intern.  There is no document that I can reach to that has foreseen this and outlines systems in place.  There is nothing I can reach to for in the way one might if it related to health and safety - that is me speaking while wearing my employment lawyer hat.  There is a way to plan and there should be an obligation to plan for such situations.  What do employers do and where do they go to on this?  I know the voluntary and sectoral organisations probably have assistance but the question is whether it is formalised.  These are matters we need to be thinking about.  I appreciate I have gone over time and I thank the Acting Chair for his indulgence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#W00200"><p>As there are no other Senators offering, I ask the Minister to conclude.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#W00300"><p>As there are no other Senators offering, how much time do I have?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#W00400"><p>It is open-ended.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#W00500"><p>Open-ended is even better.  We will make it more intimate so that we can address the matters on which Senators engaged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#W00600"><p>Marvellous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#W00700"><p>I thank my good colleague, Senator O'Donovan, for bringing us through a step in time to explain how organisations were set up and put in place in remote parts of Ireland to support families with disabilities who could not get into larger urban areas to seek support.  The Senator mentioned CoAction which is an organisation that has supported a large part of south Cork in the delivery of services.  It continues to do so and it has grown and grown.</p> <p>Senator Clonan is right.  The topic of assistive technology is wonderful, but it is only as good as the people who are supporting the persons with disabilities.  It is an enabler and a communication piece.  It is not and can never be seen as the end piece.  To any providers watching these proceedings I say that this is not a get-out-of-jail card for support individuals.  I am trying to ensure that we have equity of access for all people with disabilities, no matter where they live, and in enabling them to participate in work and social life, communication with friends and growing that friendship base.  However, that does not take away from my responsibility or the responsibility of Government, or providers of HSE services, in ensuring that we have properly funded PA and home support services.  That is and has always been a fundamental piece of my budgetary process.  Last year, I was quite happy to say that I grew the budget for PAs by six times that of the previous year's budget.  I will continue to do so for the simple reason as mentioned by Senator Clonan.  His son, Eoghan, should not have to lose his PA during the summer because he is not in college.  Eoghan's life does not stop when he leaves college.  He needs to be able to participate equally throughout the summer weeks, no different from the rest of the household.  That is what everyone needs to have.  That is why it will be a priority for me during the budgetary process that the PA provision will stay in place.  This is important for all Senators.  Not only will it stay in place, but we were not equal in how we paid the staff delivering PA or home support.  We paid them a lower wage than we pay those working in older person services.  That is why we have struggled to attract people into the delivery of such services.  This is not to give anything away.  Let us be clear: I do not have any money bagged yet.  I am before Senators in the Seanad now and I have to return to more meetings about money at 4 p.m.  I have nothing bagged.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1644" speakername="Martin Conway" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#W00800"><p>We have every confidence in the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1484" speakername="Anne Rabbitte" time="10:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2022092200002#W00900"><p>I would like to ensure that I can bring about equity for the staff who deliver PA and home support services, thereby having a good pool of people we can go to so that we are not left short of people, and at the same time, grow the budget of that piece this year.  That will support people with physical disabilities or behavioural challenges, or whatever they may face, be it part of the work or education piece.</p> <p>I refer to the devices.  Senator Clonan gave the example of lifting a laptop and the skeletal device that Eoghan missed out on because he did not have that intervention.  Senator Carrigy, who joins us in the debate, and I have talked about this on numerous times.  We do not need all of them to be clinicians.  We need people who can support the delivery of what is prescribed.  They can be assistants in occupational therapy, speech and language, or physiotherapy.  There does not need to be a weekly meeting with a physiotherapist, but the programme that has been put in place needs to be delivered, sustained and maintained until the programme is followed up six or eight weeks later with a senior level clinician.  I genuinely believe we need to make that step change within the delivery of services and not be so protective of the clinicians and their base.  We need to look to the assistant role as well.  That will be part of the progressing disability services, PDS, roadmap I am sharing with Senators today, so that every child will have a continuation of delivery and access to services.</p> <p>As I have travelled around I have listened to parents.  Some have told me that their child, who is in non-verbal, has access to a tablet with different apps.  That is an affordablity issues and that is wrong.  We should never deny a person the right to communicate.  All of us here have a great opportunity in that we can speak.  We can articulate ourselves through our voices.  By denying people the right to communicate, we are denying them the right to have their rights and voice heard.  I fundamentally believe in the rights and voice of the child, for which I have always campaigned.  We need to look to assistive technology and the augmentative and alternative communication, AAC, system such as PECS, so that from an early stage we train the early-years providers on what this device is about.  We can then enable children to participate in the room by using their devices with the PECS programme so that they are not frustrated.  That should follow on into national school and post-primary school.  It is an enabling tool, while not being the only piece.  It would ensure that users can participate and say, for example, that they would prefer Ribena to water.  Simple things make a huge difference to people.</p> <p>That is my role regarding technology.  What I am looking for from within technology comes from a very basic level.  It is like the communication board in playgrounds.  That is technology.  We do not have them in every playground around the country, although we should have.  I would like to see some of my one-off funding going to such initiatives, while at the same time letting our innovative, digital people working in services know how they could bridge gaps to support people.  My colleague talked about the health passport.  I do believe in getting that up and running through funding.  They are the pieces we need to develop.  If is for the people who have been sitting there long enough saying "If we had this, it would work".  It would provide collaboration.</p> <p>Senator Conway and I were at the launch of the IA Labs about six months ago.  His story is excellent because he explained that with investment and changing times, developments are changing to meet the needs of people.  What we learned from the Senator's story is that the 12 months it took to introduce a piece of technology did not help us.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Anne Rabbitte:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=33&amp;amp;MemberID=2436"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2436&amp;amp;pid=AnneRabbitte&amp;amp;year=2022&amp;amp;month=09&amp;amp;day=22"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is exactly what children experience in school.  That is exactly that experience.  The procurement piece that tethered Senator Lombard is tethering so many more families as well.  Health is based on a needs-led approach in that the need is identified and the support should be there.  When we have a diagnosis or the child has a need, we should not have to be waiting for the three procurements.  What we should be doing is going to what is best in the field.</p><p>I know a lady from the Senator's good side in Cork who needs assistance with a car seat.  The child has scoliosis.  At the same time, she needs to have that car seat.  She has been refused the car seat in the past number of weeks for the third time.  The child needs to have it because she has to travel to school.  She has to hold a particular position and if she does not, given the regression that is going on, she just might not have the scoliosis operation.  She should not have to wait to see when and where she can get that.  We should have on our appendix board where that can be sourced, that the seat needs to be provided and that it is verified and proved that the seat is what is needed for the child and it should be given.  Waiting is what frustrates parents completely.</p><p>A number of us here might have met a young lady from the Carlow side who did the junior certificate exam.  Her case was to do with the pictures on her English-paper exam.  It is very much down to how a student's scribe would describe what was in the picture.  One has to see what is in the picture to understand what one is seeing.  The student is dependent on a second person to interpret what it should be.  Another person has interpreted the picture but the student has to formulate an answer on it.  It is not just black and white.  That held her back considerably in doing the junior certificate.  She felt at a disadvantage because pictures were used a number of times.  The exam was actually on the French syllabus.  I apologise.  The use of these pictures meant that, on a number of her questions, she felt she was being held back completely.  We need to think twice as to how we set papers and about the people that are sitting the papers in that the students have to be totally and utterly easily able to access them.  I will support Senator Conway's campaign.</p><p>Having people able to access employment is the most important piece.  It breaks down a considerable barrier.  Senator Seery Kearney brought it up.  I met with the T&aacute;naiste approximately two years ago.  I have to be very fair to him.  We were talking about the hubs all over the country.  He asked how his Department could help.  I said we need to make sure that the digital hubs are accessible.  Having the digital hubs accessible would mean having a cubby or the sensory room within the hubs, the accommodation being right at the front and proper changing facilities provided within for people with physical, behavioural or sensory disabilities.  Guess what is happening in the PorterShed in Galway, which is PorterShed No. 3?  I see every one of those bars being hit.  That lets me know that Departments are listening and they are actioning.  There is comfort within that but we need to see it happen nationally.  That means that people can participate in employment.  They can participate if they wish to in the hub, but they can also work remotely at the same time, to prevent isolation and everything else.  Progress is being made.</p><p>As the Senator can see, I do not see technology as the final solution.  No different to the Sinn F&eacute;in Senator, my colleague, it is wonderful for me to hear the real-life stories because they shape how I respond to things.  The Senators share with me and I share with them.  That is my thinking within the Department.  It is quite difficult some times to break that down.  It does not come in a chapter and verse, as the Senator said, when it comes to how we can take on people who might be visually impaired or who might have a physical disability within Leinster House.  If we have the challenge, so do schools and people taking on interns everywhere else.</p><p>As to the rule book on what is best code of practice, maybe some disability organisation or disabled persons' organisation, DPO, listening into us today might help us in writing or putting together best practices for interns or taking on somebody for work experience or best practice for the Houses of Oireachtas, which I am not faulting whatsoever.  However, service checks could be done on the lifts around the Houses on a regular basis to ensure that they are working and to ensure that, no matter what chair or cane the people that arrive in are using, they can move freely and as independently as possible and be given the respect of dignity and inclusion.</p><p>As it was a very close grouping, I decided to go on a little bit.  I thank everybody for the opportunity.  I wish to get a decent sum in the budget to assist with assistive technology.  While there are big visions, the day-to-day pieces make an awful difference in life.  It may mean that people can access that technology from very early years and become dependent.  At the same time, the human touch cannot be forgotten about.  It is not a get-out-of-jail card for anyone.  It is an enabler for the young person to be able to communicate.</p><p>I will finish on trikes and bikes.  The Senators may have seen Variety do something about it recently.  I remember this time last year when I had to negotiate within my Department because I did not have enough money.  I had to go to ask the Minister, Deputy Eamon Ryan, because I was short money for trikes.  Trikes are not to be seen as fun toys for kids with disabilities.  I see that movement as occupational therapy.  Between the two of us, we managed to muster enough money for 32 trikes, at a cost.  They are now being rolled out, but there is a waiting list of 190 people.  I wish to see everybody off that waiting list.  That trike is OT.  It is direct intervention.  They can be recycled, upcycled or downcycled, depending on the age, weight, ability or need of the child.  If we put the child at the centre and we wrap it around that way, the Upper and Lower Houses could do a really good job for persons with disability.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2022-09-22a.85" nospeaker="true" time="10:30:00" ><p>Cuireadh an Seanad ar athl&oacute; ar 2.17 p.m. go dt&iacute; me&aacute;n lae, D&eacute; M&aacute;irt, an 27 Me&aacute;n F&oacute;mhair 2022.</p><p>The Seanad adjourned at 2.17 p.m. until 12 noon on Tuesday, 27 September 2022.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>