<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yacute "&#253;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Acirc  "&#194;" > 
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Ecirc  "&#202;" > 
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY Zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#382;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ograve "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY Ograve "&#210;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY ugrave "&#249;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY otilde "&#245;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY ucirc  "&#251;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >
<!ENTITY Uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
<!ENTITY Oslash "&#216;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.1" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="">Prelude</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.2" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Chuaigh an Cathaoirleach i gceannas ar 14:30:00</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.3" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Reflection and Prayer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.4" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Machnamh agus Paidir.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.5" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#A00100">Business of Seanad</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#A00200"><p>I have received notice from Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor that, on the motion for the Commencement of the House today, she proposes to raise the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Health to outline the recommendations of the Chief Medical Officer on the clinical and technical issues associated with transvaginal mesh surgical procedures.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to provide an update on the provision of a permanent building for Gaelscoil Cholmcille, Dublin 17.</blockquote> <p>I have also received notice from Senator Colm Burke of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Education and Skills to review Circular 22/2012 under which persons who take a leave of absence to undertake further studies are prevented from working part time.</blockquote> <p><!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">An Cathaoirleach:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1988"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1988&amp;amp;pid=DenisODonovan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have also received notice from Senator Robbie Gallagher of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Justice and Equality to provide an update on the role of the data controller in community closed circuit television, CCTV, schemes.</blockquote><p>I have also received notice from Senator Brian &Oacute; Domhnaill of the following matter:</p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Children and Youth Affairs to provide equitable remuneration to m&uacute;inteoir&iacute; r&eacute;amhscoile, pre-school teachers.  </blockquote><p>I have also received notice from<b></b>Senator Martin Conway<b></b>of the following matter:<b></b></p><blockquote>The need for the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection to provide an update on the reform of the State contributory pension.</blockquote><p>Of the matters raised by the Senators suitable for discussion, I have selected Senators Murnane O'Connor, &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in, Colm Burke and Gallagher and they will be taken now.  I regret I had to rule out of order the matter submitted by Senator Conway on the ground that it is anticipatory of the Second Stage of the Social Welfare, Pensions and Civil Registration Bill 2018, which takes place in the Seanad on Thursday, 6 December 2018.  Senator &Oacute; Domhnaill has withdrawn his Commencement matter which I had originally selected.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.8" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#B00200">Commencement Matters</major-heading>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.9" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#B00300">Medical Products</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#B00400"><p>I thank the Minister of State for coming to the House at a very busy time.  I appreciate the time he is giving me today for this important issue.  I have been contacted by a number of my constituents regarding uro-gynaecological transvaginal mesh implants for the management of stress urinary incontinence or pelvic organ prolapse and the many and often severe complications following these procedures.  My understanding was that the Chief Medical Officer was to prepare a report which was expected to make recommendations in respect of the clinical and technical issues involved.  I am informed that this report had an anticipated publication time of the first two weeks in November, yet we are currently in December.</p> <p>While we awaited this report, a number of significant system actions on mesh implants were advanced on foot of priority recommendations identified during the course of the preparation of that report.  I am aware of this and welcome the swift action in this matter.  I understand all procedures in HSE-funded hospitals involving mesh implants for the management of stress urinary incontinence, a common condition in women following childbirth or at menopause, or of pelvic organ prolapse, where a pelvic organ moves out of place, have been suspended in cases where it is clinically appropriate and safe to do so.</p> <p>There was also a recommendation to ensure that in situations where expert clinical judgment was such that there was an urgency to carry out the procedure and no suitable alternative existed, surgery should have proceeded only if a delay would risk harm to the patient and should be based on multidisciplinary team decisions and fully informed consent.</p> <p>I would like clarification that the suspension of these procedures has actually taken place pending publication of the report, and that no woman is enduring this procedure unless there is an identified risk associated with not carrying it out.  The pause in this procedure was to remain in place pending confirmation of implementation by the HSE, working in conjunction with the Institute of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists and the Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland, of three urgent recommendations in respect of surgical training, informed consent and development of an agreed dataset of mesh procedures.  The HSE has published information concerning the pause on its website for patients affected.  This is no doubt due to pressure applied by the Department and must be welcomed.  When this procedure was introduced in the early 2000s, clinical trials found efficacy and low complication rates for mesh implants used for incontinence.  However, there soon grew to be a body of evidence indicating that efficacy was lower and complication rates higher in cases of pelvic organ prolapse.  In 2012, the mesh was reclassified as high risk, and the United Kingdom has banned this procedure.</p> <p>I would like to know what we in Ireland are doing for these women.  Their lives were changed utterly and they have felt forgotten and left in pain.  The preliminary recommendations of the report identify as urgent the provision of appropriate aftercare for women suffering from mesh complications including appropriate diagnosis facilities.  Can the Minister of State clarify whether these provisions have been put in place?  A learning notice concerning mesh devices in uro-gynaecological procedures was circulated on 26 June 2018 to all maternity hospitals and acute hospitals with gynaecological services to highlight the importance of appropriate patient selection.  Under adequate information and consent, it was also recommended to inform service providers that a response group has been arranged to propose remedies for and address the provision of aftercare for complications.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Jennifer Murnane O'Connor:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2470"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2470&amp;amp;pid=JenniferMurnaneOConnor&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->This is also available online.  I am concerned, however, that this information has not been made widely available and without discrimination to all women who may be affected.  The HSE advises that all patients who have experienced complications due to mesh devices should contact their consultant's clinic in the first instance.  This advice is not getting to women.  Women have contacted my office and I have sent them to their own doctors.  Each hospital group was to have nominated an individual to co-ordinate a response to this group of patients.  Can the Minister of State confirm if this has happened?  Will there be greater awareness made of any recommendations made, and the steps being taken for aftercare and the future patients?  This is such a serious issue.  I have had women coming into my clinics, crying, who are in a very bad situation.  I hope the Minister of State has good news for me on this.  It is unacceptable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#C00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  I am taking this Commencement matter on behalf of the Minister for Health, Deputy Simon Harris.</p> <p>The report to the Minister from Dr. Tony Holohan, Chief Medical Officer, CMO, on the use of urogynaecological mesh in the surgical treatment of stress urinary  incontinence, SUI, and pelvic organ prolapse, POP, in women was published on the Department of Health website on 21 November 2018.  Synthetic mesh devices have been widely used in the surgical treatment of SUI and POP in women over the past two decades.  I accept the Senator's point but controversy about the safety of mesh devices has arisen in many countries because of concerns about the frequency and severity of complications associated with their use.  In responding to these questions and in recognition of the complexity  of the matters arising, the Minister requested the CMO to prepare a report for him on the clinical and technical issues involved in ensuring the safe and effective provision of mesh procedures in urogynaecology and an appropriate response to women who suffer complications as a result of undergoing such procedures.</p> <p>Preparation of the report has involved consultation and engagement with national and international bodies.  The report has been informed by reviews of international reports and safety reviews of mesh surgeries that have been published in recent years.  The report has also been informed by the personal experiences of women who have suffered complications following mesh surgery.  The Minister acknowledges the bravery, commitment and dignity shown by the women he met and by those women who have written to him concerning this issue, in sharing their harrowing and deeply personal experiences.</p> <p>The report identifies that for many women, surgical procedures using synthetic mesh devices have provided a more effective and less invasive form of treatment than traditional SUI and POP procedures.  Mesh devices, however, are associated with significant and severe complications in a minority of women.  These are of concern given the difficulties of mesh implant removal.  The report makes 19 recommendations, including the development of patient information and informed consent materials; surgical professional training and multidisciplinary expertise in units carrying out mesh procedures; the development of clinical guidance; the development of information systems to monitor the ongoing use of mesh devices; ensuring the reporting of mesh-related complications; and ensuring timely, appropriate and accessible care pathways for the management of women with complications.</p> <p>At the CMO's request, a programme of work to advance some of the report's more important recommendations has commenced in the HSE in advance of completion of the report.  The HSE was also asked by the CMO on 24 July to pause all mesh procedures where clinically safe to do so until a number of key recommendations are implemented.  The HSE has a published a dedicated web page about vaginal mesh implants, including contact information for women suffering complications, which I hope is a useful resource and for which we can make the link available.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#D00100"><p>The Minister of State is aware of the seriousness of this issue.  The people I have been dealing with have been trying to go England because the mesh itself cannot be taken out in full, once one has it.  That is a concern.  Evidently, part of the mesh can be taken out.  This is a crucial issue and I ask the Minister of State to convey to the Minister for Health that this cannot happen to anybody else, in particular given the way people have been affected by this.  Their whole lives have changed.  This is an important issue.  I have seen the 19 recommendations and I will return to this issue.  I hope this can be sorted and that no one else will be left in the situation of some of the people I have dealt with over the last few months.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1359" speakername="Finian McGrath" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#D00200"><p>I take the Senator's point.  The Minister for Health is committed to ensuring the safe and effective use of mesh implants and an appropriately and a timely response to women suffering mesh complications.  Last week the Department wrote to the HSE again to request that it prepare a detailed implementation plan for the complete set of recommendations set out in the CMO's report, working in conjunction with other stakeholders.  On another level, the Minister intends to meet with the Mesh Survivors Ireland group in the coming weeks to discuss the report.  I will certainly convey the Senator's genuine concerns to the Minister, Deputy Harris.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.15" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#D00250">School Accommodation</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#D00300"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an gCathaoirleach agus leis an Aire f&eacute;in as a bheith anseo go pearsanta chun an t-&aacute;bhar seo a phl&eacute; liom.  An tseachtain seo caite bh&iacute; m&eacute; istigh i nGaelscoil Cholmcille.  Bh&iacute;odar ag ceili&uacute;radh Bliain na Gaeilge agus bh&iacute; m&eacute; an-t&oacute;gtha leis an m&eacute;id a bh&iacute; ar si&uacute;l ann, idir cheol, dr&aacute;ma&iacute;ocht agus amhr&aacute;na&iacute;ocht.  Gach uair a bh&iacute;m i l&aacute;thair sa scoil ar Bh&oacute;thar Oscar Traynor cuireann an fhoireann ar fad ina lu&iacute; orm go bhfuil s&eacute; thar am d&oacute;ibh foirgneamh buan a bheith acu.  T&aacute; siad ag feitheamh anois n&iacute;os m&oacute; n&aacute; 20 bliain.  C&eacute; go raibh an m&eacute;id sin amhr&aacute;na&iacute;ochta agus dr&aacute;ma&iacute;ochta agus ceol ar si&uacute;l ag na p&aacute;ist&iacute;, bh&iacute; s&eacute; soil&eacute;ir do gach duine go raibh na h&aacute;iseanna agus an halla at&aacute; acu i bhfad r&oacute;-bheag don scoil sin.  T&aacute; an scoil ag iarraidh f&aacute;is agus dul i m&eacute;id agus t&aacute; an-chuid daoine ag iarraidh a bheith ag freastal ar an scoil ach t&aacute; an scoil ag fanacht n&iacute;os m&oacute; n&aacute; 20 bliain ar fhoirgneamh nua.</p> <p>Gaelscoil Cholmcille is doing fantastic work.  It is a very popular local primary school.  Last week I visited the school again and it was impressed upon me once more the fact it is waiting more than 20 years for a permanent building.  There is a site next door which Dublin City Council has plans to develop.  The long-term solution is right there facing the school.  The school is adamant that a process be put in place and that it would have a chance to maximise its potential as a primary school.</p> <p>I know the Minister will share with me his vision that every child will attend a school with a permanent building and can look to the future with a level of confidence.  The confidence within the school has been ebbing away over the last number of years.  When there are announcements of new schools being developed and recognised - nobody has an issue with this - this school seems to be on the end of the list when it comes to achieving what it wants to achieve.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2301"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2301&amp;amp;pid=AodhanORiordan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> I am interested in hearing the Minister's reply.  While he is new to his post, the Irish language is of particular importance to him and he wants to do what is best for everyone.  On behalf of the parents, staff and board of management of Gaelscoil Cholmcille, I note that a positive response would be greatly appreciated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#E00200"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Seanad&oacute;ir as ucht an t-&aacute;bhar t&aacute;bhachtach seo a ard&uacute; inniu.  Is l&eacute;ir &oacute;n teachtaireacht inniu &oacute;n Seanad&oacute;ir go bhfuil fuinneamh dearfach ag dul ar aghaidh sa scoil.  T&aacute; s&eacute; ceart go bhfuil s&eacute; tiom&aacute;nta agam an teanga a bheith ag baili&uacute; nirt amach anseo fosta agus gabhaim mo aitheantas chuig an ceannaireacht th&iacute;os sna scoileanna f&aacute; choinne an tiom&aacute;ntas ar son na teanga.  Mar at&aacute; a fhios ag an Seanad&oacute;ir, t&aacute; Gaelscoil Cholmcille ag obair faoin ethos Catholic agus ag obair faoin fhoras patr&uacute;nacha agus t&aacute; suas le 277 duine &oacute;ige sna mbunscoileanna ag foghlaim tr&iacute; mhe&aacute;n na Gaeilge.  T&aacute; daoine obair sna scoileanna fosta agus t&aacute; 11 cloigeann duine ag obair agus 2.5 duine ag obair i dtaca&iacute;ocht speisialta.</p> <p>In 2008, my Department provided a two-storey, semi-permanent school building consisting of 12 classrooms and ancillary accommodation for Gaelscoil Cholmcille.  As this building has a life span of 25 to 30 years, my Department has no  plans to replace it in the foreseeable future.  However, I take on board what the Senator stated in the context of parents seeking a period of certainty.  I understand that in March 2018 the school submitted an application under my  Department's additional school accommodation scheme seeking the  provision of additional temporary accommodation to provide for a  further mainstream teaching post being appointed for 2018.  Having engaged with the school to seek clarification on aspects of the application, my Department finalised the assessment of the application in September.  I am pleased to confirm that my Department granted approval for the provision of two permanent mainstream classrooms with en suite toilets and a separate assisted user's toilet to address the deficit of accommodation in the Gaelscoil.  The project was devolved for delivery to the Gaelscoil authority.  This means that it is now a matter for the Gaelscoil authority to appoint a consultant and advance the project through the design and construction phases.  Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas ar&iacute;s leis an Seanad&oacute;ir as ucht an t-&aacute;bhar t&aacute;bhachtach seo a ard&uacute; inniu.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1410" speakername="Aodh&aacute;n &Oacute; R&iacute;ord&aacute;in" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#E00300"><p>Ba mhaith liom bu&iacute;ochas a ghabh&aacute;il leis an Aire.  Unfortunately, I find the answer disappointing.  The Minister can appreciate how disappointing it is from the school's point of view, having waited so long for a permanent building only to get an indication from the Department that it does not foresee an opportunity to replace the building because it is a two-storey semi-permanent structure with a lifespan of 25 to 30 years.  I accept what the Minister says about the two permanent classrooms but I note that there is a site beside the school which is to be developed by Dublin City Council.  It is a major development with potential for 500 housing units.  There is a perfect opportunity here for the Department to engage with Dublin City Council regarding the site in order to find a permanent answer for the needs of this school.  I implore the Minister.  To say that a temporary building has a 25 to 30-year lifespan, considering that it is already ten years old, does not provide much succour to the people who care about the school.  I ask that the Department engages with Dublin City Council to find a long-term solution for this much-loved and needed school in this community.  I ask the Minister to engage more imaginatively to find a permanent solution.  This school and its current and future pupils deserve no less.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#E00400"><p>Chuala m&eacute; an teachtaireacht inniu.  I hear the message.  I place this in the context of the pressure the Department has been under over many decades.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Even going back to the late 1970s and the 1980s, many flat-roofed schools were built and they are still fit for purpose and being used today.  The Department is looking at a type of retrofit project that will address environmental and sustainability issues for schools built before 2008.  The accommodation in question was built prior to 2008 and I understand that parents and the community want a more permanent solution.</p><p>In the context of options involving alternative sites - and the Senator has come forward with options - one thing I have to say about the officials, who I have only got to know in recent weeks, is that they are very flexible and adapt to new suggestions and ideas.  Obviously, I am trying to get a figure for the budget that has been spent in the areas of Wicklow, Kildare, Meath and Dublin in the past ten years, given there has been phenomenal growth in population and we must add that to the pressures and constraints on new buildings.  I understand that when parents hear of other announcements of new schools, they obviously ask what is the situation regarding this school.  We have a ten-year capital plan and the Project Ireland 2040 plan, which points to the space we will be in by 2040.  I know parents and others in the community are not living in a space where they believe this is to be realised by 2040, but that we start working in that capital space in terms of how we get there over that period.</p><p>Cloisim an teachtaireacht &oacute;n Seanad&oacute;ir.  Ba mhaith liom mo aitheantas a ghabh&aacute;il leis f&aacute; choinne seans a thabhairt dom labhairt ar Ghaelscoil Cholmcille - ainm deas agus ceangal le mo chontae f&eacute;in, T&iacute;r Chonaill.  Nuair a bh&iacute;onn togra&iacute; scoile ar intinn ag Seanad&oacute;ir&iacute;, b&iacute;onn mo chluasa foscailte.  Beidh m&eacute; ag labhairt le mo chomhghleacaithe chun n&iacute;os m&oacute; sonra&iacute; a fh&aacute;il i dtaobh st&aacute;das an togra at&aacute;thar ag iarraidh a bhaint amach &oacute; bh&iacute; 2008 ann, agus i dtaobh an plean n&oacute; an bealach a bheidh de dh&iacute;th go dt&iacute; go mbeidh foirgneamh n&iacute;os fearr ag an scoil sa todhcha&iacute;.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.22" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#F00150">Special Educational Needs Staff</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#F00200"><p>I welcome the Minister and thank him for coming before the House to deal with this issue.  I know a number of special needs assistants who have gone back to further education who have advised me that departmental circular letter 22/2012 prevents them from taking on any employment.  The circular states:</p><blockquote>7.1 The taking up of regular paid employment of any kind elsewhere in the State while on career break would be contrary to the objectives of the scheme and shall lead to refusal of an application or withdrawal of approval already given.<br /><br />7.2 A special needs assistant on a career break is precluded from taking up an appointment in any capacity in any school within the state.</blockquote> <p>This circular came into force in 2012 when jobs were scarce.  I fully appreciate why these were the criteria set down in respect of special needs assistants who took career breaks.  The people who contacted me are those who have gone back to further education.  They are paying full college fees because they are mature students and they are technically precluded from taking on any type of employment while on career break.</p><p>It is time to review circular 22/2012, taking into account that some schools are finding it difficult to get replacements, for example, where a special needs assistant goes out sick, and this is particularly the case in areas outside Dublin.  I ask the Minister to review this matter.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Colm Burke:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2353"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2353&amp;amp;pid=ColmBurke&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I am talking specifically about people going back to further education and they should not be penalised in this way that prevents them from taking on employment.  I ask for the matter to be reviewed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#G00200"><p>I thank the Senator for the opportunity to address the matter regarding the career break scheme for special needs assistants.  In accordance with the Education Act, the terms and conditions of employment of special needs assistants employed in approved posts funded by moneys provided by the Oireachtas are determined by the Minister for Education and Skills, with the concurrence of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.</p><p>Special needs assistants are recruited specifically to assist in the care of pupils with disabilities who have additional and significant care needs in an educational context.  They may be appointed to a special school or a mainstream school to assist school authorities in making suitable provision for a pupil or pupils with special care needs.  The first priority is that the care needs of the pupils are met on an ongoing basis during the school year.  In June 2012, my Department, in conjunction with the school management bodies and the relevant trade unions, agreed a career break scheme for special needs assistants in recognised primary and post-primary schools, the provisions of which are contained in Circular 22/2012, which is available on my Department's website.</p><p>Paragraph 1.2 of the circular states:</p><blockquote>The main objectives of this scheme below, which are not exhaustive, is for employers, wherever possible to facilitate applicants in the areas of:<br /><br />- Personal Development <br /><br />- Education (including teacher training) <br /><br />- Public Representation <br /><br />- Childcare/Dependent care <br /><br />- Self-employment</blockquote> <p>The career break scheme therefore is applicable to special needs assistants who wish to pursue courses such as teacher training where participants are required to spend significant periods of time on school observation or teaching practice during the school year.  The taking up of regular paid employment while on career break would be contrary to the objectives of the career break scheme and such applications shall be refused by the employer.</p><p>Paragraph 4.2 of the circular states, &quot;A career break shall be a period of not less than one school year and may be extended on an annual basis provided the total period of the career break does not exceed five years at any one time.&quot;.  Thus the priority of my Department is to ensure that the continuity of care and the welfare needs of pupils take precedence over all other considerations in the granting and duration of career breaks.  I thank Senator Burke for affording me the opportunity to respond to the House on this matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1409" speakername="Colm Burke" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#G00300"><p>The circumstances have changed since this regulation was introduced.  The point being made to me by these special needs assistants is that they are trying to further their career.  They have gone back to full-time education and are not in receipt of any income.  Under regulations, they are prevented from getting any kind of income, and this policy should be reviewed.  I fully accept the Minister's comments about facilitating special needs assistants who wish to pursue courses such as teacher training where participants are required to spend significant periods under school observation.  They are prepared for that but the Minister knows the cost of rent and day-to-day living.  It is not physically possible for them to take time out of a full-time job, go back to college where they pay fees, all the while being prevented under regulations from taking on any type of employment.  I ask that the matter be carefully examined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1290" speakername="Joe McHugh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#G00400"><p>The Senator is being quite reasonable in his representation today.  He has spoken to a cohort of people doing tremendous work and who are very much part of the school "infrastructure", for want of a better word.  It may not be a good word but it signifies the value that students, teachers and principals place on the role of special needs assistants so integral as they are to the running of a school.  They are very much part of the ecosystem.  We are looking at reviewing the role of the SNAs and this will provide an opportunity to feed in the sentiments and observations made by the Senator today.  Maybe this matter can be considered in that context.</p> <p>I refer again to the contribution of SNAs.  There will be an increase next year and upwards of almost 16,000 SNAs will be employed; we announced another 900 in the recent budget.  This demonstrates the value of and demand for those SNAs.  In 2011 there were approximately 455 special classes but that number has increased this year to almost 1,500.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Joe McHugh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=2018"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2018&amp;amp;pid=JoeMcHugh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is the position in terms of the demand.  Obviously, it also reflects the growing choices parents have as to whether they want their children to go to a special school or to special classes within mainstream schools, be they ASD units or other forms of provision.</p><p>The most important point with regard to SNAs is the role they play.  They provide one-to-one help and support but they also play an all-inclusive, all-school role.  They play a fundamental role in education.  I acknowledge the work they have done and continue to do and obviously they will have a future role in our education system.  That is why we are going to carry out a comprehensive review of SNAs.  I will keep the Senator and this House posted on developments.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.29" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#H00200">Closed-Circuit Television Systems Provision</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#H00300"><p>I thank the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Flanagan, for taking time from his schedule to be here.  I wish to discuss closed-circuit television, CCTV, schemes and the delays being experienced in that regard.  The Minister will agree that CCTV is an invaluable tool in the context of deterring people from engaging in crime or public disorder.  In addition, CCTV can greatly assist the Garda in respect of public order issues or crimes during the investigation process and for the purpose of identifying those involved.  Most importantly, CCTV gives comfort and security to communities throughout the country where there is a CCTV scheme in operation.</p> <p>Last week, there was an incident in Monaghan town in which a young man was viciously assaulted late in the evening.  Unfortunately, incidents of this nature are occurring too often.  People are exhausted.  They are sick and tired of public order offences and public disorder in the streets.  The benefit of a properly running CCTV scheme cannot be underestimated with regard to such activity.  Garda numbers are not what we would wish them to be and in situations where garda&iacute; are not on the streets, the part CCTV can play is immeasurable.  While CCTV will not replace the garda&iacute;, it is important that we have CCTV schemes in operation.</p> <p>With that in mind it is disappointing that delays are being experienced with schemes that should have been up and running long ago.  There is a responsibility on the Government to ensure the schemes are implemented without delay.  I understand that part of the problem relates to a general data protection regulation, GDPR, issue and who the data controller is.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Robbie Gallagher:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2471"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2471&amp;amp;pid=RobbieGallagher&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is an ongoing dispute or impasse between the City and County Managers Association, CCMA, and the Department regarding the role of data controller.  Meanwhile, as this impasse continues, assaults and other serious crimes are happening on a daily basis in many towns throughout the country.  I heard recently that CCTV cameras were installed in Littleton, County Tipperary, more than 12 months ago but are not yet up and running.  I am sure the Minister will agree that this is simply not good enough.  Surely when it comes to matters of policing, responsibility lies with An Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and not with the local authorities.  I am hoping that the Minister will be able to shed some light on this issue in order that CCTV schemes that are at an impasse at the moment can progress and people will have the added security of knowing that the schemes are operational in their towns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#J00200"><p>I thank the Senator for raising this important issue.  I hear about CCTV schemes from many groups all over the country and in my capacity as a rural Deputy, I am fully aware of the desire for CCTV in local areas.  I appreciate the sense of security that CCTV brings to many communities.  In responding to community demand, the Government has made significant funding available to assist groups who wish to establish community CCTV in their areas.  The grant aid scheme administered by my Department is intended to run for three years, with the sum of &euro;1 million available each year.</p><p>The Senator will appreciate that there are a number of legal requirements in setting up of CCTV systems.  Such systems are installed for the purpose of crime prevention and as aids to policing in areas to which the public routinely have access such as town centres.  CCTV systems fall into two distinct but complementary categories, namely Garda CCTV systems and community-based CCTV systems.  Neither type of system can be set up without an appropriate authorisation by the Garda Commissioner under section 38 of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005.  There are further requirements for community CCTV, which is governed by section 38(3)<i>(c)</i>of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na Act 2005 and the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na CCTV order of 2006.  The legal framework requires that any proposed community CCTV scheme must, in the first instance, be approved by the local joint policing committee, JPC, have the authorisation of the Garda Commissioner, often on foot of a recommendation from the local Garda crime prevention officer and must have the prior support of the relevant local authority.  In this regard, it must be noted that the local authority must act as data controller.  I must emphasise that this is the legal basis for all community CCTV schemes, regardless of whether grant funding is sought from my Department to assist in their setting up.  </p><p>In accordance with this legal framework, the large majority of local authorities have previously undertaken to act as data controllers in the context of specific community CCTV schemes.  This has been the case either in the course of the current grant aid scheme administered by my Department, during previous grant aid schemes operated by Pobal on behalf of my Department or in connection with schemes funded independently by local authorities.  I understand from my Department's engagement with the Local Government Management Agency, LGMA, that the total number of local authorities that have undertaken the role of data controller for these purposes amounts to 28 out of a total of 31 local authorities nationwide.  I am also pleased to inform the Senator that the Data Protection Commission, DPC,  issued guidance on data protection and community CCTV on 29 November.  The guidance, which is available on the DPC website, confirms that there is a legal basis for community-based CCTV and that the general data protection regulation, GDPR, does not introduce any new barriers in that regard.  In particular, the DPC confirms that data protection legislation does not stand in the way of the roll-out of community-based CCTV schemes that have been authorised by the Garda Commissioner.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Charles Flanagan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=414"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=414&amp;amp;pid=CharlesFlanagan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->It also states that once the local authority in the administrative area concerned is willing to take on and deliver on its responsibilities as the data controller for the schemes concerned, there is no legal impediment under data protection legislation to the scheme commencing.<br/><br/>The guidance covers a number of other issues also.  For example, it confirms that local authorities are not required, as a result of their role as data controller, to monitor CCTV live feeds on a continuous basis.  I am confident that this and other clarifications in the note will be of significant assistance to local authorities in terms of how they carry out their role under law in relation to community CCTV.<br/><br/>The Office of the Data Protection Commissioner is also currently conducting an audit of issues, including the practice, operation and governance of CCTV.  Again, I expect the more detailed findings of that process to be of assistance to all concerned and, in particular, to local authorities.  The Senator may also wish to be aware that my Department is also engaging on an ongoing basis with the Local Government Management Agency and the County and City Management Association, CCMA, to clarify any queries that might arise.<br/><br/>A Programme for a Partnership Government commits to supporting investment in CCTV systems and, as I have said, my Department is administering a grant aid scheme to assist groups in the establishment of community based CCTV systems in their local areas.  Eligible groups can apply for grant aid of up to 60% of the total capital cost of the proposed system, up to a maximum total of &euro;40,000.  To date, there have been 27 applications to the scheme, of which 20 have been approved for grant aid, totalling more than &euro;500,000.  A further four applications to the scheme are currently being assessed and considered.  The remaining three applications have been returned to the applicants concerned to enable them to supply the information necessary to qualify for grant aid.<br/><br/>I assure the Senator that all interested groups, in both rural and urban areas, can take advantage of the availability of this grant aid scheme.  If the Senator is aware of community groups wishing to avail of the scheme, full details of the grant aid package are available to download from my Department's website <i>www.justice.ie</i>and support and guidance is available to help interested groups to apply for this funding through a dedicated email address, which is <i>communitycctv@justice.ie.</i></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1396" speakername="Robbie Gallagher" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#K00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his comprehensive response on the important issue of CCTV that I have raised.  I have spoken to a number of local authorities and as far as they are concerned, this impasse continues to exist so I am a bit confused in that regard.  Can the Minister confirm that the difficulties the CCMA were having are now resolved?  Another issue that came up for smaller local authorities, in particular, was the cost incurred by them in administering such a CCTV scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1233" speakername="Charles Flanagan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#K00300"><p>I am confident the guidance issued recently by the Office of the Data Protection Commissioner regarding data protection will be helpful to all those concerned and I put on the record my thanks to those local authorities which have already supported their communities in setting up such schemes.  I assure them that my officials are doing all they can to further streamline and simplify the process.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.36" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#K00400">Message from Dáil</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#K00500"><p>D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann passed the Social Welfare, Pensions and Civil Registration Bill 2018 on 29 November 2018, to which the agreement of Seanad &Eacute;ireann is desired.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.38" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 3.20 p.m. and resumed at 3.30 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.39" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00100">Order of Business</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00200"><p>The Order of Business is No. 1, motion regarding opt-in under a protocol to a measure in the area of the Asylum Migration and Integration Fund, AMFI, referral to committee, to be taken without debate on the conclusion of the Order of Business; No. 2, annual national transition statements, Climate Action and Low Carbon Development Act 2015, to be taken at 4.45 p.m. and to conclude at 6.15 p.m.  The opening round shall comprise statements not exceeding five minutes from seven Ministers or Ministers of State.  What am I reading?  This is a mistake.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00300"><p>That seems daft.  How many Ministers of State will we have?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00400"><p>The second round shall comprise statements not exceeding eight minutes by group spokespersons.  A Minister of State shall make a concluding statement, which shall not exceed five minutes.  No. 3 is the Employment (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill 2017 - Committee Stage, to be taken at 6.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00500"><p>I wish to confirm that time can be shared on No. 2, in case Members are keen to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00600"><p>If that is agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00700"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00800"><p>Is it ending today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N00900"><p>Yes, No. 2 is concluding today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#N01000"><p>I wish to raise the issue of rough sleepers.  A count last night showed 156 people were sleeping rough in Dublin, and that included 121 people in the Dublin City Council area.  Anthony Flynn, the CEO of the Inner City Helping Homeless charity, alluded to the fact that if those rough sleeping in the suburbs were taken into account, the figure would be as high as 200.  I heard him speak on the radio recently about a new phenomenon of people pitching tents on beaches in the Portmarnock and Killiney areas.  A total of 9,724 people are living in emergency accommodation.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Ardagh:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2473"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2473&amp;amp;pid=CatherineArdagh&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Many of the emergency hostels opened last year are closing because their leases are running out.  I raised this issue last week but it will become critical in the coming days as the weather worsens.  Rain, sleet and snow are forecast.  What does the Government intend to do to tackle the problem of rough sleepers?  It is a problem that is not getting better.  It is getting worse, and people are finding themselves in very difficult circumstances.</p><p>The second issue I want to raise concerns the Children and Family Relationships (Amendment) Act.  When will the Government commence the Act?  I have been contacted by families in same-sex marriages and unions who are very much in a legal limbo in respect of the civil parentage of their children.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O00200"><p>Hear, hear.  Well said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1407" speakername="Catherine Ardagh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O00300"><p>The Minister has alluded to technical difficulties but it is very unfair to leave parents, children and families in a position where they are unclear as to the civil patronage of their children and the way they will be treated by the State, especially in accident and emergency-type situations, which can be very upsetting.</p> <p>The third issue I want to raise is the backlog of cases at the Office of the Financial Services and Pensions Ombudsman.  There is a very large number of outstanding complaints yet to be dealt with by that office, which is a last port of call for consumers who are having difficulties getting anywhere with various financial institutions.  There has been an increase of 40% in those numbers from the beginning of 2018 to the end of October.  Many issues regarding unresolved tracker mortgage cases arose last year and have arisen again this year.  The Office of the Financial Services and Pensions Ombudsman needs to be better resourced in order to ensure consumers are not waiting in limbo for their complaint about financial concerns or irregularities to be determined.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O00400"><p>I would like to raise a number of matters that have come into the public domain internationally in the past week.  In particular, the G20 summit in Buenos Aires featured Crown Prince Mohammed bin Salman-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O00500"><p>Murderer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O00600"><p>-----being feted by the other members of the leading economies internationally.  We in this House are very much muted in expressing any views on international affairs.  When we do express views, such as on the occupied territories legislation, which I hope will be debated and concluded in the House tomorrow, we come under a major push-back from the Department of Foreign Affairs for standing up for even the basic-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O00700"><p>Human rights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O00800"><p>-----human rights of people.  I believe we should have a debate on Saudi Arabia-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O00900"><p>Hear, hear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#O01000"><p>-----and the opportunity to express our disgust at the slaughter of Jamal Khashoggi in the Saudi consulate in Istanbul and our revulsion at the fact that the person responsible for that atrocity is still striding the world like a colossus and being greeted by international statespeople.</p> <p>We should also make time to debate what is happening to the Republic of Ukraine.  It is wrong that the Russian Federation should use the fact that it built a bridge from Crimea to the mainland of Russia as a pretext to cut off access to the ports of Ukraine.  Somebody in this Legislature should stand up and say those actions are wrong and inform Putin that those standards of behaviour are unacceptable.  Unless those comments are made repeatedly, until there are resolutions of this House condemning these actions and until the timidity of Iveagh House disappears and voices are clearly expressed on these types of issues, these thugs internationally take acquiescence as approval.  I ask the Deputy Leader to make time available for us to discuss these important issues.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michael McDowell:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=719"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=719&amp;amp;pid=MichaelMcDowellPD&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We are not like <i>The Skibbereen Eagle</i>.  This is a legislative Chamber in one of the member states of the European Union.  As such, we should have the bravery and self-respect to speak our mind on these issues and collectively condemn what requires to be condemned, rather than remain mute and watch these matters as consumers of news and readers of newspapers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P00200"><p>Senator Norris used a particular word to describe the Saudi Crown Prince.  Nothing has been proven.  The Senator should be a bit more temperate in his language.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P00300"><p>I am sorry, but I did not hear what the Cathaoirleach said.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P00400"><p>You called somebody a murderer.  That is most inappropriate for this Chamber.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P00500"><p>Well he is one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.64" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P00600"><p>The Senator should reflect on that.  I call Senator Conway-Walsh.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P00700"><p>You should reflect on it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P00800"><p>He is not here to defend himself.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1378" speakername="Rose Conway Walsh" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P00900"><p>As yesterday was International Day of Persons with Disabilities, I will focus on two separate issues relating to people with disabilities.</p> <p>On the provision of personal assistants, there was an excellent presentation in the AV room earlier hosted by Deputy &Oacute; Caol&aacute;in, whom I commend on all of his work, as Chair of the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality, for people with disabilities.  I also commend the speakers who attended, particularly James Cawley and Shelly Gaynor.  They talked about the importance of the personal assistance, PA, scheme that is in operation, how it must be implemented as part of the ratification of optional protocol, how important it is to differentiate between home care or home help hours and the PA system that needs to be in operation, and that we need 500,000 more hours to be able to do what needs to be done for the PA programme.  They described the PA system as an extension of themselves and about the decision-making being left to them.  I remembered Michael Corbett, who was a great advocate for the PA system, when he spoke about how the only true experts on disability are those people who have disabilities.  The PA system allows people to live a full life and make their own decisions about where they want to go and what they want to do within society, which is important.</p> <p>James and Shelly also discussed the transition from education to employment and the importance of having a PA system or PA supports in place for that.  We need to legislate and invest in standardisation of the PA system.  It resonated with me when Ms Gaynor stated that the PA system has been eroded over the years and, instead of people being given full-time PAs to enable them to get the best out of their lives, make their own decisions and implement those decisions, they are given 42 or 45 minutes a day, which is of no use whatsoever.  Shelly asked what it is possible to do in 42 minutes and answered the question by saying, "Feck all".  I have to agree with her on that.  It is important to get that system up in place and provide the extra hours.  It is also important that the Disability (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill is put in place because it will deal with some of the issues I have raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#P01000"><p>I strongly support Senator Ardagh in what she said about gay parents and their rights.  The Bill is not yet fully implemented.  I have received a large number of inquiries about this from distressed parents and I wrote to the Minister about it earlier.  I strongly support the Senator and I thank her for raising the matter.</p> <p>A regime was recently adopted for visitors entering Leinster House.  It is a nonsense.  Computer terminals and machines have been erected and people must enter all of their information, etc.  It is not secure.  In the old days, we used to sign people in personally, but this is a lack of security.  It takes forever, it creates bad-tempered crowds, the staff agrees it is a complete and utter nonsense, and it is all part of the growing bureaucracy under which Leinster House is being strangled.</p> <p>Unfortunately, I will be unable to attend the forthcoming debate on the Employment (Miscellaneous Provisions) Bill.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator David Norris:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=1758"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=1758&amp;amp;pid=DavidNorris&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I have been given a brief by IALPA and I am sure my colleagues, whom I see nodding, have been given the same.  I hope they will take up the issues raised by the airline pilots, in particular the crucial element of bogus self-employment used by employers to do employees out of their rights.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#Q00200"><p>God bless Ryanair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#Q00300"><p>The security matter the Senator has raised is more a matter for the commission than for the Acting Leader.  Perhaps he should send a note to the commission asking it to consider the method being adopted at the moment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1392" speakername="David Norris" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#Q00400"><p>The commission loves bureaucracy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#Q00500"><p>The Acting Leader is probably not in a position to answer that, but I will leave her deal with it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1438" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#Q00600"><p>I wish to raise an issue that arose yesterday and has arisen on several occasions in recent years, which is the closure of English language schools.  I lay the blame firmly at the door of the Departments of Justice and Equality, and Education and Skills.  Both Departments have failed to regulate English language schools resulting in a number of such schools becoming visa factories.  When I heard yesterday that one of the students paid &euro;1,000 for his course in an English language school, it confirmed that this school simply distributes visas.  It also suggests that the school was bound to fail because the fees being charged would not allow it to survive.</p> <p>There is a failure to inspect these schools and a failure to verify the type of education going on there.  There is a failure in proper regulation, particularly on the part of the Department of Justice and Equality, which issues visas to students coming to Ireland based on the fact that schools are registered with it.  They may have no qualified teachers or anyone competent enough to run the school, yet they allow students to come in, provide them with visas and allow them to work at low cost.  It is driving the industry down in that it is allowing teachers to be paid low salaries as a result of these visa factories.</p> <p>There are a number of good English language schools.  This country has a good reputation for education but this situation is ruining that reputation.  Some schools want to be regulated so that they can partake in the proper education of students coming to Ireland and not these visa factory schools.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1395" speakername="Jennifer Murnane O'Connor" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#Q00700"><p>I wish to raise an issue with the Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government.  Something is very broken in the system when between 15,000 and 20,000 protesters lined the streets last weekend to protest the Government's policies on housing.  We are all working hard but there is no joined-up thinking.  People are overspending on rent and the State is not building the houses that are needed with the kind of living spaces people want and in places they want to live and work affordably.</p> <p>We have a beautiful accessible island but everything is concentrated in Dublin.  Irrespective of what the Acting Leader says in reply, this is borne out by last week's Society of Chartered Surveyors Ireland, SCSI, report.  We cannot become an island that stands on one city alone.  We would topple, not only because we would be off balance but because it goes against who we are and what and where we come from.  The Government has led a sustained destruction of rural Ireland.  It has closed post offices, stalled broadband provision, allowed large companies to see the benefits of Dublin and, but for a few, hold on to those benefits while the rest of the country suffers.  We rarely get visits in rural Ireland from IDA Ireland.</p> <p>The older person without a smartphone and a monthly commuter ticket is the one who loses.  They are alone and isolated.  When I visit them - I visit as many of them as I can - they tell me they feel forgotten.  For an older person to go collect his or her pension, he or she needs a car to get to the nearest large town because the local post office is closed.  He or she needs a bank account to lodge it because nobody carries that amount around but he or she has to be there before a certain time otherwise the counter will be closed.  He or she will have to find the nearest supermarket because the post office is closed and so is the corner shop attached to it.  If we do this to one older person, what are we doing to our younger people?  We are an island for all of us.  This is a serious issue and I am looking for Ministers to come to the House and address it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#Q00800"><p>I join Senators Ardagh and Murnane O'Connor in expressing serious concern at the ever-increasing numbers of people sleeping rough in Dublin.  While recent press coverage talks about the city, people are sleeping rough throughout the county.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Victor Boyhan:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2463"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2463&amp;amp;pid=VictorBoyhan&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->I believe that the Dublin Regional Homeless Executive showed that recently.  I note from the Taoiseach's commentary earlier that he was disappointed with the latest figures.  When one couples this with the thousands of people who protested last weekend about housing - they are not all wrong - we have to sit up and listen.  If we have to change direction, then so be it.  At this stage we have to take on board that people are genuinely concerned.  People are priced out of homes, be they to purchase or to rent; it is a crisis situation.  The Minister for Housing, Planning and Local Government can exercise special powers under special circumstances.  If a national emergency on housing is declared, I am advised that he could use some of these powers.  We have a crisis situation in every local authority, but especially in the four Dublin local authorities.  They are at breaking point with staff totally frustrated at having to turn people away day after day.  We should have another discussion on what direction the Government is going.</p><p>On more positive news, as a result of our Planning and Development (Amendment) Bill, which is now the Planning and Development (Amendment) Act 2018, I am happy to say that the regulations to scrap planning fees for elected members of councils were signed by the Minister on Friday.  I have a copy in front of me.  The Minister also authorised councillors to seek a report on a variation to a proposed county development plan change by the elected members.  Some 900 councillors lobbied strongly on those two issues.  They are welcome changes and are now embedded.  These are two issues that some Senators got over the line, despite significant opposition from the Government of the day and other Senators.  I am glad that local authority members are delighted with that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#R00200"><p>A lot done and a lot to do.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1384" speakername="Maria Byrne" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#R00300"><p>I welcome the good news that "Nightflyers", a series made in Troy Studios in Limerick, was released yesterday in the US.  The Irish embassy in the US tweeted and congratulated the film-makers on the premiere, which was shown on 2 December.  It is a series of ten films made in Limerick.  It is important to acknowledge the number of people involved in the apprenticeship and training scheme during the making of the series.  Troy Studios said that if the series was a success the producers might come back to make the next production there as well.  The important aspect is that people have been trained and have gone through the apprenticeships and skills side of the process.  They now have the skills so if the producers come back to Troy Studios, they will be available for employment.  The series is to be released on Netflix and I encourage people to watch it because it is not too often we have a science fiction series made in a local film studio.  I wish to congratulate all involved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1372" speakername="Fintan Warfield" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#R00400"><p>The Seanad reform implementation group first met on 9 May.  On Tuesday next, I hope, the group will sign off on a report and a Bill.  During Taoiseach's questions earlier in the D&aacute;il, the long running saga in Irish politics that is Seanad reform was discussed by all of the group leaders.  Some suggested that there are Members in this House who do not believe that we will ever see reform in this regard.  However, there are many people who never wish to see Seanad reform.  The Taoiseach suggested that some people may be confused by registering to vote on a number of panels.  I believe that he should give the people more credit.  He also raised cost as an issue and that he is interested in seeing the cost of any election.  We had that conversation when Fine Gael told the people that we could save money.  He also alluded to a third constituency to be retained in the form of the University of Dublin, Trinity College.  He also said that the Leader keeps him abreast of these issues in private.  I ask the Leader to explain what is the plan following the presentation of this report to An Taoiseach and when will we see the legislation before this House.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1425" speakername="Michelle Mulherin" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#R00500"><p>I wish to raise my concern about the state of health of Galway-Mayo Institute of Technology, GMIT, headquarters and campus in Galway.  Ordinarily and over the past years I have received calls to raise issues about the GMIT campus in Castlebar, but I recently received disturbing information from a solid source that there are serious financial, management and governance problems there.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Michelle Mulherin:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2309"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2309&amp;amp;pid=MichelleMulherin&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->Some of this is manifested in the decline of certain programmes in which it should be a national leader, such as in hotel and catering management.  Furthermore, the problems GMIT headquarters is grappling with will present a significant impediment to the delivery of a technological university for west.  The GMIT Galway campus, and GMIT in general, represents a weak link in the Connacht-Ulster alliance for the delivery of such a technological university.  This is terrible because if we cannot deliver a technological university in a timely fashion it means rural areas will be lagging behind on a much-needed and valuable third level institute.</p><p>Myself and Senators Paddy Burke and O'Mahony fought very hard for a recovery and sustainable plan for the GMIT Castlebar campus.  We secured &euro;3.75 million in ring-fenced funding to be spent over five years.  I want to welcome the appointment of a new vice president of GMIT, Professor Neville McClenaghan, who will be based in and will look after Castlebar's interests and who will take up his post in the spring.  It has a good academic plan for recovery.</p><p>We do not want all this to go down the tubes.  The future is bright but for this and we all understand the umbrella organisation in Galway can bring the whole ship down.  I ask that the Minister be invited in to discuss progress on the delivery of technological universities, to outline the state of health and of play in relation to GMIT headquarters in Galway and to address all the significant and serious issues I have raised today.  It is an urgent matter.  We cannot afford to be left behind in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#S00200"><p>Before I raise an issue, I want the Members to join with me in welcoming two members of Galway City Council, Councillor Ollie Crowe, a member for the city centre area, and Councillor Peter Keane, a member for Galway city west.  Both were nominated last night to contest the council elections next May.  The convention was chaired by Deputy Scanlon.  I wish both of them every success in the election.  Galway is very lucky to have such councillors.  All the members of the city council, including the mayor, are excellent and I really hope that council will be retained.  The work it is doing for the west, Galway city and the year of culture is second to none.  I wish the councillors every success for the future and thank them, on behalf of Fianna F&aacute;il, for their commitment and their work for their constituents in Galway.</p><p>I refer to No. 45 on the Order Paper, the Registration of Wills Bill 2016, which was promoted by myself and Senators Ardagh and Clifford-Lee.  This Bill is on Committee Stage and over the years, I have been attempting to get it passed but without much help from the Law Society of Ireland.  I discussed this matter with Mr. Peter Keane, a prominent solicitor who is in the Visitors Gallery, before the Order of Business.  This arises from an article by Mr. Charlie Weston in the<i>Sunday Independent</i>of 2 December 2018.  Mr. Weston outlined the exact plan of the Bill I proposed, which is now being sought throughout Europe.  I think Malta and Ireland are the two countries in Europe that do not have such a scheme.  In the article, which is worth reading, he pinned down exactly what is happening in this regard.  The Royal London insurance company asked the Minister and the Government to bring this Bill forward.  The article stated that while probate delays are a product of a complex process with insufficient resources, the lack of a centralised wills register is compounding the issue.</p><p>This Bill could be passed by the House quickly and I will seek Government time in this regard.  I will not go through the detail of the Bill again because Second Stage was passed with the co-operation of all the parties.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Terry Leyden:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=636"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=636&amp;amp;pid=TerryLeyden&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->For some reason, Deputy Joan Burton, came in as Minister and turned it down completely.  She gave it no consideration and the great and progressive Labour Party turned out not to be so progressive as far as that issue was concerned.  It is causing great distress to solicitors and those who are deprived of their inheritance where a will cannot be found.  Unfortunately, there are many situations now where will books in the offices of solicitors who go out of business for one reason or another, including retirements, are lost forever.  The House would do a good day's work if the Deputy Leader looked into the matter.  It is now the responsibility of the Department of Health rather than of the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection and I ask the Deputy Leader to contact the Minister.  I will also contact him to see if we can progress the Bill to Final Stage and pass it on to the D&aacute;il.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1381" speakername="Denis O'Donovan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#T00200"><p>I welcome Councillors Ollie Crowe and Peter Keane to the Gallery.  Given my position, I must refrain from the political analysis provided by my good colleague, Senator Leyden.  I hope the councillors have an enjoyable day in Leinster House.  I call Senator Craughwell.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1390" speakername="Gerard Craughwell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#T00300"><p>I call for a debate in the House on the gross abuse of public money to defend indefensible cases.  PDFORRA, the Defence Forces' representative body, has taken seven cases to date on the Working Time Directive and won each of them.  The latest case cost the State &euro;200,000 in legal fees and there was a five figure settlement for the claimant.  This is nonsense.  If the State is fully aware of its obligations under the directive, why is it spending money to defend indefensible litigation?  Is it because the Department has such deep pockets into which it never has to put its own money that it can take on these cases to create some kind of delay?  This is an outrageous abuse of public money.  Earlier, Members were talking about people sleeping rough yet &euro;200,000 was spent here.  There are 35 more cases laid before the High Court relating to the directive and the Defence Forces and there will be another 35 in a week or two.  I am sure there will be 35 more the week after that.  Will the Government keep throwing money at this rather than fix the problem?  As such, I would like a debate in the House on the abuse of public money.</p> <p>I also raise the need for protections for teachers working for fly-by-night language schools, which my colleague, Senator Lawlor, referred to earlier.  These teachers have been abused and treated in the most appalling way.  Thankfully, they have some representation now through the trades unions, but they had none in the past.  Any school setting up now should have to put aside a bond to ensure the final payment of the teachers working for them.  At least two months' wages for each teacher should be provided for.  It is not a lot to ask.  I agree with Senator Lawlor that many of these smaller schools have become visa factories.  There was a case some time ago where the box room of a three-bedroom house was registered as a language school with 1,000 students.  It is just outrageous.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1417" speakername="Kevin Humphreys" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#T00400"><p>I follow the previous speaker's remarks on Grafton College, Portobello, where I attended the protest last night.  It is disturbing to see language specialists who teach English as a foreign language being discarded so close to Christmas.  They have been put in a position in which they do not know where the next euro will come from.  Many of them are owed at least four weeks' salary and some are owed up to eight weeks' salary.  I ask the Deputy Leader to support our request for the Minister for Employment Affairs and Social Protection, Deputy Regina Doherty, to fast-track in some way any moneys due to employees through the insolvency scheme.  It is a practical measure which could be taken.  On previous occasions, the Department of Social Protection held special clinics to inform employees in cases like this of their rights and entitlements under its schemes.  This practical step could be taken immediately.  We did it in the case of Clerys when we met the workers at SIPTU's offices and I am sure Unite would make its building available for the teachers in this case to meet departmental officials to find out exactly what is available to them so close to Christmas.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Kevin Humphreys:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2289"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2289&amp;amp;pid=KevinHumphreys&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->There is legislation coming forward in the House this week in regard to schools.  We may have to amend that Bill to reflect this issue and give some sort of guarantee in regard to earned salary, so it is protected as outlined by the previous speaker.  There are two practical elements the Minister could address.  First, action could be taken immediately with regard to the insolvency fund.  Second, a clinic could be set up by the Department of Employment Affairs and Social Protection for those unfortunate people who find themselves in this situation in order to inform them of exactly what their entitlements are.  Above all, we need to regulate this sector, whether that is through a bond or a fund that has to be put in place to guarantee that workers get the salaries to which they are entitled and for which they have worked so hard.</p><p>I have raised several times with the Minister of State, Deputy English, the issue of the 3,500 housing units that could be provided on the Poolbeg west peninsula.  This project has run into constant problems.  The last time he was in the House, the Minister of State promised me a note on the progress on the negotiations on the 900 social and affordable units, and I would be grateful if this could be followed up.  I have approached the Minister of State about it but, unfortunately, it has not been forthcoming yet.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1411" speakername="Aidan Davitt" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#U00200"><p>I ask the Deputy Leader if she has had any report back on the review of councillors' pay and conditions.  As the House knows, this report, which is headed by Ms Moorhead, SC, was to be with us before the end of November.  I am curious to know if anything has been heard from the Minister.  If not, it might be an ideal time to invite the Minister to the House to discuss the report.  I am sure he has received it at this stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#U00300"><p>I thank the Senators who raised a variety of issues on the Order of Business.  Senator Ardagh raised the issue of rough sleepers, which is obviously a very difficult issue, especially with the weather disimproving.  I am certainly feeling the cold more today than I have in recent weeks so I cannot imagine how somebody would feel who does not have a roof over his or her head.  The rough sleeper census from last Tuesday found there were 156 individuals sleeping rough on that night.  Believe it or not, that is a reduction on this time last year.  Budget 2019 provided &euro;60 million for the provision of emergency accommodation which will support the development of facilities for rough sleepers, as well as family hubs.  The Minister, Deputy Murphy, has been working closely with the Dublin Region Homeless Executive and the Dublin local authorities on the delivery of additional emergency accommodation.  The Dublin Region Homeless Executive is co-ordinating the delivery of 203 permanent beds and 130 contingency beds.  On the night of the count, 51 of these beds had been put in place and a further 152 permanent beds will be open before Christmas.  That is the up-to-date position on the issue.</p> <p>On the Children and Family Relationships (Amendment) Act, I have also been contacted by a number of people on this issue.  I do not have an answer for the Senator but, even while I have been sitting here today, we have communicated with the Department and I am awaiting a response.  If the Senator does not see any sign of that in the near future, she could ask the Leader again, perhaps next week.  I will ask for her to be informed of when that will be commenced.  I would also like to see that happen.</p> <p>Senator Ardagh also raised the issue of the ombudsman for consumers.  There might be a necessity for further funding if what the Senator says is true.  It would perhaps be a good matter for a Commencement debate but, failing that, a debate with the Minister for Finance would be very useful.</p> <p>Senator McDowell raised the issue of foreign affairs in the House.  I do not know if there is a new sentiment but I have always found this to be a Chamber, certainly during the last Seanad, where foreign affairs issues were discussed very regularly.  In fact, much of the time an issue on a particular country is tabled and only two or three Members turn up in the House to discuss it.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->That is the other side of it and there is a balance to be achieved.  I agree with the Senator and I am fully in favour of a debate in the House on the events surrounding the death of Mr. Khashoggi and the involvement of Saudi Arabia.  As for Ukraine and the Russian influence there, the current events are frightening.  The current leader has a popularity rating of under 10% now but he was still able to introduce martial law.  Issues involving Russia, Ukraine or Georgia are frightening and it could be very useful to discuss them in the House.</p><p>We should never be seen as a House only here to rubber-stamp what happens in the D&aacute;il.  As Members of the Oireachtas and a European Union legislative Chamber, as the Senator pointed out, we have the opportunity to make our opinions known on matters like this.  We have disagreements with the Department on occasion but this is not a reason for us to be deterred in raising matters of serious importance internationally in the House.  I fully support the Senator in raising the prospect of those two debates.  Perhaps they will happen in the new year.  The other side of the matter is that people must turn up for these debates.  We ask for them but people do not necessarily attend the House when the debates materialise.</p><p>Senator Conway-Walsh mentioned yesterday being International Day of Persons with Disabilities and the presentation in the AV room.  I agree with the comments on personal assistance, as the system provides some liberty and independence to disabled people.  It is certainly something that could be useful if discussed in this House.  Perhaps the relevant Minister of State, Deputy Finian McGrath, would be willing to come here in the new year to discuss the matter.</p><p>Senator Norris also raised the family relationships Bill, as well as other matters, but as he is not here I do not see why we should expend time responding to his contribution.  Senator Lawlor raised the very important matter of the language school.  We all really feel for those individuals and teachers who have been affected by this.  As Deputy Humphreys mentioned, there is a Bill coming to the House tomorrow - the Qualifications and Quality Assurance (Education and Training) (Amendment) Bill 2018 - and four Senators have tabled amendments that specifically deal with this matter.  It is very timely, although the events are unfortunate.  Perhaps the Senator will contribute to the debate on the Bill tomorrow.</p><p>Senator Murnane O'Connor raised the matter of housing and rural Ireland.  She is not here but I will briefly respond in saying that the Government has made unprecedented investment in rural Ireland.  We must acknowledge that some of the indicators show improvements with respect to people locating in towns.  However, if we managed to reverse urbanisation as a phenomenon, we would be the first country in the world to do so.  We are trying very hard but it is very challenging.  A week ago, the first recipients of the Government's ten-year &euro;1 billion rural regeneration and development scheme were announced.  These were towns and villages with under 10,000 people.  There has been a significant increase in Government investment in towns and villages, especially in the past three years.  It is starting to bear fruit.  That is as far as I will go to respond as the Senator who raised the matter is not here.</p><p>Senator Boyhan spoke about rough sleepers and I have addressed that matter.  Senator Maria Byrne mentioned a positive story-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1403" speakername="Michael McDowell" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#V00200"><p>She is not here either.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#V00300"><p>Okay, although neither was Senator Murnane O'Connor and I spent a few minutes responding to her contribution.  As a rule, I will not respond to Member's contributions if they are not present to hear the response.  It is not the proper use of time in the House and sometimes Ministers are waiting outside.  Members often just raise the matter but are obviously not that interested in the response.  I was very interested to hear about the "Nightflyers" science fiction series and I must watch it.</p> <p>I do not have a direct answer to Senator Warfield's question but I will come back to him.  I know the report is due and it will go to the Taoiseach.  I imagine he will act fairly swiftly but I cannot provide precise dates.  Senator Mulherin is not here but she raised some matters of concern about Galway-Mayo Institute of Technology.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Senator Catherine Noone:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=1&amp;amp;HouseNum=25&amp;amp;MemberID=2354"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=2354&amp;amp;pid=CatherineNoone&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span--> Senator Leyden referred to the legislation on the registration of wills.  That is a Private Members' Bill so his party can use its Private Members' time for that.  It is also something that could be raised as a Commencement matter in order that further details might be obtained.  However, the Senator can definitely use Fianna F&aacute;il's Private Members' time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W00200"><p>I appreciate that but I was asking for Government time.  Our Private Members' time might not be available for a considerable period.  The time must be shared among other Members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W00300"><p>It is a Private Members' Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W00400"><p>Yes, but it could be adopted by the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W00500"><p>The Senator can also talk to his colleagues about using their time for it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W00600"><p>I will.  I have no difficulty appealing to my colleagues on all sides of the House to accommodate us.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W00700"><p>I have no objection to it coming before the House.  I am trying to assist the Senator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W00800"><p>The Senator has been extraordinarily helpful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W00900"><p>He can table it for his party's Private Members' time or come to an agreement with the Leader as to another time for which it could be scheduled.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1393" speakername="Terry Leyden" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W01000"><p>The Senator has given me the very good idea to talk to my Independent colleagues.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W01100"><p>It is in the Senator's hands.</p> <p>Senator Craughwell referred to how public moneys are being spent.  I will not comment on the particular case involved.  However, this would be suitable for a Commencement debate in order to obtain a specific answer.  Failing such a move being successful in the context of gleaning the relevant information, the working time directive could be discussed with the Minister.  However, the Senator could get information directly from the Minister.  The Senator also referred to language schools, an important issue which I have addressed.</p> <p>Senator Humphreys is not present.  Senator Davitt raised councillors' pay and conditions.  The new year would be a good time to invite the Minister back to the House.  I am not sure of the status of that report but it is due, at least, so it would be timely to have a discussion on it in January or February, at the latest.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.105" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Order of Business agreed to.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.106" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W01300">Asylum Migration and Integration Fund: Referral to Joint Committee</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#W01400"><p>I move:</p><blockquote>That the proposal that Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:Proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Regulation (EU) No. 516/2014 of the European Parliament and the Council, as regards the re-commitment of the remaining amounts committed to support the implementation of the Council Decisions (EU) 2015/1523 and (EU) 2015/1601 or the allocation thereof to other actions under the national programmes,a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 20th November, 2018, be referred to the Joint Committee on Justice and Equality, in accordance with Standing Order 71(3)(k), which, not later than 6th December, 2018, shall send a message to the Seanad in the manner prescribed in Standing Order 75, and Standing Order 77(2) shall accordingly apply.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.108" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Question put and agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.109" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 4.20 p.m. and resumed at 4.45 p.m.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.110" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#DD00100">Annual National Transition Statement on Climate Action and Low Carbon Development: Statements</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#DD00200"><p>No. 2 is the annual national transition statement on the Climate Action and Low Carbon Development Act 2015.  This is quite unusual because there will be seven Ministers or Ministers of State, each of whom will have five minutes, while group spokespersons will have five minutes for their contributions.  The Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, will be called on to reply at 6.10 p.m., and statements will conclude at 6.15 p.m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1379" speakername="Victor Boyhan" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#DD00300"><p>To clarify, may we respond to each Minister or Minister of State separately or will we allow all the Ministers and Ministers of State speak before we ask questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#DD00400"><p>I should have clarified that and I thank the Senator.  Each Minister or Minister of State will speak in sequence, after which Senators will have an opportunity to respond.  </p> <p>I call the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment, Deputy Bruton.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#DD00500"><p>Five minutes is a short time and, therefore, I will try to be concise.</p> <p>I attended the UN climate conference in Poland yesterday and the message was stark for anyone who was not already aware.  It was made clear that the window for the world to respond to the massive challenge we face is closing fast, and that the consequences of failing to respond are truly catastrophic, not only in the impact on individuals and countries but also on migration, the natural environment and civilisation, as David Attenborough said.  It was also stark that, in general, the technology to achieve the set targets is already available.  People are not, therefore, being asked to do something impossible or original.  We have the technology.  The clear message was that if we fail to respond to a challenge of this scale, it will have such an impact on the prospects of future generations that we will have utterly betrayed the people who will come after us.</p> <p>It was a stark message and it puts our transition statement in perspective.  During the crash, we seemed to conform to many of our climate obligations but once the recovery resumed it was clear we had failed to break the link between growth in emissions and growth in the economy.  As of today, by 2020, for which we had a target to reduce emissions by 20%, we will have reduced emissions by only 1%.  No sector other than the power sector is on track or has even reduced its targets by a significant degree.  Some areas such as services, which are generally good, are better than others such as the transport and agriculture industries, which are quite bad.  No sector, however, is on track to reduce emissions at the scale that was intended.</p> <p>The UN also maps the measures that are in place and how they will have an impact.  It has calculated the impact of the published national development plan, with which the Senators will be familiar.  It is encouraging to see that the plan will have a significant impact.  It is calculated that its impact will be 2,200 million tonnes cumulatively over the period to 2030, which will be just short of half of what we need to do by then.  It shows the measures we are introducing are important and will have an impact but also that we need to step up our ambition considerably.  The Taoiseach admitted we are a laggard in this area but it is my intention that we seek to be a leader in it, and the mandate that I have received supports that intention.<!--/p--><!--p></p--><!--p--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#91;</span--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">Deputy Richard Bruton:</span--><!--a href="http://www.oireachtas.ie/members-hist/default.asp?housetype=0&amp;amp;HouseNum=32&amp;amp;MemberID=119"></a--><!--a href="../zoomin?readform&amp;amp;chamber=seanad&amp;amp;memberid=119&amp;amp;pid=RichardBruton&amp;amp;year=2018&amp;amp;month=12&amp;amp;day=04"></a--><!--span class="speakercontinuing">&amp;#93;</span-->We have the opportunity and the seriousness of this has been underlined by not just the UN conference, but by our Citizens' Assembly and by the Oireachtas which has set up an all-party committee to report by the end of January.  I intend to work in parallel to the work of the Oireachtas committee.  I intend to produce an all-of-government plan by the end of February.  I am working on a similar schedule to try to bring together the measures that can make an impact.</p><p>I plan to look at this under six headings.  One is the regulatory framework.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#EE00200"><p>Excuse me Minister.  Could we have some quiet at the back of the Chamber.  I ask the usher to ensure that the door is closed because it is very distracting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.117" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1293" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#EE00300"><p>I will outline the six headings under which I hope to develop a whole-of-government policy working with my Government colleagues in all Departments as this cannot be confined to a single Department.  One is the regulatory framework.  The second is how we spur the adoption of known technologies throughout the community.  The third is how we address market failure.  As many Senators will know we have clearly signalled that we need to set a trajectory for carbon price.  The fourth is how we will drive change in business models.  As well as posing a challenge to business there are great opportunities for business in moving to a low-carbon environment.  We need to ensure businesses anticipate and become leaders not followers in that sphere.  The fifth is how the public sector can lead by example.  The public sector owns a very substantial stock of housing and buildings.  It purchases many vehicles and has other procurement.  Much of that can impact and lead the way to a low-carbon environment.</p> <p>The last heading, which in some ways is the most important one, is how we will engage with citizens and communities so that everyone plays their part.  This cannot be funded by the State.  For example, the cost of upgrading our housing to the standards we need to achieve by 2030 would be about &euro;50 billion.  Over the next ten years the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Donohoe, has allocated about &euro;4 billion to my Department in supporting that.  The vast majority of the funding has to be achieved by people making investments on their own.  While they will pay back, the payback periods will be long.  We will need to consider how we can support the funding of these changes that people will need to make.</p> <p>The same is true as we go through each sector.  While it is very important that we accommodate a just transition, which was very much a theme yesterday, Senators must bear in mind that the State cannot fund all the change that must be made.  A just transition cannot mean the State picking up the cost because that is simply not possible.  We must make major behavioural change as a community, including in enterprises, in homes and in the way we travel, live and eat.  It goes across every segment.  I am delighted to have the opportunity to say a few words on the transition statement today.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#EE00400"><p>I thank the Minister and I apologise for the tight timescale.  The next speaker is the Minister for Agriculture, Food and the Marine, Deputy Creed.  He is also against the clock.  We do not normally put Ministers against the clock in the Seanad.  He has five minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.119" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#EE00500"><p>Is it correct that the Minister for Communications, Climate Action and Environment comes back in at the end?  I thought that was the original-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#EE00600"><p>No.  The Minister of State, Deputy D'Arcy, will come in at the end.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1405" speakername="Alice Mary Higgins" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#EE00700"><p>I knew there was a concluding Minister.  I just wanted to confirm that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1406" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#EE00800"><p>There is a concluding Minister.  I laid that out at the outset.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1285" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:30:00" url="http://debatesarchive.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/takes/seanad2018120400002#EE00900"><p>I am pleased to appear before the Seanad to present the annual transition statement for the agriculture, forest and land-use sector.  As one of the key sectors involved in the country's national mitigation plan, it only right to restate the vision for the sector which is an approach to carbon neutrality in the agriculture and land-use sector, including forestry, that does not compromise capacity for sustainable food production.  This is consistent with the principles of both the Paris Agreement and the European Union Council conclusions of October 2014, which recognised the role of agriculture and land use in tackling climate change and their contribution to achieving climate ambitions.</p> <p>One of the first actions we committed to in the national mitigation plan was to engage with research to further elaborate on the concept of carbon neutrality.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/seanad/2018-12-04a.124" nospeaker="true" time="14:30:00" ><p>Additional debate to follow.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>