<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.2" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.3" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Eric Byrne, Senator Michael Comiskey, Deputy Áine Collins, Senator Hildegarde Naughton, Deputy Pat Deering, Senator Mary Ann O'Brien, Deputy Timmy Dooley, Senator Pat O'Neill, Deputy Bernard J. Durkan, Senator Feargal Quinn. Deputy Martin Ferris, Deputy John Halligan, Deputy Anthony Lawlor, Deputy John Lyons, Deputy Éamon Ó Cuív, Deputy Willie Penrose, Deputy Thomas Pringle, Deputy Peadar Tóibín,</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Arthur Spring.</p><p>DEPUTIES MARCELLA CORCORAN KENNEDY, ANDREW DOYLE AND SEÁN KYNE IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.5" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#B00100">Sitting with Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine and Joint Committee on European Union Affairs<br />Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#B00200"><p>A document outlining the format of today's joint meeting of the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine and the Joint Committee on European Affairs has been circulated to the members of all three committees.  I intend to follow that format and ask members to confine themselves to the two-minute speaking time allocation when asking questions.  If there is time, I will allow supplementary questions.</p> <p>  Apologies have been received from Deputies Dara Calleary, Michael Conaghan, Se&aacute;n Crowe, Dominic Hannigan, Michael McNamara and Joe O'Reilly, and Senators Terry Leyden and Mary White.  Deputy Pat Deering is delayed but will arrive in due course.  I propose that we suspend briefly to allow time for the Minister and his officials to take their seats.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.7" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Sitting suspended at 1.35 p.m. and resumed at 1.40 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.8" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#C00100">Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership: Discussion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#C00200"><p>I wish to inform members of the committees that this meeting will be carried live on UPC channel 207, eVision channel 504 and Sky channel 574.  I remind members, visitors and those in the Visitors Gallery to please ensure their mobile telephones are switched off for the duration of this meeting as they interfere with the broadcasting equipment even when in silent mode.  Members are here this afternoon to discuss the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, a potential European Union-United States trade agreement currently under negotiation.  I welcome the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton, and his officials to the meeting to discuss the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership.  I am delighted to be joined today by Deputy Andrew Doyle, Chairman of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine and Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne, Vice Chairman of the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs, as well as other members of these committees.</p> <p>  In view of the cross-sectoral nature of this issue, members are delighted to have the opportunity to meet the Minister, Deputy Bruton, in joint session to discuss areas of particular concern to their respective committees.  These concerns relate primarily to investment protection and investor-state dispute settlement, ISDS, mechanisms.  There are fears that these basic investment protection rules allow for potential abuses.  There also are concerns regarding the potential for job displacement, which, despite the potential overall increase in employment, may prove to be a difficult hurdle for some citizens.  I am aware that despite these concerns, there also are many opportunities within TTIP.  The key findings of the Copenhagen Economics report, TTIP impact in Ireland, are highly positive overall with a potential impact of a 1.1% increase in GDP.  This is more than double the impact for the European Union as a whole.  As matter of particular interest to the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, the potential reductions in regulatory complexities and costs for exporters are welcome, especially as this is expected to benefit disproportionately small and medium-sized enterprises, SMEs.  Today's discussion will be enlightening and will serve as a platform for the ongoing participation of the committees present today in analysis of the negotiations and in informing members' parliamentary colleagues on the contents and merits of the agreement when member states are asked to ratify the agreement.  I now invite the Minister, Deputy Bruton, to make his presentation to the committees.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#C00300"><p>I thank the Co-Chairman.  At the outset I  wish to state how pleased I am to be here.  From my point of view I have never participated in a joint meeting of three committees.  This meeting presents me with an excellent opportunity and I thank those concerned for organising it.</p> <p>  To give members the backdrop to why trade negotiations are an important concern in Europe, it stems from the fact that if one considers global growth, 90% of it will occur outside the European Union in the coming years.  As one looks from a European context, where growth has been subdued for many years, one must be aware that the potential for trade with these fast-growing economies is an area that should not be missed.  This is why Europe has identified bilateral trade discussions with numerous different countries as a major potential growth source.</p><p>It has been estimated that it would have a growth potential of approximately 2.5% of European GDP if all of those agreements were put in place.  That is the backdrop.<br/><br/>From the point of view of the US, and why it is so prominent, one third of all global trade among major regions occurs between Europe and the US.  It is, therefore, a very significant area of investment.  In fact, 50% of US foreign direct investment, FDI, comes to Europe and a similar proportion of European overseas investment goes to the US.  These economies are quite closely interlinked.  Ireland probably has the highest exposure to the US of any European economy.  US companies in Ireland employ approximately 135,000 people and have been a source of significant growth, particularly in the past couple of years, as the country has emerged from a very difficult period.  It is interesting that Irish companies involved in exporting - they are supported by Enterprise Ireland in this regard - have targeted the US market to a great degree in recent years.  This market has shown remarkable growth in recent years, with the relevant rate averaging out at approximately 20% in the past four years.  So it is a significant growth market and is particularly important for Irish service producers.  The potential for Ireland of a trade agreement that will reduce tariffs, removes non-tariff barriers and increases the capacity to remove unnecessary costs for those involved in trading - for example, pharmaceutical companies - is very significant.  There is no doubt about that.  We tend to gain, on a <i>per capita</i>basis, approximately double what would be the typical gain.  As a result, the potential gains for this country would be significant.<br/><br/>From where do the gains come?  If tariffs are removed, the prices Irish exporters would receive in return for their goods in the marketplace would rise.  Similarly, if we remove tariffs, consumers obtain better value for goods they purchase.  There are a number of routes through which the benefits occur.  By and large, however, tariffs are not the big element.  Average tariffs between the US and the EU are running at approximately 3% to 4% and higher in the case of some agricultural produce.  The latter is because there are larger barriers in the context of agriculture.  The largest barriers are to be found in the non-tariff area and, on average, they stand at over 20%.  In some areas, such as the dairy sector, these barriers are very significant and keep Irish dairy exports to the US to very low levels.  They are also very substantial in areas such as pharmaceuticals.  Effectively, as a result of the fact that there is no regulatory co-operation, virtually the same tests often have to be carried out in both jurisdictions in order for products to be approved for sale.  This imposes a cost.  That is the backdrop to this aspect of the matter.<br/><br/>During Ireland's Presidency of the EU, the mandate was agreed.  This mandate is very ambitious but it also lays down some important markers.  One of these relates to the fact that there will be no interference with the right to uphold high standards, particularly in Europe but on both sides in general, in the context of protecting labour, environmental standards and food standards.  Explicit statements were made to the effect that there would be no change to the European rules on genetically modified organisms, GMOs.  There was also an explicit statement to the effect that there would be no question of this agreement being used to privatise public services.  The legitimacy of running such services how one chooses is absolutely recognised.  In addition, it was stated that there will be no interference with the right to make new regulations if, as and when the public demands this.  The mandate was agreed and, at this stage, we are entering into the negotiation period.</p><p>An investor dispute settlement mechanism, ISDS, was included in that mandate but only if it met Europe's interests and the reason it was included was that in the US, there are 50 different states and they do not automatically incorporate treaty agreements into their law.  An Irish company wanting to trade in different states will benefit from having a single mechanism whereby issues that arise under the agreement can be resolved without having to, separately, take their chance in different states.  In the same way, the US sees the same benefits in not having to have separate rules applied in different courts across the EU.  In principle, one can see the advantage of this.  Many people hoping to engage in negotiations with Asian countries would recognise the merit of having an agreement that would protect investment and that is the backdrop to this.</p><p> Poor investor-state dispute settlement agreements have been put in place over the years and many of them have given rise to legitimate public concern that they did not sufficiently protect the government's right to regulate and that they have been managed in a way that has been too secretive and so on.  The committee has probably heard many of these objections.  During the negotiations in recent times, Europe has been keen to make sure the design of an investor dispute settlement approach would be robust and meet the public needs that have been expressed in various consultations that have occurred, which has been done.  There are two source documents, if members want to inform themselves of the protections that have been put into the investor settlement structure.  One is the existing Canadian agreement.  There is an investor dispute settlement mechanism in the agreement between Europe and Canada, which sets out clearly the limited circumstances where there is blatant discrimination.  It is only in such cases that a dispute can arise and they are set out in the agreement.</p><p> The second document is Commissioner Malmstr&ouml;m's recent paper in which she set out an additional set of protections that she intends to ensure.  They set out the absolute right of governments to regulate; the transparency of the mechanism for any adjudication; the fact that the adjudicators must be qualified to be judges and be selected by the governments, that is, the EU and the US - they are not selected by industry; an appeals mechanism; and a provision to either choose to go to the courts or to the dispute mechanism in either jurisdiction whereby one cannot be played against the other.  The dispute mechanism cannot be used to overturn domestic court decisions.  Many protections have been included to deal with the concerns that have been raised and that is the backdrop.</p><p> In an Irish context, we have conducted an evaluation of the potential impact of the agreement.  It depends on what is put into a model and we have only speculated on what might be agreed.  To allow us to prepare for the agreement we considered where the threats and opportunities might arise and how we should prepare ourselves for those.  We had this done by Copenhagen Economics, which is the most reputable source for such modelling.  They assumed a 100% tariff reduction, a 50% non-tariff reduction and so on.  They made a series of assumptions on what could be achieved and then they ran a model.  It gave information, which members will have had access to, on where the potential gains and threats might be.</p><p>Overall, it shows that we could see a gain somewhere in the order of &euro;2 billion from a successful agreement.  It represents an increase of around 1.1% in GDP, 4% in investment, 1.5% in real wages and the creation of between 5,000 and 10,000 additional exports-based jobs.  These are only models and one can dispute the assumptions upon which they are based, but they are helpful in that they show there are significant opportunities in the dairy sector, for example, but there may be what are termed "defensive interests" in the beef area and so forth.  The report suggests there could be significant gains in the pharmaceutical sector but other areas could be a cause for concern.</p><p> We are a small, open trading economy and we depend on exporting.  I am old enough to remember the Anglo-Irish trade agreement of the 1960s and the opening up of EU markets and how these developments transformed and modernised our economy.  We employ twice as many people now as we did when we joined the EU, which is a remarkable statistic.  That has occurred because we have been an open trading economy and have taken the opportunities presented to us.  That said, I agree with those who argue that we cannot be naive.  We must view this as a give and take process and protect our interests.  In that context, we are determined to ensure we arm ourselves to deal with the threats and to exploit the opportunities which range across different areas.  Regulatory co-operation is one area of opportunity which is about trying to take out unnecessary costs that might stand in the way of trade while not in any way diluting our standards of medical, food and labour protection.  It is about removing red tape, essentially.  There are also opportunities in areas such as the rules governing customs systems and so forth.  Energy is on the agenda and for the first time there are two chapters which clearly indicate Europe's interests.  The first is a chapter on the SME sector, with Europe aiming to ensure this sector is at the heart of any agreement and will benefit from it, and the second is on sustainable development, which emphasises that this is about maintaining and increasing the standards of environmental and climate protection, labour protection and so forth.  Europe is also determined that there will be no interference with the democratic right of Parliament to make regulatory decisions.  These issues are nailed into the preliminary discussion documents.</p><p> On displacement, it has been estimated that in the overall European context displacement will amount to about 0.7% and will happen over a number of years.  Obviously there will be growing sectors and sectors that decline, but the implementation of an agreement like this would not be expected to be a sudden jolt causing rapid change.  None the less, we must be alert to the fact that some sectors will come under pressure and we must be prepared for that.  Overall, the displacement levels identified in some studies compare favourably with natural displacement levels in Enterprise Ireland and IDA companies of about 5% per annum.  There is always a churn in exporting companies, as opportunities and sectors wax and wane.  While we must be alert to potential displacement and be prepared, we cannot stand with our finger in the dam trying to stop change from happening in certain sectors.  It is about being ahead of the change and trying to position ourselves to take advantage of the new opportunities that will arise.  In the long term, that is where a lot of the dynamism of a US-EU agreement could arise.  If we can be part of the growth sectors of the future, like the convergence of medical devices and ICT, for example, the so-called internet of things and so forth, we will benefit hugely.  Ireland is well placed in that regard because we have a combination of multi-national and indigenous companies operating here.  If we get a wider US-EU setting of standards, we could be at the heart of a standard-setting, innovative marketplace.  In the longer term, that is where many of the opportunities will emerge from agreements of this nature.</p><p>That gives just an outline.</p><p> We need to be wide awake in any negotiations and this is no different.  Both sides need to be satisfied at the end of this.  It goes to the Council of Ministers so each member state must be satisfied and the European Parliament must be satisfied.  There are many checks and balances in this process.  The negotiation is only under way and it has been very transparent compared with predecessors.  Many more documents have been put out for inspection.  Stakeholders' meetings are held regularly in order that people can be a part of it and concerns can be flagged well in advance.  Commissioner Malmstr&ouml;m has been very sensitive and open in how she handles the negotiations.  She has been here and she gives access to Ministers, and parliamentarians, including MEPs and so on.  She is determined to get a good agreement with which everyone will be happy at the end.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#G00200"><p>I thank the Minister for his presentation.  Owing to the number of attendees at today's meeting, I ask members to limit their questions to two minutes initially.  If time permits, some supplementary questions may be allowed.  Before inviting statements from the Co-Chairmen, Deputies Doyle and Kyne, I have two questions.  The Minister might respond to the three of us together at the end.</p> <p>  Will the Minister elaborate on the next steps in ISDS following the publication of the concept report, in particular the items the European Commission has indicated will not be subject to change when ISDS negotiations recommence?</p> <p>  Will the Minister highlight the sectors of SMEs in Ireland that are likely to avail of the decreased regulatory complexity and reduction in tariffs to start exporting and increase the volume of their exports?</p> <p>  I invite the Co-Chairman, Deputy Andrew Doyle, the Chairman of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and Marine, to make his opening remarks and ask his questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#G00300"><p>On behalf of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and Marine, I welcome the Minister, Deputy Bruton.  As with the other committees, the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and Marine has been closely following developments in the ongoing TTIP negotiation process.</p> <p>  Last month we had a briefing from officials from the Department of Agriculture, Food and Marine on the six monthly report.  It included an exchange with them on TTIP.  In May I attended the meeting the Minister chaired in the European Commission buildings in Dublin where various stakeholders outlined their views, including representatives from the farming organisations, IBEC and the trade unions as well as members of the EU trade negotiators team and the chief American negotiator, Ms Elaine O'Brien.</p> <p>  Much of what was outlined today was outlined that day.  Those in the Irish farming sector naturally have some concerns and need reassurances that hormone-treated beef will not flood into the European market and distort it.  As the Minister said, the beef sector may need to adopt a defensive position.  It may come down to a certain choice of cuts from the US that will enter the EU very selectively.</p> <p>  The other issue is the potential expansion of genetically modified organism products into Europe under TTIP.  This is an area we have been following closely.  Last week the committee sent a political contribution to the European Commission outlining our views on the issues of GMOs with regard to the autonomy of individual states to reject certain GMOs.</p> <p>  With the abolition of milk quotas at the end of March, TTIP offers the potential for Irish dairy farmers to increase production if the US market opens up.  Mindful of the nature and scale of the increase, however, the committee produced a report, entitled Managing Volatility in the Dairy Industry.  We advocated a cautious approach in the area of dairy expansion.  I believe we said everyone should get better before they get bigger initially, which is a very simple strapline.</p> <p>  We are aware that TTIP is in its early stages and that this is a complex process.  We look forward to hearing the Minister's views on the agricultural areas that may be affected.</p><p>What does the Minister expect the total impact of TTIP on the beef industry to be?  We are aware that we may need to adopt a defensive strategy should US beef enter the EU market.</p><p> I ask the Minister to outline the potential impact of TTIP on the dairy industry.  We are aware the dairy sector may present opportunities for Irish dairy producers to sell their produce.  The Minister spoke about sustainable development and climate change.  The Irish production system is probably one of the most efficient in the world for producing food from an environmental perspective.  We have one argument to get over with the EU first.  Following that, the potential in Ireland should not be constrained simply to achieve a statistical figure on percentage of output.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#H00200"><p>I invite the Co-Chairman, Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne, the Vice Chairman of the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs, to make his opening remarks and ask questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1110" speakername="Se&aacute;n Kyne" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#H00300"><p>I welcome the Minister to these discussions on TTIP.  I am also a member of the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  This is a very important cross-sectoral issue, which does much to enhance the parliamentary oversight of these negotiations.  The Joint Committee on European Union Affairs has taken a very active role in monitoring the TTIP negotiations.  Last year the committee submitted a political contribution to the EU institutions on the topic and the committee recently met stakeholders from the European Commission, the American and Irish Chambers and the Irish Congress of Trade Unions to discuss certain elements of TTIP, in particular the ISDS aspect.  At that comprehensive meeting we heard statements from Dr. Tom Healy of the Nevin Economic Research Institute, who stated there is no experience of ISDS in this jurisdiction; that the matter raises complex questions over how the Irish Constitution would operate and possibly in terms of the jurisdiction of Irish courts <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>any external tribunal or mechanism; and that a note of caution needs to be entered there.</p><p>Mr. Mark Redmond from the American Chamber said it did not want a deal for the sake it, that it should not be rushed but it wants a comprehensive deal.  However, Mr. Mark O'Mahoney of Chambers Ireland stated it should not be rushed for the sake of passing it because the decision might be regretted for years afterwards.  He also said we needed a monitoring system to ensure the provisions benefit small and medium-sized enterprises.</p><p>Ms Patricia King of ICTU said that Ireland has a perfectly good judicial system and has democratic mechanisms through the Oireachtas to make rules and regulations, and if anybody has a problem with the rules systems are in place to deal with them.  She saw no reason for one particular group to have a supranational mechanism.  So there is quite a debate on ISDS, which is of concern to many people.</p><p>How can we show that the national parliaments retain the right to regulate under the ISDS arrangements?  The Chairman of the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs, Deputy Hannigan, who gives his apologies for his absence, recently attended an interparliamentary meeting in Paris on the European Union's trade policy and on TTIP.  At that meeting there seemed to be a lack of enthusiasm for TTIP among certain larger member states.  Does this surprise the Minister and can he comment on it?  What does he believe are the main concerns of the larger states?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#H00400"><p>That is comprehensive.  On the next steps on ISDS, I believe the schedule is that the Commission will publish proposals on the ISDS in September for the member states to agree.  It would only be after that when an exchange would occur with the US.  There has been no exchange at this stage with the US.  The red-line issues have been published.  The Canadian agreement has that general approach.  In addition, there is the document that has been set out about the appeal mechanism and so on.  In September those principles will be firmed up into hard clauses in a negotiating context.  It will give a considerable degree of reassurance to people who have genuinely well-founded concerns if we were to just import some of the ISDS agreements that have occurred elsewhere.</p> <p>  Perhaps I should take the point made by the Co-Chairman, Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne, at the same time.</p><p>While it is true that Ireland has never had investor-State dispute settlements, ISDSs, there are thousands of such settlements in the European Union, including nine between the United States and member states.  While one is right to scrutinise what is occurring, what one must do is to look at the documentation.  The reason Ireland has never had such mechanisms is the strength of Article 43 of the Constitution, as the protection of property rights in the Constitution would trump any ISDS in terms of the robustness of the defence it offers to investors.  Moreover, it has always been recognised as such, whereas obviously we are negotiating at European level on some of the ISDSs.  Since the passage of the Lisbon treaty, the European Union has been the negotiator on trade issues.  Consequently, the agreement it puts in place must accommodate all member states, including those which have such ISDS mechanisms.  However, the aim will be to examine the quality of the ISDS and the extremely restrictive areas to which it will apply.</p><p> On the sectors that will benefit, all sorts will do so.  To revert to Deputy Marcella Corcoran Kennedy's question, pharmaceuticals are very significant, as are cheeses and nutritional products.  Public procurement is an issue, in that many Enterprise Ireland-backed Irish companies are focused on the United States in developing software services, but they are blocked out of public procurement.  This will be a significant opportunity for them.  There are many other sectors listed, of which medical devices is another in which clearly there will be major benefits in a common approach to regulation.  As for dairy and milk powders, the United States does not recognise or accept the standards we apply and such powders are effectively blocked from entry to the market.  Consequently, there are many barriers and one can identify sectors that will benefit.</p><p> Hormone-treated beef simply cannot come in, about which I can be absolutely categorical.  Choice of cuts certainly is an issue, in respect of which I refer to the Canadian model.  We will seek a whole-carcass phased tariff reduction and there will be a quota.  It will be for hormone-free beef.  </p><p> There cannot be expansion of genetically modified organisms, GMOs, under the agreement.  The European rules for GMOs are the ones that will apply and there is no change in them.  </p><p> As for the impact on the beef and dairy sectors, if it comes down to quotas, obviously it will be related to the size of quotas and so on.  There are estimates to hand.  The beef sector is unique in that we have both offensive and defensive interests.  In the long term any significant increase in beef imports to the European Union could have adverse effects on the Irish industry.  Ireland is the largest net exporter of beef to European Union countries and our place in these markets could be threatened by a large volume of cheap imports.  This does not look likely, as US prices are at an historic high of &euro;4.90 per kilo, well above European Union prices.  However, this does mean that we have legitimate concerns about the size of the quota that may be offered to the United States in terms of the absorption capacity of the European Union market.  Ireland has proposed to the Commission which negotiates the agreements that these sensitivities be reflected in the size, composition and administration of any quota.  I can tell members that each time I or anyone else goes, Ministers absolutely insist on this.  The other side, however, is that we are seeking a significant quota for Irish beef into the US market.  As members are aware, following the reopening of the market, Irish beef exports this year will be covered by a 65,000 tonne quota for other countries on a first come, first served basis.</p><p>This quota was only 85% filled last year, mainly by countries in Central America.  There are, therefore, opportunities and threats.<br/><br/>In the dairy sector there are only opportunities.  This is one of the areas in which we hope to be able to get in behind the regulatory barriers.  There are significant tariffs, but of far more significance are the barriers, some of which I have described, namely, the fact that the United States simply does not recognise the standards we apply to our products which, as a result, are not approved for sale.  If we can negotiate a reduction in this regard, we see market opportunities for branded packaged butter such as Kerrygold, cheese, powdered and sports products, prepared consumer foods and fish products.  These could all benefit from trade liberalisation.  There are significant opportunities across the sector.  I take the point made by the Co-Chairman, Deputy Andrew Doyle, that because Irish beef cows are grass fed, we are in a much better position in the context of our carbon footprint.  That is something which we will obviously seek to have recognised.<br/><br/>On Deputy Se&aacute;n Kyne's point, some member states have very specific concerns.  The French term in this regard is &quot;<i>l'exception culturelle</i>&quot;.  It is explicit in the mandate that the authorities in France will seek to maintain the cultural diversity there.  Some countries will be sceptical about different sectors or issues.  It is, however, the investor dispute issue which has garnered the greatest attention.  There was not as much focus on this issue when the agreement with Canada was being negotiated when, by and large, the protections nailed in were accepted.  However, there is greater suspicion or concern on this occasion.  The European Union's negotiators are responding and seeking to address these concerns.  They met both the Austrians and Germans who had particular concerns and have helped to shape the proposals Commissioner Malmstr&ouml;m has brought forward.  There has been very open engagement and the concerns emerging in different member states are being reflected in the mandate and the negotiating position the European Union is adopting.  Like Ireland, all other member states are trying to ensure their concerns will be taken into account.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#K00200"><p>We will now take questions from members.  I call Deputy Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n who is a member of the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#K00300"><p>Gabhaim bu&iacute;ochas leis an Aire as ucht a chur i l&aacute;thair.  I welcome the process in which we are involved because the issue before us is an extremely important one which must be dealt with.  I welcome this new innovation of cross-committee investigation of matters of this nature.  There is no doubt that international trade is good, but the TTIP is a very invasive treaty when it comes to sovereignty and democracy.  There is a cost benefit to all international trade and many are of the view that as a result of treaties of this nature, costs fall on consumers and workers, while many of the benefits accrue to many of the larger companies.</p> <p>  Does the Minister accept that the ISDS model was not necessary in Ireland previously because of the existence of strong property rights in the Constitution?  Does he accept that the statutes of European member states are sufficiently strong that there is no actual need for an ISDS model?  The Centre for Economic Policy Research has found that 1.3 million jobs in Europe will be displaced as a result of the actual treaty.  The Austrian Foundation for Development Research points out that the Commission has not made provision for any of the costs arising from such a large number of jobs being lost.  What is the Minister's view on how these costs should be dealt with?  Are they the responsibility of nation states or does the Commission have a role to play?</p> <p>  We are regularly informed about the opportunity for SMEs to benefit from this process, particularly from a reduction in levels of bureaucracy and red tape.  Outside these two, what will be the tangible benefits for SMEs as a result of the treaty?</p><p> The Minister mentioned public services.  Will he detail the chapters in the treaty in which public services are discussed?  Will he also detail the definition of "public services" because I understand it to be narrow and that it has no commercial impact whatsoever?  Previously, the Commission has explicitly identified certain sectors which shall not be privatised or come under pressure such as water provision.  Would it not be better for the Commission to identify explicitly these public services and not leave it to a definition that could be understood in a different manner?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#L00200"><p>The evidence, in so far as we have it, does not bear out what the Deputy says.  It does not fall on consumers.  Consumers are among the beneficiaries because the agreement will result in lower prices.  If tariffs and non-tariff barriers are taken out, there will be lower prices on both sides because they both are forms of increasing prices and, therefore, consumers will benefit.</p> <p>  With regard to wages, the model run for Ireland showed a 1.5% increase in wages.  Again, the model suggests there will be benefits for our workers from the agreement.  The fact that we can conduct more trade in dairy products, medical devices and pharmaceuticals means more earnings for companies, but it also benefits their workers.  There will not be exclusivity whereby because we have more dairy exports and this will favour big businesses over producers.  If we get our beef into the United States, as we have just done, and can sell premium cuts, everyone will benefit in the marketplace.  Companies and their workers will do better and farmers will earn a higher premium if they can get quality products into strong markets such as the United States.  That is not a valid criticism.</p> <p>  The Deputy cannot say it is an invasive treaty because nothing has been agreed to.  This is about entering negotiations to reduce tariffs, bring down tariff barriers and provide for investor disputes.  Nothing is agreed to at this stage.  Some argue that there should not be an ISDS in the agreement.  It is included in the Canadian agreement and nobody argued against it at the time.  However, it has become an argument and we need to face up to it.  There is some validity to the need to protect ourselves in an investor dispute.  The Deputy's presumption is that this is bad, but we are big traders with the United States.  Bringing down barriers in the United States is good for countries such as ours which trades with it and has investment with it.  Therefore, I do not accept the assumption in the Deputy's question.  The mandate which was agreed to before the negotiations started states: "Services supplied in the exercise of governmental authorities defined by Article 1.3 of GATT shall be excluded from these negotiations".  Both chief negotiators confirmed after the seventh round that there would be no commitments on public services.  This means that the TTIP will have no implications for health, education, social services and public utilities such as water provision.  There is, therefore, a double lock.  We excluded it from the negotiations mandate and both sides have stated they will not negotiate in this territory.  It is excluded.</p> <p>  Turning to the issue of whether sectors will come under pressure, that could happen.  In the Irish case, it does not look like there will be sectors that will be greatly exposed, although it is possible that some business services will face increasing competition and there will be threats and opportunities for both sides in the beef industry.  The estimate of the impact is seven in every 1,000 over a ten-year period as it is rolled out.  That will not be a huge impact compared to 5% of turnover in export-oriented companies every year.  Fortunately or unfortunately, markets change and companies rise and fall.</p><p>It is not a big source of new uncertainty, whereas there is a real opportunity to grow the economy.  Clearly we must be conscious of where the opportunities are and we must brace ourselves to deal with them.</p><p> On the question of tangible benefits for SMEs, they are throughout all sectors.  Farmers are producers of dairy products and they would stand to gain.  There are small players in the milk powder market and in software.  If we gain access to public procurement, the beneficiaries will be mostly small Irish companies.  The growth of services in the US has been significant.  The pace of growth of Irish companies in the US is huge, and our services companies are growing more in the US than anywhere else.  Our service companies are not growing anything like as fast in Asia as in the US.  All the growth is coming from SMEs, small Irish owned internationally trading services companies.  There are areas that will open up and if we get a good deal we will get tangible benefits.  We need to push to get those opportunities.</p><p> The US is protectionist in terms of public procurement.  It will be difficult to negotiate public procurement contracts.  There will be tough negotiations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#M00200"><p>Does Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n have a supplementary question?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#M00300"><p>All government spending on goods would come under public procurement.  My understanding of the definition of public services is a service where there is no commercial element to it.  However, when one sees public services delivered in this State, be it health, education or all the other public services, obviously there is a commercial element to it.  It is the narrowness of the definition that worries us.  The Minister mentioned that 0.7% is a low figure.  In Ireland that would mean the displacement of about 13,000 jobs.  I do not know of any plan at present to deal with that level of displacement.  Is there a plan from the Government side in regard to that?  There is a level of convergence currently within and outside the treaty.  We have seen the convergence outside the treaty start to ramp up, because the treaty is the political yardstick for development.  Things such as cleaning meat with lactic acid, which was not allowed previously, will be allowed by the European side.</p> <p>  The importation of tar sands oil from Canada has rocketed.  What does convergence mean in respect of these particular issues?  We have regulatory standards that are higher than the United States and it will mean that there will be a reduction in our standards whether that will be workers' rights or environmental protection.  How does the Minister envisage that our negotiators can fight against that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#M00400"><p>I have dealt with the public service, it is not on the agenda.  It is excluded from the mandate and the negotiators do not intend to open it up.  That is as categorical as we can get.</p> <p>  We spend most of our time planning how we will deal with potential displacement.  Some 5% of jobs created by Enterprise Ireland and IDA are displaced every year.  Many of the Enterprise Ireland programmes are about introducing lean production processes; encouraging companies to involve themselves in innovation; improving the management and leadership capability of companies; getting them to look at markets where they could expand should they be under pressure in some other market.  Enterprise Ireland spends a great deal of time dealing with its existing base of companies and looking at how they can better position themselves either to deal with a threat or an opportunity.  The same is true increasingly now of the IDA companies.  IDA invests increasingly in transformation agendas, which are very similar to those sort of EI programmes, looking at how to win new mandates and protect jobs in the areas they are in.  We are very actively engaged and have a great many proven policy instruments to deal with displacement should it arise from this source.</p> <p>  I invite members to read the chapters on regulatory co-operation.  I probably do not have time to quote them for members.  They absolutely set out categorically that there will be no dilution in the standards on either side.  The US is as adamant as the EU that will be no reductions in its standards.</p><p>It is explicit in the text that there will be no undermining of the democratic mandate and right of parliaments to set regulations.  What is being looked at is areas of good practice so that if Europe is introducing a new regulation, information on its impact will be shared in order that people can anticipate and prepare for the new standards expected.  For example, if the fat content of an item is tested in Ireland, there can be mutual acceptance across Europe of the accuracy of that measure of fat content such that the item does not have to be re-tested elsewhere to obtain the same result.  This is the type of unnecessary work we are seeking to remove.  That is very significant.  Most of the things that are barriers to trade may have been used as protectionism but many of them are about having to replicate costly proofs of what a product is doing rather than about standards.  This is where the regulatory convergence will occur.  These regulations come under the heading of mutual recognitions.  A good example would be an architect and a mechanism by which the qualification on both sides can be recognised.  This is the type of issue on which convergence is sought, not to say that an architect can be just a draftsman, thereby undermining a standard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#N00200"><p>I invite Deputies Eamon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v, Martin Ferris and Thomas Pringle, who are members of the Joint Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, to ask their questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#N00300"><p>I welcome the Minister.  This is a very useful meeting.  As a member of the Committee on Agriculture, Food and the Marine, I propose to focus on agricultural issues.  First, in the context of these discussions and, in particular, the US presidential election, when will these negotiations be brought to a conclusion?  I got the impression from the Minister that he and the European Union agree that the overall concept is a very good idea.  The Minister reiterated many times all the positives he sees arising out of this agreement.  This leads to the following very obvious question.  When it comes to the final meeting of Ministers on these negotiations, how will the decision be made and will it be made by qualified majority voting?  In other words, will the interests of the overall supersede the interests of particular member states on especially sensitive issues?</p> <p>  In regard to food, there are 130,000 farmers in Ireland and multiples of that number of people involved in the food industry here.  The biggest issue relating to food is that of standards in GMO and hormone-free beef, as discussed earlier.  While we might sell quality cuts to America, so too might another beef producer if the price is high.  If, however, the price of beef collapses and the other producer has had a good production season, will there be restrictions on that producer putting vast quantities of beef into Europe, thereby undermining our market because 95% of our beef is sold on the European market?</p> <p>  How can we be sure that, as we near the end line, the agricultural interests in particular of this country will not be sold out in the interests of getting a big deal?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1047" speakername="Martin Ferris" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#N00400"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for the presentation.  In response to a question from Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n, the Minister said that this agreement, if implemented, will benefit the consumer by making things cheaper.</p><p>How will this affect the Irish producer in the agricultural sector in particular?  How will it affect the cost of producing beef competitively?  Historically, it has been far easier and cheaper for US producers.  How will this affect our market?</p><p> I refer to EU standards of traceability on the use of hormone treatment for cattle which are very stringent.  How will US standards compare?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1001" speakername="Thomas Pringle" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#O00200"><p>I welcome the opportunity for this engagement with the Minister.  My questions are not directly to do with agriculture.  My first question is about freedom of information requests and the discovery made by the Corporate Europe Observatory that 93% of the negotiations at the early stages were between corporate bodies and lobbyists on each side of the negotiations and that the Parliament and the Council were excluded from that early stage.  I ask the Minister to comment.</p> <p>  A question related to agriculture is about job displacement.  The Copenhagen report does not deal with job displacement in the Irish economy.  The Minister previously mentioned job displacement when speaking about Enterprise Ireland and IDA Ireland.  What about job displacement in the agricultural sector and jobs in rural Ireland where it will be very difficult for former workers to retrain and relocate in order to gain employment?  What does the Minister intend to do in this regard?</p> <p>  What opportunity could be included in the ISDS for a future Irish Government to regulate wages by means of the Low Pay Commission?  As the Minister said, most things, including governmental actions, have been excluded from ISDS, therefore, it must be asked what is the need for it. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#O00300"><p>In reply to Deputy &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v's points, the expectation is that a framework could be agreed by the end of the year but the negotiations would continue.  When this process started Mike Forman talked about it being done on a single tank of gas.  That hope has not been realised.  If the US Congress grants this negotiation mandate that President Obama is seeking - it is through the Senate but not yet through the Congress - it will accelerate matters.  The decision will be by unanimity not by qualified majority voting but it will also require a vote in the Oireachtas, in the European Parliament and in the parliament of every other member state.  There will be considerable protections.</p> <p>  There is no question of flooding the market in a good season because restrictions on beef, for example, will be by way of quota not free access.  As Co-Chairman, Deputy Andrew Doyle said, there will be issues around cuts and whole carcasses and not just issues about expensive cuts.  The Deputy raises the issue of whether some sectors will gain more than the agricultural sector.  We are probably in a better position now in that the dairy sector is a significant gainer and there are opportunities as well as threats in respect of the beef sector.  I think we are in a position to negotiate an agreement which will be positive for the agricultural sector.  It is not a question of trading opportunities for agriculture against opportunities for the non-agricultural sectors.  I think we can do a good deal in agriculture that will bring benefits to Ireland.  I refer to our cultural connections with the US through the diaspora and the benefits these bring for marketing.</p><p>All of that gives us a real opportunity in the food area and I am sure that Bord Bia will be out of the traps like a shot as those opportunities open up.  </p><p> Deputy Ferris asked whether benefits to consumers would mean that producers would lose out but that is not the way it works when one is taking down tariff and non-tariff barriers.  In the case of tariffs, if anyone loses out it is the Government, which loses customs revenue.  There is an opportunity for both producers and consumers in that regard.  The Deputy must forgive me - I am an economist by trade - but generally any reduction would be shared between the producers and consumers, depending on the conditions in the market.  It will be shared out in some way.  In the case of non-tariff barriers, no-one benefits as such but rather a cost is being incurred through the replication of standards or through keeping goods or services out, as is the case with Irish dairy produce.  A lot of our dairy produce is simply kept out of the market by non-trade barriers.  Consumers get the benefit of new products coming in at better and more competitive prices because the tariffs and non-tariff costs are not included.  At the moment Irish producers must get over the non-tariff barriers and have to pay the equivalent of 20% to do so, as well as the equivalent of 3% in tariffs.  They are paying almost 25% to get over the barriers and into the market.  That 25% is available to be shared, obviously, between the producer and the consumer and that is why both can gain in this situation.  </p><p> In the context of non-hormone treated beef, obviously there will have to be pretty tight and insistent demands as to how the US replicates the standards of traceability that we have in Europe.  That is an issue which is being very closely watched to make sure that in the case of beef that is not hormone treated, the US must be able to replicate the standards of traceability.  The US will have to satisfy Europe that it has delivered on that.  The importing country must be satisfied that traceability standards are being met.  </p><p> I am not familiar with the lobbyist's report to which the Deputy referred.  I was around for the negotiation of the Canadian agreement and some of the agreement with Japan but the process has never been more open and transparent than now.  The documents are laid, stakeholders meetings take place after each round, there is interaction with Parliament on the negotiations and there are very few restricted documents, even though these are high-stakes negotiations.  It is a very open process.</p><p> On the issue of regional displacement, one of the initiatives I am taking this year is to seek to introduce the concept of a regional enterprise strategy for every region.  We are trying to engage with the various agencies, business leaders and other players in each region to get them involved in shaping regional strategies.  I am very keen that we develop clusters of strength in every region to that they can look at an agreement like this and see the opportunities in it.  There will be real opportunities for rural communities in this agreement.  The US is a good market for rural and regional Ireland to target.  We must have a successful regional enterprise strategy that develops the aforementioned clusters, of which there are very few embedded here at present.  We have co-location but we need to do more to embed them.  Developments like the technology centre for the dairy sector, which brings together the best minds from academia and industry, will build businesses in rural Ireland that will be capable of competing globally.  </p><p> The documents pertaining to the Canadian agreement are instructive.  Under that agreement, a breach of the "fair and equitable treatment obligation" can only arise when there is a denial of justice in criminal, civil or administrative proceedings; a fundamental breach of due process, including a fundamental breach of transparency in judicial and administrative proceedings; manifest arbitrariness; targeted discrimination on manifestly wrongful grounds, such as gender, race or religious belief; or abusive treatment of investors, such as coercion, duress and harassment.</p><p>This is not an easy route, with people just being able to say they want to take a case.  They must prove, not only that they suffered damage by the action, but that it was done in a wholly discriminatory manner.  Tough requirements are being insisted upon by Europe.  Even in the Canadian agreement the requirements were tough.  Obviously, this will go beyond that, with many other protections, such as the right of government to regulate, that will be embedded in any agreement that may emerge from the US.</p><p> Why are these ISDSs there?  We could understand better why they figure if we looked at an example.  Take, for instance, a situation where one is negotiating an agreement with Asia, where there are significant concerns about the safety of intellectual property and whether one could get redress if one was ripped off.  That is the backdrop and one reason there might be a need for an investor-state dispute settlement.  The ISDS would give the investor some certainty that he or she would not be ripped off in an arbitrary manner.  Another situation might be where an Irish company is going into the United States.  The United States does not enshrine trade agreements into the domestic law of each of the 50 states, so having to take a suit in different states would be a high cost barrier for a small country to consider.  There is an advantage to being able to say there is an arbitration procedure in place instead.  However, we must satisfy ourselves that this arbitration procedure is fair, equitable and transparent.  That is the reason it was included in the first place.  We must satisfy ourselves that what is negotiated at the end of the day is good. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q00200"><p>The Minister said there would be a quota, but how big would the quota be relative to Irish production?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q00300"><p>Obviously that has to be negotiated.  The assumption that was used by the Copenhagen report was 75,000 tonnes above the existing quota.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q00400"><p>What is the production of Irish beef?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q00500"><p>It is 500,000 tonnes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q00600"><p>That is quite significant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q00700"><p>We are looking for opportunities to trade as well.  It is a two-way process.  There will be quotas in both directions.  Like any other trading, there are opportunities also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1044" speakername="&Eacute;amon &Oacute; Cu&iacute;v" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q00800"><p>We should note that currently the world's highest price for beef is in Britain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.47" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q00900"><p>I am not an expert in that area, but I understand the US herd is in somewhat of a retreat, so there is reasonable optimism in regard to US prices remaining high.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q01000"><p>I want to move on to other questions.  I thank the Minister and now invite representatives of the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs to put their questions to the Minister.  I will call the members in the order they have indicated their interest in putting questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Q01100"><p>In regard to the removal of administrative barriers and tariffs, what are the possibilities of the reintroduction by a circuitous route of further administrative barriers or red tape?  Is that likely in the context of the negotiations and has provision been made to counter that.  In regard to a threat to internationally provided services in this jurisdiction, has the impact of the TTIP been measured in the context of the possibility of a threat to those services or possible consequent job losses?</p> <p>  We were informed that there would be no privatisation of public services, but who defines what is a public service?</p><p>For instance, one could have a different interpretation of public services on the US, Canadian or European sides or whatever the case may be.  Is this aspect taken into account?</p><p> I wish to inquire about the more important carbon reduction proposals.  They have been adopted by the European Union, though not necessarily adopted by all participating countries in TTIP to the same extent.  I want to know to what extent will carbon reduction impact on Europe, and particularly in this jurisdiction?  Will it be compensated for in the context of TTIP?  Has compensation been provided for already?  Is it likely to be provided for?</p><p> The next issue is quotas in the food industry and in the beef and dairy industries.  Will quotas be the only controlling factor?  Will there be a degree of regulation that might identify some of the issues that might impact unnecessarily against us?</p><p> The last issue I wish to raise is supply and demand.  If supply and demand becomes the only arbiter of what prevails, in the course of TTIP, then how do we address this?  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#R00200"><p>I invite Deputy Eric Byrne to commence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#R00300"><p>I pass in preference to my colleague here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#R00500"><p>The first question was whether barriers can be circumvented by other measures.  Clearly, that is what the idea of regulatory co-operation is about, if there are other measures.  I think we would all insist that Governments should have the freedom to introduce regulations in the interests of public safety or that they can introduce them but there would be some sharing of that information.  Therefore, it would have to be done explicitly by a Government in the context of a regulatory initiative.  I mean it cannot be done behind the door.  The idea behind regulatory co-operation is that that would be in some way flagged in advance.  We are not taking away the rights of Government to introduce regulations.  Clearly, if some regulations were purely discriminatory against a product, or if one was not applying the regulation to one's own producers but was applying it to a foreign producer, then one would be in breach of the agreement.  Once this is done across the board, and domestic producers have to do the same thing, then a Government is entitled to do likewise and I think most members would agree with that.  We want to introduce our tobacco rules and so on.</p><p>In terms of a possible threat, there was analysis of the threat.  I do not want to do an injustice to the document.  Copenhagen Economics did have a look at it.  I think, to a large degree, it was thrown up by the fact that, as it saw it, people moved to other sectors.  I mean if it saw an opportunity arise in medical devices and certain areas then there would be some pressure through wage increases and one would see some loss of competitiveness in other service sectors.  One might see a decline in that way.  It was in a relatively benign sort of environment where it was assumed there was a fixed labour pool, which of course there is not when one has a 10% rate of unemployment and a very open economy like ours.  The threat is the same but could present a new source of competitive pressure on sectors.  Our trading sectors deal with competitive pressures every day of the week.  We will offer the same sort of service, that I outlined to Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n earlier, in terms of supports to companies.</p><p>The definition of public service comes from the General Agreement on Trade in Services or GATS which states: <blockquote>&quot;services&quot; includes any service in any sector except services supplied in the exercise of governmental authority;<br /><br />&quot;a service supplied in the exercise of governmental authority&quot; means any service which is supplied neither on a commercial basis, nor in competition with one or more service suppliers.</blockquote>The EU's mandate specifically states that services supplied in the exercise of governmental authority as defined by Article I.3 of GATS shall be excluded from these negotiations.</p><p>These provisions apply in commonality; they are not left to each member state to decide.  As I said, the negotiators have indicated public services will not be on the agenda.</p><p> On the issue of carbon reduction measures, if the European Union introduces measures for other reasons, they will apply with equal force to any producer.  It is down to the European Union to regulate this and such measures will not be undermined by the agreement with the United States.  In other words, the European Union cannot be told to withdraw carbon measures it considers to be in the global public interest.  Even if the United States does not have the same carbon reduction commitments as the European Union, a level playing pitch is achieved by how the European Union applies its special measures to products.  That issue does not arise in the context of the agreement.  If the European Union has super-protection in place for any particular reason, it will apply these rules uniformly across all sectors.  It will not just be a question of quotas.  There will also be the issue of the equivalence of food standards, as referred to by Deputy Martin Ferris, and the question of how we replicate traceability.  US producers of non-hormone beef must be able to demonstrate they have met the same standards on which we insist for European producers.  Both sides will have to agree to a framework within which this can be done.</p><p> I am not sure I fully understood Deputy Bernard J. Durkan's question about whether matters would be left to supply and demand.  If the non-tariff barriers are brought down, it will be up to companies to take the opportunities which present from this, but there will be an effort to inform SMEs of what these opportunities are.  Bord Bia and Enterprise Ireland will be working to help people to take advantage of such a change.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#S00200"><p>My question was related to the degree to which supply and demand in some sectors in the past had not always worked out so well.  There might be peaks and valleys, as the Minister referred to, and the issue concerns the extent to which protection is provided against this.  There will be a competitive advantage for countries in both the East and the West which do not contribute as greatly as the European Union to carbon reduction efforts.  To what extent is this likely to become a contentious issue in the course of the negotiations?</p> <p>  The Minister referred to investor-state dispute mechanisms and the limited areas to which they might be applied.  Is it foreseen, notwithstanding Ireland's amendment of its Constitution to accommodate membership of the European Union and the European Union's own regulations, that a major international player could sue a government after discovering something that had not been anticipated or was provided for in the agreement or that such player did not anticipate when signing up to the project?  This possibility was put to us during discussions at the Joint Committee on European Union Affairs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#S00300"><p>The issue of carbon rules and what responsibilities different countries take on in containing climate change and carbon build-up in the atmosphere will not be discussed in the negotiations.  That is an issue for discussion at the United Nations, not the in negotiations on the trade agreement.  </p> <p>  An international player could only use an ISDS in the limited circumstances I outlined, as per what was proposed in the Canadian agreement.  The first circumstance is that such a player would have to have suffered damage.  Second, that damage would have to have been discriminatory and in breach of fair and equitable treatment obligations.  In other words, the party would have to show both that it had suffered damage and, second, there had been a fundamental breach of due process or there was evidence of targeted discrimination.</p><p>The party would have to demonstrate those two phenomena before it could even initiate a case.  If it has initiated a case and is successful, it cannot force the Government to change its regulations, but it could get compensation.  That is the way that system works.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#T00200"><p>I thank the Minister.  I invite questions from the other members of the joint committees in attendance.  I will take them in the order in which the members have indicated their wish to contribute, beginning with Deputy John Lyons, followed by Senator Hildegarde Naughton and Senator Mary Ann O'Brien.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1023" speakername="John Lyons" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#T00300"><p>The proposal, as it stands, has many merits.  I wish to refer to the potential impact on some of the poorest countries in the world, such as those in Africa and Asia.  There are a number of pieces of research, including the review by the EU Directorate-General for External Policies on the potential impacts of TTIP, which states it will have a negative impact on some countries outside the area it covers.  Numerous other studies predict there may be some losses, some serious, for some of the world's poorest countries owing to such a wide trade agreement between both sides of the Atlantic.  Bangladesh and Pakistan have massive clothing industries.  This is just one concrete example.</p><p>I am very conscious that most of the debate today has rightly focused on many of effects the agreement may have on Ireland <i>per se</i>but, given our stance on supporting the developing countries and how our Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade supports the developing countries, I have two questions, in particular.  Is TTIP, as it stands, undermining the EU's own commitment to policy coherence for development?  Does it stand up to the EU's own policy on coherence for development?  Given that the publication of the sustainability impact assessment on TTIP has been delayed until the end of 2015, would it not be safe to say not enough has been done on the impact of TTIP on countries beyond the areas covered on both sides of the Atlantic, particularly the world's poorest countries?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1187" speakername="Hildegarde Naughton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#T00400"><p>Along with other groups and agencies, such as the Galway chamber, I am very much in favour of TTIP.  As has been highlighted here by contributors, there are some understandable concerns around the ISDS mechanism.  Parties to the treaty all operate transparent and independent legal systems.  I am just not convinced on allowing investors to take legal action in the domestic courts.  I would like to know the Minister's views on incorporating the treaty into our domestic legislation.  Currently, there are very good trade relations between the EU and US.  Everyone would wish that to continue.  It is happening currently without the ISDS mechanism, and we can improve those relations by way of the proposed treaty and still not have a system whereby investors can, over the heads of states, take legal action internationally.</p> <p>  As with any treaty, there are often unforeseen consequences.  I take the point that we are currently in negotiations.  This is a critical time in which to ensure that if an ISDS provision is put in place, the system will be drafted in a watertight fashion.  That is a clear message.  I acknowledge that the Minister has outlined it but it is important that we have safeguards and ensure the arrangement is of benefit to Ireland also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1169" speakername="Mary Ann O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#T00500"><p>I thank the Minister for his presentation.  I am one of the excited ones with an ulterior motive because I have been exporting to the United States, including all 50 states, for 12 years.  There have been ups and downs and some great success.  Some 30% of our revenue is now coming from the United States.  There are many learnings; I could write a book and have many scars to show, as one can see from my appearance.  We have dealt with Starbucks, United Airlines and many multiples.  The chocolates were quite easy although the tariffs are quite onerous.  There is a level playing field between the Belgians, French and the rest of us.</p><p>I have a few questions for the Minister about the dairy sector.  After three years of red tape and bureaucracy, we have just got our dairy desserts into the United States, although into bonded warehouses because they are going onto airlines.  I am excited for my workforce because I can see an easing of opportunities.  I wonder what the timeline is for TTIP?  </p><p> Does the Minister have plans to increase the numbers and knowledge bank of his Enterprise Ireland workforce to meaningfully put people in place in the United States?  It is an absolute monster to take on for an SME, so we really need knowledge on the ground, as well as chiefs and Indians all over the place.  It is never too early to start laying the turf.</p><p> As regards the beef sector, I see it as an opportunity between orange and green.  With grass-fed livestock we can punch above our weight and maybe even obtain a premium.  As the Americans evolve they are crazy about grass-fed beef products, which they lack to some extent.  I would like to hear more from the Minister about our grass-fed dairy sector, including the exact value-added opportunities now that quotas have gone.  How quickly can our farmers have a vision to look forward to?</p><p> Some 80% of foodstocks in the US contain GMOs, but I am not a fan of them.  I do not want our children eating genetically modified products.  The Minister has given us comfort on GMOs but what does he think about GMO foodstuffs coming in here? </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#U00200"><p>To go back to Deputy Lyons' question, quite a degree of attention has been paid to this issue.  Our own study suggests that there would be positive spill-over effects on third countries.  The Commission has examined that and believes that overall it will have positive gains in increased demand for raw materials, components and machinery.  The impact on third countries that has come out of all these models has been positive rather than negative.  I am sure one could find some country that is positioned in such a way, but I do not pretend to be so knowledgeable.  However, there is also a belief not only that the US will import more from third countries, but also that the development of common standards will make it easier for third countries to export to the EU.</p> <p>  This will be a positive move in that countries can adopt standards.  In the absence of the WTO being able to negotiate these, it gives a multilateral ability to target markets which have agreed common standards among themselves.  It makes it easier for developing third countries to deal with a single set of specifications that apply in a very large market and thus gives them advantages.  </p> <p>  To be fair to Europe, the US trade agreement is not the only instrument to try to promote development in countries.  They have their own direct trade agreements with poorer countries to encourage and support such trade.  Through the various WTO agreements, the EU will invest in trade facilitations, including infrastructural capability within those countries.  Europe has a reasonable suite of measures in that respect.</p> <p>  Senator Naughton asked why there is an investor-to-state dispute settlement, or ISDS, clause.  There was an ISDS clause in the Canadian agreement and no one has found any great fault with it.  Nine European countries already have ISDS clauses with the US.  The Commission is negotiating for all 28 member states, so it has to accommodate the environment for all of them.  Why would we not seek to incorporate this?  We would not want to bring US law into Irish law and have US courts interpreting our legislation.  Therefore I do not think we would want to take that step.</p><p>The best approach is where we try to produce as good an ISDS as possible.  Obviously, we are conscious that if we do not like what is agreed, it is one of the issues people will be watching very closely but the Commission is investing a lot of time and effort in this.  The appeal mechanisms, the way arbitrators are selected, the rules that will apply to the arbitration process, the grounds on which a case can be taken, the right of appeal and the fact that one must choose one or the other and cannot take a shot at the ISDS and then go back to the courts or take a shot in the courts and having failed in the domestic courts, switch to the ISDS are designed to give people confidence but we must see the outcome.</p><p> I agree with Senator Mary Ann O'Brien in respect of 30% of revenue coming from the US.  Much of the service growth has been in the US market.  Over 30% of Enterprise Ireland service growth is from the US market so many SMEs like that of the Senator would be exploiting the US market and would stand to gain, particularly in areas like public procurement in the case of services.  </p><p> The hope is that there will be a framework agreement by the end of the year.  There is the ambition in the US to agree it within President Obama's term.  It remains to be seen whether that can be done.  Obviously, the benefits would roll out after the agreement was concluded.  We are beefing up Enterprise Ireland.  We provided 20 additional staff in its overseas offices, some of whom went to the US.  Austin in Texas was a new Enterprise Ireland opening.  As I am sure the members will agree, we have fantastic people in these offices.  Both Enterprise Ireland and IDA people overseas are really great representatives of the country.  They certainly don the Irish jersey every time they go out.  It is a pleasure to work with them and we would encourage companies to use those opportunities.  </p><p> I cannot really add to what I have already said on GMO.  The European rules will not change and it is not on the table in terms of negotiation with the US.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#V00200"><p>I thank the Minister for coming before us and giving us an up-to-date briefing.  Could he continue to do this because we like to keep abreast of the ongoing negotiations as we might not always be able to pick up any information?</p> <p>  Will there be a problem with shelf companies that may exist in either the US or Europe that import products from outside the US to take advantage of the trade agreements?  How will we monitor standards used outside the EU or US to produce products?  </p> <p>  Europe has a strong history of red tape.  I can see going to the US being a real advantage to European companies because red tape in the US is not as strong as it is here.  How does the Minister see that benefiting trade between us and the US?  I saw an example of red tape this morning in a small school.  It was a primary school event for entrepreneurs and innovators.  A teacher told me that the amount of red tape they had to follow was unreasonable.  If it is like this for six, seven and eight-year-olds, what is like for the rest of us?  It is something that must dealt with because it is a serious problem.  </p> <p>  Do we require a referendum to ratify this?  Does it need to be put before the people or can we do it through the legislative process?  The Minister spoke about how great it is.  What is the one thing he is worried about?  There must be something in the back of his mind that gives him a nagging feeling. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.66" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1145" speakername="Feargal Quinn" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#W00100"><p>I am sorry, I missed a little of the debate because I had to leave for a vote.  The Minister may have covered part of this question already.  It relates to energy.  Will there be an effort to get a level playing field in energy?  In Britain today I understand they have given permission for shale fracking in Lancashire.  This may be the start of fracking to obtain energy from under the ground.  In the United States this has changed the source and cost of energy dramatically.  Some ten or 15 years ago everything was imported from the Middle East.  Now, they are able to develop much of their own energy.  Is there a possibility that this could be regarded as unfair competition?  Will there be any effort to try to balance that between the two?</p> <p>  The second question relates to the next stage.  Does South America come into it at some point?  Will we find ourselves in a situation where Chile, Argentina and Brazil are also going to be involved in an added way?  Has that even been thought of at this stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.67" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Co-Chairman (Deputy Marcella Corcoran Kennedy)" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#W00200"><p>Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n, you indicated that you had another supplementary question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#W00300"><p>Yes, if that is possible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.69" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Co-Chairman (Deputy Marcella Corcoran Kennedy)" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#W00400"><p>That is fine as long as it is not something that has already been addressed and as long as it is a question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#W00500"><p>It relates to some points the Minister brought up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.71" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Co-Chairman (Deputy Marcella Corcoran Kennedy)" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#W00600"><p>You have one minute.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#W00700"><p>The Minister referred to the EU-Canada Trade Agreement, CETA.  He mentioned the fact that there has not been criticism of the investor-state dispute settlement.  There is an example whereby the European Union created a mechanism to reduce carbon within oil and oil-type products.  The mechanism was used in an effort to improve the environmental opportunities for European countries.  Yet, in those negotiations Canada put fierce pressure on the European Union with regard to the use of tar sands oil, which has levels of carbon dioxide approximately 23% higher than ordinary oil.  The European Union then changed its regulation with regard to transportation fuels.  Is that not an example of how these types of agreements actually change policy within jurisdictions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#W00800"><p>Deputy Tony Lawlor asked about shelf companies.  They are explicitly excluded from the ISDS provisions.  Deputy Lawlor referred more to rules of origin.  There are explicit requirements to establish rules of origin.  These are in place to protect against what he was referring to.  They have to be policed and that is a challenge.</p> <p>  Reference was made to Europe and red tape.  I believe it depends on the sectors.  Committee members might be surprised to learn that in some sectors Europe is good in this regard.  In medical devices, for example, products get a far faster route to market in Europe than in the United States.  This has been an area of competitive advantage.  It is not all one-way traffic in this regard.</p> <p>  I have never seen companies prevented from moving to the United States.  There is not much to stop them.  European companies employ more than 4 million people in the United States already.  There are no barriers to European companies going there.  I am unsure whether red tape is what is sucking companies out.  It is an internal issue for Europe.  There has been a significant effort at European level to start to rationalise red tape and there are initiatives to do that.  It will not require a referendum, but it will require the approval of the Houses.  There would have to be a vote in the Oireachtas.</p> <p>  Delay is a concern.  We had hoped to get it done during this presidential term.  That is one concern.  The only concern is to ensure we prepare ourselves to take advantage of the opportunities and protect ourselves against any threats.  Any deal of this nature is a deal and there are winners and losers.</p><p>We have to take advantage of the opportunities and prepare for the threats.  That is not a worry because our agencies are prepared, but I have found that not many companies have engaged with the negotiations.  At this stage there is not much engagement.  I would prefer to see more from sectors in which opportunities arise in order that they will play a bigger part in shaping the agenda.<br/><br/>On the question about energy, the agreement is not about imposing standards on countries.  The negotiations are working towards mutual recognition and the removal of non-trade barriers, but the agreement will not dictate the standards that should apply to fracking or any other activity.  It will include an energy chapter and given that restrictions are in place on US exports, clearly that will be an area in which the European Union could access cheaper sources of energy.  The energy chapter will be approached in the same way as other chapters.<br/><br/>There is no doubt that the European Union's ambition is to have more free trade agreements.  The agreement with South Korea has resulted in significant growth of 35% in European trade with that country, three times the growth rate in trade with comparable markets in that region.  The Commission is of the view that the agreements are proving themselves in generating activity.  Agreements with South American countries are also on the list for negotiation.  An agreement with India could be reignited.  The European Union is negotiating an investment treaty with China, although it is not a full trade agreement.  There are numerous negotiations at different stages of development, but, with the slow progress of the World Trade Organization in achieving multilateral agreements, we are seeing more bilateral agreements. <br/><br/>Having secure energy supplies is of interest to the European Union, particularly in the light of other sources of supply.  The issues of so-called carbon leakage and energy intensive industries moving from Europe to the United States are a source of concern that informs the discussion on the energy chapter.  In respect of the Canadian agreement, I do not know the details on carbon reduction in oil products.  I was pointing to the way in which the Canadian agreement represented a massive advance on previous ISDS structures.  The next agreement with the United States will be dramatically different, but the European Union will always retain its right to regulate.  No agreement can tell either side what its regulations should contain.  I have not seen many signs that the European Union is downgrading its regulatory environment without very good reason.  It is conscious about maintaining high standards of protection for the environment and labour.  That is the European <i>acquis</i>.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#X00200"><p>The European Union was going to focus on regulating the offspring of cloned animals, but the issue was taken off the table because of the Americans' dissatisfaction.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#X00300"><p>I will have to investigate the details of that issue, as I do not have an answer for the Deputy.</p><p>Generally speaking, Europe is very cautious.  The policy of the European Union is to maintain very high standards, but obviously if new evidence emerges, standards can change.  Europe must be open to that.  Certainly it is very clear that a trade agreement of this nature is not about diminishing regulatory protection.  The regulatory protection is stated at the outset and in various chapters, and it will be an article of the regulatory agreement.  The insistence on maintaining high regulatory standards is being tightened and is a characteristic of every aspect of the agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Y00200"><p>I thank the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, Deputy Richard Bruton and his officials for coming here to engage with the committees in what has been a very constructive and informative meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Y00300"><p>I wish to clarify that cloning failed because of the disagreement between the European Parliament and the Council.  It was not an international disagreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Y00400"><p>This is an opportunity to discuss that issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1016" speakername="Richard Bruton" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Y00500"><p>The Deputy will have to table a parliamentary question because I-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Y00600"><p>The Minister is correct in saying that is the direct reason, but it is the political pressure of the TTIP negotiations that causes those things to happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Y00700"><p>I want to bring the meeting to a close.  I thank the Minister, Deputy Bruton, and his officials for coming here to engage with the committees in what has been a very constructive and informative meeting.  The Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation will continue to monitor developments in respect of the negotiations and revisit the issue.</p> <p>  I invite Deputy Andrew Doyle to make some brief closing remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1103" speakername="Andrew Doyle" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Y00800"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials.  Negotiations to make trade agreements more open will only work if they are mutually beneficial.  I think we accept that.  If one reflects on when Ireland joined the then EEC in 1973 and one compares the landscape then and now, we benefited from the removal of tariffs, not only in trading with member states but also with our largest trading neighbour, the United Kingdom.</p> <p>  We should look at this as an opportunity with significant challenges as opposed to a threat.  It is a relief that it will not necessitate a referendum, but ultimately the member states will make a decision.  It is important we have a process whereby Oireachtas Members are kept briefed.  We are waiting for round ten of the negotiations.  In the European Parliament building last month, when the question was posed on the number of rounds in the negotiations, no one would give an answer.  That is just to get the agreement ratified in order that the Council can sign off on it before it goes through legal scrubbing and other things in the meantime.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUJ2015062300002#Y00900"><p>I remind members that the Joint Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation will meet again on Tuesday, 30 June 2015, when the Vintners Federation of Ireland will appear in public session, followed by private business.  The select committee will meet on Wednesday, 1 July at 2 p.m. to consider the Committee Stage of the National Minimum Wage (Low Pay Commission) Bill 2015.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.86" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 3.30 p.m. until 1.30 p.m. on Tuesday, 30 June 2015.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.87" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Environment, Culture and the Gaeltacht</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.88" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 14:15</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Noel Coonan, Senator Terry Brennan, Deputy Ruth Coppinger, Senator Cáit Keane, Deputy Robert Dowds, Senator Fiach Mac Conghail. Deputy Helen McEntee, Deputy Tony McLoughlin, Deputy Catherine Murphy, Deputy Brian Stanley,</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Seán Kyne.</p><p>DEPUTY MICHAEL MCCARTHY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.89" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 2.25 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.90" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#C00100">Electoral Commission in Ireland: Discussion (Resumed)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#C00200"><p>I remind members to turn off their mobile phones as they interfere with the sound system and we will not get coverage if there is interference with microphones and other equipment.  Apologies have been received from Senator Ned O'Sullivan.  The meeting has been convened for the purpose of consideration by the committee of matters relating to the consultation paper on the establishment of an electoral commission in Ireland.  The committee will now discuss the matter.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  It is proposed that this part of our meeting will conclude at 5 p.m., if not previously concluded.  There might not be a break between this part and the private meeting but we will deal with the matter when we get to it.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>I welcome from the Standards in Public Office Commission, SIPO, and the Referendum Commission Mr. Seamus McCarthy, who is also the Comptroller and Auditor General, Mr. Peter Tyndall and Mr. Paddy Walsh; Ms Mairead Ahern, county registrar for Louth, and Mr. Fintan Murphy, country registrar for Mayo, who are representing returning officers; and Mr. Joseph Nugent, Mr. Conn Murray and Mr. Vincent Norton from the Local Government Management Agency, LGMA, and the County and City Managers Associations, CMMA.</p><p>By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to this committee.  However, if they are directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in relation to a particular matter and they continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise nor make charges against any person, persons or entity either by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.</p><p>The opening statements may be published on the committee website after the conclusion of the meeting.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  I invite Mr. Seamus McCarthy to make his opening statement.  He has approximately ten minutes, as was the case last week.  I suggest to members that they take five minutes initially and then another five minutes for a supplementary question.  There will not be time for a reply if they take ten minutes initially.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.92" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Seamus McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#C00300"><p>On behalf of the Referendum Commission, I welcome the public consultation on the establishment of an electoral commission in Ireland and thank the committee for its invitation to contribute to this process.  By way of background, a referendum commission is formally established at the discretion of the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, to carry out specific functions in relation to a particular referendum.</p><p>As members may be aware, the Chief Justice nominates the chairperson of the commission who is usually a serving judge of the High Court.  The other members who are <i>ex officio</i>are the Clerk of the D&aacute;il, the Clerk of the Seanad, the Ombudsman, Mr. Peter Tyndall, and the Comptroller and Auditor General or specified alternates in the event of a vacancy.<br/><br/>The current referendum commission, under the chairmanship of Mr. Justice Kevin Cross, was established for the purposes of the marriage referendum and the age of presidential candidates referendum.  The legislation governing the establishment of a referendum commission is the Referendum Act, 1998, as amended by the Referendum Act, 2001.  Under the current legislation, the primary roles of the commission are to provide general explanations of the subject matter of a referendum proposal; to promote public awareness of the referendum; and to encourage the electorate to vote.  The requirement under the 1998 Act to set out arguments for and against a particular referendum proposal was removed by the 2001 Act.<br/><br/>Funding for the commission is provided from the relevant departmental Vote and any unspent balance must be returned to the Department after each campaign.  Each commission exists only for a set period and is disestablished subsequent to presentation of a formal report to the Minister and in any event within six months of polling day.  As a result, commissions have often had limited time in which to prepare materials and advertising campaigns and have not had the time or the resources to undertake an ongoing or even a pre-planned programme to promote voter registration and turnout or an in-depth analysis of the factors that influence them.<br/><br/>Low voter turnout for constitutional referendums, especially young voters, has been a matter of serious concern to previous referendum commissions.  Turnout has varied considerably, with a high turnout often only occurring where the referendum coincides with national or local elections.  However, some issues in themselves have also attracted a high turnout.  For example, the turnout for the recent referendums was in excess of 60%, which was the highest since referendum commissions were established.  On the other hand, the turnout for the children rights referendum in 2012 was only around 33%, one of the lowest ever for a referendum.<br/><br/>The referendum commission is of the view that there is a clear and urgent need for an ongoing campaign, among young people in particular, to encourage voter registration and voting.  In that regard, we consider that a single body with a permanent existence and the capacity to run an ongoing and well planned voter awareness campaign would be more effective than a body brought into existence a few weeks prior to a referendum and with a strictly limited remit.  The current referendum commission endorses the position adopted by its predecessors that the solution to this problem is the transfer of all of the functions of the referendum commission to an independent electoral commission.<br/><br/>I will address a couple of issues in my capacity as Comptroller and Auditor General, separately from my <i>ex officio</i>membership of the standards in public office and referendum commissions.  They relate to questions Nos. 5 and 7 in the consultation paper.  Because the electoral commission would be funded from money provided by the Oireachtas, it would be expected that the Comptroller and Auditor General would be appointed as the commission&rsquo;s auditor.  The consultation paper raises the issue as to whether the Comptroller and Auditor General could, or should, additionally be a member of the commission.  If the electoral commission was statutorily or operationally obliged to adopt the annual accounts, it would create a clear conflict if one of its members was also the auditor.  I note that in some jurisdictions the chief electoral officer is the Accounting Officer.  In such cases, if responsibility for the preparation and presentation of the annual accounts was a personal responsibility of the Accounting Officer, rather than of the electoral commission as a whole, this conflict could be avoided.  However, it is difficult to see how the Comptroller and Auditor General could participate as a member of the electoral commission with a broad remit and, at the same time, carry out examinations of the performance of the commission as provided for under section 9 of the Comptroller and Auditor General (Amendment) Act 1993.<br/><br/>I am happy to deal with these matters in more detail, as the committee requires.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#D00200"><p>I call the Ombudsman to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.95" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Peter Tyndall" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#D00300"><p>I am going to deliver the statement that would have been delivered by the chairman of the Standards in Public Office Commission, Mr. Justice O'Keeffe, who, unfortunately, cannot be with us today.  </p> <p>  On behalf of the Standards in Public Office Commission, I welcome the opportunity given to the commission by the committee to make a formal submission setting out the views of the commission on this new venture, which is likely to have a profound impact on the electoral process in Ireland in the next few years.</p><p>I also welcome the opportunity to address members today, to answer any questions they may have and to contribute to the debate on the matter.  Hopefully, our contributions will help the joint committee in making informed decisions on this very important matter.</p><p> The Standards in Public Office Commission is very much in favour of the establishment of an electoral commission to bring together under one umbrella all the functions and responsibilities of the electoral system.  If, as seems to be the intention, the new electoral commission takes on functions such as maintaining the electoral register, managing elections and referendums, maintaining the register of political parties and the like, then to the Standards in Public Office Commission, it seems to make perfect sense to transfer to the electoral commission the responsibilities under the electoral legislation that currently are under the control of the Standards in Public Office Commission.</p><p> The Public Offices Commission was established in 1995 with responsibility for one piece of legislation only, namely, the Ethics in Public Office Act 1995.  Other responsibilities were subsequently added under the electoral legislation, which would more appropriately have been assigned to an electoral commission, had one existed in 1997 when the Electoral Act was applied.  The Standards in Public Office Commission was established in 2001 and the functions conferred on the Public Offices Commission by the 1997 Act were conferred on the Standards in Public Office Commission.  Perhaps the time is now right for the Standards in Public Office Commission or its successor, given the review of the ethics legislation, to revert to its original role of supervising political activity under the ethics legislation, including the additional responsibilities recently added under the lobbying legislation, rather than electoral matters which are more appropriate to an electoral commission.</p><p> It seems to the Standards in Public Office Commission that the timing of this review of the electoral processes, with the establishment of an electoral commission, is opportune as it coincides, as I mentioned, with the review of the ethics legislation that was announced last week.  The public sector standards Bill will have implications for the staffing of the Standards in Public Office Commission but if certain of its functions under the electoral legislation are transferred to the new electoral commission, then the overall effect on the staffing complement should turn out to be neutral, given the additional responsibilities that are likely to be involved under the public sector standards Bill.  It is important therefore, that both items of legislation are processed through the Oireachtas at the same time in order that it will be apparent to Members of the Oireachtas how decisions with regard to one item of legislation may have an effect on the other.</p><p> The Standards in Public Office Commission is available and would like to be engaged in the development of the new legislation on the setting up of the electoral commission and indeed in respect of the development of the new public sector standards Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#E00200"><p>I now invite Ms Mairead Ahern, the country registrar for County Louth, to make her opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.98" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Mairead Ahern" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#E00300"><p>I am Mairead Ahern and I am the county registrar and returning officer for counties Louth and Meath.  I am accompanied by my colleague, Mr. Fintan Murphy, who is the returning officer in counties Mayo and Roscommon at present, because we are doubling up.  We welcome the opportunity to address the joint committee in the deliberations concerning the implementation of the Government commitment on an electoral commission, an area in which returning officers play a key role on the operational side.  I believe members have had the opportunity to hear the opinions of academics and others on the many matters they are considering.  I believe I am correct in suggesting they all are in broad agreement that the actual running of the electoral events nationally is competently carried out by the returning officers.  Our opening statement, which we forwarded to the joint committee previously, sets out our position.  We believe firmly in the electoral process as it operates at present.  In our opinion, no process could be more transparent.  Each voter is presented with a ballot paper and from the time that this ballot paper enters the ballot box, it is completely secure.  Each vote cast then is brought under escort to its count centre and from there, the ballot papers are in full view of the public until such time as a count is finalised.  Occasionally, complaints are made as to the length of time taken until a final result is announced.  Returning officers are meticulous in ensuring that a count is completely accurate and this can take some time.  However, the benefit is that once concluded, there can be no doubt as to the accuracy of the result and we consider this to be a result worth waiting for.  This system has stood the test of time and regardless of whether the overarching body is a Department or an electoral commission, we argue there is no case for changing what is working well on the ground.</p><p> While other aspects of the issues being addressed by the committee do not fall within our remit, we believe an electoral commission could result in substantial improvements on the issue of voter registration.  There is an ongoing problem with voter registration and voters can, naturally, be upset when they attend at a polling station and discover that, through no fault of their own, they are not listed on the register.  Despite the Trojan work carried out by local authorities and the Department in their efforts to have members of the public check the register, how many of us actually do so?  Registers are complex documents and local authority staff are under immense pressure to ensure they are accurate.  This is extremely difficulty and labour-intensive work and the area is completely under-resourced.  Various models such as a rolling register, a nationally compiled register or changing the methodology for compiling the register to incorporate PPS numbers must be examined.  It is an overwhelming task and dedicated, experienced staff are required to deal with it.  It would be a step forward if, under the auspices of an electoral commission, permanent or full-time staff who could access appropriate databases for the purposes of constantly updating the register were allocated.</p><p> We are of the view that consideration should be given to appointing at least one returning officer to the board of any electoral commission.  We are willing to assist any committee or sub-committee set up for any purpose by a commission.  Our unique and extensive experience qualifies us in all areas of the electoral system and we have a great deal to give when considering these aspects of the system.</p><p> We will be happy to answer questions members may wish to pose or provide any further detail they require.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#F00200"><p>I call Mr. Nugent, CEO of the Local Government Management Agency, to make his opening statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.101" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Joseph Nugent" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#F00300"><p>The Local Government Management Agency, LGMA, the County and City Management Association, CCMA, and local authorities generally are appreciative of the opportunity to make a submission on the Government&rsquo;s consultation paper on the establishment of an electoral commission in Ireland.  I am joined by Mr. Conn Murray, chief executive of Limerick City and County Council, and Mr. Vincent Norton, executive manager in the office of the CEO of Dublin City Council.  We intend to refer to the submissions we have made but also to that made by Deputy City Council on this issue.<br/><br/>As members are aware, local authorities have played a key role in the operation of the electoral system since the foundation of the State.  The extensive knowledge and experience of local authorities, built up over so many years, are key elements in maintaining trust in the electoral processes.  Members are well aware of the primary responsibilities of local authorities for, among other things, the maintenance of the electoral register, running local elections and the regulation of election spending at local level.  Of most significance are the continued activities of local authorities in providing the direct and tangible link on the ground between the electorate and the voter and the electoral process as a whole.  This local presence is a very significant factor in demonstrating the openness and transparency of the process, to which reference has been made, leading to the very high level of confidence of all stakeholders in the electoral system.  Based on the experience of previous electoral change, the LGMA, the CCMA and local authorities are of the view that this continued local link is essential to maintain the public trust in the electoral system.  In our written submission we proposed that the primary focus of an electoral commission be in the areas of electoral policy; oversight and audit; and promoting and maintaining confidence in the electoral system as a whole.  We are also of the view that responsibility for the delivery of the operational aspects of the election process should be vested in the local authority system, where the foundations of a thriving functioning system of local democracy provide confidence in the electoral system in an individual's own area, consistent with the Government's policy document, Putting People First, which affirms local government as the primary means of providing public services at local level.<br/><br/>The joint committee heard last week about the operation of the register of electors.  Whereas there has been a general discussion about the register, there are, in effect, 31 separate and unconnected registers that are maintained by separate local registration authorities.  The local authority sector has improved the customer service experience of the registration process through the delivery of a national register portal, <i>www.checktheregister.ie.</i>, but this merely provides a single point of contact to the separate registers.  For many years those involved in the local authority sector have been consistent in the view that improvements can be made and the removal of legislative barriers would facilitate significant improvements to the registration process through the establishment of a single national register of electors database, with the PPSN used as the unique identifier for electors; moving the register process from one static in nature to a rolling register, thereby removing the current annual deadline requirements; the new register to deliver online services, allowing electors to manage their personal electoral information, including on registration, address changes, etc.; the online process to streamline and simplify the current application procedures and forms and also provide opportunities to deliver contact details to electors for polling stations and the potential for transmission of polling cards electronically, where sought; and the delivery of a range of services for others authorised to access the register, including the development of a portal for returning officers to facilitate the printing of polling station books for election day; a portal for political parties to access local register data for individual areas and the Courts Service to meet jury service requirements.</p><p>Consistent with Government policy determining local authorities as the focal point for delivering services locally, the sector believes it can efficiently deliver the operational aspects of the electoral process within the policy parameters established by any new electoral commission.  Additionally, with the enactment of necessary legislation in respect of the compilation of the electoral register, the local authority sector believes significant efficiencies can be delivered in the related processes.</p><p> At times, we take our electoral system for granted and, at times, when we reasonably criticise and call for changes, we ignore that, in general terms, the system works.  There would, therefore, be a major risk in taking a big bang approach.  We believe change should be made through a series of small developments within the framework of an agreed programme of transformation.  Our democracy works on the back of public trust, and open debate on change of the type taking place here today should be encouraged.  This consultative process is warmly welcome.  We are happy to take further questions in this regard.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#G00200"><p>I welcome the representatives from the various bodies.  It is good to have present all the bodies that may have a role in future electoral commissions.  There seems to be a broad consensus around the need for an electoral commission and my party is in favour of this.  That there is not a uniform means to deal with referenda and that there are problems with the register of electors and the oversight of the electoral and political processes has troubled us for a long time and we would like to see them improved.</p> <p>  The major difference between the CCMA and the other bodies is that it still sees a major role for local government in the electoral process, which I am inclined to go along with.  If the role of local authorities is abolished, there will be problems.  However, Ms Ahern referred to the integrity of the process and I share her view on trust in the current process at the point where people enter the polling station and put their ballot paper in a box.  I have never had any reason to think otherwise but problems arise in respect of people who do not feel the need to vote, those who are not aware they can vote, those who do not know how to vote and those who can vote several times.  I have highlighted the latter issue many times.  I raised the case of 27 people being registered to a derelict house in County Monaghan prior to the second last local government election.  That is far from satisfactory but the issue played itself out.  I have seen similar examples that were not as bad as but we need to prevent a scenario where people are registered multiple times.  The current system does not address that.</p> <p>  No matter how thorough officials are or how good the system is, if the electoral register is not correct, the process will be flawed.  We have asked many times for PPS numbers to be used to register voters.  I raised this with the previous Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government, Mr. Hogan, a number of times and he said there were approximately 6.5 million PPS numbers in the State.</p><p>This includes PPS numbers for people who have died, people who have returned to their countries of origin and Irish people who have emigrated.  A rolling register would appear to be the way forward.  The current registration system, in terms of the times when a person can register and the September and December deadlines in relation to the draft register and appeals system, is very restrictive.  I would like to hear the views of the other delegates on what Mr. Nugent had to say and on my commentary in relation to local government.  <br/><br/>The local government system worked well.  I believe that where possible, local government should continue to play a significant role in the electoral process.  The system falls down because we no longer have rate collectors on the ground, with rates now being paid by way of electronic transfer.  As we also no longer have rent collectors the intelligence system in relation to the register of electors is also not as good.  Town councillors, rate collectors and rent collectors played a major role in terms of feeding into that process.  The fact that political parties no longer have as large a membership on the ground as was the case in decades gone by is also a significant problem.<br/><br/>In regard to the conduct and management of elections and referenda, in the delegates' view which of these functions should be transferred as soon as possible to a commission, if it is agreed that one should be established, and what functions should remain with the local authorities?  Members of other commissions such as the <i>ad hoc</i>boundary commission and referenda commissions are appointed by the Minister.  Who should appoint the members of the proposed electoral commission bearing in mind the need for integrity and for the people to have trust in it?  Politics is a competitive game.  That is the nature of the democratic process.  Who should appoint the members of the electoral commission?  Should this be done by the Minister or the Public Appointments Commission?  If we are agreed that we should move to an electoral commission to deal with all of the issues outlined should this be done in one fell swoop or over, perhaps, a five or ten year period?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#H00200"><p>Were the Deputy's questions directed to a particular witness?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1102" speakername="Brian Stanley" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#H00300"><p>I would like to hear the views of Mr. Tyndall and Mr. McCarthy on the question in relation to the role of local government.  I have heard with Mr. Nugent had to say.  While I agree to a large extent with what he said I am a little conflicted because local government is now so different.  That is not to suggest it is better.  It is different now in terms of it no longer having rate collectors.  It is a fact of life that we now have fewer councillors and intelligence gatherers on the ground.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.107" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Seamus McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#H00400"><p>In regard to local government functions, this is probably not a matter with which the Referendum Commission or Standards in Public Office Commission would have been much engaged.  We have not taken a public view in regard to how an electoral commission would function at local government level.  In regard to the sequence of functions to be transferred and the timing of transfer, a big bang is very high risk.  Having a clear model for transfer of functions and a phased gearing up of an electoral commission is probably a much safer approach.  Some functions will be easier to transfer than others.  Incorporation of Referendum Commission functions and the creation of a permanent referendum management focus in an electoral commission could probably be done relatively easily.  In terms of what the Referendum Commission has done in the past, that would probably be something that could be an early transfer.</p><p>There is a distinction between heavy spend areas and regulatory-type functions.  Starting with regulatory-type functions may be less problematic than moving a programme like central oversight of the electoral register.  That would probably be a big project which would involve an IT requirement and significant logistics to make it work.<br/><br/>On the final question about who should appoint members of the commission, my colleagues and I are<b></b><i>ex officio </i>members of commissions and that makes it easy to ensure there is no political interference or political question around the persons who are involved in the commissions.  I suppose there could be an element of continuing that type of appointment to the commission and there are other models in the administrative system whereby people are <i>ex officio </i>members of a commission or of a similar structure.  Whether that gives the right blend of skills and experience and perspectives is a question and maybe it is a blended appointment structure.  Mr. Tyndall may have other observations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.109" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Peter Tyndall" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#J00200"><p>I will respond to Deputy Stanley's point about the political nature of the process to be overseen by the commission.  I take the view of having an independent appointment process so that if members are not <i>ex officio</i>, they would be appointed by some process that would be accountable to the Oireachtas rather than to an individual government of the day.  It is inevitable that given the contested nature of some of the decisions that will be taken on issues like boundaries and so on, it clearly is better to find a way of ensuring people are appointed without any suggestion that their independence is tainted.  I am sure anyone who took on the role would behave independently, but it is best to appoint such persons in a way that simply removes the possibility of the suggestion that they are other than independent.<br/><br/>On the question of the transfer of functions, I agree with the suggestions.  The particular issue of concern to me is that the staff currently providing support to the electoral aspects of SIPO and also to the Referendum Commission are engaged also in the business of ethics.  Separate ethics legislation is going through and it will be very important that in managing transition, the two processes are run in parallel to avoid them tripping over each other, so to speak, in practice.  I re-emphasise the point made by Mr. McCarthy in his presentation on behalf of the referendum commission.  On the business of promoting voter registration and promoting voter participation, I refer to a hugely successful exercise in the most recent referendum which was partly driven by the context of the referendum and partly driven - I hope - by the work of the commission.  Having that work undertaken on an ongoing basis seems to be important.  I agree that as well as the regulatory functions being an early part of the focus of any new body, I also see promotion of registration and promotion of participation being an early part, with some of the larger functions transferring as the new body became more mature.<br/><br/>That said, I would not want to see the process being over-extended because once the process of transition starts, the staff currently engaged in those tasks will be looking to their futures and I am sure that something that extended over many years would have a destabilising and perhaps demoralising effect.  Therefore, it needs to be done in a phased way and over a set period, but not an over-extended one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.110" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Fintan Murphy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#K00100"><p>I would share the views of Mr. McCarthy and Mr. Tyndall in respect of the positives of the electoral commission and how it might commence its work in that there are clearly identifiable modules that are currently carrying out work under the auspices of the Standards in Public Office Commission or the Department.  Those regulatory functions would constitute a far easier transfer than some of the other matters.<br/><br/>In terms of what returning officers meet daily in election events <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>the electoral register, like many issues, it is not simple and the solution is not simple either.  However, there is a willingness all round, in the new environment in which we find ourselves with social media and other methods of communication, to improve the accuracy of the electoral register.  At the previous referendum, through the efforts of the Referendum Commission and many other agencies, there was a big turnout, not least because of the question that was asked.  The electoral register can be improved immeasurably and we do not have to wait for the finality of an electoral commission to do that.<br/><br/>I have been working closely with local authorities over the past 19 years on 31 different registers, but the authorities are extremely willing and able to embrace new technology to try to improve the effectiveness of voter registration.  There are positives and negatives in this.  One of the negatives, as pointed out by Deputy Stanley, is the reduced intelligence on the ground compared with days gone by.  In our main statement we have suggested that whatever about potential difficulties in utilising PPS numbers, we should definitely consider that option.  The register would certainly benefit from being able to utilise PPS numbers in some way.  However, there are data protection and other issues involved and I would not be qualified to decide how they would be dealt with definitively.  That said, I believe those issues should be dealt with and it is my understanding that legislation will be required.<br/><br/>Voter registration is a big issue.  Regulatory transfer of functions is much easier to attend to than the greater matters of transfer to an electoral commission.  I agree with Mr. Tyndall that the methodology should be both phased and deadlined.  It is up to the body here and perhaps the commission itself how that would take place.  On appointments, my view echoes that of other speakers, namely, that any appointments to an electoral commission will have greater legitimacy if they are completely independent.  For that, we would welcome some form of independent oversight by the Houses of the Oireachtas rather than the Government.  Again, that is an issue that must be decided down the road.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.111" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Conn Murray" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#K00300"><p>In response to Deputy Stanley, I would agree that it must remain as local as possible in terms of politics.  The connectivity we referred to in our submission is extremely important as we go forward.  That said, there are issues and concerns pertaining to the current process around the register itself.  The incident referred to, while not acceptable, is more the exception than the rule.  The reality we face, in the context of timelines currently imposed, leaves us in a very difficult position when faced with a substantial increase in the number of people who wish to register at the last minute.</p><p>Dublin City faced more of that than other areas with the recent referendum.</p><p> That is all very good, but the increase in the number seeking to register presents challenges.  We have recommended and suggested that the move to a rolling register would remove those timeline pressures and give a greater chance of having the accuracy that is necessary for any referendum or election.  In addition, we have made much of the proposal for a unique identifier.  The lack of a unique identifier in the current electoral system means that registration authorities have no way of cross-checking registrations within the relevant jurisdiction or outside of it.  This can lead to duplication and election fraud.  We need a change in the legislative process to enable improvements in the register.  There is no lack of willingness or expertise to respond to the issues that have been referred to here, but that requires change.  I welcome the fact this discussion is taking place and hope it will lead to that type of change.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1052" speakername="Catherine Murphy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#L00200"><p>I do not believe there is any danger of a big bang approach, considering the fact that this debate is happening at this stage in the electoral cycle and that the Minister has stated that getting the commission up and running is the main issue.  I would completely echo the points that have been made.  However, this does not mean that the process must continue as it is indefinitely.  We must decide on what process will be followed, what will be included and within what timeframe.  We must have certainty on this and make it clear.  While inevitably there is a concentration on the electoral register, the establishment of an independent electoral commission is a much bigger enterprise, but we can learn lessons from good examples in other countries similar in size to Ireland.</p> <p>  I echo what has been said in regard to returning officers.  I have never doubted the results they have produced in an election.  I have contested many elections and have always had confidence in the process, although it may take longer to get the final result and often there is not enough time for celebration on the day.  There are good elements to our system and we should not lose them.  Therefore, it is important to be thoughtful in regard to how we proceed.</p> <p>  I would like to know what will be the ultimate goal of the electoral commission and what will be included.  I believe the issue of political funding should be part of the commission's remit and I see that as important in terms of building confidence.  Professor Marsh said last week that the establishment of a referendum commission each time we are to hold a referendum is very wasteful of resources.  The message he took from each of the reports was that they all felt they should have had more time.  Therefore, the establishment of a permanent commission would be beneficial and probably less wasteful.  It is important we consider what lessons we can learn from that.</p> <p>  I was interested in the point made regarding the potential conflict in the case of the Comptroller and Auditor General as the Accounting Officer.  I would like to hear more on that matter because we must ensure that when we set something up it has been properly thought out.  We often understate the turnout at elections and referendums due to the duplication on the register.  Sometimes we count the full register, while many of those on the register can only vote in local elections.  However, duplication is the main issue.  I would like to see a greater use of postal voting whereby, for example, people on holidays who do not want to be disenfranchised can vote.  There are many issues we could raise regarding how things could be done differently.</p> <p>  The Houses of the Oireachtas Commission is not a perfect entity and not all groups are represented on it.</p><p>There are whole sections of the Oireachtas that are not part of it.  In the D&aacute;il neither Sinn F&eacute;in nor the Technical Group, for example, has any representation on it.  There must be a wider aspect but I take the point about the commission not being exclusively under the remit of the Government.  The remit would have to be broadened to make sure that it is inclusive.</p><p> In regard to SIPO, a lot of what has happened in SIPO has been positive but I would like to see it have greater teeth in terms of sanctions.  I could point to several instances where there has been flagrant abuse of the limits.  It is up to people to make complaints after the event but people do not complain.  It is not the nature of things and when the battle is over then it is over.  That reality will not come as a surprise to most of us who have contested an election.  In order to have confidence in the system then one must have meaningful sanctions that ensure the process is as fair as possible.  </p><p> I am interested in hearing about the timetable.  People have said they do not want a big bang.  What is a realistic timeline for putting in place a comprehensive system?  There will always be an element of adding things.  Would a realistic timeline be five years?  Do we need more time?  What elements would the witnesses like to see added and in what order?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.115" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Seamus McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#M00200"><p>I shall comment on a few of the points.  I have no disagreement with any of the points made about ensuring the integrity of the register of electors.  The committee may wish to get some information from the Department of Social Protection on its project for the development of a public services identity card.  The project is under way and aims to provide an identity card for every citizen.  The structure that will underpin the project, in terms of an individual identity number and the ability to link it with an image of a person, can be useful to the electoral register.  There is probably scope, in the longer term, to synchronise the systems and even to have recognition in polling stations, etc., when people present their cards.  The detail of that would be something that an electoral commission would negotiate with the Department.  Even to understand the model might give the committee some idea about what it would recommend as ways forward in regard to that matter.</p> <p>  I  referred to the conflict of interests in regard to the audit of an electoral commission.  Under the Constitution it is my obligation, as Comptroller and Auditor General, to audit the accounts of all funds under the authority of the Oireachtas.  Therefore, if funding is provided by the Oireachtas to an electoral commission then it would be expected that I would be the auditor of same.  In order to ensure that I have independence, as the auditor, I cannot then be involved in decision-making about the application of funds.  That is fundamentally the question.</p> <p>  The electoral commission, as envisaged, will be a spending body and there will be substantial funds going through same.  The difference broadly between, let us say, SIPO or a referendum commission, is that there is normally a fairly small budget involved.  In the case of SIPO it is a very small budget.  There is also an Accounting Officer, separately, to account for that.  Once one is the auditor who is tasked with reporting to Parliament, in regard to how resources are managed and applied, then it would not be consistent to be on the inside making the decisions and so on.</p><p>I was drawing a distinction between possibly putting a system in place with an Accounting Officer, where the commission would sit above the Accounting Officer level and would not necessarily be involved in the day-to-day resourcing decisions.  A model could be crafted but when it comes down to performance and decisions being made about developing a major IT project to underpin voter registration and identification, I think it would be very difficult for someone on the commission also to be the auditor.</p><p> On the point about giving SIPO more teeth, I would certainly agree that we are not always in a position as a commission because we act within the law and within the parameters set down by Parliament.</p><p> On the point about spending limits, that refers to electoral spending where there are limits in place.  There are strict rules around when the clock starts and stops ticking.  It is generally recognised that there are ways of doing things early that give the impression of a campaign up and running and there is very little SIPO can do because it has to operate within the law as it stands.  As to timelines, it depends on what one wants to do and what it is decided the electoral commission would achieve.  Looking at the consultation paper, the experience elsewhere has been that this is a multi-year project.  Any major IT project will be three to five years and that is generally the experience with large-scale projects.  That timeline of three, four or five years is probably what one is looking at for a comprehensive shift and realignment of functions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.117" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Peter Tyndall" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#N00200"><p>I will comment on the remarks about funding.  At present, SIPO deals with both electoral funding and the ongoing funding of political parties.  There is a question to be answered as to whether one would separate funding specifically related to expenditure in elections and ongoing funding of political parties.  Given the proposals for the future of the ethics regime, there has been an argument that the ongoing funding fits with the ethics and the lobbying in that they all relate to ongoing political activity as opposed to election related activity, but that would have to be teased out in a detailed discussion because the proposal in the ethics legislation to set up a standards commissioner might well have an impact on the decision on where to locate the function of ongoing political party funding.<br/><br/>The Comptroller and Auditor General has spoken about the impact on his role of creating an electoral commission, the role of <i>ex officio </i>members and how that might transfer.  Electoral commissions in some countries fall within the parliamentary ombudsman jurisdiction.  Were it decided for the future, and that is another decision that will have to be made as part of the ongoing consideration of legislation to bring an electoral commission within the Ombudsman jurisdiction, that would have an impact on the possibility of an <i>ex officio</i>role for the Ombudsman.<br/><br/>I would endorse the issue about the need for sanctions with more teeth.  The current regime probably is designed in a way that makes it very difficult to enforce it actively.  One would hope that any regime could be more actively enforced to deal with the kind of issues that Deputy Catherine Murphy was properly raising.</p><p> On a timeline, it seems that a lot of it relates to when a referendum may be held in the next Oireachtas and when the next set of elections might be held.  It appears as though it would be helpful, for instance, to put in place some aspects of a referendum process before a referendum might take place under the auspices of a new D&aacute;il.  This is probably a consideration.  I would have said three to five years as a timeline, with the latter figure on the outside because it would be good to see something in place.</p><p> To revert to the matter of appointments, I picked up on the issue of the current Oireachtas arrangements perhaps not being seen to be all-encompassing in respect of the various political parties.  However, it appears that fundamentally there should be an objective appointments process to public bodies and that appointments should subsequently be ratified by the Oireachtas in order that they would be perceived as being owned by it but undertaken in an objective and neutral fashion.  This would provide greater confidence in the new arrangements.  I have probably dealt with the elements that should be included.  As I stated, neither the Standards in Public Office Commission nor the Referendum Commission has taken a view on the role of local government.  It did not fall within our broad remit and it did not seem to be appropriate to comment.  Therefore, the ongoing points being made by representatives of local government probably have more relevance than anything it would be appropriate for us to say.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.119" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Paddy Walsh" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#O00200"><p>For Deputy Catherine Murphy's information, as long ago as 2003 the Standards in Public Office Commission raised the issue of election spending and the election period and what it was appropriate to cover.  As the Deputy probably is aware, it covers the period from the date on which an election is called until polling day, whereas a lot of money is front-loaded in the weeks in advance of that period.  In particular, when it is known that an election will take place, there will be a lot of front-loading.  As I said, the commission raised this issue as long ago as 2003.  It is also important to note that during the years the commission has raised the issue of the absence of teeth in the electoral legislation.  It can write to individuals about various aspects of what we suspect they are doing, but they can ignore us completely and there is no sanction for their failing to respond to us.  Obviously, we will suggest to any electoral commission that were it to consider all of the recommendations made in the past 12 years, it would be starting from a good point to be encompassed in any new legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.120" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Seamus McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#O00300"><p>On the point raised by Deputy Catherine Murphy about political funding, Mr. Tyndall has referred to the distinction to be drawn in respect of ongoing political funding, about which I made a quick analysis this morning.  It is running at approximately &euro;13 million to &euro;14 million per year for the parliamentary leaders allowance, Electoral Act funding and funding to Independents.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#O00400"><p>Will Mr. McCarthy confirm that the figure for State funding for political parties is &euro;13 million per year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.122" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Seamus McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#O00500"><p>It is &euro;13 million to &euro;14 million.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#O00600"><p>Through the party leaders allowance and the-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.124" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Seamus McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#O00700"><p>Through the party leaders allowance and funding povided under section 17 of the Electoral Act, 1997.  Expenditure on the parliamentary leaders allowance, Electoral Act funding and payments to Independents amount to approximately &euro;7 million, &euro;5.5 million and &euro;800,000, respectively.  The figures are relatively stable year on year.  When one considers the moneys that go through the finance accounts and which come from the Exchequer, they include returning officers' expenses, the reimbursement of expenses to candidates and election postal charges.  If one adds in Referendum Commission costs when referendums are held, the variance is incredible.  It varies from &euro;15.5 million in 2013 to &euro;65 million in 2011, when there was a general election.  It reflects the number of elections.  In 2011 there was a general election and a presidential election and referendums were held on the same day as the presidential election.</p><p>There are other instances when two referendums have taken place in the same year and then there are European and local elections to consider.  The position is quite variable but the amount involved comes in at between &euro;15 million and &euro;65 million.</p><p> One of the things that has struck me, as both an auditor and a member of SIPO, is the complexity of the onus on political parties and public representatives to account for the moneys they receive as a result of the fact that such moneys come under several guises and have to be accounted for discretely under separate guises.  There is a clear distinction between ongoing political funding for administrative purposes and moneys that are spent in the course of electoral campaigning, which is not funded from the public purse.  I think and I hope that the accounting for political parties, which will kick in with effect from this year and which will be reported from 2016, will bring a bit more clarity to the entire exercise involving the provision of public funding and the accounting for that.  There will need to be a distinction in the accounting between moneys for administrative, normal and ongoing purposes and campaign funding.  The guidelines that have been issued by SIPO require that kind of distinction to be made.  As stated, comprehensive reporting by political parties will be a major step forward in terms of knowing what is spent and how it is spent.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#P00200"><p>In Mr. McCarthy's estimation, what is the cost to the Exchequer of the holding of a referendum?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.127" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Seamus McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#P00300"><p>In terms of the direct spend through the Exchequer, I think it is of the order of &euro;15 million to &euro;15.5 million.  However, there may also be local authority expenditure involved.  If there is only one referendum in a particular year, there are obviously costs associated with maintaining the register and also the preparations relating to holding it.  The funding from the Exchequer is, as already stated, approximately &euro;15 million.  In 2014, the Exchequer paid out in the region of &euro;28 million in respect of the European and local elections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#P00400"><p>Does anyone else wish to contribute to the debate on those points raised by Deputy Catherine Murphy?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.129" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Joseph Nugent" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#P00500"><p>In the context of identity, prior to taking up my current role I served for five years as head of the Passport Service.  It is interesting that many of the issues associated with public identity are also emerging here.  I concur with Deputy Catherine Murphy in respect of the need to associate some of those other initiatives that are under way - whether it is the public services card or whatever - with what is being done.  At this point, none of the initiatives in question tackles all the issues at hand.  I have a public services card but, for example, it does not indicate one's citizenship.  This is relevant in the context that one's entitlement to vote in different types of elections is very different.  Notwithstanding that, there are sensitivities involved in using people's PPS numbers.  We all accept this to be the case.  If it is decided to use those numbers, we must ensure they will only be used within the confines of the trust the electorate bestows upon us.  PPS numbers are invaluable not just for the purpose of mitigating against people appearing on more than one register but also because they allow for that linkage to death events that would be recorded by the General Register Office and the automatic processing of related materials.</p> <p>  Issues of timing must be given careful consideration.  Clearly, the Electoral Acts, as amended, provide timelines for certain existing parameters and infrastructures.  For example, registration authorities and the timelines relating to the register are defined.  When drafting legislation, therefore, one would need to be very careful to ensure it does not fall foul of the problems associated with commencement of new provisions and that all the necessary infrastructure to facilitate a new regime, whatever that might be, would be put in place.  I return to the point I made in my opening contribution in respect of people referring to "the register".  There are 31 unconnected registers as matters stand.  This would seem to be an appropriate place to start in the context of examining the relevant issues to discover how one might provide the legislative authority to bring all those registers together into something that is more coherent and also, through the introduction of a unique identifier, how one might assist in that process.</p><p>With the pressures associated with deadlines, a rolling register is a key element associated with removing the impediments to the current process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.131" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Vincent Norton" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#Q00200"><p>On the registration process, Dublin City Council is probably one of the few local authorities that still uses inspectors to go around and check the register.  We find now increasingly that there is difficulty accessing premises.  There are many gated communities and very often we do not get that access.  An online facility is required at this stage in order that people can communicate with the local authority or the registration authority to register their intention to vote.  We firmly believe that minimal legislative change would facilitate that and this would make it much easier for people to vote.  That is one element of what the committee is considering but the registration process has been an issue of concern to many of its members.  Minimal change will allow that to take place.  Combined with a rolling register, that would make it much easier for people to get on the register.</p> <p>  Deputy Murphy made an important point about postal votes because, increasingly, people are away on holiday, working or in hospital and cannot vote and they increasingly ask for a postal vote, which is not available to them.  That is something else the committee could consider in its deliberations on the process.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.132" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#Q00300"><p>I apologise for not being present for the presentations but we had three divisions in the Seanad and, therefore, I was late.  I am not sure who the county manager or the county registrar was at the time but I met a guy at a meeting either before the previous general election or the previous local elections but he had voted nine or ten times in Northern Ireland.  He had spent the day visiting polling stations in various parts of Northern Ireland.  He was registered in County Louth and when I checked the then most recent supplementary register, his name was on it for County Louth and I discovered he was on the register five times in the county.  I know he only had one vote where he lived.  This happens more often than we think, particularly in Border counties, for whatever reason.  Using PPS numbers is the only way to ensure this cannot happen whereby a number corresponds to a name.  The person to whom I referred still lives in County Louth and I am sure he has only one vote now.  Had I not been at a meeting and identified him with the help of a rates collector, I would not have known about this.  I asked the rates collector whether this person was a chubby guy with a curly head and he said he was.  He was on the register five times.  We must stop this.</p> <p>  I refer to the issue of people living away from home.  My children do not live at home.  They did not have their bums on seats until they were off the register in County Louth.  I blame that on a person locally who was keeping the register up to date.  Depending on one's politics, one could be removed from the register.  That is the reality.  I know people on the register who are married with families in London and Belfast.  I hope I have never done a bad turn against anyone and I do not intend reporting them but there has to be some way to ensure this does not happen.</p><p>I know of a family coming home in six weeks.  If they were still on the register, they could vote.  What I have described is the reality and it is happening.</p><p> When somebody dies, a public representative should be able to let the local authority know.  I do not believe anybody would give false information on a death maliciously.  We must ensure the registers are more up to date.  I believe the only way to eliminate much of what is occurring is to use a PPS or PRSI number.  If a person is away from home and has not used his PPS number for years, this should provoke the local authority into asking where that individual was for the years in question.  I describe the reality.  I know people married with families in London who are still on the local register.  I do not know who is to blame and whether it is a result of party-political broadcasting.  Perhaps that is the reason.  In so far as we can, we should maintain the registers.  We all have a contribution to make.  We should have a more up-to-date register throughout the country.  I am not singling out County Louth because conditions are very good there.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#R00200"><p>Would any of the witnesses like to respond to that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.135" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Vincent Norton" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#R00300"><p>At present, it is a question of a household return in respect of voting on the register.  Very often, one finds the head of the household will make the return even though people are away.  What we look for is individual responsibility for registering to vote, using the PPS number.  What we do in Dublin city is obtain dates of birth.  Very often we can do searches to ensure there is no duplication.  However, the ideal response is to use a PPS number and individual registration.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1138" speakername="Terry Brennan" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#R00400"><p>What is the big problem with using the PPS number?  Does everybody have one?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.137" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Vincent Norton" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#R00500"><p>Everyone has a PPS number.  The issue concerns data protection.  We have seen the issues this has raised in other areas.  If there were responsibility to submit the PPS number according to an arrangement whereby it would not be held but used initially only for verification, that would be the way around the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#R00600"><p>Like Senator Brennan, I apologise as I was detained in the Seanad.  The delegation is very welcome.  This debate was had before.  The recommendations in the Geary Institute report give some food for thought on how we should proceed.</p> <p>  Some very good submissions have been made.  A very good feature of this committee is that it can consider submissions by outside bodies, academics and others.  Given that politicians are in the middle of the issue, they may be the worst people to consider it.  Therefore, outside views and views from academia are useful.  I thank the people who are not here today who made submissions.  I will not mention any names.</p> <p>  I fully agree on the views expressed regarding PPS numbers.  The savings would be minimal if they were taken from local authorities.  I would like to see an analysis to determine what the savings would be, if anything.  I was a member of South Dublin County Council for 25 years.  That local authority was one of the first to become very modern in its use of IT.  Local authorities are now well able to become even more modern and link in with any relevant national body.</p> <p>  Lest the witnesses get me wrong, I must welcome the formation of the electoral commission.  It is very necessary but it is not necessary for the full role of local authorities to be subsumed under it.  The roles of each body should be defined absolutely.  I have spoken all my life &mdash; I will not change now &mdash; about the devolution of functions to local authorities.  Too many tasks are centralised and we must have devolution of functions.  Who better to know people on the ground than those in local authorities?  Senator Brennan referred to duplication.  The rate collectors of long ago knew everybody.  Staff in local authorities and local councillors are knowledgeable and there is all the local information.  If there is too much centralisation, all that will be lost.</p><p>I note there was a good submission from the Association of Irish Local Government, AILG, on these issues, including on what would be lost if everything was to be centralised.  Some things should and must be centralised.  A single co-ordinating body is a necessity.  Other than that, administration can be managed locally but oversight should be centralised.  In my experience, everything in local government has been above reproach.  <br/><br/>There are issues concerning household versus individual registration.  The PPS number has to be used because there is no other identifiable method.  However, we ran into trouble in using it before when it was recommended that it be used for water charges purposes.  It must be held for a specific purpose and this is such a purpose.<br/><br/>The accuracy of the electoral register is often called into question.  Councillors, Deputies and Senators have pointed to inaccuracies.  It should be publicised that it is not necessary to de-register in one county before a person registers in another.  One can move house from one county to another, which is a feature of greater mobility.  I compliment the <i>checktheregister.ie</i>website which has moved on a lot from where it was when I started off.<br/><br/>The link with birth, marriage and death records is necessary.  When a person dies, if a red flag were to pop up, the record could be removed from the electoral register.  The <i>rip.ie</i>website provides another record.  I attended Eoghan Culligan's funeral and it put everything into perspective.  <br/><br/>Enhancing participation in elections should be a national issue.  If the electoral commission did not enhance participation, it should be sacked straightaway.<br/><br/>The absence of centralised data is a problem.  I receive emails to obtain data for tallies.  The commission should have a role in that regard.  These are historical records, but it is left to Mr. Se&aacute;n Donnelly in <i>elections.org</i>or Mr. Chris Took in <i>electionsireland.org</i>to provide them.  Incidentally, I could not open Mr. Took's submission because of the way it had been saved in WARC, rather than in a pdf file or Word.  I will have to take up that matter with the IT unit.  These websites do the work a national body should be doing in the case of historical election records.  Their work should be aided because they know how to do it.<br/><br/>The Constituency Commission should remain because it is independent and does work that could not be left to others.  SIPO should be amalgamated in some way with the commission because two bodies are not needed to do the work.<br/><br/>We should not throw the baby out with the bath water.  We could lose more than we would gain by taking something away from local authorities.  Local councils would do the work better if they had more IT staff and a good programme for checking the electoral register.  I would be careful about centralising everything because we are seeking devolution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.140" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1082" speakername="Tony McLoughlin" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#S00200"><p>The delegates are very welcome.  I support what previous speakers said about PPS numbers.  I have raised both here and in the D&aacute;il the issue of abuse concerning draft electoral registers.  At the last local elections in my constituency quite a number of people who were registered were not living in the country.</p><p>The draft register arrived at very late stage.   These people who were working in Canada, the US, Australia and various other places were on the register.  Certain people examined the matter closely to ensure they did not vote.  In the past, rate collectors looked at this.  I know it has been said that the system is different in Dublin but it is very difficult in the country to know who is on the register.  It is vitally important.</p><p> I represent Sligo-North Leitrim.  This constituency will now include Sligo, Leitrim, west Cavan and south Donegal.  After the next election, I will, hopefully, be representing four counties.  There is no justification for splitting because I have seen what has happened in Leitrim over the years.  There has been a history there over the years because it was suitable for the constituency to be broken up, regardless of whether part of it went to Roscommon and the other part went to Sligo.  All of Leitrim is now back in the constituency but it also includes west Cavan and south Donegal.  These people feel that they are totally disenfranchised by being put in a different constituency.  It is also very difficult for us as public representatives.  Could the witnesses give us their comments on that?  </p><p> It is vitally important that the draft register be examined as well because significant abuses are occurring.  Deputy Troy mentioned a person voting on nine occasions.  It is our business as public representatives to see that people are registered.  The problem is that come election day, people who want to vote are not on the register.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.142" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Seamus McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#T00200"><p>In respect of the PPS number, Senator Keane mentioned the register of births, marriages and deaths.  There is already an automated system based on the PPS number whereby deaths notified to the registrar feed automatically into the system in the Department of Social Protection and payments are stopped fairly quickly.  The HSE uses that information as well.  More than 30 services take the information and automatically feed it in using data matching techniques but one must have a unique identifier that can link the two databases.  There is clearly a consensus here that as a control mechanism, it is certainly a way forward.  Talking to the Department about the public services identity card may be worthwhile for this committee's deliberations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.143" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Joseph Nugent" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#T00300"><p>To follow up on Mr. McCarthy's comments, all local authorities routinely receive the death event notification but in the absence of the unique identifier, there are limits to what we can do.  Clearly, every effort is made is to try to match as best we can but, ultimately, the absence of that direct linkage with the PPS number is a barrier.</p> <p>  I appreciate Senator Keane's agreement about the need for local involvement in this.  I will provide an anecdote involving a friend of mine whose father was bereaved and whose polling card had been pulled locally as a result of that local awareness, which was referred by Senator Keane and Deputy McLoughlin.  That local effort and knowledge are certainly very valuable and important elements of the process.  In our view, centralising that and taking away some of that local knowledge will not address trust and provide the support one would want.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.144" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Mairead Ahern" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#U00100"><p>Some of the most disappointed voters who appear at polling stations on the day are new Irish citizens.  Some people may not be aware of what I mean, but there is an L mark beside their name on the list.  This means they can only vote in the local elections.  Some of these people have recently gone through the Irish citizenship ceremony.  I wonder whether it would be possible for those people to be notified and for that database to be available to the local authorities to verify the change of status.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.145" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1135" speakername="Ca&iacute;t Keane" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#U00200"><p>A big problem that has occurred in the past relates to people arriving at polling stations only to find they are not on the register, having been removed from it for no good reason other than that they were not at home when someone called or whatever.  That has been a problem.  There should be double checks and balances such that when a name is actually clicked off the list, the person is gone.  That is a major problem as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/996" speakername="Michael McCarthy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ENJ2015062300002#U00300"><p>That is a good point.  Do the witnesses wish to make any closing statements?  No.  I thank them kindly for their assistance this afternoon.  This will help us greatly in deliberating on the issue.</p> <p>  I have some comments on the Standards in Public Office Commission.  I stood in several elections before I became a Deputy.  I remember in 2002 the Kelly judgment delayed the time by which forms had to go back.  I wish to put on record my appreciation for the people I dealt with in trying to meet deadlines.  They offered all types of assistance.  Mr. Walsh might have been one of those concerned.  It was a major leap to go from virtually no declarations to filling out forms, meeting various limits and getting peace commissioners to sign documents.  I appreciate the effort that people go to in offices like SIPO as well as their professionalism and that of the local authorities.</p> <p>  We have been lucky in my area in that the register of electors is fairly accurate.  There are various traditional reasons for that.  When people are in an area where public services are good, they tend not to appreciate where the system may not be as good.  That is no reflection on the people concerned.  Perhaps the system itself may not be as uniform as it should be.  I thank the witnesses very much for their assistance.  They are free to go.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-06-23a.147" nospeaker="true" time="14:15:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 3.50 p.m. and adjourned at 4 p.m. until 2.15 p.m. on Tuesday, 30 June 2015.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>