<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.2" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on European Union Affairs</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.3" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 10:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Eric Byrne, Senator Colm Burke, Deputy Seán Crowe, Senator Catherine Noone. Deputy Timmy Dooley, Deputy Bernard J. Durkan, Deputy John Halligan, Deputy Dara Murphy,</p><p>DEPUTY DOMINIC HANNIGAN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.5" nospeaker="true" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500002#A00100">Forthcoming General Affairs Council: Minister of State at the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500002#A00200"><p>I ask people to switch off their mobile telephones and iPads.  It is not sufficient to put them in silent mode, they need to be switched off.  We have received apologies from Senator Kathryn Reilly.  The first item on the agenda is a discussion on the forthcoming meeting of the General Affairs Council.  We are pleased to be joined again by the Minister of State with special responsibility for European affairs, Deputy Paschal Donohoe, who will attend the meeting in question in Brussels next Tuesday.  The General Affairs Council is expected to discuss the Greek Presidency programme and the preparations for the European Council meeting in March.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500002#A00300"><p>I thank the Chairman.  It is always a pleasure to address the joint committee.  I greatly appreciate the committee's decision to change the time of this meeting to facilitate my appearance here.  I asked for the meeting to be rescheduled because I am travelling to Berlin tomorrow afternoon for a number of engagements.  While I am in Berlin, I will have an opportunity to meet my new ministerial counterpart, Michael Roth, before we start to work with each other formally at next week's meeting of the General Affairs Council.  The committee will be aware that I believe it is important to invest time in continuing to develop bilateral relations with colleagues in all EU member states.  I appreciate the rearranging of this meeting to allow me to do that.  I will travel to Warsaw later this month for the same reason.</p><p>  The Chairman and Deputy Eric Byrne have raised the specific question of Bosnia with me on a number of occasions, including at this forum in December.  I have just returned from that country and I will provide a short update on my meetings there later in this statement.  As there was no General Affairs Council meeting in January, it is some time since I have met the committee in this way.  I was with the Taoiseach in mid-January when he made his post-European Council statement to the House.  I answered a number of questions on the European Council meeting that occasion.  I do not propose to go through all of that again.  Instead, I will speak about next week's General Affairs Council, which will start the preparatory process for the March European Council meeting, deal with the Greek Presidency programme and consider a proposal on genetically modified maize.</p><p>  As members are aware, Greece took over the Presidency of the Council at the beginning of this year.  This is Greece&rsquo;s fifth Presidency.  It is the final Presidency in the trio of Presidencies that started with Ireland in January 2013.  As members will know from their meeting with the Greek Ambassador to Ireland on 16 January last, a busy and challenging period lies ahead.  There will be considerable change within the European institutions as a result of the European elections in May and as preparations are made for the new college of Commissioners in the autumn.  The election of a new European Parliament and the appointment of new Commissioners will of course have an impact.  I understand the Presidency has taken this on board.  It intends to prioritise the completion of first readings in the European Parliament before April, before focusing primarily on the Council during the latter part of its term.</p> <p> Under a banner of "Europe: Our common quest", the Greek Presidency will continue to work on existing files while drawing on its own strengths to bring a Mediterranean and maritime flavour to its six months of the Presidency.  Four thematic areas of work have been identified by our Greek colleagues.  They are growth-jobs-cohesion, further integration of EU-eurozone, migration-borders-mobility and maritime policies.  We are supportive of all four of these important areas of work.  We will press in particular for progress on the first two areas.  It is vital that Europe continues to support the work of member states in ensuring economic recovery; in improving the employment opportunities for the unemployed, particularly the young; in maintaining financial stability; and in making sure that recovery is sustainable.  The focus on migration and maritime policies is welcome as both are areas where we believe that Greece can add an element of leadership that is particularly useful to the Union.  </p><p> The Presidency has a substantive body of work planned but I might just refer to some of the files we believe will be of particular importance to Ireland.  In the economic and financial sphere, the most significant result would be to reach agreement with the European Parliament on the single resolution mechanism under the banking union.  The Presidency will manage the Council's input into the interim evaluation of the Europe 2020 strategy and its targets and will oversee the European semester process.  This is, of course, of significant national interest.  The European Commission recently published a communication on a 2030 framework for energy and climate policies.  This is an important document that I believe will lead to a lot of discussion in most member states.  Ireland has a particular interest in ensuring that appropriate account is taken of agriculture and food security.  I will come back on this point and on the European semester later under the European Council agenda item.</p><p> We will support the Greek Presidency in progressing outstanding Single Market issues.  I am also pleased to see that the Presidency will be keeping trade as clear priority and we hope strong progress will be made on the negotiations with the US under the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, process.  Alongside that, I look forward to continuing work on the negotiations with other countries.  On enlargement, Greece will build on recent work by previous Presidencies, including Ireland.  Having formally opened accession negotiations with Serbia on 21 January, the Greek Presidency will be aiming to advance those talks over the coming months.  It also wants to continue discussions with Montenegro.  The Greeks have clearly identified maritime policy as a cross-cutting priority and will look at several initiatives to develop a more integrated approach.  Ireland's own Presidency had a strong maritime focus and we are pleased to see this issue receive continued focus.  There is clearly a lot to do and I look forward to working with the Greek Presidency and in particular with my Greek counterpart, Mr. Dimitris Kourkoulas, to ensure that maximum progress is achieved.</p><p> The second item on the agenda next Tuesday is, of course, the preparation of the next European Council.  This is a crucial function of the General Affairs Council, bringing political-level influence into the European Council preparations.  This is the very start of the preparatory process so we will not be getting into a lot of detail at this stage.  The reason for this is because the next European Council meeting will be in March so there will be another General Affairs Council meeting before then.  In consequence, this session is very much in the early stages of preparation.  We will, however, consider the draft annotated agenda which includes the European semester, industrial competitiveness, climate and energy and external relations.  I will say a few words on each of these items.</p><p> The Council will mark the next key phase of the European semester.  As the committee is aware, this fourth European semester cycle is the first in which Ireland will be a full participant.  Again, the reason for that is because having exited the external aid programme, we move into the semester process which already contains other members of the eurozone.  It is also the first European semester cycle to take place under the further enhancements to the Stability and Growth Pact introduced by the Two Pack regulations.  These regulations are the proposals in place in respect of the preparation of national budgets and their impact on the national finances of member states.  The European Council will provide clear orientations to member states for preparation and submission in mid-April of their stability programme updates  under the stability and growth Pact and national reform programmes under the Europe 2020 Strategy.  The European Council in December had already agreed that member states and the European Union will continue to take determined action to promote sustainable growth, jobs and competitiveness.  This, of course, is an emphasis that is already reflected strongly in the clear direction we have set at national level, including through the interlocking action plan for jobs and Pathways to Work strategies.  </p><p> The Spring European Council will also focus on industrial competitiveness, including innovation and skills.  I expect that exchanges here will be informed by the deliberations of the Competitiveness Council on 20 February and on the recent Commission Communication, For a European industrial renaissance.  This includes a particular emphasis on the economic significance of the manufacturing sector, which accounts for over 3.8 million of the roughly six million jobs lost across Europe since 2008.  Creating the right conditions to underpin internationally competitive manufacturing firms, including linkages with bundled services, will, therefore, be an important feature of a successful and durable European recovery.  The Spring European Council will also take note of the first evaluation of the Europe 2020 strategy, which falls for review this year.  A communication in this regard is expected from the Commission over the coming weeks.  The Spring European Council is likely to be followed by a full public consultation, the outcome of which will then be taken forward by the new Commission.  I also understand that when the Commission's Secretary General, Catherine Day, met the committee on 23 January, she emphasised the importance of strong stakeholder engagement with this review, including, of course, that of national parliaments.  </p><p> The European Council will also consider the Commission&rsquo;s January Package, the key element of which was a communication setting out its ambition for a 2030 climate and energy framework.  It also included a communication on energy prices and costs in Europe; a legislative proposal on emissions trading; a communication on industrial policy, which I have already mentioned; and a recommendation on unconventional oil and gas.  In terms of EU policy development, the proposed framework addresses the next critical milestone in the high-level EU objective on transition to a competitive, low-carbon economy in 2050.  In addition, the climate pillars of the proposed framework are central to EU engagement and leadership in the international climate process under the UN framework convention on climate change.  The proposed framework comprises a package of policy proposals, including greenhouse gas emission and renewable energy targets for 2030, a set of new indicators to ensure a competitive and secure energy system and a totally new governance structure based on member state plans for competitive, secure and sustainable energy.</p><p> These individual pillars and the framework as a whole will require careful consideration in terms of the challenges for Ireland and the opportunity to strengthen national competitiveness in the emerging global green economy.  By way of initial response, Ireland has acknowledged the communication as a good basis for the policy debate on a 2030 framework and stressed the need for cost-effectiveness.  While the proposals will now need to be examined in detail, we welcome the recognition that renewable energy has an important contribution to make to the 2030 goals.</p> <p>Further clarity is, however, needed on the binding nature of the renewable energy target and the governance framework proposed.  This includes further information from the Commission regarding the assumptions behind its modelling of the proposed renewables target which will not be binding on individual member states but on the EU as a whole.  We look forward to working with member states and the Commission to ensure the cost-effective implementation of the renewable energy element without placing a disproportionate burden on EU energy consumers.</p><p> The proposal in the communication to examine and pursue the most appropriate climate policy approach to agriculture and land use, is a major and very welcome development from the Irish perspective.  Since current EU climate and energy policy for the period to 2020 was finalised in 2008, Ireland has pursued and continues to pursue, a case for a more holistic policy approach to greenhouse gas emissions and removals from agriculture and land use, including forestry.  A coherent and cost-effective approach to the parallel priorities of food security and climate change is fundamental to a realistic way forward at national, EU and wider international level under the UN convention.  We will be prioritising and engaging intensively in the discussions on the agriculture and land use element of the framework.</p><p> The General Affairs Council discussion on the climate and energy package will be followed by further preparatory discussions in the coming weeks at the relevant sectoral councils dealing with competitiveness, environment and energy, culminating in the European Council meeting on 20 and 21 March.  This will be a period of intense work in order to digest and analyse the Commission&rsquo;s proposals.</p><p> The third substantive item on the General Affairs Council agenda is a proposal concerning a genetically modified maize crop.  This proposal relates to an authorisation under consideration to allow a maize seed product to be placed on the market for cultivation across the European Union.  The European Commission has been obliged to expedite consideration of this issue following a successful action in the European Court of Justice by the Pioneer company which owns the seed.  The maize in question has been modified to withstand the European corn borer worm which affects crops in warm climates.  Growing the modified maize would reduce the need for application of certain pesticides.  However, the crop in question is not relevant in an Irish context as the pest is not an issue for Irish agriculture.</p><p> The deliberate release of GMOs is primarily a matter for the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government.  The Minister, Deputy Hogan has consulted with ministerial colleagues as well the national competent authority for GMO matters, the Environmental Protection Agency.  The European Food Safety Authority and the EPA agree that the product will not pose a threat to human health or the environment.  Nevertheless, we note that GM cultivation continues to be a divisive issue across the member states.  Given that the product is not directly relevant to Irish agriculture, Ireland will abstain in the upcoming vote.  The Government has endorsed the voting position proposed by the Minister, Deputy Hogan.</p><p> I wish to take this opportunity to speak about  my visit to Bosnia and Herzegovina last week, although this is not an issue on the General Affairs Council agenda.  Members will have seen that over the course of a very intensive programme I had the opportunity to meet with the Chairman of the Council of Ministers - the Prime Minister - the Foreign Minister and members of the joint committee for European integration of the parliamentary assembly.  I met with a range of representatives from the international community, including EU special representative Mr. Sorensen and the Council of Europe head of delegation, Mary Ann Hennessy, both of whom have addressed this committee in the past.  I met the head of the OSCE Delegation, Mr Fletcher Burton and the EU High Representative for Bosnia and Herzegovina, Mr Valentin Inzko, whom members will recall addressed the COSAC meeting in Dublin last June. </p><p> I also had the wonderful opportunity to address students at the University of Sarajevo which is something I try to do in all of my visits abroad.  When I visit a country I always try to deliver public engagements so that people abroad and at home understand the nature of our work.  I met with some of the Irish community in Bosnia and Herzegovina, including the members of the Defence Forces stationed with the EU mission in Camp Butmir.  Before travelling to Sarajevo, I met with members of the Bosnian community here in Ireland and they provided me with very valuable perspectives and insights.  The Bosnia community in Ireland numbers 2,000 members.  Ireland has a strong and proud tradition of helping that country.  Throughout my visit I sought to express a number of key messages in both my private and public meetings, the first message being Ireland&rsquo;s support for Bosnia and Herzegovina.  I made clear that this support comes from the Government and the Oireachtas.</p><p> The second message is our support for Bosnia and Herzegovina&rsquo;s path towards membership of the EU.  I spoke of Ireland&rsquo;s experiences of EU membership, setting out the benefits as well as the challenges that Union membership presents.  The third message is our encouragement for Bosnia and Herzegovina to advance on its EU path.  I specifically highlighted the importance of implementing the European Court of Human Right's ruling in the Sejdic-Finci case ahead of elections later this year and of establishing a co-ordination mechanism on EU issues among state institutions.  As members will be aware, the Sejdic-Finci ruling requires that all members of the communities in Bosnia and Herzegovina have equal opportunities to participate in public and political life in the country.  My interlocutors all expressed their appreciation for the support shown to Bosnia and Herzegovina by the Irish people and successive Governments over the years and for our ongoing support for their EU accession process.</p><p> I look forward to returning to further discussions on the issue of Bosnia and Herzegovina in this committee on a future occasion, but given the number of times this issue is dealt with in this committee I wished to record the awareness and appreciation in Bosnia and Herzegovina for Ireland&rsquo;s support.  I take this opportunity to update the committee on the recent visit I made to Albania.  I visited Albania because of the strong Irish support for ensuring that the European Union plays a positive and a prominent role in that region supporting the peoples of those countries in their road towards EU membership or towards a better relationship with the European Union.  I met the prime minister, the foreign minister and a large number of representatives from all political parties, including the speaker of the house of parliament, the local mayor.  I also spoke in Tirana to Albanian students, non-governmental organisations and I participated in a public meeting to explain Ireland's position with regard to their country.  </p><p> I will conclude by emphasising the strong interest shown by the Government and our EU policy in that region and my determination to play a positive role.  I hope this presentation has given the committee a reasonable overview of the General Affairs Council discussion topics next week and a brief update on my visits abroad.  I am happy to answer questions from members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500004#C00200"><p>I have a question about Bosnia and Herzegovina which this committee visited about 15 months ago.  We met with many of the people the Minister of State also met.  We met the European integration committee, Mr. Fletcher Burton, Valentin Inzko and we also travelled to see the Irish soldiers at work in Camp Butmir.  It was a very interesting and informative visit.</p> <p>One message we got from our trip was that, since the Dayton peace agreement, there had been little development in the political life of Bosnia-Herzegovina, BiH.  Will the Minister of State update the committee briefly on how that situation is developing?</p><p> Yesterday, the committee met a number of guests, including Dr. John O'Brennan from NUI Maynooth.  He specifically mentioned the issues of integration and enlargement.  In his opinion, there were unmistakable signs across European capitals that the appetite for enlargement was on the wane.  At the Conference of Community and European Affairs Committees of Parliaments of the European Union, COSAC, last week, the representative from the Former Yugoslav Republic of Macedonia, FYROM, spoke along those lines and queried why enlargement was a priority for the Greek Presidency during its last Presidency, which was its fourth, but was not its priority this time.  Has the issue of enlargement gone off the boil, particularly as regards Turkey and the Balkan states?  It is a priority for Ireland.  Is there still a desire throughout the Union to continue with the enlargement policy?</p><p> I mentioned our meeting yesterday.  An RTE journalist, Mr. Tony Connelly, also attended.  We discussed the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, which the Minister of State mentioned in his address, and the problems involved in moving forward with same.  Mr. Connelly made the point that the TTIP was a priority for us during our Presidency and that, due to our historical and strong links with the US, we managed to get TTIP up and running.  He questioned whether we should step in and try to push it forward.  Would our Government have an enhanced role in progressing the TTIP?</p><p> Our third guest yesterday was former MEP and Deputy, Proinsias de Rossa.  He referred to how our committee could play a role in the selection of the next Irish Commissioner.  He suggested that the nominee should appear before us and take questions on his or her views on Europe and the Commission itself.  Would this be a useful exercise for the committee?</p><p> The Minister of State will lead a series of discussions in our universities on the Irish working in EU institutions.  I commend him on this worthwhile initiative.  Will he provide a quick outline of what it will involve?</p><p> Before calling members, I will ask a final question about the Commission's communication last week on voting rights for EU citizens.  It criticised five nations for not giving their nationals sufficient voting rights, those being, us, the UK, Malta, Cyprus and Denmark.  This is a matter in which the committee is interested.  We intend to hold meetings to discuss the Commission's guidance and how Ireland can improve voting rights for our diaspora.  Does the Minister of State have an opinion on what could be done and how we should progress this issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500005#D00200"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I have two questions about matters touched on by the Chairman.  The Minister of State's comments on enlargement were interesting.  If there is to be enlargement, what will be the further reduction in the number of MEPs?  I should probably know the answer, but I do not.</p><p>  Yesterday, we held a discussion with three guests.  The disconnect between Irish citizens and the EU in all its guises seemed to be to the fore in people's minds.  Does the Minister of State have ideas for improving this situation?  I have done some work in this regard recently.  Forums could be held on, for example, a quarterly basis affording MEPs an opportunity to explain what they were doing in Europe.  The broadcaster also has a part to play.  Showing the European Parliament on television once per month in the middle of the night is not ideal.  MEPs should be drawn on by RTE for comment.  The EU rarely gets credit for the work it does, particularly on consumer issues, etc.  I would be interested in the Minister of State's reply.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.13" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1094" speakername="John Halligan" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500005#D00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State and offer him belated congratulations on his appointment.  I have not had a chance to do so officially yet.  He is doing a good job.</p><p>  I have visited BiH.  What is the Minister of State's opinion?  It is a decentralised country with three ethnic groups, ten federations and a large degree of political, economic and religious segregation.  I found the politics uncomfortable, as do many of those living there.  Is the Minister of State satisfied with the EU's efforts to pull BiH into line?  We might as well be blunt - the country itself acknowledges that there is a great deal of corruption there, even within the political system.  The minority group politicians that the Chairman, others and I met acknowledged this.</p><p>  There seems to be a mad rush to bring BiH into the EU.  I do not have a problem with that, as the more people who join the EU, the better.  However, we do not seem to have put much effort into dealing with a country that is so decentralised.  According to people I know who live there, the situation appears to be worsening.  I am not trying to put the Minister of State on the spot, but is he satisfied with the EU's efforts or could much more be done before BiH could even be considered for membership?  There is also a mad rush for it to join NATO.  That this will probably happen before it joins the EU is appalling.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500005#D00400"><p>I thank members for their questions.  The Chairman asked about BiH and whether there was fatigue regarding enlargement and a more prominent role for the EU in the Balkans.  That is not the case.  Consider the EU's strong role in the breakthrough in the Serbia-Kosovo relationship.  The High Representative, Baroness Catherine Ashton, played a pivotal role in that regard.  Serbia is making progress in developing its relationship with the EU.  It goes without saying that we are holding this discussion in the aftermath of our friends in Croatia having successfully joined the EU.  The EU's recent track record in the region shows one new member state and the Union playing a significant role in seeking to advance stability and good relations between the region's countries.</p><p>  We must acknowledge that the nature of the accession process has changed significantly for many of the countries currently involved in it.  This is because the Union itself has changed.</p> <p>The level of integration within the European Union has evolved considerably for existing member states.</p><p> The process Ireland went through to join the European Union is incomparable to the process gone through by countries that recently joined or those seeking to join.  Given that the Union has changed and the integration within it has deepened, the accession process has changed in parallel to that.  Having been in Albania and Bosnia-Herzegovina and talking to people in other countries in the region, I understand the difficulties that can create for them but this is all about trying to put in place a process that is right for countries seeking to join the Union and for the Union itself.</p><p> The Chairman is correct is saying that the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership, TTIP, negotiations is of huge importance to Ireland and I am aware it is becoming the source of increased public comment in America where much discussion is currently taking place.  We believe that negotiations in this regard are continuing to progress in a satisfactory manner.  We are very much aware of the role our country played in this regard during our Presidency when we got much of this process up and running, and we have a clear stake in ensuring that continues.  When the Taoiseach and other members of Government visit America in the near future it would provide a great opportunity to emphasise this point and make clear the scale of the mutual prize open to America and the European Union.</p><p> On the Chairman's point about the role of this committee in the selection of the next Irish Commissioner, he will be aware that I am a firm supporter of the clear delineation between the role of the Oireachtas and the role of the Executive.  It is entirely up to this committee to decide what it wants to do and how it wants to structure its engagement with that candidate or any other candidate.  I would note, however, that when the candidates go forward they will face a thorough scrutiny process within the European Parliament, but I will leave that matter to the Chairman. </p><p> Regarding the series of discussions in the universities, the background to this, which I will briefly explain to the committee, is that we find ourselves in a position where a very large number of our citizens are represented in the European institutions, such as the Commission, at senior and middle management levels.  As those people move on to other endeavours, we will find ourselves in a position where the kind of representation we have had in the past will decline.  We are currently putting in place a proactive campaign on two different levels.  The first is to encourage Irish graduates - people already working - to consider careers within the European institutions.  The second is to examine what we can do to ensure that Irish people currently working within our civil and public services have the opportunity to work within these institutions as part of their careers.</p><p> With regard to what I am doing to support each of those elements, particularly the college element noted by the Chairman noted, I am travelling to all the colleges to launch the campaign.  We have done two of those.  We started off last Monday in University College Dublin, UCD, we then moved on to Trinity College, and we will work our way around the country to do the same.  I was struck by the number of people who turned up at each of these events.  More than 150 people attended the event held in UCD.  It was standing room only; the room was packed.  The Trinity College event was over-subscribed by a multiple of three.  We ended up with an attendance of between 130 and 140 people and we could probably have filled a room twice the size of the one in which we held the event.  Such attendance would be driven by different reasons, with which members would be very familiar, but I was encouraged that a very large number of very capable young Irish men and women showed an interest in working in our public services and our European public services.  Were that to develop, that would be to our collective benefit, to the benefit of Ireland and Europe.  As candidates become apparent who want to apply and who are credible in terms of being successful at the other end of the process, we will help them in that process because we want to support people through it and give them every support we can.</p><p> Senator Noone raised two points.  On her point regarding a reduction in the number of MEPs, I am well aware, as is the Senator, of the change we have had here.  We will still have a very significant representation within the European Parliament.  Our MEPs are of a very high calibre and I am sure that will be the case following the next European Parliament elections.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500006#E00200"><p>There are some excellent candidates also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500006#E00300"><p>Absolutely.</p><p>  On Senator's Noone's point about the perceived disconnect between European institutions and Irish people, I am well aware of that.  However, I see some positive signs of where that is changing.  I have been struck by a few small changes recently which when put together could have a cumulative effect.  In recent weeks RTE in its coverage has given considerable recognition to debates taking place in the European Parliament.  That happened yesterday when Mr. Paul Murphy, MEP, and Mr. Se&aacute;n Kelly, MEP, were quoted in respect of their contributions in a debate on a report that emanated from the Commission.  Prior to that there was great deal of focus on proposals from the European Parliament on plain packaging on cigarettes.  Following the devastation that has taken place in many of our cities across the country, we can see how quickly and correctly people have identified the role of the Commission in providing emergency funding to deal with this difficulty.  On a smaller scale, any person who has the opportunity to holiday abroad this summer will get a message on their  mobile phone from the European Union to alert them that their usage has gone over a certain level.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500006#E00400"><p>They will get a message.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500006#E00500"><p>They will get a text message.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1153" speakername="Catherine Noone" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500006#E00600"><p>I do not think the EU gets credit for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500006#E00700"><p>The text message that comes through on the network on my mobile telephone makes reference to the European Union.  All these changes with regard to the role of the European Union at consumer level, if nothing else, over time will have an effect in the way people perceive the role of the Union and the work it can do.</p><p>  On Deputy Halligan's direct point regarding my impressions of Bosnia-Herzegovina and if I am happy with the structures there, I was struck by the very decentralised structure that he correctly identified.  That has been very successful at bringing to an end the terrible violence that afflicted that country for so long.  I was struck by two aspects regarding Sarajevo, the city I visited, of which the Deputy may be aware.  The first is that it was subjected to the longest seize in recent military history and, second, that the city into which I flew was a no-fly zone 20 years ago.  When progress has been made from those times, one must conclude from that, as I did, that the decentralised political structure, to which the Deputy referred, and the two entities within the federation - in other words, Republic of Srpska and the structure for Bosnia Herzegovina - have played a positive role in bringing all that conflict to an end.</p><p>  However, the big question that the Deputy at least inferred is whether they are structures that are capable of meeting the aspirations of the communities within them with regard to a standard of living and all the other issues about which everybody cares.</p> <p>This was brought home to me by the approximately 100 young people who attended my public address at the University in Sarajevo and expressed desire for the types of things about which Irish people talk and their concerns in regard to whether they will materialise for them.</p><p> On whether the European Union is playing a strong enough role in Bosnia, I believe it is.  Mr. S&oslash;rensen, in terms of his prominence in public life in that country, is doing an enormous amount of work.  I believe we are doing all we can to support that country on the journey it needs to make.  However, there are two perspectives in this regard, of which the Deputy will probably be aware from his time there.  Any plan or long-term solution for the country must come from the people.  We are all aware of the understandable concerns that arose in Ireland, a country 40 years a member of the European Union that has a standard of living and income per head that is significantly ahead of that in Bosnia and Herzegovinia, in relation to the issue of conditionality, the role of the European Union in its domestic affairs and the level of debate that has taken place in that regard.  It is important, therefore, for the Union to be extremely careful and sensitive in terms of the role it plays in the affairs of all other countries, particularly those that are not yet members.  I am very much aware of how careful the European Union and Mr. S&oslash;rensen are in this regard.  </p><p> A point raised many times during my visit was the Sejdic-Finci ruling and the prominence it plays in relation to the European Union and its policy towards Bosnia and Herzegovinia.  I strongly support the role of the European Union in this regard.  I am sure we are all agreed that if the European Union is about anything, it is about everybody being equal and working hard to ensure that where inequality is identified, nation states or the Union deal with it.  A fundamental consequence of this is that everybody should have equal ability to participate in the public life of their country.  The Sejdic-Finci ruling cuts to the heart of this.  I believe it is entirely correct that the European Union place such value in progress being made in relation to that ruling and all of its consequences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500007#F00200"><p>The Minister of State did not respond to the question on voting rights but might do so following the next round of questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500007#F00300"><p>I will.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1030" speakername="Eric Byrne" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500007#F00400"><p>In regard to the Minister of State's reference to a Mediterranean and maritime flavour over the next six months, I hope he likes eating fish and drinking quality wine and that if he can get some time off from his busy schedule he will enjoy doing so.</p><p>  I understand the Minister of State wishes to concentrate today on issues such as security of energy and so on.  However, he has caused a drift in the discussion towards Bosnia.  I do not propose to say too much other than that I have a particular interest in Bosnia and the Irish-Bosnian community having experienced a close relationship with the student refugees involved in the Tuzla bombing and taken in by Ireland who went on to be fine students in our universities, some of whom have chosen to become citizens of Ireland.  Having worked with the OSCE in the region, I am very familiar with the people.  </p><p>  During the last COSAC meeting, Mr. Valentin Inzko agreed with me that a lot of time had been wasted and that much had been assumed in regard to the evolutionary process that would take place.  Given Croatia's move into Europe, he thought there would be a natural progression by the people of Bosnia and Herzegovinia in that direction.  However, that did not happen.  It would have been explained in great detail by the ex-pats that Europe was not assisting in the development of proper politics in the region and that it if it imposed more authority on the country things could progress.  Mr. Inzko admitted some mistakes had been made.  </p><p>  It was stated by one of the witnesses at yesterday's meeting that Bosnia and Herzegovinia represented a most reluctant country embracing nationhood.  I thank the Minister of State for his comprehensive engagement on the issue of Bosnia, including with students at the universities and with ex-pats here.  I wish him continued success in that regard.  The Minister of State might elaborate on the Irish role in the European institutions, which issue was also referred to at yesterday's meeting.  The Minister mentioned that in this regard we are in a transitionary stage.  I do not know why that would be the case.  I am not surprised to hear that 1,500 students attended the address in TCD and UCD.  Perhaps it was in the context of job prospects that they attended.  Is the Minister of State suggesting in the context of the forthcoming European elections in May that many of the people in the institutions will lose their jobs?  I thought they were ingrained in those institutions.  </p><p>  It is a fascinating experience for us to engage with Irish people engaged in Europe.  For example, the committee met yesterday with a team of OECD representatives who monitor the Irish aid programme, including our project in Malawi, which work is being compared with that of a similar Portuguese agency working in that area.  One of the key OECD members is an Irish woman.  There are many talented Irish people working in this area.  We should not be too surprised by this given the fantastic statistic released this week that 90% of our student cohort go on to complete the leaving certificate.  I congratulate the Minister of State on his engagement with the university sector although I am not sure of the reason for his encouraging third level students to take up jobs in the European Commission structures.  I would have thought it to be a natural progression for them.  Interestingly, during the review by the Joint Committee on Foreign Affairs and Trade of Irish foreign policy one of the first out of the hatches was an Irish academic based in Copenhagen University who made a phenomenal contribution to the debate about Ireland's new role in the world.  Bright intellectual Irish people keep popping up everywhere.</p><p>  I have a few specific questions for the Minister of State.  Notwithstanding what we heard yesterday, I would like to think that the Minister of State will continue to recognise the role Albania has to play.  I would like at this point to pay compliment to one of the contributors to yesterday's meeting, namely, Mr. Tony Connelly, RTE's Europe Editor, who plays an enormously important role in educating Irish people about what is happening in Europe.  He does a phenomenal job.  </p><p>  One of the Minister of State's key areas for debate is that of migration.  It was suggested at yesterday's meeting that in this regard we have it all wrong.  I refer members to the hysteria among the British to the free movement of labour from Bulgaria and Romania, in particular the British media in terms of its obscene presence at the airport to report on the influx of migrant workers into the country.  It was suggested at yesterday's meeting that Europe is an ageing region.  For example, we know that Germany has an ageing population and that the populations of Latvia, Lithuania and other countries are declining.  Perhaps the Minister of State will say whether in his view the manner in which Europe is dealing with the migration issue is wrong and needs urgent review. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500007#F00500"><p>I thank Deputy Byrne.  The next speaker is Deputy Dara Murphy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00100"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I compliment Mr. Tony Connelly, with whom I shared a platform last year at the Centre for European Studies.  There is talk about how the European institutions could be publicised better.  He has an encyclopaedic knowledge of the institutions, the personnel and the infrastructure.</p><p>  The European Parliament elections take place this year - the last ones were in 2009 and the previous ones in 2004.  Coincidentally, those are the three years that Cork city has been hit by catastrophic flooding.  The Minister of State mentioned an increased role for the Commission in this regard.  County Cork has a population of almost 500,000 and the greater Cork city area has a population of 250,000 to 300,000.  For the second morning in a row-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00200"><p>Is this relevant to the General Affairs Council?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00300"><p>Yes, it is absolutely relevant.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00400"><p>Can we get to see that relevance?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00500"><p>Considerable latitude was given to other speakers.  Dare I say-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00600"><p>We need to move on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00700"><p>-----we might not even be here this morning if Grafton Street had been flooded, given the chaos that would ensue in the capital city.  To be fair to RTE, its entire programme this morning was broadcast from Cork.  It is something that needs to be addressed urgently.  If the Minister of State comes to Cork, we can show him how we need to progress this.  Even though I took up two minutes of the committee's time to discuss a major flooding event in the second city of the Republic of Ireland-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00800"><p>We are all very concerned about the flooding, but this is the Oireachtas Joint Committee on European Affairs and we are here to discuss the General Affairs Council.  That is my point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G00900"><p>In his remarks, the Minister of State mentioned an increased role for the Commission in flooding matters.  How am I, therefore, out of order in raising the issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G01000"><p>The Deputy is not out of order.  However, I asked him to make his point and I would appreciate if he did that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G01100"><p>I have already done it, as I said.  We have given up more time in this discussion as to whether I am on or off.  Clearly, I am on and discussing matters relevant to the Minister of State.  I appreciate that the Minister of State has a role in this regard and it could well be raised at the General Affairs Council.</p><p>  Two weeks ago the Secretary General of the European Commission appeared before the committee.  It is very heartening that the issue of the Irish working in the Commission is being addressed urgently, as we discussed last week.  I was not aware that the Minister of State was so on top of the issue.</p><p>  I recently went to our university - I should say one of the universities in Ireland since mention of Cork seems to upset the Chairman.  The issue of languages was addressed.  One of the professors there mentioned the languages that students are taking concurrent with their degree courses.  I studied French in UCC and we read works by Albert Camus and the impressionists.  However, there is not a course in French targeted at, for example, people studying for engineering, medicine, science or technology degrees.  Rather than trying to come with a one-size-fits-all university language degree, they should be more tailored to the courses people are doing so that when they leave universities they have a language basis that complements the course they studied.</p><p>  The Minister of State mentioned the European semester is also on the agenda for the General Affairs Council.  Two weeks ago, the Chairman and I attended the European Parliamentary Week.  Ireland's budgetary cycle now appears to be out of synch.  We are moving to a budgetary process of country-specific recommendations, draft budgets and so on, with the final point being the budget.  Are there discussions about reaching a similar budgetary process in every country?  Do we need to get our committee structure in front of the budgetary process as is done in Sweden and many other European countries?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/957" speakername="Bernard Durkan" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G01200"><p>I apologise for my late arrival; I had questions being taken in the House and it is difficult to be in the two places at the same time.  I wish to pursue a few items the Minister of State mentioned.  I ask him to outline the possible implications of GMO maize on this country.  To what extent have the various stakeholders been consulted on the matter?  To what degree is the cereal industry likely to be affected?  To what extent have our European colleagues examined that impact?  To what extent will future developments in the area of world trading in cereals apply?</p><p>  The Minister of State rightly indicated that the European Commission has recently announced some modification to its energy policy with particular reference to reviewing alternative energy requirements.  It needs to be borne in mind that we are in a somewhat more difficult situation than some of our European colleagues in that we do not have oil and have a limited amount of gas.  The gas that we have is taking a long time to come on stream.  We certainly are dependent on either imports or alternative energy.  I ask the Minister of State to impress on his European colleagues the importance of recognising the provisions we need to make in order to keep within the emissions requirements and the degree to which we can economically provide alternative energy in this jurisdiction without reliance on our colleagues.</p><p>  The Minister of State referred to the economic and financial sphere, which will bear ongoing perusal and monitoring.  Over the past ten or 15 years, that particular stream could have borne considerably more attention than it got.  Obviously if certain indicators had been identified in reasonable time, the full extent of the economic situation, in which we now find ourselves, would not have been as great.</p><p>  I do not want to go over topics mentioned by other speakers.  Enlargement was discussed at yesterday's meeting and I do not want to go through the whole thing again.  It should be brought to the attention of all our colleagues in Europe that we are in a state of flux to a certain extent.  One major country is considering exiting the European Union, which could have a huge impact on the entire continent of Europe, the European Union and the eurozone, internally and externally.  That is an issue that needs to be kept to the fore and its consequences for the rest of the European Union examined on a daily basis because to quote John Donne, "No man is an island".  There is a tendency in the European Union, including in this island, to presume that we are all islands.  We cannot exist that way; we coexist and depend on each other.  The extent of that interdependence should be borne in mind and will emerge as having greater importance as time goes by.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1037" speakername="Se&aacute;n Crowe" time="10:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500008#G01300"><p>I welcome the Minister of State.  I apologise if the points I make were covered earlier.  The Minister of State referred to the four priorities of Greece's Presidency which are growth, jobs and cohesion; further integration of the EU and eurozone; migration, borders and mobility; and maritime policies.  I do not believe anyone would have any difficulty with any of those priorities.  We previously mentioned the disconnect people have with the European Union and the entire European project to a certain extent.  Among those countries, including Ireland, which have had difficulties in recent years there is a certain solidarity and a realisation that the EU as a body needs to roll up its sleeves and give more support to such countries.</p> <p>Given that the Greeks hold the Presidency, one would like to believe there will be a greater urgency with many of the issues that need to be addressed.</p><p> The Minister of State referred to jobs.  Anyone following this debate will be asking what it means for them in simple terms.  Will it mean more jobs and, if so, what type of jobs?  We are talking about growth, but what type of growth?  If it does not mean jobs or that the inequalities which exist are addressed or that the difficulties people have in their lives will improve, what does it mean?  I suppose it is rather like the case of those who were left behind during the Celtic tiger era.  They did not get the bounce.  People are wondering whether this will be the same.  We hear all the time about green shoots and Europe turning a corner and so on.  Last night, Ms Christine Lagarde made a speech about how positive things were and the great things the IMF did.  The reality in many areas is that people are not seeing growth or jobs or anything new on the horizon.  They do not see the task force on jobs and so on.  Many of us take the view that the only way we are really going to stimulate growth is through a package of measures that will include spending and creating jobs.</p><p> I imagine the Greeks have similar views about the write-down.  The Minister of State referred to institutional churn and transition.  He said that if there is to be major movement, it would be at the start of the year.  How does the Minister of State see that developing in respect of jobs?</p><p> Migration was mentioned.  Some of us were at a meeting on Friday attended by people from many countries, including Libya, Egypt and Tunisia as well as bordering countries.  They commented on the difficulties they have with people coming from conflict zones, who arrive in Europe in countries such as Greece and Bulgaria and other countries that have been mentioned.  There is a lack of solidarity between the south and the north in respect of the difficulties these people have.  Some of these people are having serious difficulties in trying to get growth and jobs, and vast numbers of people are fleeing conflict.  Will that be a priority?  What sense does the Minister of State have in this regard?  Does it make a difference that the Greeks have the Presidency?  People are disillusioned about the lack of solidarity in the economic sphere and certainly this applies to the area of migration as well.  Certain states are carrying the burden.  Others, like ourselves, are on the periphery of Europe.  There is an issue in terms of population and the number of people coming to Ireland.  Many people have a major difficulty with that.  The Minister of State will be aware from his constituency, as am I from mine, that people do not understand and it is characterised as a case of more people coming in and taking from the same pot.  Certain countries within Europe are carrying the burden of people fleeing conflict.  People are looking for a new economic future for their own children and so on.  What sense does the Minister of State have of the issues in respect of the Greek Presidency?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="11:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500009#H00200"><p>I will begin with an issue I accidentally omitted in my first round of answers relating to the question of voting rights.  The first point is that this is an area of national competence in terms of how it is organised and provided to the citizens of each country.  I am aware of the report mentioned.  I am also aware of the fact that the Constitutional Convention is doing work in this area and that it has made recommendations on how we could change or improve our situation.  That will be the subject of debate.</p><p>  Deputy Dara Murphy raised several issues.  I represent a constituency that was flooded in 2010 and I have first-hand experience of the devastation that people are going through as well as the extraordinary stress on people when this happens.  I know it is an extremely difficult time for the people in Deputy Murphy's constituency and for all the others who have endured the devastation inflicted upon them.  In my contribution earlier, I referred to the fact that I have heard a discussion taking place publicly regarding whether an application would go in from the Government in respect of supporting work that needs to be done.  Certainly, if I can give any help to that cause I will do so because I have first-hand experience of the stress people are feeling the moment and the havoc that has been wreaked upon their homes and lives.</p><p>  I acknowledge the Deputy's point on languages, although it is not one I have considered before.  I am aware of a similar issue in a different area, that is, the practice of law.  One of the areas of speciality for which there is a significant demand is that of lawyer linguists, people who have the ability to draft law, which by its nature is technical, in different languages.  I acknowledge the point that perhaps we should consider the same approach in respect of engineering and science.</p><p>  A point was made about the compatibility of national budgetary systems and processes with the European semester.  My understanding is that due to the changes made to bring our budget back to October, we are fitting in to the budgetary architecture which the European semester, the two pack and all the other measures require of us.  Perhaps at the tail end of the meeting I will get some more observations from the Deputy in respect of how we might be out of sync.  My understanding is that the changes we have made bring us into the framework where we need to be.</p><p>  A point was made regarding the role of committees.  I would actively encourage this committee and other committees to consider the work that will take place on the drafting of the national reform plan, which will be discussed during March, April and May.  What role can committees play?  I believe this committee can and should play a constructive role and I encourage the members to think about it.  My recollection is that this is something the committee was examining but I believe it is worthy of bringing to a conclusion in the coming weeks.</p><p>  Deputy Durkan made several points.  He touched on the question of genetically modified organisms and asked a specific question on the role of stakeholders.  I assure Deputy Durkan that the Environmental Protection Agency, our key stakeholder in this area, has been intimately involved in our evaluation of these crops and the associated issues.  The agency has played a direct role in informing the national position on the issue.  We are very much aware of the sensitivities on the matter at home and in other countries.  The committee will be aware that, with the exception of one test that is taking place at the moment, we are not growing genetically modified crops in the country.  However, many of the foodstuffs being used within our agricultural communities contain GM products.  The Environmental Protection Agency has been directly involved in stakeholder consultation.</p><p>  A point was raised about energy.  The simple answer to that question is "Yes".  All the points the Deputy asked to be raised will be actively considered and raised by us.  I offer one example of this work, that is, the increased recognition evident in the European Commission proposals on the role of agriculture in emissions and the associated impacts.</p> <p>We all worked hard on that issue to ensure that greater recognition would be given, and that has happened.  We will continue to pursue other matters to which the Deputy referred in that vein.  The Deputy also made a point about economic and financial spheres and policy areas.   We will continue to raise issues that are very important to our country, such as the agreement on banking union and the role the EU can play on job creation, to which Deputy Crowe alluded.</p><p> The UK position on enlargement is related to who could be forming the next government there and what might happen in the next parliament.  The Conservative Party and the Liberal Democrat Party have articulated views in that respect.  We are very aware of that.  It is a matter of significant interest for Ireland, due to the consequences it could have for us, and it is something that I have now addressed in a number of public contributions in other countries, as well as here at home.  I want our principles to be very clear on this issue, which I believe they are.  The Government's view is that our future is firmly within the European Union, and there is no ambiguity about that.  As long as the Irish people give their consent to that, either through general elections or through the ballot box in whatever way, that is the position of this Government and hopefully of future governments as well.</p><p> Deputy Crowe raised a number of different issues.  We need to be very clear that for all the discussion we hear about things like the digital economy and pharmaceuticals and so on, we need to have diversified sources of job growth.  Out of the six million jobs lost in Europe during the crisis, under 4 million of them have been within manufacturing.  If we want to get those 4 million people back to work, they have to be in jobs which they are skilled to do or can be retained to do.  A clear example of that is in respect of the role of the European Investment Bank in Ireland at the moment.  The amount of investment that bank has put into our country has quadrupled in recent years, and we can see the fruits of that with people working on the Grangegorman DIT campus and on the new Luas line across Dublin.</p><p> Deputy Crowe made about a point about institutional churn.  The change we are talking about is not happening as a result of what might happen in the European Parliament elections, or what might happen following the appointment of new Commissioners.  We are talking about the career cycle and the life cycle of people who are in those institutions at the moment and who are either retiring or going on to do different things.  It is not related to the political cycle that we were discussing earlier on.  That is why we are putting effort into that at the moment.  The Greek Presidency is focusing heavily on the type of growth that can occur, because unfortunately they have a very deep understanding of the difficulty that the economic crisis has caused.  Through our action plan on jobs, we will continue to do the same.  We need to have diversified sources of job creation to reflect the fact that not everybody will want to work in Google or be able to work in Google, or in any company like that.  We need to reflect that in the training that we have within our economy.</p><p> Migration and fleeing from conflicts are issues that have received increased prominence due to the terrible difficulties in other countries to which Deputy Crowe referred.  They were the subject of significant discussion at the last European Council meeting.  The European Council agreed a number of measures on the increased role of bodies like Frontex, which is a co-ordinating cross-national body that examines how different countries police their borders.  There is a task force in place on this, and it will produce some recommendations to look at the issues to which the Deputy referred.  The European Council and the Justice and Home Affairs Council of Ministers will then have a discussion on how we can deal with this.  There are many countries that are currently bearing a very heavy burden due to their location and they want to initiate a discussion on how this can be dealt with in the future.  We will participate in such a discussion.  We are all aware of some of the sensitivities on this issue, but Ireland has shown itself to be capable of responding to humanitarian crises across Europe and elsewhere.  Deputy Byrne spoke about the role we played in the conflict in Bosnia Herzegovina and the break up of the former Yugoslavia.  We will certainly participate constructively in any discussions on that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/985" speakername="Dara Murphy" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500010#J00200"><p>I missed the start of the Minister of State's speech, but I noticed that the General Affairs Council meeting will discuss the climate and energy proposals from the Commission for 2030, so climate is on the agenda.  Any climate policy will have to take into account how the peripheral nations and islands are being affected by climate change.  It is on the agenda so I ask the Minister of State to bring it up at the meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1076" speakername="Dominic Hannigan" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500010#J00300"><p>I thank the Minister of State for attending today, for his comprehensive presentation and for answering our questions so thoroughly.  We wish him all the best at his meeting next week in Brussels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.45" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1007" speakername="Paschal Donohoe" time="11:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EUJ2014020500010#J00400"><p>I thank the Chairman.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.46" nospeaker="true" time="11:10:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 11.30 a.m. and adjourned at 11.35 a.m. until 2 p.m. on Thursday, 13 February 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.47" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.48" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 12:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Niall Collins, Senator Ivana Bacik, Deputy Marcella Corcoran Kennedy, Senator Martin Conway, Deputy Anne Ferris, Senator Tony Mulcahy, Deputy Seán Kenny, Senator Katherine Zappone. Deputy Pádraig Mac Lochlainn, Deputy Finian McGrath, Deputy Ann Phelan,</p><p>DEPUTY DAVID STANTON IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.50" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 12.20 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.51" nospeaker="true" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500003#C00100">Small Claims and Payment Procedures: Motion</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500003#C00200"><p>No apologies have been received except Deputy Farrell said that he might be late arriving.</p><p>  The purpose of the meeting is to consider a proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Regulation (EC) No. 861/2007 of the European Parliament and the Council, of 11 July 2007, establishing a European Small Claims Procedure and Regulation (EC) No. 1896/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council, of 12 December 2006, creating a European order for payment procedure.  A briefing note has been circulated to members.  </p><p>  I welcome the Minister for Justice and Equality, Deputy Alan Shatter, and his officials to the meeting who will assist the committee in its consideration of the matter.  I ask everybody to please turn off all mobile phones.  I ask for them to be switched completely off as it is unsatisfactory to have them on silent.  </p><p>  I invite the Minister to brief the committee on the motion and it will be followed by a question and answer session.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="12:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500003#C00300"><p>I thank the Chairman.  At the outset I thank the committee members for their willingness to deal with this matter today, at short notice.  It is important that Ireland is seen to be in a position to play a full part in the negotiations which have begun in regard to this instrument, and a positive response to the motion which has been tabled will facilitate our achieving that objective.</p><p>  The proposal for a new Regulation amending Regulation (EC) No. 861/2007 of the European Parliament and the Council of 11 July 2007 establishing a European Small Claims Procedure and Regulation (EC) No. 1896/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 12 December 2006 creating a European order for payment procedure was presented by the Commission at the end of November.  It effectively amends two proposals into which we have already opted.  The amending proposal&rsquo;s legal basis is to be found in Title V of Part Three of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union.  As a result, the protocol which we share with the United Kingdom, whereby we have three months to exercise our option to take part in the adoption and application of relevant measures, applies.  The exercise of that option is, of course, subject to the prior approval of both Houses of the Oireachtas.  We have been informed that the three month period in respect of the proposal will expire on 25 February next. </p><p>  The proposal which is being examined today is the most recent in a long line of proposals to which the protocol applies and which have come before the Houses of the Oireachtas in recent years.  It is not especially controversial and I hope that the committee will give it its support.    </p><p>  The proposal under discussion should be seen against the background of the development at EU level of measures geared towards the enhancement of judicial co-operation in civil matters.  The overriding aim of this development is that of making access to justice easier for the individual litigant.  It is predicated on the fact that in a genuine European area of justice, individuals or businesses should not be prevented or discouraged from exercising their rights by the incompatibility or complexity of legal and administrative systems in the member states.  The regulation establishing a European small claims procedure was adopted in 2007 in order to enhance access to justice by simplifying and speeding up cross-border litigation concerning small claims, and also reducing the costs of such litigation.  </p><p>  Article 28 of the 2007 regulation requires the Commission to present a report by 1 January 2014 reviewing its operation.  The proposal now before the committee follows on from that review.  It is also noteworthy that, in the 2013 EU Citizenship Report, the Commission identified the revision of the 2007 regulation as an action necessary to strengthen the rights of European citizens and the initiative is also included in the European Consumer Agenda as a means of improving enforcement of consumer rights.  Moreover, the revision of the regulation supports the EU's current political priority of promoting economic recovery and sustainable growth by creating more efficient, simplified court procedures and by making them more accessible to SMEs. </p><p>  Committee members will be aware of the small claims procedure which has been operating in the District Court since 1997.  That procedure is an alternative method of commencing and dealing with a civil proceeding in respect of a small claim.  The procedure originally applied only to consumer claims but, since January 2010, it has also covered a limited range of business to business claims.  It is designed to handle claims speedily, inexpensively and informally without involving a solicitor.  It is administered by a small claims registrar, who is an official of the court, whose function it is to process the claim and, if possible, reach a satisfactory settlement without the need for a court hearing.  Should this prove unsuccessful the claim will then go before a District Court judge.</p><p>  Use of this procedure as a means of settling low value consumer and business claims not exceeding &euro;2,000 is consistently high.  In 2012, the last year for which statistics are available, over 3,000 applications were lodged.  Most of those claims concerned household and electrical goods, with others relating to building services, motor vehicles and holidays.   </p><p>  Regrettably, the success of our domestic procedure is not matched by an equal success in regard to the EU procedure and use of the EU Small Claims Regulation has been low in Ireland.  I have been advised by the Courts Service that 44 such cases came before the Dublin District Court last year, and that a small number of additional cases were taken in other areas.  Unfortunately, the Courts Service does not compile its statistics in such a way as to extract a breakdown of the type of cases taken under the EU procedure.  This low level of usage accords with the Commission contention that the procedure is still little known and remains under-used several years after the entry into application of the regulation.  The low usage of the regulation was a major factor in the determination of the amendments which the Commission has proposed should be made to the regulation.  </p><p>  First among those is a proposal to increase the monetary scope of the regulation from claims not exceeding &euro;2,000 to claims not exceeding &euro;10,000.  This proposed increase is represented as being of particular assistance to SMEs, as raising the current threshold will allow parties to litigate a substantially bigger number of cases on the basis of the simplified European procedure, thereby benefitting from reduced costs and shorter length of proceedings.  It is envisaged that consumers will also benefit from the proposed increase in the financial scope.</p> <p>The European Commission estimates that the reduction in costs related to raising the threshold from the current &euro;2,000 to &euro;10,000 amounts to approximately &euro;233 million across the EU.  This estimate is based on the assumption that 50% of court cases concerning claims between &euro;2,000 and &euro;10,000 in member states where there is a simplified procedure would be filed under the European small claims procedure.</p><p> My Department has undertaken a process of consultation in respect of the proposal, which is now in its final stages.  In the broadest of terms, the outcome of that process to date indicates that there is support from bodies representing businesses for an increase in the threshold to &euro;10,000.  However, concern has been expressed by the Courts Service and legal professionals about the desirability of an increase to such a level<i>.</i> The reasons behind this concern include the appropriateness of dealing with legally and factually complex claims at the higher end of the scale in a simplified procedure.  </p><p> I am inclined to the view that an increase in the threshold is both desirable and necessary.  However, the negotiation process has only just begun - in fact, the first meeting of the relevant working group took place yesterday.  In its deliberations that group will attempt to reach a view as to the level of threshold which is both appropriate and likely to be acceptable to the majority of member states.  Early indications are that a number of member states seem to be of the view that the proposed increase is pitched at too high a level and does not have regard to what is considered to be a small claim in those member states in the context of their social and economic circumstances.  On the other hand, some member states are very positively disposed to the proposed threshold, which is actually lower than the value of a small claim under their national systems.  The question of the threshold was discussed at the recent Justice and Home Affairs informal meeting and the views expressed on that occasion were in accordance with those which I have just outlined.  </p><p> The 2007 small claims regulation applies only to disputes where at least one of the parties is domiciled or habitually resident in a member state other than the member state of the court or tribunal which is seized with the case.  It is now proposed to enlarge the scope of the regulation to cover cases which have an important cross-border element, notwithstanding the fact that both parties to the case are domiciled in the same member state.  For instance, the case of parties who are domiciled in the same member state, but who are involved in a car accident in another member state, would be comprehended by the new regulation &ndash; the cross-border element being the place where the harmful event occurred.</p><p> Another element of this proposal concerns the use of electronic communication, including the service of certain documents by electronic means.  The 2007 regulation prescribes postal service with acknowledgement of receipt as the primary method of service.  It is now proposed to put postal service and electronic service on the same footing in member states which desire to do so, and where a party has expressly indicated in advance that documents may be served electronically.  This safeguard is appropriate because there will always be a minority of cases where people do not have access to means of electronic communication or do not use such means frequently.  Furthermore, it has been suggested that many types of communications between the parties and the courts could, in principle, be carried out by electronic means, which would save time and reduce costs in cross-border scenarios and that electronic communication would be the norm where communications of a routine nature are concerned.  </p><p> The committee may be interested to note that the Courts Service has recently completed the development of a new online small claims system.  Should the proposal for electronic filing of EU small claims be agreed, the Courts Service has indicated that it is likely that the domestic system could be adapted to accommodate an extended European small claims procedure.  </p><p> Also included is a proposal concerning the use of video-conferencing, tele-conferencing and other means of distance communication for the conduct of oral hearings and the taking of evidence.  A very good case can be made for the use of those means of communication in the European justice sphere and I support their use in this context.</p><p> However, it is important that participation in the electronic elements of the proposal is voluntary and has regard to the relative technological advancement of each member state.  Indeed, voluntary action is one of the key principles of the Strategy on European e-Justice 2014-2018, which was adopted at the December 2013 Justice and Home Affairs Council.   </p><p> The proposal also envisages that a limitation would be placed on court fees charged for the procedure to ensure that they are proportionate to the value of the claim and that member states should facilitate electronic means of payment of such fees.  Furthermore, member states will be obliged to inform the Commission of the court fees concerned and of the means of payment which are accepted.  These are significant elements of the procedure which facilitate transparency and access to justice.  Indeed, enabling the creditor to make an informed decision as to whether the cost of taking the claim is proportionate to the value of that claim was an issue of major concern to Ireland during the negotiations of the 2007 regulation and our concern is reflected in the preamble to that regulation.  </p><p> The Commission has drawn attention to the high charges levied in some member states in respect of a European small claim.  For instance, in one member state, the court fee for litigating a claim of &euro;500 is &euro;115 while in another member state a fee of &euro;180 applies to a claim worth &euro;1,000.  I can tell the committee that the fee payable in Ireland in respect of a European small claim is &euro;25, the same fee as is payable for a claim taken under the domestic small claims procedure.  This amount is well within the parameters considered desirable by the Commission, which are either a maximum set fee of &euro;35, or a fee of not more than 10% of the value of the claim.  </p><p> While I share the Commission's concerns about high fees being charged in respect of low value claims, I have some doubts about the appropriateness of EU intervention in this area as there is an argument to be made that the settling of court fees falls squarely within the autonomy of member states and should not be interfered with.  Having said that, this State has an interest in ensuring fees are kept at a reasonable level or, at a minimum, they are proportionate to the claim being made.  It is to the benefit of our citizens and residents in this State should they need to access this new proposed small claims procedure, or even the existing one, that fees are not excessive and do not act as a barrier to using the small claims apparatus.  The recently developed online small claims system to which I referred earlier includes a facility for the payment online of fees associated with domestic small claims.  Again, this facility could also be used in respect of the European small claims procedure.  </p><p> I now turn to the proposed amendment of Regulation (EC) No 1896/2006 creating a European order for payment procedure.  By way of background, the European Order for Payment Regulation establishes a European-wide procedure for getting a court decision in respect of an uncontested claim.  Its key features are that an order is obtained in the first instance without the debtor taking part in the action.  It is then served on the debtor who has the option of abiding by it or contesting it within a short period of time.  Failure to act leads to the order acquiring the status of enforceability.  Article 17 of the regulation provides that where the defendant opposes the claim, the proceedings are automatically continued in accordance with ordinary civil procedures, which do not include the European small claims procedure.  It is now proposed that in those circumstances, it should also be possible to continue an appropriate claim under the European small claims regulation.  I support this extension of the choices available, which is to the benefit of the ordinary litigant and again will keep costs down.   </p><p> In both the European and domestic sphere, I am of the view that it is crucial that parties involved in legal conflict do not incur more legal costs than are necessary in circumstances in which they have to resort to litigation.  On the domestic front, members will be aware that I have increased the monetary jurisdiction of both the Circuit and the District Courts with effect from Monday of this week.  Those changes should be of benefit to litigants in bringing about reduced legal costs for individuals and companies involved in litigation and have particular significance for litigants of low value claims which do not come within the scope of either the domestic or EU small claims procedures. </p><p> I have said in the past to this committee in regard to other proposals, and I emphasise it again today, that opting into the proposal at this time does not mean that we necessarily agree with every aspect of it.  The opt-in process merely ensures that we can be active participants in the negotiation process and this carries with it the undisputed right to make proposals to alter the text should that seem desirable and to participate in any votes that may arise at working group and other levels.</p><p> Ireland has in the past taken a very positive approach to participation in the various civil law instruments which have been presented and our approach on this occasion is very much in keeping with past practice.  It is important that we honour the commitment given in the context of successive treaties that we will take part in relevant measures in the justice area to the maximum extent possible.  Also, given that we have no fundamental difficulties with the proposal, we do not want to create a perception that such difficulties do in fact exist in so far as Ireland is concerned.</p><p> From previous consideration of these issues, the committee will be aware that it is the case that, under the protocol, we may accept a proposal any time after it has been adopted.  However, it has always been our considered view that in the absence of any significant policy issues, early opt-in to the discussions on particular proposals will maximise our ability to influence the shape of the final outcome.   </p><p> I thank the committee for making the time available to deal with these matters.</p> <p>These two instruments are of particular importance and relevance to individuals across the country, particularly in the context of the extent to which those resident in the State and citizens engage in commercial transactions on a cross-border basis and the manner in which the Internet works and the capacity to purchase goods in Ireland that may be on sale in other parts of the EU through website offers.  It is particularly important that there is ready access to the Small Claims Court should difficulties arise regarding the commercial transaction or the contract.  One may not realise there is a contract but one participates in a contract to acquire goods or services.</p><p> I welcome this initiative by the Commission.  It is in our interest as a State to fully participate in the discussions that are taking place.  I look forward to the comments of committee members and I am happy to respond to questions.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500005#E00200"><p>As a Deputy representing a Border constituency, I am well aware from my conversations with business people of their concerns about pursuing cases across the Border.  With regard to building an all-Ireland economy that is fair and provides people with appropriate recourse, I have no difficulty with the regulation and with supporting the Government's proposal to opt in and engage in negotiations.  It is in everyone's best interest across the EU.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1148" speakername="Ivana Bacik" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500005#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister for setting this out clearly.  All of us recognise the desirability of the changes.  Like many of us, I am concerned about the small number who have taken up the EU small claims procedure in Ireland.  Only 44 such cases came before Dublin District Court last year and we do not know what types of cases are involved.  Presumably, the low usage of the regulation is not unique to Ireland.  The Commission has proposed these amendments to make it more broadly used across member states. I welcome most of the changes, particularly the change to cover cases where both parties are domiciled in the same member state but there is a cross-border element.  One can imagine that, for example, in the context of holidays, which are the focus of many domestic small claims disputes, where two Irish people go on holiday in another member state and an issue arises with the provider of accommodation or services there, that this would be an attractive route for them to pursue a claim.  Is there low usage of the regulation generally in the EU or is that unique to Ireland?</p><p>  I refer to the increase in the threshold for a claim to &euro;10,000.  I agree with the Minister that this is desirable and necessary, given the low take-up and given the cost, for example, of holidays.  A threshold of &euro;2,000 is low.  If we support the proposal, does that mean we support the threshold of &euro;10,000 or are we supporting the negotiations to increase it and it may not ultimately be as much as &euro;10,000 because of differing views among member states?  It could, for example, be &euro;5,000 or &euro;6,000.  The Minister also said the Courts Service has expressed concern about the desirability of an increase.  Has the service sufficient capacity to deal with these claims?  According to the briefing from the Library and Research Service, the impact of the moratorium and difficulties with staffing may impact on capacity but that should not be a factor if we believe it is desirable to increase the threshold.  Can we be sure the service will cope with the volume of claims if the number increases because of the change to the threshold?</p><p>  The Commission's estimate of the reduction in costs is based on an assumption that 50% of court cases would be filed under the European small claims procedure.  On what basis is it making that assessment?  Is that based on the take-up of the procedure to date using the lower threshold or has a more scientific method been used?  It would be wonderful if that cost saving could be made and it would be welcomed by both small businesses and consumers.  If the threshold was reduced from &euro;10,000, there would be presumably be fewer claims and a lower saving.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="12:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500005#E00400"><p>The low take-up across the EU is principally because the availability of this facility is not known in many member states.  There is also an issue where oral hearings are required.  Individuals may not want to travel and incur the expense of such hearings for small claims.  The cost of travel and accommodation may offset any benefit to be accrued by engaging in this procedure, which is why the use of electronic means in the context of videoconferencing and so on will increase usage.  The translation cost of documentation required to make a claim in another member state is also an issue that arises and I have referenced the variance in fees in member states.</p><p>  With regard to where the Commission gets its projections from, it has made an impact assessment based on certain assumptions, including that fees will not pose a barrier to bringing applications and there will be greater knowledge of the availability of this service among individuals who get caught up in minor legal conflicts in a financial sense, which are important to them.</p><p>  I have an open mind on the &euro;10,000 threshold but it is unlikely it will settle at that figure because it is high.  The recent changes effected to our District Courts increased their jurisdiction from IR&pound;5,000 or &euro;6,350 to &euro;15,000.  A threshold of &euro;10,000 is on the high side but I have an open mind on where it should settle and I am open to being persuaded.  It should be not less than &euro;5,000 but this will be discussed by the working groups and an accommodation will be reached.  I will not be upset if is &euro;6,000 and it would be workable at &euro;5,000 but it is inevitable it will be lower than &euro;10,000.</p><p>  With regard to numbers, resources and capacity, the reality is the Courts Service, like all other parts of the justice family, has had to reorganise and use its resources with greater efficiency and ensure it effects financial savings.  The service has not been entirely immune to the budgetary reductions, though it has been substantially protected from them.  The decrease in funding to the service compared to other sections within the justice family has been small.  Even without this measure, I am currently considering an increase in our Small Claims Court jurisdictional level.  It has been &euro;2,000 for some years.  It was at that level when the District Court was at the level I mentioned earlier and now that has been increased to &euro;15,000.  However, I do not want to create confusion by amending our jurisdiction and then discovering in nine months that I have to change it again because of the outcome of discussions at European level.  We are examining that.  If the discussion on this instrument was not taking place, I would be tempted in the next few weeks to increase the Small Claims Courts jurisdiction to between &euro;3,000 and &euro;5,000 because the cost of goods and services is increasing.  Where one might have spent &euro;1,500 or &euro;1,800 on something six or seven years ago, today one might spend &euro;2,200 or &euro;2,300.  Our small claims jurisdiction is too low but it would create terrible confusion if I increased it now only to find I had to do so again in a year.</p> <p>I am very conscious, however, that it takes considerable time for even the most worthy European instruments to be processed to a conclusion.  The likelihood of this being completed, between the engagement of the European Parliament, the working group and the Ministers, before the elections to the European Parliament is limited.  There must be some uncertainty as to whether it will conclude before there is a new Commission.  I want to discuss this with my officials.  If there is no possibility that this could become operational for 18 months to two years, there is a benefit in our increasing the jurisdiction, at least to a modest extent, of our Small Claims Court.  I expect the Courts Service will make appropriate adjustments to accommodate that, for the blindingly obvious reason that if the matter is not dealt with in the Small Claims Court, it will go to the District Court proper and the service will have to accommodate it.</p><p> This is an attempt to make justice more accessible to, and less expensive for, citizens and residents in this country and for business.  The Small Claims Court has been a very useful location in which to deal with issues in a more efficient and less expensive way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500006#F00200"><p>I welcomed the establishment of the Small Claims Court some years ago as a step in the right direction for the consumer.  I now welcome its extension to the EU.  The fee payable in Ireland is &euro;25.  If the value of cases increases to &euro;10,000, there will presumably be extra work involved.  Will the costs rise?</p><p>  Many people do not know about their right to access the Small Claims Court.  Is there a role for the National Consumer Agency to run a public awareness campaign?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500006#F00300"><p>I will take the last question first.  Yes, once these facilities are available to help people resolve small claims disputes, it is important to have the maximum public knowledge of them.  Some of the consumer bodies publicise this from time to time.  It is not an issue that generates major media excitement.  The problem in publicising anything nowadays is that unless something arises that becomes a media focus, be it in print media, television or radio, people tend not to know about it.  Unless people look for the website they will not find the information.  I am happy to encourage any of the agencies that seek to assist consumers to publicise the availability of this matter.  It is on the court&rsquo;s website, and in the EU practitioner's guide, and it will be in the EU user&rsquo;s guide, which will be available shortly, all online.  The problem is if I have paid for a holiday that does not work out, I would not necessarily search for these sites.</p><p>  I mentioned that the European Commission envisaged a fee of something like &euro;35.  There are technical legal reasons it may be outside the Commission&rsquo;s competence to specify the fee.  It is important for consumers and business that the fees are not set at an unnecessary level.  I am also conscious that in our present circumstances, the funding available to me for court services is not likely to increase any time soon beyond the additional funding we will have for the establishment of the Court of Appeal.  It will be important to bring in revenue to try to make some of the services more self-financing than they are.  I would not see major changes in our fee levels, but if we increase them to between &euro;3,000 and &euro;5,000, I would be very tempted and do not think it would create any great barrier or be unreasonable to increase our fee from &euro;25 to &euro;35.</p><p>  When agreement is reached at EU level, there may be a case to be made that we should fix a fee that is proportionate to the claim made, provided it is a modest fee.  For example, if someone made a claim of &euro;6,000, I would not see it as a major barrier if the fee were 10% or some proportion of it.  That would not be unreasonable.  We need to think about this and ensure we do not create barriers.  I am probably getting my percentages wrong because for a claim of &euro;6,000, I would envisage a fee of &euro;60 rather than &euro;600.  There is a reasonable case if we increase our jurisdiction to increase our fees modestly and reconsider that later, on the assumption that the EU does not ultimately agree a global fee across member states, although it may be outside the competence for that to be fixed.</p><p>  We all have an interest in the fees not being unduly high in some member states.  Even if it cannot be dealt with by way of a legal instrument, it would be in the interests of businesses and consumers across the Union if there was informal agreement between member states that they would fix their fees but not beyond a certain amount.  I would not be unhappy if it was discovered that although there may be technical issues, they do not prevent some sort of arrangements being agreed that ensure fees do not become excessive. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500006#F00400"><p>I thank the Minister.  It is a pity the Courts Service cannot compile the statistics to give us a breakdown of the type of cases taken.  It would be very useful if there was some way to arrange that.  I know it produces a report on the Small Claims Court but the European one would be interesting, especially if, as we hope, there is an increase in its use.  That it is little known raises the concern about the need to publicise it.</p><p>  The Minister said the legal professions have concerns about the desirability of increasing the level to &euro;10,000.  Does he want to expand on who they are and what their concerns are?  The use of electronic communication, which cuts down on paperwork and cost, is welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.63" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="12:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500006#F00500"><p>In respect of the legal profession, the design of the Small Claims Court is such that people are not represented.  There is an informal procedure to facilitate a resolution or adjudication on matters.  One argument is that if one is dealing with claims at that level, to protect people&rsquo;s rights they should have legal representation, or the facility for that, but the moment legal representation comes into a Small Claims Court, the costs for everyone involved increase substantially.  There is a balance to be achieved.  I understand those concerns, particularly if issues of great legal complexity arise.  There could be a mechanism whereby were that to happen the case could transfer from the Small Claims Court to the District Court where it would be dealt with as an ordinary District Court case.  We cannot, however, provide a European prescription designed solely to meet our court structure.</p><p>  It would be helpful if the courts maintained statistics on the different types of disputes on which they adjudicate.  I will write to the Courts Service suggesting that would be of help.  It would also help because annual publication of that information would give the public some insight into the nature of the cases, if it was reported.</p><p>  I have some statistics for the Small Claims Court.  I do not have the 2013 figures but in 2012 it received 3,067 applications in this State.  That was fewer, for reasons I am not aware of, than in 2011, when it received 3,836.  In 2012, the court adjudicated on 345 cases, and in 2011, on 286.  The cases adjudicated on in a year were not necessarily initiated in that year.</p> <p>Some cases initiated in 2011 would have been determined in 2012 and so on.  There were 73 cases dismissed in 2012 and 86 in 2011.  In 2012, 304 cases were either struck out or withdrawn, and it was 310 cases in 2011.  In instances where cases are withdrawn or struck out, it may be as a consequence of the individuals who made the claim deciding not to pursue it or that the claim is resolved and settled and the issues in dispute have been dealt with.  These are some of the statistics from the extracts of the 2012 Courts Service annual report.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500007#G00200"><p>We have exhausted the questions.  I thank the Minister and his officials most sincerely for their attendance.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.66" nospeaker="true" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500007#G00300">Messages to Dáil and Seanad</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="12:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUJ2014020500007#G00400"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:<blockquote><br />The Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality has completed its consideration of the following proposal:That D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:<blockquote>a proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Regulation (EC) No. 861/2007 of the European Parliament and the Council of 11th July, 2007 establishing a European Small Claims Procedure and Regulation (EC) No. 1896/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 12th December, 2006 creating a European order for payment procedure,</blockquote>a copy of which was laid before D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann on 27th November, 2013.</blockquote>  In accordance with Standing Order 72 the following message will be sent to the Seanad:<blockquote>The Joint Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality has completed its consideration of the following proposal:That Seanad &Eacute;ireann approves the exercise by the State of the option or discretion under Protocol No. 21 on the position of the United Kingdom and Ireland in respect of the area of freedom, security and justice annexed to the Treaty on European Union and to the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union, to take part in the adoption and application of the following proposed measure:<blockquote>a proposal for a Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council amending Regulation (EC) No. 861/2007 of the European Parliament and the Council of 11th July, 2007 establishing a European Small Claims Procedure and Regulation (EC) No. 1896/2006 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 12th December, 2006 creating a European order for payment procedure,</blockquote>a copy of which was laid before Seanad &Eacute;ireann on 27th November, 2013.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.68" nospeaker="true" time="12:40:00" ><p>The joint committee went into private session at 1.05 p.m. and adjourned at 1.25 p.m. sine die.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.69" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.70" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 16:00</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Richard Boyd Barrett, Senator Trevor Ó Clochartaigh, Deputy Alan Farrell, Senator Susan O'Keeffe. Deputy Charles Flanagan, Deputy Noel Harrington, Deputy Michael Healy-Rae, Deputy Seamus Kirk, Deputy Michael P. Kitt, Deputy Helen McEntee, Deputy Michelle Mulherin, Deputy Aengus Ó Snodaigh,</p><p>DEPUTY PÁDRAIG MAC LOCHLAINN IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.72" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 5.25 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.73" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014020500003#J00100">Decisions on Public Petitions Received</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014020500003#J00200"><p>We are in public session.  We have had the opportunity to discuss and deliberate on a number of the petitions.  We will now relay the decisions our committee has made in regard to them.  The first petition is No. 00023/13 from Mr. Frank Mulcahy, former head of ISME, regarding the alleged reneging by the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation on an agreement made with Deputy Ruair&iacute; Quinn in 2004.  The Department agreed, following an internal investigation, that if its files showed that the allegation re EU grants levelled at Frank Mulcahy never had merit, it would publish that evidence.  This has not been done.  What we have agreed today is to defer that particular petition for more consideration at a later date.</p><p>  The next petition is No. 00028/13 from Mr. Ron Horgan claiming that his medical records were accessed without his permission or a court order.  The petition appears to fall foul of Standing Order 165C(1)(<i>d</i>) and (<i>e</i>) in so far as it names individuals, contains language which is in the nature of being defamatory and is, therefore, inadmissible.  The subject of the petition also appears to relate to an individual case that may already have been adjudicated on by the courts and, therefore, is also outside the remit of the committee.  It is proposed to deem the petition to be inadmissible.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  It is also proposed to return all correspondence to the petitioner to avoid any scenario in the future where the petitioner may seek to claim privilege over said documents.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  Petition No. 00030/13 from Mr. Desmond Lafferty is entitled &quot;Requiring consistency in public office&quot;.  The petitioner states that he is asking that Government Departments be required to develop an explicit set of rules for dealing with complaints to avoid vacillation and inconsistency, and that the handling of his case by the Department of Foreign Affairs and Trade be reviewed.  He is also asking the committee to examine and evaluate his dealings with the Office of the Ombudsman and to recommend that appeals, including his against the Ombudsman's findings, be handled by a body separate from the Office of the Ombudsman.  This is the second time the petitioner has submitted a petition.</p><p>  Elements of this petition have already been considered and addressed in a previous petition submitted by the petitioner.  It is proposed, therefore, that the petitions be deemed as inadmissible pursuant to Standing Order 165C(1)(<i>f</i>), which states that a petition is inadmissible if it &quot;is the same as, or in substantially similar terms to, a petition brought by or on behalf of the same person, body corporate or unincorporated association during the lifetime of that D&aacute;il and which was closed by agreement of the Committee&quot;.  The petition was refused initially because we do not second-guess the decisions of the Ombudsman.</p> <p>We are not permitted to do so because it is not within our Standing Orders.  The committee notes that there is already an established appeals procedure within the Office of the Ombudsman.  It is therefore proposed to inform the petitioner that the committee has found no grounds at this time to question the procedures followed by the Ombudsman's office.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p> Petition No. 00075/12 is from Ms Melissa Halpin.  The petitioner had sought the revocation of a foreshore licence granted to Providence Resources to drill in Dublin Bay and a public inquiry into the granting of the licence by the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government on the basis that the public consultation process was inadequate.  During the course of its deliberations, the committee noted that Providence Resources plc had voluntarily surrendered the foreshore licence.  Therefore, the issue was deemed to be resolved.</p><p> However, the committee agreed to ask the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government to inform it of any proposed changes to the relevant regulations.  The committee has been monitoring progress in this regard.  It was noted that during the pre-legislative scrutiny of the general scheme of the maritime area and foreshore (amendment) Bill 2013, the Department emphasised that one of the main aims of the Bill is to transfer development-consenting responsibility for projects from the Minister for the Environment, Community and Local Government to An Bord Plean&aacute;la and local authorities.  Once that transfer has been effected, the public participation provisions of the Planning and Development Acts will be utilised under the new consenting regime.  Do members wish to comment on this petition?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014020500004#K00200"><p>I accept that the committee has little choice but to respond to the petitioner indicating that the petition is closed.  In the intervening time since Ms Halpin, on behalf of the Save our Seafront campaign, submitted her petition, the group's aim has been achieved in that Providence Resources has been forced to withdraw its application.  The Government has indicated that the maritime area and foreshore (amendment) Bill will address the concerns expressed by the petitioner regarding public consultation and planning issues.</p><p>  I acknowledge that the committee cannot take the issue any further, but it is right that we would indicate to the petitioner, as we have agreed, that if the Bill does not deal satisfactorily with the issues of public consultation, recourse to justice on planning decisions on the foreshore and so on, she should feel free to come back to us.  The group the petitioner represents and other groups have argued, and I agree with them, that the proposed heads of the Bill do not deal adequately with the issues of public consultation and a proper regime for dealing with planning and development on the foreshore.  I would like to think that will change.  In the meantime, I accept that the appropriate forum for that debate is the environment committee.  It is right and proper that the petitioner should have the right to come back to us when that is done and dusted if, in her view, the legislation is not satisfactory.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014020500004#K00300"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  The next petition is No. 00007/13, from Mr. Paddy Lambe, regarding concerns over inappropriate standards related to dive industry legislation.  The petitioner has issues with the proposed new dive industry regulations which, in his view, will impose additional requirements concerning certificates of medical fitness to dive.  The concern is that recreational instructors will be required to carry out the same medical examinations as those involved in heavy industry diving.  The petitioner is proposing that dive instructors be allowed to perform the standard diving medical for recreational purposes, as per international standards and best practice.  The proposed regulations, he argues, could put people out of work and impose excessive costs.  The petitioner is also concerned about the Pre-Hospital Emergency Care Council being designated as the only registration body for first aid training and the Further Education and Training Awards Council being given the same designation for other instructor courses such as manual handling.</p><p>  The proposed new regulation was the subject of public consultation, a process in which the petitioner did not participate.  The Department's reply to the petition is very clear and comprehensive.  Members will agree that the changes, although necessitating a stricter regime, are being introduced for all the right reasons in that this is ultimately a health and safety issue.  It is proposed, therefore, that the Department's correspondence be forwarded to the petitioner for information and the petition be closed.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  The next petition is No. 00010/13, from Mr. Pat Smyth, on the failure of the State to provide a framework for rectification of errors made by the banking system, especially in regard to indiscriminate over-lending, otherwise known as reckless lending.  Mr. Smyth is seeking legislation to deal with this issue.  Are there any comments on this petition?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014020500004#K00400"><p>I commend Mr. Smyth on bringing this proposal to the committee.  Most people agree there was reckless lending by financial institutions, that these practices landed individuals and the country as a whole in a great deal of trouble and that legislation should be introduced to criminalise the type of behaviour that did so much damage.  I accept, however, that the request for such legislation should, in the first instance, be presented to the Minister for Finance.  Let us see what he comes back with, after which we can decide how to proceed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2014020500004#K00500"><p>Is it agreed that the committee will issue correspondence to the Minister for Finance seeking a response on this matter?  Agreed.</p><p>  The next petition is No. 00018/13, from Ms Margaret Gilbert of the Killygordon and Crossroads Youth Club in County Donegal, calling for the introduction of legislation to make cyberbullying a criminal offence.  The petition also seeks the banning of anonymous posting on websites.  The committee has examined this proposal on several occasions and is sympathetic to its objective in the context of the tragedies that took place in recent years, particularly in Donegal and Leitrim in particular.  It is proposed that a copy of the correspondence from the Internet Service Providers Association of Ireland and the Office for Internet Safety be forwarded to the petitioner for information.</p><p>  It is further proposed that the petitioner's attention be drawn to the Official Report of 24 January 2014, when the Minister for Communications, Energy and Natural Resources welcomed in the D&aacute;il the report of the Joint Committee on Transport and Communications on addressing the growth of social media and tackling cyberbullying, which was published in July 2013.  The Minister informed the D&aacute;il that late last year he established an Internet content governance advisory group under the chairmanship of Dr. Brian O'Neill of the Dublin Institute of Technology and comprising experts from industry, the legal profession and the child protection sector.  The group is due to report at the end of May 2014.  We have asked it to answer a series of questions on the most appropriate next steps in terms of policy on online content governance.  It is proposed that a copy of the Official Report of 24 January 2014 be forwarded to the petitioner together with contact details for the Internet content governance advisory group, informing her of how she can engage in the public consultation.  As cyberbullying is very much on the parliamentary agenda and plans have already been put in place by various Departments to tackle the issue, the petitioner should be encouraged to participate in the consultation process and the committee should then close the petition.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  The final petition is No. 00024/13, from Mr. Kevin Sharkey, regarding recruitment policy at RTE.  The petitioner is concerned that there is a policy within the broadcaster to employ only white people as presenters.  The committee considered this petition at its meeting on 11 December 2013 and agreed to write to RTE seeking a response to the issues raised in the petition.  At its meeting on 22 January 2014, the committee considered RTE's response but deferred making a decision on how to proceed.</p><p>  The decision we have made today is to seek further clarification from RTE of its policy concerning the employment of people from different ethnic and racial groups, particularly regarding the appointment of presenters.  It is proposed that the petition be again deferred pending receipt of that clarification from RTE.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  I thank members for their co-operation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.80" nospeaker="true" time="16:05:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 5.40 p.m. until 4 p.m. on Wednesday, 12 February 2014.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.81" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Transport and Communications</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.82" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 09:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Paudie Coffey, Senator Terry Brennan, Deputy Michael Colreavy, Senator Eamonn Coghlan, Deputy Timmy Dooley, Senator Paschal Mooney. Deputy Dessie Ellis, Deputy Tom Fleming, Deputy Noel Harrington, Deputy Seán Kenny, Deputy Patrick O'Donovan, Deputy Ann Phelan,</p><p>In attendance: Deputy Sandra McLellan.</p><p>DEPUTY JOHN O'MAHONY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.84" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" ><p>The joint committee met in private session until 10.15 a.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.85" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500003#E00100">Competition in Ports Sector: Competition Authority</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500003#E00200"><p>The purpose of today's meeting is to meet the Competition Authority to discuss its study of competition in the Irish ports sector and how port services might be improved.  On behalf of the committee, I welcome from the Competition Authority Ms Isolde Goggin, chairperson, and Ms Vivienne Ryan, Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward, Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Quigley and Mr. David McFadden.</p><p>  I draw the attention of witnesses to the fact that by virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of their evidence to the committee.  However, if they are directed by it to cease giving evidence on a particular matter and continue to so do, they are entitled thereafter only to qualified privilege in respect of their evidence.  They are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise or make charges against a person or an entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  I advise that any submissions or opening statements submitted to the committee will be published on its website after the meeting.</p><p>  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him or her identifiable. </p><p>  I invite Ms Goggin to make her opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.87" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500003#E00300"><p>I thank the committee for the invitation to discussion our work on competition in the ports sector.  We are pleased to be here.  I am accompanied by Ms Vivienne Ryan.  She is head of the advocacy division that  examines studies into markets where there is not an enforcement issue but where we feel areas of competition could be improved.  I am also accompanied by Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward, a case officer in the Competition Authority.  He is the main author of the ports study and I intend to direct hard questions to him.  Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Quigley is the secretary of the authority and head of corporate services and Dr. David McFadden is our legal adviser.</p><p>  Let me put the study in context.  We got a request from the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation to carry out a study into the ports sector in the context of the Action Plan for Jobs.  The underlying motivation for the study is competitiveness, jobs, keeping exports competitive and import prices down, and the role that can be played by the ports study.  Timelines were set out in the Action Plan for Jobs.  We worked towards that and produced the study last November.  </p><p>  We asked whether the competition in the Irish ports sector worked well for consumers and the economy.  In many ways the ports sector has a very low profile.  It is enormously important for exports to remain competitive.  As an island nation we are dependent on ports.  Therefore, our future economic success depends on our ability to trade.  Prices are very sensitive to transport costs, particularly to port costs, and unnecessarily high charges or inefficient ports will increase the cost of importing and exporting goods.  It is estimated that a 10% hike in transports costs can lead to trade volumes being reduced by more than 20%.   Additionally, it is not just about costs but efficiency.  It is about the throughput of ports and the speed with which goods are turned around or brought in and out.  It is estimated that every extra day in transit reduces trade volumes by about 1%.  </p><p>  As part of the process of conducting a study, we decided in December 2012 to issue a consultation document.  The rationale behind it was to verify our understanding of how competition works and invite interested parties to identify ways to strengthen competition.  Before that we held a series of one-to-one consultations and had over 30 meetings with those involved such as Departments, public agencies, industry representatives, the ports and transport  companies, port authorities and other port users.  The consultation helped to build an understanding of the sector and identified key issues because not a whole lot has been written about the sector.  </p><p>  We received 33 submissions and the response was generally very positive because people were in agreement and indicated how it works.  We also had a very good response from the various stakeholders because we sought further information and meetings to verify our understanding.  They put a lot of time and effort into their responses and we thank them all for their co-operation.</p><p>  There are two aspects of ports that are important.  First, competition between ports or inter-port competition.  Second, the intra-port competition which is competition in the same port between different terminals or different service providers.  </p><p>  The main focus of the study was on unitised cargo.  First, lo-lo which is load on-load off cargo that needs large cranes and port infrastructure to move cargo in and out.  Second, ro-ro which means roll on-roll off cargo that is driven on and off a ship.  Third, bulk cargo which refers to large and heavy material such as liquid fuel, coal, fertiliser and animal feed.  Exports are dominated by the unitised cargo of lo-lo and ro-ro and imports are dominated by bulk cargo.</p><p>  The kind of things that influence inter-port competition are as follows: port location, traffic trends, the quality of the roads infrastructure, haulage costs, the degree of specialisation at the ports and service frequency. </p> <p>We found that the level of competition between ports in Ireland, that is, inter-port competition, is limited as is the scope for inter-port competition, mainly for historical and geographical reasons.  Lo-lo terminal users increasingly utilise larger ports like Dublin, Belfast and Cork that are located next to large urban centres.  They have the volume of traffic that justifies investment in the port infrastructure.  Exporters and importers value the level of choice, service and frequency, while container shipping lines value large scale terminals that can minimise cost by facilitating bigger vessels and larger more efficient cranes. </p><p> Competition for ro-ro services is limited to east coast ports, including from Belfast, Warrenpoint, Drogheda, Dublin, Rosslare and across to the different ports in the UK.  Frequency is a big issue because many ro-ro services are time dependent where people look at the supply chain from start to finish.  They need to minimise the transit times and fit in the rest times for lorry drivers and so on so frequency of service is a big deal for those users.  Where there is heavy bulk cargo, customers will generally seek to use the nearest port as happens at Shannon and Cork.  I sent a copy of some documents to members of the committee which includes some useful diagrams.  Much of the bulk cargo goes into Shannon, coal into Moneypoint and aluminium ore into Aughinish Alumina.  They are location dependent.  Customers will not go to some other ports and incur the transports costs to go to those industries.  Similarly Whitegate is used for the oil going into Cork.  </p><p> Customers will also seek to use the nearest largest port which has the greatest frequency of service.  Ensuring that competition within a port, that is, inter-port competition, works well is very important.  It is particularly important in Dublin Port because it is the largest port in the country and the only one in the State that has grown its market share since 2005, and export focused cargo is becoming increasingly concentrated there with the improvements in the road network.  In 2012, Dublin handled 43% of ro-ro and 57% of lo-lo cargo. </p><p> We looked at the leasing and licensing arrangements for lo-lo terminal operators and for service providers in Dublin Port.  We are concerned that they may be restricting competition because they are very long arrangements.  Some of the arrangements were entered into about 20 years ago.  One has 110 years left of the lease and one has 85 years left and there is no scope for improvements in terms of performance measures.  The third is providing lo-lo services under a general stevedore licence granted 20 years ago and is due for renewal.  It can be renewed for another 20 years on identical terms once certain conditions are met.  That is a concern.  Those are very long timescales and it is hard to see how anybody else can get.  If they could do it better, how are they to get in because of the restricted capacity.  What tends to happen if there are restrictions in competition is that the service gets worse and the charges increase.</p><p> While Dublin Port Company can impose performance measures on the licensed operator it cannot do it on the lease holders which have 85 and 110 years left to run.  We recommended that Dublin Port Company should consider reducing the duration of those leases to address their anti-competitive impact.  It should look at whether the repeated renewal of the licence of the third lo-lo terminal operator should be amended to facilitate new entry.  We think those leases should be awarded for a shorter period on a fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory basis and should include efficiency measures that are enforced by Dublin Port Company.   That means turnaround times and so on and ensuring that the operator is getting the cargo in and providing a good service to users.</p><p> There are only two general stevedore licences for the common user quays in Dublin Port - effectively, one operates on the northside and the other operates on the southside - and the licences are for 20 year periods and are automatically renewed.  Dublin Port Company should issue at least two new general stevedore licences and should not have the clause in the current licences which allows for repeated renewal on more or less the same terms and conditions.  In all ports, general stevedore licences should be granted to applicants on a fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory basis or through a tendering process.  If cargo lines want to self-handle they should have that opportunity because many of them do that and are able to save money in that way and do not necessarily have to hire the services of a stevedore.  </p><p> One issue that arose in the consultations when we talked to people was the idea of port closure and amalgamation.  If ports are struggling, amalgamation may reduce and lower administrative costs.  It is not likely to have much effect on inter-port competition or to generate the necessary scale to compete with Dublin Port.  If a merger between ports is being proposed, we recommend that the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport be required to seek the views of the authority, as we have a general function to look at mergers within the economy but they have to be above a certain threshold and normally the ports would be below that threshold.  Either the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport should seek our views or there is a facility to designate a certain class of mergers as being notifiable to the authority regardless of the turnover.  That could be done by our own Minister.  We recommend that the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport should seek our views on competition effects of possible port mergers and amalgamations.  The ports should be given intra-port competition as a key objective, that is, if a port can sustain competition for ancillary services, the stevedoring licences and so on.  Some port authorities do not recognise the benefits of intra-port competition as a way of attracting users.  In regard to competition and monopoly it has been said that the best of all monopoly profits is a quiet life.  Sometimes if one has a single monopoly and a quiet life one does not feel the urge to do everything one possibly can to promote competition.</p><p> Investment to improve road and rail infrastructure may be justified for a number of reasons, one of which is competition, but also to remove bottlenecks or to abide by EU requirements for access to ports or to drive regional development objectives.  We do not consider that type of investment will be warranted purely on competition grounds.  We recommend that people consider it from other points of view but not to put money into ports on the grounds that it will drag traffic away from larger ports because the experience shows it does not happen but goes the other way around.  </p><p>  An issue that haunted the authority throughout the study was the difficulty in measuring performance and having access to proper data.  This is not just an Irish phenomenon, it appears to be the case generally that ports differ a great deal.  It is very hard to compare them across countries.  If we take a concentration of ports along the North Sea coast such as Rotterdam, Amsterdam and Antwerp they do much transit traffic and are not just looking at traffic for that country, whereas here, being an island nation, the traffic is in and out, it is for Ireland.  It is a bit different here than in continental countries.  We recommend that the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport should priorities the collection and development of new data metrics and port performance measures for the main ports in order that it is able to track performance over time and see that the ports are improving.  The study was published in November.  Its recommendations are mainly directed towards the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation and Dublin Port Company.  The Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport has committed to responding to all the recommendations within six months of publication.  We are interacting on a constant basis with our parent department, the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  </p><p> Dublin Port Company is reviewing its franchise arrangements and concluded its consultation at the end of last week.  It had held off doing so until it had an opportunity to look at our study.  In its review Dublin Port Company acknowledge the length of the leases and licences and said that it would not consider granting leases and licences on such terms today and will seek to replace existing leases and licences with more modern and appropriate franchises.  It indicated that there has been substantial investment and growth over the years and has raised the question as to how far it can go to undo the terms of an existing licence.  We will await the outcome of that review and the response from the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  This will be an ongoing process when we will be working with all the relevant parties.  We will be happy to answer any questions the committee may have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="09:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500004#F00200"><p>Thank you, Ms Goggin, for all that information.  Before I hand over to members I wish to put a quick question.  I note in today's edition of <i>The Irish Times</i> a big investment in Ringaskiddy port, which is categorised as a tier 1 port.  For clarification purposes, what are the other tier 1 ports?  What is a tier 2 port?  Perhaps we can have examples to clarify that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.90" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="09:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500004#F00300"><p>I will invite Mr. Ciaran Aylward to respond to that question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.91" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="09:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500004#F00400"><p>It is quite similar to the categorisation that the EU Commission has adopted.  Tier 1 ports are deemed to be of high national significance and generally ports whose overall tonnage exceeds 20% of the national total.  Dublin, Cork and Shannon Foynes are tier 1 ports.  They are in line to get priority in terms of investment from the European Union.</p> <p>The tier 2 ports, which are of regional significance, would be Waterford and Rosslare.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="09:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500005#G00200"><p>Into which category would Galway Port be placed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.94" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="09:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500005#G00300"><p>Galway Port is categorised as more of a tier 3 type of port.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="09:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500005#G00400"><p>That is interesting.  The poor old west, once again, seems to be losing out.  We will now have questions from members, beginning with Deputy Dessie Ellis.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1022" speakername="Dessie Ellis" time="09:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500005#G00500"><p>I thank Ms Goggin and her colleagues for their presentation.  Their study is very important in terms of ascertaining the level of competition and how the ports are operating.  At a time when Ireland is performing well when it comes to exports, any ideas or contributions towards improving that performance are worthy of consideration.</p><p>  Traditionally, there have been very lengthy leases on many of our ports, which do not allow much scope for new operators to enter the fray.  The delegates indicated that these leases should be reviewed.  I am not sure how that might work and am very interested to hear the witnesses' thoughts in this regard.  I assume operators would, in general, be very protective of their leases.</p><p>  Wage structures, the workforce and the potential for job creation are not mentioned in the review, presumably because they were not part of the remit.  There has been a great deal of discussion in recent times about the salaries being paid to chief executive officers in various organisations and management companies.  Will the witnesses comment on that?</p><p>  There is little or no mention of the potential for some of our ports to enhance their leisure facilities, which is another issue we have discussed in this committee.  Will the delegates indicate whether they took account of that issue as part of their review?</p><p>  Road and rail infrastructure is an issue that is raised regularly in the committee, particularly in the context of the inadequacy of access at certain ports.  Does Ms Goggin have any ideas in that regard?</p><p>  On the question of combining ports, I am not clear which particular ports might be considered suitable in that context.  I do not doubt there is scope for more interaction between different ports, including shared management.  I am interested to hear more from the witnesses on how such mergers might work.  An issue that comes immediately to mind is that people are generally very protective of their own patch.  How is it envisaged that different ports might operate together and what benefits are foreseen from such co-operation?  Would those benefits be primarily monetary, for example, or would there also be benefits in terms of tourism?</p><p>  There has been a great deal of talk about new ports coming on stream.  For instance, a location near Drogheda has been mooted as suitable for a deep-sea port.  Do the delegates have any ideas as to whether there is scope for new facilities in new locations?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.97" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="09:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500005#G00600"><p>Deputy Ellis has raised several interesting questions.  In terms of how leases might be changed, we are looking to Dublin Port Company to come up with ideas in that regard.  The company has acknowledged that existing leases are too long but the reality, as the Deputy noted, is that contracts are in place and cannot not easily be altered.  The company might certainly look at whether it would be possible to negotiate some changes to the leases.  Even if their duration cannot be changed, we are strongly of the view that consideration should be given to building in performance measures.  The operators might be obliged, for instance, to ensure quick turnaround times and the provision of a good professional service to users.</p><p>  We did not look at wage structures and the workforce, but we do see scope for more companies to enter the sector.  New entrants would, of course, be looking to grow jobs and employment.  We have made recommendations regarding stevedoring licences, because what is there now seems quite restrictive and operators do not have the incentives they could have to grow competition.</p><p>  The Deputy is correct that we did not look at the leisure industry, including cruise and passenger business.  Our mandate was very much focused on competitiveness in the sense of jobs and exports and in the context of the Action Plan for Jobs.  The cruise sector is growing, but many of its concerns are common to operators across all cargo types.  Improvements to services in the ports will benefit cruise licence holders in the same way they benefit other operators.  It should be noted that cruise vessels account for less than 2% of the total number of vessel calls to Irish ports.  Passenger and tourist car numbers have been declining over the past decade.  As with cruise operators, the same types of issues arise for passenger operators as do for all operators.</p><p>  Mr. Aylward referred to the categorisation of ports as tier 1, 2 or 3, which is the classification system operated by the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport under its national ports policy.  Tier 3 ports have been instructed to look at their tourism potential, leisure facilities and amenities for both larger and smaller vessels.  This aspect, as I said, was outside of our  competitiveness remit, which required us to focus on tier 1 and tier 2 ports because they are the ones of national and regional significance.</p><p>  In regard to management structures, we did not look at that issue from the bottom up, but we did make recommendations that management be given a greater incentive and mandate to promote competitiveness by providing better services and seeking to attract more business.</p><p>  The Deputy asked about amalgamations.  Dublin Port took over Dundalk Port because, as I understand it, the latter was losing money.  When it comes to amalgamations, the benefits are more in the back office end of things.  Management and administration functions might be merged, but that will not make more ships call to Dundalk, for instance, if they are not going there for other reasons.  We took into consideration the rationale for amalgamations, but we do not see them as being of critical importance in terms of promoting competition.  In a situation where two adjacent ports come together, there might be a negative impact on competition.  Normally when two companies with, say, a turnover of &euro;40 million each seek to merge, there is an obligation on them to notify us of the proposal.  We will give clearance or otherwise, generally within a month.  Where particular issues arise, we can extend the period of consideration before coming to a decision.  Our view is that it would be worthwhile to have a similar process for port mergers, even if they are below the threshold, in order to prevent mergers that might damage competition.</p><p>  We did examine the proposed Bremore development north of Dublin and concluded that it could place more competitive pressure on Dublin Port.  Under the national ports policy, no further Exchequer funding will be forthcoming, so this and any similar projects will be dependent on private investment, significant increases in trade and a capacity to attract container shipping lines away from Dublin Port.  The current climate is not particularly conducive in terms of attracting people who are looking to make that type of investment.  The Dublin Port tunnel and the new motorways have greatly improved access to Dublin Port in the past ten years, which makes the city more attractive for food exporters and others who are very sensitive to such factors as frequency of service, timing and so on.  Dublin Port is well placed to serve the needs of the greater Dublin area.  Looking through the competitiveness lens, our view is that the Government should focus first on enabling ports like Cork, Shannon and Waterford to develop more and better services and ensuring competition within Dublin Port is working as well as possible.  These, in our view, are the priority issues at this time.  In five or ten years, when the climate has changed, we might have a different view.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.98" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500006#H00100"><p>As Ms Goggin mentioned the development of Bremore Ireland Port will take significant private investment and will require the shipping lines which invest to commit to it.  At present, Dublin Port, in particular since the development of Dublin Port tunnel, is serving the export-import industry very well.  When Stena Line and Irish Ferries ships come in at 5.30 a.m. to 6 a.m. one sees a trail of trucks go up the port tunnel and out on to the M50 to serve the central distribution centres of the food and chemical industries.  That appears to be working quite well.  It would be quite difficult for another port to attract the shipping lines from Dublin Port.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1092" speakername="Paudie Coffey" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500006#H00200"><p>I thank the delegation for coming before the joint committee.  From the perspective of public policy, this discussion is helpful and timely.  The body of work of the Competition Authority will feed into the process of restructuring.  I support the idea that the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport would consult the Competition Authority in advance of restructuring of the port system.</p><p>  I wish to make a slight correction to Mr. Aylward's contribution on the categorisation of the tiers structure of ports.  He mentioned that the Port of Waterford and Rosslare Europort were regional ports.  Tor the record, they are categorised as national ports.  The tier 1 ports, which are responsible for 15% to 20% of overall tonnage through Irish ports, are Dublin Port, Shannon-Foynes Port and Port of Cork.  The nationally significant - tier 2 - ports are Port of Waterford and Rosslare Europort.  The remaining ports are tier 3 ports.</p><p>  I represent the Waterford constituency.  I am specifically looking at balanced regional development, something for which I have always argued.  The infrastructure servicing Dublin Port, the Dublin Port tunnel and access to the motorways, is brilliant.  Rosslare Europort and the Port of Waterford are the gateways to mainland Europe.  All the main trunk roads and motorways are adjacent to both ports.  The ports are also serviced by rail and major national infrastructure such as water and gas.  I believe they have not been developed to their full potential.  I am not taking the parochial view, but there is a push towards a dominant player in the sector.  My fear is that if Dublin Port on the eastern seaboard continues to development at its present rate, it could almost monopolise imports and exports.  I would have major concerns in that regard.  That is the reason I think the Competition Authority's input is essential.  The Competition Authority would have a broader view on how port infrastructure should develop.  It would obviously be observing fair practice and fair competition.</p><p>  Did the Competition Authority look at the destination of the imports that come in through Dublin Port?  Is the cargo staying in the Dublin region or is it being transported beyond that region?  That is an interesting factor because we need to be aware of how the internal transport costs are playing into the whole mix.  Similarly, are the exports from Dublin Port originating mainly in the Dublin region or have they been transported from other regions for onward transport from Dublin Port?  Has the Competition Authority gone into that level of detail?  If we are to maintain healthy competition, we need to look at the regional movement of export and import cargo and consider utilising the potential of existing ports.  Perhaps some of the traffic could be directed to other ports in a more efficient way.</p><p>  Regarding proximity to trading partners, I repeat that the Port of Waterford and Rosslare Europort are nearest to mainland Europe.  When transport costs were mentioned, I presume it was in reference to the cost of rail and road transport, but the proximity of the port to our trading partners is also a factor.  Is the proximity of the Port of Waterford and Rosslare Europort to the ports in Great Britain and mainland Europe taken into account?  How do the transport costs balance once they arrive on the mainland?</p><p>  I note the concerns about existing practice and management.  I would have serious concerns about the continuation of leases without a review of the terms and conditions.  I am amazed that key performance indicators and efficiency measurements are not included in the new licensing applications for stevedores, for example.  If they are not, should we as policy-makers not be asking questions on the reason they are not part of the licensing arrangement.  What can be done about this in the short to medium term?  Another Deputy mentioned that one cannot break long-term leases or licence arrangements, but when they come up for review, is it just a recommendation that the Competition Authority will look at the means of making them more competitive?  Has the Competition Authority a view on what we can do about addressing that problem, which has not been under the spotlight?</p><p>  What three things should change in the short term to improve competition in the port sector?  I am aware that the Competition Authority has made recommendations, but I would like its representatives to outline the three things that should change in the medium term to improve competition in this area.  This is very important for the economy, given the level of imports to and exports from our island nation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.100" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500006#H00300"><p>I will ask my colleague, Mr Aylward, to comment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.101" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500006#H00400"><p>It is worth making the point that in recent decades our way of thinking about transport has changed.  It is not just about what port one uses but the overall cost of transporting a product from A to B.  An exporter in the south east wishing to send product to the Asian market must take many factors, including geography, on board.  For example, it might be worthwhile to bring the product by road to Dublin or it might be worthwhile to transport it from Waterford.  One must take account of the infrastructure, road and rail, the proximity to ports in other countries and also the onward connections from the port to Shanghai.  One of the problems with Waterford Port in particular, is getting the cargo container onto a ship to Rotterdam for the outward journey to Shanghai.  The demand for services in Waterford will not be as high as they are in Dublin.</p><p>  In response to the Deputy's question about the origin and destination of cargo, some studies have been done and many of the imports are being sourced along the M50 region.  It makes natural sense to send imports to Dublin Port.  Generally there is more freedom when exporting products.  Most of the food export companies are based around Cork, Tipperary and the south east, and many of them would tend to use the Port of Waterford and Rosslare Europort.  It is worth mentioning that we formed a view from speaking to those involved in the Port of Waterford that they expected the new road would open up opportunities for Waterford Port, but in some ways it has harmed the port.  When the road was poor, Glanbia, for example, might have preferred to use Waterford Port because it was cheaper for it, but with the brand new road, once their product is at Dublin Port, they have a greater choice of destination and a higher level of frequency which is particularly important for manufacturing firms.  Waterford Port, might have only one sailing on a Thursday but Dublin Port will have a frequent service.  The cost to a company of missing an order is extremely high as jobs can be lost if they fail to supply on time, and that cost is much greater than the increase in the haulage charge to drive the product to Dublin.</p><p>  The Department is looking at the management structure of Rosslare Europort in particular.  The structure is different compared with other ports in Ireland.  Rosslare Europort has a complicated structure and is partially owned by Irish Rail.  It is not a semi-State.  The view of hauliers and exporters in the south east is that more could be done to improve Rosslare Europort and there is a feeling that if the management was more proactive, more could be done to improve the quality of service.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.102" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500006#H00500"><p>Will Mr. Aylward respond to the question on the stevedore licences?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.103" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500007#J00100"><p>On performance measures in respect of stevedore licences, which matter is under consideration in Europe, among the factors that must be looked at are efficiency measures such as the number of lifts per hour versus the number of staff employed, tonnage per hour, ship turnaround times and so on.  As mentioned by Ms Goggin, comparison between ports of efficiency measures for stevedores is difficult because ports do different things.  For example, Shannon-Foynes Port is largely bulk operated while the Port of Waterford is largely lo-lo operated.  It is akin to trying to compare apples and oranges.  In the context of performance of stevedores, we are considering benchmarking their performance over a ten year period to see if there have been improvements.  It is not perfect but it is a start.  The Irish Maritime Development Office, IMDO, which comes under the remit of the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport, is gathering the statistics in this regard.  As this is a matter relevant to that Department's national ports policy, it is an issue it needs to address.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.104" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500007#J00200"><p>I thank the Deputy for his support and suggestion that we be consulted in relation to mergers, which I believe would be very helpful.  Reference was made to there being a push towards dominant players in the ports sector.  It is true that the trend is that larger ports get bigger because they provide more services, attract better infrastructure and have greater frequency of services.  However, there are other developments.  In recent weeks there have been developments on the ferry side in terms of the new ferry from Rosslare to St. Nazaire in France and to Gijon in Spain.  Irish Ferries will also operate a new route from Dublin to Cherbourg.  Ports manage to attract or create business.  However, we have not looked specifically at that issue.</p><p>  The main focus of our study was intra-port competition and, if big ports tend to get bigger, which appears to be the trend in continental Europe, what can be done within those ports to ensure operations are run as efficiently as possible.  There tends to be little change in terms of operators, and as such we would like to stir things up a bit.  We were asked earlier what three things we would do in the short term.  I do not believe things in the port sector ever happen in the short term as what is involved is big heavy infrastructural investments.  We would like TPC Management to reduce, by way of negotiation, the leases under which the lo-lo terminals operate, building in efficiency measures and publishing them.  Publishing this type of information adds a great deal to the public debate and allows people to see what is going on and whether things are improving from year to year.  We would like to see more stevedoring and handling licences granted, which will act as an incentive for people to seek more business.  We would also ask that licences in all ports be granted on a fair, reasonable and non-discriminatory basis or through tendering.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/995" speakername="Noel Harrington" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500007#J00300"><p>I welcome the delegation and thank them for their interesting submission.  As stated, 90% of goods moving in and out of this country come through our ports.  This means the manner in which ports operate is important to the overall national trade picture.  Was analysis carried out of the impact of the charging structure in ports on the overall transport costs for Ireland?  I acknowledge that is a very broad question and may be difficult to answer but I would welcome any information the witnesses can provide in that regard.</p><p>  On the submissions received by the authority, did any of them raise the issue of the impact of increased competition on safety in ports or on industrial relations?  I share the delegation's concerns in relation to the long leases issue in respect of the terminals and stevedores.  Leases of 20 years in such a restricted market are quite lengthy.  I take the point that competition is not always around the corner and people are not always readily available to carry out that work.  I am interested in hearing the delegation's views on intra-terminal competition within our ports and on performance related targets for stevedores.  It is disappointing that the only statistics to which the authority can look in the context of the performance of stevedores is performance indicators over the past ten years, which means it could be copperfastening poor performance over ten years.  It cannot be beyond the authority to find some international ports with best practice or that have achieved what could be regarded as best practice.  I submit that that would be a more appropriate way of looking at performance targets for stevedores.</p><p>  I believe short term rolling leases, under which security not alone for the companies but the State could still be guaranteed, might be more appropriate than 20 year leases, including 20 year leases with automatic options to renew.  This issue needs to be addressed.  Many of the savings that can be achieved will come from larger vessels carrying larger loads but not necessitating larger ports.  How will this impact on competition?  While it might drive economies of scale in the short term, is there a longer term impact?  Has the authority looked at any of the European initiatives introduced in this area?  For example, would the Marco Polo and Motorways of the Sea initiatives, which encourage states to take transport goods by sea rather than road, which initiatives are largely driven by carbon emissions targets and so on, improve our ports' ability to do business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.106" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500007#J00400"><p>In terms of actual costs, the literature to which we have looked in this regard indicates that the cost of moving goods through our ports in terms of overall transport costs is approximately 10%, including haulage costs of approximately 5%.  The largest cost is generally cash and cargo handling, which is the stevedore and lo-lo handling charges, which amounts to 60% to 90%.  As mentioned by Ms Goggin, it is not necessarily the cost that has a disproportionate effect on trade volumes.  A 10% increase in transport costs results in a 20% decrease in terms of volume.</p><p>  On the submissions, concern was raised about the safety issue, although more in the context of the level of space on quays in particular.  The concern as expressed by the ports is that there should not be ten or 11 stevedores operating in a confined space.  We are seeking information from the ports, supported by evidence, in regard to where limited space is available.  If in some cases there is only limited space available and it is not possible to provide for ten operators in a quay space, there are ways of getting around this, including tendering, which would ensure competitive influence is retained.  For example, where for safety reasons it is only possible to allow three operators in a particular space, a five year contract could be awarded and renewed thereafter.</p><p>  In regard to intra-terminal competition, we have looked in depth at the different types of ports in Ireland, their sizes and the best management model for each.  For example, Dublin port is a type of landlord port.  When a port is large, it is generally operated by a public operator and private service providers operating under lease and licence.  The economic literature indicates that in some cases it is better to have a tool port structure, whereby the port company is publicly owned but in some cases owns some of the infrastructure and leases out operation of the labour.</p> <p>We believe that would work and would be a more efficient operation in ports such as Cork and Waterford.  However, we feel more could be done in terms of internal competition.  For example, in Cork all the lo-lo cranes are operated by the port company.  Perhaps there could be two competing stevedores who get a contract to operate the same crane.  That has been done in other countries and is often deemed to be best practice.</p><p> In terms of the lease lengths, we looked at best practice in a number of different countries.  Ms Goggin mentioned that the lease length in Dublin, in particular, is 80 to 110 years.  It is generally deemed that 15 to 30 years should be the adequate length.  Deputy Harrington mentioned rolling contracts.  Belfast recently renegotiated the length of the lease structure and it has a five-year lease that operates to a maximum of 20 years.  We would like to see something along those lines to improve competition.</p><p> We did some research into the effect of increasingly larger vessels; they seem to be increasing across the board.  There is some scepticism over the impact this will have on Ireland, as an island nation on the outskirts of Europe.  Most of the ships tend to be feeder-type vessels that either go directly to the UK or the hub ports in continental Europe.  While there has been some increase there, will they become vessels of the size of the large Panamax ships?  They probably will not because they tend to have their disadvantages.  The throughput in Dublin Port, for example, is not sufficient.  While there might be economies of scale in having a large vessel, it might take a week to fill it up so there is not much point in it.</p><p> However, Cork Port and the Shannon Foynes Port have natural advantages in terms of water depth.  If there is an increase in vessel size in the future, it will be important for the Government to be aware of improving the transport links to those ports, particularly the rail links, because the depth of water in Dublin might not be sufficient to accept the larger vessels.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.108" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K00200"><p>Deputy Harrington asked about the impact of the cargo handling charges.  They form a very substantial part of the port costs - between 60% and 90%, depending on the degree of automation.  For some reason, transport volumes are very sensitive to port charges.  If the port charges increase by 20%, the cargo volumes decrease by 20%.  So it is a very significant element.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.109" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/995" speakername="Noel Harrington" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K00300"><p>Did the possible effect of any of the European initiatives come into the Competition Authority's studies?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.110" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K00400"><p>We did not look at it in any great detail.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K00500"><p>I thank the witnesses for the submission.  The physical constraints in ports should be a consideration.  Panamax vessels are already a fact of life for bulk ports, particularly the Shannon Foynes Port in my constituency.  It is no coincidence that the port will attract the investment and the attention it deserves into the future simply because it happens to be the deepest.  What analysis did the Competition Authority carry out into the physical constraint of the water depths at these ports?  Larger Panamax vessels will become a fact of life, particularly for bulk cargo.  Moneypoint has the largest coal-burning electricity generation plant in the country and some of the biggest ships in the world go in there.  They cannot get into any other port in the country.  Physical constraints will have to form part of the basis when considering competition between ports.  There is no point talking about ships that may or may not call to port; the reality is that they are already calling to those ports.</p><p>  Has this been looked at in the context of the operation of European ports and intra-port competition in terms of stevedoring and things like that?  In some cases the stevedores are employees of the ports and might have built up employment rights, etc., depending on their length of service.  How would the model of competing interests in the port operate on the basis that the infrastructure in many cases is owned by the port, the workers are employees of the port and the port is a State entity?  How has this model worked in other countries where increased levels of competition have been introduced?</p><p>  During the analysis of competition within ports, what interaction did the Competition Authority have with the stakeholders, including the employers and haulage operators?  Would those people have had similar experiences in European or UK ports?  If there is greater levels of competition in those countries, is there evidence that it leads to improved levels of competitiveness from the point of view of the stakeholders?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.112" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K00600"><p>I might ask Mr. Aylward to answer the specific questions on the intra-port competition, particularly looking at the European examples.</p><p>  On the physical constraints, we had many meetings with the stakeholders.  We had about 30 meetings before we did the consultation and had various meetings afterwards.  We asked people for specific information, once we had firmed up on our ideas as to what to look for.  We found that the different sectors are quite different in terms of the physical demands.  In the case of a bulk transporter transporting very heavy stuff to a specific destination, the client wants to be as close as possible to where that is, for example, with Aughinish Alumina or Moneypoint.  However, they also need good deep-water ports for the bulk transport.</p><p>  In other cases, the end-to-end timing is much more crucial especially in the case of food and drink imports and exports, where people require short sea crossings.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K00700"><p>Is the main thrust of the Competition Authority's submission based on roll-on roll-off rather than bulk?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.114" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K00800"><p>It is all of those - roll-on roll-off, load-on load-off, and bulk.  The only ones we did not look at were passenger and cruise ships because they are contingent on other activities in the port and the cruise thing is still quite short.  We considered bulk in considerable depth.  It is quite different from the other sectors because the transport costs on land are so crucial.  That is why people want to have the power station near the deep-water port or have the deep-water port near the power station - I am not sure which is the chicken and egg in that case.  Bulk is crucial and it tends to be very local; it cannot go anywhere else and has to be in that location.</p><p>  I will ask Mr. Aylward to respond on the issue of comparisons with European ports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.115" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K00900"><p>We looked at the benefits of intra-port competition in general.  In Europe, there is a move towards a landlord-type model, which means there is public ownership and management of the port, with the operation of it licensed out to private operators.  Ports such as Rotterdam, Antwerp and Bremen would have three or four different competing lo-lo terminal operators.  In the research, not just in Europe but also in South America, that has been proved to reduce the cost of handling compared with having just one provider and where there was a lack of intra-port competition.  There is considerable debate in Europe at the moment with changing directives in this area.  There are certainly differences of opinion between the northern European view on this and the Mediterranean view, where there are stronger workers' unions which are reluctant to a move away from monopolies towards more intra-port competition.  Overall, there is a move towards competing terminals.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500008#K01000"><p>In Rotterdam, for example, if three terminals are operating within the one estuary, they are essentially three standalone ports operating in the same geographical area.  Obviously within each of those this issue also exists because they will be run by a single management company.  Are they run along similar lines to how Irish ports operate, with the neighbouring ports, as with D&uacute;n Laoghaire and Dublin Port, for instance, but independent within the one estuary?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.117" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00100"><p>It is similar to what is occurring in Dublin Port at the moment for lift-on lift-off vessels.  Dublin Port Company oversees the regulation of the port.  Then, there are three separate private lo-lo operators, operating under licence or lease.  Basically, they operate their companies as they see fit.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00200"><p>How did that experience improve competitiveness from the point of view of employers, importers and exporters?  Did the authority examine that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.119" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00300"><p>It has been like that in Dublin Port for a long time.  We do not have data or information from when the services were provided by one operator.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00400"><p>I want to get to the kernel of the matter.  I presume the basis the Competition Authority had for examining this area was to improve competitiveness and reduce costs for the importer, the service user, the exporter and the economy as a whole.  Is there evidence from European ports that have done what is being suggested to the effect that this actually happens?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.121" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00500"><p>Yes.  Mr. Aylward made a point about the northern and southern European ports.  There are numerous competition cases relating to ports.  They tend to be in the area of abuse of dominance.  They tend to have shown that where there is a single port and a single port operator, not only are there higher charges, but it is the area of inefficiency where the real damage gets done.  There is no incentive to put goods through quickly or to invest and accept more and more traffic.  There is a good deal of evidence showing where monopolies have operated against the public interest and against the interests of importers and exporters in particular, and that a lack of competition has resulted.  It is not only about price, it has much to do with service quality, the services offered to importers and exporters, the frequencies of sailing, the turnaround times and the length of time goods are left on the docks before they are brought in and out.  The whole area of efficiency is crucial.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00600"><p>Were Irish port users surveyed as part of their experience in respect of the services that are available at Irish ports?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.123" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00700"><p>I am unsure whether "surveyed" is the word I would use.  We talked to them and we held individual meetings with them.  They told us of their experiences in respect of all the tier 1 and tier 2 ports.  I would not exactly describe it as a survey, but we certainly talked to them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.124" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00800"><p>As part of the consultation process we had over 30 meetings before we produced a consultation document.  We spoke to the Departments, public agencies, industry representatives and all the port authorities.  We also spoke to the major ferry companies, the terminal operators and hauliers across a wide stream.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/964" speakername="Ann Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L00900"><p>Some of the questions I had intended to ask have been dealt with already.  For the record, the Port of Waterford happens to be in Kilkenny.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01000"><p>They had better rename it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/964" speakername="Ann Phelan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01100"><p>Yes, we had better rename it.  I am a little disappointed to hear that the road has had something of a negative effect on the port.  I remember from my time on Kilkenny County Council that a good deal of investment has gone into the area and the port.  The new road was cited as one of the most positive reasons to put in a good deal of investment and infrastructure.</p><p>  The deputation answered the question I was going to ask about modifying existing ownership and management models.  Is there anything else the deputation wishes to add to that?  I understand the physical constraints and that it is definitely a difficulty for ports, particularly on that side of Ireland.</p><p>  In the course of the survey, did the authority do an examination of the services that exist in the vicinity of the port?  Could the availability of broadband, water services or information technology services help or offer an advantage if a port was to sell itself?  Would it benefit if it had several information technology areas around it?  Did that come under the radar of the authority?  I am unsure whether it did.  Does the authority have an opinion on it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/981" speakername="Sandra McLellan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01200"><p>Did the study incorporate the economic aspects of port operation, for example, leases with upward-only rent reviews?  Did the study incorporate other areas of potential development, for example, maintenance or repairs of ships?  Did the study incorporate an examination of the level of goods transported to ports by road that could be transported by rail freight?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01300"><p>Deputy Harrington has a supplementary question.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/995" speakername="Noel Harrington" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01400"><p>Given what we have heard thus far and given the many constraints, whether geographical or because of specialised ports, is the Competition Authority satisfied with the competition that exists between and within ports?  What is the level of satisfaction or dissatisfaction at the authority?  Does the authority believe it might be appropriate for interventions such as legislation, or would other interventions assist?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.131" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01500"><p>A question was asked about services.  As Mr. Aylward said, we spoke to a large number of port users.  They did not raise the issues of broadband or water services.  I wonder whether these would be more relevant to the tier 3 ports, those designated by the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport as having a future more in the leisure industry rather than national and regional transportation.  The point related to the question of a port selling itself.  Some ports make good efforts in that respect but it was not quite the area of our study.  We were asked to examine competitiveness, the cost of imports and exports, jobs and so on.</p><p>  We examined the issue of leases but people did not raise upward-only rent reviews, which is a relatively recent phenomenon.  Most of the leases have been in place for so long.  They date back to the 1980s.  Upward-only rent reviews are more recent and came in with the property boom.  I am unsure whether they were a feature.</p><p>  We did not examine the maintenance repairs business because we were not examining the shipping industry.  One person raised that issue with us from a port on the east coast.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.132" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Mr. Ciar&aacute;n Aylward" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01600"><p>A good deal of maintenance repairs are done by what is called a ships agency.  Generally, there seems to be a good level of competition there.  It was not raised as an issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.133" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01700"><p>It could have been dealt with if people had come to us and said that it was a problem, but they did not.</p><p>  There was a question about goods transported by road that could be transported by rail.  This arose only indirectly in the sense that people would explain that there was rail freight option into a given port and not into another.  However, the major point emerging was the magnet effect that larger ports seem to have.  They seem to draw more and more traffic in once they hit a certain critical mass.  Then, the frequency of service increases and that makes it more attractive again.</p><p>  There is an issue around climate change and the relative carbon cost of various forms of transport and so on, but dealing with environmental matters is far beyond our level of expertise.  Another area that could be examined relates to the point raised by Deputy Harrington earlier about sea freight versus air freight.  Exporters tend to fall into using one or other category, either air freight or sea freight, by the nature of the goods in question and the value-to-volume ratio.  If goods are small, light and high-value, they can go by air and everything else tends to go by sea.</p><p>  Are we satisfied with the level of competition?  The is the short answer is "No, we are not".  We believe a good deal more could be done.  We would prefer to wait until we see the response of the Department of Transport, Tourism and Sport.  The Department said it would get back to us in six months.  We will have a good look at what Dublin Port Company came out with last week on its franchise review.  We will talk to the Department and come back in a further six months and then decide whether more needs to be done.  We have put it up to people.  We have outlined what we believe the issues are and what we believe is within the power of parties to change.  We would like to see how that goes and whether that meets our concerns.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500009#L01800"><p>Is it the intention of the authority to examine air freight in future?  All the air freight is conveyed through the State airports and they are all owned essentially by one company.  The landing charges are set by the State company.  Is it the intention of the authority to examine how the operation of our State airports impacts on importers and exporters?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.135" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500010#M00100"><p>I must say that is not at the moment.  We have barely recovered from the last exercise, but that was given to us in the context of the Action Plan for Jobs.  The next action plan for jobs, which we are awaiting, will probably ask us either to look directly at some area or to do a study on what areas would be good to look at.  We want to look at areas where people are telling us there is a problem.  We do not particularly think it would be a good use of our time to look at something and for people to say there is no problem, but if the Deputy feels there is an issue here, we could have a chat about it and put it into the mix.  It will probably be given to us as a job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1058" speakername="Patrick O'Donovan" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500010#M00200"><p>There is greater monopoly in this country at the moment than the State airports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.137" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Isolde Goggin" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500010#M00300"><p>That is a very good point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1073" speakername="John O'Mahony" time="10:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/TRJ2014020500010#M00400"><p>Thank you very much.  I think it was a very engaging and informative discussion.  I thank you for coming in.  Many developments are taking place and will take place, so perhaps you will be back with us again at some stage in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2014-02-05a.139" nospeaker="true" time="10:40:00" ><p>The joint committee adjourned at 11.25 a.m until 9.30 a.m. on Wednesday, 19 February 2014.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>