<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.2" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Education and Social Protection</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.3" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 13:00</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.5" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500002#A00100">Business of Joint Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.6" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500002#A00200"><p>Apologies have been received from Deputies James Bannon and Clare Daly and Senators Fidelma Healy Eames and Averil Power.  At the request of the broadcast recording service, I ask members to turn off their mobile telephones completely.  The proceedings are carried on UPC channel 207.  Is it agreed to go into private session to deal with the minutes, correspondence and other matters?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.8" nospeaker="true" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500003#C00100">Rent Supplement Scheme: Discussion with Department of Social Protection</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.9" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500003#C00200"><p>I welcome officials from the Department of Social Protection who will make a presentation on the rent supplement.  I welcome Ms Helen Faughnan, Ms Jackie Harrington and Ms Lisa Doyle.</p><p>  By virtue of section 17(2)(<i>l</i>) of the Defamation Act 2009, witnesses are protected by absolute privilege in respect of the evidence they are to give this committee.  If a witness is directed by the committee to cease giving evidence in relation to a particular matter and the witness continues to so do, the witness is entitled thereafter only to a qualified privilege in respect of his or her evidence.  Witnesses are directed that only evidence connected with the subject matter of these proceedings is to be given and witnesses are asked to respect the parliamentary practice to the effect that, where possible, they should not criticise nor make charges against any person or persons or entity by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  The opening statements submitted to the committee will be published on the committee website after the meeting.</p><p>  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice that they should not comment on, criticise or make charges against a person outside the House or an official by name in such a way as to make him or her identifiable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.10" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="13:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500003#C00300"><p>I thank the committee for the opportunity to appear before it today on the matter of the Department's rent supplement scheme.  I propose to update the committee members on rent supplement matters in general and to address the specific issues raised by the committee specifically on rent limits, rent deposits and the processing times.</p><p>  The Department's primary role in this area is the provision of income support through the rent supplement scheme for which the Government has provided a sum of over &euro;403 million for 2013.  The purpose of rent supplement is to provide short-term income support to eligible tenants living in private rented accommodation whose means are insufficient to meet their accommodation costs and who do not have accommodation available to them from any other source.</p><p>  There are currently approximately 86,000 rent supplement recipients, of which more than 54,000 have now been in payment for more than 18 months, representing over 60% of the total.  The Department provides on an ongoing basis relevant details of these long-term claimants to the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government, with a view to transferring them to the rental accommodation scheme, known as RAS.</p><p>  Budget 2012 provided for a number of changes to the rent supplement scheme including a review of the maximum rent limits which were set after an analysis of the most up-to-date market data available.  During 2012, approximately 48,700 rent supplement claims were awarded at the revised limits.  As the Department currently funds almost 30% of the private rented sector, it is essential that State support for rents is continually kept under review, that it reflects current market conditions and that it does not distort the market in a way that could increase rent prices for others such as low-income workers.  The Department acknowledges that the rental market has changed since the limits were revised.  It is currently carrying out a review of the current maximum rent limits.  It is expected that these new limits will be introduced in June of this year.</p><p>  The review process includes an analysis of the private rental market using publicly available data sources as well as consultation with other bodies and organisations involved in the area of housing support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.12" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500004#D00200"><p>As a vote has been called in the D&aacute;il, I propose that we suspend the sitting until after it has taken place.  Members can ask questions when we resume.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500005#E00100"><p>I will now take questions.  I have the agreement of spokespersons to call Senator Marie Moloney first as she is due to speak in the Seanad.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="13:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500005#E00200"><p>Thank you, Chairman.  I thank the departmental representatives for attending.  I am the person who requested that they attend to brief the committee on a number of issues, one of which is the important matter of rent caps.  My firm belief is that the rent caps are too low across the country.  Rents are demand-led.  I will speak about the area I know best - Killarney - where there is a huge demand for rental properties.  Rents have decreased somewhat but not significantly.  The cost of renting a property in Killarney is still very high.  In the guide for the Kerry area a single person is asked to stay below the cap of &euro;84 per week.  Nowhere in Killarney town will one find accommodation on offer for &euro;84 per week.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="13:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500006#F00200"><p>I, along with other committee members, have raised the top-up or under-the-counter payments with the Minister on several occasions.  The answer I usually get is that the Department has no record of this being a wide-scale practice.  It might not have records of it because the clients paying this top-up payment do not want to come forward as they are afraid of losing an apartment or a house they have managed to secure despite the shortage.  They will only complain to Deputies or councillors at constituency clinics.</p><p>  This practice has got much worse in recent years, given the shortage of properties available, particularly in Dublin.  The only solution, which I have suggested to the Minister, is that rent supplement and housing assistance payments be paid directly to the landlord.  I understand changes are due to be made to the rent supplement scheme and the housing assistance payments, but if the Department has any influence, it should ensure those payments are made directly to landlords.  There would be several advantages in doing this.  First, it would cut out the top-up payments.  Second, it would ensure the landlord gets the money and it is not abused like in the case of a chaotic drug user who would be tempted by having the rent cheque in their pocket.  Third, it would also facilitate the registration and legal compliance of landlords.</p><p>  When the changes were made to the maximum rent limits, the Department stated an analysis was done.  Other members mentioned Killarney and Galway, where there are also high rents, but in Dublin, which I know best, the new maximum rent limits did not reflect what was happening on the ground in any shape or form.  It has contributed to chaos for many people.  I am not one who wants to subsidise private landlords as I believe the State should be putting most of this money into building social housing.  I am not suggesting we should give private landlords more than they deserve, but the Department claims it was trying not to distort the market.  In some ways, it was distorting it downwards with many landlords opting out of making their properties available to social welfare recipients.  This, in turn, contributed to fewer properties being available to rent.  If one wants proof of how few properties are available at present, Dublin City Council now cannot source properties for the rental accommodation scheme.  It is dire and has forced many people into chaos.  Hopefully, the Department will have seen sense and when it is analysing the figures again, it will move the maximum rent limit upwards for a temporary period until the housing assistance payment is introduced, which will be a significant change.  Does the Department have any details of when the housing assistance payment scheme will be introduced?  What areas have been suggested as pilot schemes and for how long will they go on?</p><p>  I know of some cases where people have had difficulties in getting deposits back.  In some cases where the landlord&rsquo;s property has been foreclosed on by the banks, the tenant&rsquo;s deposit has been lost.  It is with the bank.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500007#G00200"><p>Could Ms Faughnan go through those questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.20" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500007#G00300"><p>With regard to Senator Moloney's queries, we determine rent limits by using the most available data sources to ascertain both the market trends and current asking prices for the various one, two and three-bedroomed properties throughout the country on a county-by-county basis.  In particular, we have access to the Private Residential Tenancies Board, PRTB, databases.  A departmental employee is on the board of the PRTB.  We also consult leading websites that advertise properties for rent.  The bonus of being able to access the PRTB data means that we know the actual rents being paid rather than the asking prices on the rental websites.  We also use the CSO rental indices and local knowledge.  As part of the rent review, we consult with many organisations working in the housing sector including local authorities, the Simon Community and Threshold.  Departmental staff have built up a huge amount of expertise in carrying out these reviews over the past number of years.  We are aware that the market is changing substantially, which is why we are carrying out our current review.  We hope to have the new rent limits available with effect from June 2013.  They were supposed to come in from July but we have intensified the work and are bringing them forward by a month.  We should have our report completed at the end of May and the new limits should be available from June.  The report and how we came about the data will be published on the Department's website as well.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500007#G00400"><p>Could Ms Faughnan give us any indication of the new limits today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.22" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500007#G00500"><p>We do not have them.  We are still in the process of working them out and checking the data.  We would look at a county but would also go into detail because there are distortions with areas near a big urban centre or attached to a university or areas with a considerable amount of employment.  That distorts the availability as well.</p><p>  It is an income support payment.  This was set up as a short-term measure so that we are the helping hand for somebody who has been renting and now finds himself or herself unemployed.  We hope that person will get back into employment and be able to pay their own rent.  Due to the recession, our short-term scheme has evolved into a longer-term scheme. </p><p>  Senator Moloney also spoke about domestic violence.  We offer specific care and attention to people who are suffering either domestic violence or intimidation, which, unfortunately, has become a feature of some housing areas.  Where cases of domestic violence arise, that person will be helped to get accommodation away from that situation even if they have a share in the house.  This is where the discretion of the former community welfare officer arises.  I would be most concerned if cases are not being looked after and I ask the Senator to bring such cases to my attention because we will definitely look into them.  That would be a top priority for us in terms of making sure that people are looked after. </p><p>  Senator Moloney mentioned the different rent caps in Killarney.  I do not have the specifics for Killarney but in the south Kerry constituency, the evidence available to us is that there are properties available in or around the rent limits there.  We have a concern that people are telling us about the top ups, to which Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh referred.  Unfortunately, we can only act on the evidence presented to us.  If somebody tells us that the landlord is not willing to engage, our duty of care is to the tenant.  We want to engage with the tenant to ensure that they can seek accommodation.  I reiterate that we cannot make all accommodation available in all areas for customers.  We will not offer the full spectrum of choice.  The same applies to the local authorities.  Some people want to live in a specific area but this depends on availability.  If there is considerable demand for accommodation in that area, we may not be able to facilitate the person within the rent limits.  </p><p>  We have a duty of care to the taxpayer to ensure that we are getting best value for money.  We are a big player in the rental market with a stake of about 30% so in terms of ensuring value for money, we cannot keep upping the rent limits because landlords will follow the trend.  When we set the limits in the 2010 rent review, there was a 4% weighted average reduction in the rents.  In effect, we are setting the bar.  Landlords declare rent to the PRTB and the Department and the PRTB send on that data to the Revenue Commissioners.  It is fraud if somebody-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500007#G00600"><p>The problem is that they are declaring the rent minus the top-up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.24" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500007#G00700"><p>Senator Moloney can come back when the other questions are asked.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.25" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="13:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500007#G00800"><p>We appreciate that it is an issue but our hands are tied if the tenant does not come forward to let us know.  Under a recent Act, our social welfare officers have powers to ensure that if they are doing a check on a landlord, that landlord must declare actual rents.  It is an offence if they are not declaring the right amount.  These powers are available to our special investigation unit and our staff to enable them to improve that situation.</p><p>  Senator Moloney mentioned the recoupment of deposits.  We are aware of the deposits that are being paid.  To put it into context, approximately 5,600 deposits were paid in 2012.  From talking to NGOs, these are a key support, particularly to help people avoid homelessness.  It helps people who need accommodation but do not have the resources, particularly those on social welfare or HSE payments, to save the money for a deposit.  In 2012, approximately 48,700 rent supplement claims were awarded so the amount of deposits issued is a very small percentage at approximately 11%.  The corollary of that is that 43,100 new awards did not receive a deposit.  I accept the Senator's query about whether this is a circular process whereby a deposit must be made available.  We agree that there are better uses for this money and welcome the scheme that the Minister of State with responsibility for housing and planning is looking at putting in place.  We will be looking at the rental deposits scheme when this protection scheme comes into play.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.27" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500008#H00200"><p>It certainly would not be five days.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.28" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500008#H00300"><p>Prior to attending the meeting, we checked around the country to see if all the documentation is received and completed, whether rent supplements are processed fairly quickly and definitely within two to five days.  A rent supplement form is not straightforward.  There are many elements to it because we need the household or family details, including whether there are children in the house, the income details of the claimant and his or her spouse or partner, savings, third party details, the details of the property being rented, details of the landlord, including his or her tax reference number, and a housing needs assessment, and we need to know whether the person meets the habitual residence condition.  By its nature, it is a detailed process but if all the elements are there, the decisions are made quickly.  The issue is when some of the elements are missing and it is up to the client to come back with them.  To try to assist in the processing of all of this, there used to be a rent pack.  Having taken feedback from customers and NGOs, last August, a new rent supplement application form was produced.  It is much more streamlined and there is a tick box to remind customers, employers and landlords of the different elements they have to complete.  As a result of that form, the number of incomplete application forms has dropped.  We are getting the completed application forms in and that is helping the processing times.</p><p>  With regard to discretion, I assure the committee that the people processing rent supplement claims are former community welfare officers.  The discretion remains and they have a huge amount of local knowledge.  While we have rent limits, in some areas the rent paid might be less because the officials are aware in the area that accommodation is available at less than the rent limit amount.  If somebody has a disability in the household or there is a specific case of concern, there is a small amount of discretion.</p><p>  I refer to rent supplement and landlords.  If the tenant comes to us and says he or she wants the payment made directly to the landlord, we will facilitate that.  Approximately 20% of rent supplement payments are paid currently to a person other than the tenant.  In some cases, a person acts on behalf of the tenant but the rent supplement scheme is designed specifically for the benefit of tenants to assist them with short-term accommodation needs.  If we were to start paying landlords directly, this would create a new relationship between them and the Department.  Currently, that would mean up to 86,000 additional clients and that is not on the cards for us but under the housing assistance payment, HAP about which Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh asked, it is planned that the payment will issue directly to the landlords because currently under the rental accommodation scheme, that is what happens.  However, the rent supplement scheme is designed to be short term.  When landlords have grievances about non-payment of rent, etc., by a tenant, there are specific measures in place through the dispute resolution process of the PRTB if they wish to go through that.</p><p>  I will update the committee on HAP.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government is taking the lead in the development of the payment with significant interaction with our Department.  Detailed legislation will be required on the housing side to bring in HAP and the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government is working on that.  In tandem with that, its officials are carrying out a detailed economic assessment of this proposal and they are also examining the business planning process behind this because this will be a fundamental change in how housing supports are administered.  There is also a major concern among local authorities.  Many of their tenants have fallen into rent arrears and there is a concern that the proposed set up under HAP should not make this situation worse.</p><p>  I referred in my opening contribution to the household budgeting facility.  This scheme is operated by An Post on behalf of my Department.  It is an excellent scheme, which helps people, particularly those on low incomes, to manage their budget more effectively.  They can pay their gas and electricity bills and so on out of that.  Currently, 33,000 local authority tenants are paying their rents under the household budgeting system.  Part of the difficulty was when they signed up to a tenancy agreement with a local authority and household budgeting, they were able to unsign a week or two later.  We introduced a provision in last December's Social Welfare Bill to make it mandatory that when a tenant signs up to the household budgeting facility under the new tenancy agreements, he or she cannot unsign without the agreement of the local authority.  We hope to have this new facility by the end of next month and that will be a help to the local authorities.</p><p>  The pilot schemes will commence once the necessary housing legislation is in place.  The Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government is working with the local authorities to select the pilot locations.  I do not have the details to hand but they will become available once the Department publishes the housing Bill.  It is not clear how long the pilot schemes will be.  That element has not been worked out yet but as part of the business processing, we will test the various elements to ensure the interaction between the local authorities, our Department, the Department of the Environment, Community and Local Government and whatever housing agencies make this new process work.  We will tease out any of the issues that might arise before full roll-out commences.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500008#H00400"><p>I thank Ms Faughnan and her team for their presentation.  I add my voice to those who said the caps are too low.  The average rent in Fingal, which I represent, is &euro;1,200 for two to three-bedroom homes, which is well in excess of the cap of &euro;775 for a one-parent family or a couple with one child and &euro;825 for a one-parent family or a couple with two children.  The gap is too great.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1181" speakername="Patrick Nulty" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500009#J00200"><p>I thank the Chairman for allowing me to contribute to this discussion.  I also thank the officials from the Department, Ms Helen Faughnan and her team, for their input.  Everybody present would probably agree that the long-term solution to this problem is the provision of social housing, but, unfortunately, the State has failed to provide it.  While rent allowance may, in theory, be a short-term support, in practice it is an integral part of housing policy.</p><p>  I, too, will comment on top-up payments.  I have spoken to community welfare officers who tell me that they know when signing off on rent forms, the rent is a fiction.  They are trying to keep families in their homes.  Tenants must renegotiate their rents each year, year in year out, and if they do not succeed in negotiating downwards and remaining in their homes, they must take their children out of school and uproot themselves from the neighbourhood and neighbours with whom they have built links.  It is Orwellian to suggest there is no evidence of top-up payments being made; no one can accept this.  I am sure members recognise that top-up payments are rife in the system.</p><p>  I will comment on rent caps.  My colleague, Deputy Brendan Ryan, mentioned Fingal.  I am using it as an example because I know it and the Dublin 15 area best.  This morning I looked at the properties available for the different categories under the caps.  For a family with two children, I found three properties; for a single adult, I found one property; and for a family with three children, I found two properties.  There is a disconnect between the prevailing market rate for houses and the rate at which the cap is set.  The availability of properties for renting in Dublin is at its lowest level since 2007 according to <i>daft.ie</i>.  There is no relationship between demand and supply.  In addition, recent legislation was introduced to govern bedsits and the quality of private rented accommodation.  In the Dublin area the differential for a single person in contrast to a couple, both with no children, ranges from &euro;175 to &euro;225, yet these two household units are competing for the same properties.  The only rationale for the differential is that it was assumed that single people would move into bedsits, but that is no longer the case.  Have the departmental officials recognised that the cap for a single person in the Dublin area must be increased significantly if he or she is to access housing?</p><p>  The take-up of the rental accommodation scheme, RAS, has been moderate at best and poor in practice.  One of the commitments in the programme for Government was to reduce the criterion in respect of eligibility to six months to move to the RAS.  I have tabled parliamentary questions on this issue and the response from the Department is that this will not be done.  Will the officials confirm that one will be able to move to the RAS after six months and, if not, why not?  Is the programme for Government wrong or is the response from the Department wrong?  A very clear commitment was made in the programme for Government that the criterion in respect of eligibility would be reduced to six months.  NGOs have been campaigning on the issue for three or four years.</p><p>  Senator Marie Moloney raised the question of the exceptional needs payment.  I have come across cases - I do not like to use individual cases, but they illustrate the point - of women who experience domestic violence and have had property damaged in incredibly difficult circumstances.  The landlord refuses to return the deposit and they must go through the ordeal of going to the PRTB and a very long process to get the deposit back.  They have encountered major difficulties in getting the money for another deposit together.  That is what is happening in practice.</p><p>  While I appreciate the report, it is Orwellian when compared with the experiences of individuals, often on very low incomes, who are seeking or are in receipt of rent supplement and trying to access supports.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="13:45:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500009#J00300"><p>I thank the delegation for its presentation.  We are all aware of current financial circumstances and all Departments have attempted to make savings.  I note the following: "The Department currently funds almost 30% of the private rented sector..."; however, three years ago the Department funded 40% of the private rented sector.  Therefore, the proportion of the sector being funded by the Department has fallen very significantly.  I also note that the budget for 2013 is &euro;403 million and we know that it has been reduced from a figure of &euro;500 million a number of years ago.  This is in the face of 250,000 people having become unemployed.  It is inexplicable that the proportion of the rental sector being funded by the Department has fallen so substantially in the face of such increased demand.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.34" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="13:55:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500010#K00200"><p>I shall respond to the last speaker first regarding the reduction in the amounts paid.  Approximately &euro;80 million was the difference between last year's rent supplement expenditure and that of 2011.  Approximately &euro;20 million of that sum was related to rent limits and the remainder was for increase in the minimum contribution.  Budget 2012 increased the minimum contribution that each tenant had to pay which reduced the expenditure on rent supplement.</p><p>  There was also a reduction in the number of people claiming rent supplement.  I want to reiterate that rent supplement is a demand-led scheme.  People are finding accommodation and 48,700 rent supplement claims were awarded last year.  People are securing accommodation and their payments are being met.  Last year there was a drop in the live register of about 45,500 people over the 2011 figures.  A small proportion of people on the live register claim rent supplement, approximately 10% if I remember correctly.  Therefore, I do not accept Senator Hayden's claim that access to the supplement was limited by stealth.  Rent supplement is a demand-led scheme and people will be assisted if they present with a need for accommodation and discretion still exists, particularly for the homeless.  </p><p>  I was responsible for the homeless male and female units in Dublin.  The staff who work in those units do fantastic work in engaging with people who are at risk of becoming homeless.  Part of their work is liaising with organisations such as the Simon Community, Threshold and the Fr. McVerry Trust.  If someone at risk of homelessness is brought to their attention they will try to secure accommodation for them even if discretion is required.  They will find a housing solution for them where local authority or social housing is not in place.  The units also reach prisons and hospitals.  The staff go into prisons and hospitals prior to people being discharged in order to make sure that people have accommodation when they get out.  </p><p>  We are caught between a rock and a hard place when it comes to rent reviews and existing data.  If landlords are lying on their returns to the PRTB then they are lying to the Department and Revenue.  It is difficult for my Department to get a handle on the problem if the tenant is complicit.  It is difficult for the Department to take action if the tenant and landlord are signing declarations on the Department's application forms stating a certain amount is paid. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1172" speakername="Aideen Hayden" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500011#L00200"><p>It is more.  Rents have increased by 10% in south Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.37" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500011#L00300"><p>We are aware that there are particular issues in the Dublin area, mainly because of availability.  I am aware from the Daft report published in the first quarter of the year that Dublin rents have increased 5% year on year.  The increase is almost 6% in the Dublin city centre area.  There are availability issues as the number of properties available for rent has fallen sharply.  Fewer than 2,000 properties are available to rent in April, which was the lowest number of any period in the last eight years.  We have a particular problem in Dublin which we will have to address as part of our rent limit review.  We are conscious of that.</p><p>  Mention was made of the centralised rent units.  We are aware that there have been issues in relation to the administration of those rents.  They were particularly based in the Dublin area and were established to meet a particular need and problem.  On the transfer of the community welfare service into the Department, 27 temporary CWOs were lost and the number of claims increased substantially by approximately 62%.  It is not ideal and we are looking at the mechanisms around how we process rent claims.  The majority of claims are processed in small hubs where a person seeking rent supplement can come in and hand in an application which can be checked to ensure all necessary documentation is being provided.  The person can also receive any necessary support in terms of processing a claim.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500011#L00400"><p>On that, someone referred earlier to waiting times, etc.  The advantage of having a decision made locally was that there were no waiting times.  Decisions were made very quickly.  Someone looked at a form and if a person did not have relevant documentation, he or she could be helped there and then to complete the application.  There are real advantages to that system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.39" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500011#L00500"><p>Exactly.  We appreciate that and are looking at it.  The Department has merged staff from the former employment and community services of F&Aacute;S and the community welfare service of the HSE.  Approximately 1,700 staff have merged in with the existing staff of the Department and we are examining a more integrated service for the customer under the auspices of the new Intreo model which is being rolled out.  Approximately ten Intreo centres have been developed and we are in the process of putting in place Intreo services in 33 other centres.  One aspect of that is an integrated reception area.  If someone comes in to access any of the Department's services, including rent supplement, he or she will be met at reception.  He or she will be able to access a form and if he or she needs support to complete it, he or she will get it.  The form will be accepted and processed through the back office.  That is where the service is moving to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" time="14:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500011#L00600"><p>I will be brief as much of what I wanted to raise has been raised by other speakers.  I want to repeat the issue about making the payment directly to landlords.  I reiterate that there is a significant benefit in doing that.  It means that someone does not fall into significant arrears.  I urge the Department to ensure that continues through whatever process is required to be put in place.  It needs to happen.</p><p>  The rent cap causes significant problems for me in County Roscommon.  While Ms Faughnan makes reference to situations where one is adjoining another town, what she said does not happen in reality.  We have one rent cap for County Roscommon and it applies equally in Monksland in the south of the county, which is literally the distance of the white line in the middle of the road from the town of Athlone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500012#M00200"><p>The number of people receiving rent supplement may have reduced in recent years.  Why is there a drop and to what extent, taking into account people in the rental accommodation scheme?  The Minister is clamping down on social welfare fraud.  Is there any such initiative on rent supplement?  There may be arrangements whereby people fraudulently receive a rent payment.  If someone in a particular part of the country cannot get a property under the rent cap, are they given any help in sourcing accommodation by the Department?  What is the situation in Britain for similar payments?  Do they have the same set up as us?</p><p>  If the top-up problem is endemic, should they be brought into the open so that top-ups are allowed?  There could be set payments according to the market, with the analysis the Department does, but we could also allow top-ups as they are happening anyway.  Has the Department considered this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1132" speakername="Marie Moloney" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500012#M00300"><p>I thank the officials of the Department for attending and providing responses.  We may not agree with all of the responses but the officials made an effort to come in and talk to us.  I ask Ms Faughnan to acknowledge that the problem is not Dublin-based.  She continually referred to a problem in Dublin but there is life beyond the Red Cow.  The problems were articulated by other members.</p><p>  Does Ms Faughnan accept that top ups are taking place?  Ms Faughnan referred to discretionary payments but that is subject to the approval of the Minister and takes time.  Committee members, who are trying to help clients, cannot get information because it is unavailable to us.  We cannot tell our clients what is happening.</p><p>  Ms Faughnan referred to a duty of care to the taxpayer but I put it to her that she has a duty of care to the vulnerable as well.  These people are left unemployed, with no money to pay rent.  What can we do?  We cannot drive them out of the community.  Ms Faughnan said that if accommodation beneath the rent cap is not available in that community, there is nothing the Department can do.  However, we must keep people in the community as children may be established in schools and parents may be working in the community and involved in groups and organisations.  We cannot drive people out of an area they are used to living in.  We have a duty of care to those people as well.  We cannot put more financial pressure on them by driving them out so that they must buy a car and incur petrol and diesel expenses going to the local town.</p><p>  Ms Faughnan said she had local information on the ground but the feedback we receive suggests the Department does not have a handle on what is going on.  There is no way the cap reflects rents in the area.  Every committee member has said that but the Department does not seem to take that on board.  When I rudely interrupted Ms Faughnan, as the Chairman pointed out, it was to say the PRTB reflects the rents minus the top-up.  The PRTB is not going to tell about the top-up, nor is the tenant in case the accommodation is lost.  There is no record of it and the landlords do not have to pay tax on the top-up because it does not exist.  I thank the witnesses for attending and I appreciate their comments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:15:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500012#M00400"><p>I welcome the fact that new rental limits will be announced in June.  I hope that people see sense, particularly in my area.  I presume the overall rent supplement budget or envelope within the Department cannot be breached if new rental limits are accepted.  If the cap goes up in one area, does it go down in another area?  How will the new rental limits be estimated within the Department or is it done solely on the cost of property?</p><p>  The following issue with rent supplement has arisen a number of times and in most cases the community welfare officer has been willing to budge.  It applies to single men, in particular, who have overnight access or weekend access to their children but cannot get rent allowance for a property bigger than a single bedsit.  Is there a directive in respect of single men with court order access to their children?</p> <p> My other issue relates to the fact that there are not as many single-bedroom properties available in the city.  I presume the situation is the same in rural Ireland.  Sometimes, the only available property in an area is a two-bedroom one.  In such a case, does a community welfare officer have discretion to allow a person to move into that property, which is normally capped for people with children?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.46" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500013#N00200"><p>I wish to address Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh's question on whether a fixed amount of money is available for rent supplement in this year's budget.  How would any increase in the caps associated with a review be decided?  Is there scope for an increase?  In comparison, if 1,000 people are made redundant, God forbid, the Department must find social welfare payments for them.  If market rents increase and people need additional money, it ought to be found.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.47" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500013#N00300"><p>Deputy Naughten referred to the Roscommon area.  We are aware of the issues, as our staff on the ground have fed them back to us.  We will examine them as part of the review.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1177" speakername="Denis Naughten" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500013#N00400"><p>They have been feeding in for a long time.  I am not referring to today or yesterday - this situation has been ongoing for a number of years.  Staff have been feeding it in since the cap was introduced.  It has caused significant hardship.  Despite all of the reviews, nothing has happened.  Will Ms Faughnan assure me that something will happen this time?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.49" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500013#N00500"><p>We will definitely feed that information back into the review this time.  We can set out the current limits.  It might also be useful for the Deputy if, ahead of the rent review, we provided information on the rent supplement tenants who are in receipt of support in the area.</p><p>  I reassure Senator Moloney that we are aware of every area in the country.  The staff based in Sligo know the highways and byways of Ireland through their work.  We are aware of the county borders and that some discretion is being applied in that regard.  We will take the various comments on board as part of the review, as this is an important matter.  Under law, discretion is nominally applied on the Minister's behalf.  Each local member of staff has that discretion.  He or she need not go up the line seeking approval.  An immediate response is possible.</p><p>  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh mentioned our budgetary envelope.  The caps are set in line with the market.  When we conduct our research and feed information in, we set a level that we believe is reasonable in terms of the market.  We do not just bear in mind the taxpayer.  We in the Department are conscious of the fact that we are the front-line support for the country's many vulnerable people.  We take this responsibility seriously.</p><p>  In terms of recipients, there has been a decrease in customer numbers.  In 2010, there were more than 97,000 rent supplement recipients.  In April of this year, the number was 85,800.  This has reduced the pressure on our budgetary envelope as part of the Estimates process.  It is a demand-led scheme.  If our budget must be extended, we will negotiate with the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform.</p><p>  Deputy &Oacute; Snodaigh raised the issue of single men in split parenting arrangements.  Every claim for rent supplement is determined with regard to an applicant's circumstances.  Our staff - formerly CWOs - would engage with the person seeking the payment.  We must be satisfied that whatever rental accommodation the person is seeking is suited to the residential needs of the applicant and his or her claimant.  Due to a large number of marriage and relationship break-ups, there are split parenting arrangements.  If a married or cohabiting couple has split, a man or woman is residing in the family home and the other partner, who is working and renting a two-bedroom or three-bedroom house or apartment, has visiting or access rights but then loses his or her job, we will not make his or her situation any worse.  We will meet the accommodation needs.</p><p>  Although I would not call it a trend, we are aware of some instances of single men seeking to leave their family homes and asking us for two-bedroom accommodation where they have no history of access arrangements in respect of their children.</p><p>  We must be aware of various situations.  Staff engage with customers, explore the issues and examine housing needs, particularly those of the children involved.  Each case is decided on its merits.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500013#N00600"><p>Even if the father does not have a tradition of access, surely it should be encouraged for the sake of the child.  Obviously, there are exceptions to this general rule.  Should the Department&rsquo;s attitude not be that it is better for everyone concerned to facilitate the other parent, even if the access arrangements have not been used previously?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.51" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500013#N00700"><p>Yes.  It is a question of people showing us proof of their access arrangements.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.52" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500013#N00800"><p>In some cases, they do not have access arrangements.  They must go to court to get them.  If a person is in a one-bedroom flat, he or she cannot get larger accommodation to accommodate his or her children.  The person has gone to court because he or she wants to play a role, yet is not allowed to have his or her children in a single-bedroom flat, particularly if the case is one of the many instances of a father and daughter.  The only option is to find a larger flat.  It is at this point that there seems to be a blockage in the system.</p><p>  It should not be down to us to negotiate the hassle or to encourage a CWO to reconsider a case.  We are seeing more such cases.  It is a difficult situation for everyone.  While I hope that it is a temporary arrangement for people, the staff - formerly CWOs - should take greater cognisance of the fact that, if people go to court and win overnight access, they should be accommodated inasmuch as is possible until their situations change again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.53" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="14:25:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500013#N00900"><p>Yes.  That one parent is in receipt of rent supplement does not automatically debar the other person from receiving rent supplement.  Each case is decided on its merits.</p><p>  Fraud was mentioned.  Control is an integral part of all of our schemes' maintenance, including rent supplement.  Generally, we conduct a biannual review of all rent supplement claims and maintain ongoing contact within the Department to ensure that the correct amounts are being paid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1028" speakername="Aengus &Oacute; Snodaigh" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500014#O00200"><p>Would Ms Faughnan consider engaging in a sting operation, such as what Deputy Brendan Ryan stated, and visiting some landlords to see what they are suggesting to people?  The fraud level, at 2.4%, is low; clients may not be ripping off the Department, but there is fraud in the sense that the documentation landlords and tenants are signing does not mention a top-up payment.  I suggest publicity on the possibility fraud is one approach to take.  Since the change in the caps, those who have been paying have had to top up the top-up payment, which is putting them in dire straits because there is no alternative available for them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.56" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500014#O00300"><p>We appreciate that.  The difficulty is trying to prove it when the landlord and the tenant are complicit.  We will take on board the Deputy's suggestion of publicising and highlighting the fact that the top-up payment is fraudulent.</p><p>  Anti-social behaviour in social housing is a major problem, but the Department does not have a relationship with the landlord and tenant behaviour is a matter for the landlord in the first instance.  Landlords can avail of the dispute mechanism of the Private Residential Tenancies Board and have recourse to the Garda in the matter.  Again, it is imperative to move responsibility to the local authorities because they have the anti-social element built in as part of the tenancy arrangements with their tenants.  The social welfare legislation provides that if the Department is notified of anti-social behaviour and the tenancy is affected, we stop the payment of rent supplement payment in these instances.</p><p>  The Chairman asked about international policy, particularly in Northern Ireland.  If a person decides to move into a property for which the rent is higher than the rate set, he or she pays the difference and it is a personal choice.  If we were to out top-up payments, would the rent demands being made by landlords just keep rising to try to meet what we were setting?  There would be a risk in doing this.</p><p>  We do not source accommodation for tenants.  They source it in advance of coming to us.  Let me give an example.  When the rent limits are reviewed and the landlord will not agree to reduce the rent, the tenant and community welfare service staff sit down and discuss the matter and try to come up with a solution.  We would never make somebody homeless as a result.  We work with him or her to try to come up with a solution that meets their particular needs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500014#O00400"><p>This is a general question addressed to Ms Faughnan.  In terms of the review under way, does she believe she will be able to address all of the issues raised today?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.58" speakerid="unknown" error="nomatch" speakername="Ms Helen Faughnan" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500014#O00500"><p>We hope to take on board everything that has been said today on the rent limit review.  It is a very practical review and locally based.  We see what is available within the limits and what can be achieved through negotiation.  Accommodation is available.  Some 50,000 people secured accommodation last year.  We hope the new rent limit review will address the issues raised because of the changes in the rental market of which we are aware in Dublin and elsewhere, particularly on the borders.  Last November my officials and I briefed Oireachtas Members on the issue of rent supplement, reviews and so on.  If members of the committee would find it helpful, we could organise another briefing session to take them through the rent limit review, the findings of which we will make available to all Oireachtas Members.  Following its publication, we can make a presentation and answer questions on issues arising from it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="14:35:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/EDJ2013051500014#O00600"><p>I thank Ms Faughnan and her colleagues for briefing us so comprehensively.  We may raise outstanding issues with the Minister.  I very much welcome the fact that Ms Faughnan will brief us on the findings of the review when they are available.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.61" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="">Committee on Finance, Public Expenditure and Reform: Select Sub-Committee on Public Expenditure and Reform</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.62" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 14:00</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.64" nospeaker="true" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500002#A00100">Construction Contracts Bill 2010: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B00200"><p>I call the meeting to order.  I welcome the Minister of State, Deputy Brian Hayes, and his officials before the committee this afternoon.  The purpose of the meeting is to consider the Construction Contracts Bill 2010 from the Seanad.  The Bill was referred to the select sub-committee by D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann on 20 June 2012.  Is it agreed to conclude consideration of the Bill today if possible?  Agreed.  I accept some changes have been made to the Bill but I propose that we adjourn at approximately 4.25 p.m. and assess progress at that stage.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  I ask all members, the Minister of State and his officials, and those in the Gallery to switch off their mobile telephones as they will interfere with proceedings if they are not switched off.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B00500"><p>Amendment No. 1 has been ruled out of order as it is outside the scope of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B00600"><p>I am not happy with that.  Could you explain the reason?  The amendment is an essential change to the Bill to deal with those who supply bespoke materials as part of a construction contract.  Throughout the process everyone has spoken about including this element in the legislation.  I received the letter stating the amendment is outside the scope of the Bill.  Will you explain to me in non-technical language the reason we cannot deal with the issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.69" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B00700"><p>The purpose of the Construction Contracts Bill is simple.  The Title says it all, namely, that its purpose is to regulate payments under construction contracts and to provide for related matters.  The Bill does not cover the following: the supply and-or delivery of materials under construction contracts, registered employment agreements, bonds or the provision of payments, securities or insurance, apprenticeship schemes, payments of expenses, or decisions of disputes adjudicator.  Specifically on Deputy Fleming&rsquo;s amendment and Deputy McDonald&rsquo;s amendment No. 7, the proposal to extend the scope of the Bill to include the supply of construction material does not fit with the Bill&rsquo;s concerns on the regulation of payments under construction contracts.  It does not apply to the delivery of supplies of goods under construction contract.  Therefore, the amendments are outside the scope of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B00800"><p>I do not understand that because we are talking about construction contracts and related matters.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.71" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B00900"><p>The Deputy is better aware of Standing Orders than I.  I do not have to engage in any further explanation on the matter and I decide not to do so.  I will now proceed on the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01000"><p>That is most unfair.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.73" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01100"><p>The Deputy can discuss the matter with me outside of the meeting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01200"><p>This is Committee Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.75" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01300"><p>The Deputy has been a member of this House for longer than I have and he knows the rules.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.76" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01400"><p>My amendment No. 3 has been ruled out of order.  I am puzzled by that because in May 2012 on Second Stage, the Minister of State, Deputy Hayes, said that having examined similar legislation in other jurisdictions, he could see the merit of broadening the scope of the legislation to include bespoke construction supply contracts.  I, too, would like an explanation as to why our amendments have been ruled out of order.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.77" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01500"><p>The best way to facilitate this is that, as I have done on other occasions, when we move to discuss the section of the Bill in its entirety, the Deputy can then introduce those two matters.  I will afford the same opportunity to Deputy Fleming at that time rather than discussing the matter now.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01600"><p>I will take the opportunity to discuss the matter at that time also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01800"><p>I move amendment No. 2:<blockquote><br />In page 4, subsection (1), line 20, to delete paragraph (<i>g</i>).</blockquote>The amendment provides for the exclusion of mining and drilling operations from the scope of the Bill.  Currently section 1(1)(<i>g</i>) includes mining and exploration as a construction activity.  These activities should not have been included because similar activities are specifically excluded from the definition of construction activities under EU Directive 2004/18/EC, which relates to procurement procedures for the award of public award contracts.  It was not the intention to include such activities as it is our understanding that there is no evidence of payment disputes in these sectors.  In any event, given the potential of such sectors, a further regulatory impact analysis would be required before they would be considered for inclusion.  It is accepted that when this provision was included, it was done in error, given the fact the sectors are uniquely dealt with, and even if one were to deal with this, it would require a wider exploration than the issues we examined which were exclusively construction related at the time of the regulatory impact statement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B01900"><p>I am even more puzzled now as to why we had contracts relating to drilling and extraction of oil included in the Bill and the Minister of State has chosen to remove them, but what we thought was germane and essential to the Bill &ndash; people supplying quarried material, concrete materials and items fundamental to the construction of the project at hand - cannot be covered.  The legislation is seriously deficient.  All the complaints I have received, on which I spoke at length on Second Stage, related to people who supplied tarmacadam, quarried material, ready-mix concrete and other such materials and they cannot get paid because their materials were bespoke and specific to the particular projects.  The products cannot be removed if the supplier is not paid.  What is the purpose of the legislation if it does not cover some of the people most affected?  While I accept tradesmen and those working on construction contracts must also be paid, what is the purpose of the legislation if a person who supplied quarried material, aggregate, ready-mix concrete and tarmacadam get no protection whatever under the legislation?  I do not understand the purpose of the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B02000"><p>I accept the Minister of State's explanation for the removal of drilling and the extraction of oil or natural gas from the legislation.  He has explained that fairly and well.  However, I do not understand why bespoke materials do not come under the scope of the legislation.  The Minister of State indicated on Second Stage that he understood that it would be a necessary measure and that he was minded to consider it and to expand the scope of the legislation.  It will make a nonsense of the new measures if suppliers and contractors who provide bespoke materials find themselves burnt and unable to get a remedy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B02100"><p>Does Deputy Twomey wish to speak?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.84" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B02200"><p>No, I will speak on section 1.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500003#B02300"><p>There is broad acceptance of the amendment proposed, but in fairness to Deputies Fleming and McDonald I should reply to the issues they raised, as it is a key issue that we must debate.  That is the purpose of Committee Stage.  It is a good thing.</p><p>  Four outstanding issues emerged from the regulatory impact statement.  Members will see that the amendments I proposed, which broadly have the support of the House, reflect the views expressed in the Second Stage debate.  Three of the four outstanding issues have been resolved.  The one issue that was raised, in fairness to Deputies Fleming and McDonald and other colleagues, was bespoke suppliers.  We must have the debate.  I did not rule the amendment out of order.  That is a matter for the Chairman and I respect his ruling.  However, it is an important debate that we must have.  If we can find a solution to it, I am all ears.  We will take as long as we like to deal with the Bill.  If members wish to spend ten months talking about the issue, that is fine with me.  I have always taken a co-operative approach to the Bill, as Deputies are aware.  The Bill is not the preserve of the Government as it was introduced by Senator Quinn.  We have looked closely at the issue of bespoke suppliers.  We have examined international experience and the experience in this country.  I regret that we have been unable to include it in the current phase of the Bill.  However, it is not as difficult as people say.  The issue of supply and install is covered in the Bill.  In other words, if I as part of a contract ask someone to design and install a staircase, as far as we are concerned, that is covered in the Bill and it is allowable.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.87" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C00200"><p>Before I call Deputies Fleming and McDonald, while it might not be the standard operating procedure of the committee, I acknowledge the presence in the public gallery of Senator Quinn, the originator of the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C00300"><p>I hear what the Minister of State is saying.  We all have a considerable amount of material on this legislation, which affects people's livelihoods, with people going out of business if they are not paid for work.  We have letters from the Irish Concrete Federation, the Irish Small and Medium Enterprises Association, and several other bodies, indicating their preference to have bespoke materials included.  Was the industry aware before we became aware that our amendments on the bespoke issue would be ruled out of order?  Was that generally known in the industry or was it news today?</p><p>  The Minister of State has suggested that if we can come up with a more refined and specific wording-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.89" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C00400"><p>We will look at it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C00500"><p>-----for Report Stage, he will consider it.  I signal my intention to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.91" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C00600"><p>From the outset, I have had a very open approach to the Bill, because it is not my Bill.  When it returns to the Seanad, I will not be taking it and it will be a matter for Senator Quinn to take forward.  The Government has been really committed to trying to get this to work.  However, it must not extend it so far beyond the original objective that it becomes inoperable and a much bigger concept.  That has always been my <i>modus operandi</i> and I hope the Deputy accepts that.  It may be possible to phrase appropriate amendments, but we have not found a solution to it.  If it requires more conversations between our officials and colleagues in advance, I have no difficulty in going through those arguments with them.  That is open to them.</p><p>  I cannot speak for the industry representatives.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C00700"><p>Were they aware?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.93" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C00800"><p>I cannot comment on whether they were aware.  The date for this committee meeting was set, amendments were tabled by colleagues and we tabled our amendments.  It is not a question of whether they could have been aware of it one way or another.  When they were published they were in the public domain.  I fully accept there is a very strong view on the issue.  I still have an open view on it and this might be more fruitfully advanced through some detailed conversations between now and Report Stage to see if we can sort it out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C00900"><p>We should avail of that opportunity.  I do not accept the logic of the Minister of State's argument on broadening the scope of the legislation so much that it becomes a catch-all.  It is very clear that we are discussing bespoke materials for construction projects.  If the Minister of State has an open mind on the matter, we should certainly use the time between now and Report Stage to hammer out the wording.  He says it is implicit in the legislation that, for example, a staircase-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.95" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01000"><p>Supply and install.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01100"><p>Yes, supply and install.  He suggests that therefore the issue of bespoke materials is covered implicitly in the legislation.  We want to get to an explicit articulation of that.  For my part, I would be more than happy to take up the opportunity to find that wording.  We will certainly be tabling this amendment again on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.97" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01200"><p>We should consider both ends of the spectrum.  At one end are cases such as that of specially designed and treated steel supports for a large structure that were created, angled, designed, cast, etc., for a specific structure and could not conceivably be used for any other structure.  The Minister of State said they would be included if they were manufactured by the same company.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.98" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01300"><p>If they are installed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01400"><p>However, if they are manufactured by one company and installed by a separate company, the installation company is covered by the legislation, but the people who made them are not.  That is one end where I believe it would be clear that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01500"><p>That could be put into a contract.  The great dilemma in this area arises as a result of the lack of contracts.  That is why we are here discussing the Bill.  There is nothing to stop the subcontractor as part of that overall contract putting that as a condition.  That would mean that if one designs and installs the structure, it is totally operable within the context of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.101" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01600"><p>I understand.  However, if some solution is not found, the concern is that the manufacturer will not be covered.  It seems to me that we would like to find a way for the manufacturer of such a clearly expensive, bespoke piece of kit to be covered.  I can understand that the official concern is over someone who argues that the paint he or she created is also bespoke because it contains a little bit of coloured fleck, and obviously judgment calls need to be made in such cases.  Is it the Minister of State's intention to accept an amendment if we can find a wording to cover items that are clearly a one-off and could not be used for anything else?  If these people do not get paid they have just lost the money.  We are looking for something that would cover such products.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.102" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01700"><p>I wish to clarify this.  Is there a level of confusion between manufacturer and supplier where a builder provider provides a material without being its manufacturer?  The manufacturer could be four or five times removed from the building site.  Is the Deputy referring to the supplier?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.103" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01800"><p>No, but that is also a fair point.  We are differentiating between the person who installs the item and the person who supplies or manufactures it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.104" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C01900"><p>I believe the debate is changing, if we are really being honest about this.  Deputy Fleming had submitted an amendment on bespoke materials.  Bespoke is not similar to ready-mixed concrete, is it?  I understand the concrete lobby is seeking to have this included.  However, let us be honest.  That is not bespoke or one-off.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.105" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C02000"><p>It could be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C02100"><p>It is not the same thing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.107" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C02200"><p>No, it is not the same thing, but it could be.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.108" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500004#C02300"><p>We need to be honest about what we are saying.  Deputy McDonald reminded me about what I undertook.  It is always good to read what one said about a year and a half ago.  It is always good to put it on the record - she might do it herself the odd time.  At the time we looked at the question of bespoke items.  We have looked at this question and it is difficult.  We need to make a distinction, as I did on that occasion, between something that is designed for a specific purpose, as Deputy Donnelly set out, and something that might be described as irretrievable after its installation.  Concrete is irretrievable once it is put into a building.  Between now and Report Stage the invitation is there to sit down with my officials and go through the issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D00200"><p>Will the Minister of State examine the issue of retention of title?  I remember a case from 30 years ago involving a group of pig farmers who sold pigs to a factory which went into liquidation.  Initially they were told by the liquidators that because the pigs had been processed into bacon they were no longer entitled to payment, but they identified the sides of bacon in the factory and the High Court stated they retained title even though a side of bacon is not a pig.  By the same token, the Irish Concrete Federation argues that when concrete and steel are set the concrete is no longer concrete as it was sold, but the elements are still identifiable as concrete and steel.  Following a retention of title court case from 30 years ago, which was decided by Ms Justice McGuinness, concrete and steel are identifiable even though they have changed.  Has the Minister of State considered this as a solution to this issue?  A simple contract could allow the concrete company to retain title in a very simple manner.  Perhaps we could consider this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.111" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1027" speakername="Peter Mathews" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D00300"><p>My experience in validating disbursements for interim payments on contracts is that great reliance is placed on the work of quantity surveyors who are able to disaggregate what becomes set in concrete.  They are able to separate the steel element, the concrete element and other parts of the physical delivery, and the physical constituent parts of the practical completion of the contract.  They would be able to disaggregate back to the source supplying contractors.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D00400"><p>With regard to amendments tabled by Opposition members, as we move towards Report Stage I suggest we engage with the Bills Office to seek assistance and support to see how to draft amendments so they will not be ruled out of order.  Rather than the submission of amendments, I suggest more engagement with the Bills Office.  I know this is an important issue but I must deal with the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.113" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D00500"><p>From studying this in recent years I have learned about the complete lack of construction contracts in Ireland.  There is poor practice throughout the industry with regard to regulating contracts and ensuring we have enforceable contracts.  One of the reasons the Bill was presented by Senator Quinn and others was that people had been burned substantially.  On an all-party basis we agreed this can never happen again and that we needed to put the industry on a new footing where proper enforceable contracts would be in place and fairness would be applied through proper adjudication.  One of the purposes of the Bill is that once it is established it will lead to better practice in the industry.  It is this better practice which I expect will result in more supply and install elements in contracts.  We will also have recourse to these contracts, which previously did not exist.  The Bill will set a new standard and the industry will have to respond to it in a way that has not happened in the past.</p><p>  With regard to the point raised by Deputy Twomey, he is correct that title is a fundamental issue, but it is not my job to decide the issue of title.  It is a larger issue and I suspect the Minister for Justice and Equality will have a view on it.  The legal issue is clear in that if something is not installed and fixed it is retrievable, in that it belongs to the person who supplied it.  Once it is installed and fixed it really is an essential part of the property and the questions of beneficial ownership and the title of the property come into being.</p><p>  This is another example of the point I made earlier.  If we extend the Bill it will become something it is not at present.  The intention of Senator Quinn's Bill is to resolve a problem quickly, this problem being the plight of subcontractors and ensuring people are paid on time.  The real problem in the industry is that people are not paid on time, and we know this.  People were burned substantially as a result of what occurred in the crash.  If we make a fundamental change on title it will become a wider Bill.  This is my dilemma.  It would require five or six Ministers across five or six Departments, including the Departments of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation and Justice and Equality.  It has taken a long time to get the Bill this far and I want to get it over the line to ensure it is applicable for a generation of people who need it.  I accept that title is a problematic issue.  If something is fixed and installed it is part and parcel of the existing current title of the owner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D00600"><p>I must interrupt the Minister of State, because it is my job to get the Bill over the line this afternoon if I can.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D00800"><p>Amendment No. 3 has been ruled out of order as it is outside the scope of the Bill but Deputy O'Donnell may discuss the issue when we are discussing the section if he wishes to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D00900"><p>I move amendment No. 4:<blockquote><br />In page 4, subsection (1), line 33, to delete &quot;Finance&quot; and substitute &quot;Public Expenditure and Reform&quot;.</blockquote>This amendment allocates responsibility for policy and administration of legislation to the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform.  This is a standard provision.  He is my boss.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D01100"><p>Amendments Nos. 5, 13 and 38 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.121" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500005#D01200"><p>I move amendment No. 5:<blockquote><br />In page 4, subsection (1), between lines 42 and 43, to insert the following:&quot; &quot;social contract clause&rdquo; means a clause that obliges an executing party to&mdash;<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) employ some unemployed persons who are on the live register and who are under 25 years of age, and<br />(<i>b</i>) employ some persons who are long term unemployed;&quot;.</blockquote></blockquote>The intention of the amendment is to include a social contract clause in contracts with the purpose of ensuring, particularly in an era with high unemployment, youth unemployment and long-term unemployment, that an opportunity is provided in major contracts for such people to get work.  In other jurisdictions provision is made for this.  I tabled a parliamentary question on this topic some time ago and received a reply that this could displace older workers with more experience.</p><p>  This is also linked to an issue of which the Minister of State is very well aware, which is the number of people who have not finished their apprenticeships in various trades because firms went out of business and many people were left high and dry.  F&Aacute;S has been trying to make some arrangements to recognise the final phases of apprenticeships and get training and experience for the people involved.  We all have constituents who emigrated a few months short of their final apprenticeship qualifications.  There is no employment here, but they are not able to get their papers to take up employment in other countries.</p><p>  Everybody recognises that the biggest problem we have in Ireland, leaving aside the country's financial affairs, is the employment issue, particularly the employment of young people and the growing number of young people who are unemployed.  We must do something concrete - I apologise for using the pun again; I will try to think of a different phrase when I next speak.  We must do something definite, particular or specific to help young unemployed people not only complete their apprenticeships but get work and practical experience.  I know this will lead to a cost for tendering companies but if it is part of the tender document everybody will tender on an equal footing and no company or business will be at a disadvantage.  I have not been specific about percentages, numbers or turnover and I am just asking the Minister of State to open the door to examining the issue.  Most people would agree we are trying to establish a worthwhile principle.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.123" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500006#E00200"><p>I will bring the Deputy in on the other ones while we are at it, if he wishes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.124" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500006#E00300"><p>That is the point I wanted to make.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500006#E00400"><p>I will now call the Minister of State to respond to amendment No. 5.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500006#E00500"><p>Deputy McDonald has one as well.  It is the same issue.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500006#E00600"><p>Does Deputy McDonald wish to comment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500006#E00700"><p>They are grouped together so I shall discuss the amendment but will not move it until later.  It is important that the social clause is referenced in the legislation.  The Minister will see that my amendment is cast more broadly than that of Deputy Fleming.  It therefore addresses the issue of long-term unemployment, but also addresses apprenticeships, compliance with fair employment, equality and anti-discrimination legislation, and compliance with the green public procurement national action plan.  We have modelled this on the clause included for the A5 project.  There is a real opportunity in public procurement to achieve not just efficiency and value for money but a number of other key social objectives.  The most obvious being the need for employment and training opportunities for younger people as well as for long-term unemployed persons.</p><p>  Under the EU directives there are specific rules and regulations in respect of public procurement.  However, in other jurisdictions they have quite successfully managed to knit key social requirements and objectives into the public procurement processes.  We need to move in that direction here.  </p><p>  In March, I received a response from the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, Deputy Howlin, in which he told me something I already knew.  He said that his Department and the National Procurement Service are examining the use of social clauses as a means of supporting activation.  I am aware that that important work is under way and I am keen to support it.  I would like to see this kind of provision contained in this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.129" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500006#E00800"><p>I cannot anticipate what the Minister of State will say about this matter, but all of us would like to see a situation whereby people finishing their apprenticeships are facilitated.  In addition, we also want to see unemployed young people getting an opportunity to work and long-term unemployed people getting a chance to re-enter the workforce, particularly in a sector where they may previously have been employed.  There is a danger, however, that we might be seeking to solve all the problems of the construction sector in this Bill.  Those currently employed in the construction sector would not thank us if their jobs were put at risk to facilitate these amendments.  If we can put construction on a sound footing, with people getting paid for the work they are doing, surely that in itself is a step in the right direction to facilitate the issues of concern.  If we stitch too much into this Bill we may run the risk of undermining its core objective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.130" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500006#E00900"><p>I will put on record the official reply and we can then have a discussion about it.  I am addressing amendments Nos. 5, 13 and 38.  While there are merits in the Deputy's proposals, they are focused on issues that are really outside the scope of this legislation.  This Bill is designed to address failures to pay construction sector contractors, subcontractors and sub-subcontractors who have completed work to the required standard on construction projects.  The Bill will address these issues by providing statutory arrangements concerning payment under construction contracts, including providing for interim payments and, second, by introducing a new mechanism for the swift resolution of payment disputes through a process of adjudication.</p><p>  The manner of social clauses in public contracts is something that I am closely examining.  The inclusion of a social clause in all public procurement contracts could require, for example, that a quota of long-term unemployed be employed in the delivery of a contract.  It must be said that an initiative along these lines would pose a number of risks.   In the current economic climate and, in particular, bearing in mind the difficulties in the construction sector, businesses have for obvious reasons been reducing their existing workforces rather than taking on new employees.  Consequently, it would be expected that where a business is awarded a public contract, the work would be carried out by the existing employees of that business.  In such circumstances a social clause requiring that a number of long-term unemployed be employed in delivering a public contract, could either impose an additional cost on SMEs that they may not be able to afford, or result in an employee of the supplier being let go in favour of a long-term unemployed person.  </p><p>  The Government is deploying a wide range of measures to facilitate job creation and support labour activation measures, with a particular emphasis on assisting long-term unemployed people.  Obviously, the main purpose of public procurement is to ensure that goods, services and works are purchased by the State in a manner that is legal, transparent and of high probity.  Our key requirement is the achievement of value for money.  However, I am examining the use of social clauses as an additional means of supporting activation.  We are seeking to identify the scope for the use of social clauses in parts of the capital area in particular.</p><p>  Taking Deputy Creed's point, we do not think it is applicable or germane to the Bill, but I do see that there is merit in the proposal.  I have already said that to Deputy McDonald when we discussed this in the House some time ago.  The matter was also raised in the House recently by way of a Topical Issue.  The question is how we do it and doing it in the most sensible way possible.  Deputy McDonald spoke about the A5, which was something that her own colleague, Minister Murphy, put into the contracts.  He put it into the A5 contract, but it was not put into a specific piece of legislation and was not done as an application throughout construction.  It was not done for capital construction, but for a specific project.</p><p>  All that shows that social clauses are applicable, workable and effective if one specifies a project or group of projects.  It will then be clear for those going into public procurement that this will be a condition of the contract because we will not get through EU procurement law unless that is clear.  One cannot discriminate against long-term unemployed people in Poland, Ireland, Britain or wherever, so we must set a very clear, level playing pitch.  The way to do that is to set it upfront as a clear policy of the Government that we want to see social clauses in an area of capital projects.</p><p>  We are in discussions with the National Development Finance Agency concerning the next devolved schools programme whereby, as a specific aspect of that contract, a social clause would apply.  We would make it a condition of awarding those contracts that somewhere in the region of 10% of the people involved would come from the long-term unemployed.  We think that is a more sensible way to approach this.  I am not talking about public private partnerships, but about a bundle that would be delivered through the NDFA's funding model for the purposes of schools development.  </p><p>  The key issue is one of monitoring and enforcement.  There is no point in having a big, laudable 10% of these jobs going to people who are long-term unemployed construction workers with particular skills, unless it is monitored and enforceable.  We must ensure that that can happen.  We want to see progress here and I can reliably tell the committee that we are making progress in this regard. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.133" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500007#F00300"><p>Amendments Nos. 6 and 14 to 19, inclusive, are related and will be discussed together.  Amendments Nos. 15 to 19, inclusive, are alternatives to amendment No. 14.  Amendment No. 16 is an alternative to amendment No. 15 and amendment No. 19 is an alternative to 18.  I hope Deputies are able to follow that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.134" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500007#F00400"><p>Amendments Nos. 6, 15, 17 and 18 are grouped.  I move amendment No. 6:<blockquote><br />In page 4, subsection (1), to delete lines 43 and 44 and in page 5, to delete lines 1 to 4.</blockquote>This is one of the main issues that was raised in the consultation process that formed part of the regulatory impact assessment.  I recognise the work of Deputies Fleming and McDonald who were part of that regulatory assessment.  It has been some time since we met but the usefulness of going through all these major issues with a range of people in the construction area, big and small, was very good in teasing out some of the issues before we got to Committee Stage.  I thank colleagues here and people in the industry for their involvement in that.</p><p>  The regulatory impact assessment examined the experience of adjudication in other jurisdictions and found that the majority of disputes that used such processes were for contracts valued somewhere between &euro;13,000 and &euro;65,000.  Therefore, the regulatory impact assessment concluded that these thresholds were too high and should be reviewed or removed.  The amendment I am putting forward today removes the current thresholds in the Bill, which are &euro;200,000 for private contracts and &euro;50,000 for public contracts, and replaces them with a single contract threshold of &euro;10,000.</p><p>  There has been some confusion as to what the threshold will relate.  The new threshold of &euro;10,000 relates to the overall contract value.  Therefore, subcontractors will be free to refer payment disputes relating to lesser amounts to adjudication.  For example, if a contract with an overall value of &euro;11,000 gives rise to a payment dispute of &euro;1,000, this can form part of the adjudication process once the overall contract is more than &euro;10,000.  When Senator Quinn placed the Bill and put inserted those thresholds, he realised within a short time that the international experience is to have very limited thresholds so that this would apply to virtually everybody in the industry.  We have done that by removing the &euro;200,000 and &euro;50,000 thresholds on public and private contracts and we have now a single threshold of &euro;10,000.  It is not that it applies to subcontractors with &euro;10,000 or more.  On the contrary, if the total value is in excess of &euro;10,000, even though I have a dispute regarding a sum less than &euro;10,000, I can seek adjudication on that.  This is one of the major issues that came out of the arbitration process, the regulatory impact assessment and the D&aacute;il debates.  I gave a commitment that I would take action in this area and we are now responding.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.135" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500007#F00500"><p>Generally, I agree with everything the Minister of State has said.  I will just make some specific observations.  Many of us felt the figure was so high it would be very restricted in who it could apply to.  Many of the people who were burned - caught financially - were well down the line, subcontractors of subcontractors, and might not even know who the main contractor was in the first place.  It is important that the scope be brought down to a much more manageable figure.  Some people might think it is too low.  I would imagine some people might say &euro;10,000 is a relatively small contract to be caught by this legislation, but I am of the view that &euro;10,000 is a reasonable amount of money.  If a tradesperson is out of pocket by &euro;7,000 to &euro;9,000, it could be a large part of his or her income for several months, so it is important that this would be included.</p><p>  My only concern is regarding how the threshold is drafted.  The text excludes contracts from the application of the Bill if the value of the contract is not more than &euro;10,000.  There are a number of scenarios where this could lack clarity.  Take an architect's initial design contract for, say, &euro;5,000.  Will that be included in the specific contract or is it the overall project we are talking about here?  There are many projects where the construction contract could be only a fraction of their project costs.  We have all seen it from the Luas line.  The pre-construction costs can, in some cases, comprise the majority of the costs, and it varies depending on the nature of the contract.  It could lead to some High Court litigation.</p><p>  What would happen in a situation where variations are allowed in a contract?  Many contracts have a figure that is subject to variation depending on various elements in it.  I can envisage difficulties and possible adjudications having to go to court, not through the procedures in the Act, where the &euro;10,000 figure is breached because of variations in a contract where it might not have been specified in the original amount.  The contract could move over &euro;10,000 during this period were some additional amounts added.</p><p>  There could be a situation where the main contractor could raise a counter charge for a difficulty with the quality of work provided by somebody he had contracted to do work.  One party could say they are owed &euro;50,000 while the other could say that party did a bad job and they are therefore claiming &euro;40,000 back, which brings the amount down to less than &euro;10,000.  Where do these opposing items fit into that kind of issue?  While I agree with the principle of what the Minister of State is doing here, it needs to be very tight to avoid unnecessary litigation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500007#F00600"><p>I welcome the Minister of State's contribution on this.  The headline stories on the collapse of the construction sector were all about the big players and I do not need to recall their names for this committee.  On closer examination, it transpired that most of those companies had very few, if any, direct employees.  The real workhorses of the sector, and the people we came in contact with, were the subcontractors for whom &euro;10,000 or &euro;1,000, whether for a fitted kitchen, a roofing contract or an electrical wiring job, was the difference between having a wage or no wage at the end of the week.  The consultation process, the regulatory impact assessment and the engagement that has gone on have significantly improved the Bill.  Dropping the threshold down to &euro;10,000 is very welcome and will go a long way towards addressing the concerns of those small subcontractors.</p><p>  In a neighbouring constituency of mine in west Limerick not long ago, I recall the issue of Kilfinane school and the subcontractors there, all of whom were badly burned and could get no redress.  That is a story that sticks as a visual manifestation of this problem.  It is too late for them but at least now, under this legislation, they will have recourse in future when it comes to contracts.  That is important because in recent years all the big players in the industry, while they might have had a site foreman, had all their work carried out by subcontractors, and those subcontractors were left high and dry when the tide went out.  This provides solace for them.  The thresholds previously envisaged were far too high in terms of the impact on these small subcontractors, and this is a good day's work.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.137" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500007#F00700"><p>And the Deputy is referring very specifically to the C2 category of worker in that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.138" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500007#F00800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.139" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500007#F00900"><p>I very much agree with what Deputy Creed said.  In fairness to Senator Quinn, the whole objective of the Bill was to help the small guy to ensure he had some rights in this and that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.141" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500008#G00200"><p>I welcome the lowering of the thresholds.  We all agreed that they were set too high, but why have a threshold at all, or why not set it at &euro;5,000 or &euro;2,000 instead of &euro;10,000?  I am taking on board Deputy Creed's comments in respect of those who were burned, those whose work was worth modest sums in the greater scheme but for whom those sums became significant when unpaid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.142" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500008#G00300"><p>At the end of Second Stage I took the view that there should be no thresholds.  If we were going as low as &euro;10,000, why have any threshold at all?  We could have made it clear for everyone.  However, the Attorney General's advice was, to avoid vexatious claims, there should be some threshold limit.  Given the fact that we all must take advice given on the basis of precedent and long-standing experience, I had no difficulty with accepting the &euro;10,000 threshold.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500008#G00400"><p>As a lay person, my understanding of an implicit element of the law is that, if I am subcontracted on a major construction project and fear that I will not be paid, I have the right to withdraw my labour and terminate my contract, be it written or not, for the works involved.  Given the fact that the Bill envisages a resolution process, I take it that there is nothing implicit in the legislation that cuts across the fundamental right to terminate a contract.  Just because a resolution process is available, I should not be obliged as a subcontractor to continue providing my labour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500008#G00500"><p>Two issues arise.  First, the Bill makes provision for the withdrawal of labour, although I am unsure in which section.  This is important.  There is a recognition of the need for a cooling down period whereby, if people take this route, they can re-examine the issues and achieve a fair resolution.  Notwithstanding any adjudication procedure, every citizen has a fundamental right to take an action if he or she believes that he or she has been unfairly treated.  This right exists in this Bill as it does elsewhere.  However, section 5 sets out a clear provision in respect of the right to suspend work for non-payment.  It is a fundamental part of the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500008#G00700"><p>Amendment No. 7 has been ruled out of order, as it is outside the scope of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500008#G01000"><p>Although I mentioned that I would invite discussion, we have already covered the matter.  Do members have additional comments to make?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500008#G01100"><p>I will vote "N&iacute;l" for the simple reason that we must still straighten out the issue of bespoke materials.  I want to put that on the record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="14:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500008#G01400"><p>I move amendment No. 8:<blockquote><br />In page 5, before section 2, to insert the following new section:2.--(1) Before awarding a construction contract, a state contracting entity shall publish a notice of intention to award such contract, and such notice shall include--<blockquote>(<i>a</i>) the name of the prospective executing party,<br />(<i>b</i>) an invitation to interested parties to submit observations to the state contracting entity in relation to the construction contract, such observations to be submitted within 28 days of the publication of the notice.</blockquote>(2) A state contracting entity shall have the authority under this Act not to proceed to award a construction contact to a prospective executing party on the basis of information received under <i>subsection (1)(b)</i>, such information to be independently verified.&quot;.</blockquote>This proposal has been made to me by people in the construction industry in light of the situation in other jurisdictions.  It is one of the major problems.  It is regularly known in advance whether a contractor awarded a contract has a bad record of paying people on other sites, yet the contractor can come to the next project with a clean sheet if, by some miracle, he, she or it is able to get bonding.  I do not know how such contractors are able to manage this.  In some cases, a separate company is set up within a group and meets the financial requirements necessary to be granted a contract.  Often, the local authority officers who grant contracts know that, in light of the other work done by the contractors or companies within groups, there is a high chance that local suppliers will be left unpaid.  However, because a contractor made the lowest bid, possessed financial bonds and had its financial statements checked by the local authority, an officer has no reason not to award the contract despite knowing the record of the people in question or, indeed, people associated with the contractor.</p><p>  The Minister of State might correct me, but a recent figure showed that the contractors involved in 10% of all school projects last year went out of business.  One in west Limerick has been mentioned, but I know of several contractors who went bust during their contracts.  This causes major delays and leaves people unpaid.  Sometimes, contractors use contracts to pay previous bills but this eventually catches up with their cash flow.  It also means that work falls back on the contracting authority.  In some cases, the taxpayer must pick up additional costs if the completion of the work must be repriced, which itself has many inherent problems.  Many contractors will be unsure of the quality of the work done to date.  Consequently, submitting a bid to complete a contract is more expensive than the project would have been had a competent contractor been awarded the contract originally.</p><p>  I suggest that a notice be given to interested parties so that they might make submissions within 28 days of the publication of a notice of intention by a contracting body to award a contract.  The reason is simple and applies extensively.  I regularly see newspaper notices about the intention of the Environmental Protection Agency, EPA, to grant a licence.  People have 28 days in which to make submissions.  This provides an opportunity for issues to emerge that have not already come to light.  If nothing arises, the licence can issue.</p><p>  Planning permissions are more important and germane to every construction project under this legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500009#H00200"><p>I agree with Deputy Fleming but support his amendment for a different reason.  Before I was elected to the D&aacute;il, I was involved in PPPs, public private partnerships, and financial modelling on the private sector side.  I only began to take a look at them from the public sector side in the past two years.  I have been astounded by the lack of public sector capacity to negotiate these arrangements properly.  Vast profits are being made in some of these contracts which should not happen, particularly if one looks at the returns on invested capital.  There is an opportunity for the State to tighten up the value it obtains in these contracts.  If we are to examine the kind of profits the developers made during the property bubble, we would probably find there were super profits made off State assets and permits.</p><p>  A provision like the one in this amendment would be some way of other contractors not just warning the State against potential issues with another contractor but advising it will be taken to the cleaners.  I do not believe the apparatus of the State is set up to get the best value from these construction contracts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500009#H00300"><p>I support the sentiment of Deputy Fleming's amendment.  I have, however, a concern about not awarding a contract to a party on the basis of information received in the manner outlined.  That would be open to challenge and could be problematic.  That said, Deputy Fleming has set out clearly a strong case for considering some provision of this nature to be included in this legislation.  I would contend, however, that it should be thought out more carefully and cast in safer terms.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500009#H00400"><p>Deputy Fleming has identified a real problem of cowboy companies re-inventing themselves legally and getting new State contracts.  This legislation is about providing solutions where a contract has gone wrong.  The State, however, should be preventing these issues arising in the first place.</p><p>  While I am not sure the amendment would stand up to a legal challenge, the Department should get a handle on it.  The main cases of the practice Deputy Sean Fleming alluded to with which I am familiar are contracts with the Department of Education and Skills.  I am sure this example is repeated throughout the country.  A school gets a grant for a two-classroom extension which is put out to tender.  Several contracts come in within &euro;1,000 of each other.  As the grant does not meet the full cost of the building, the board of management, which has to raise funds locally, cannot understand any logical reason why it should not take anything but the lowest price.  Then, one has all the problems that flow from this.</p><p>  I have written to the Minister for Education and Skills on this issue, asking him to oblige boards of management to employ appropriately qualified people, say quantity surveyors, to construct tender documents and assess them.  What mainly happens is that schools employ a civil engineer to do up a design but who is then obliged to assess the tenders and so forth.  This is where we run into difficulties.  It would be better if schools and others involved in evaluating State contracts were not so preoccupied with taking the lowest possible price but were cognisant of a contractor&rsquo;s capacity to undertake the job, not to leave other contractors unpaid and a trial of destruction behind him.</p><p>  Quantity surveyors are a critical profession in this context and should be used to determine whether a job can be done for the price quoted.  In the instances where projects ran into trouble, one will find they were not used appropriately.  It is understandable why parents or a board of management would take the lowest price in a tender.  The amendment is about preventing problems.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1027" speakername="Peter Mathews" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500009#H00500"><p>The objective of Deputy Fleming's amendment is worthy.  There is a danger, however, that it could enable a contractor&rsquo;s competition to effectively put him out of business if there had been, say, a delicacy in his financial affairs.  A delay in a recent contract could have been caused by a loss-making contract, just a bump.  A competitor could exploit that bump within the 28 days&rsquo; notice period.  We need to be careful about that.</p><p>  Deputy Creed has also put his finger on the problem of tenders.  It is about qualified and experienced personnel judging the delivery capacities in a contract which is mainly quantity surveyor territory.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500009#H00600"><p>Deputy Fleming and I discussed this in the last D&aacute;il when we were on the environment committee.  It is not just concerned with the schools building programme but also uncompleted housing estates, even before the property collapse, and the builders who reneged on development bonds, did not adhere to planning application conditions and who were serial offenders in this regard but who kept coming back and getting local authority contracts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500010#J00200"><p>Deputy Fleming is right in saying there is a problem.  I want to be up-front and admit there is an issue here largely driven by the fact that there is such competition for construction contracts because the price has come down substantially.  If one speaks to the Minister for Education and Skills, he will tell one that on average, there has been a reduction of between 30% and 40% on what we are spending now for the unit cost of primary schools <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i> what was the case at the height of the boom.  With that reduction and the extraordinary value we are getting now, there is obvious competition for that work from those who remain in business.  The excessive profits are not there anymore and people are litigious and look at every aspect of the contract to make sure that it is delivered as stated in the contract and there is nothing above and beyond it.</p><p>  There are two fundamental issues feeding their way back into public contracts and the Chairman is right in highlighting that.  It is an issue in my own Department regarding the Office of Public Works.  I know it from the flooding issue where we give out a major contract of &euro;2 million, &euro;3 million, &euro;4 million and sometimes &euro;7 million to main contractors.  One needs to keep a close eye on everything that is going on because the profits in the industry are not as high as they were in the past.  We are getting more value and much greater bang for our buck even though the amount we are spending has come down.  We are spending &euro;17 billion over a five-year period.  We are getting much greater value because of the competition that is there.  </p><p>  I understand that Deputy Fleming is trying to address a problem with his amendment but I do not believe this is the place to address it.  When I read the amendment again, I saw the reference to the period of time when this information would be published and an invitation to interested parties to submit their views.  Who are interested parties?  In most cases, it is the competition because there is a standstill period of between 14 to 16 days under EU procurement law.  In the great majority of cases, it is the person who has not got the contract who is the interested party.  To whom is Deputy Fleming referring in respect of interested parties because that happens anyway?  </p><p>  What Deputy Fleming is trying to address - it is a real issue - is a pre-tendering stage where any good public procurement individual or group of individuals really needs to know who they are dealing with.  This refers to the point made by Deputy Donnelly.  The pre-tendering stage is when all the work should be done to assess difficulties with other tasks that may have been there in the past.  That would be a major problem with this amendment.  Who are interested parties?  </p><p>  Second, one is trying to get a piece of work done.  This extends the period of time by opening up this new opportunity.  I know the recent case in west Limerick which has been referred to where the person would not pay up but it was not as a result of insolvency.  It was just that he would not pay up because of the existing contract.  There is a wider problem here which we are looking at.  </p><p>  There has been progress in recent years on public procurement generally in these contract areas.  I take Deputy Donnelly's point about PPPs.  We had some spectaculars in this area in the past decade and a half but there has been very little PPP activity in the past number of years because no one was prepared to invest in the country.  I recently spoke at a conference at the National Convention Centre.  There is substantial interest again.  The new areas where we will be engaging in PPPs are, if I can be very blunt about it the bog standard stuff - schools, primary health care centres and Garda stations.  They will be not be trophy projects delivered in certain constituencies with all kinds of fanfare.  That day is over.  It is the kind of activity we need to keep the public administration system together.  There is significant interest in Ireland because of the improvement in many areas.  As I continually say, if one makes the sovereign look less risky, people are prepared to invest in the country again.  So there is interest again and we are heavily involved in that aspect.  </p><p>  The Deputy is right.  The level of supervision in the past and the way these contracts were handled was appalling.  That will be helped by the fact that we are centralising public procurement, as the Deputy is aware.  We have a new office located within but independent of the Department of Public Expenditure and Reform, if that is not a contradiction in terms.  Someone from outside is running public procurement.  Due to the fact that we are getting value because the money is not there and so many more parties are competing for this work, we must monitor those very closely.  Monitoring the contract is everything because it is at that stage that things can deteriorate.  The day of these large-scale trophy projects around the country is over.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500010#J00300"><p>I am pleased the Minister of State is looking at monitoring but it is also a matter of the construction of the contracts.  The kind of ratios I have seen embedded in some of this are extraordinary.  Private contractors would not let the other party make as much profit for the level of capital risk and IP they are bringing to the table as the State allows the private sector to make.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500010#J00400"><p>The major difference is that we now have standardised contracts which have made a significant difference in terms of giving certainty to public authorities engaged in this.  I will be frank.  There are too many people involved in public procurement who do not have the specialist knowledge of markets and sectors.  One of the things we have done within procurement recently is to recruit people from outside who have knowledge of and expertise in specific markets on a contract for five or seven years.  That has made a big difference in terms of knowledge of markets.</p><p>  We are in a new space.  We will not get everything right but there has been a significant improvement in the procurement agenda and public contracts are fundamental to that.  Standardised contracts involve having the agreement of the offices of the Chief State Solicitor and the Attorney General and everyone signing up to it.  Previously, people did not work together.  This was a ludicrous situation whereby the State's lawyers and authorities were putting these contracts together but were not working together.  This has changed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500010#J00500"><p>Deputy Twomey has indicated that he wishes to speak.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1095" speakername="Liam Twomey" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500010#J00600"><p>Deputy Fleming's amendment might be dealing with situations before the contract is awarded.  The Minister of State talks about how he looks at these issues.  Does he review every single tendering contract particularly when they fail?  There are two reasons why tendering contracts fail.  One is that there are many people who are desperate for work, tender too low and simply fail to achieve the result the expected to achieve.  The other reason relates to what is actually driving this kind of subcontractors' legislation.  There are people who set out to rip people off from the outset and never have any intention of paying anybody.  There is that difference.  Do we look at every single tendering contract in the public sector that fails and examine the reasons why it failed?  That would then follow through on what Deputy Fleming is talking about.  We would be identifying people who fail and who fail on a regular basis and we might identify who we describe in this country as cowboys.  I remember talking to some proponents of this legislation a number of years ago.  They told me that it was used very infrequently in the UK particularly where the arbitration issue was concerned and that they had seen an increase in its use in the UK after our construction industry collapsed because a number of people who used to work in this country moved to the UK, brought their bad practices with them and found themselves facing arbitration in a way they were not used to expecting in this country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500010#J00700"><p>The Minister of State mentioned an invitation to interested parties.  This invitation is to the public and anyone with an interest in responding.  It is not a specified list.  I regularly see advertisements in newspapers-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.167" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500010#J00800"><p>From An Bord Plean&aacute;la?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:10:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500010#J00900"><p>Yes.  The Minister is looking at it in the very narrow and confined way that public officials might look at it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K00200"><p>Every school principal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K00300"><p>I could list 100 bodies that are in a position to sign contracts spending taxpayers' money.  We are raising an interesting point here because in the case of a new school run by the Department of Education and Skills that will be the contracting body but those are big projects.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K00400"><p>Every board of management.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K00500"><p>Normally it is the board of management and the local parish priest, or the local principal in some cases.  Most of these people are genuine and operate to the best of their ability but they feel that their hands are being tied as part of this process too.  They cannot give the contract to the builder who built the school a couple of years back and is a good person but they give it to somebody from 80 miles away whose track record they do not know and about which they are concerned.</p><p>  So many people are able to sign contracts on behalf of the Irish taxpayer, many of whom have no training in this area and maybe do it only once in their entire career, for example a school principal.  Not everybody can get everything right the first time around.  I am not talking about taking power away from them.  We put these strictures in place to prevent them going off the rails then they turn around and say the strictures have prevented them giving the contract to someone they know.  It is a circular argument so I will leave it at that but the Minister of State gets the point.</p><p>  I would like the Minister of State to ultimately produce a list - I am sure the media could produce it - of all those contractors on public bodies who went bust during the term of a contract.  The Minister of State or his officials should have that list on their desks, as should all Ministers, and those contractors should not be considered.  The Minister of State will probably tell me that he could be sued if these people were not considered but somewhere along the line the taxpayer's interest has to come into the equation because some of those people are well known and they should not be in the frame the next time around.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K00600"><p>That is an interesting discussion but I am not sure how germane it is to the Bill.  It is an important part of the construction sector as we try to improve construction levels and see greater activity in the area.  I think it is fair to say that public procurement within the construction sector operates in the most successful way when the authority makes clear what it wants at the pre-tendering stage and that it has the power to go through that information rigorously to make sure that it is satisfied with those who are looking for the work.</p><p>  The Deputy asked if I have the list of those who go out of business.  That list is a matter for the contracting authority.  The Minister, Deputy Howlin and I set the standard and norm which is applied across the system.  The best example of getting a handle on that is the tax clearance mechanism for which the Revenue Commissioners have responsibility.  That should highlight difficulties where people are looking for work.</p><p>  The Deputy asked a fair question about the number of people employed in public procurement.  There is a figure set out in the Accenture report.  I understand it is 580.  I said when the report was published that it is still too many.  We do not want people involved part-time in public procurement.  This is full-time business.  I hope the Deputy supports us when we centralise this as we are doing because there are enormous opportunities for substantial savings if we get this prize.  Accenture said that somewhere between &euro;280 million and &euro;550 million can be obtained over a three year period by better procurement.  The prize is &euro;500 million over three years if we get this right.  That requires having people in place who know their business.  It does not require people who do this part time.  I fully concur and agree with the Deputy on that point.  That was very clear in the Accenture report.</p><p>  This is all about proper payment practices and one of the things we are considering, which may have come out in parliamentary questions to me or to the Minister, is a project bank account which he is examining in the Department.  This would be a payment mechanism structured around a trust account where staged payments due to named beneficiaries, that is main contractor and specified sub-contractors, are notified to the bank and the agreed amounts are paid via the account directly to the beneficiaries.  That would give the State much more oversight and, arguably, of how and when people are paid for work done on that contract.  We have seen good international examples of this where it seems to have worked.</p><p>  Have I answered all the Deputy's questions?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K00700"><p>I understand what the Minister of State is saying.  I got the gist of it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.176" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K00800"><p>That is half the battle.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K01000"><p>Amendment No. 9 in the name of Deputy Fleming has been ruled out of order as being outside the scope of the Bill.  Likewise Amendment No. 10, which involves a potential charge on Revenue.  Amendment No. 11 in the name of Deputy Fleming also involves a new section.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:20:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500011#K01300"><p>I move amendment No. 11:<blockquote><br />In page 5, before section 2, to insert the following new section:&quot;2.&mdash;It shall be the duty of a State contracting entity, to place a notice at the site entrance, each time the state contracting entity makes a payment to the executing party, such notice to state the date the payment was made and amount paid to the executing party.&quot;. </blockquote>  This is a very blunt instrument.  I know that the Minister of State proposes to change the definition of a &quot;State contracting entity&quot; but it is still in the legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1027" speakername="Peter Mathews" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00100"><p>A queue of subcontractors would be lining up.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.182" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00200"><p>Precisely.  They would know the main contractor got a cheque in the morning and they would want their cheques by lunchtime.  Rather than, as Deputy Mathews mentioned, a main contractor saying he is waiting for a quantity surveyor to approve the staged payment and that it is held up for another month and then another month and having all that flouting around, the State body could put a notice on the site to the effect that a cheque for &euro;200,000 arrived this morning.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1027" speakername="Peter Mathews" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00300"><p>The white flag has been raised.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00400"><p>The subcontractors would queue up for their cheques and they would all go home with them at lunchtime.  It is a blunt instrument and a direct approach.  It would save a good deal of trouble and many subcontractors, and subcontractors of subcontractors, would know that money had arrived on the site that day and it was time for them to get paid.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00500"><p>I have two observations regarding the amendment.  A constituent who is a subcontractor on a State contract contacted me recently.  The State was about to pay the main contractor but there was a significant danger that if the cheque was paid to the banking institution dealing with the main contractor's banking arrangements, the funds would not be released subsequently to pay anybody because of the precarious nature of the main contractor's financial circumstances.  That is something of which we must be conscious.</p><p>  I understand where Deputy Fleming is coming from in tabling this amendment.  He is sending a signal to all and sundry that somebody has received perhaps substantial amounts of State funding but it might not only be the subcontractors who might turn up at the main contractor's door.  Other guys in balaclavas could turn up as well.  That is a legitimate concern and, therefore, I am not so sure about this amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00600"><p>Once they are not paid in cash-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00700"><p>He could be kidnapped.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00800"><p>The first question that came to mind when I read this amendment was who was going to pay for the site notice being erected.  This is about public contracts but what about private contracts?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L00900"><p>The Minister of State proposes to abolish the definition in the next section and, therefore, it will apply to everyone.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01000"><p>When a contract is awarded, a schedule of payments by the State to the main contractor is agreed.  The contractor then receives those payments as the work is done and he or she in turn pays the subcontractors.  I know what the Deputy is getting at, but I do not see the significance of this.  When I read this again last night one of the first thoughts that came to mind was that it is part of a public authority's contract to make payments on the basis of staged payments.  I do not know if information could be made available through its website that it had paid people.  The State makes payments and it is pretty good at paying.  As long as we get the money from the outsiders, we can keep writing the cheques.  I do not know how this proposal would help in that respect.  It would set up a dichotomy between public authorities and private individuals and companies who equally procure construction contracts.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.191" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1027" speakername="Peter Mathews" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01100"><p>During the past 40 years the balance of credit power has moved very much in favour of main contractors compared to the past.  I remember one of the country's largest contractors used to be clients of ICC Bank and their reliance on loans was much greater in yesteryear than it has become in recent years because they, in turn, receive their credit not from their bank, but from their subcontractors.  They had to have a large amount of cash on hand every Friday to pay the wages of the labourers who would have numbered 4,000 across the country.  That is no longer needed because all their inputs are in the form of subcontractors who, in turn, employ the labour.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01200"><p>Deputy Fleming is right that this is a crude instrument, but I would put forward an observation for consideration on this matter.  I was at a talk by, I think, the ex-president of Tanzania who spoke about how to ensure that schools paid teachers and they turned up for work.  One of the big problems was that the money was coming from the state for the school to do its job but the principal and the teachers did not show up and schoolbooks were not bought.  The money was not being used as it was meant to be used.  There is an analogy between that situation and this one.  As the Minister of State said, the State pays but the purpose of Senator Quinn's Bill is to address the problem that the money is going where it is meant to go.  That ex-president said that the single most effective thing they ever did was to pass a law or a rule whereby the payments as they were made were nailed to the front door of the school and all the parents could see them.  The notice was to the effect that this month the school is being paid this amount of money, this is the number of teachers who should be in the school, this is the amount that has been paid for books, and so forth.  He said it was the single most effective thing they were ever able to do for rural and urban education because it empowered the parents to demand that the state money was used as it was meant to be used.  I am struck that there is quite a clear analogy between that and what Deputy Fleming is trying to do here.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01300"><p>That is a very good suggestion.  The INTO, ASTI and TUI should be asked for their observations on that.  It is a very interesting suggestion that the money would go to the schools and based on the hand-over to the teachers we should all know about it, rather than the current centralised system where they are paid on time every two weeks.  They might have something to say about that, but it is an interesting proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01400"><p>Just to be clear, I am not proposing that should be done in the case of schools.  However, Deputy Fleming is proposing that something like that would be done on building sites where we have a history of the State paying the money and it not going to those companies.  I am simply giving the Minister of State an example of where it has worked in another industry in another country.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01500"><p>I may take to posting a notice on the door to the committee room if we do not proceed through the Bill this evening in terms of being efficient, cogent and clear.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01600"><p>This is a crude device.  I do not see the Minister of State accepting this amendment.  I am guessing he will knock it out of the park.  We should forget about putting notices on sites but there is an issue around the ability of a subcontractor in circumstances where a schedule of payments has been agreed with a main contractor to check that those payments have been processed and made.  That is the net point.  I do not think there is any serious suggestion that the Minister of State would detail somebody to erect notices across the countryside, but there is merit in being able to tract that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01700"><p>Perhaps the Minister of State would examine the idea of a main contractor being obliged to register all his subcontractors with the Department.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01800"><p>We are examining that in terms of a project bank account, which is the point Deputy McDonald raised.  These have been established in the UK and, as I understand it, the main contractor and the subcontractors are all referred to and paid out of this designated project account and in that way they know exactly where they stand in terms of the total drawdown funds that the state makes available for that project or group of projects.  It is a stand-alone account to which they are named parties, as is the main contractor.  That is one way around this.  The UK has operated this for some years.  We are examining this intensively at present.  I think that would resolve the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L01900"><p>Will the Minister of State consider this for Report Stage?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L02000"><p>It does not need to be included in legislation.  It is a policy decision.  We do not need to put it into law.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L02100"><p>I will take a final comment from Deputy Fleming.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500012#L02200"><p>The Minister of State asked me why I referred to State contracting authorities in my amendment.  He used that wording to that effect in the legislation and I was using his terminology.  The majority of the complaints I received in my constituency regarding subcontractors not being paid related to State contracts.  The subcontractors contacted me as a public representative.  If a local shop was having development work carried out or a private company was building a housing development and something were to go wrong, that would be a public sector issue but we are in the public domain.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/986" speakername="Michael Creed" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M00200"><p>They are all taking a cut.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M00300"><p>Yes, they all take a percentage.  I hope for a mechanism to cover not just the main registered subcontractors but also to pay the people who work on the job.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M00400"><p>It might be useful to have a separate meeting, as it is not part of the legislation.  I will have no difficulty in coming back to the committee to have a more detailed discussion on that issue.</p><p>  It is not our experience that main contractors sit back.  They are the people who must deliver the project.  It depends on the size of the contracting company and it is common for it to use subcontractors.  I do not think it is correct to say main contractors-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1027" speakername="Peter Mathews" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M00500"><p>They carry the liabilities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M00600"><p>Yes.  That they simply wash their hands of the issue is not our experience.  However, I agree with Deputy Sean Fleming's other point on volunteer boards of management.  He is correct that we are asking volunteers to take on a significant responsibility because the board is ultimately liable for the school under the Education Act.  We need to ensure people receive the training and support they require and have the confidence to deliver these contracts properly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M00700"><p>How stands the amendment?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M00800"><p>It is a very good one.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M01100"><p>Amendment No. 12 is out of order as it is outside the scope of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M01400"><p>Amendment No. 13 has been discussed with amendment No. 5.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M01500"><p>I move amendment No. 13:<blockquote><br />In page 5, before section 2, to insert the following new section:&ldquo;2.&mdash;It shall be the duty of a state contracting entity to ensure that a social contract clause is inserted into every construction contact that the state contracting entity may award to a prospective executing party.&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M01800"><p>Amendment No. 15 has been discussed with amendment No. 6.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M01900"><p>I move amendment No. 15:<blockquote><br />In page 5, subsection (1), lines 33 to 35, to delete paragraph (<i>a</i>) and substitute the following:&ldquo;(<i>a</i>) if the value of the contract is not more than &euro;10,000, or&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.222" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M02100"><p>Amendment No. 16 cannot be moved as it was an alternative amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M02300"><p>I move amendment No. 17:<blockquote><br />In page 5, subsection (1)(<i>b</i>), line 36, to delete &ldquo;the value of the contract is more than &euro;200,000, and&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M02500"><p>I move amendment No. 18:<blockquote><br />In page 5, subsection (1), to delete line 42 and in page 6, to delete lines 1 to 3 and substitute the following:&ldquo;her residence.&rdquo;.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M02900"><p>I apologise for my absence as I had to ask a parliamentary question.  Has the issue relating to the figure of 200 sq. m been discussed?  Has the figure of &euro;200,000 been discussed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03000"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03100"><p>I apologise for being missing for a few minutes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.233" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03200"><p>All of the limits have been pushed down to &euro;10,000.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03300"><p>But not the figure of 200 sq. m.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03400"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03500"><p>That figure has not been discussed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03600"><p>No.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03700"><p>I have not tabled an amendment on this issue.  Perhaps it might have been resolved through the reference to the money and perhaps both amendments are not required.  There is a proposal to lower the figure of 200 sq. m to 40 sq. m.  I ask the Minister of State to consider bringing forward an amendment on Report Stage on the issue.  There is potentially a loophole being created.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03800"><p>I assure the Deputy that it was not discussed while he was absent from the room.  I understand the point he is raising.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M03900"><p>We discussed the issues of footage and square metres.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M04000"><p>They are linked.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M04100"><p>I wanted to raise this issue.  There is concern that a loophole would be created in the case of very large residential properties which involve large contracts and substantial sums of money.  The resolution mechanism envisaged in the legislation should prove to be efficient and cost-effective.  Outside of the loophole relating to very large single residential developments there is the question as to why parties should be denied access to such an efficient, timesaving and cost-effective process.  I recognise no specific amendment has been tabled.  I hope, however, that the Minister of State will consider this issue again in order that some amendment could be tabled on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M04200"><p>I have explained that the thresholds were introduced because of a securities issue.  When that issue was highlighted for Senator Feargal Quinn at the time, the view was taken to resolve it.  As a consequence, the issue of thresholds would be resolved, as they were linked.  Now that the issue of the thresholds has been resolved, this issue was brought to my attention very recently.  I do not think it arose from the regulatory impact assessment carried out at the time.  I have given a commitment to look at it again in advance of Report Stage.  We want to have a fair system for everyone.  Without giving a firm commitment, I will look at it again because it was only recently brought to my attention that this could be a difficulty.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1107" speakername="Stephen Donnelly" time="15:40:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500013#M04300"><p>That is very welcome.  My understanding is that if one is building something that is less than 200 sq. ft. or 2,000 sq. ft. in old money, one does not have access to the adjudication process which is hugely useful, arguably more so in the case of the small stuff because at the larger scale there are fewer barriers to expensive arbitration.  Perhaps it might be taken out.</p> <p>The figure given to me was that 40 sq. m would be better but it seems that if one is building less than whatever that is - 2,100 sq. ft. - which is most houses, adjudication is exactly what one should be getting access to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N00200"><p>We do not want a situation where people who have a genuine grievance, which cannot be resolved through the adjudication process, find that grievance cannot be resolved.  However, we want to get the balance right by having genuine thresholds, which we have on the monetary side.  I refer to the argument on the existing 200 sq. m and whether that provides some difficulty.  As I said, it was very recently brought to my attention.  I gave a commitment to look at it again and I give that commitment to the committee also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N00300"><p>For the purposes of clarity, should this, along with the issue of the bespoke materials, be something on which the Opposition spokespersons should enter into conversation with the Minister of State's officials rather than second-guessing what he might or might not do?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N00400"><p>The issue of the 200 sq. m is not the same difficulty as the bespoke supplies.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N00500"><p>I am not saying they are comparable levels of difficulty.  In the interests of getting all of this right and in the way we have proceeded with this legislation, it would be an idea for us to talk to the Minister of State's officials.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N00600"><p>That would be very useful.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/990" speakername="Ciar&aacute;n Lynch" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N00900"><p>Amendments Nos. 20 and 21 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01000"><p>I move amendment No. 20:<blockquote><br />In page 6, subsection (1), to delete line 24.</blockquote>This is simply to try to prevent the misuse of conditional payment clauses.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01100"><p>Section 3 deals with payments under the construction contract.  Simple contracts can stipulate fixed amounts to be paid at stages, such as the completion of foundations, external walls, roofs, etc.  Larger contracts allow for a fixed period between each interim payment.  Typically, such payments are monthly.  However, the amounts associated with interim payments are not stipulated but are based on progress on site and are tied to rates for elements of the work.</p><p>  In addition, some contracts may not have a final payment at contract award stage but instead the final payment or total contract sum may not be fully computed until a substantial amount of the work is completed.  Such contracts may have a tendered contract sum which both parties are aware is subject to change depending on the actual extent of work completed and the final contract sum is calculated on a re-measurement of the completed work.  Deleting line 24 of section 3(1) would remove the discretion of parties to the contract to provide any flexibility under a construction contract and, if limited to section 3(1)(<i>a</i>) and (<i>b</i>), would only reflect the typical range of contracting arrangements.  </p><p>  I note the comments that section 3(1) and (2), which refer to adequate mechanism, may result in uncertainly but I suggest it is important to permit parties to make their own contractual arrangements.  Under section 3(1) the parties can simply make arrangements for stage payments but this may be unsuitable in cases.  Parties would be in a position to agree on how the stage payments would be calculated but it may be unduly restrictive to prevent this.  </p><p>  Obviously, if parties are allowed some leeway to make their own arrangements, this involves a value judgment on whether it is adequate but this may be a matter for the courts ultimately.  Of course, it is a matter of policy whether to allow this flexibility. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01200"><p>Whatever about affording a level of flexibility within the contracts, I would be concerned that this opens up an exit clause or a level of ambiguity in respect of pay out on the contract terms.  That is why I tabled my amendment.  The genesis of this legislative initiative is that promises were entered into with sub-contractors but were not met and people were left high and dry.  My concern is that there is almost a get out clause in this legislation.  It states, "shall provide for each interim payment and shall provide for the amount of the final payment to be made under the construction contract or for an adequate mechanism for determining those amounts".  That is not just flexible but is extremely fluid in respect of placing obligations on the party concerned.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.257" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01300"><p>The concern we have is that by deleting the line in question, it makes all rulings virtually applicable on subsections (<i>a</i>) and (<i>b</i>), that is, the amount of each interim payment to be made and the amount of the final payment.  Not all cases fall under those two categories - that is the point.  There are other circumstances in any contractual relationship where they may not.  If one takes out the words &quot;or for an adequate mechanism&quot; for determining these amounts, it becomes very rigid.  While they might not be the majority examples, there might be other minority examples which I understand apply in certain circumstances.  That is the concern we have with this.  There needs to be some flexibility.  What the Deputy proposes to do is to take that out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01400"><p>To try to be helpful, can I suggest that is something we might consider before Report Stage?  If we look at the wording, instead of saying "or for an adequate mechanism" for determining these amounts, could we consider the words "and for an adequate mechanism" for determining those amounts?  We can talk about this again because I take the Minister of State's point on the flexibility.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01500"><p>If one takes out "or" and puts in "and for an adequate mechanisms for determining these amounts"------</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01600"><p>Does the Minister of State see my concern?  My concern is that "or" gives one an absolute out in respect of the interim payments.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01700"><p>Can the Deputy see my concern that by taking the line out-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01800"><p>I understand the Minister of State's concern about taking the line but I am trying to-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N01900"><p>Let us look at that again.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N02000"><p>We will come back to it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N02200"><p>I move amendment No. 21:<blockquote><br />In page 6, subsection (5), line 42, after &quot;contract&quot; to insert the following:<br />&quot;(done otherwise than as part of a mechanism for determining the amount due)&quot;.</blockquote>This is a clarifying change for the avoidance of doubt.  Typically, payments under a construction contract are conditional upon a certificate of payment being used by the named certifier under the contract.  If section 3(5) was not amended, it may not be clear that this provision complies with the provisions of the Bill.  Amendment No. 21 is intended to clarify the position of the architect, engineer or any other named certifier under a construction contract.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.267" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="15:50:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500014#N02300"><p>Will the Minister of State clarify that again?  He is saying the person can now be paid when the work is certified.  What happens if the person who is to certify the work is slow to do so and is somebody the main contractor uses regularly to certify work but who takes his time?  There is no time limit specified for the person to certify the work has been done.  There is an intermediary there to help but sometimes an intermediary might not be as helpful to the person waiting for payment as they might be to the person who is paying them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.269" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O00200"><p>My understanding is a contractor does not retain the certifier.  In fact, it is separate entirely to the process.  The contractor does not use a certifier for that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O00300"><p>I am still not sure what the Minister of State is saying.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.271" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O00400"><p>By taking this out?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.272" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O00500"><p>Can the Minister of State go through the note again, slowly?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.273" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O00600"><p>This is a clarifying change for the avoidance of doubt.  Typically, payments under a construction contract are conditional upon a certificate of payment being issued by the named certifier under the contract.  If section 3(5) were not amended, it might not be clear that this provision complies with the provisions of the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.274" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O00700"><p>Who pays the certifier?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.275" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O00800"><p>The employer.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.276" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O00900"><p>That is what I am coming at.  Does anyone certify the payment for the subcontractor?  This seems to be between the awarding authority and the main contractor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.277" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01000"><p>That is between him and the main contractor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.278" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01100"><p>There is no cover here as between the subcontractor and the main contractor.  The main contractor has cover.  He gets paid when his payment is certified.  The essence of the whole Bill is to help subcontractors rather than main contractors to get paid.  We are assuming most main contractors get paid.  The issue and the genesis of the legislation is not to guarantee the protection of the payment to the main contractor, which must happen.  Nothing can happen if the main contractor does not get paid.  While the essence of the Bill is to ensure subcontractors get paid, the Minister of State appears to be clarifying the mechanism to ensure the main contractor is paid by the awarding authority.  I thought our emphasis today was to guarantee-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.279" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1027" speakername="Peter Mathews" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01200"><p>Through the Chair, where a quantity surveyor certifies an amount of work done by the main contractor, by implication the work carried out by the subcontractor, which is part of that overall work, will have been certified also.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.280" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01300"><p>Where does the subcontractor come into this?  Is the certificate of use to the subcontractor?  It is not.  It is useful only to assist the main contractor to get his cheque drawn down.  I am trying to get a mechanism.  The work is ongoing for-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.281" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01400"><p>I am not sure I understand Deputy Fleming's point.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.282" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01500"><p>The subcontractor is on the site for six months for a big job.  The main contractor will get paid as the certificates are produced to show that the work is at a certain point.  He will get staged payments.  The purpose of the Bill is to ensure the staged payments get passed on to subcontractors.  Is there a mechanism in the Bill for a certification on behalf of the subcontractor doing block work or ground works where he has completed 20%, 40% or 60% of the work?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.283" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01600"><p>I think we are talking at cross purposes.  I will keep it simple.  The way a subcontractor agrees the contract with the main contractor is not relevant to the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.284" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01700"><p>I thought that was the sole purpose of the Bill.  The Bill is not about helping the main contractor.  It is about helping the guy at the bottom of the food chain to get paid.  It is not about the main guy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.285" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01800"><p>The objective of the Bill is to ensure people get paid on time and to provide for an adjudication process where there is a dispute.  What we are trying to obtain from the legislation is very net.  The arrangements people come to as to how they are paid is a matter entirely for them to negotiate in contracts with the main contractor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.286" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O01900"><p>We are here because that system is failing.  People would not be looking for money if that system worked.  That is the genesis of the concept behind the Bill.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.287" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O02000"><p>The Schedule makes provision for all of the payments.  There is now a legal provision for this.  Where a person cannot get paid, an action will be taken under the adjudication process, presumably.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.288" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O02100"><p>We will come to that later on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.289" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O02200"><p>Is the Deputy happy now?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.290" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1100" speakername="Se&aacute;n Fleming" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O02300"><p>We will not go that far.  We will move on.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.292" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1008" speakername="Mary Lou McDonald" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O02500"><p>I move amendment No. 22:<blockquote><br />In page 7, subsection (6)(<i>a</i>)(ii), line 7, to delete &quot;the presentation of a petition to wind it up&quot;.</blockquote>The amendment is proposed because we must be sure that if insolvency is used as a rationale for non-payment, there is a genuine insolvency event.  The amendment is intended to add a level of certainty and to close down the escape hatches in respect of non-payment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.293" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/958" speakername="Brian Hayes" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/FI22013051500015#O02600"><p>The presentation of a petition to wind up a company is an important tool for subcontractors and suppliers.  It provides a means for them to seek compensation in the event of non-payment.  Similarly, it is an important indicator of a company's financial standing.  I have been advised, therefore, that the definition included in the Bill covers the appropriate level of insolvency situations.  This is one of a number of indicators used in all public contracts as a gauge of a company's financial standing.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.298" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="">Select Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.299" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 09:30</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.301" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500002#A00100">Business of Select Committee</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.302" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500002#A00200"><p>We have a quorum and the select committee is now in public session.  Apologies have been received from Deputies Anne Ferris and Finian McGrath.  At the request of the broadcasting and recording services, will committee members ensure their mobile phones are switched off completely and not just left in silent mode?  They need to be switched off they will interfere with our recording system.</p><p>  We will start our consideration of the Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) (Amendment) Bill 2013<b>.</b></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.303" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500002#A00300"><p>Before we begin, may I thank the chairman and members of the select committee for sitting so early and for being so bright eyed and bushy tailed at this time.  We will re-engage with each other later in the morning.  At some stage, I think we should have a meeting at 7.30 a.m. and then all go off to breakfast.</p><p>  Let me make a general opening remark on the Bill.  I remind members of some of the matters I mentioned on Second Stage.  I intend to introduce a number of amendments on Report Stage to deal with the threat to life and property posed by explosive devices which make use of mobile communications technology in their construction and activation.  The purpose of these amendments will be to allow for a direction to issue to mobile phone service providers to cease service provision in a limited area in order to prevent death or damage to property.  The provision will contain safeguards to ensure that any interference with services is limited to the extent necessary to deal with the threat.  In order that all Members of the House will have an opportunity to consider these new elements of the Bill, I am advised that they should be introduced on Report Stage rather than on Committee Stage.  This will involve a procedural recommital to Committee Stage before the whole House to allow for the new elements to be considered in depth.  Report Stage is scheduled for 22 May 2013.  Deputies may also wish to note that as these provisions are outside the scope of the current Title of the Bill, it will be necessary to amend the Title.</p><p>  The upcoming G8 summit in County Fermanagh has brought a particular reality to the necessity for this legislation.  It is possible that terrorist groups may try to use the occasion of the summit to, at the very least, garner publicity for themselves.  This is not to ignore the very real danger of the loss of life if such a device were successfully detonated.  In addition to those proposed amendments, I hope that it may be possible to bring forward other provisions as Report Stage amendments, some of which were contained in the general scheme as published last year.  There is pressure on the Office of the Parliamentary Counsel arising from the increased burden of troika related legislation, so it was not possible to include them in the Bill as originally published or as Committee Stage amendments.  These amendments may include a provision to transfer the authorisation and monitoring of trust or company service providers, or TCSPs, as they are known, which are subsidiaries of credit or financial institutions to the Central Bank and technical amendments to refine certain references to lawyers, competent authorities and the monitoring of unusual or complex transactions.</p><p>  I am sorry that I interrupted the Chairman but it is important that I put on record that we are in order in a procedural sense when we get to Report Stage.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.304" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500002#A00400"><p>That is very interesting.  I noted in other jurisdictions that mobile phone operators were asked to shut down as well.  As nobody wishes to comment on that we will proceed with the Bill.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.305" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500002#A00500">Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) (Amendment) Bill 2013: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.308" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500002#A00800"><p>I move amendment No. 1:<blockquote><br />In page 3, between lines 11 and 12, to insert the following:<br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 17 of Act of 2010</b><b>2. </b>Section 17 of the Act of 2010 is amended by the substitution of the following for<br />subsection (4):<blockquote>&ldquo; (4) An application for an order under subsection (2)&mdash;<br />(a) shall be made <i>ex parte </i>and shall be heard otherwise than in public,<br />and<br />(b) shall be made to a judge of the District Court assigned to the<br />district in which the order is proposed to be served.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote>The purpose of this amendment is to clarify that orders which may be made by a District Court judge under section 17 of the Act of 2010 are <i>ex parte </i>and are not held in public.  Section 17 is contained in Part 3 of the Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) Act 2010.  The purpose of Part 3 is to provide a mechanism which enables the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to take immediate action to halt a service or transaction where there are reasonable grounds to suspect that a particular service or transaction may be linked to money laundering or terrorist financing and enable the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na to conduct an investigation.</p><p>  Section 17 operates in two possible ways.  Subsection (1) provides that a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na not below the rank of superintendent may by notice in writing direct a person not to carry out any specified service or transaction for a specified period, which cannot exceed seven days, if satisfied this is necessary to enable preliminary investigation be carried out.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.314" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500003#B00700"><p>I move amendment No. 2:<blockquote><br />In page 5, to delete lines 30 and 31 and substitute the following:&ldquo;(b) in subsection (6)&mdash;<blockquote>(i) by the substitution of &ldquo;is, or has become, a politically exposed person&rdquo; for<br />&ldquo;is a politically exposed person&rdquo;, and<br />(ii) by the substitution of &ldquo;subsection (4)(a), (b) and (c)&rdquo; for &ldquo;subsection (4)(a)<br />and (b)&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote>Section 37 of the Act of 2010 sets out the enhanced customer due diligence or CDD measures to be taken by a designated person in relation to customers who are politically exposed persons.  For the purpose of the Act, a politically exposed person is a person residing outside the State who has been entrusted with a prominent, public function at any time in the preceding 12 months.  Section 6 of the Bill amends section 37(4) in order to provide that a designated person must also apply such measures to an existing customer, who subsequently becomes a politically exposed person.  The purpose of this amendment is to apply the same approach in subsection (6) so that a designated person must apply the enhanced CDD requirements in subsection (4), both when a beneficial owner connected with the customer or services of politically exposed person and if they subsequently become one. I commend the amendment to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.319" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500003#B01300"><p>I move amendment No. 3:<blockquote><br />In page 6, between lines 17 and 18, to insert the following:<br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 55 of Act of 2010</b><b>9. </b>Section 55 of the Act of 2010 is amended&mdash;<blockquote>(a) in subsection (4), by the substitution of &ldquo;shall be retained by the designated<br />person&rdquo; for &ldquo;shall be retained by the designated person, at an office or other<br />premises in the State,&rdquo;, and<br />(b) by the insertion, after subsection (7) of the following subsection:<blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(7A)  The records required to be kept by a designated person under this section may be kept outside the State provided that the designated person ensures that those records are produced in the State to&mdash;</blockquote>(a) a member of the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na,<br />(b) an authorised officer appointed under section 72,<br />(c) a relevant authorised officer within the meaning of section 103, or<br />(d) a person to whom the designated person is required to produce such<br />records in relation to his or her business, trade or profession,<br />as soon as practicable after the records concerned are requested, or where the obligation to produce the records arises under an order of a court made under section 63 of the Criminal Justice Act 1994, within the period which applies to such production under the court order concerned.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>Section 55 of the Act of 2010 contains the record keeping obligations, which apply to designated persons.  Section 55(4) provides that such records must be retained at an office or a premises in the State.  This is causing difficulties for some sectors, particularly in the financial area, in which companies are often part of a wider international group where the practice may be that documentation such as records are often retained by one member of the group in a particular location.  I understand the practice of storing records, particularly electronic records on service in other states, is common in a number of industries.  In addition, Ireland is itself a base for the storage of records for a number of multinationals and other companies.</p><p>  The purpose of the amendment is to provide the flexibility that is required in relation to where records are stored, while also ensuring that the records are readily available to relevant authorities such as the Garda S&iacute;och&aacute;na and competent authorities to carry out their functions and powers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.323" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500003#B01700"><p>Amendment No. 4 is in the name of the Minister.  Amendments Nos. 4 and 5 are related and will be discussed together, by agreement.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.324" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500003#B01800"><p>I move amendment No. 4:<blockquote><br />In page 7, between lines 4 and 5, to insert the following:<br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 104 of Act of 2010</b><b>10. </b>Section 104 of the Act of 2010 is amended by the substitution of the following for subsection (5):<blockquote>&ldquo;(5) The Minister may publish a register in written, electronic or other form and a member of the public is entitled to obtain a copy of a register or of an entry in a register on payment of such reasonable copying charges as may be prescribed (if any).&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote>These are amendments to sections 104 and 109 of the Act of 2010, which respectively deal with registers for trust or company service providers, TCSPs, and persons directing private members clubs.  Chapter 9 deals with the authorisation of TCSPs which fall within my remit as Minister for Justice and Equality under that Act and includes detailed provisions in relation to the granting or refusal of applications for renewals and other related issues.</p><p>  Section 104 provides that the Minister shall establish and maintain a register of persons authorised under this chapter.  Section 104(5) provides that a member of the public is entitled to obtain a copy of the register or of an entry in the register.  The purpose of this amendment is to ensure that such information is more readily available to members of the public and will enable the register to be published on the Department's website.  It will also enable persons seeking to engage in business with such entities to verify that a business is registered, which I think is particularly important.  </p><p>  Section 109 provides that private members gaming clubs which fall within the definition of designated persons under section 25(1)(h) are required to register with the Minister.  Such clubs are monitored for compliance with the money laundering obligations by the anti-money laundering compliance unit in my Department.  The purpose of the first part of the amendment to section 109 is to provide public access to the register and as in the case of TCSPs to provide that the register may be published in written, electronic or other form.</p><p>  The second part of the amendment is to provide for the removal of a club from the register, either at its own request or by the Minister or the anti-money laundering compliance unit, if it is no longer involved in such activities.</p><p>  I commend the amendments to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.326" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1025" speakername="Alan Shatter" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500003#B02000"><p>I move amendment No. 5:<blockquote><br />In page 7, between lines 4 and 5, to insert the following:<br /><b>&ldquo;Amendment of section 109 of Act of 2010</b><b>11. </b>Section 109 of the Act of 2010 is amended by the insertion after subsection (6) of the following subsections:<blockquote>&ldquo;(7) The Minister may publish the register in written, electronic or other form and a member of the public is entitled to obtain a copy of the register or of an entry in the register on payment of such reasonable copying charges as may be prescribed (if any).<br />(8) The particulars entered in the register pursuant to this section relating to a person who is a designated person pursuant to section 25(1)(h) may be removed from the register where that person ceases to be a designated person pursuant to that provision.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.330" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500003#B02400"><p>I thank the Minister and his officials for attending today.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.332" nospeaker="true" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500003#B02600">Message to Dil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.333" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/978" speakername="David Stanton" time="09:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/JUS2013051500003#B02700"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:<blockquote><br /><br />  The Select Committee on Justice, Defence and Equality has completed its consideration of the Criminal Justice (Money Laundering and Terrorist Financing) (Amendment) Bill 2013 and has made amendments thereto.</blockquote></p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.335" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="">Joint Oireachtas Committee on Public Service Oversight and Petitions</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.336" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" ><p>The Joint Committee met at 16:00</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.339" nospeaker="true" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500003#J00100">Decisions on Public Petitions Received</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.340" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500003#J00200"><p>The committee has had an opportunity to deliberate on petition No. P00027/12 from Mr. John O'Sullivan regarding shortcomings in the Employment Appeals Tribunal process.  I open the meeting up to members to summarise our recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.341" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500003#J00300"><p>This particular matter is a significant one.  While the petitioner has had difficulties, there is a public interest issue in a broader sense, which is the committee's focus.  Having read the petition, I would like to invite him to appear before the committee and to notify him that the Minister is considering legislation that might impact on this matter.  If the petitioner is to inform the Minister and the legislative process, inviting him to outline for us the various aspects of his petition, particularly regarding the lodging of a bond and the fact that liquidators do not need to be certified, would be useful.  It would be on the committee's record.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.342" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500003#J00400"><p>I support the Senator's recommendation.  In the interests of openness, transparency and a proper debate, representatives of the employer groups should also be invited so that they might participate.  Doing so would be fair and proper and we would have a balanced discussion on the matter.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.343" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:00:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500003#J00500"><p>This is an important petition - not just for the petitioner, but in light of the wider implications for many people.  A series of firms have been liquidated and employees have been left high and dry - at least, they would see it that way - as regards whether they can have proper recourse.  Our deliberations could feed into suggestions for the legislation.  I agree that we should hear from the petitioner, but we should also hear from representative organisations that have dealt with some of the situations in which workers have been left high and dry.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.345" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1122" speakername="Trevor &Oacute; Clochartaigh" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K00200"><p>The petition points to the role that the committee can play, in that we do not necessarily deal with a person's individual gripe with a system.  Rather, if someone's difficulties highlight a problem with the system, we can make recommendations.</p><p>  I agree with the previous speakers.  If appropriate, it might be useful to invite someone from the Employment Appeals Tribunal to attend our hearing so that we might discuss the matter with him or her.  From my reading of the petition, the person states that the onus appears to be on the employee, the expense is laid on him or her and, even if he or she wins a case, the employer is not compelled to live up to the agreement reached at the tribunal.  It would be interesting to know whether the Employment Appeals Tribunal views this as a systemic problem.  Given the fact that the Bill's heads have not been agreed, this is the ideal time to feed into the debate.  If it is acknowledged generally that an issue exists, it can be addressed in the new legislation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.346" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K00300"><p>To summarise, we will write to the Minister and ask how he specifically proposes to address the issues arising for the petitioner.  We will also invite the petitioner to appear before us, alongside the IMPACT trade union, IBEC-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.347" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K00400"><p>No, MANDATE.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.348" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K00500"><p>My apologies - the MANDATE trade union.  We will also invite IBEC and the Employment Appeals Tribunal.  Is this a fair summary?  Agreed.  We will also write to the petitioner advising him of how matters stand.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  Petition No. P00047/12 is from Mr. Niall Donohoe concerning policy issues with the Defence (Amendment) Act 2007.  We have had an opportunity to deliberate on this petition and I open the floor to members to summarise their recommendations.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.349" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1003" speakername="Richard Boyd Barrett" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K00600"><p>We need to ask people with more relevant expertise for their opinions.  This concerns procedures for making complaints or taking actions against senior officers in the military by lower ranking officers.  The petitioner is claiming that there is no mechanism for doing so, but I suspect that none of us knows.  I suggest that we contact the Permanent Defence Force Other Ranks Representative Association, PDFORRA, which represents rank and file soldiers, and ask whether, in its opinion, this is a substantial issue in the Army that merits an investigation by the committee.  We could have an informed discussion on what to do next.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.350" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K00700"><p>I second that proposal.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.351" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K00800"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.  We will write to PDFORRA and then re-engage with the petitioner.</p><p>  Next is petition No. P00057/12 from Mr. Jason O'Sullivan regarding the removal of roaccutane from the market.  We have deliberated on this petition and I open the floor to members.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.352" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1049" speakername="Michael Healy-Rae" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K00900"><p>This petition has various complexities.  Mr. O'Sullivan has experienced difficulty in dealing with the petition due to the seriousness of his medical situation.  We must push the boat out and offer every support possible to the petitioner.  I support Senator O'Keeffe's suggestion.  Perhaps she will propose it now and I will second it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.353" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1129" speakername="Susan O'Keeffe" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K01000"><p>This process can be off-putting for people who have difficulty engaging with it.  It is up to us to recognise such moments and ask whether a matter of public interest arises.  Of course, one does.  The drug in question has been around for a long time and has been associated with many difficulties, for example, reports of people experiencing serious illnesses and committing suicide.</p><p>  The petition has been brought and we should treat it seriously.  Perhaps we should take the weight off of the petitioner and ask the Irish Medicines Board for its opinion, whether it is satisfied with the list of contra-indications supplied with the drug, whether it is satisfied that those are up to date and whether it has received requests from members of the public, general practitioners, GPs, or consultants to remove the drug from the market.  We could write to the European Medicines Agency in tandem and ask for its advice.  In this way, we can determine the position, leave the petition open and decide on whether to take further action following the organisations' responses.  I hope that this approach will show the petitioner that we are trying to assist him and do not expect him to engage with the process directly.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2013-05-15a.354" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/998" speakername="P&aacute;draig MacLochlainn" time="16:05:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/NVJ2013051500004#K01100"><p>Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p><p>  Petition No. P00018/13 is from Mr. Ronnie "Indeterminable".  It looks like we have gremlins in our system.  We must record petitions in sequence on the system.  Is it agreed that this is an invalid petition?  Agreed.</p><p>  I thank members.  I propose that we adjourn until 4 p.m. on Wednesday, 29 May when we will have a follow-up meeting with Dr. Ambrose McLoughlin, Secretary General of the Department of Health, regarding the legacy issues adverted to by the Ombudsman in her presentation to the committee.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>