<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE publicwhip
[
<!ENTITY aacute "&#225;" >
<!ENTITY eacute "&#233;" >
<!ENTITY iacute "&#237;" >
<!ENTITY oacute "&#243;" >
<!ENTITY uacute "&#250;" >
<!ENTITY yen    "&#165;" >

<!ENTITY Aacute "&#193;" >
<!ENTITY Eacute "&#201;" >
<!ENTITY Iacute "&#205;" >
<!ENTITY Oacute "&#211;" >
<!ENTITY Uacute "&#218;" >
<!ENTITY zcaron  "&#381;" > 
<!ENTITY hellip  "..." >
<!ENTITY bullet  "&#8226;" >
<!ENTITY Dagger  "&#8224;" >
<!ENTITY eth  "&#240;">

<!ENTITY ndash   "&#8211;">
<!ENTITY mdash   "&#8212;">
<!ENTITY iexcl   "&#161;">
<!ENTITY divide  "&#247;">
<!ENTITY euro    "&#8364;">
<!ENTITY trade   "&#8482;">
<!ENTITY bull    "&#8226;">
<!ENTITY lsquo   "&#8216;">
<!ENTITY rsquo   "&#8217;">
<!ENTITY sbquo   "&#8218;">
<!ENTITY ldquo   "&#8220;">
<!ENTITY rdquo   "&#8221;">
<!ENTITY bdquo   "&#8222;">
<!ENTITY dagger  "&#8224;">

<!ENTITY Scaron "&#352;" >
<!ENTITY scaron "&#353;" >
<!ENTITY Ouml   "&#214;" >
<!ENTITY szlig  "&#223;" >
<!ENTITY agrave "&#224;" >
<!ENTITY acirc  "&#226;" >
<!ENTITY atilde "&#227;" >
<!ENTITY auml   "&#228;" >
<!ENTITY ccedil "&#231;" >
<!ENTITY Ccedil "&#199;" >
<!ENTITY egrave "&#232;" >
<!ENTITY Egrave "&#200;" >
<!ENTITY ecirc  "&#234;" >
<!ENTITY euml   "&#235;" >
<!ENTITY icirc  "&#238;" >
<!ENTITY igrave "&#204;" >
<!ENTITY iuml	"&#239;" >
<!ENTITY ntilde "&#241;" >
<!ENTITY nbsp   "&#160;" >
<!ENTITY ocirc  "&#244;" >
<!ENTITY ouml   "&#246;" >
<!ENTITY oslash "&#248;" >
<!ENTITY uuml   "&#252;" >
<!ENTITY thorn  "&#254;" >
<!ENTITY Icirc  "&#206;" >

<!ENTITY pound  "&#163;" >
<!ENTITY sect   "&#167;" >
<!ENTITY copy   "&#169;" >
<!ENTITY reg    "&#174;" >
<!ENTITY deg    "&#176;" >
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#177;" >
<!ENTITY sup2   "&#178;" >
<!ENTITY sup3   "&#179;" >
<!ENTITY micro  "&#181;" >
<!ENTITY para   "&#182;" >
<!ENTITY middot "&#183;" >
<!ENTITY ordm   "&#186;" >
<!ENTITY frac14 "&#188;" >
<!ENTITY frac12 "&#189;" >
<!ENTITY frac34 "&#190;" >
<!ENTITY oelig "&#339;" >
<!ENTITY aelig  "&#230;" >
<!ENTITY Aring  "&#197;" >
<!ENTITY aring  "&#229;" >
]>


<publicwhip scrapeversion="a" latest="yes">
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.2" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="">Select Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.3" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 13:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Dara Calleary, Deputy Gerald Nash (Minister of State at the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation), Deputy Seán Kyne, Deputy Peadar Tóibín. Deputy Anthony Lawlor, Deputy John Lyons,</p><p>DEPUTY MARCELLA CORCORAN KENNEDY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.4" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#A00025">Credit Guarantee (Amendment) Bill 2015: Committee Stage</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.5" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#A00125"><p>As we have a quorum, we can proceed.  Apologies have been received from Deputies &Aacute;ine Collins and John Lyons.  This meeting has been convened to consider the Credit Guarantee (Amendment) Bill 2015, referred to the select committee by order of the D&aacute;il of 26 November 2015.  I welcome the Minister of State with responsibility for business and employment, Deputy Nash, and his officials to the meeting.  Before we begin, I ask members to switch their phones to safe or flight mode; it is not sufficient to put them in silent mode as that maintains the level of interference in the committee room and impacts negatively on the broadcast.  Some 30 amendments have been tabled and it is proposed we will consider the Bill until we conclude Committee Stage.  Is that agreed?  Agreed.  </p> <p>  A list of amendments grouped for the purposes of debate has been circulated.  We will commence our consideration of the Bill.  Amendments Nos. 1 and 2 are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.6" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.7" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#A00325"><p>I move amendment No. 1:</p><blockquote>In page 3, between lines 7 and 8, to insert the following:<div>&ldquo;PART 1<br /><br />PRELIMINARY AND GENERAL</div><b>Short title, commencement and collective citation</b><b>1. </b>(1) This Act may be cited as the Credit Guarantee (Amendment) Act 2015.<blockquote>(2) This Act shall come into operation on such day or days as the Minister may appoint by order or orders either generally or with reference to any particular purpose or provision and different days may be so appointed for different purposes or different provisions.<br /><br />(3) This Act and the Credit Guarantee Act 2012 may be cited together as the Credit Guarantee Acts 2012 and 2015.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>On Second Stage of the Bill in November, I indicated I would bring forward some technical amendments on Committee Stage which would improve the drafting and publication of the Bill.  The Government also agreed to a proposal by the Minister for Finance that the Departments of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation and Finance would work together on any necessary additional amendments to the Bill relating to a role for the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland, SBCI.  </p><p>I informed the House it was intended to move Committee Stage amendments to provide for a new section setting out in law the detailed criteria under which the Minister shall calculate premiums, primarily that they should not exceed the level needed to defray or partially defray the costs of the scheme, and clarifications to ensure finance providers meet applicable law in respect of the conduct of their business under the legislation.  </p><p>These technical amendments were circulated last week and cover premium setting and clarification of the need for finance providers to meet all appropriate legal requirements before being eligible to benefit from the guarantees.  These changes will impact on sections 5 and 8 dealing with the power of the Minister to make schemes in consultation with colleagues in the Departments of Finance and Public Expenditure and Reform and his powers to set different premia for different schemes.</p><p>In addition I indicated there would be important changes in a new and separate part of the Bill under the following headings.  One, provision for State promotion of financial institutions that will in future work with the Minister through this legislation to enhance provision of credit to SMEs and two, a role for the Minister to be able to give counter guarantees intended to enable promotion of financial institutions to unlock matching guarantee facilities from EU sources and share the risk across banks; and the promotion of finance providers, for example, the SBCI, the Minister and a number of potential EU sources.  In respect of the latter, it is envisaged this counter guarantee would operate in conjunction with the leveraging of related EU financial instruments in this area, such as the European Programme for Competitiveness of SMEs, COSME, Horizon 2020 funding earmarked for SMEs and the European Fund for Strategic Investment, EFSI, administered by the European Investment Bank and the European Investment Fund - the Juncker plan.  In this way Ireland will be able to optimise its return from major EU initiatives.  </p><p>My Department and the Department of Finance completed work with the Office of the Attorney General on these points and the appropriate revisions were circulated to the House last week.  The amendments are, by and large, contained in a new Part 3 of the Bill, sections 9 to 15, inclusive.  Arising from the additional part, there are some technical amendments to the earlier parts of the Bill which I will flag as we proceed.</p><p>During the debate on Second Stage I stressed that the overarching economic need to ensure Irish firms had the full suite of financial and other supports available to enable them to compete internationally was paramount.  The Bill and the additional revisions to it will ensure that in the area of credit guarantees, Ireland will have a framework that will be more than just fit for purpose, covering an extensive suite of products, it will ensure we will have the ability to make best use of the EU funding made available to member states by means of risk-sharing financial instruments.  The Bill and the Committee Stage amendments I have outlined, particularly those that will facilitate the leveraging of EU funding, will significantly benefit firms, employees, SMEs and the economy at large.</p><p> I flag to the committee my intention to submit three further amendments on Report Stage which will impact on employment rights, the Workplace Relations Act and the Companies Act.  They are purely technical in nature and will enable the recently enacted legislation to be fully effective.  </p><p> As I said, the Bill and the Committee Stage amendments contain major changes to the 2012 Act.  One of the proposals is that the original section 1, with its brief definition of the principal Act, be deleted.  A Part 1 break is being inserted and the new section 1 will deal with citations and the like, mirroring section 10 of the 2012 Act.  The new section 2 will contain the necessary definitions of "Minister" and "Principal Act" which currently are included with other definitions but which are being moved because they apply to all parts of the Bill, with section 1 being deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.9" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.10" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B00300"><p>I move amendment No. 2:</p><blockquote><b>2. </b>In page 3, between lines 7 and 8, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Definitions</b><b>2. </b>In this Act&mdash;<br /><br />&ldquo;Minister&rdquo; means the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation; <br /><br />&ldquo;Principal Act&rdquo; means the Credit Guarantee Act 2012.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.11" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.12" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 1 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.13" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 2 agreed to. 

SECTION 3</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.14" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B00700"><p>I move amendment No. 3:</p><blockquote>In page 6, between lines 29 and 30, to insert the following:&ldquo;(c) the finance provider is a crowd funder which operates as a credit facility and its liquidity is sourced from the general public and provides loans to businesses in a peer to peer arrangement.<br /><br />(d) the finance provider is a credit union which operates in Ireland under Central Bank regulations.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>Much of the debate on the credit guarantee scheme from its inception has been about the fact that the banking system is broken.  These are new products that have been designed to fill the gaps left by the banking system which is not working properly.  We have, to all intents and purposes, an oligopoly in the State and need to make sure we have other elements in the credit system that can function properly and add to the choices for consumers of credit.  The amendment deals with two unloved sectors of the credit ecosystem.  </p><p>It is welcome that the Minister of State has broadened the credit facilities that may be used in the future under the Bill.  However, on Second Stage I brought to his attention the necessity of using crowd funding as an opportunity for the State to funnel cash towards small businesses.  In Britain, for example, 10% of all crowd funding loans are backed by the State.  The sector is very small here and it is finding it hard to gain traction owing to the lack of backup from the State.  That is why it is necessary for the Government to include crowd funding as part of the credit guarantee process.  </p><p>The second area about which the amendment speaks is the credit union sector.  We dealt with a Private Member's Bill recently and representatives of the credit union movement appeared before the joint committee.  The credit unions stated they had &euro;13 billion in capital for which they needed a home.  They also referred to the fact that they were very well regulated and had come through the crash unscathed in comparison to the banking sector.  In that context, I call on the Minister of State to make sure these two key components which will provide opportunities in the future, in terms of credit, are included.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.15" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B00800"><p>I welcome the amendments proposed which will make this a far superior Bill to the one originally published.  I hope it will have the impact we all desire.  I commend the Minister of State for the work he has done on this issue since he took office.</p> <p>  I support Deputy Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n's amendment.  The credit union movement is open for business and very keen to get involved in SME lending, in particular.  Unfortunately, however, it is being rebuffed at every opportunity in being allowed to exploit its asset base and encourage its membership which is locally based to support locally rooted SMEs.  The obstruction is in the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation but in the Department of Finance and the Office of the Financial Regulator.  This is an opportunity to rebrand the scheme.  The success of Microfinance Ireland since its reorganisation is a clear indication of the demand for small-scale SME lending.  The credit union movement and crowd funders are ideally suited to meet that demand.  Several crowd funders have made presentations to the joint committee.  What could be done through this channel is phenomenal, particularly for new enterprises and start-up companies which are still finding it very difficult to obtain funding.  Crowd funders are ideally situated and the inclusion of such funds would truly bring the Bill into the 21st century.  We should partner with crowd funders and the credit union movement in the provision of SME funding.  The credit union movement is very keen to get involved, but it is being rebuffed at every turn by the Government.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.16" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B00900"><p>In response to Deputy Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n's amendment, in extending the scope of the legislation and introducing additional flexibility, there will be scope to examine how a range of finance providers can operate under the Bill.  I cannot accede to the amendment which relates specifically to crowd funding and credit unions.  As far as the Government is concerned, these provisions are not exhaustive and we do not believe there is a need in primary legislation to explicitly refer to finance providers or the sectors in which they operate.  The scope of the scheme is broad enough to allow these two operations to be accommodated in what we are trying to achieve.  Fundamentally, this is about ensuring we will have alternative sources of finance for SMEs, in particular.  The Bill is sufficiently broad to accommodate what Deputies Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n and Dara Calleary wish to achieve.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.17" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B01000"><p>On Second Stage the Minister of State said crowd funding could not be included because its definition was not tight enough.  I now understand he is saying there is a possibility, given the breadth of the Bill, that crowd funders could be included in the future.  Will he give me a commitment that they will be so included?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.18" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B01100"><p>We are satisfied that the scope of the Bill is broad enough to provide for the alternative financing arrangements to which Deputy Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n refers.  Section 2(1)(b) provides that the "finance provider stands approved for the time being by the Minister in accordance with this section".  This is sufficiently broad to cater for what the Deputy wants to achieve.  We are all trying to provide alternative financing arrangements.  We all know that different arrangements are required for the SME sector, in particular.  That is what the Bill and our proposed amendments are about.  I am satisfied that we can achieve the Deputy's objective.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.19" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B01200"><p>It would improve the legislation if we were to be upfront and say credit unions and crowd funders would be part of the scheme apparatus.  We are not making it exclusive to them, but the fact that we would incorporate them in the legislation would show that we took them seriously as organisations with a role to play in the provision of financing for SMEs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.20" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B01300"><p>We are taking them seriously.  As I said, there is sufficient scope and flexibility to ensure we will have as broad a range of alternative financing arrangements for SMEs as possible.  We are taking this issue seriously, but we do not want to go down the road of specifically identifying in primary legislation different sectors because that could tie our hands in terms of the extent and breadth of any scheme introduced.  I suggest the Bill is sufficiently broad to cater for the objectives of the amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.21" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#B01400"><p>As Opposition Deputies, we have an opportunity to discuss what the Bill states and will do.  If we simply agree that it should be left to the Minister to decide what should be included in the scheme at some point in the future, we abdicate our responsibility as Opposition Deputies to the different sectors that are components of a functioning and healthy economy.</p><p>If we simply decide that it should be left to a Minister to decide some day in the future on what should or should not be included, we, as Opposition Deputies, are obviously abdicating our responsibilities to the different sectors of a functioning and healthy economy.  It is our job to ensure we build legislation correctly from the start, rather than leave it as a husk to be filled by a future Minister in whatever way he or she wants to fill it.</p><p> The Minister of State said on Second Stage that crowd funding would not be included in this legislation because he could not get a definition for it and the fact he would not give a commitment that it will be included in the future gives me no confidence in this legislation.  One of the key points put forward by the credit unions when they made presentations to the Oireachtas was their deep frustration in regard to the limiting of their ability to function within the SME sector.  It is difficult to understand that in a credit squeeze, the sector that least abused its position now feels it is being limited by the Government and Central Bank regulations with regard to trying to provide small loans to small businesses.</p><p> I would not mind so much if the Minister of State told me credit unions could be involved, but could only provide microfinance, like Microfinance Ireland for example which has a &euro;50,000 or &euro;75,000 ceiling on its ability to loan.  I would agree that this would be a prudent first step in their foray into this space.  In representing these sectors, SMEs and entrepreneurs in society, we as Opposition Deputies should at least commit to ensuring that they will be included in this scheme in the future.  Otherwise, we are just involved in creating loose legislation that does not address the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.23" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#C00200"><p>We in the Department and I, as a constituency Deputy, are in constant contact with the credit union sector, as is the Department of Finance, in regard to the role of credit unions and how that will evolve in the context of the SME sector.  We have asked the credit unions to bring forward proposals in that regard.  As far as I understand, there has been no significant detail from the credit unions regarding how they intend to operate in that sector in the future.  The Government and the Oireachtas should be always mindful of the role credit unions and other alternative financiers and finance organisations can play in supporting the SME sector.</p> <p>  Clearly there is a difference of opinion between us and the Deputy in regard to how we accommodate the role of the credit unions, crowd funders and others, but the definition of "finance providers" in this legislation is sufficiently wide to include crowd funders and credit unions.  However, what we do not want to do is to arrive at a position where we list off in an exhaustive way the type of funding arrangements and providers that would or could be considered in the context of any scheme to the point where we might end up excluding some.  This is a rapidly evolving area, nationally and internationally, so the definition is left open enough to allow for the development of crowd funding and how it will be defined in the future.  I am satisfied we have sufficient flexibility here to allow us to achieve that and to do the things Deputies T&oacute;ib&iacute;n and Calleary want to see happen.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.24/1" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#D00100"><p>Amendment put:Amendment put:</p><p>The Committee divided: Tá, 2; Níl, 5.</p><br/><br/><p></p></speech>
        <division id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.24/2" nospeaker="true" divdate="2015-12-08" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#D00100">
            <divisioncount ayes="2" noes="5" />
                <mplist vote="aye">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/" vote="aye"></mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/" vote="aye"></mpname>
                </mplist>
                <mplist vote="no">
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/" vote="no"></mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/" vote="no"></mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/" vote="no"></mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/" vote="no"></mpname>
                    <mpname id="com.kildarestreet/member/" vote="no"></mpname>
                </mplist>
        </division>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.24/3" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#D00100"><p>Amendment declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.25" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#D00200"><p>I move amendment No. 4:</p><blockquote>In page 7, between lines 14 and 15, to insert the following:&ldquo;(5) The Minister will commission a report within 3 months of the Act becoming operational outlining how the Credit Guarantee Scheme can help make it easier for businesses that owe money to banks exiting the Irish SME market to refinance those debts with domestic institutions.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>Given the difficulties with this scheme in the past and how important it is to get this one right, I propose that we get a report within three months to ensure that the scheme, as redesigned, is meeting its objectives and that we do not see the kind of delays we saw on the last occasion.  Concerns were highlighted early in the lifetime of the last scheme and were ignored, which resulted in many of the delays.  This amendment aims to prevent any such difficulties and to ensure that all the objectives of the scheme are met.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.26" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#D00300"><p>I thank the Deputy for his words.  I know he is particularly interested in the scheme and we have spoken about it.  I am not accepting amendment No. 4 which deals with a specific matter which is not appropriate for legislation.  The Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, the banks and other finance providers and the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland, SBCI, will actively promote the revised system and ensure that businesses are aware of the possibilities available under the new schemes and the Department will report on progress on a quarterly basis.  It is open to the Minister under the current scheme to review it frequently, to publish reviews of the scheme and to identify if there are problems.  We have had a comprehensive review and are trying to fix the problems identified.  There is provision to conduct regular reviews which would be published and brought to the attention of the Oireachtas and it is appropriate that be the case but that it be done on a case by case basis.  If there are problems with the operation of new schemes and the new provisions provided for here, we will certainly do that but I will not accept Deputy Calleary&rsquo;s amendment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.27" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.28" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E00200"><p>Amendment No. 5 is in the name of Deputy Calleary.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.29" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E00300"><p>Before I move the amendment, I would like to seek clarification from the Minister of State.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.30" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E00400"><p>Amendment No. 5 is a logical alternative to 22, 23, 25, 27, 28 and 30 and so those amendments will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.31" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E00500"><p>I move amendment No. 5:</p><blockquote>In page 7, between lines 14 and 15, to insert the following:&ldquo;(5) (a) The Minister shall work with his colleague in the Department of Finance to facilitate a role for State promotional financial institutions such as the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland in the scheme in order to enhance the provision of credit to SMEs directly.<br /><br />(b) The Minister shall be empowered to give counter-guarantees designed to enable State promotional financial institutions access to match guarantee facilities from EU funding sources such as Horizon 2020 funds earmarked for SMEs and the European Fund for Strategic Investment.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>We feel there should be a role for SBCI in this scheme enhancement and also with regard to other State promotion of financial institutions and EU funding.  It is obviously an aim shared by the Government and in that context, given that it is effectively the same amendment as amendment No. 22, I am happy to withdraw it. </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.32" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E00600"><p>That is precisely the point I was going to make.  It is probably sufficiently answered by Part 3 of the Bill in terms of the SBCI and its role as a promotional financial institution.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.33" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E00700"><p>To clarify, will the Minister's section allow SBCI to directly provide credit to SMEs?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.34" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E00800"><p>No, it will allow it to provide the counter guarantee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.35" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E00900"><p>To provide the counter guarantee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.36" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01000"><p>Yes, to provide the counter guarantee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.37" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01100"><p>There are no changes with regard to SBCI.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.38" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01200"><p>No, it is already providing credit through the on lenders but this is in the context of it operating under a counter guarantee scheme and operating the counter guarantee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.39" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01300"><p>Separate legislation would be necessary to change the SBCI system but it is important to say that the SBCI has to go through a pillar bank or another form of lending to have access to consumers which limits its engagement and ability to lend.  Often the pillar banks have proven that they simply do not feel the need to promote SBCI funding.  I have heard from firms that went to a bank for SBCI-type funds but the bank asked them to consider the bank's funds instead.  In that way they were diverted from the fund and the process fell apart.  In its report today, the Central Bank talks about the limited competition in the State.  It is important to find a role for SBCI to lend directly to SMEs in the future.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.40" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01400"><p>The SBCI is a new part of the landscape and something we all welcome from the point of view of competition.  The SBCI is working extremely hard to promote the opportunities available to those who cannot access particular types of finance through the pillar banks or are in a particular set of circumstances   We are anxious to ensure that SBCI products are available and are front and centre in terms of the offering of the pillar banks, in their roles, essentially, of on lenders for the SBCI.  It would be useful to reflect on the performance of the SBCI in its infancy.  It has only been in operation for a few short months in terms of the first products it is providing.  In recent weeks, agreements have been signed with two new on lenders - Finance Ireland and Merrion Fleet Management.  We are hopeful that SBCI will continue to expand its operation and work with other finance providers over the next period of time.  Up to 30 September 2015, &euro;110 million in SME loans were approved and drawn down by 3,200 SMEs and more than 90% of those were for investment purposes.  It would be useful for the committee to know that close to one third of the loans drawn down were in the agricultural sector and the average loan size is &euro;35,000.  There is also a strong regional focus; the bulk of the loans drawn down under the aegis of the SBCI were outside of Dublin.  That is something we all welcome.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.41" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01500"><p>There were also some in north Dublin.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.42" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01600"><p>There were a few in north Dublin.  I know some very productive farmers there and farming is a very important part of the economy in north Dublin.  SBCI has been a very welcome addition to the landscape over the last few months and is performing very well in the short period it has been in existence.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.43" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1053" speakername="Anthony Lawlor" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01700"><p>I concur with that having attended a number of SBCI briefings through the banks.  Will the Minister of State encourage SBCI to use its new partners to get out there to meet people?  I welcome competition and if SBCI is to be part of that competition pillar, it is important for it to get out there through its new agencies so it is not all seen to come through the two pillar banks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.44" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E01800"><p>The Deputy may have been at the ploughing championships, as I and others in the House were.  There was a very strong representation there from SBCI; its representatives talked to the agricultural community about the possibilities that are available through SBCI.  At Taking Care of Business events, the Department includes dozens of agencies which are under its aegis and which operate in the SME space.  The SBCI has been very involved in that, not only by having representation at those events but by ensuring they are front and centre at seminars so that SMEs right across the country are familiar with the products available through on lenders.  The SBCI offering is being improved and enhanced all the time.  It is considered to be a promotional financial institution and is the first of its kind in this country.  It has received a mandate from Government to do a particular piece of work and has accessed funding from Europe and the Pension Reserve Fund to do that.  At present, it is the only PFI in Ireland and it was created to increase competition where it is needed in the SME sector.  It will make a big impact.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.45" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment, by leave, withdrawn.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.46" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 3 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.47" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>SECTION 4</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.48" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E02200"><p>Amendments Nos. 6, 7 and 24 are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.49" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E02300"><p>I move amendment No. 6:</p><blockquote>In page 7, line 17, after &ldquo;section&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;and <i>section 11</i>of the <i>Credit Guarantee (Amendment) Act 2015</i>&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>Section 4 of the principal Act, entitled &quot;Power of Minister to give guarantees&quot;, contained a number of important elements including the spread of risk and an effective monetary cap of &euro;11.25 million on the State's contingent liability being the product of the 75% limit on individual loans in subsection (<i>2</i>), the 10% portfolio cap in subsection (<i>3</i>) and the &euro;150 million aggregate limit in subsection (<i>4</i>).  One of the main findings of the review that led to this legislation and these amendments in the first place was that the risk elements were disproportionately skewed in favour of the State.  The Government agreed to increase the 75% and 10% figures to 80% and 13%, respectively.  The latter is in line with State aid requirements and advice we received.  Another implication of this is that the State's maximum contingent liability also increases to &euro;15.6 million and the Government decided that the combination of both credit and counter guarantees should have this combined ceiling of &euro;15.6 million.  For that reason, there are linking cross references to the new section 11 on counter guarantees.  I commend these amendments to the committee.  </p><p>The purpose of amendment No. 24 is to place a maximum monetary limit on the liability that the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation can incur in any one year from entering into both the credit and counter guarantee schemes.  This amendment will ensure that the Minister does not enter into any combination of credit guarantees and counter guarantees that would exceed a maximum monetary limit of &euro;15.6 million in any one year.  The Department will ensure adherence to this overall limit by stipulating in each counter guarantee scheme an agreement with promotional financial institutions, the methodology by which the limit cannot be exceeded.  I commend the amendment to the committee.  </p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.50" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E02400"><p>On the issue of the ceiling of &euro;15.6 million, is that the amount of guarantees that would exist in any one year?  Will the Minister of State talk me through that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.51" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#E02500"><p>It is the combined exposure from the operation of the credit guarantee scheme and the counter guarantee scheme.  One of the reasons we are including the SBCI here - there is broad agreement as to why we should - is to leverage support from European institutions, such as COSME, and from the Horizon 2020 initiative.  We want to ensure that we spread the risk in many ways.</p><p>There are good reasons for doing that and ensuring liabilities and exposures to the State are limited.  We have the cap of &euro;15.6 million.  That is the equation that is factored into this.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.53" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F00200"><p>To what specifically does that relate?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.54" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F00300"><p>The limit is &euro;150 million.  Under the counter guarantee scheme, the lending that can take place to small and medium enterprises is &euro;200 million.  The credit guarantee scheme limit and the counter guarantee scheme limit is combined.  I have lost my train of thought.  I reflected on this earlier but I will reiterate it.  Section 4 of the principal Act, entitled power of Minister to give guarantees, contained a number of important elements, including the spread of risk and an effective monetary cap of &euro;11.25 million.  That is being increased to take into account the counter guarantee scheme as well.  There is a 75% limit on individual loans in subsection (2); a 10% portfolio cap in subsection (3); and a &euro;150 million aggregate limit in subsection (4).</p> <p>  We have changed the equation a little.  For example, one of the main findings of the review was that risk elements were disproportionately skewed in favour of the State, so we are sharing the risk across the different institutions.  With the inclusion of the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland, SBCI, we are allowed to leverage more resources and risk across the various European financial initiatives as well.  The Government agreed to increase the 75% and 10% figures to 80% and 13%, respectively.  The latter is in line with state aid requirements and as Deputies are aware, there are serious state aid issues relating to how these types of schemes are operated right across the European Union.  This is fundamentally concerned with designing it to ensure there is a risk appetite from the financial providers to take on the responsibility of providing more resources to the small and medium enterprise, SME, sector.</p> <p>  The old limit was &euro;11.25 million with respect to exposure of the State but that is now up to &euro;15.6 million.  That would be the absolute maximum.  By sharing the risk, the bulk of the risk is not now being taken by the State.  We wanted to ensure the appetite for taking on this risk was spread more evenly across different agencies and institutions.  That will succeed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.55" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F00400"><p>What are the practical implications for somebody seeking support under the credit guarantee scheme?  If I make an application, how will this limit impact on my business?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.56" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F00500"><p>There will be more institutions involved with this arrangement.  The risk is spread and we are trying to bring people along with us on this.  The experience of the scheme did not meet our expectations initially and we are broadening it and including the SBCI.  There will be more success in doing this.  In spreading the risk, more SMEs will become involved.  We need to promote this, which is very important, and there will be higher coverage of individual loans.  This is going to work.  The 75% figure has been increased to 80%, which might be relatively marginal, but it will work, according to our calculations.  We want people to use this to its fullest extent so that as many lenders can be involved as is possible.  As I said earlier, we are not excluding any form of alternative financing arrangements.  We went into the details of that earlier.  We believe this will succeed but we want to fundamentally ensure the exposure for the State is limited.  By including the SBCI and leveraging additional resources from Europe, we can spread that risk.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.57" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F00600"><p>Given that there will be &euro;15.6 million of risk to the State, what is the ratio between level of risk to the State and the total amount of funds expected to be delivered?  There is a ratio between level of risk and the total of amount of lending expected to be delivered through the system.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.58" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F00700"><p>The Act placed the maximum limit on the value of funds that could be lent to SMEs at &euro;150 million per annum.  If we consider that in the context of the &euro;15.6 million, it is fairly limited.  We are trying to spread the risk and increase the appetite of lenders so they can get involved in the process.  This will achieve that goal.  There is much potential to increase lending without a commensurate increase to the risk and exposure for the State.  That is why we must get the balance right.  We want to make as many resources available to the SME sector as possible but at the same time making sure that the taxpayer is not exposed.</p> <p>  The overall amount of additional lending that can take place will depend on a range of different factors, as well as the number and type of schemes that will be operated under this legislation, the Minister's participation and each counter guarantee scheme.  There is &euro;150 million available per annum but the exposure is capped.  It is important that we send a message to the taxpayer that there is a limit and exposure would be limited.</p> <p>  These are very significant funds that will be made available to the SME sector and we need to promote this very strongly over the next period.  The Irish Small and Medium Enterprises, ISME, association report from late last week indicated that an understanding and appreciation of the credit guarantee scheme is growing, which is useful.  Similarly, with Microfinance Ireland there is an understanding of its work and what is available there, which is useful from an SME perspective.  This is a demand-led scheme so we cannot at this point measure how many SMEs want to become involved.  Nor can we measure precisely the type of demands on the scheme over the next period.  We will be promoting this new approach, along with banks and institutions like the SBCI.  Departments, Ministers and agencies will promote this because it needs to be promoted.  People must have a clear understanding of what this could mean for business and the risks involved.  This can work.  It has been a long time in genesis but we want to reduce the risk, in so far as we can, to the State while at the same time making as many funds available to the SME sector.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.59" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F00800"><p>I understand there is currently &euro;20 billion of lending to SMEs and, considering the size of that figure, exposing the State to &euro;15 million of lending, with 40% of it in default, does not seem very ambitious.  To tease it further, what are the expectations?  When this credit guarantee scheme was initially announced, it was indicated that X amount of firms would be affected with X number of jobs to be created, etc.  What is the range of objectives for this change?  How many firms will be affected?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.60" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F00900"><p>It is a demand-led scheme.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.61" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F01000"><p>When the scheme was first launched, it was very clear that X number of jobs would be created with X number of firms affected.  Is the Government rowing back on delivering expectations on this?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.62" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#F01100"><p>No.  I can clarify the numbers to the best of my recollection.  Just under 1,000 jobs have been supported by the credit guarantee scheme and we cannot put any ceiling on our ambition with regard to the number of jobs that would be maintained and supported.  During the difficult years of 2012 and 2013 - the early years of the scheme's operation - we had to value the role that the scheme played, albeit in a limited way, in maintaining jobs.  This was when people were trying to keep the doors open over the past number of years.</p> <p>  There are major possibilities for the scheme but they will very much depend on the way in which this is promoted.  Of course, the scheme will benefit SMEs by enabling them to access credit where they would not otherwise be able to obtain it.  That is the point, as the purpose of developing the scheme in the first place was to ensure that we could address a market failure during a very difficult time for banks.  As bank balance sheets continue to be repaired and as those institutions develop a greater appetite for providing financing in the normal way, the role of this scheme and the SBCI may evolve.  New products and markets will come on stream and new possibilities will emerge.</p> <p>  One of the fundamental points is that the SBCI's involvement is crucial from a counter guarantee perspective.</p><p>It would facilitate the combination of the scheme with other opportunities and other sources of risk sharing capital from Europe, significantly increasing the amount of resources available for SMEs.  We are not rowing back on this.  We recognise that this scheme has had a limited effect and did not achieve its original ambitions and that is why we are here today, to try to fix that and to ensure we are happy to accept the changes proposed in the review.  We have had that discussion on Second Stage and at other fora.  We want to champion and introduce changes that will make this scheme more attractive, to lead to an improved situation for SMEs and increased use and awareness by banks of what is available through the scheme and other finance providers.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.64" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.65" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G00300"><p>I move amendment No. 7:</p><blockquote>In page 7, line 23, after &ldquo;subsection (3)&rdquo; to insert &ldquo;and <i>section 11 </i>of the <i>Credit Guarantee (Amendment) Act 2015&quot;.</i></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.66" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.67" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G00500"><p>Amendments Nos. 8 to 11, inclusive, are related and may be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.68" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G00600"><p>I move amendment No. 8:</p><p>In page 7, between lines 39 and 40, to insert the following:</p><blockquote>&ldquo;(5) The Minister shall, in relation to a credit guarantee scheme, after consultation with the participating finance provider concerned, and by notice in writing given to the provider, specify the maximum value of financial products that may be provided by that provider pursuant to qualifying finance agreements&mdash;<blockquote>(a) entered into in any year, and<br /><br />(b) to which guarantees under this section apply.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>These amendments apply to a new subsection 5 being inserted which is designed to achieve certainty on transitioning between years.  This also necessitates the re-numbering of the following sections.  I commend these amendments to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.69" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.70" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G00800"><p>I move amendment No. 9:</p><blockquote>In page 7, line 40, to delete &ldquo;(5) The Minister&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;(6) The Minister&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.71" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.72" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G01000"><p>I move amendment No. 10:</p><blockquote>In page 8, line 5, to delete &ldquo;(6) An agreement&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;(7) An agreement&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.73" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.74" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G01200"><p>I move amendment No. 11:</p><blockquote>In page 8, line 7, to delete &ldquo;(7) In this&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;(8) In this&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.75" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.76" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 4, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.77" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>SECTION 5</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.78" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G01600"><p>Amendments Nos. 12, 19, 20 and 26 are related and may be discussed together.  Amendment No. 20 is a physical alternative to No. 19.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.79" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G01700"><p>I move amendment No. 12:</p><blockquote>In page 8, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:&ldquo;(iv) by the substitution of the following paragraph for paragraph (d):<blockquote>&ldquo;(d) without prejudice to the generality of section 8(4), the method of payment of the premium under section 8 and the time or times at which the premium shall be paid;&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote> <p>I will discuss amendments Nos. 12, 19, 20 and 26.  Section 5 of the principal Act is primarily about the schemes made under legislation to date, namely during 2012 and 2015.  The amendments to section 5 of the Bill are to ensure new schemes can adequately cover the expanded types of financial products to be covered.  There are also some amendments covering matters flagged on Second Stage, particularly subsection (d) which is a necessary cross reference to the correct part of the new section 8 on policies and principles on the matter of charging a premium to cover the Minister's costs.  I will return to this topic later.  I commend amendment No. 12 to the committee.</p><p>Regarding amendment No. 19, section 8 of the principal Act relates to payment of premia to the Minister.  The substitution is designed to take account of the types of products and the need for flexibility in the rate referred to.  By this approach we have, in effect, already gone a long way towards accepting the principle of Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n's amendments and the revised section 8 meets his requirement which regards credit unions and crowd funding, while also ensuring appropriate scope for flexible application of the legislation.  I commend the revised section 8 to the committee.</p><p>I will now turn to amendment No. 26.  Under the current legislation on credit guarantees, the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation receives a premium in respect of the guarantees issued.  This amendment provides that the charging structure for the counter guarantee schemes operates within the charging structures and principles contained in the Bill.  It will be designed to ensure the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation will receive the same level of premium adjusted to reflect the level of risk to which the Minister is exposed in each counter guarantee scheme.  When determining the level of premium, the Minister must have regard to a number of factors as set out in the amendment.  These include the objectives of the scheme and the likely expense of running the scheme.  The manner in which the premium will be calculated must be clearly set out in each counter guarantee scheme.  The amendment provides that the premium for a counter guarantee can only be used towards defraying the cost of the scheme.  In this way the cost of the premium will be kept as low as possible for the SMEs accessing finance under such schemes.  I commend the amendment to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.80" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G01800"><p>I tabled amendment No. 20 because credit is too expensive in this State, be it for those in mortgage distress who are paying a premium over their counterparts throughout Europe or small businesses who are paying a premium over that being charged to European banks - and this is even outside the credit guarantee scheme.  Paying for credit at such an enormous rate is a competitive disadvantage for Irish SMEs.  The credit rate might have been acceptable at a time when the banks were actually in a loss making situation and needed to make profits but we have seen some massive profits come from the banks in recent times.  The Department of Finance has struggled to excuse the differential that currently exists in this State <i>vis-&agrave;-vis</i>European counterparts.</p><p>There seems to be some rowing back on the 2% premium within the Government's own amendments.  Will the Minister for State indicate if within the Government's amendments, other than the administrative costs of the loans, there is no existing premium within the credit guarantee scheme?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.81" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G01900"><p>We are allowing for premia of less than 2% in certain cases.  The legislation provides for flexibility in the premia that can apply to schemes.  Any premium can only be used towards defraying the costs of the operation of the scheme.  A case could be made, when looking at future schemes, to take an approach to a particular sector and design a specific scheme - or if there is an attractive opportunity to do that -  in order to address a structural problem in a targeted way for example.  The premium could be reduced or amended to assist that sector.  Flexibility is included to allow this to happen.  The 2% premium is still there but there is flexibility.  The 2% applies to the credit guarantee scheme and the counter guarantee scheme and absolutely goes towards defraying the costs of the credit guarantee scheme which applies to the enterprise.  The 2% premium is understood but it can be adapted and made flexible to respond to evolving needs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.82" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G02000"><p>The problem is that the 2% premium is part of the reason this scheme has not been successful so far.  Credit is already too expensive for small businesses out there.  When one is operating on low margins and running very tight cash flow levels, 2% is a significant difference in terms of credit.  In a mortgage situation for example, any family who pays 5.3% will know the difference on their monthly repayments to a family who pays 3.3%.  I do not understand why the Government is taking a very minimalist approach to providing a line of credit to a small business.  I want to make sure that everybody is covered with regard to costs and that nobody gets stung with the premium rate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.83" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#G02100"><p>The 2% premium is the case for now and that is understood, but it is not expressly specified in he Bill as flexibility is required to be able to respond where needed.  For example, if a particular scheme is targeted at a specific sector experiencing difficulties with structural problems, flexibility would be needed to reduce the cost of the premium, if a case could be made.  Flexibility is enshrined in the Bill to allow a response to those situations.  I hope colleagues can support this.  The figure of 2% is the understood rate at the moment and there is a cost involved in operating a scheme like this.  These are resources that would be flown to SMEs that would not otherwise find their way to SMEs, in the absence of a scheme like this.  While there is a cost involved, the premium can only be used to defray the costs of the scheme's operation.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.84" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.85" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H00200"><p>Amendments Nos. 13 to 18, inclusive, are related and will be discussed together.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.86" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H00300"><p>I move amendment No. 13:</p><blockquote>In page 9, to delete lines 10 to 12 and substitute &ldquo;person who has, subject to subsection (6), a controlling interest in the finance provider,&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>Section 5 of the principal Act is primarily about the schemes made under the legislation to date, in 2012 and 2015.  The amendments to section 5 of the Bill are primarily about making sure that any or all new schemes can adequately cover the expanded types of financial products to be covered.  There are also some amendments covering matters I flagged on Second Stage, including some clarifications on the way in which the Minister is to obtain information, records and so on relating to the diverse types of finance providers and the need to ensure that all finance providers are compliant with all appropriate regulatory requirements.  I commend this group of amendments to the committee.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.87" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.88" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H00500"><p>I move amendment No. 14:</p><blockquote>In page 9, to delete line 39.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.89" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.90" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H00700"><p>I move amendment No. 15:</p><blockquote>In page 10, line 12, to delete &ldquo;and&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.91" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.92" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H00900"><p>I move amendment No. 16:</p><blockquote>In page 10, line 15, to delete &ldquo;scheme applies.&rdquo;.&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;scheme applies, and&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.93" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.94" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H01100"><p>I move amendment No. 17:</p><blockquote>In page 10, between lines 15 and 16, to insert the following:<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;(e) the methodology referred to in section 8(1).&rdquo;,&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.95" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.96" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H01300"><p>I move amendment No.18:</p><blockquote>In page 10, between lines 15 and 16, to insert the following:&ldquo;and<blockquote>(d) by the insertion of the following subsections after subsection (4):<blockquote>&ldquo;(5) (a) The Minister may require that any information referred to in subsection (2)(a) given to him or her by a person in compliance with a scheme under this section be attested as to the truth of the information by a statutory declaration made by that person.<blockquote>(b) The Minister may require that any document, information or report referred to in subsection (2)(f) given to him or her by a finance provider in compliance with a scheme under this section be attested as to the truth of the contents of the document or report or, as the case may be, as to the truth of the information, by a statutory declaration made by that finance provider.</blockquote>(6) For the purposes of this section, controlling interest shall be construed in accordance with subsection (14) of section 494 of the Taxes Consolidation Act 1997 and, accordingly, that subsection shall apply in relation to a finance provider subject to any necessary modifications.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.97" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.98" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 5, as amended, agreed to.

NEW SECTION</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.99" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H01600"><p>I move amendment No. 19:</p><blockquote>In page 10, between lines 15 and 16, to insert the following:<br /><br /><b>&ldquo;Payment of premium to Minister by participating enterprise</b><br /><br /><b>6. </b>The Principal Act is amended by the substitution of the following section for section 8:<blockquote><blockquote>&ldquo;<b>8</b>. (1) Subject to this section, a participating enterprise shall, in accordance with a credit guarantee scheme that applies to the enterprise and a qualifying finance agreement entered into by the enterprise with a participating finance provider, pay to the Minister an amount (in this section referred to as the &lsquo;premium&rsquo;) determined by the Minister in accordance with the methodology specified in the scheme for the purposes of making that determination.<br /><br />(2) The Minister shall, in specifying, in a credit guarantee scheme, the methodology referred to in subsection (1), have regard to&mdash;<blockquote>(a) the expenses referred to in section 11 incurred or likely to be incurred, or both, in relation to the scheme, and<br /><br />(b) the objectives of the scheme.</blockquote>(3) The Minister shall, in specifying, in a credit guarantee scheme, the methodology referred to in subsection (1) in so far as the expenses referred to in section 11 are concerned, have regard to&mdash;<blockquote>(a) the size and quality of the participating enterprises to which the scheme applies,<br /><br />(b) the risks associated with those participating enterprises,<br /><br />(c) the typical risks associated with the business sector or sectors to which those participating enterprises belong,<br /><br />(d) the duration of guarantees given under the scheme,<br /><br />(e) the Minister&rsquo;s liability under section 4(2) in relation to a qualifying finance agreement to which the scheme applies, and<br /><br />(f) the nature of qualifying finance agreements to which the scheme applies.</blockquote>(4) The premium may be charged annually, may be paid by one payment or by instalments, and may be paid at such time or times, as may be specified in the credit guarantee scheme.<br /><br />(5) The Minister shall apply the premium received by him or her from a participating enterprise for the purpose only of defraying the costs of the credit guarantee scheme which applies to the enterprise.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.100" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1071" speakername="Dara Calleary" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H01700"><p>I wish to indicate that I may consider tabling an amendment in respect of this matter on Report Stage.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.101" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.102" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment No. 20 not moved.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.103" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 6 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.104" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 7 agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.105" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>SECTION 8</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.106" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H02400"><p>I move amendment No. 21:</p><blockquote>In page 11, line 16, to delete &ldquo;by this Act&rdquo; and substitute &ldquo;by this Part&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>This is a purely technical amendment with an application provision from the Principal Act being switched into the new Part 2.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.107" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.108" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 8, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.109" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>NEW SECTIONS</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.110" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H02800"><p>I move amendment No. 22:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:<div>&ldquo;PART 3*<br /><br />COUNTER GUARANTEES</div><b>Definitions</b><b>9. </b>In this Part&mdash;<blockquote>&ldquo;asset credit facility agreement&rdquo; means an agreement (other than a loan agreement or a credit facility agreement) under which a finance provider agrees to provide to a qualifying enterprise credit in the form of tangible movable property upon&mdash;<blockquote>(a) such date or dates as may be specified in the agreement, or<br /><br />(b) the happening of such event as may be so specified, </blockquote>in consideration of that qualifying enterprise agreeing to make payments to the finance provider on such date or dates, or the happening of such event as may be so specified, and &ldquo;asset credit facility&rdquo; shall be construed accordingly;<br /><br />&ldquo;counter guarantee agreement&rdquo; has the meaning assigned to it in <i>section 10(1)</i>;<br /><br />&ldquo;counter guarantee scheme&rdquo; means a scheme under <i>section 12</i>;<br /><br />&ldquo;credit facility agreement&rdquo; means an agreement (other than a loan agreement) under which a finance provider agrees to give or advance to a qualifying enterprise, or to a third party nominated in that behalf by a qualifying enterprise, a sum or sums of money upon&mdash;<blockquote>(a) such date or dates as may be specified in the agreement, or<br /><br />(b) the happening of such event as may be so specified,</blockquote>in consideration of that qualifying enterprise agreeing to repay to the finance provider the said sum or sums of money so given or advanced, and interest or charges (if any) thereon, on such date or dates as may be so specified, and &ldquo;credit facility&rdquo; shall be construed accordingly;<br /><br />&ldquo;credit guarantee scheme&rdquo; means a scheme under section 5 of the Principal Act;<br /><br />&ldquo;finance agreement&rdquo; means&mdash;<blockquote>(a) a loan agreement,<br /><br />(b) a credit facility agreement,<br /><br />(c) an asset credit facility agreement, or<br /><br />(d) an invoice finance facility agreement;</blockquote>&ldquo;finance provider&rdquo; means a person who, in the ordinary course of business&mdash;<blockquote>(a) provides financial products to qualifying enterprises,<br /><br />(b) arranges for the provision by other persons of financial products to qualifying enterprises, or<br /><br />(c) provides facilities for the provision on credit of goods or services by the person to qualifying enterprises,</blockquote>but does not include a person who is prohibited under the law of the State or any other state from engaging in any of the activities specified in the foregoing paragraphs, and references to the provision of a financial product shall be construed accordingly;<br /><br />&ldquo;financial product&rdquo; means&mdash;<blockquote>(a) a loan,<br /><br />(b) a credit facility,<br /><br />(c) an asset credit facility, or<br /><br />(d) an invoice finance facility,</blockquote>provided to a qualifying enterprise under a finance agreement;<br /><br />&ldquo;invoice finance facility agreement&rdquo; means an agreement under which a finance provider agrees to give or advance to a qualifying enterprise a sum or sums of money in consideration of that qualifying enterprise assigning to the finance provider the right to recover debts owed to that qualifying enterprise, and &ldquo;invoice finance facility&rdquo; shall be construed accordingly;<br /><br />&ldquo;loan agreement&rdquo; means an agreement under which a finance provider agrees to give or advance to a qualifying enterprise a sum or sums of money upon&mdash;<blockquote>(a) such date or dates as may be specified in the agreement, or<br /><br />(b) the happening of such event as may be so specified,</blockquote>in consideration of that qualifying enterprise agreeing to repay to the finance provider the principal of any sum or sums so given or advanced, and interest (if any) thereon, on such date or dates as may be so specified, but does not include an agreement to provide a facility (commonly known as an overdraft facility, credit card facility or credit line facility) to a qualifying enterprise, and &ldquo;loan&rdquo; shall be construed accordingly;<br /><br />&ldquo;participating PFI&rdquo; means a promotional financial institution that has entered into a counter guarantee agreement and&mdash;<blockquote>(a) in relation to a counter guarantee agreement, means the promotional financial institution that has entered into that agreement, and<br /><br />(b) in relation to a counter guarantee scheme, means the promotional financial institution that has entered into the counter guarantee agreement to which that scheme is scheduled;</blockquote>&ldquo;PFI guarantee scheme&rdquo; means a scheme&mdash;<blockquote>(a) that is made and operated by a promotional financial institution,<br /><br />(b) that applies only to finance agreements entered into between finance providers and qualifying enterprises, and<br /><br />(c) in accordance with which the institution referred to in <i>paragraph (a) </i>may give guarantees in respect of agreements referred to in <i>paragraph (b)</i>;</blockquote>&ldquo;promotional financial institution&rdquo; means&mdash;<blockquote>(a) the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland, or<br /><br />(b) a national promotional bank or institution within the meaning of Regulation (EU) 2015/1017 of the European Parliament and of the Council of 25 June 2015 on the European Fund for Strategic Investments, the European Investment Advisory Hub and the European Investment Project Portal and amending Regulations (EU) No 1291/2013 and (EU) No 1316/2013 &ndash; the European Fund for Strategic Investments;</blockquote>&ldquo;qualifying enterprise&rdquo; shall be construed in accordance with section 3 of the Principal Act (and, accordingly, the reference in that section to &ldquo;Act&rdquo; includes this Part);<br /><br />&ldquo;qualifying finance agreement&rdquo; has the meaning assigned to it by section 1 of the Principal Act;<br /><br />&ldquo;qualifying PFI guarantee agreement&rdquo;, in relation to a qualifying PFI guarantee scheme, means a guarantee agreement entered into by a participating PFI in accordance with that scheme;<br /><br />&ldquo;qualifying PFI guarantee scheme&rdquo; means a PFI guarantee scheme&mdash;<blockquote>(a) in respect of which there has been compliance with the conditions specified in a counter guarantee scheme under <i>subsection (4)(c) </i>of <i>section 12,</i><br /><br />(b) belonging to a class of PFI guarantee scheme to which a counter guarantee scheme applies,<br /><br />(c) that is made for the purpose of promoting the provision of credit or additional credit to qualifying enterprises, and<br /><br />(d) that does not permit the promotional financial institution operating the PFI guarantee scheme to provide guarantees as would result in the maximum value referred to in <i>subsection (4)(d) </i>of <i>section 12</i>, specified in the counter guarantee scheme referred to in <i>paragraph (b)</i>, being exceeded.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.111" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.112" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H03000"><p>I move amendment No. 23:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Power of Minister to give counter guarantees</b><br /><br /><b>10. </b>(1) Subject to this section and <i>section 11</i>, the Minister may, in accordance with a counter guarantee scheme, enter into an agreement (in this Part referred to as a &ldquo;counter guarantee agreement&rdquo;) with a promotional financial institution guaranteeing the due repayment to that institution of such part, as is specified in the counter guarantee agreement, of moneys (excluding any interest and other charges) paid by that institution to finance providers pursuant to qualifying PFI guarantee agreements.<blockquote>(2) A counter guarantee agreement shall&mdash;<blockquote>(a) have scheduled to it the counter guarantee scheme to which it relates, and<br /><br />(b) include a declaration, by the promotional financial institution entering into the agreement, that it agrees to be bound by the terms of the scheme referred to in <i>paragraph (a) </i>and the other terms (if any) of that agreement.</blockquote>(3) The Minister shall not, pursuant to a counter guarantee agreement, be liable, in relation to any particular qualifying PFI guarantee agreement, to pay to the participating PFI an amount exceeding the Minister&rsquo;s maximum liability, referred to in <i>subsection (4)(e) </i>of <i>section 12</i>and as specified in the counter guarantee scheme scheduled to that counter guarantee agreement, in respect of moneys&mdash;<blockquote>(a) for the time being standing unpaid to the finance provider under any finance agreement, and<br /><br />(b) that the participating PFI has paid to the finance provider, pursuant to that qualifying PFI guarantee agreement, in respect of those moneys standing so unpaid.</blockquote>(4) For the purposes of this Part, the Strategic Banking Corporation of Ireland, in its capacity as a promotional financial institution, has the power to give guarantees to finance providers in respect of finance agreements.<br /><br />(5) (a) The Minister may, in respect of a counter guarantee agreement, notify the participating PFI in writing that that agreement shall not apply in relation to qualifying PFI guarantee agreements (in this section referred to as &ldquo;new qualifying guarantee agreements&rdquo;) entered into by the participating PFI after such date as may be specified in the notice.<blockquote>(b) A counter guarantee agreement the subject of a notice under <i>paragraph (a) </i>shall not apply to new qualifying PFI guarantee agreements.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.113" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.114" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H03200"><p>I move amendment No. 24:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Monetary limit on Minister&rsquo;s liability</b><br /><br /><b>11. </b>The Minister shall not exercise the powers conferred on him or her by section 4 of the Principal Act or <i>section 10* </i>in such manner as would result in the aggregate of the Minister&rsquo;s liability in respect of&mdash;<blockquote>(a) all qualifying finance agreements, to which guarantees under a credit guarantee scheme apply, entered into in any year, and<br /><br />(b) all qualifying PFI guarantee agreements, to which counter guarantees under a counter guarantee scheme apply, entered into in that same year, exceeding &euro;15.6 million.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.115" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.116" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H03400"><p>I move amendment No. 25:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Counter guarantee schemes</b><br /><br /><b>12. </b>(1) The Minister may, with the consent of the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, make a scheme or schemes for the purposes of this Part.<blockquote>(2) Without prejudice to the generality of <i>subsection (1)</i>, a scheme under this section may make provision in relation to all or any of the following matters:<blockquote>(a) the giving of information to the Minister, as he or she may reasonably require, for the purpose of the making of a counter guarantee agreement;<br /><br />(b) the extent of the Minister&rsquo;s liability, in accordance with a counter guarantee agreement, to the participating PFI in circumstances where the participating PFI fails or refuses to comply with this Part or the scheme under this section;<br /><br />(c) the variation of the terms of a counter guarantee agreement in circumstances where the participating PFI fails or refuses to comply with this Part or the scheme under this section;<br /><br />(d) without prejudice to the generality of <i>section 13(4)</i>, the method of payment of the premium under <i>section 13</i>and the time or times at which the premium shall be paid;<br /><br />(e) the preparation and maintenance by the participating PFI of records, books of account and such other documentation as may be specified in the scheme under this section;<br /><br />(f) provision with regard to the giving of documents, information and reports by the participating PFI to the Minister;<br /><br />(g) such other matters as the Minister, after consultation with the Minister for Finance and the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, considers necessary or expedient for the purposes of this Part.</blockquote>(3) A scheme under this section shall specify conditions, with which the participating PFI shall comply, relating to&mdash;<blockquote>(a) the policies and practices of the participating PFI as respects&mdash;<blockquote>(i) the giving of guarantees generally,<br /><br />(ii) the giving of guarantees in respect of moneys provided to qualifying enterprises, and<br /><br />(iii) the recovery of sums paid by the participating PFI under a guarantee given by the participating PFI,</blockquote>(b) the administration and management of the participating PFI in relation to the giving of guarantees, and<br /><br />(c) the procedures in relation to the supervision of guarantee agreements entered into on behalf of the participating PFI by members of staff of the participating PFI.</blockquote>(4) A scheme under this section shall specify&mdash;<blockquote>(a) the class or classes of qualifying PFI guarantee schemes to which the scheme shall apply,<br /><br />(b) the purposes for which a counter guarantee under the scheme is given,<br /><br />(c) subject to <i>subsection (5)</i>, the conditions that shall be complied with in relation to the entering into of a guarantee agreement by the participating PFI in accordance with a qualifying PFI guarantee scheme,<br /><br />(d) the maximum value of financial products that may be provided pursuant to finance agreements&mdash;<blockquote>(i) entered into between finance providers and qualifying enterprises, and<br /><br />(ii) that are subject to qualifying PFI guarantee agreements to which the counter guarantee under the scheme applies,</blockquote>(e) the Minister&rsquo;s maximum liability under the scheme to pay to the participating PFI an amount in respect of moneys&mdash;<blockquote>(i) for the time being standing unpaid to the finance provider under any finance agreement, and<br /><br />(ii) that the participating PFI has paid to the finance provider, pursuant to the qualifying PFI guarantee agreement concerned, in respect of those moneys standing so unpaid,</blockquote>(f) the methodology which ensures that the scheme cannot operate in such manner as may result in a contravention of <i>section 11</i>, and<br /><br />(g) the methodology referred to in <i>section 13(1)</i>.</blockquote>(5) The conditions referred to in <i>paragraph (c) </i>of <i>subsection (4) </i>may, in relation to the qualifying PFI guarantee scheme concerned, include conditions specifying the class or classes of&mdash;<blockquote>(a) finance agreements,<br /><br />(b) finance providers, and<br /><br />(c) financial products,</blockquote>to which that scheme shall apply.<br /><br />(6) A scheme under this section shall specify the ground or grounds on which the Minister may terminate a counter guarantee agreement by notice in writing given to the participating PFI specifying the ground or grounds concerned and the date from which such termination shall take effect.<br /><br />(7) (a) The Minister may require that any information referred to in <i>subsection (2)(a) </i>given to him or her by a person in compliance with a scheme under this section be attested as to the truth of the information by a statutory declaration made by that person.<blockquote>(b) The Minister may require that any document, information or report referred to in <i>subsection (2)(f) </i>given to him or her by a participating PFI in compliance with a scheme under this section be attested as to the truth of the contents of the document or report or, as the case may be, as to the truth of the information, by a statutory declaration made by that participating PFI.&rdquo;.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.117" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.118" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H03600"><p>I move amendment No. 26:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Payment of premium to Minister by participating PFI</b><br /><br /><b>13. </b>(1) Subject to this section, the participating PFI shall, in accordance with the counter guarantee scheme, pay to the Minister an amount (in this section referred to as the &ldquo;premium&rdquo;) determined by the Minister in accordance with the methodology specified in the scheme for the purposes of making that determination.<blockquote>(2) The Minister shall, in specifying, in the counter guarantee scheme, the methodology referred to in <i>subsection (1)</i>, have regard to&mdash;<blockquote>(a) the expenses referred to in <i>section 15 </i>incurred or likely to be incurred, or both, in relation to the scheme, and<br /><br />(b) the objectives of the scheme.</blockquote>(3) The Minister shall, in specifying, in the counter guarantee scheme, the methodology referred to in <i>subsection (1) </i>in so far as the expenses referred to in <i>section 15 </i>are concerned, have regard to&mdash;<blockquote>(a) the size and quality of the qualifying enterprises which may enter into finance agreements with finance providers to which guarantees given by the participating PFI apply and to which counter guarantees given under the scheme may apply,<br /><br />(b) the risks associated with those qualifying enterprises,<br /><br />(c) the typical risks associated with the business sector or sectors to which those qualifying enterprises belong, and<br /><br />(d) the duration of counter guarantees given under the scheme.</blockquote>(4) The scheme charge may be charged annually, may be paid by one payment or by instalments, and may be paid at such time or times, as may be specified in the counter guarantee scheme.<br /><br />(5) The Minister shall apply the premium received by him or her from a participating PFI for the purpose only of defraying the costs of the counter guarantee scheme which applies to the participating PFI.&rdquo;.</blockquote></blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.119" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.120" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H03800"><p>I move amendment No. 27:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Review of counter guarantee scheme</b><br /><br /><b>14. </b>The Minister may, at any time, conduct a review of the operation of a counter guarantee scheme and, not later than 2 months after completing such review, make a report in writing to each House of the Oireachtas of his or her findings and conclusions resulting from that review.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.121" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.122" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H04000"><p>I move amendment No. 28:</p><blockquote>In page 11, between lines 20 and 21, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;Expenses</b><br /><br /><b>15. </b>The expenses incurred by the Minister in the administration of this Part shall, to such extent as may be sanctioned by the Minister for Finance, with the consent of the Minister for Public Expenditure and Reform, be paid out of moneys provided by the Oireachtas.&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.123" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.124" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Section 9 deleted.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.125" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H04300"><p>I move amendment No. 29:</p><blockquote>In page 11, after line 28, to insert the following:<b>&ldquo;10. </b>The Minister shall within 12 months and every 12 months thereafter, from the passing of this Act prepare and lay before D&aacute;il &Eacute;ireann a report detailing the impact of all measures contained in this Act on the availability of credit to SMEs, rates of bank lending to SMEs, levels of lending under the scheme and relevant default.&rdquo;.</blockquote> <p>I submitted this amendment because this scheme had a rocky start.  We have come through one of the deepest credit crises for enterprise and we are still not out of the woods in that regard.  Figures from ISME for the last quarter show that there are still major difficulties with obtaining credit.  We have dealt with a lot of the elements of this amending Bill before and many of the issues we are amending were discussed at the initial stages by members of the Opposition, myself included.  We must keep an eye on the outputs of this legislation and make sure that we measure its impact on entrepreneurs and small businesses in the future.  The amendment provides that if the provisions of this Bill are still limping along, we can rectify the problem at the earliest opportunity.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.126" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H04400"><p>I would be more optimistic than Deputy T&oacute;ib&iacute;n about the potential of this Bill and the credit guarantee scheme.  We have accepted the vast bulk of the review.  We commissioned that review and understood that changes had to be made.  I accept that it has been frustrating for everybody that it has taken a long time to get to the point where we can make amendments to the legislation to allow for the scheme to operate to its fullest potential.  However, I am very confident that it will do so.</p> <p>  It is normal procedure for the operator of the scheme, Capita Asset Services, to provide quarterly reports and they are published on the website of the Department of Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation.  It is not proposed to legislate to allow that happen.  Rather, it is proposed that we continue with the current arrangements under the revised legislation.  Those arrangements cover the credit guarantee and the counter guarantee elements.  We do this already and it is important that such information is available to be assessed by anyone who wishes to determine the success, or otherwise, of the scheme.  I assure Deputies that where any scheme is not meeting its potential, we will make any changes necessary.  We were very upfront about the gaps, deficits and deficiencies in this particular scheme and that is why we worked to address them as quickly as possible.  We all have a responsibility to work with SMEs to provide the jobs that we all want to see and we all have a responsibility to ensure that our finance system is functioning.</p> <p>  More generally, material on rates of bank lending to SMEs is more broadly a matter for the Minister for Finance.  In that context, it would not be appropriate to include such a provision in this legislation.  The Deputy's amendment is not appropriate to this legislation on credit guarantees but we will be publishing information in the normal way.  That information will be available to the public to allow them to make an assessment of the scheme.  Where there are issues arising, they will be addressed.  I am optimistic and confident that the amended scheme and the approach we are now taking will herald a new dawn for SMEs.  We have done the same with Microfinance Ireland and the figures for that body are improving all of the time.  We changed the way the Microfinance Ireland scheme operates and made it more attractive and accessible to micro-enterprises who need to use it.  We are not averse to holding our hands up, admitting that something is not working, fixing it when necessary and working with our colleagues in the Oireachtas to do so.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.127" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H04500"><p>Is the amendment being pressed?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.128" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1080" speakername="Peadar T&oacute;ib&iacute;n" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H04600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.129" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment put and declared lost.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.130" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>TITLE</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.131" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1067" speakername="Gerald Nash" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#H04900"><p>I move amendment No. 30:</p><blockquote>In page 3, line 5, after &ldquo;2012;&rdquo; to insert the following:&ldquo;to enable the Minister for Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation, pursuant to a counter guarantee scheme made by that Minister of the Government, to give counter guarantees to promotional financial institutions for guarantees given by the institutions to finance providers in respect of finance agreements entered into by the finance providers with qualifying enterprises; to place a yearly monetary limit on the potential liability of that Minister of the Government in respect of all credit guarantee schemes and counter guarantee schemes taken together;&rdquo;.</blockquote></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.132" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Amendment agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.133" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Title, as amended, agreed to.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.134" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>Bill reported with amendments.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.135" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#J00100">Message to Dáil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.136" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1099" speakername="Marcella Corcoran Kennedy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/BUS2015120800002#J00200"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p> <p>  The Select Committee on Jobs, Enterprise and Innovation has completed its consideration of the Credit Guarantee (Amendment) Bill 2015 and has made amendments thereto.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.137" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The select committee adjourned sine die.</p></speech>
    <major-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.138" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="">Committee on Education and Social Protection: Select Sub-Committee on Education and Skills</major-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.139" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The Select Committee met at 13:30</p><p>MEMBERS PRESENT:</p><p>Deputy Michael Conaghan, Deputy Jan O'Sullivan (Minister for Education and Skills), Deputy Charlie McConalogue, Deputy Brendan Ryan. Deputy Jonathan O'Brien,</p><p>DEPUTY JOANNA TUFFY IN THE CHAIR.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.140" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The select sub-committee met in private session until 1.35 p.m.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.142" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#D00200">Estimates for Public Services 2015<br />Vote 26 - Education and Skills (Supplementary)</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.143" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#D00300"><p>I ask everybody to put their phones on safe or flight mode or switch them off.  The general note on privilege applies.  Absolute privilege applies in respect of evidence but if anyone is directed to cease giving evidence on a particular matter, only a qualified privilege applies.  Members are reminded of the long-standing parliamentary practice to the effect that they should not criticise or make charges against any person outside the Houses or an official either by name or in such a way as to make him, her or it identifiable.  I welcome the Minister for Education and Skills and officials for her Department.  We are meeting to consider the Supplementary Estimate, Vote 26 - Education and Skills, for the amount of &euro;175 million.  For those allocations under discussion, the committee has an opportunity to review the additional allocations being sought on an item by item basis, focus on why they are being sought, and review the targets set for the relevant items, the resources available for them, and the outputs and impact of the activities concerned.  I invite the Minister to make brief opening remarks.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.144" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#D00400"><p>I thank the select committee for the opportunity to discuss my Department&rsquo;s requirement for a Supplementary Estimate of &euro;175 million for 2015.  My Department provided background briefing material to the committee and, therefore, I propose to keep this opening statement brief.</p> <p>  The Supplementary Estimate sought will increase my Department&rsquo;s overall net voted allocation from &euro;8.012 billion to &euro;8.187 billion.  The additional &euro;175 million sought comprises &euro;125 million for current expenditure and &euro;50 million for capital expenditure.  A sum of &euro;40 million in current funding is required to cover the cost of a projected 600 additional retirements across the education sector in 2015.  While 1,540 retirements were originally provided for, the number being forecast is in excess of 2,150 retirements.  The additional funding is required to meet both the lump sum element and the ongoing pension cost element of the additional retirees.  My Department has little control over this component of expenditure.  Estimating the number of retirements in recent years has been difficult, due in part to the extension of the grace periods with regard to the calculation of retirement salaries - subheads A8 and C10 refer.  A further &euro;78 million in current funding is required to cover additional costs associated with third level student supports in 2015, &euro;61 million of which is needed to alleviate financial pressures being experienced by higher education institutions, HEIs, by bringing forward to December 2015 payments in respect of the student contribution that were originally due to be paid to the HEIs in January 2016.  An additional &euro;17 million is required, in large part to meet upward demographic pressures not originally provided for - subhead C11 refers.</p> <p>   The &euro;50 million required in capital expenditure is needed to progress projects under the 2014 summer works scheme that were not progressed or finalised in that year.  Applications were submitted by schools in November 2013 for inclusion in the 2014 scheme.  A total of 787 schools were initially approved to undertake school improvements across five categories of projects - gas, electrical, mechanical, the upgrade of toilet facilities and roof improvements.  Schools whose applications were not reached in 2014 were advised that their applications would be reviewed in the event that funding became available.</p><p>In April last, a further 559 schools were approved to undertake works across the remaining four project categories - upgrading and replacement of windows, school specialist room refurbishment, school building improvements and external works such as closed circuit television and fencing.  The total value of these projects was &euro;108 million and &euro;50 million is needed to complete this work in 2015 - subhead D3 refers.</p><p> A further &euro;6 million is required to provide for the increase in demand in the number of students requiring access to special needs assistants, SNAs, in schools, including students in special classes and students enrolling in special schools.  Government approval for an additional 610 SNAs was granted in July 2015.  This builds on the increases of 365 additional SNA posts provided for in last year&rsquo;s budget and the 390 additional SNA posts announced in December 2013.  The July 2015 decision increased SNA numbers from 11,330 to 11,940, and represents an increase of 11.7% in SNA posts available for allocation to schools since the Government came to office - subhead A6 refers.</p><p> A total of &euro;12 million is required to cover an estimated shortfall in appropriations-in-aid receipts, due to an overestimation of the level of these receipts to be brought to account in 2015.  These receipts mainly cover superannuation contributions, pension-related deduction receipts and European Social Fund receipts.  The receipts are effectively offset against the Department&rsquo;s gross expenditure figure to produce the figure for net expenditure.  The 2015 Revised Estimates allocation provided for receipts of &euro;573 million, but this will reduce to &euro;561 million in the Supplementary Estimate.</p><p> All these additional expenditure requirements amount to &euro;186 million.  However, my Department has also identified offsetting net savings of &euro;11 million in the Supplementary Estimate.  These savings arise on subhead B5, covering grants to SOLAS in respect of further education and training activities.  The net saving of &euro;11 million comprises savings of &euro;14 million.  Based on expenditure returns received from the education and training boards, ETBs, there is an estimated accumulated surplus of &euro;14 million in the Exchequer funding from SOLAS to the boards in respect of further education grants.  SOLAS has agreed with the ETBs to recoup these surpluses by reducing the final tranche of payments to be made to them before the end of the current financial year.  The saving of &euro;14 million in the ETBs will be offset by additional expenditure of &euro;3 million, which will be required to cover the cost of the 75% Christmas bonus announced by the Minister for Social Protection in budget 2016.  This &euro;3 million will cover the cost of paying the bonus to 18,000 participants on vocational training opportunities scheme, VTOS, courses and other ETB programmes that fall under my Department&rsquo;s remit.</p><p> This summarises my Department&rsquo;s requirement for a Supplementary Estimate and I am happy to respond to any questions the committee may have.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.146" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#E00200"><p>We will first consider subhead A6 - SNAs.  I refer members to page 3 of the secretariat's brief and to page 3 of the Department's document.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.147" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#E00300"><p>I thank the Minister and her officials for attending to discuss this Supplementary Estimate.  The 610 additional SNA posts, which the &euro;6 million increase will cover, is approximately 5% more than was projected in the original Estimate for 2015, which is a significant overshoot.  What has led to the increase of 5% in demand?  Is that indicative of increased application numbers or did the number of applications increase by more than 5%?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.148" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#F00200"><p>I presume that figure is not the full year cost but rather the cost from September to December.  Next year we will have to have a full year cost.  Is it fair to say the extra cost will be &euro;12 million next year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.149" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#F00400"><p>It is always difficult to estimate exactly what the needs will be.  The National Council for Special Education will give an indication early in the year as to what it thinks they will be.  As members will understand, as children are enrolled in schools and their needs identified, further applications are made through SENOs.  It is difficult to predict in advance, therefore, what moneys will be needed.  Members will see from the figures - it also happened in previous years - that last year an additional number of SNAs were announced later in the year.  It happens consistently as the year goes on, coming up to September, that one finds that one needs more than anticipated.  Everybody here wants to ensure that where a child is in need of SNA support, he or she will receive it.  We estimate as well as we can in advance what the needs will be, but the experience in recent years has been that they have turned out to be greater than anticipated.  It is hard to answer Deputy Charlie McConalogue's original question because there are more children who are in need of support and we can all understand why.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.150" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#F00500"><p>Do we receive any information from preschools on the number of children identified as having special needs?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.151" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#F00600"><p>The information we receive is improving all the time.  On a related issue, one of the reasons we were not able to introduce the new model for resource teachers was that we needed to receive more accurate information on children with complex needs.  Much of it was coming from the preschool sector and the HSE on what they had identified as being the needs of younger children.  We receive a certain amount of information, but we are constantly trying to improve on it in advance in order that it is as accurate as possible in predicting needs.  I have some figures which I can circulate to members for the school years from 2011 to 2015-16 for students in mainstream education accessing SNAs, students in special classes and students in special schools.  For example, in mainstream primary school classes in the 2011-12 school year the number was 12,150 students; in the 2015-16 school year it is 16,023.  There has been a gradual and steady increase in the intervening years.  In special classes the number increased from 3,286 to 5,100 students, while for special schools the figure increased from 6,848 to 7,607.  I assume the increase is due to a combination of increased awareness, increased demand and, possibly, increased need.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.152" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#F00700"><p>We would be cribbing if the Minister did not provide the extra &euro;6 million.  The increase in the number of SNAs is welcome and it is a trend that will continue as teachers are becoming more aware of the special needs of students and identifying them earlier.  While the process of identifying additional needs improves, one cannot put a figure on it.  I have no issue with the subhead included in the Supplementary Estimate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.153" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#G00100"><p>The Minister will recall a considerable discussion earlier in the year on the need to move towards an input-output model of reporting along the lines of the New Zealand model that we saw as being the standard.  Obviously the increased number of SNAs is an increase in input.  How can we look at the numbers in terms of moving towards that input-output approach?  In terms of output what will we see as a result of the increase?  The Minister might argue that it is an increase to meet a particular need or growing numbers.  In terms of expectation of literacy and numeracy what can we expect?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.154" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#G00200"><p>The purpose of an SNA is to provide for the care needs of the child in school so that the child can attend school.  We are not necessarily looking at an educational outcome but we would measure issues such as improved attendance and improved school retention.  In other words, that the children who need that support actually attend school more regularly, stay in school longer and remain on to complete the leaving certificate and, possibly, further studies.  Those are the outcomes we would measure rather than academic attainment.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.155" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#G00300"><p>Can the members of the committee have an expectation that there will be a greater focus on those outputs and that they will be a routine part of her presentation?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.156" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#G00400"><p>We can do that in so far as we can measure it but because of the role of SNAs the output is different from the outputs we would measure in other areas of education.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.157" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#G00500"><p>Given that it is the first item for discussion it is important to reflect the expectations of the committee in terms of reporting in such a manner.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.158" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#G00600"><p>On that point, the purpose of an SNA might have to do with care but, obviously, it would free up teaching hours.  An issue that has arisen is whether the SNA facility was being used in the correct way.  The reform being proposed by the national council as to how we look at these matters is that we are not just putting in the numbers of SNAs, but asking if they are needed, if they are being used correctly and allocated correctly around the system.  The Minister mentioned the number of SNAs but we have no idea of the number of pupils it relates to or what it means in terms of outcomes in the classroom.  The question of literacy and numeracy is related.  If an SNA is provided does it mean that more effort can be put into the teaching and learning?  What does the number of SNAs mean in terms of the number of pupils who would be affected?  Has the Minister any views on that issue?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.159" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#G00700"><p>I would take a slightly different approach from that of the Chair.  In terms of SNAs, one cannot measure the outputs in educational terms because they are not teachers and are not there to teach but to assist the individual pupils with their needs, such as helping them go to the bathroom, to get on and off buses and with extra-curricular activities such as swimming.  Therefore, it is much harder to measure SNA outcomes.</p><p>I would be wary of trying to get an outcome based on literacy and numeracy.  That should be based on the class as a whole rather than individual pupils who have access to SNAs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.161" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#H00200"><p>It is not that they are not interconnected.  A special needs assistant in a classroom has a relationship with education.  That may not be the SNA&rsquo;s role, although many would argue differently.  The SNA is there to help the child stay in the classroom.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.162" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#H00300"><p>The SNA helps the teacher and the functioning of the classroom.  Deputy O&rsquo;Brien is right that SNAs have transformed classrooms.  We should support this.  The Minister is right to support this area in a practical way.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.163" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#H00400"><p>The information is provided in the old fashioned way, a certain sum of money equals a certain number of SNAs.  It does not tell us anything else.  If the Minister and the Department are sympathetic to the idea that we use SNAs to the best of our ability for a system of education, it has to be more than &euro;6 million equals 300 or so extra SNAs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.164" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#H00500"><p>One way to measure it would be to say if a pupil in a mainstream school did not have access to a special needs assistant would he or she be able to remain in mainstream or have to go into a special school.  It is not possible to measure outputs in terms of literacy and numeracy because there are more factors than having a special needs assistance in a classroom.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.165" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#H00600"><p>The SNAs are there for the care needs of the children.  That is their purpose.  We can measure the number of extra children who can be in a mainstream classroom because they have a special needs assistant.  The teacher is the educational professional.  The children are given the SNA support in order that they can benefit from the professional teaching and have their care needs attended to, so that they are on an even playing pitch with the other children in terms of educational opportunities.  We have very good measurements of literacy and numeracy which show that Ireland has been improving in those areas.  They are good for a variety of reasons, one of which is that children have SNA support who otherwise would not be there to benefit from the opportunities to learn and improve literacy and numeracy.  We can use this measure for educational outcome in other areas of my budget.  In this area it is a question of being in mainstream classes or in special classes in mainstream schools, or in special schools.  We should be able to give figures on attendance and retention.  This is one of the areas on educational outcomes where the input of the SNA is primarily to facilitate children to be in the classroom to benefit from educational opportunities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.166" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#H00700"><p>If there is any way the Minister can develop this process and work with us and the committee secretariat would be welcome.  Could it be said, if this discrete group of pupils improved their educational outcomes, that the improvement related also to SNAs, resource teachers or technology to help students with special needs?</p><p>Money is being spent by the Department.  It is not that it is not connected to educational outcomes at all, it must be.  I would not go along with the idea that there is no relationship.  I understand exactly what an SNA is but it is not separate from the educational outcomes.  Perhaps for future reference we could develop the information provided.  This is very much what we would have got in the past.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.168" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#J00200"><p>It is very difficult to measure the educational outcomes from having an SNA in a classroom.  I speak from my experience of dealing with SNAs.  They are there to provide for care needs and, yes, that will allow a student to be in class more often.  However, because the student is in class more often does not mean that better educational outcomes for him or her are due to the SNA.  They are due to the teacher and the child&rsquo;s ability.  A child with dyspraxia, Asperger&rsquo;s spectrum disorder and dyslexia who has access to an SNA to look after his or her care needs will not improve his or her educational attainment.  The improvement will happen only because the child is in a mainstream setting and accessing education.  I do not know that they can be correlated.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.169" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#J00300"><p>The Deputy has just correlated them.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.170" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#J00400"><p>It is impossible to measure that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.171" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#J00500"><p>Perhaps.  However, the Deputy stated that if they stay in a classroom longer, their educational outcomes are potentially improved.  Therefore, he has made the connection.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.172" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#J00600"><p>No, I am saying if they stay in a mainstream setting they have educational opportunities but those opportunities cannot be measured because every individual student must be assessed on his or her own ability.  If somebody is severely dyslexic, whether he or she has access to an SNA does not change the fact that he or she is dyslexic.  The education he or she receives is down to the teacher and the relevant programmes - such as those which involve assistive technology or those which are part of the curriculum - that are in place.  If there are two students with severe dyslexia, one with access to an SNA and one without, it is not possible to correlate their educational outcomes.  That is impossible.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.173" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#J00700"><p>The Minister gave some figures but I did not catch to what they referred.  Was it the number of students transferring from mainstream to special schools or from special schools to mainstream?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.174" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#J00800"><p>There are three sets of figures, information relating to which I can give the Deputy afterwards.  The number of students in mainstream primary and post-primary accessing SNAs - approximately 12,000 in 2011 and going up to 16,000 - comprises the first set.  There is a second set of figures for students in special classes who are accessing SNAs and a third set in respect of those in special schools who are accessing SNAs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.175" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#J00900"><p>The figures we are being given and the explanations for them are exceptionally fudgy.  They do not explain the dynamic of this increase.  I welcome it because I know from engaging with schools that there is a real stress factor in respect of matching up the need for SNAs with the provision of SNAs.  In many cases there is a sense that there are not enough to meet the need there.  The 610 extra SNAs is an increase of 5.4% on the total number.  That is welcome but it is a very significant increase in one year.  There is no explanation of what is behind that.  We are being told that demand is increasing, that more students are coming in and that this leads to an increase.  We are expected to accept this as the explanation.</p><p>However, something much more substantial is leading to this.  There was insufficient resourcing in previous years, where it was suppressed, and the provision for SNAs was tightened up.  Now, however, resources are starting to be released.  That seems to be the primary explanation behind it because I presume in making projections for the 2015 Estimates and having looked at previous trends, where the number of SNAs was increasing as demand was increasing, an increase in demand would have been built in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.177" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#K00150"><p>An increase was built in.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.178" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#K00300"><p>Even with that built-in additional demand based on experience we are still in a position where there is a 5.5% increase in the number of SNAs.  There is some dynamic here and we are not being given a clear explanation as to what that is.  I do not have a clear answer but I would have thought that it having been delivered and the money allocated for it, we would have a clear explanation as to what was at play.  If there is a 5.5% increase in the number of SNAs, has there been a core related increase in the number of resource hours being allocated to schools during this period?  If there is a dynamic leading to a 5.5% increase in SNAs why are we not given a similar request for a few hundred extra resource teachers?  Certain things can be done in terms of projecting the number of SNAs who will be required.  It is difficult to know for those who are starting school what their demand will be.  However, there is a band within which the Minister can project that demand will be similar to the previous year plus a bit extra.  For those who are moving from junior to high infants, if they had an SNA in junior infants there is every likelihood they will carry it on to senior infants, and likewise through all the classes.  For those already in the school system, projecting the SNA demand for next year is a manageable job.  That confines it to those who are entering the system for the first time.  In that case, that goes nowhere near explaining a 5% increase.  When there are 14 classes all together in the primary and secondary system, a 5% increase in SNAs cannot be identified as being simply down to those entering the school system for the first time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.179" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#K00400"><p>I was just checking.  I call Deputy Conaghan.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.180" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1031" speakername="Michael Conaghan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#K00500"><p>For a number of years the financial support to the schools for this category of work was not being delivered.  What is happening now is that a catch-up is starting in terms of extra provision.  There was a time when the assistance needed was not being provided in terms of SNAs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.181" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#K00600"><p>It is a combination of many factors.  It is not a case that when a child enters junior infants we suddenly discover he or she needs an SNA.  There are children in mainstream schools who, due to the changes in the curriculum in recent years, are only being identified with additional needs when they move from senior infants to first class.  It is a progression through the school as a whole.  I know many children who have been only recently diagnosed with Asperger's syndrome or dyspraxia at the age of six or seven years.  The curriculum is designed to try to find those special educational needs of students.  There is a better understanding of children's needs and a better detection system within schools.  Teachers are more aware of special educational needs which are identified, not only at entry level but at senior infants and second class level.</p><p>No doubt a catch-up is in place but the 5% increase cannot be put down to solely catching up.  I think there are other factors such as better understanding and detection.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.183" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#L00200"><p>I will try to answer some of the questions including specific ones from Deputy McConalogue.  We did allocate an extra 365 posts in the Estimates process before last year.  We allocated funding for extra SNAs but on top of that we had to allocate the additional ones.  We are carrying out a focused policy assessment of the SNA scheme which is currently under way.  It will involve the identification, analysis and evaluation of relevant data to ensure that the scheme continues to meet its objectives and that resources are being utilised effectively and efficiently in line with the guidelines.  A review is ongoing to ensure that the funding is being appropriately spent.</p> <p>  In 2011-12, the number of special classes attached to mainstream schools was 549.  There are now more than 1,000.  Members will be aware from their constituencies of schools putting special classes on to mainstream schools, especially for autism.  It is the right thing to do.  Deputy O'Brien and Deputy Conaghan are correct.  We are identifying the need and it is right that we are meeting that need.  </p> <p>  I wish to inform Deputy McConalogue that we also allocated an extra 600 resource teachers.  There is also an identified increasing need for resource teaching hours as well as for SNAs, albeit that the purpose-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.184" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#L00300"><p>That was in the original Estimates.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.185" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#L00400"><p>We are better able to identify the resource hour needs.  As Deputy O'Brien said, the SNA need is sometimes identified during the school life of the child.  I accept that we want to be more accurate in predicting these issues and we are happy to work with the committee in doing that.  The review will help us.  The percentage of students accessing SNA, relative to the demographic increase, is constantly higher than the actual demographic increase.  Clearly, we are finding more need in the growing number of students as a whole.  I think that is due to the fact that as a nation we are becoming more aware of the needs of children who have particular learning difficulties or particular physical needs.  When we identify those needs we endeavour to find the resources to meet those needs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.186" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#L00500"><p>Has the review anything to do with the value for money recommendations?  The 2015 Estimates includes a provision to further implement recommendations of the SNA value for money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.187" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#L00600"><p>It is related to that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.188" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#L00700"><p>Okay.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.189" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#L00800"><p>It is also quite focused.  We have already implemented some of the recommendations of the value for money report because they were specific.  Many of the others are ongoing in terms of implementation.  This is a specific focused review of the SNA.  If it is identified that one suddenly needs to spend more money than anticipated it is important to identify why one was not able to anticipate that need and, second, to ensure it is appropriately spent.  We have to be conscious of value for money but we also have to be conscious of need and ensure these young children can benefit from the educational opportunities.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.190" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#L00900"><p>In terms of the extra 610 special needs assistants, is it that they are employed and then the Department has to supply the money?</p><p>There is no issue around having to employ those people now.  They were employed in addition to what was anticipated and now the money has to be put in place.  The expansion was made without the sanction.  What is the procedure there?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.192" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M00200"><p>It would be for the forthcoming year.  The Estimates are done in the autumn and the first set of identified needs comes in January.  More come in later in the year.  One then finds one is going to need more, so the money has to be put in place to employ the people for the following school year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.193" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M00300"><p>How many additional special needs assistants are in the system for the school year September 2015 to June 2016?  I know there were 610 posts, for which approval was obtained in July.  The Department's explanation is that this builds on the increase of 365 additional SNA posts provided for in last year's budget.  Does that mean it was the 2015 budget?  Was the total number of additional SNAs starting this year 975?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.194" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M00400"><p>Yes, bringing it up to 11,940.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.195" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M00500"><p>There were 975 additional SNAs in total this September over the previous September, is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.196" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M00600"><p>There were 610 on top of the 365 we had already budgeted for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.197" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M00700"><p>The 365 were allocated by the budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.198" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M00800"><p>Yes, they were already budgeted for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.199" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M00900"><p>That works out as a 9% increase in September this year in the total number of SNAs.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.200" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01000"><p>Yes, if we count the 365 that were already budgeted for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.201" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01100"><p>That is an exceptionally high number.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.202" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01200"><p>It certainly requires review.  The Deputy is right.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.203" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01300"><p>The Minister said it was for next year.  I need this clarified.  This Estimate is for this year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.204" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01400"><p>Yes, September 2015, this current school year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.205" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01500"><p>Those people have been employed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.206" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01600"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.207" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01700"><p>It is not that they have yet to be employed.  They are already employed.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.208" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01800"><p>Yes.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.209" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M01900"><p>I thank the Minister.  Are there other questions?  If members are happy, we will move on to superannuation in respect of first and second level schools and institutes of technology.  I refer members to pages 4 and 5 of the committee secretariat brief and page 3 of the Department's brief.  Are there any questions or comments?  We will move on to student support and related services on page 5 of the committee secretariat brief and page 4 of the Department brief.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.210" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#M02000"><p>I have two questions on this.  On the additional funding we will provide before the end of the year, we were due to split it 50-50 and yet we are now moving towards providing 80% of the funding in 2015 and 20% in January 2016.  What consequences does that have for next year?  The higher education institutes are stating that they are having difficulty with cashflow and that there are cashflow pressures within the institutes.  I imagine those pressures are not going to just disappear overnight.  What impact does it have if we are giving them more money this year which was earmarked for next year?  What will be the knock-on consequences for next year?</p> <p>  In respect of the figure of &euro;17 million to meet demographic trends which we did not account for, how did we not account for demographic trends?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.211" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00100"><p>On Deputy O'Brien's first question, we will do the same next year; 80% will again be paid in 2016 for the following year and 20% in 2017, the same as for this year.  That is the intention.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.212" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00200"><p>That does not solve the long-term problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.213" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00300"><p>No, it does not.  Some of the institutes of technology in particular have issues and the Higher Education Authority is in discussion with the sector.  Everybody knows that the issue is under consideration by the group led by Peter Cassells, which is due to report shortly.  I will publish that report.  It is a broader issue in terms of the funding of higher education in general.  There are various views about how those pressures should be dealt with.  In terms of this matter, it is intended that we would do the same next year as this year, with 80% provided before Christmas and 20% after.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.214" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00400"><p>We have to get to a stage at some point where we are not in a position of having to front-load it.  Are we saying that the Cassells report is going to address some of the reasons there are cashflow issues within the institutes?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.215" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00500"><p>It will certainly be an issue and probably one on which the political parties will take positions.  It is going to be a big question for the future funding of the sector.  It is not just a cashflow issue but is more generally linked to the fact that the demographics are constantly growing.  I will come to that in response to the Deputy's second question.  The population is continuing to grow.  It will even off at primary level around 2019 or 2020 but will not do so at third level until we are way into the late 2020s or further on.  We will have to consider how we fund higher education with the demographic growth that is going to continue for quite some time.  That is a broader question than what we are addressing today and is probably one on which we all have views.  We will exercise our minds about it.</p> <p>  On the upward demographic pressures that account for some of this figure, the CAO applications for 2015 were up by 1.82% or 1,333 applications as compared to 2014.  The number of those sitting the leaving certificate in 2015 went up by 2.25% on 2014.  The number of postgraduate and undergraduates enrolled in higher education was up by 2% in 2015-16 compared to 2014-15.  The number of grant holders for 2014-15 was 80,555 compared to 78,965 for the previous academic year.  That is also a 2% increase.  That demographic is showing itself in the need for increased funding for student support.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.216" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00600"><p>On bringing the payment forward, has the Department considered whether the pressures might come up again before the next front-loading, say if there was a similar cashflow problem towards the summer if the money is paid earlier?  It is just deferring the problem.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.217" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00700"><p>I suppose the answer is that it is the same amount of money and they are just getting more of it earlier.  They are aware of that and have to factor it into how they plan their year.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.218" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00800"><p>Why would they need more of it now than later?  Why is there an issue about cashflow now?  If the money is the same, what is the benefit to the colleges of getting it earlier?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.219" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N00900"><p>The Higher Education Authority is watching their financial position.  They are feeling pressure which we want to try to alleviate insofar as we can.  They are aware that there is a full year to plan for and they have to do that.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.220" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N01000"><p>What is the cause of the pressure?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.221" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#N01100"><p>It is partly increased numbers.</p><p>It probably is the fact that the financial position in recent years has not allowed the Government to provide more funding for higher education, as it would have wished to do had more finance been available.  Obviously, there are pressures at all levels of education.  It is a matter of balancing and, for example, not wishing to increase class sizes at primary level possibly means one cannot then increase funding at higher education level.  It is a matter of judgment when one is working with reduced budgets, with which my predecessor obviously was working.  We have been fortunate in that we have had slight increases in budgets this year and last year because of the improved economy.  I will not make a political speech about that but the reality is one must balance the different levels and try to do the best one can with the budget one has.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.223" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#O00200"><p>While the explanation by the Department describes the problem as being purely a cashflow problem or in terms of cashflow pressure, it appears as though it might be more than a cashflow issue.  In respect of getting 50% earlier and now getting perhaps 80%, the sector will be getting approximately 120% in this year.  Will this need continue in future years or will the changes in the way in which it is being delivered be adequate to meet the needs?  It has been written up as being cashflow pressure but one can see it is more than that, in that basically, they have a need for greater funding than they are getting.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.224" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#O00300"><p>I have acknowledged in my reply to Deputy O'Brien that higher education in general undoubtedly is experiencing difficulties in trying to provide for increased numbers of students and in trying to provide a wide range of courses in response to pressures from the workplace.  I refer, for example, to instances in which workplaces identify the need for a certain number of information technology specialists or whatever it might be and colleges then are trying to respond to that.  They certainly are facing pressures but this is an effort to assist them with what I acknowledge to be the same amount of money, albeit they will get some of it a little earlier.  In addition, there is another element to it, in so far as Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, now also has become quite efficient.  There was a time when not all the grant applications were processed as early as is now the case.  People will acknowledge SUSI has become more efficient in the speed at which it processes applications.  That may be part of it, although I do not suggest this is the main reason this measure is being taken.  However, there was a time when SUSI perhaps did not have a lot of the applications processed before the Christmas period whereas it by and large now does, unless there is some extremely complicating factor.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.225" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#O00400"><p>Obviously, it is not just cashflow and as Deputy Ryan has observed, it cannot simply be a cashflow issue.  There must be some reason behind it and there are some pressures on the system.  Will the introduction of technological universities address some of the pressures the higher education institutions, HEIs, are experiencing?  I am aware there is a proposal to bring through that legislation before the Oireachtas breaks for Christmas.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.226" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#O00500"><p>As the Deputy is aware, the Bill now has been published and I hope to be able to introduce it.  Obviously, less than two weeks of D&aacute;il time now remain but I intend to introduce the Bill.  Some funding is available to help with the process of the different regions getting to the point of applying for the status of technological university.  However, I must acknowledge this again is not the major factor in terms of the pressures on the higher education sector.  The major factor really is it is the sector that constantly is in a competitive space with the rest of the world in the first instance.  While might not agree with league tables, I am told they are things of which one must take some note.  The other point concerns the growing demographics and the growing demand from the workplace for higher levels of educational attainment.</p><p>Whereas one previously could get a job with a primary degree, one now might need a higher qualification for the same job.  The higher education sector is dealing constantly with all these pressures and obviously, the funding then becomes part of the issue with which it must deal when the Government has not been able to increase the sector's funding in any significant way in recent years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.228" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#P00200"><p>At the same time, I note the Irish Universities Association appeared before the joint committee.  At the time of cutbacks, the universities increased the level of funding they brought in from other sources in different ways, such as by providing courses, through philanthropy or whatever.  A couple of issues arise from that.  First, as we are coming out of the recession and a recovery is under way, surely now is the time to start spending more at the different levels, including third level?  Second, has the Higher Education Authority been consulted to figure out whether part of the sector is more under pressure than other parts?  Is the university sector better than the institute of technology sector and, if so, has this been considered or examined?</p> <p>  On another point, which I acknowledge is a discussion for another day, as a country, we were able to go from spending &euro;15 billion per annum on social welfare to &euro;20 billion per annum for X number of years.  As it is known there is a defined period during which the demographics will increase at third level and obviously, more people will be at work to pay taxes, can a decision be made to the effect that the type of increase that was made for a little while in respect of social welfare - because obviously there was a crisis with which to deal - could be made in respect of third level education for a defined period?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.229" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#P00300"><p>I would love to have more money to spend in education but obviously, that is a matter for the Government to decide and is a matter for decision of Estimates etc.  As for demographics, for example, in respect of school building and capital programmes and in maintaining the pupil-teacher ratio - and improving it slightly this year, as was done at both primary and post-primary levels - in all those decisions the Government has recognised the demographic pressures, particularly in the school capital programme, must be dealt with.  This is why the Government was building schools and providing money for building schools despite the recession, as well as ensuring there were additional teachers every year and additional resources for schools, particularly additional teachers, even during the difficult times.  However, on a broader scale I am sure everyone at this meeting probably would agree we should be spending more money on education and that it is an area in which there are growing demographics.  However, that must be a matter for the Government, whosoever is in government at a particular time.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.230" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/984" speakername="Jonathan O'Brien" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#P00400"><p>If I might make an observation as a new first-term Deputy, I believe all the Departments work in silos.  All Departments are fighting their own corner and there is no overarching examination of how the Government works.  If one examines those countries that have some of the best education systems, such as Finland, they prioritise education.  It is a joint decision by the Government, everyone works towards that goal and it pays long-term dividends, whereas I believe we have five-year cycles in Ireland where everyone in government is just looking after his or her own little corner and there is no long-term vision.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.231" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#P00500"><p>Clearly, we have programmes for Government that are agreed.  While we are straying away a little now, a programme for Government that is agreed at the outset of a Government's life presumably makes decisions on priorities.  Everyone present would agree that education must be a priority.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.232" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#P00600"><p>I believe it is the case that in the institute of technology sector in particular, the institutes statutorily are not allowed to run a deficit and consequently must balance their books by the end of each year.  Is it the case that a certain number of institutions are telling the Minister they will be in the red at the end of the year unless there is a bailout in the form of this front-loading of the student contribution fee?  If this is a factor, is it only a factor at the level of the institutes of technology and if so, how many institutes of technology might be in that situation?  Is this also the position at university level?</p><p> The student contribution charge has increased from &euro;2,000 to &euro;3,000 during the past four to five years.  Is it the case, and the Minister might be able to explain this, that as that additional amount of student contribution has been paid for grant students by the Government to the college, the amount being paid in other capitation fees and grants to the colleges has been reduced commensurate to that?  The additional &euro;250 imposed on students each year has not been an additional &euro;250 each year per student going to the universities.</p><p> This is a &euro;1.5 billion additional Estimate, of which the &euro;175 million with which we are dealing with today is part.  It came in at the side of the scrum, so to speak, in that it was not flagged.  It was a surprise.  It certainly was not part of parties' budgetary projections.  My understanding is that taking it as a whole, &euro;1.5 billion is now built into the system in that it is recurring expenditure.  Therefore, is the net Supplementary Estimate of &euro;175 million for education this year now built into the budget for next year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.234" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q00200"><p>It is.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.235" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q00300"><p>This particular pot we are dealing with, the &euro;1 million, has been front-loaded for the higher education institutions into 2015.  Does that mean there will be a similar breakdown of that &euro;175 million extra in the budget next year, according to the different sections, or will it be up for grabs again depending on what part of the education system needs it?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.236" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q00400"><p>I will try to answer all the questions.  With regard to institutes of technology, they would be in constant contact with the Higher Education Authority with regard to their cashflow issues.  We are not talking about the scenario the Deputy painted.  They would constantly work with the Higher Education Authority in terms of ensuring they are able to continue to carry out their functions during the year.  However, there is a difference between them and universities in that universities can borrow whereas institutes of technology cannot under the current legislation governing them.</p> <p>  With regard to the student contribution being offset, that is the way it has been consistently, and is not something that has come in either this year or in the past few years, where the student contribution is offset against the funding generally paid to colleges.  With regard to the &euro;175 million, it is built into next year's funding so it would be there as part of the base for next year.  Of the &euro;175 million, &euro;50 million is capital, but the non-capital element of it is built into the base.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.237" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q00500"><p>Will the &euro;78 million in respect of the student support and related expenses, subhead C11, which we are discussing, be recurring expenditure under that subhead next year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.238" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q00600"><p>Not necessarily under that subhead.  It will be in the general overall base-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.239" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q00700"><p>The overall education budget.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.240" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q00800"><p>-----for the Department of Education and Skills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.241" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q00900"><p>Does the offsetting, to which the Minister referred, mean that the additional increases in the student contribution fee have not increased in any way or have not gone directly to the college but have been offset by reducing capitations elsewhere?  Is that correct?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.242" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q01000"><p>Yes, that is how it works but, as I said, that is not something that just started in the past few years.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.243" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q01100"><p>Is the Minister saying that there are not any institutes of technology in the red at present needing that funding?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.244" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q01200"><p>No.  I  am not saying they are not in the red, I am saying that they are in constant discussion with the Higher Education Authority, which is the body with which they would deal directly, to ensure that they can continue to operate financially.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.245" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q01300"><p>Would it be fair to say that if some of them did not get the forward loading of this fee, they would be in the red for the year?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.246" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#Q01400"><p>I am not saying that.  I am saying this will assist them with the financial pressures in terms of how they operate.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.247" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00100"><p>The Minister said that some of the front-loading is related to the greater efficiency achieved by the Student Universal Support Ireland, SUSI, which is a good sign, as it could be said that is a performance by the Department in the sense that it set up SUSI and it is delivering in terms of greater efficiency.  It is part of the issue with regard to the front-loading of the money.  Of the &euro;78 million, can the Minister put a figure on the amount that is being front-loaded because of the greater efficiency of SUSI?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.248" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00200"><p>I will try to get the Chairman a figure for that.  I do not have a specific figure.  To be clear, the &euro;61 million goes to the Higher Education Authority and it then deals individually with the institutes of technology and the universities.  It is not the case that a specific institute gets a specific amount of money directly from the Department; it goes through the Higher Education Authority and it allocates it.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.249" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00300"><p>We will move on to the next item, subhead D3, which covers building, equipment and furnishing of primary and post-primary schools.  Are there any questions on that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.250" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00400"><p>On what page is that?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.251" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00500"><p>It is on page 6 of the secretariat briefing and page 5 of the Department's briefing.  It is subhead D3, which covers building, equipment and furnishing of primary and post-primary schools.  It is on the last page of our secretariat briefing.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.252" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00600"><p>I wish to ask about the additional expenditures relating to applications made under the summer works scheme the previous year where the applications were kept on file in the Department.  In the interim period a number of the schools, on receiving news that their applications for the scheme in 2014 were not successful, would have carried out the works and funded them by taking out loans or by other means.  They would then have got word in 2015 when the additional Estimates funding was made available that their applications were successful, but they already had the works completed.  In those cases were those schools awarded the funding even though they may have had the work carried out?</p> <p>  In regard to the minor works grant, and the payment of that grant for this autumn, does any of this allocation relate to that or from where did the payment for minor works come because I understood no provision was specifically made for a minor works grant in the original 2015 Estimates?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.253" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1013" speakername="Brendan  Ryan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00700"><p>In regard to particular projects that were not progressed or finalised under summer works scheme in 2014, would this be part of a typical pattern with regard to such projects over the years?  Was this an unusual year in the sense that &euro;50 million worth of projects were not finalised, or would this be something that would typically happen most years and, if so, why would it not have been forecast?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.254" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00800"><p>On Deputy McConalogue's question around the projects that did not proceed in the first year, the schools would have been told that the files were being held, in other words, that they were still on file should more money become available.  As he knows, certain categories were done and certain other categories were held for the next year.  The schools would have been told that if they held out, there was a chance that there would be further funding.  There then was further funding.  There were a small number of schools that did go ahead and carry out the work</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.255" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R00900"><p>The problem was that-----</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.256" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#R01000"><p>-----but they would have been made aware that funding may become available.  Apparently, there are only about two cases.  I do not know what specifically what happened with regard to them.  We can clarify the position if there are any such cases of which the Deputy is aware and that he wishes to bring to our attention.</p><p>The minor works scheme money was found in the overall provision for the Department.  Deputy Brendan Ryan's question was on whether this would happen at other times.  In some cases work would be delayed or started in one year and finished in the following year.  This would have happened before.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.258" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S00200"><p>The summer works scheme has just closed for the receipt of applications.  When does the Minister expect to make an announcement on them?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.259" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S00300"><p>At the end of February or in March.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.260" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S00400"><p>Subhead E covers appropriations-in-aid and is the last item to be considered.  I apologise, but there was another subhead, subhead B, on page 4 of the briefing document.  It covers grants for further education and training activities.  Expenditure under this subhead is projected to be &euro;50 million, less than what was provided for.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.261" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S00500"><p>What exactly is happening?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.262" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S00600"><p>There was a saving of &euro;14 million.  This was around the time SOLAS and the education and training boards were established.  It extends over two years rather than just one.  It relates to part of the agreement between SOLAS and the education and training boards.  The Exchequer funding goes from SOLAS to the education and training boards and it is proposed to recoup the surpluses by deducting the amounts from the final tranche of payments made to the education and training boards before the end of the current financial year.  In other words, SOLAS was allocating more funding than the education and training boards were drawing down.  That is why there is a surplus.  The surplus is &euro;14 million, of which &euro;3 million will be used to pay for the Christmas bonus to those on the relevant education and training courses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.263" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/999" speakername="Charlie McConalogue" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S00700"><p>The money was allocated for the provision of courses.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.264" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S00800"><p>Yes.  According to my note, the main areas in which surpluses were identified were participant and training allowances under the vocational training opportunities scheme, VTOS, and Youthreach.  The cohort of participants varies from year to year and it is difficult to estimate the cost of allowances, particularly for VTOS participants where they receive a training allowance in lieu of their Department of Social Protection payment.  It was difficult to anticipate how many would be in that category and who would need to draw down the money.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.265" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S00900"><p>Although it is not exactly related, I have been told, as a public representative - I am sure it has been said to others also - that a person may know somebody taking a training course and although the person does not attend, he or she is receiving the allowance.  The people involved might declare themselves sick, for example.  This has certainly been raised as an issue during the years.  Are there checks to ensure there is no abuse of the system?  In some cases, a person might receive more than he or she receives in social welfare.  Are there checks to ensure the allowances are spent in such a way that we can ensure people are genuinely attending courses?</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.266" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1061" speakername="Jan O'Sullivan" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#S01000"><p>We are very conscious that people have to attend courses.  The purpose in some cases is to reach those who most need to be given opportunities to find employment.  This relates to the Youth Guarantee which is used in some cases and so on.  We really want to reach the people in question to ensure they are attending and benefiting from courses  From the Department's perspective, we put pressure on the education and training boards through SOLAS to track people.</p><p>To my knowledge, the ETBs ensure people's attendance is monitored but if I can obtain further information on that, I will provide it to the Deputy.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.268" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#T00200"><p>We move to subhead E, appropriations-in-aid.  I understand the Minister must attend Leaders' Questions in the D&aacute;il so if there are no further questions, we will conclude our consideration of the Supplementary Estimate.  I thank the Minister and her officials for their attendance today and thank members for their input.</p></speech>
    <minor-heading id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.269" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#T00300">Message to Dáil</minor-heading>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.270" speakerid="com.kildarestreet/member/1010" speakername="Joanna Tuffy" time="13:30:00" url="http://oireachtasdebates.oireachtas.ie/debates%20authoring/debateswebpack.nsf/committeetakes/ED12015120800002#T00400"><p>In accordance with Standing Order 87, the following message will be sent to the D&aacute;il:</p> <p>  The Select Sub-Committee on Education and Skills has completed its consideration of the following Supplementary Estimate for public services for the year ending on 31 December 2015: Vote 26 - Education and Skills.</p></speech>
    <speech id="com.kildarestreet/committees/2015-12-08a.271" nospeaker="true" time="13:30:00" ><p>The select sub-committee adjourned sine die.</p></speech>
</publicwhip>